<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0289F04C2C16431DA54EBFABB979ED88" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>112 HR 5533 IH: Healthy at Home Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5533</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230918">September 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To combat toxic indoor mold, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5646CEBC8801457A93EDEA88890D54B2" style="OLC"><section id="H98DE0B3E010D42D294F18E45C925E693" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H8AA739353AD54AEB96905BEDA2B888F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy at Home Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD6D10E94F0664F6B91F2085545DCFFBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H98DE0B3E010D42D294F18E45C925E693" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HAD00C28AB38C4E7089ADDFDAAC64819B" level="section">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD9FEF7BF27F54E2E9FAC36EBF4544196" level="section">Sec. 3. Interagency research on health impacts of indoor residential mold.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4D63BC3D9B7D49F3965E0E3838D0F214" level="section">Sec. 4. Health, safety, and habitability standards and model standards.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H420FA9F7CA2941D69D737F0AA4AB5536" level="section">Sec. 5. Mapping.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3E3FFE0AA94C46E08D48F7C05415B18D" level="section">Sec. 6. Housing stock quality requirements.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H986062E1A73944FCABBA06B9F34801A3" level="section">Sec. 7. Construction requirements for public housing and certain other -assisted construction.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEA126D174D4E4F6FB5099FAD10C8E553" level="section">Sec. 8. Preservation grants for properties receiving section 8 project-based rental assistance.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA6715D9CDC9C4152ADE4667E678EA1B5" level="section">Sec. 9. Public information and education campaign.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2F1F3C8D418E49F3A184821EA0BB4404" level="section">Sec. 10. Empowering tenants.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H14CD7A14C4A8460E8E838A7E59772638" level="section">Sec. 11. Healthy Homes incentive for requiring indoor residential mold and other hazard disclosure.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H400C61708C884BB7AD643B2F3ACB3080" level="section">Sec. 12. Uniform physical inspection sampling.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H973493B7146843ADAC9B1959722FD1C7" level="section">Sec. 13. Denial of depreciation deduction for properties with failed NSPIRE inspections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9E7DB6D5AB744171B5EE526DB54AF0A0" level="section">Sec. 14. Supporting landlords to receive timely voucher payments.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H78D06604575D4FFCA7353554BDB39C0A" level="section">Sec. 15. Project-based contract administrator reporting requirements.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB774F673FEE7499FA935FE1D4260C936" level="section">Sec. 16. Coordination Between USDA and HUD.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEC180D56DE954BBAAAB58F55CAC7D6C4" level="section">Sec. 17. GAO study on health and safety concerns in federally-assisted housing.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4C1403DE4C2E48AC804052FF850A0644" level="section">Sec. 18. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF45CCB9389A04BD99965B829872520B3" level="section">Sec. 19. Administrative provisions.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HAD00C28AB38C4E7089ADDFDAAC64819B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD512CAB128144B0C8248AC542920FF0E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indoor residential mold</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>indoor residential mold</term> means any form of multicellular fungi in indoor environments, including cladosporium, penicillium, alternaria, aspergillus, fusarium, trichoderma, memnoniella, mucor, stachybotrys chartarum, streptomyces, and epicoccumoften found in water-damaged indoor environments and building materials. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DB85A2554734983AA9ABD5043BB23F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Residential mold inspection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>residential mold inspection</term> means an inspection, by a certified or licensed mold inspector or other indoor environmental professional, including through the Real Estate Assessment Center, of real property that is designed to discover—</text><subparagraph id="HA5082E0913824D6884E27A2BBF47ABA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">indoor mold growth in residential properties;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H384DBDC4CDD04BE8B97A16E5EBF61BC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conditions that facilitate indoor residential mold growth; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F8DE23F7A4E4C76A770CE94E5872D7B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">indicia of conditions that are likely to facilitate indoor residential mold growth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7369F85CE6C04564A0278DECE8FD1CDB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Toxigenic mold</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>toxigenic mold</term> means any indoor mold growth that may be capable of producing a toxin or toxic compound, including mycotoxins and mVOCs, that can cause pulmonary, respiratory, neurological, gastrointestinal, or dermatological illnesses, or other major adverse health impacts, as jointly determined by the Director of the National Institutes of Health, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HD9FEF7BF27F54E2E9FAC36EBF4544196"><enum>3.</enum><header>Interagency research on health impacts of indoor residential mold</header><subsection id="H814AB717EC7F4D0FBBACEEA63EC9D7AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research</header><paragraph id="H429DB18E54D94ED8831F458076CAFFDD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences at the National Institutes of Health, in conjunction with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the President of the National Academy of Sciences, and the Chair of the board of directors of the National Institute of Building Sciences shall jointly conduct a comprehensive study of the health effects of indoor residential mold growth, using the most up-to-date scientific peer-reviewed medical literature.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H019B5D9C2BB94A9BBF88A65A4C9A2059"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study conducted under paragraph (1) shall ascertain, among other things—</text><subparagraph id="H12C7B4715449402AAB0A8012762C3530"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">detailed information about harmful or toxigenic mold, as well as any toxin or toxic compound such mold can produce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D70777B944148D6B708E99558D8B7A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the most accurate research-based methods of detecting harmful or toxigenic mold;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DEAB34F74914F30AD2A1194C3AD1EF3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>potential dangers of prolonged or chronic exposure to indoor residential mold growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67621523AC634975B8F0E43056CB94E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the hazards involved with inadequate residential mold inspections and improper indoor residential mold remediation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF42E4B01280C4668B8DDE96AA6536553"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the estimated current public health burden of new or exacerbated physical illness resulting from exposure to indoor residential mold, including its disproportionate impact on vulnerable communities, including children and seniors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7148F4AD77BA4CD4B08563D1A80BBFBC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improved understanding of the different health symptomology that can result from exposure to mold in indoor residential environments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD69020F818B34E7AB6C339AC60744DDC"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ongoing surveillance of the prevalence of idiopathic pulmonary hemorrhage (AIPH) in infants; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DB9C76F2FD14A10BE86B2E7468C2876"><enum>(H)</enum><text>longitudinal studies on the effects of indoor old exposure in early childhood on the development of asthma and other respiratory illnesses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCB14F3A4B6645A6809CD9D5006C1A3D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the expiration of the 3-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1) shall be submitted to Congress and the President and made available to the general public.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4D63BC3D9B7D49F3965E0E3838D0F214"><enum>4.</enum><header>Health, safety, and habitability standards and model standards</header><subsection id="H824ACBB860FB4014A34A2C160EF31F08"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Model standards for preventing, detecting, and remediating indoor residential mold growth</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based on the results of the interagency health study conducted under section 3, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, in conjunction with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health at the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, the Secretary of Energy, the Executive Director of the National Institute of Building Sciences, and the President of the National Academy of Sciences shall, in accordance with section 12(d) of the National Technology Transfer and Advancement Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/272">15 U.S.C. 272</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/113">Public Law 104–113</external-xref>), jointly issue model health, safety, and habitability standards for preventing, detecting, and remediating indoor residential mold growth, including—</text><paragraph id="HD18111FB0DDF459895DA68C955E7E61A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>model indoor residential mold inspection standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDA05A2685404F89BF9AF87C661B9B58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>model indoor residential mold remediation standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF035A6FD13A49A4928328A8163ED5C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">standards for testing the toxicity of indoor residential mold and any toxin or toxic compound produced by indoor residential mold;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD3FF6FB7C55498AAEBE7C68A6376F5C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health and safety standards for the protection of indoor residential mold inspectors and remediators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A0F2AE8BC774D6587A19331BFCA33B6"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">standards for indoor residential mold testing labs; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3A8DDBEFDE141AD9CB3B456774C0AB0"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">model ventilation standards for the design, installation, and maintenance of air ventilation or air-conditioning systems to prevent indoor residential mold growth or the creation of conditions that foster indoor mold growth in residential properties; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCE94E5B9E9547D2A10C63C23ECC588D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">model building code standards to control moisture and prevent mold growth in indoor residential environments. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCE458D6F2564EB29B6A7B026A4E730B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the maximum extent possible, model standards issued under this section shall be developed in consideration of the needs and vulnerabilities of low-income populations and with the assistance of—</text><paragraph id="H8654286875944AAB8E124209EB96E239"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organizations that develop mold and water damage standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C848CC61EE64364AB8598575CDFA28A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>organizations involved in establishing national building construction standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5C4453683CD41C1BECB91F726177963"><enum>(3)</enum><text>representatives of State or local authorities responsible for building inspections and issuance of certificates of occupancy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC464EA76D3084394B28126D902A03A3B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organizations involved in improving indoor air quality;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A26E35FBB934084B1455FC895096B6D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">public health advocates; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02349D0BFC0548E7BB550C4E3BED7E9E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health and medical professionals, including practitioners that care for children and other vulnerable populations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAB84C72BC8F84E85B7C35CF018C50F60"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Resiliency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Model standards issued under this section shall take into account geographic diversity, propensity for extreme weather or flooding, and other resiliency metrics.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6CC3E09D40B2472F80D4A59D58133A05"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><paragraph id="HD204FAD48CBD4750940E6B90CFAE5853"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public review and comment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The officers identified in subsection (a) shall make draft standards issued under this section available for public review and comment at least 90 days prior to publication of the final standards or model standards pursuant to paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48E16303557E44CBB876A0AEAA3FD0DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the results of the study conducted under section 3 are submitted to Congress in accordance with such section, the officers identified in subsection (a) shall issue, and make available to the public, final standards and model standards under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE05F382607A742BCB68C2D7FB5FA1DF1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Review and updates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The officers identified in subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H3A9BF80D81EB48BC9BC405712C760CEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review the model standards issued under this section at least once every 3 years based on latest scientific advances and published studies relating to indoor residential mold growth; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09BCACEF514E46ADB46647A9D6E3F5E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">update such standards and model standards as necessary to adequately and effectively inform the public and protect human health, preserve and improve the quality of federally-assisted housing, and reduce the displacement of tenants.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60241C96862448768AA0B001EDFF245E" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Physical condition inspections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the publication of standards and model standards under subsection (a), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall revise the requirements for conducting uniform physical condition inspections under part 5 of title 24, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation, to incorporate the model standards issued under this section, as applicable.</text></subsection></section><section id="H420FA9F7CA2941D69D737F0AA4AB5536"><enum>5.</enum><header>Mapping</header><subsection id="H7AFC1AD870B74E6EB9456C7C5E4C1C58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall, using the previous two years of inspection data, establish a geographic information system mapping tool that identifies areas which are impacted by a known presence of indoor residential mold.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA90390C3136242D6B1E8044D2EABFA9A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required inclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include, as part of the mapping tool—</text><paragraph id="H35BF0583CF614C609831305CB901C6E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>inspection documentation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FB20CE8AEB64BE78DAB01B502331B90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>management and occupancy reviews;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0F00D01116340ECAFADF7C2E4AD872C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>transfers of budget authority for contracts under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC694D5DF2CC1475BA2263C1A460ED7B3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any additional information, as required by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2424454DBC87442FB15E172CB30E7A85"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary shall update the mapping tool with the latest inspection data not less often than once per year.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3E3FFE0AA94C46E08D48F7C05415B18D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Housing stock quality requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subsection (v) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H03FB2E811E4D4C7C9275904CFBE371EC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HBD5AC465C45B4FC294BE584F98D55532"><enum>(w)</enum><header>Standards for physical condition and management of housing receiving assistance payments</header><paragraph id="H1EDCB318C0DF484AB1CE68CDA7926113"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any entity receiving housing assistance payments under this section shall maintain decent, safe, and sanitary conditions, as determined by the Secretary, and comply with any standards under applicable State or local laws, rules, ordinances, or regulations relating to the physical condition of any insured or non-insured property covered under a housing assistance payment contract for project-based assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC7E156BE313408C821ED6A729C97437"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Remediation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall take action under paragraph (3) when a multifamily housing project with a housing assistance payment contract under this section or a contract with the Department of Housing and Urban Development for similar project-based assistance—</text><subparagraph id="H0A36D9395E8846CBB3B43BC0A6D0D456"><enum>(A)</enum><text>receives a failing score on a physical inspection by the Department; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H539ED8E15C5247508E14C949EC36CEE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fails to certify in writing to the Secretary within 3 days that all severe health or safety deficiencies identified at the project by the inspector have been corrected.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph"> The requirements under this paragraph shall apply to insured and non-insured projects with assistance attached to the dwelling units under this section.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A7235316FED432186863449E75B1BCD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice of default</header><subparagraph id="HA381A9B5C4FC4858870DC6AB5E636883"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Issuance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 15 days of the issuance of the Real Estate Assessment Center inspection, the Secretary shall provide the owner with a notice of default that shall include a specified timetable, determined by the Secretary, for correcting all deficiencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02B95A94E4D44532BE33D297FB558146"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Copies</header><text>The Secretary shall provide a copy of the notice of default to the tenants of the property, the local government for the jurisdiction within which the property is located, any mortgagees, and any contract administrator.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6C9C17E3F42431A8A83DE6721FBA0A6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appeal; withdrawal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the owner appeals the notice of default and the appeal results in a passing Uniform Physical Condition Standards score for the property, the Secretary may withdraw the notice of default.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H29A1A6DEBCBA44379F40033F134730BD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the owner fails to fully correct all deficiencies identified in the notice of default by the end of the time period for correcting such deficiencies specified in the notice, the Secretary shall, in consultation with the tenant organization, one or more of the following actions, and provide additional notice of those actions to the owner and the parties specified in paragraph (3)(B) to improve property conditions and preserve housing assistance:</text><subparagraph id="H4C3C5A01926A4FD382383BB72156800C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Take any regulatory or contractual remedies available as deemed necessary and appropriate by the Secretary to improve property conditions, protect tenants from displacement and harm, and preserve the housing assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5700468D1F014BD1902F7F6E5AF8720A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Require immediate replacement of the project management with a management agent approved by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86034C8A6620443BBC8DD258E6838FE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Abate the section 8 contract, including partial abatement, as determined by the Secretary, until all deficiencies have been corrected.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD304EAEDAEAD4F389B367D6AC60CA129"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursue transfer of the project to an owner approved by the Secretary, in consultation with the tenant organization, under established procedures, who shall be obligated to promptly make all required repairs and to accept renewal of the assistance contract if such renewal is offered, in conjunction with the appropriate public housing agency or other local entity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD992303571245B9A1A22C8EB4A54806"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transfer the existing section 8 contract to another project or projects and owner or owners who have demonstrated financial and organizational capacity to rehabilitate the project, in consultation with tenants and the appropriate public housing agency. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37BE23C5E70B40D79E1D00619B8A1E43"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Pursue exclusionary sanctions, including suspensions or debarments from Federal programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AC98F49F19D49D7A9C948E21BD208F8"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Relocate tenants while providing the same level of housing assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9B8C1F261624AD2AC65194BF1DDBF4B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Seek judicial appointment of a receiver to manage the property and cure all project deficiencies or seek a judicial order of specific performance requiring the owner to cure all project deficiencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94629AA0A1B9493F92CC339A01601E04"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cooperate with receivership efforts by State or local governments or lenders which aim to improve the property conditions and preserve the project-based housing assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47E38762633643599638905EBB531ADC"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Work with the owner, lender, tenants, or other related party to stabilize the property in an attempt to preserve the property through compliance, transfer of ownership, or an infusion of capital or other resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5E537FB028C43D88D3B1FACE23DB34E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Prohibition on rent increases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective upon the expiration of the 12-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall prohibit any increases in rents for dwelling units in the property until the owner fully corrects all deficiencies identified in the notice of default or demonstrates an ability to financially address conditions by—</text><subparagraph id="H884727BFB0A546DDA041A036E57A6A3F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing a rehabilitation plan, developed in consultation with the tenants and approved by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB1453863F5E4644BA291B9718A2C0D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">separately demonstrating a written and enforceable commitment by the tenants and the Secretary that any increases will address the conditions of the property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H35730F21FFEE40FDA9D9C148DC45E231"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Infeasible properties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall take appropriate steps to ensure that project-based contracts for rental assistance remain in effect, subject to the exercise of contractual abatement remedies to assist relocation of tenants for major threats to health and safety, taken after written notice to the affected tenants. To the extent the Secretary determines, in consultation with the tenants and the local government, that a property is not feasible for continued rental assistance payments under such section 8 or other programs, based on consideration of—</text><subparagraph id="HADC23338B87246C4843408A8D11B6165"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the costs of rehabilitating and operating the property and all available Federal, State, and local resources, including rent adjustments under section 524 of the Multifamily Assisted Housing Reform and Affordability Act of 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref> note), and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20B34292A2CF49819CF6CA457C0A45F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>environmental conditions that cannot be remedied in a cost-effective fashion, </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">the Secretary may contract for project-based rental assistance payments with an owner or owners of other housing properties, and to the maximum extent practicable, ensure that the project-based rental assistance is available to tenants from the originating site.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AF363FAC0A549C4B3C24CC475DC0B50" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reporting</header><subparagraph id="H4AA6C6136DC245C1A02478AB0E3832D0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit a report to the Committees on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate semi-annually identifying all properties covered by this subsection that received a failing physical inspection score or have received an unsatisfactory management and occupancy review during the 36-month period ending upon submission of such report. Each such report shall include—</text><clause id="H3EF6D32B8BF7447FAF3AE26F76FA5AB7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identification of the enforcement actions being taken to address such conditions leading to such score at each such property, including imposition of civil money penalties and termination of subsidies, and identification of properties that have such conditions multiple times; </text></clause><clause id="H8990F3094A6F4062BA1232515526D1C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identification of actions that the Department of Housing and Urban Development is taking to protect tenants of such identified properties; and</text></clause><clause id="H96DC4EBF31164DA9964AF957A64C957C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any recommendations for administrative or legislative actions to further improve the living conditions at such properties.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE825F759474A461CA3C73D14070AADF1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The first report required under subparagraph (A) shall be submitted not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, and the second report shall be submitted within 180 days of the submission of the first report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H986062E1A73944FCABBA06B9F34801A3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Construction requirements for public housing and certain other federally-assisted construction</header><subsection id="H1F5633BCE991499F8ECB71B74AF60F4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Effective date; applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall take such actions and impose such standards and conditions as may be necessary or appropriate to ensure that any public housing constructed after the date of the issuance of the model construction standards and techniques established under subsection (b), is constructed in accordance with such model standards and techniques.</text></subsection><subsection id="H447F4EA88C794AB4890D44CBAF1C75EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Model construction standards</header><paragraph id="H014979C9A4F64281B8959D339BC4569C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, jointly with the Executive Director of the National Institute of Building Sciences, and the President of the National Academy of Sciences, to the extent such Director and President agree to participate, shall develop model construction standards and techniques for preventing and controlling indoor residential mold in new residential buildings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0277089DE27A4FAAA1A4FFD3FE7687DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The model standards and techniques shall provide for geographic differences in construction types and materials, geology, weather, and other variables that may affect indoor residential mold levels in new buildings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H959CB1BCBDC9431FB62E5D9DBCFE8AF6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>To the maximum extent possible, such standards and techniques shall be developed with—</text><subparagraph id="HE235E891177A4469A930BF4168A1A1D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the assistance of organizations involved in establishing national building construction standards and techniques;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECB69E3E61534ED7A0D00BEC8CD58FE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the assistance of organizations that develop mold and water damage standards; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H959AD551AD89409DA543EF06FA6469D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>representatives of State or local authorities responsible for building inspections and the issuance of certificates of occupancy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H467DA40A0202411494C8896131AA4D8D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">public health advocates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95E9241A3B064A73B49366E1BD03E1FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">housing advocates and organizations representing the interests of tenants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H35A18C5003714A46936131FF32094980"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Secretary shall make a draft of the document containing the model standards and techniques available for public review and comment. The Secretary shall make final model standards and techniques available to the public not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8273C223B77A4811B24C2591437CB6E4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Applicability to new construction and rehabilitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 1 year of the publication of the final model standards and techniques required by paragraph (4), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Energy, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of the Treasury, and the Secretary of Defense shall each include such model standards and techniques as a requirement for residential rehabilitation or new construction projects funded with Federal appropriations made available by such agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4615DBCFDCB943E2842A40AD033B6D35"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Applicability to rental assistance demonstration and RAD section 18 blend programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 1 year of the publication of the final model standards and techniques required by paragraph (4), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall ensure that any rehabilitation or new construction through the Rental Assistance Demonstration program under the heading <quote>Rental Assistance Demonstration</quote> in title II of the Transportation, Housing and Urban Development, and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2012 (division C of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/55">Public Law 112–55</external-xref>; 125 Stat. 673), or through any program blending such Rental Assistance Demonstration and section 18 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 complies with such model standards and techniques.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEA126D174D4E4F6FB5099FAD10C8E553" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header>Preservation grants for properties receiving section 8 project-based rental assistance</header><subsection id="H92CD544A72C44BA4B6EE19F04851CD16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development to provide assistance to owners of properties receiving project-based subsidy contracts under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>) or to municipalities or other units of local government that may administer repairs to a property receiving such project-based subsidy contracts, $250,000,000, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DCFF9C996B144559C4F19AAEB664F56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Set aside for new construction</header><paragraph id="H6A86AEA08D334B67BF73EA51A1FD1019"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Set aside</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the total amount of funds provided pursuant to this section, not less than 10 percent shall be available to eligible recipients described in subsection (a) for the purpose of adding new dwelling units to properties already receiving project-based subsidy contracts under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F4FE7E733954722A3F33B3915B95B22"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>Funds made available under this subsection for new construction may only be used by an eligible recipients who are already receiving an award for rehabilitation under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE549D21017544222A9F71948B5A6697D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority of work</header><text>Eligible recipients who receive funds for both new construction and for rehabilitation shall complete rehabilitation work before beginning new construction and shall provide certification to the Secretary, in a manner to be determined by the Secretary, that the rehabilitation has been completed in a satisfactory manner to eliminate health and safety risks before receiving any funds for new construction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A6F2782BECA4ABEBEF24E9380C1D1AB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Model building standards</header><text>Within one year after the publication of the model building standards under section 7(b)(4), the Secretary shall require eligible recipients who receive funds for new construction and rehabilitation to ensure that new construction and rehabilitation projects are in compliance with the model building standards and techniques developed under section 7(b)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7892BDECF2A94DDEA6C44A557E558735"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Set-Aside for technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the total amount of funds provided pursuant to this section, not less than 3 percent shall be used to provide technical assistance to applicants and to advertise the availability of funds under this section to areas disproportionately impacted by health and safety concerns in federally-assisted housing.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC37F30B8BA2B42D3BFF2208602A1A211"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><paragraph id="H2BEE763CA6EF465ABC5C4F3614D99E31"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts provided pursuant to this section shall be used for competitive grants and low-interest loans for capital improvements to such properties, including grants for activities that mitigate threats to the health and safety of residents, reduce lead-based paint hazards, reduce other housing-related hazards, including carbon monoxide, radon, or indoor residential mold, improve water and energy efficiency, or reduce the risk of harm to occupants or property from natural hazards, or for low-interest loans for the same use. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46BA961615194BAF9105D17974D4F542"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Loan and grant eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An owner of such a property shall be eligible for—</text><subparagraph id="H461D33652D0245909EBCF87DBDDF39BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a grant under this section only if such owner is a nonprofit entity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AF608B06C3B4E28A1B03DA62952B994"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a low-interest loan under this section only if such owner is a for-profit individual or entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D1A6863BC774420B51718C702454CC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligibility of units of local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A municipal government, county, or other unit of local government may receive a grant under this section if sufficient capacity is demonstrated in their application to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A42495AC838493181DB10A1C79C5BAF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants for areas of high and persistent poverty</header><text>Of any amounts made available pursuant to this section, not less than 30 percent shall be available without regard to any requirement regarding minimum grant amount and only for eligible uses within or directly benefitting—</text><paragraph id="H1B0FD378DA5E472F810F6CB80E7AD237"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any county that has consistently had 20 percent or more of the population living in poverty during the 30-year period preceding the date of enactment of this Act, as measured by the decennial census data obtained during those years and the most recent annual Small Area Income and Poverty Estimates as estimated by the Bureau of the Census;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H262F13B6419A4FC7B057470D564EF4E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any census tract having a poverty rate of at least 20 percent as measured by the most recent 5-year data series available from the American Community Survey of the Census Bureau; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H762099476936464C9F9D0571110CBC75"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any census tract having a predominantly disenfranchised population or a population disproportionately impacted by health and safety hazards in federally-assisted housing (as defined by the Secretary).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9158643866E44DB7B4E522513EFB9780"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall prioritize awards that ameliorate or prevent indoor residential mold or other severe health or safety threats.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDDEB13A1072B4AC59B9796DC2300047C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Wage rate requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Projects funded with funds provided under this section shall comply with the same requirements of subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code that are applicable to contracts described in section 3142(a) of such title.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4897D489BED4C0293F309C00C488396"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Policies; procedures; contracts</header><text>Grants and low-interest loans under this section shall—</text><paragraph id="H04A54548E7F44B59B55037C614C72B64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be provided through the policies, procedures, contracts, and transactional infrastructure of the authorized programs administered by the Department of Housing and Urban Development, on such terms and conditions as the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development deems appropriate to ensure the maintenance and preservation of the property, the continued operation and maintenance of energy efficiency technologies, and the timely expenditure of funds; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H790DC55CB9EE43908A20D911D0EC26EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include a financial assessment and physical inspection of such property.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H90D7D0BC7E0F4DB3AC7578391C98435C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible owners</header><text>To be eligible for a grant or low-interest loan under this section, the owner of the property shall have at least a satisfactory management and occupancy review rating, be in substantial compliance with applicable performance standards and legal requirements, and commit to an additional period of affordability determined by the Secretary, but of not fewer than 50 years. Owners shall include nonprofit owners and preservation purchasers, including public housing agencies and nonprofit developers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H01ACDE5FA742416BA184B63301B67184"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Loan terms</header><paragraph id="H0566782E769847EBA3894F9AB3BB1C6A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A loan under this section shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD9FE48554E2F486FA6B11055851D1B21"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">bear interest at a rate, determined by the Secretary, that—</text><clause id="H3301F94F99914606B6D473DC62C7A28B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>does not exceed by 3 percentage points the discount window primary credit interest rate most recently published on the Federal Reserve Statistical Release on selected interest rates (daily or weekly), commonly referred to as the <quote>H.15 release</quote> or the <quote>Federal funds rate</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H60F98EF99EE54F39B5D0AB5383849472"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is below the average interest rate at the given time for a home improvement loan; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DA695387AAA493EBD0C80A9C7406B45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a term to maturity of 10 years or 20 years, as determined by the Secretary based on the credit of the borrower.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B225738FC674284A28792563FB26786"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Violations</header><text>If the owner of a property receiving a loan under this section does not use the loan amounts as required under subsection (b)(1), does not maintain the affordability of the property as required under subsection (i), or does not comply with any other requirements established by the Secretary, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2CFE1D001F184785B139119319783846"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">work with the owner for not less than 30 days to ameliorate any violations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H389B32692D2949DD8F17C2FBF4B42F91"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if after 90 days such violations are not ameliorated—</text><clause id="H62AB729971924AE49D8073E49EA4CE0E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>increase the interest rate of the loan by not less than 15 percentage points above the Federal funds rate; and</text></clause><clause id="H77A2165AF6FB41B8BC37F938209154DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reduce the term to maturity of the loan to not more than 5 years.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06BB89453CB545C79879DD944732DA35"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Conditions of receipt of grant or loan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish conditions on the receipt of a loan or grant under this section, as follows:</text><paragraph id="H94362F2C8EDA4B4D94B2B34C71AB9E48"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Record; capacity</header><text>The Secretary shall take reasonable steps to ensure that the owner or purchaser has no significant record of material noncompliance with applicable program standards and has demonstrated capacity to perform the obligations specified under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H367787EA5B884878B368B3C036551AEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Repairs</header><text>The Secretary shall require owners to agree to promptly make all required repairs, and when required by the Secretary, to develop a rehabilitation plan in consultation with the tenants and that will be approved by the Secretary, in conjunction with appropriate capital needs planning and required reserves, to ensure the provision of decent, safe, and sanitary housing throughout the full term of any extended restrictions and contracts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF40A9147A90453AB4B19A872A8224CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use restrictions</header><text>The Secretary shall require owners to agree to a longer use restriction of 50 years and to agree to a perpetually required renewal of the housing assistance payments contract if offered by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA40714E4089841C98262C0BD0401FCA5"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Transfer authority</header><text>Of the amounts made available pursuant to this section, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development may transfer up to 0.5 percent to the account for <quote>Department of Housing and Urban Development, Program Offices—Office of Housing</quote> for necessary costs of administering and overseeing the obligation and expenditure of amounts made available pursuant to this section and such transferred amounts shall remain available until September 30, 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA6715D9CDC9C4152ADE4667E678EA1B5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>9.</enum><header>Public information and education campaign</header><subsection id="HDEB13ACCF6064B0BBE7B8A8C3AF35EB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, and the heads of any other relevant Federal agencies, as determined by such Administrator and Secretary, shall jointly develop and carry out a public information and education campaign regarding indoor air quality and related issues that provides information required under this section on a recurring and annual basis through public outreach. The campaign shall commence within 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection><subsection id="H19012B814F1147AA853A9F9830CFC853"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Topics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information and education campaign shall include information on the dangers and prevention of indoor residential moisture and mold, volatile organic compounds, dust, smoking, pollution, indoor origins of smoke, including cooking, and any other health risks, as determined by such Administrator and Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCA38008F7A2147E48958A95A7BBCB070"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Indoor residential mold information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information and education campaign shall include, at minimum, the following information regarding indoor residential mold:</text><paragraph id="H621F7A32E70443088AAB156B6E232989"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The conditions that facilitate indoor residential moisture and mold growth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB44FA52B44747DDB9253473C47612C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Guidelines for inspecting indoor residential mold growth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8821C63306848C0880A40A62C24D6CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Guidelines for remediating indoor residential mold growth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAE55232ADBC4DF1A98AE430BDFD18B0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The dangers and health risks of exposure to indoor residential mold growth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21A2EA13CA6F4E1487CE75FD3A04B4BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The importance of ventilation and methods to prevent moisture accumulation in indoor residential environments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H648737A717E2465FB86F10D244D3F836"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any other information as determined appropriate by the heads of the agencies referred to in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B9EA75EA20F4C86B8AB51F6C368A2F0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Tenant rights information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information and education campaign shall include providing covered tenants with information on tenant rights to a safe and habitable living environment and other related information as determined by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, which shall include information on who to contact if a tenant experiences problems or issues with building management or ownership, including, in the case of housing assisted under a contract for project-based assistance how to contact the performance-based contract administrator and, in the case of the Housing Choice Voucher program how to contact the housing authority.</text></subsection><subsection id="H33E5EC431740442997B6E07A420DEF62"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Modes of communication</header><paragraph id="H745E86F45A5C40B680A5CEEB24384BEF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The public information and education campaign shall provide education and information through modes of communication that are commonly utilized and able to be easily consumed by relevant individuals or organizations, which shall include communication through advertisements on public transit in all 50 States and in territories and possessions of the United States, and distribution of the pamphlet developed pursuant to subsection (j) as required under such subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E89D259E7A1403E931661213ED11E3D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All education and information that is part of the information and education campaign shall be made publicly available on the websites of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Department of Housing and Urban Development, and any other applicable Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA32811D56AE4BCB83530C403E64C2F3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Targeted groups</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The public information and education campaign shall be designed to reach tenants, tenant organizations working directly with tenants in project-based rental assistance and other types of federally-assisted housing, resident groups, landlords, health professionals, the general public, homeowners, prospective homeowners, the real estate industry, the home construction and renovation industries, the health, property and casualty, and life insurance industries, technical and vocational schools and colleges, and other academic institutions.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF70A48E02FF461FA0334836333C3486"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Information Specific to Health Professions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The public information and education campaign shall include information about warning signs of mold and other indoor air exposure pollutants and shall include education for health professions on mold-related illness, including for health professions who work with vulnerable populations and children in school or daycare settings.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94467DE2C889468DABC542A833C9585F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing and carrying out the public information and education campaign, the heads of the agencies referred to in subsection (a) may coordinate with the Ad Council.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5524F871719438EBF65BB092C2CE396"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Language</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All information provided under the public information and education campaign—</text><paragraph id="HD2E957D3AFC04ACAB03CFC4DA845F8C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be provided in at least two languages, as determined by the Secretary, based on the most common languages spoken in the neighborhood, tribe, municipality, State, or region, and may be provided in additional languages based on the most common languages spoken in the neighborhood, tribe, municipality, State, or region, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D9C1654FF7643A8BF6919D612893951"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be provided in language that is at a sixth grade reading level and is easy to understand.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8ADD020D64647F480B5FAEACD9E8912"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Provision to covered tenants</header><paragraph id="H491E7980373B459EA06F5C3739CA757E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, and the Attorney General shall ensure that all appropriate information under the information and education campaign is provided to covered tenants upon signing and any renewal of a lease for the dwelling unit of assisted housing that the covered tenant resides in.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96793EC7008E4A67A82A093DE1159350"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered tenants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>covered tenant</quote> means a tenant who resides in a rental dwelling unit that is assisted, through tenant-based or project-based assistance, under a housing assistance program administered by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development or the Secretary of Agriculture or who receives rental housing assistance under a program administered by either such Secretary, including the following programs: </text><subparagraph id="HEAB6CD605DB64C6EA22AE1C1D083A665"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>), including the direct loan program under such section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F0914AC6F73401D8EBFB8D0F7E718D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The program under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC0045C45F874CAFBF60CE666B26F4AC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The program under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FAFC6E4ECAE41D4AFE25B8AFFC9A23A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The programs under title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H221EC1BF50C14796B2A1550D9F117100"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The program under subtitle A of title II of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12741">42 U.S.C. 12741 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72D9688153154DDBA58125C2ADD84C72"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The program under paragraph (3) of section 221(d) of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715l">12 U.S.C. 1715l(d)</external-xref>) that bears interest at a rate determined under the proviso under paragraph (5) of such section 221(d).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H130AC25A645F4CEE986C4D1740EDF29E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The program under section 236 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715z-1">12 U.S.C. 1715z–1</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07961043C4B54B87B61908500F75190B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The programs under sections 6 and 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437d">42 U.S.C. 1437d</external-xref>, 1437f).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAE40E6F6FC447B8A81311A9D31FC743"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The programs for rural housing assistance provided under sections 514, 515, 516, 533, 538, and 542 of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1484">42 U.S.C. 1484</external-xref>, 1485, 1486, 1490m, 1490p–2, 1490r).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F7D954E9D224BCA930186D278366FD7" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The low-income housing tax credit program under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/42">section 42</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50CC113B78594761B80E262575F9B805"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of assistance from the Housing Trust Fund established under section 1338 of the Federal Housing Enterprises Financial Safety and Soundness Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4568">12 U.S.C. 4568</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD84F06D18BE4A9AB445EDEC261B2015"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The provision of assistance for housing under the Comprehensive Service Programs for Homeless Veterans program under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/20">chapter 20</external-xref> of title 38.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F9703AF73904B9C97BBC50013FBD253"><enum>(M)</enum><text>The provision of assistance for housing and facilities under the grant program for homeless veterans with special needs under section 2061 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H450A56A409C6436595F57D32E821BD73"><enum>(N)</enum><text>The provision of assistance for permanent housing under the program for financial assistance for supportive services for very low-income veteran families in permanent housing under section 2044 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE409C51CCB09417BAABCA0003C0E9DFF"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of transitional housing assistance for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, or stalking under the grant program under chapter 11 of subtitle B of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12351">34 U.S.C. 12351 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7B382F2D1EC431F97D3CA06B5AF8EC7"><enum>(P)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Low Income Home Energy Assistance Program and any other program administered by the Department of Energy that provides residential home rehabilitation or energy efficiency assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC44320DBC69C47028050CB77D27DC909"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>Any other Federal housing programs providing affordable housing to low- and moderate-income persons by means of restricted rents or rental assistance, or more generally providing affordable housing opportunities, as identified by the appropriate agency through regulations, notices, or any other means.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31839989DA0F45D68F9E51547D053D00"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Pamphlet</header><paragraph id="H8B2F6504FE694EA8B1B87D139CABE777"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, in consultation with the Director of the National Institutes of Health, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the heads of any other agencies the Secretary considers appropriate, shall develop, publish, and revise, not less frequently than every 5 years, a pamphlet regarding indoor residential mold hazards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81FD0CB5F9964C24AD7359B81475F1E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content</header><text>The pamphlet required under this subsection shall—</text><subparagraph id="HF5E8EEE8E1014A0ABA10ED8C2E03CAE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contain information regarding the health risks associated with exposure to indoor residential mold growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99D783E62EC84815A02B00A76FD13FBE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information on the hazards of indoor residential mold growth in federally-assisted and federally-owned housing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H431AB74E9EEB46AD9A340F685B34D4C7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe the risks of indoor residential mold exposure for persons residing in a dwelling with toxigenic mold;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H741B638961E048BB804ED98EBE8B7ECE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information on approved methods for evaluating and reducing indoor residential mold growth and their effectiveness in identifying, reducing, eliminating, or preventing indoor residential mold growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3153A8F3B4C4CD3AB4DC6128B11A234"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide advice on how to obtain a list of persons certified to inspect or remediate indoor residential mold growth in the area in which the pamphlet is to be used;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F8023BCFF8340F0A1B103CEC873872B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a statement that a risk assessment or inspection for indoor residential mold growth is recommended prior to the purchase, lease, or renovation of target housing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA38519617254E8C9BA01E00808DB511"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a statement that certain State and local laws impose additional requirements related to indoor residential mold growth in housing and provide a listing of Federal, State, and local agencies in each State, including address, telephone number, and electronic mail address, if available, that can provide information about applicable laws and available governmental and private assistance and financing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA85DB7CCDDE94F278EEE1CC54A5D5CB4"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information considered by the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to be appropriate or necessary to promote awareness of the hazards posed by indoor residential mold;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C8D7F4E12304CBE9AEE2B0F44521B96"><enum>(I)</enum><text>include information on indoor air quality safety generally, including best practices when cooking, taking a shower or bath, and smoking cessation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H448247C94A7044CD86C1C22306C21DF0"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be publicly available on the websites of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, the Environmental Protection Agency, and other applicable Federal agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70806335824644D4B72FDBF95706AD32"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include any other information considered by the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to be appropriate or necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB50E9051D7884CB59BC6CBAB936041AC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tenants in federally-assisted housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development and the Secretary of Agriculture shall ensure that a copy of the pamphlet required under this section is provided annually to all covered tenants mail by a hard copy left at the tenant address, by United States mail sent to the tenant, or by electronic mail sent to the tenant. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F8664CFF1744E4590A3DE29DA9E3405"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2F1F3C8D418E49F3A184821EA0BB4404" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>10.</enum><header>Empowering tenants</header><subsection id="H70625759AD714BB29DAADF98E2F007AD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification to tenants of inspection results</header><paragraph id="H5737B5AE15A749AFB334BFE35EDF5235"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall provide direct notification of the results of any inspection of covered property to the tenants and resident organizations, as provided in this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56A1F717A6D644C69E707BF74CB3D49D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Method</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notification shall be provided to tenants in easy-to-understand language in the form of a written hard-copy document provided through United States mail or through electronic mail, or both, with one copy provided for the tenants of each building in the covered property, and shall include the inspection score and a detailed description of the inspection results, including any health and safety violations found and the timeline for their remediation, while ensuring tenant privacy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3C794C3166B4073B3BF224D7A885646"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Posting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The owner or manager of the covered property shall post a hard copy of the notification of the inspection results in at least one centrally located and easily-identifiable location each building of the covered property that is accessible to all tenants, which may include next to the front door, in communal space, or next to the mailboxes for tenants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF2151908B3B44E28408778C9075B4DB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notification shall be provided—</text><subparagraph id="H67FF596988574915889E77F7CB92425C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of any inspection that found no severe health or safety issues, no later than 30 days after completion of the inspection; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF00966B0628A453CB9DE1A682FE7C08E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any inspection that found severe health and safety issues, as soon as the score is final.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D87F97AFCFC4071AFFFB62E427531C7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Opportunity for tenant questions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The notification shall include contact information, including electronic mail address, phone number, and mailing address, of the appropriate person or entity to contact should tenants have questions about the results of the inspection. Owners who fail to post the notice shall be subject to a Management and Occupancy Review.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF8BF3A1BAD24C56901B7F0317961367"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Request for second inspection</header><paragraph id="HF03AD1E3FA224DD6B9A4F87A1D5927A1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursuant to a request made to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Secretary shall carry out a subsequent inspection for a covered property that has passed a previous inspection, if the following requirements are met:</text><subparagraph id="H8E595C5CEBA94DAAB466D70177976B23"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Score</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The passing test score for the previous inspection for the covered property did not exceed the minimum score required to pass inspection by more than 15 percent or the most recent score for an inspection for the covered property is 15 percent or more less than any other score for the property for an inspection of the property conducted during the preceding 10-year period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H330D77E82EBE41A8866EC671CA937ED9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Tenant vote</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vote of tenants of the covered property was conducted on the proposition of whether the property should have passed the most recent inspection, which vote—</text><clause id="HE2C5850B362E4FCBA5A3CC88F9286F2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was administered by the tenant association for the property or an independent third party;</text></clause><clause id="HA2A42FBC82EA4C6595A4FC656E36D266"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilizes the democratic process and may have utilized an anonymous voting platform, either electronically or through paper ballots, for casting votes; and</text></clause><clause id="HA6B96F495CD54C0D9146B97E0D3ADB48"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">resulted in 51 percent or more of the tenants residing in the property voting against the proposition that the property should have passed the most recent inspection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45554DB6743F4276B6444179996ACBE3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notification</header><clause id="H6A22A4ACDBC5477389E87EB1614E3DE6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>To HUD</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The chief executive officer of the tenants association notifies the Secretary, the project-based contract administrator for the covered property, and the owner or management of the property of the results of the vote and requests a second inspection for the covered property, which notification and request—</text><subclause id="H96605CC05C004FDF9A0D0640F9CCA610"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a copy of the tally of the vote;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAF43ED23B033459089DA5EAC73185865"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not, in verifying the 51 percent majority vote, disclose personally identifiable information of the tenants, including by their signatures; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H591722EAB0854B6DACEB4E110D0EFACC"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is transmitted, both by electronic mail and by mailing a hard copy, not later than 60 days after receipt of the notification under subsection (a) regarding the passing result of the previous inspection for the covered property.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H49825175732346C2B3F76F72A8767651"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notification of second inspection score</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tenants shall be notified of the score of the second inspection using the same notification criteria as apply to the first inspection and shall be provided with the contact information of the person or entity that they can contact with any questions about the second inspection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H57315037757A4EE88E211C255C29AEAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mediation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a second inspection is conducted pursuant to a vote under paragraph (1) and the covered property is assessed a passing score for such second inspection, and if another vote is taken that complies with the same requirements applicable under such paragraph to the first inspection, and such vote results in 51 percent or more of the tenants residing in the property voting against the proposition that the property should have passed the second inspection, the Secretary shall provide a tenant association representative an opportunity for mediation with the building owner and the project-based contractor administrator regarding continuing issues and inspection findings and the process for a Management and Occupancy Review shall begin concurrently. The mediation shall be conducted within 180 days of the second inspection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD1E1BCEEE0646FFA87726B6865A526C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tenant hotline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Commencing not later 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall—</text><paragraph id="H9C4EC9D835C14847BD7C632CDB602A4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>undertake ongoing activities to advertise the availability and telephone number of the Multifamily Housing Complaint Line of the Multifamily Housing Clearinghouse;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03188E51F7B4457D817C6433518B0B8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>periodically provide tenants of covered property, through the website of the Department and otherwise, as the Secretary considers appropriate, with information about what happens when they call the complaint line;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF599EB73A733445AA8B3247640DF9AA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide sufficient staff for the complaint line to ensure that the complaint line is sufficiently staffed for a minimum of 12 hours each day and so that the waiting time to speak live to an employee of the Department does not exceed 15 minutes on average as measured over a given one-week period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D9A65F05E44426DA3445E2B2D54EC2A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure that the complaint line offers tenants of covered properties intake for health and safety issues at such properties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA124EDBAA444A29AA3FA4DDE5AD40D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensure that upon calling the complaint line, a tenant of a covered property is first informed of how to contact the project-based contract administrator for the property to discuss the issue the tenant called about, and if the tenant has previously contacted such administrator or does not wish to involve such administrator, the person answering the call on the complaint line is capable of providing assistance for the tenant directly or can intake tenant information to assist with the request;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7E91FE576CC4926ACCA70CE20FABAE6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>ensure that if the complaint line has received calls within any 60-day period from tenants of a covered property representing 15 percent or more of the dwelling units in the property, the appropriate regional office of the Department shall be notified; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B72C066D15A48CEB0D678AE0D976323"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that if within three months after the notification of the appropriate regional office of the Department, the tenant hotline has received any additional calls from tenants of the same covered property, the headquarters office of the Department shall be notified; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD34BE1D2018F4DE482DD9C2B18AA7D85"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide availability of translation services for the complaint line.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA576FF5A7CA04B678E5A90AC32F3AC14" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Covered property</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>covered property</quote> means a multifamily housing property that is subject to inspection by the Real Estate Assessment Center of the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89976FBE06DE409DBD7D7DC7CF78DCA4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advance notice to tenants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall update inspection procedures and requirements to ensure that tenants of covered properties have at least 7 days of advance notice of when their building will be inspected. In the advance notice of inspection, tenants shall be provided the opportunity to inform the Department of Housing and Urban Development or inspectors, or both, of specific issues regarding the unit or building.</text></subsection></section><section id="H14CD7A14C4A8460E8E838A7E59772638"><enum>11.</enum><header>Healthy Homes incentive for requiring indoor residential mold and other hazard disclosure</header><subsection id="H2215AB6A4A82466BA4B20B505844405B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Supplemental healthy homes funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for use under the Healthy Homes Initiative, pursuant to sections 501 and 502 of the Housing and Urban Development Act of 1970 (12 U.S.C. 1701z–1 and 1701z–2), and for related activities and assistance, $80,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2028, for financial awards under this section. Amounts appropriated pursuant to this section shall supplement, but not supplant, amounts otherwise appropriated. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6902B41670734B2282000FA379074103"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Financial awards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall provide financial awards under this section for a fiscal year to each State, Indian tribe, county, unit of local government, and other unit of government that requires, to the satisfaction of the Secretary, that during such fiscal year sellers of residential properties containing not more than 4 dwelling units shall complete and provide to the purchaser a disclosure form indicating the presence of all environmental hazards, including radon, carbon monoxide, formaldeyde, lead, asbestos, and indoor residential mold, that are known to the seller. Such a disclosure form shall be its own conspicuous form that includes information regarding health and dangers about such environmental hazards.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC94926D78944FDD98BD01327009BFA5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts provided as financial awards pursuant to this section shall be used only for activities that make health-related improvements to housing units that serve primarily low-income persons and are located within the jurisdiction of the State, Indian tribe, county, local government, or other unit of government that is awarded such assistance.</text></subsection></section><section id="H400C61708C884BB7AD643B2F3ACB3080"><enum>12.</enum><header>Uniform physical inspection sampling</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall revise the regulations of the Secretary under subpart G of part 5 of title 24, Code of Federal Regulations (relating to physical condition standards and inspection requirements), as follows:</text><paragraph id="H909EBDAD781248F392557290940CAD65"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual inspections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In section 5.705, as amended by the final rule for National Standards for the Physical Inspection of Real Estate (88 Fed. Reg. 30442), to provide that physical inspections are conducted annually without exception.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7483F2EFC6BC4A20AF1A2E337FA7F8A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sampling of units</header><text>To provide that, in carrying out uniform physical inspection requirements under an annual inspection, the Department of Housing and Urban Development shall ensure that any units in HUD housing that were not inspected during the previous two annual inspections shall be inspected during the next occurring annual inspection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99626B01FE844146BA0259038EE2BC73"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inclusion of priority units in score</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out uniform physical inspection requirements under an annual inspection, the Department of Housing and Urban Development shall ensure that any and all individual units requested to be inspected by tenants are included as part of the composite score of the property.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H973493B7146843ADAC9B1959722FD1C7" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>13.</enum><header>Denial of depreciation deduction for properties with failed NSPIRE inspections</header><subsection id="H28A413136BE245728385F016845ED731" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/167">Section 167</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (i) as subsection (j) and by inserting after subsection (h) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H41760AAACB524C6EA7FAD49A68865A87"><subsection id="HB36F7C7AC24A445085FF3CCA6353C4B9" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Disallowance of depreciation deduction for property which fails national standards for the physical inspection of real estate</header><paragraph id="HD879CE6A03AF4495823FCE8438599B44" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), no depreciation deduction shall be allowed under this section (and no depreciation or amortization deduction shall be allowed under any other provision of this subtitle) to the taxpayer for the taxable year with respect to any property described in section 168(e)(2)(A)(i) which fails an NSPIRE inspection during the taxable year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0230596ECCA04BC08A512A9E18AF9E38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="H44111F8A949F40A29547BBF6AF266113"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No deduction shall be denied under paragraph (1) in the case of a health or safety violation which causes a property to fail an NSPIRE inspection if either—</text><clause id="H056010D5B5B347CCA782F864AC083229"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such violation is cured within 90 days of the date of a failed inspection, or</text></clause><clause id="HB3902258DEB74225A693B2B8BC3C01DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the inspector finds sufficient evidence that such violation was caused by the tenant and not by the owner or management of the property. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40A30BA5932A46929E42D05445EC544E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extension of time to cure</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services may provide 30-day extensions of the 90-day period described in subparagraph (A)(i) on a case-by-case basis and communicate such extensions to the Secretary of the Treasury. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7AD319CDE0241ECA08C73C54F172F9C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>NSPIRE inspection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>NSPIRE inspection</quote> means any housing inspection required under the National Standards for the Physical Inspection of Real Estate of the Real Estate Assessment Center of the Department of Housing and Urban Development. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BC16E6E139C4D469BAF0983E2E48B0C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Increased duration for disallowance in the case of multiple failed inspections</header><text>In the case of a property which fails two consecutive NSPIRE inspections, paragraph (1) shall be applied by substituting <quote>for the taxable year, and for the immediately succeeding taxable year,</quote> for <quote>for the taxable year</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7761ACFF35B4D9092CFBC5D0C839F4B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Disallowed depreciation amounts may not be taken in future year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The depreciation deduction allowed with respect to the property described in paragraph (1) with respect to any future taxable year shall be determined without regard to the amount denied for any year for which such deduction was denied.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD83A1A95DA434AB183A9C31DCBBCD155"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Basis adjustments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, but for this subsection, a depreciation or amortization deduction would be allowable to the taxpayer with respect to any property—</text><subparagraph id="HA246F06C20DE471E9BC8B84E560782BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the taxpayer’s basis in such property shall be reduced by any depreciation or amortization deductions disallowed under this subsection, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBAA5C25CA19403080F839A3E7C3C538"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the basis of the remainder interest in such property shall be increased by the amount of such disallowed deductions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD336222E8CF64790AC9581E1FB305F9A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><subparagraph id="H795F6EA2EDC54956AEBED40EC1895427"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, after consultation with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes of this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31466AADA8224BB7A40019F0E9097744"><enum>(B)</enum><header>HUD Secretary</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall prescribe regulations to establish a mechanism for providing information to the Secretary detailing which properties have failed an NSPIRE inspection during the taxable year and which properties have received extensions of time to cure. In creating this mechanism, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall ensure that the Secretary of the Treasury receives information about failing properties at least once per calendar quarter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H5566EA3F9D9542398D67B43B7D864DB8" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date that is one year after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="H9E7DB6D5AB744171B5EE526DB54AF0A0"><enum>14.</enum><header>Supporting landlords to receive timely voucher payments</header><subsection id="H793502E931C0475C8ECED724657D3B88"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding and other provision of law, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall allow public housing agencies to approve a tenancy using a voucher provided under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) and make a payment under such voucher before inspection of the dwelling unit if the inspection will be conducted more than 14 days after receiving a tenancy package.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2555A18A7DBE4F20BEFB90025533DF48"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Failed inspections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the unit fails inspection and is not brought into compliance within 14 days, the owner of the unit shall repay the payment received from the public housing agency within the following 14 days and shall not hold the tenant responsible for payment and shall not evict or terminate the tenant on such basis. If the tenant is in the unit at the time the payment is issued but the unit does not pass inspection, the public housing agency shall be responsible for relocating the tenant and providing additional assistance.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE6E86FD9E69540AEA7A3E2A88FC95C35"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional incentives</header><text>Within 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall establish additional incentives for public housing agencies to perform expedited inspection of dwelling units.</text></subsection></section><section id="H78D06604575D4FFCA7353554BDB39C0A"><enum>15.</enum><header>Project-based contract administrator reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall require, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, that project-based contract administrators shall submit to the Secretary data on projects and project owners covering the previous 180 days, including an analysis of any trends identified over the previous 180 days on housing conditions, tenant complaints, tenant hospitalizations brought to the attention of the contract administrator, and any other information as required by the Secretary. </text></section><section id="HB774F673FEE7499FA935FE1D4260C936" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>16.</enum><header>Coordination Between USDA and HUD</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall ensure, to the greatest extent practicable, that the minimum requirements and physical quality standards for housing properties assisted by the Department of Agriculture meet or exceed the standards established by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development pursuant to section 4 of this Act.</text></section><section id="HEC180D56DE954BBAAAB58F55CAC7D6C4"><enum>17.</enum><header>GAO study on health and safety concerns in federally-assisted housing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than the expiration of the 3-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to the Congress analyzing and assessing the communication, as applicable, between public housing agencies, landlords, and tenants over resolving problems with the health, safety, or other issues of dwelling units that are federally subsidized and inspected through subpart G of part 5 of title 24, Code of Federal Regulations, landlord responsiveness regarding such issues, opportunities for improvement in such communications, and how tenants understand their rights and how they are responded to when issues arise, including protocols for responding to tenant complaints and tenant understanding of such processes. The report shall include recommendations for how to improve such communications and the physical quality of the housing stock for which such assistance is provided.</text></section><section id="H4C1403DE4C2E48AC804052FF850A0644"><enum>18.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that the Departments of the Treasury and Housing and Urban Development should work together cooperatively, including through development of a Memorandum of Understanding if appropriate, to ensure that implementation of this Act is consistent with the provisions of the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3601">42 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></section><section id="HF45CCB9389A04BD99965B829872520B3"><enum>19.</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development—</text><paragraph id="HD34E0CEEED5D4A65B643E537930458D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2024, for costs to the Department of implementing this Act and the amendments made by this Act, including costs of providing staff to carry out this Act and such amendments; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4F615BA687042D28769F0973B7E4987"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 and 2026 for continuing costs of carrying out this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

