<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE45BA743B3254C228C30A674899203C4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1670 IH: Making Access To Cleanup Happen Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1670</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230321">March 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Credit Act of 1978 with respect to pre-agreement costs of emergency watershed protection measures, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB8973B844F8F486CB60F3E3958CD8A33" style="OLC"><section id="H036517A1F98F4AFA93316D12C382603C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Making Access To Cleanup Happen Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MATCH Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5EF4BE7EC66D4375BE9B78893DEA1EE9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Emergency watershed program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 403 of the Agricultural Credit Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2203">16 U.S.C. 2203</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HE809FDF49510420EB3E32BA0B56D7772" style="OLC"><subsection id="H7D6D8EF7A5154ACAB4B8FB8EADF3A4ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pre-Agreement costs</header><paragraph id="H80664BFB602C41729367F82441917417"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sponsor</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>sponsor</term> means a State or local government, or an Indian Tribe (as defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/450b">25 U.S.C. 450b</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2031854A5A041DFBA37087614D637BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pre-agreement project costs</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H0F50C6A290EB4B9D9B7777FE727DA354"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify a list of emergency watershed protection measures the cost of which may be incurred by a sponsor prior to entering into an agreement with the Secretary pursuant to this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC1861004963415D929CAC3EF5B57A60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop a procedure, including appropriate deadlines, to be implemented at the State level, through which a sponsor may request, for a specified natural disaster, additional emergency watershed protection measures the cost of which may be incurred by a sponsor prior to entering into an agreement with the Secretary pursuant to this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59CBE9E2C5D64825890D67E7812D54AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Agreement contribution</header><text>If the Secretary and the sponsor enter into an agreement pursuant to this section, the Secretary shall consider any applicable pre-agreement costs incurred by a sponsor for undertaking emergency watershed protection measures identified pursuant to paragraph (2) as meeting part of the sponsor’s contribution towards the project costs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C33EA97CB9942B7B8B2C352BEA6FC58"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Assumption of risk</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection requires the Secretary to enter into an agreement with a sponsor, and a sponsor undertaking emergency watershed protection measures prior to entering into an agreement with the Secretary pursuant to this section shall assume the risk of incurring any costs of undertaking such measures.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

