<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H609EDC9924764513BE9C272D111DF319" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3879 IH: Supporting Families through Addiction Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3879</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a grant program for family community organizations that provide support for individuals struggling with substance use disorder and their families.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCE7B7A4E2B2745119A5F9557DC581A6F" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC830D1C8926B442694A315B9C9690AE1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Families through Addiction Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBC4E4604A0DC49818D25BCC33CED12BD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Family support services for families of individuals struggling with substance use disorder</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290dd">42 U.S.C. 290dd et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H858B269AF343476385EF4D80DA699661"><section id="H106FB9B5B4924869BAAC38064DC6D9C1"><enum>553.</enum><header>Family support services for families of individuals struggling with substance use disorder</header><subsection id="H61CBDEF44C4A45689E6188DA8EF2B5B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HC09082E9570844C081E39B6C5480C873"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>family community organization</term> means an independent nonprofit organization that—</text><subparagraph id="HD41098BB514245AFA3867F73FF7763DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>mobilizes resources within and outside of the community of families that include an individual living with a substance use disorder, to provide a support network, education, and evidence-informed tools for families and loved ones of individuals struggling with substance use disorders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8E9724FB1A8453B9654B2A93D16DF3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is governed by experts in the field of substance use disorder, which may include—</text><clause id="H3D1184F4815A40298A73FCE445424C4F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>experts in evidence-informed interventions for family members;</text></clause><clause id="HE2884427DA9E48728EF64D74D1152E70"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>experts in the impact of substance use disorder on family systems;</text></clause><clause id="H60C3518AEBEA4CC08F135E40E74CD12C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>families who have experience with substance use disorder; and</text></clause><clause id="H3C6D8B119ABE48938F45948557AE07B4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other experts in the field of substance use disorder; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1934B680D1D845719D1523C6FC3B7B05"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>family support services</term> means resources or programs that support families that include an individual with substance use disorder.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2E7271695854A7C896B09B162B3B9FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to family community organizations to enable such organizations to develop, expand, and enhance evidence-informed family support services.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7146F4E2DBEA40669BBAEA92674349FE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the costs of a program funded by a grant under this section may not exceed 85 percent.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE3FDFCC7BFE54AA79803ECA30E5ECB50"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Grants awarded under subsection (b)—</text><paragraph id="H86008AEAEEBD496BB5F52D04994C7982"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be used to develop, expand, and enhance community, Tribal, and statewide evidence-informed family support services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37CF21BEEE99416F8C677A385466F32D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may be used to—</text><subparagraph id="HF9FCDC6A56DD488FB9E93353352C4F9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>build connections between family support networks, including providing technical assistance between family community organizations and peer support networks, and with other family support services, focused on enhancing knowledge of evidence-informed interventions for family members and loved ones of individuals living with substance use disorders and reducing harm by educating service providers on current evidence regarding substance use disorder and the family, including—</text><clause id="H4C9C898D064B4FA38822F5180CE604A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>behavioral health providers, including such providers focused specifically on family and couples therapy in the context of substance use disorder;</text></clause><clause id="H217F67A8AAD44ECF81B9FD677917EEA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>primary care providers;</text></clause><clause id="HBB05C71075964F5B9E785D6C951F510E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>providers of foster care services or support services for grandparents, guardians, and other extended family impacted by substance use disorder; and</text></clause><clause id="H70063CC14FA4409A851AD2495BBE11A5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other family support services that connect to community resources for individuals with substance use disorders, including non-clinical community services;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6350568F3BA4213B0658B2B79D43341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduce stigma associated with families that include an individual with a substance use disorder by improving knowledge about substance use disorder and its treatment, providing compassionate support, and dispelling myths that perpetuate such stigma;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57CC458158E94C6D835B9CB3B9679759"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conduct outreach on issues relating to substance use disorders and family support, which may include education, training, and resources with respect to—</text><clause id="HECEC3CEC99004D779238D1A99D4B1666"><enum>(i)</enum><text>building a resilience- and strengths-based approach to prevention of, and living with, substance use disorder in the family;</text></clause><clause id="H6AD69F8669EF4206BA062ACB807F1BAD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identifying the signs of substance use disorder;</text></clause><clause id="H4FA8E2AC69B6490B992CFBCAB52D96AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>adopting an approach that minimizes harm to all family members; and</text></clause><clause id="HD8C0A4C5B2784D7A9163A208FE878A56"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>families that include an individual with a substance use disorder, including with respect to—</text><subclause id="HE76C7F2879FF4D7CAB425438215F493A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>navigating the treatment and recovery systems;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3919474CFD0E4906BA98FAA738908FBC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>paying for substance use disorder treatment;</text></subclause><subclause id="H993C7431871A4C5EB101CD693491A9F9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>education about substance use disorder; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H49680D49CE90405586636D24A2D8B910"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>avoiding predatory treatment programs; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF296F7F9C1C4056AB79CAFF8DAFBEA6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>connect families to evidence-informed peer support programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C2CCCE1771D4192B5E4DB68F2FB90C4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Data reporting and program oversight</header><text>With respect to a grant awarded under subsection (a), not later than 90 days after the end of the first year of the grant period, and annually thereafter for the duration of the grant period, the entity shall submit data, as appropriate and to the extent practicable, to the Secretary regarding—</text><paragraph id="HFA3D1EE021CE47BA92C61B2E76D0C429"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the programs and activities funded by the grant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2E5F3F4E7334EAEA2060F865C11AD65"><enum>(2)</enum><text>outcomes for the families of individuals with a substance use disorder who received services through programs supported by the grant, as evaluated by an independent program evaluator through the use of outcomes measures, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC048E403ED242F6B171C3730753B375"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require for the purpose of ensuring that the grant recipient is complying with all the requirements of the grant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E130467D7B14133A76AEAAEB95B123C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

