<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD104D71B9BB149ECBB72E1B5D39E76ED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 452 IH: Education Savings Accounts for Military Families Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 452</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001156">Mr. McHenry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to allow parents of eligible military dependent children to establish Military Education Savings Accounts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1AC3D788DA614AA39B5DE610753D38FA" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H628C059279BF41629E2360DCE64E58B1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Education Savings Accounts for Military Families Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7A55F188FC7F4A0E9198BF30E0DE1361"><enum>2.</enum><header>Military education savings accounts</header><subsection id="HF6B55038E3794F2082D5B236BCFAB970"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VII of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7701">20 U.S.C. 7701 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 7012 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H51AF32F983134743BE843804A4463509"><section id="HB0E4F2ABFE1B47D98802FDB9D800148F"><enum>7012A.</enum><header>Military education savings accounts</header><subsection id="H0B529030391E4C849203BCFADA7733C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Education, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, shall carry out a program under which the Secretary of Education shall—</text><paragraph id="H8CA0438AFDE9476BAAEC6264B39857D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at the request of a parent of an eligible military dependent child, establish an account on behalf of such child (to be known as a <quote>Military Education Savings Account</quote>) into which the Secretary shall deposit funds in an amount determined under subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H456727206BF54FBBAE95313894C98636"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a procedure under which the parent of the child may use funds in the account to pay for the educational expenses of the child in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27F7702A8FBA470D9C29EED391F683AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="HF131FAC699254038A2AAD4CC8A2B204A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to participate in the program under this section for a school year, a parent of an eligible military dependent child shall submit an application to the Secretary in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78FD1742E04F46CEB6A871199DE0E6F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application process</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HA83203F1D287406A8A830301764CCE35"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">accept applications on a year-round basis and establish procedures for approving applications in an expeditious manner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H938ADC359FFC417FA231CC64EF015DD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">create a standardized form that parents can use to apply for the program and ensure that such form is readily available in written and electronic formats, including on a publicly accessible website.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAE4E6766E8D4285A8A1710C686A3A95"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Approval</header><text>Subject to the availability of funds to carry out this section, the Secretary shall approve the application of a parent to establish a Military Education Savings Account if—</text><subparagraph id="HBA5DE8E39F474B1CAC99EC75D58DDDAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the application is submitted in accordance with the application process established by the Secretary pursuant to this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18E8A9BE255E4E16AE703D2D6A2E6C01"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the application demonstrates that the child on whose behalf the Military Education Savings Account is to be established is an eligible military dependent child; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3FE6FC10A024EC1A20B59310EFCE540"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the parent who submits the application enters into a written agreement with the Secretary under which the parent agrees—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE20AA6DFC2846C5A06E181B64A9E6AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide the child with instruction in, at minimum, the fields of reading, language, mathematics, science, and social studies;</text></clause><clause id="H7E3ED9C3C643456CADC2D9F350CC23B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to not enroll the child in a public elementary school or a public secondary school, on a full-time basis while participating in the program;</text></clause><clause id="H7D65199E86E2474690C3CB94B9FB108D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to use funds in the Military Education Savings Account only for the purposes authorized under this section; and</text></clause><clause id="H953F289973A141F8B13F147435A92789"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to comply with all other requirements of this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H73287ECF06734422846BC3818BD544A9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Renewals</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process for the automatic renewal of a previously established Military Education Savings Account except in cases in which—</text><subparagraph id="H98D06F0771EC41E4B99A0DF22918C1AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the parents of the child on whose behalf the account was established choose not to renew the account; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H910F76FA15BB4487B12D17053EA78556"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the account was used to commit fraud or was otherwise not used in accordance with the requirements of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H8D81A2B895E945D482012A27DE96E338"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority in the event of insufficient funds</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H6ED6C0F08F01418E95D30A7FE95BA0ED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the funds appropriated to carry out this section are insufficient to enable the Secretary to establish and fully fund a Military Education Savings Account for each eligible military dependent child whose parent has an application approved under subsection (b) for a school year, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H89E6004A5B504D7DAEA1EEC0A08A8A31"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">first renew and fully fund previously established Military Education Savings Accounts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCCD815CF01754C67AE01A9143F4C5ED9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if funds remain available after renewing all accounts under subparagraph (A), conduct the lottery described in paragraph (3) to select the children on whose behalf accounts will be established using the remaining funds.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FB0B25B71C54532BB2747145100F7AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may transfer amounts from any account of the Department of Education to renew and fully fund previously established Military Education Savings Accounts under paragraph (1)(A). The authority to transfer amounts under the preceding sentence shall not be subject to any transfer or reprogramming requirements under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6062E36D2A59463E803546BBAFCF1201"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Lottery</header><text>The lottery described in this paragraph is a lottery in which—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE91C21DA0490471DA80BC1F50C0C0596"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">siblings of children on whose behalf Military Education Savings Accounts have previously been established have the highest probability of selection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HAEB2BD358E2A45C4A4AEC9491A978C77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>children of enlisted members have the next-highest probability of selection after the children described in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H836D924FC3BA4018A7C45C8CB9233268"><enum>(C)</enum><text>children of warrant officers have the next-highest probability of selection after the children described in subparagraph (B); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC987E8B4DDB8446C9DDF5EEE7FBB670D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">children of commissioned officers have the lowest probability of selection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7DD85868DA3441B383324DEDB075FE50"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amount of deposits</header><paragraph id="H35E08C6455324F8EB191B77C55911395"><enum>(1)</enum><header>First year of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of funds deposited into each Military Education Savings Account for the first school year for which such accounts are established under this section shall be $6,000 for each eligible military dependent child covered by the account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED48F576DBA4482CA233F575CB6BD384"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent years</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of funds deposited into each Military Education Savings Account for any school year after the year described in paragraph (1), shall be the amount determined under this subsection for the previous school year increased by a percentage equal to the percentage increase in the Chained Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers (as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor) over the period of such previous school year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43C120AB965048B3B742D68C42CAFD42"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds deposited into a Military Education Savings Account for a school year may be used by the parent of an eligible military dependent child to make payments to a qualified educational service provider that is approved by the Secretary under subsection (f)(1) for—</text><paragraph id="HB9C6035A4A464E7FA8EB5F16A6699D38"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">costs of attendance at a private elementary school or secondary school recognized by the State, which may include a private school that has a religious mission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29D756B3CF344113B0F0C44AF4D68306"><enum>(2)</enum><text>private online learning programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA2B72B35A454CCEB408A9F5062E15BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>private tutoring;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12E3F2BE6261454CAE11FBD5F62842FD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>services provided by a public elementary school or secondary school attended by the child on a less than full-time basis, including individual classes and extracurricular activities and programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42897015765F4F5ABA98B2410A712AFA"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">textbooks, curriculum programs, or other instructional materials, including any supplemental materials required by a curriculum program, private school, private online learning program, or a public school, or any parent directed curriculum associated with K–12 education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE69C0A154BCE429EBA1067A2CAB32670"><enum>(6)</enum><text>computer hardware or other technological devices that are used to help meet a child’s educational needs, except that such hardware or devices may not be purchased by a parent more than once in an 18-month period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF123B8D2A5214CE08A6904BDFCDC5082"><enum>(7)</enum><text>educational software and applications;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A077CC3818C4896851469AD9C3E9D4B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">uniforms purchased from or through a private school recognized by the State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE846348562CF4A05819F9BEAFFCF8E0C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>fees for nationally standardized assessment exams, advanced placement exams, any exams related to college or university admission, or tuition or fees for preparatory courses for such exams;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B975842B1214BDCAC39036BF07A039D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>fees for summer education programs and specialized after-school education programs (but not including after-school childcare);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D65D9FB42294AE08FBA8CC34A8D0ED8"><enum>(11)</enum><text>educational services and therapies, including occupational, behavioral, physical, speech-language, and audiology therapies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D9E3EC370D541B698C4D31CB1F3EDB6"><enum>(12)</enum><text>fees for transportation paid to a fee-for-service transportation provider for the child to travel to and from the facilities of a qualified educational service provider;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H83AA0F2040FC42B483A3C7F5C5484B7F"><enum>(13)</enum><text>costs of attendance at an institution of higher education;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2AE4B0F147C042C9BA237EB4A98C0D67"><enum>(14)</enum><text>costs associated with an apprenticeship or other vocational training program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6876BA9BBDF74674936CCE06F53D9E9B"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fees for State-recognized industry certification exams, and tuition or fees for preparatory courses for such exams;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H465C5163FD4E4324B5B5571547D22F5D"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contributions to a college savings account, which may include contributions to a qualified tuition program (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529">section 529(b)(1)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) or other prepaid tuition plan offered by a State; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43693F53F214440DB99DF7125F9C8B1F"><enum>(17)</enum><text>any other educational expenses approved by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1671647370CF4E7C97B077D640EE6158"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Requirements for qualified educational service providers</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H0F9C88CA1AD94A07B6B32A8BB8401766"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Registration and approval</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and maintain a registry of qualified educational service providers that are approved to receive payments from a Military Education Savings Account. The Secretary shall approve a qualified educational service provider to receive such payments if the provider demonstrates to the Secretary that it is licensed in the State in which it operates to provide one or more of the services for which funds may be expended under subsection (e).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDEDAFC563F82440AA6BAA7FD43218E38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Participation in online marketplace</header><text>As a condition of receiving funds from a Military Education Savings Account, a qualified educational service provider shall make its services available for purchase through the online marketplace described in subsection (g).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H332ABA4418D84604B8199A8D3D3293FA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Surety bond</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2BDF94BACCAC48B8A3C449BFF461DA4E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall require each qualified educational service provider that receives $100,000 or more in funds from Military Education Savings Accounts in a school year to post a surety bond, in an amount determined by the Secretary, for such school year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA02E83698EB94F50A998B353FDD6C98F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Retention</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe the circumstances under which a surety bond under subparagraph (A) may be retained by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H3A96E23828094AF58A71506B1023498B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Online marketplace</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H9038B0BD669E489B9FE946A84B009E23"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to enter into a contract with a private-sector entity under which the entity shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7B44A156D43846B79A877AED2E1C384E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and operate an online marketplace that enables the holder of a Military Education Savings Account to make direct purchases from qualified educational service providers using funds from such account;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE2170CA5F2B4F759FDD8831E39030BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that each qualified educational service provider on the registry maintained by the Secretary under subsection (f)(1) has made its services available for purchase through the online marketplace;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA487B95F2F694FAEA64D2103370EF575"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that all purchases made through the online marketplace are for services that are allowable uses of funds under subsection (e); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84BBB22BA0744E60857B02E230F9998F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and make available a standardized expense report form, in electronic and hard copy formats, to be used by parents for reporting expenses in accordance with subsection (h)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF574AD7A568E4F24A898E320412D4C35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require the holder of a Military Education Savings Account to make purchases using the online marketplace described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDC67D9273974C48B856BCCF332FCCDD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Transfer schedule</header><paragraph id="HD8C71D3C51B4432D8EE1E366411BB046"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary shall make quarterly transfers of the amount calculated pursuant to subsection (d) for deposit into the account of each eligible military dependent child, except that the Secretary may make transfers according to another transfer schedule if the Secretary determines that a transfer schedule other than quarterly transfers is necessary for the operation of the education savings account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A95DBECEE4C46DDA88D0EA1F7DD0869"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Choice of schedule</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process under which the parent of a child on whose behalf a Military Education Savings Account is established may choose a transfer schedule other than a transfer schedule determined under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27257FA8A9B3468BBEBABFFB9AE90933"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expense reports</header><subparagraph id="H8BD00428A9FE454E814A99D08FF5E673"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Submission required</header><text>Before receiving a transfer under paragraph (1) or (2), the parent of an eligible military dependent child on whose behalf a Military Education Savings Account is established shall submit to the Secretary an expense report demonstrating how funds from the most recent transfer were expended.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1410FB2312541E6B01D745439D71879"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Format</header><text>Each such expense report shall be submitted using the standardized expense report form developed under subsection (g)(1)(D).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HD46670D0B175400CA233B9F14B61DEE4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rollover</header><text>Amounts remaining in the Military Education Savings Account of an eligible military dependent child at the end of a school year shall remain available for use in accordance with subsection (e) until the date on which such account terminates under subsection (j).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HDF9EB456359F4FFB82303F3ADB7364B5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination and Return of funds</header><paragraph id="H943A5ACE1B0F41DF979E718911F1951F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Military Education Savings Account of an eligible military dependent child shall terminate on—</text><subparagraph id="HD3EC11A9446C45899FFA5E305FA5CE0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the child enrolls in a public elementary school or secondary school on a full-time basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37E9153795134F019FDFDFC70989EFB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a child who is pursuing postsecondary education, the earlier of—</text><clause id="HBD01C3404D6F49188E23513BEB44996E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the child completes postsecondary education; or</text></clause><clause id="H437F51E1D9794BAFBB9B402312E64D48"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date on which the child attains the age of 22 years;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64A13919B22348659D33452685C5D196"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a child who is an individual with a disability, the date on which the child attains the age of 26 years; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A8D663BE68740358EC11D72CF8A02DB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual not described in subparagraph (B) or (C), the earlier of—</text><clause id="H5564DFAFBBA443C899D7EB0DC0C5913C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the child attains the age of 22 years; or</text></clause><clause id="H40599402C1BA49088B4F0836C457B217"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the expiration of any 2-year period during which funds in the account are not used in accordance with this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEACE79CA6EC6420E84897DF48BD7573F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Return of funds</header><text>Any funds remaining in a Military Education Savings Account on the date such account terminates under paragraph (1) shall be returned to the Treasury of the United States and shall be used to carry out the program under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD369588835E64715AB6D5396BEAE20AE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Compulsory attendance requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State that receives funds under this title shall consider a child with a Military Education Savings Account for a school year as meeting the State’s compulsory school attendance requirements for such school year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H30E6D7A739DD470390FA39A72CC04C44"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a child with a Military Education Savings Account who attends a public school on a less than full-time basis in a school year—</text><paragraph id="H6808BE456E914CA29991B2D43C390D0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the child may not attend the public school free of charge; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7F9F13B106A4733992A43C1B7F255C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">funds in the account, in an amount determined pursuant to an agreement between the parent of the child and the local educational agency concerned, shall be used to pay for the child’s costs of attendance at such school.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HADC1F515155142E592897948972A2453"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Tax treatment of accounts</header><paragraph id="HD833BB279CBC4E3AB7C82070F15C0570"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A Military Education Savings Account is exempt from taxation under subtitle A of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF9BCAEAEC754184A5BC96470C70A587"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contributions and distributions</header><text>For purposes of subtitle A of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986—</text><subparagraph id="H82F0596304704AF5A4925D124FDF171C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any contribution to a military education savings account by the Secretary under this Act shall not be includible in the gross income of the individual for whose benefit such account is maintained or the parent of such individual; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0B8B3F529EC4949AC3F7245A2F4C021"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any distribution from a military education savings account which is permitted under this Act shall not be includible in the gross income of the individual for whose benefit such account is maintained or the parent of such individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB4C846F318E648D0B33BE8ACD98BE877"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Fraud prevention and reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a website and a telephone hotline that enable individuals to anonymously report suspected fraud in the program under this section. The Secretary also shall conduct or contract for random, quarterly, or annual audits of accounts as needed to ensure compliance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H47340E518C9D47509F97F1B8B59F0A40"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may enter into one or more contracts for the purpose of carrying out the responsibilities of the Secretary under this section.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HDCFDE05AF9C54DA6AE8F202266524DD0"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Refunds</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process under which payments from a Military Education Savings Accounts to a qualified educational service provider shall be refunded to the account in the event of fraud or nonperformance by the provider.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5FAA460495434FDDB02D064D0398AF3C"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><paragraph id="HB00D38040ABD42B1BF5294B54356F7DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nonagency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified educational service provider that receives a payment from a Military Education Savings Account pursuant to this section shall not be considered an agent of the State or the Federal Government solely because the provider received such payment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A77B7D1C0174967B54279032ABF75EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition of Federal or State supervision or control over nonpublic education providers</header><subparagraph id="H3D79F1285661409085430BD9C658BBFB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit, allow, encourage, or authorize any Federal or State control or supervision over any aspect of any qualified educational service provider, including a private, religious, or home education provider (without regard to whether a home education provider is treated as a private school or home school under State law). This section shall not be construed to exclude private, religious, or home education providers from participation in programs or services under this Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD27B7D4E52C048D4A9116F308C597489"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No religion-based discrimination</header><text>The Secretary shall not exclude, discriminate against, or otherwise disadvantage any qualified educational service provider with respect to programs or services under this section based in whole or in part on the provider’s religious education character or affiliation, including religiously based or mission-based policies or practices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7904876D5047379B78A1BF9671AE34"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Imposition of additional requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal requirements shall apply to a qualified educational service provider other than the requirements specifically set forth in this section. Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a qualified educational service provider to alter its creed, practices, admissions policy, or curriculum in order to be eligible to receive payments from a Military Education Savings Account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EA88B475C82451CA7CE7B33AE87D23F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment of assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of any Federal law, assistance provided under this section shall be considered assistance to the eligible military dependent child or to the parents of a child on whose behalf a Military Education Savings Account is established and shall not be considered assistance to the qualified educational service provider that uses or receives funds from a Military Education Savings Account.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB660924EF9F147208E7F21C48E7240CC"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Legal proceedings</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H75FBFB7EC6894F6183BE752E28F84E1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Burden</header><text>In any legal proceeding in which a qualified educational service provider challenges a requirement imposed by the Department of Education on the provider, the Department shall have the burden of establishing that the requirement is necessary and does not impose any undue burden on the provider.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H15FC1DA2C4454D1E8A87C32CFEEEC279"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on liability</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H06CB422BA11647B58F55384A246CF2CE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No liability shall arise on the part of an entity described in subparagraph (B) solely because such entity awards, uses, or receives funds from a Military Education Savings Account.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5A7C05B56C834C72881FDFCF1E243F3A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entity described</header><text>The entities described in this subparagraph are the following:</text><clause commented="no" id="H577F92EE4FF44825B0096EBFAB03D4B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Department of Education.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H3C6D05E7B6734786BB6F3249BC9EFE1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An entity that enters into a contract with the Secretary pursuant to subsection (g) or subsection (o).</text></clause><clause id="HA31EC41060704DB89E226C5FE11AAA5A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A qualified educational service provider.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6021CA52A475467C956DE279E56ED0F8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Intervention</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5AAF11922AD643DBB2B8FD4992395BBD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (B), a parent of an eligible military dependent child or a parent of a child on whose behalf a Military Education Savings Account is established may intervene in any legal proceeding in which the constitutionality of the program under this section is challenged under a State constitution or the United States Constitution.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H826C9AFBAF41433691631F79E4426080"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>For purposes of judicial administration, a court may—</text><clause commented="no" id="H3DE7C177F6CA445AB1886E4BE802684E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>limit the number of parents allowed to intervene in a proceeding under subparagraph (A); or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HBF8A84B71A3148F4B9C50C42FFDAAF80"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require all parents who have intervened in a proceeding under subparagraph (A) to file a joint brief, except that no parent shall be required to join any brief filed on behalf of a State that is a defendant in the proceeding.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE564CFE7B7D74566A75256BDABDA833D"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Administrative expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may use not more than 5 percent of the funds made available to carry out this section for the direct costs of administering Military Education Savings Accounts.</text></subsection><subsection id="H170D4215CA83464081AA171E993CC28E"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H2968248DCC6B404AB092F743D6DD4A6F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <term>commissioned officer</term>, <term>enlisted member</term>, and <term>warrant officer</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 101(b) of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H160170BD07DB459DA30C27A3208DA72B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible military dependent child</term> means a child who—</text><subparagraph id="H3B6C2973E39E42FBB98C51F331EAE6EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a parent on active duty in the uniformed services (as that term is defined in section 101 of title 37, United States Code, except that such term does not include an officer in the National Guard who has been activated); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F4A38F2729D4B22A5977684D196A09E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a child seeking to establish a Military Education Savings account for the first time, was enrolled in a public elementary school or a public secondary school for not less than 100 consecutive days in the preceding school year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF426BEF9C30D4E898B4F5C12F931A2B9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C3E0078495347898A8715685FC26D4B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>qualified educational service provider</term> means an entity or person that is licensed by a State to provide one or more of the educational services for which funds may be expended under subsection (e), including—</text><subparagraph id="HB48FDDE33B724F4680DE36578733BB71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a private school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9858B6739633429AB0C8FA8B5BA2B2B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a non-public online learning program or course provider;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D0FE9CD89C84091A8C63909DCA62073"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an institution of higher education, which may include a community college or a technical college;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CF2337E03EA48719538E3EA09AD12AA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a public school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C0C80BED6F24B68A96A5D151F9996A3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a private tutor or entity that operates a tutoring facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA53B7C09A034F28B7AF4EB32CACED7B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a provider of educational materials or curriculum;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70576014CD5F4E37AF6FF18593EE43C4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a provider of education-related therapies or services; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB83266B9B72C450F94B5E8144D0E0A1D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any other provider of educational services licensed by a State to provide such services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H689018F7F64A492990A9843B828808DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents in section 2 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7012 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDEB944F2991A4E57AE854455E7719756"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 7012A. Military education savings accounts.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H36D0A32E3D504C93BC415D802D77F61A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7014 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7714">20 U.S.C. 7714</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD834F727B1B44AB3BDB971EF32D57CF8"><subsection commented="no" id="HA3CF39EDB4C84D70A0DDBEBB00605BE1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Military education savings accounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of carrying out section 7012A—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H98DC0D3E46ED428082F6CAD022363B48"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there are authorized to be appropriated $1,200,000,000 for fiscal year 2024; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD7E2703A0DE74A569936DBF195F262E1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each fiscal year beginning after fiscal year 2024, the amount authorized to be appropriated shall be the amount authorized to be appropriated for the previous fiscal year increased by the percentage increase in the Chained Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers (as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor) over the period of such previous fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

