<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFF5187EC3F44A7180524F56E592390E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5331 IH: Government Surveillance Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5331</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to require that notice of criminal surveillance orders be eventually provided to targets, to reform the use of nondisclosure orders to providers, to prohibit indefinite sealing of criminal surveillance orders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H300907FAF62640CBAEE01F0B85A0AB34" style="OLC"><section id="H9F520ABC00714A54847AEAA243CC49F0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Government Surveillance Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HFB1F5E0EEB4A436F8B8193D12A32F2D9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Criminal surveillance orders</header><subsection id="HFE48083DD32348868530B91C07E3E3CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part II of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after chapter 206 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F9617B6DCDF4E128E152E95EA3E62B1"><chapter id="H4BEAD705A26A489396D9AA51E87680C5" style="OLC"><enum>206A</enum><header>Criminal surveillance orders</header><toc><toc-entry level="section">Sec. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H5DAA54A92A8C42338764F422EB257FF6">3131. Definitions. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H5331FFD9316043F2B9F5056E0143344D">3132. Criminal surveillance orders. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H41EA7B29787F4D758AB825FAC2FEB974">3133. Request for unsealing or challenging redactions. </toc-entry></toc><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H5DAA54A92A8C42338764F422EB257FF6"><enum>3131.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this chapter:</text><paragraph id="HD4F39E756E73495C85A859E372BDA5C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The term <term>application</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H573F657B4CBE403294ED9D2DFA6E5FDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an application for a criminal surveillance order; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E6966F45E7B4DDB952B81739F0BFE02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes all supporting affidavits and exhibits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD27CF671885B41F8AC1A620FA8C29762"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pen register; trap and trace device</header><text>The terms <term>pen register</term>, and <term>trap and trace device</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3127. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H364F045A86364A2A9B11478CE4A8BDD8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criminal surveillance order</header><text>The term <term>criminal surveillance order</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H8D480AE88601415F885DA2479DA9C58C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an order authorizing or approving the interception of a wire communication, oral communication, or electronic communication under chapter 119 or under an equivalent State law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H661BA44B39D94A878C84C9EA22E9E1E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an order authorizing or approving the installation and use of a pen register or a trap and trace device under chapter 206 or under an equivalent State law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H457B577FFB9D4B839E2281A1B62E5894"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an order for the installation of a mobile tracking device under section 3117;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D822E4265D54729824CE1B3DBD637A0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an order for disclosure under chapter 121; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB31E9FE521243D59B04B6653AE00AFD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an order for a delay of notification or nondisclosure under section 2705;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H316916C2C359418E8CFF021E1787F5D4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a search or seizure warrant issued using the procedures described in the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure or in the case of a State or Tribal court, issued using State or Tribal warrant procedures; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF34D33EC132C4924B98524B8C99272D2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in the case of a court-martial or other proceeding under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/47">chapter 47</external-xref> of title 10 (Uniform Code of Military Justice), a warrant or order issued under section 846 of that title; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3389660569B14D039CCD047B295A726E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a warrant under section 3103a;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45EB750260964F8ABE7F2945F24ECA9A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an order under section 1651 of title 28;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5B6292777C24461A583B267307909FC"><enum>(J)</enum><text>an order for third party assistance under section 2518(4) or section 3124; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68FBA940A12240B8A9BE47781E6BD9E2"><enum>(K)</enum><text>an order to enforce the assistance capability and capacity requirements under section 2522. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1E526AF48A94137B091B1FED68F0F45"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Electronic communication; oral communication; wire communication</header><text>The terms <term>electronic communication</term>, <term>oral communication</term>, and <term>wire communication</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 2510.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0334B23473C44572ACB65CB2415F284F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1533AAFCF6F34FA982A2F71C57E8626D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Inventory</header><text>The term <term>inventory</term> means the inventory and other materials—</text><subparagraph id="H0A38BE71E25B4746B6B691CCB96925BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>returned to a Federal, State, or Tribal court or a court-martial or other proceeding under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/47">chapter 47</external-xref> of title 10 (Uniform Code of Military Justice) in connection with the execution of a criminal surveillance order (including under paragraph (1)(D) or (2)(B) of rule 41(f) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, under comparable State warrant procedures, or under procedures applicable to a court-martial or other proceeding under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/47">chapter 47</external-xref> of title 10); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFD98B6F3F3643549165B8ADE0B45857"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provided to persons and other parties described in section 2518(8)(d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10320DE0F13642E1A63EB6F69F9C537D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, and the United States Virgin Islands. </text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD64C564D2EBF44D7A01D198536EF1083"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Substantially prevails</header><text>The term <term>substantially prevails</term> has the meaning given the term in section 552(a)(4)(E) of title 5.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5331FFD9316043F2B9F5056E0143344D"><enum>3132.</enum><header>Criminal surveillance orders</header><subsection id="H75E58D3755934F35B8CF91FB33EB5784"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on sealing</header><paragraph id="H194CB2E5998444BEB713CEBE6438BE90"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), a court may not seal a criminal surveillance order, application, or inventory for a period that extends after the later of—</text><subparagraph id="HA11066EB90424CA98180319DDF15A4A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>date the order is executed; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FA8FFE17D7948DEBEE581251AA5D88D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date on which the authorized surveillance ends.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H822E70B15ED04DFD960371B93958EE1B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="HB61D5A4EBE7042498A656781390582EB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An applicant for a criminal surveillance order may file a written request for the court to seal the criminal surveillance order, the application, or the inventory for a period not to exceed 180 days after the later of the date the order is executed or the date on which the authorized surveillance ends, which request the court shall grant if the applicant certifies that there is reason to believe that failure to seal will have an adverse result described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E70920D172D4934AD99AE209C9328F9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Adverse result</header><clause id="H197F3E327216447BA332BC8368CE0FE1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An adverse result described in this subparagraph is—</text><subclause id="HE1B3AC1D940545F9A5673374853D4246"><enum>(I)</enum><text>endangering the life or physical safety of an individual;</text></subclause><subclause id="H54E3C2D7B84840968406C96B1F0509A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>flight from prosecution;</text></subclause><subclause id="H2A0DB129DBF44C478DEF0AE1A051254B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>destruction of or tampering with evidence;</text></subclause><subclause id="H860027CB1F7347439F07AD2DAB0A5DEA"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>intimidation of potential witnesses; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HB401A1E5625D4A1D82FFE2962BC7B6D1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>otherwise seriously jeopardizing the investigation to which the criminal surveillance order relates or unduly delaying a trial resulting from the investigation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HDF639652E4B045C0A5ED35BA667E5036"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other requirements</header><subclause id="H602DD8BA410740DEB2834F39BD26D5B0"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>When certifying an adverse result, the applicant shall certify that there is reason to believe that the person whose information is targeted by the order does not know—</text><item id="HE8C1B74FCAB7400C88AF613023E1D8D3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>about the investigation; and</text></item><item id="H74D962623E1E4DEEB0C4E585B4E2B7CE"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that they are a target or person of interest in the investigation.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H2CFCA7904D1B4613B22671F7523515A9"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Failure to certify</header><text>If the applicant does not satisfy the requirements of subclause (I)—</text><item id="H4F3BCA710CBC491E940BB819777D28A8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the applicant must follow the higher standard of judicial review required by subparagraph (C)(ii); and</text></item><item id="H093A286A66D340AD9854D99DC394D29C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the failure to satisfy such requirements shall be disclosed in both the criminal surveillance order and any preclusion of notice order issued for that criminal surveillance order.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H02079567121749CBB8AC999D22909367"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Review by court</header><text>The court may, in its discretion, require the government to provide the factual basis for the certification described in clause (i) and may review that factual basis for sufficiency.</text></clause><clause id="HDD35EF24B6E944DFA1DEF2F55029E64A"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Notification</header><subclause id="HA2FD2A7DE3AE46E19FF74EE76C7C60B9"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any criminal surveillance order, application, or inventory that is sealed at the Government’s request, the Government shall promptly notify the court if the Government no longer has reason to believe that removal of a seal will have an adverse result described in this subparagraph.</text></subclause><subclause id="H00BAE5917B0D477A94BAFC7AF061EE38"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Unsealing</header><text>After being notified by the Government under subclause (I), the court shall unseal the criminal surveillance order, application, or inventory. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC11BBD54093245A6925B84B24F0B7D6B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Extensions</header><clause id="HEF827A9D0C9B44938DC313BFF1541E42"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court may grant a single extension of a sealing order for up to 180 days, upon the applicant’s motion, based on a renewed certification that failure to extend the sealing period will have an adverse result described in subparagraph (B).</text></clause><clause id="H24E02BB33E0C421486AD5A48515D78E1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Heightened judicial review of subsequent extensions</header><subclause id="HE0416B9EE2C4411290E541D3967458EB"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any extension after an extension under clause (i), the court may grant an extension of a sealing order for up to 180 days, upon the applicant’s motion, if the applicant—</text><item id="H18CC2D8F2A844D57ACCA339F42BF1867"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>demonstrates— </text><subitem id="HCCF777305DFA4FFB946501B2EAEDFF16"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>a particularized showing that failure to extend the sealing period will have an adverse result described in subparagraph (B); and</text></subitem><subitem id="HCE72A4CB65474550A96A7C0A98062C94"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a particularized showing that the adverse result would not be avoided by redaction of specified words, phrases, or passages in the criminal surveillance order, application, or inventory; and</text></subitem></item><item id="H28FBC7907C004E6A9149A8D2386CEE23"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>details—</text><subitem id="H7578D1773B134A2AB7F8C7DFEB71B3A7"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the nature of the investigation;</text></subitem><subitem id="HEBAE33DBC0284206898CCB1FCD875D53"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the suspected crimes;</text></subitem><subitem id="HCCBD0F72C9AD46C9A1420CA22BD47876"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>the name of the target; and</text></subitem><subitem id="HAD4501BA048848C2BFE3EFCC41E427B6"><enum>(DD)</enum><text>specific facts that substantiate the need for the extension. </text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="H8C7746580AB644CD91AA22EAB1BF30C6"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Redacted documents</header><item id="H03A91BD508A6406FB82239D2F85D90B8"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the court determines that an applicant has met the requirements of subitem (AA) of subclause (I)(aa), but not the requirements of subitem (BB) of subclause (I)(aa), the court shall order the applicant to submit proposed redactions to each sealed document.</text></item><item id="HA3C0D761E72F4E389EA74E88D6BB191D"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Disposition</header><text>After considering the proposed redactions of the applicant, if any, the court may order the applicant to refile 1 or more sealed documents with such redactions as the court finds appropriate, direct the clerk to unseal the entirety of 1 or more sealed documents, or order that 1 or more sealed documents remain under seal.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB846F148464E47F2969B639913D767CA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Sealing of rejected applications and unexecuted criminal surveillance orders</header><text>A court may, pursuant to subparagraph (A), seal an unexecuted criminal surveillance order, or a rejected application.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H4B8ED3404C6A4599BA3CA6430F198915"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Challenge of adverse result certification or extension</header><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H9CDEA9997CC540639C8626EBA7BCFBEA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person subject to and seeking to challenge a preclusion of notice order or any person seeking to unseal a surveillance order, application, or inventory may challenge—</text><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB33904DFC8C9440D8CC32EAB59D1AD99"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a certification of the adverse result under this paragraph; or</text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H784E425965374BBA9B6A34E7253C739C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the particularized showings and detailed information necessary for a second and subsequent extension. </text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21745359CF514B408CB4A7A76BA9DADF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Heightened standard</header><text>If an order under this paragraph or a preclusion of notice order for a subpoena or emergency request is issued earlier than 1 year before the date on which a challenge under clause (i) is made, the requirements of subparagraph (C)(ii) shall apply to a warrant or order sealed in accordance with chapter 206A or the subpoena or emergency request.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16DC3F93D9E2487398035DBDADEFD5B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>If a person substantially prevails in a challenge under this subparagraph, the court shall order the applicant for the criminal surveillance order at issue to pay the litigation costs of the person (including reasonable attorney's fees). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H51E5B64B4916478E8B825ECC112B1296"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Docketing and publication of criminal surveillance orders, applications, inventories, and associated docket records</header><paragraph id="H03B90B15C514432488B40AFE2EBBBE6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Docket records</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), regardless of whether a court seals a criminal surveillance order or application under this section, the public docket record for any criminal surveillance case shall—</text><subparagraph id="H85189C2E5E1D4FB2AD6E66866B3D72E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be made available as an open Government data asset and under an open license, as such terms are defined in section 3502 of title 44, and in a manner that facilitates downloading docket records in bulk, in accordance with rules promulgated by the Judicial Conference of the United States, after consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Administrator of General Services, the Electronic Public Access Public User Group, private entities offering electronic case management software, the National Center for State Courts, and the National American Indian Court Judges Association, on the website of the court; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EDC12629D604CDDAE69D3A9E1D9E666"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include, at a minimum—</text><clause id="HE6E89DE8B6BF4E77A107638A063F52C6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date and time the application was filed, the order was entered, and the warrant was returned to the court, where applicable;</text></clause><clause id="HCA1AAC5941784DE893F93363ED968F04"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the type of order, including—</text><subclause id="H4593CDE7FE6C46D6BAE730053542B85C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the statutory authority under which the order was issued;</text></subclause><subclause id="HEFF3D77CF7314406A301BCD786887AE5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the type of crime under investigation;</text></subclause><subclause id="H38060B1DC9F841189F2ACCF03501E1A9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the investigating agency;</text></subclause><subclause id="H77E1B4CD214F46F986F9DE3C048CBE74"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the duration of the requested surveillance if any;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCF1E7A48EF194637A22B8E7A9051DF24"><enum>(V)</enum><text>whether sealing and deferred notice were requested, if so for how long;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB52EFD7ABD874114A0324A0752B7A4C4"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>whether an order for third party assistance was requested; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9EA2AD64E9904D3295E1C526F397FE8E"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>disposition by the court, whether granted, modified, or denied;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF73F3A7FB4D74C65AC7215C093339D84"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an index describing any subsequent filings or orders related to the case;</text></clause><clause id="HF7578048782E415AAEFAA8AD3FB45217"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the unique case number in accordance with paragraph (3); and</text></clause><clause id="H833746C602894068981787990441012F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the date on which the seal will expire (unless extended pursuant to subsection (a)(2)(C)). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC349C164F9C4996B204C17FA79D3A78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Showing of adverse result</header><text>If an applicant in a sealed case demonstrates that public disclosure of any docket item listed in paragraph (1)(B)(ii) will have an adverse result described in subsection (a)(2)(B), the court may direct the clerk to withhold that item from the public docket record until the sealing order expires.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64BA9346AE7C46FCA925EB9EA93E3817"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Case number and caption</header><subparagraph id="H9062CE5497B840629F46A97332D80F20"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court shall assign for each application—</text><clause id="HB4CE23A033E240B98BB192A32E721FC8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a unique case number for every identified target, including for each unique street address, parcel, person, phone number, device, or account targeted; and </text></clause><clause id="HAFB74544F47849E4A62505829B0D30D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a case caption providing only generic information about the type of order sought and the target of the order.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF44D2EE0CF0747B491361451D4E735B4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A court shall assign a case number and case caption under subparagraph (A) in accordance with rules promulgated by the Judicial Conference of the United States, in consultation with the Electronic Public Access Public User Group, or in the case of a State court, in accordance with rules promulgated by the highest court of the State, and in the case of a Tribal court, in accordance with rules promulgated by the highest court of the Indian Tribe. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B95F2F986354B97A80CB008EA842482"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Compliance with the Rehabilitation Act of 1973</header><text>Each criminal surveillance order, application, inventory, and public docket record for any criminal surveillance case required under this subsection shall be published in a form that complies with section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4088614C8A214C2CBD6551DD749D9E11"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nondisclosure orders</header><text>When applying for an order for nondisclosure under section 2705, to prevent the disclosure of a subpoena—</text><subparagraph id="H08FDCA6C35144EAAA5A9AF69B54DEC59"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicant for the order shall include a copy of the subpoena; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H975240B4088F45BFB685EB359A44878A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the court shall docket the subpoena as part of the application for the order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9889EB876EA47B4965ADF419F4F2868"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Automatic unsealing and notification</header><text>The court shall employ a technical mechanism to automatically—</text><subparagraph id="HBEDDD7668E1041A4AA25926E1CC506EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>unseal criminal surveillance orders not later than the end of the next business day after the seal expires; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46F3C9E1FB914DE088C2E8A8E96FB761"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide notice, 10 business days before scheduled unsealing, to the law enforcement agency that filed the application for the criminal surveillance order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E604D9EBE9A4C668F1CBE3CBAB4292E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Filing</header><text>An application and the inventory shall be filed electronically.</text></subsection></section><section id="H41EA7B29787F4D758AB825FAC2FEB974"><enum>3133.</enum><header>Request for unsealing or challenging redactions</header><subsection id="H90F19D915DAB4F2A8E5E91816817C5D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person may submit a request to a court to—</text><paragraph id="H2157576C02884575B2302B9A56DBB28C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">unseal an application for a criminal surveillance order, a criminal surveillance order, or an inventory; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H505C7175EC6240DF9347FA3777DA8B9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">challenge a redaction under section 3132(a)(2)(C)(ii)(II). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H41C542F3FDB74165B42CA669ECDC6D33"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A request described in subsection (a) may be submitted as part of—</text><paragraph id="HFAE9933ABFAA458CA0FEF30523FD486E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the particular criminal surveillance matter, including as a motion to unseal; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DFF19F34FE24693B6B9CD6AB38B0926"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as a stand-alone, separate case.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H184D38AB787B42E7926644A5E319F38B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Multiple applications and orders unsealed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A request described in subsection (a) may include more than 1 application for a criminal surveillance order, criminal surveillance order, or an inventory.</text></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7E9C02E7713D401B828F2A886393E323"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H51599DD5D70244649E313053103DB852"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H49CB067543B04DADAC8129AD5D361F76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 2518(8)—</text><clause id="H4BBF4BC44889415BAA5935A0107E1423"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (b); and</text></clause><clause id="H72D6C4377E4F4FB1A76DE042C0242D9A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (c) and (d) as subparagraphs (b) and (c), respectively;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F2EE538BB28497192FD13234DAC88E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 3123, by striking subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50C72F041E2146258A3E69E985886CDA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 3103a(b)(1)—</text><clause id="H0DAB66C776404759A46A1DA6E0926458"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2705</quote> and inserting <quote>3132)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H1DAE747F49384A9D85B7AB80EC4D976B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>trial)</quote> and inserting <quote>trial</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0056F18DBCE14F259E2C4D33326B5114"><enum>(2)</enum><header>E-Government Act of 2002</header><subparagraph id="H75950BC310DA43858C194F632998BDCD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 205 of the E-Government Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/44/3501">44 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><clause id="HDAF9E7F5F3DF499A8582C029E6F13991"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE47528F86984E66BA7BB5D3C53B7D25"><paragraph id="HE7B1E289212E41BB9B4AA43465CFCADF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Access to the substance of all applications for criminal surveillance orders, criminal surveillance orders, and inventories in a text searchable format in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/206A">chapter 206A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="HF073275B0ACA4189841AD9742D21A3DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subclause id="H268ACD17C6AC4B52928139CBA9AC1F04"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D614186355F43E5B261F41F160F4457"><paragraph id="H95459D5005154FA88EEFD51645DB8BD3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="H7B2133CD6826488E8F55361DDFA00C6B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Documents that are filed that are not otherwise available to the public, such as documents filed under seal, shall not be made available online.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61F19AA9CBE4498FAB5FD93044EDAE23"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Criminal surveillance orders</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to applications for criminal surveillance orders, criminal surveillance orders, and inventories that are publicly available in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/206A">chapter 206A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="HEA97A6327C9E46B38A8BBCE0BB3A3F7A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H600F0A0CBA0541A3A22BFFB152E3CF93"><subparagraph id="H5E852E138C3F409AA70B9FACD6506BF5"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Supreme Court shall update the rules prescribed under subparagraph (A) to address personal information included in criminal surveillance orders, applications, and inventories that are made available to the public.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DA6046FED7A4954826255F197C2A96B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Table of chapters</header><text>The table of chapters for part II of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 206 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6B24228B92B4F41B3D1DA64953C534C"><toc><multi-column-toc-entry level="chapter" bold="on"><toc-enum>206A.</toc-enum><level-header level="chapter">Criminal surveillance orders</level-header><target>3121</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A8F4C2AB0D84379B405C68CE9F814EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H8F9FAC7DE30F4F31A41002D609DFF87E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraphs (2) and (3), the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date that is 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF2168E9DEB142659C325E32BEDC169F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delayed applicability for certain State and Tribal courts</header><subparagraph id="H5922377DF32B43BB91E287E631272271"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsections (b)(1)(A) and (c) of section 3132 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a) of this section, shall apply on and after the date that is 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act—</text><clause id="HA78757CC22D941F982C2E77A0A353A39"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to a State or Tribal court that, on the date of enactment of this Act, does not offer electronic docketing or public online access to dockets; or</text></clause><clause id="HF983A2921ED04C3BBEEA2AF31CF74CBF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to any State or Tribal court that certifies that the court needs more time to comply with the requirements of those subsections.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DDD2B665FB244B1869892B39CED51A8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority to delay electronic filing</header><subparagraph id="HA69D9588E81E4219B78C18488067B915"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Certification</header><clause id="H82995E08B69B417DADB8A22D356CB59C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Federal courts</header><text>The application of subsection (c) of section 3132 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a) of this section, to Federal courts under paragraph (1) of this subsection shall be delayed for 1 year if the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts certifies that the system used by Federal courts for electronic filing is not sufficiently secure.</text></clause><clause id="H42FE9EC6568E4A74AC84BCAE1C2ECBE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>State and Tribal courts</header><text>The application of subsection (c) of section 3132 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a) of this section, to a State or Tribal court under paragraph (1) or (2) of this subsection, as applicable, shall be delayed for 1 year if the chief judge of the highest court of the State or Tribe certifies that the system used by the State or Tribal court for electronic filing is not sufficiently secure.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8EC8B82CA874D47A48EAA6FE6547DEB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>A certification under subparagraph (A) shall include an estimate of the date by which the electronic filing system of the applicable court will be sufficiently secure.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42FC3B0D31F74E8A85B4340E05B1CFB7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Renewal of delay</header><text>The delay of the application of subsection (c) of section 3132 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a) of this section, to Federal courts or to a State or Tribal court may be delayed for 1 or more additional 1-year periods if the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts or the chief judge of the highest court of the State or Tribe, respectively, submits an additional certification in accordance with subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E6B000B2C914A238D71359F86C13F6E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Any certification under this paragraph shall be— </text><clause id="HC77EA0C0790C4E58B3BFD0DA22A31F3E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>made available on the website of the court system with respect to which the certification is submitted; and</text></clause><clause id="H99D87D25E78246CA98E77A66585F539D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>submitted to the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A34FE3FC8C044B9A0B3C0FE5E474457"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applicability</header><paragraph id="H16B88012496B4FB1B9AB832E64799170"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>application</term>, <term>criminal surveillance order</term>, and <term>inventory</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 3131 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF233D8F0C7948C7AD3A79E21FB3EBC8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to—</text><subparagraph id="H306183963012412FBA915DB7B8DAE460"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any application filed or inventory returned on or after the date described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EB2EBB930E4497B940F7516F9484542"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any criminal surveillance order entered on or after the date described in subsection (d). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DC88A2ECD354502A6158DE347F54252"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding unsealing</header><text>Nothing in the amendments made by this section shall be construed to prohibit a court from unsealing—</text><subparagraph id="HDC1687C774C24D4A904667B1EFEE44A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a criminal surveillance order entered or inventory returned before the date described in subsection (d); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE30258315A848CA8C9BC81837C46053"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an application for a criminal surveillance order made before the date described in subsection (d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A22E11C91EE4105B4B48654E67A2E99" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding interpretation</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall be liberally construed in favor of public access to documents, to the extent possible. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H2A8E89524EE04C418BDD15309FC99A0F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Notice to courts of unlawful surveillance</header><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H58572B72054F4935BAB8C0C463BA51FD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required disclosure of customer communications or records</header><text>Section 2703(d) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H51C83D6D314E477390DFA182E557133F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A court order</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7DD8A3E0E9844A6B874E9727CE108A3"><paragraph id="H86620B486E10441C9A4617EED713D0B0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court order</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD7C90C9A2D7842DC854F4BFADF38329D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0F6D2FFA02014A7EAF230FD7A281CDAB"><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB96D278E910F4FD690DFD20D300513F4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required inventory</header><text>A court order for disclosure issued under subsection (b) or (c) shall require an inventory described in rule 41(f)(1)(B) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, or any successor thereto, be promptly returned to the court if the provider disclosed to the government any data not authorized by the court.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H497CDD55DCD24D04BE828BE3F1E95FD9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Issuance of an order for a pen register or a trap and trace device</header><text>Section 3123(b) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H0C86F6CAFB194A7EBB03308B39559E0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(D), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD11790A736084E3384E307C1BA6C85BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HF1B23D9C6B3948E79E481E6169BE544F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C96F13493CA440787862F374F87F82B"><paragraph id="HA0068DCF4BD5460F9F016F2DD1F0104F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall require an inventory described in rule 41(f)(1)(B) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, or any successor thereto, be promptly returned to the court if—</text><subparagraph id="H037A7A2E43A64CA9BBD587C966610384"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the provider disclosed to the government any electronic data not authorized by the court; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E192000961B49FB99533E8F876FF68F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the government obtained dialing, routing, addressing, or signaling information that was not authorized by the court or in a manner that exceeded the authorization granted by the court.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HBA58BDDF4E4844EE9C1249B6EE13D2BF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule 41</header><text>Rule 41(f)(1)(B) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure is amended by inserting after the period at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDBDE6FDDE27F4DF0827B24A7BEF9A65D"><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">If an inventory is required pursuant to this rule, or if an inventory is required by section 2703(d)(2) of title 18, United States Code, or section 3123(b)(3) of that title, the inventory shall— </quoted-block-continuation-text><clause id="HCE27A70EA9734B78BEC9D13B39E47B8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>disclose whether the provider disclosed to the government any electronic data not authorized by the court and, if so, provide detailed information regarding the disclosure; and </text></clause><clause id="H54094859604A4C9B831B490B95BC36C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>disclose whether the government searched persons or property, including accounts or electronic devices, or obtained dialing, routing, addressing, or signaling information not authorized by the court or in a manner that exceeded the authorization granted by the court and, if so, provide detailed information regarding the search.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H9DC42E404E234541B8D44E3D73FAB280"><enum>4.</enum><header>Notice to subjects of law enforcement surveillance</header><subsection id="H45F45F97D9434EAF8F40551E8526F234"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2703 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H750295C7243941099D9C938596D5FBF8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), in the first sentence—</text><subparagraph id="H0EA72692D2E24A859D35F0AB07C49E1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning a warrant</quote> after <quote>the procedures</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14FCB732D1A94DD193933F41EE749115" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and execution and return</quote> after <quote>State warrant</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C804F992BC94CB0BB2C97E3733595A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning such a warrant</quote> after <quote>that title</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA44D7298E259488F8AF841840868A9EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H006FBABDECDB409B8D28B9ECB47CFD79"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="HCE8CEAE4E89B4143AD127A94A880322F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HD6027210E5F349EDAD79C988F063F600"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>without required notice to the subscriber or customer,</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H2F589ACCF9464AE79114F510EE331A5A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning a warrant</quote> after <quote>the procedures</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6F79750E3AA542CA811964FBEFEC1F11" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and execution and return</quote> after <quote>State warrant</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H572CA9BD72934B9FB483786D15AA4BBC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning such a warrant</quote> after <quote>that title</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1474539A795C4D359B3A728EE4E9B28C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="HD7CFFAF07D3240178311B27732C28405"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting a period; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H33E2A17FD9E64458B403D8B430755D4C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the matter following clause (ii), by striking <quote>except that delayed notice may be given pursuant to section 2705 of this title.</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76FCC305C2FA4350ABB5E13EB962DE43"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC167F820695048348A77D3FE9A1CC9F4"><paragraph id="HBEBCA73154DD4E618801FBD7B3B0C2CF" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Notice may not be delayed pursuant to section 2705 for a disclosure under paragraph (1)(B)(i).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H53D5AB763B4441F3B3CA8B24EDAB5A8F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H97503394FCEE49FC9A03ECB5CE2FB185"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A)—</text><clause id="H169344A8F9A94E75A8D55A7BF383AC8D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning a warrant</quote> after <quote>the procedures</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H936674082CEB400C820980ADC3F58827" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and execution and return</quote> after <quote>State warrant</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H6E070F9FCAC442549E96E575B91A37A1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning such a warrant</quote> after <quote>that title</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C5EB06DF71845E5BC84CF2AE15A4060"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H24D83324E1E74F13B703A9F1D5B977B8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d), as amended by section 3(a) of this Act, by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1569CA177A084D29944E342EDBEC2296"><paragraph id="H9D1A15A38CBC40F9949126F0B70EA8F0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Orders under this subsection shall be issued in accordance with the requirements for executing and returning a warrant under the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H021937F92BBC4EB4A36D3E0B8F59F27B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC61FD986732B4F868B8825F8D9A870D3"><subsection id="H4C44DCB01539474FBCE375D98A024CF7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Service</header><paragraph id="H73609C438AD444EAA47EABD9D9C292A1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A governmental entity receiving records or information under subsection (a), (b), or (c) of this section or seeking an order under section 3123 shall provide notice prior to conducting the court-authorized surveillance to the subscriber or customer or the person described in subsection (b)(1)(A) of that section, as applicable, unless notice is delayed in accordance with section 2705. If prior notice is infeasible due to inadequate contact information, the governmental entity shall provide the required notice within 7 days after receipt of adequate contact information from the provider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF30C4B7894DE488BB4045F1F1DD13A05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other requirements</header><text>For purposes of serving a copy of a warrant or order described in this section and a receipt for the warrant or order—</text><subparagraph id="H1B4E244065B44C93878937181ED1D4AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the person or persons whose wire or electronic communications are obtained under the warrant or order shall be the person or persons whose property was searched or who possessed the information that was seized or copied; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5CFF74287284A74A5C3C6BF422DC48D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>service of the copy of the warrant or order and the receipt may only be delayed in accordance with section 2705.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6FE617DC790446819EBFA3A985AD689A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Writs</header><text>Section 1651 of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HED3AD2717A194E0CAA21049C6F7656C3"><subsection id="HF92A5D44D3F34630858A93748AF2F42A"><enum>(c)</enum><text>In seeking an order to a third party under this section, the Federal Government shall comply with any requirement for notice applicable to warrants issued under the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6CC020B356A04A57957858753D8E043C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Voluntary disclosure of customer communications or records</header><text>Section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2388B1BE80F44F61AB5A8C3B623C74A9"><subsection id="H31D56AF4D91D4C2F826383113D013129"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>If a governmental entity requests and receives a voluntary disclosure from a provider described in subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="HC2C975281B6244808AE24E00181A6273"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the contents of communications pursuant to subsection (b)(8); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D48A4B55014F588AFE8028B5C42400"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a record or other information pertaining to a subscriber to or customer of such service pursuant to subsection (c)(4),</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">the governmental entity shall within 7 days provide notice to the subscriber or customer, unless notice is delayed in accordance with section 2705.</continuation-text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H4FC6FE194010429F928129F7AF80BEBE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Delay and preclusion of required notice</header><subsection id="HDE648D80EB5F433C8C4EACC1630DF47D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2705 of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2721F45780F477AB290B9CEFD1902F9"><section id="H943BE94FE9E147598221FCD167121F83"><enum>2705.</enum><header>Delay and preclusion of notice</header><subsection id="H1BE61731763A41A3AAFE198389B7D5F4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Delay of required notice to customer or subscriber</header><paragraph id="H6590C16C9B5745AB9D4C8E468A156541"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A governmental entity acting under section 2702, 2703, or section 3123 may apply to a court for an order delaying the required notice to the person whose wire or electronic communications or records or information are obtained.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1399737C726D45E68AF741232CA97088"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Warrants and orders</header><text>The court may enter an order described in paragraph (1) with respect to a warrant or order only if the warrant or order is sealed in accordance with chapter 206A, and only for the period during which the sealing order is in effect.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA64D0448064C48FDA6E9CFACE491BA14"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Subpoenas and emergency requests</header><subparagraph id="H9F7804A45D0A40B9B9D8CBE6080C94B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court shall enter an order described in paragraph (1) with respect to a subpoena or emergency request for a period not to exceed 180 days after the return date of the subpoena or the emergency request if the governmental entity certifies that there is reason to believe that failure to issue the order will have an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE620476D46724120AF66AE6682ADEF05"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extensions</header><clause id="H31BD35781FA5438DA74E880579E8F74A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court shall grant a single extension of an order described in paragraph (1) with respect to a subpoena or emergency request for a period not to exceed 180 days upon the governmental entity's motion, based on a renewed certification that failure to extend the order will have an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></clause><clause id="HAFBD311DFCC14B3DB18D3F64DAEE6050"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Subsequent extensions</header><subclause id="H07B0CE2F8FC64DF494C578B3C28DE610"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any extension after an extension under clause (i), the court may grant an extension of an order described in paragraph (1) with respect to a subpoena or emergency request for up to 180 days, upon the governmental entity's motion, if the governmental entity demonstrates a particularized showing described in subitems (AA) and (BB) of section 3132(a)(2)(C)(I)(aa) and details the information described in item (bb) of section 3132(a)(2)(C)(I).</text></subclause><subclause id="H5B93BDD1E0144CC0B148A2F11EC406A7"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Redacted documents</header><text>The court shall consider and order redactions under this clause in accordance with the procedures under section 3132(a)(2)(C)(II).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06A927FA5CAD42B0947BF22778CFCF93"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Review by court</header><text>The court may, in its discretion, require the governmental entity to provide the factual basis for the certification described in subparagraph (A) and may review that factual basis for sufficiency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1B2B1A58775456EA9CB1067261A3CDA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Notification</header><clause id="HF2E2E855B64D455F9D936B82FCE30C76"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A governmental entity shall promptly notify the court once the governmental entity no longer has reason to believe that the order is necessary to prevent an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></clause><clause id="H08185AF6D3B2419F89CA9F8A60E93335"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>After being notified by the governmental entity under clause (i), the court shall revoke the order.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3DBD43AF85F545D4B149B24EA6BD1D45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Preclusion of notice to subject of governmental access</header><paragraph id="H069F4A8AD5E14A0EAD83A6792795719B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><subparagraph id="H4B772278ED0E4653B043B9DEB3CBE91B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2) a governmental entity acting under section 2703 or section 3123 may apply to a court for— </text><clause id="H52FF7766BDA04713B1AEFB494332C771"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an order commanding a provider of electronic communications service or remote computing service to whom a criminal surveillance order, as defined in section 3131, or subpoena is directed, not to notify any other person of the existence of the criminal surveillance order or subpoena; or</text></clause><clause id="H1B2E646C8A894CFBBB87215DC276538D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an order commanding a person owning or leasing the line or other facility to which the pen register or a trap and trace device is attached or applied, or who is obligated by the order to provide assistance to the applicant, not to notify any other person of the existence of a pen register or trap and trace device, as such terms are defined in section 3127.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94E35A411B76488BAADDE04CE96C63E8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Criminal surveillance orders</header><text>The court may enter an order described in subparagraph (A) with respect to a criminal surveillance order only if the criminal surveillance order is sealed in accordance with chapter 206A, and only for the period during which the sealing order is in effect. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BEAA9FE81814FDBBDE628BB8E80BF0B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Subpoenas</header><clause id="H8FE3B4C1932E48ACB71747A555A9AD98"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court shall enter an order described in subparagraph (A) with respect to a subpoena for a period not to exceed 180 days after the return date of the subpoena if the governmental entity certifies that there is reason to believe that failure to issue the order will have an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></clause><clause id="H981C536ACC0E460CBA48D2D64C4683F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Extensions</header><subclause id="H4DC4CDCF025E44FF8106557271694FD4"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court shall grant a single extension of an order described in subparagraph (A) with respect to a subpoena for a period not to exceed 180 days upon the governmental entity's motion, based on a renewed certification that failure to extend the order will have an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></subclause><subclause id="HF7C6751DEB1F41ECA916021FC66B26C1"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Subsequent extensions</header><item id="H55C35324325D4716BA1F464FDDF5A2FA"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any extension after an extension under subclause (I), the court may grant an extension of an order described in subparagraph (A) with respect to a subpoena for up to 180 days, upon the governmental entity's motion, if the governmental entity demonstrates a particularized showing described in subitems (AA) and (BB) of section 3132(a)(2)(C)(I)(aa) and details the information described in item (bb) of section 3132(a)(2)(C)(I).</text></item><item id="H5E2651EBE99A444BBA677C3C70CC2EEF"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Redacted documents</header><text>The court shall consider and order redactions under this subclause in accordance with the procedures under section 3132(a)(2)(C)(II). </text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HD8220BC7354B463AAFD108FF416BAA1A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Review by court</header><text>The court may, in its discretion, require the governmental entity to provide the factual basis for the certification described in clause (i) and may review that factual basis for sufficiency. </text></clause><clause id="H1ED5F100735A455483A5CF961158ABC4"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Notification</header><subclause id="H22A0216B39654BDE9AA4CC05E3AA1689"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A governmental entity shall promptly notify the court once the governmental entity no longer has reason to believe that the order is necessary to prevent an adverse result described in section 3132(a)(2)(B).</text></subclause><subclause id="H8236596E997B41159F06FF30556CBA1F"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>After being notified by the governmental entity, the court shall revoke the order. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9DD5353EE92499298BBA87C43D6394F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Preclusion of notice orders that may be issued only under subparagraph (A)(i) to criminal surveillance orders or subpoenas that are listed in the preclusion of notice order. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1D20D700BD84A18906085FA8D4A79CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to—</text><subparagraph id="H3BF95A8757B74BE6BE11DBA088DCC4D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any person to whom disclosure is necessary in order to comply with the request;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC630BAEEEC9F41FDA1FDAC57B1F8B591"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an attorney in order to obtain legal advice or assistance regarding the request; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H450E2C08EB484688A508719645A53A61" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other person as permitted by the court.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA33905E936D04DA797566F580940F13F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to prohibit a recipient of an order under this subsection from challenging the order on grounds that the order violates the Constitution of the United States or, in the case of an order issued by a State or Tribal court, the State or Tribal constitution. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7B903248347D4978B2CDBA573650882A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports concerning preclusion of notice orders</header><paragraph id="H9D6AEABAE4EB404FAA0F6880ABD984EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In January of each year, any judge who has issued an order (or an extension thereof) under subsection (b) that expired during the preceding year, or who has denied approval of a request for a preclusion of notice order, shall report to the Administrative Office of the United States Courts—</text><subparagraph id="HDBAEB2A2574D47DFB421561316463A88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the fact that an order or extension was applied for;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE613CE44F91C42A2838AB61BA36A8FC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fact that the order or extension was granted as applied for, was modified, or was denied;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7788047A897B4BEC8DC15C58421B560E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the period of the preclusion of notice required by the order, and the number and duration of any extensions of the order;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA68FB78999348D89FBCFC98C4A23363"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the nature of the offense or criminal investigation that was the basis for the underlying criminal surveillance order;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C5D125D8CA5414DBC5176C1364D078E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the name of each provider of electronic communication service or remote computing service served with the order, if so granted; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E47311A998442AA86D45B69B69D46BF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the investigative or law enforcement agency that submitted the application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H11F811B61CBA476F98E85EA36A3E3A05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public report</header><text>In June of each year, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall publish on the website of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts and include in the report required under section 2519(3)—</text><subparagraph id="HDF8F9BCE75A74E1FA5AC936EB0323F53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a full and complete report concerning—</text><clause id="H7018D39897744887A45B4A391852B425"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of applications for orders authorizing or approving the preclusion of notice pursuant to this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HC1CB374CE8E149CF89CEB05EF208B706"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of orders and extensions granted or denied pursuant to this section during the preceding calendar year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BD10FDD1EEC47A1A55EAE2E1EE59040"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a detailed summary and analysis of each category of data required to be reported under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDAA346F5B084B1FBC4C0DBB8B09E5BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Format</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall, in consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Administrator of General Services, private entities offering electronic case management software, the National Center for State Courts, and the National American Indian Court Judges Association, publish a machine readable form that shall be used for any report required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFD41DEA3AA34FB091DEBBDA17B6B032"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts may promulgate regulations with respect to the content and form of the reports required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21C49ACE68AF4396A23DC291A51CBC94"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Any order issued under subsection (a) or (b) before the effective date of chapter 206A shall be for a period of not longer than 180 days.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H57C0883A566D4CC5904223311A1E0357"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional grounds for issuing warrant</header><text>Section 3103a of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3F9575DEFF3C48948634C47A18A79DFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(3), by inserting <quote>, not to exceed 180 days,</quote> after <quote>certain</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2079DFF33EBD459D8E132A85A9B533C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by inserting <quote>, not to exceed 180 days</quote> before the period at the end; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA2667F02B564EC098FDA84745BEF9DF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1)—</text><subparagraph id="H2C53E58DBDCB4ABDA0DE9A3E239A0B56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB65D7EDD2DA42CBA012A09120F693EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0DFFB984BBE40B3A703E9B3839BB117"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96542FF38FA9448D98081B4EE4D3A070"><subparagraph id="HA1A9F1C6B8F946A4963976D19DBA0D3F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the identification of the statute or rule of law authorizing the search and seizure of property or material.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD9C13978AA0447D696B818CD5CB67322"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 2705 and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HB0375623CC8343209DB1AA3656779221"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H943BE94FE9E147598221FCD167121F83">2705. Delay and preclusion of notice.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HCF5B9F6533DC434E9CEADD25FF132123"><enum>6.</enum><header>Incentives for State and Tribal courts to implement requirements</header><subsection id="HE8E1BF366542446991059FB7D75079E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendments</header><paragraph id="H9297AB85BAC9477A9F8EF428A1F51F8A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Stored communications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">Chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HAA84F0817B7D410297BC6B368CAA6E03"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 2703, as amended by section 4(a) of this Act, by inserting after <quote>return procedures</quote> each place the term appears the following: <quote>and containing a certification that the court is acting in compliance with chapter 206A</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF6B234ECE2E4D3C8550805C82C11386"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2711(3)(B), by inserting <quote>that is acting in compliance with chapter 206A</quote> after <quote>search warrants</quote>. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7590F1CDDF614AB9BDCE234D986F5368"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Wiretapping</header><text>Section 2516(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>The principal prosecuting attorney of any State</quote> and inserting <quote>If a State requires that courts in the state comply with chapter 206A, the principal prosecuting attorney of that State</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FA058687C924D9B855AA14E5AFBE5A2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pen registers and trap and trace devices</header><text>Section 3122(a)(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>and if the State requires that courts in the state comply with chapter 206A,</quote> after <quote>law,</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDB2B5F60FE34DA6B5A0F3EDE754CFDD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Full faith and credit</header><text>The third undesignated paragraph of section 1738 of title 28, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, provided that any criminal surveillance order, as defined in section 3131 of title 18, shall be entitled to full faith and credit only if the order contains a certification that the court that issued the order is acting in compliance with the requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/206A">chapter 206A</external-xref> of title 18</quote> before the period at the end. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H970637570B5F464BBEA70125B663B8C0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H9DEB6925ECF4405F8E357653C35489DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date that is 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF07C935A49A1496C9DF0A7D73730FF17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delayed applicability for certain State and Tribal courts</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply on and after the date that is 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act—</text><subparagraph id="HCE6F15D8F734462689DD4CC0043DA17A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to a State or Tribal court that, on the date of enactment of this Act, does not offer electronic docketing or public online access to dockets; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H468A4464405A4326AFCF1794A9347DC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to any State or Tribal court that certifies that the court needs more time to comply with the requirements of the subsection. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3DAC3114E3034DC387449BF11B73F34E"><enum>7.</enum><header>Modernizing criminal surveillance reports</header><subsection id="HBBC22F2727C74809B85BDA8AAD1DFF93"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports concerning access to customer communications or records</header><paragraph id="HE06480D19545455996BB93D55DC6E129"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2703 title 18, United States Code, as amended by section 4(5) of this Act, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67A28D0A96404A36B9C846168D6B4F8B"><subsection id="H26718970BB484E36B067CF12E832202D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reports concerning access to customer communications or records</header><paragraph id="H0BEF8FE7CFE84E8D8A4FAF4EC7BB0E0F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In January of each year, any judge who has issued an order under this section or a warrant to obtain records described in this section, or who has denied approval of an application under this section during the preceding year, shall report to the Administrative Office of the United States Courts—</text><subparagraph id="HE82BEC2E794648A882DB3F5C0B35705C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the fact that the order or warrant was applied for; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1738A2ACF4D4D2A900317B4EE075EF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the type of records sought in the order or warrant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41E88598F87C422594BAA895AFA8B6D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether the order or warrant was—</text><clause id="H20B37F17543A453AB916CF9F8BBDAA4F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>granted as applied for; </text></clause><clause id="H42738AB255C042838FD6D7407AB8226D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>granted as modified; or </text></clause><clause id="H5814BF62170149E1AF88B42B7F6E7783"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>denied;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5C4AD9C23864B84806EFACFEE8609FE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the subsection of this section under which the application for the order or warrant was filed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E52B3D19C0148379435A3DD0A139B5C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the nature of the offense or criminal investigation that was the basis for the application for the order or warrant; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38E73F06EC8B4F71B5A539F78EC0B3DE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the name of each provider of electronic communication service or remote computing service served with the order or warrant, if so granted; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D81E0E8019F4525B8FA86E26A3430B9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the investigative or law enforcement agency that submitted the application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5216139B878D458D853DE5892276929D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public report</header><text>In June of each year, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall publish on the website of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts and include in the report required under section 2519(3)—</text><subparagraph id="H4EE1EC92A27542F28017B521F76EA5AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text> a full and complete report concerning the number of applications for orders or warrants requiring the disclosure of, during the preceding calendar year—</text><clause id="HF4C14BB6B80E47108E97FEF9C33F892A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the contents of wire or electronic communications in electronic storage under subsection (a); </text></clause><clause id="HAB062395996E42AEA424BD575803989F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the contents of wire or electronic communications in a remote computer service under subsection (b); and</text></clause><clause id="H16E500CA611E469CB911C1F64FB4A8C0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>records concerning electronic communication service or remote computer service under subsection (c);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAC795CB7C164CDCA3873D4B2B5F01F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text> the number of orders and warrants granted or denied under this section during the preceding calendar year; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD240D05B23934FD79AF7932A95C6420F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a detailed summary and analysis of each category of data required to be filed with the Administrative Office of the United States Courts under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C90396E13C44029AF3EB1839B8E45B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Format</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Government Surveillance Transparency Act of 2023</short-title>, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall, in consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Administrator of General Services, the Electronic Public Access Public User Group, private entities offering electronic case management software, the National Center for State Courts, and the National American Indian Court Judges Association, publish a machine readable form that shall be used for any report required under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD62111D1423435EB0F5AEC3DE1B49ED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts may issue binding regulations with respect to the content and form of the reports required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H20FB420A1B354A19A7BF32095219BAFE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>Section 2519(3) of title 18, United States Code, is amended, in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>publish on the website of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts</quote> before <quote>transmit</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H41F9CFFEBF37464E918F9B24058EA2FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports concerning pen registers and trap and trace devices</header><text>Section 3126 of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0CC5A9526C96432FAE1C13685D0A1F00"><section id="H45965446D9EE4461BC637D01014B6EE5"><enum>3126.</enum><header>Reports concerning pen registers and trap and trace devices</header><subsection id="H148B999939BC4BC3A26506AE67C332D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In January of each year, any judge who has issued an order (or an extension thereof) under section 3123 that expired during the preceding year, or who has denied approval of an installation and use of a pen register or trap and trace device during that year, shall report to the Administrative Office of the United States Courts—</text><paragraph id="H4A9F1C7B5E2B409ABEB27797498C5623"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the fact that an order or extension was applied for;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F30392B7C224A0ABBC9FE04CFD64FA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the kind of order or extension applied for;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H059A52E7730945FE95C0819FC0DC6695"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the fact that the order or extension was granted as applied for, was modified, or was denied;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A6D275318654CBB92E68ABB86EBC9D0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the period of installation and use of a pen register or trap and trace device authorized by the order, and the number and duration of any extensions of the order;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA01BE0FC3D234B69A68E04E5AB5497D6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the offense specified in the order or application, or extension of an order;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5838778975DE4C69AE39CF8D4BB6E0A4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the precise nature of the facilities affected and the precise nature of the information sought; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H498ADE75A77044DC83797D18D1FD3A81"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the investigative or law enforcement agency that submitted the application.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H18B647CCCDC14283BDB5D545C3509DBC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public report</header><text>In June of each year, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall publish on the website of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts and include in the report required under section 2519(3)—</text><paragraph id="H9EF0D96416BC4AA8BD91FA5D08DB0533"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a full and complete report concerning—</text><subparagraph id="H132E1BAF0A7048B38D3F15043F936146"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of applications for orders authorizing or approving the installation and use of a pen register or trap and trace device pursuant to this chapter; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E9CFF6A0BD24DF9BCD18B3093EB11A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of orders and extensions granted or denied pursuant to this chapter during the preceding calendar year; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD8105B74B04419880710ABA3BDFCEA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text> a detailed summary and analysis of each category of data required to be reported under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H802DE5ACF0104595ABE90481233196EE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Format</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Government Surveillance Transparency Act of 2023</short-title>, the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall, in consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Administrator of General Services, private entities offering electronic case management software, the National Center for State Courts, and the National American Indian Court Judges Association, publish a machine readable form that shall be used for any report required under subsection (a). </text></subsection><subsection id="H2053A184BC79483C934AA0D14B6077BA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts may issue binding regulations with respect to the content and form of the reports required under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC8FEFFDDD4EA4C7F85067110D3A2DE16"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting of emergency disclosures</header><text>Section 2702(d) of title 18, United States Code, is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>and publish on the website of the Department of Justice</quote> after <quote>Senate</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBB4287FBCFC2442AB533DDC5B78A9C69"><enum>8.</enum><header>Grants</header><subsection id="HE49FE1E95F724E078677B38B78097E87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="H09804CF5EFE7445C8EA8FB19702C6BB3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21699B52482E4281A03118066CE6E8F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>State</term> means each of the several States of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, and the United States Virgin Islands.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H716FFD0279D24FAB892E5DDD71A148EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Attorney General shall make grants to State and Tribal court systems for the cost of implementing the requirements under the amendments made by this Act for the 5-year period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC89F5E8A8807471AB1306C66B0C66E1B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The total amount of grants awarded under this section shall be not greater than $25,000,000.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6DF580137C9742AE88160735820FD2A0"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated—</text><paragraph id="H124DB47F81394CF08F3A27DE99592D97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$1,000,000 to the Administrative Office of the United States Courts to implement the requirements of this Act and the amendments made by this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC1288F0BA304BC4BF10E6D484379F11"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$25,000,000 to carry out the grant program under section 8.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5CC3738C800B425682B1C70BCFA7F8AF"><enum>10.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such a provision or amendment to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remaining provisions of and amendments made by this Act, and the application of the provision or amendment held to be unconstitutional to any other person or circumstance, shall not be affected thereby. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

