<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8420CEF285D5420F9B7233B99ECB9337" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4458 IH: Improving Contract Transparency for the SNS Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4458</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230703">July 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title III of the Public Health Service Act to provide for clarity with respect to the duration of contracts for procurement of supplies for the Strategic National Stockpile, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1655606210AF428087CA707046BE6B2A" style="OLC"><section id="HE476017811CC46A4B02CEBDEACE69D22" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Contract Transparency for the SNS Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1DD5B18D6B214F4389E2A53B05D61465"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strategic National Stockpile procurement contract duration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 319F–2(a) of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 247d–6b(a)) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9FD414A1D41E4F34B96C0E1046CAAC64" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HDB8011D562C646EA949BD62F8DABE128"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Procurement contract duration</header><subparagraph id="H309E91E0342641FA810981AF404BA589"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A contract for the procurement of a drug, vaccine or other biological product, medical device, or other supplies for the stockpile under paragraph (1) shall be for a period not to exceed five years, except that, in first awarding the contract, the Secretary may provide for a longer duration, not exceeding 10 years, if the Secretary determines that complexities or other difficulties in performance under the contract justify such a period. The contract shall be renewable for additional periods, none of which shall exceed five years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC07C626541C04F4BBE31904223E4BF00"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>The Secretary shall notify—</text><clause id="HDC2A8787BF5C4C74A8D5816E0CC5C8A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate upon a determination by the Secretary to modify, renew, extend, or terminate a contract referred to in subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H613B1ACFB4BB4EA1B7AE6D6D651BC8E3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the relevant vendor within 90 days of a determination by the Secretary to modify, renew, extend, or terminate such a contract.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

