<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H90434442AD024E0B9655DC20A61B6DFC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 761 IH: Securing American Families from Exploitation at the Border Act </dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 761</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency to establish a grant program to reimburse individuals for loss or damage to property near the southern border of the United States caused by an individual illegally crossing the border, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H46E443AFD1134FD9A5221F3098236193" style="OLC"><section id="H2C1A06BF1FEA4906AD2A26EC835AB977" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing American Families from Exploitation at the Border Act </short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAFE Border Act</short-title></quote> .</text></section><section id="HC6B2AF2733204A959E16A58AD916397A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H7FB0EE67472E48D4A131BCF319EB72DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Impacted party</header><text>The term <quote>impacted party</quote> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H6A35E3CC175841E8B15D6B809E41CE19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>owns real property within, the border zone; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6440BBB9EA614A91BE803F2209791143"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has experienced property theft or property damage on the property, as applicable, by an individual illegally crossing the U.S.-Mexico border. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB023AFEA8C249E08F586F7AC01B86D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>At-risk party</header><text>The term <quote>at-risk party</quote> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HF25675F9EEFF47199AF084ED15167782"><enum>(A)</enum><text>owns property within the border zone that does not have a bollard-style border barrier that is adjacent to such property; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H519471ECB6034BA28D606768E4627140"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reasonably believes to be at risk of experiencing property theft or property damage on the property, as applicable, by an individual illegally crossing the U.S.-Mexico border. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D3E447032344B34999CB36721E07720" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Border zone</header><text>The term <quote>border zone</quote> means the area of the United States that is within 10 miles of the U.S.-Mexico border.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H45E89DCEBAE249A0955136E60D69842A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Southern Border Landowner Security Grant Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall establish a grant program to be known as the Southern Border Landowner Security Grant Program to provide grants to impacted parties to cover losses or damage to property and to at-risk parties to improve the security of certain property. </text></section><section id="H07E9001F9DE94477B30A337F3B211C0A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants to impacted parties</header><subsection id="HF27CAEADD65F4F2D999584C0DDC03F0F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may provide grants under this Act to an impacted party to cover loss or damages not otherwise covered by insurance to the impacted property if such party certifies, to the satisfaction of the Administrator, that the property—</text><paragraph id="H8A6C78961D27427A900F0CEB3BFCC5C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>was located in the border zone at the time such loss or damage occurred; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7749294A14524559BD2688D806098061"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the loss or damage was caused by an individual illegally crossing the U.S.-Mexico border.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82587BF2065F491EB9575B69737B0667"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an impacted party shall submit to the Administrator an application that includes documentation of the loss or damage and an estimate of the value of such loss or an estimate of the cost to repair such damage.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB1E55B0E0DE04895A3EA72777A4363A6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grants to at-risk parties</header><subsection id="HDC768FAE31234BBDB7BDBFE43363B804"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may provide grants under this Act to an at-risk party to improve the physical security of property located within the border zone if such party certifies, to the satisfaction of the Administrator, that the party reasonably believes that the property of such party is at risk of loss or damage caused by an individual illegally crossing the U.S.-Mexico border.</text></subsection><subsection id="H325D2169191D46FFA8E9779ABACB6679"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on use of funds</header><text>Not later than 290 days after an at-risk party receives funds under this section, such party shall submit to the Administrator documentation on how the party spends such funds. Any funds that remain unspent on the day on which such documentation is submitted shall be returned to the Administrator for further provision under this section. </text></subsection></section><section id="H853EE86697AF42409D6737F0AA3170AC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Funding</header><subsection id="HA46941C6548B49EFB937D7A31E7F450E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transfer of funds</header><text>Of the funds appropriated under the heading <quote>Procurement, Construction, and Improvement</quote> for use by the U.S. Customs and Border Patrol that are unobligated and unexpended as of the date of enactment of this Act, $75,000,000 shall be transferred to the Administrator to provide grants under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5FE062D1F80847D1BDF6BAAF4849C7D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fiscal year limitation</header><text>Of the funds transferred under subsection (a), the Administrator may expend $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2022 through 2024.</text></subsection><subsection id="H76FDA66DFBC0433EB2240008D5ACB33B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation on grant amount</header><text>An individual may not receive more than a total of $25,000 under this section for fiscal years 2022 through 2024.</text></subsection></section><section id="H56BCA99EA45148EC949C80BCC4BC2CD5"><enum>7.</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator may issues such regulations as are necessary to carry out this Act, including—</text><paragraph id="HCC5EC7A66FC24A1A89C0834777C185F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requirements that applicants for funds under this Act submit evidentiary documentation, including property deeds, police reports, insurance coverage documentation, and other documentation considered appropriate by the Administrator;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4A88C0757AA4883BAA74BBE28AB8F9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a review process conducted by the Administrator or the inspector general of the Agency to review applications annually for waste, fraud, and abuse; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H927A7753E0924A4CB4EAA056BC2CCF9D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the applicable penalties for fraudulent claims or false statements.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6339D45B7C6445C3A85FBCB3E33BAE21"><enum>8.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The authority to provide grants under this Act shall cease on the last date of fiscal year 2026. Any funds that have not been obligated under this section before that date shall be transferred to the heading <quote>Procurement, Construction, and Improvement</quote> for use by the U.S. Customs and Border Patrol.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

