<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H785B9A8CDDBD4F228C4247DCCAF1CE0F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3408 IH: Developing Responsible Individuals for a Vibrant Economy Safe Integrity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3408</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish an apprenticeship program for commercial drivers under the age of 21, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HD2D54BF475B24C9E90BD266064F243BD" style="OLC">
<section id="HD21DE82176A149C5B5F0ECB7983FFDC1" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Developing Responsible Individuals for a Vibrant Economy Safe Integrity Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DRIVE Safe Integrity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H468C2803FADC431EAFD606C550D866EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HAD52E94B01B04702A5E3ABD4FC868686"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Seamless, efficient, and resilient supply chains are essential to the production and delivery of goods across the nation to meet the needs of American consumers and maintain the economic security of the country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H96428981F4DC4989A6E4514E8790FA85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>These supply chains are heavily dependent on trucking across a variety of sectors and require a steady pipeline of professional truck drivers to transport goods in a safe and timely manner.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA79B3C86597C41D29A0736AF2CD2E174"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In 2022, the shortage of qualified drivers reached a near-record level of 78,000. The already substantial shortage is expected to increase to 160,000 drivers by 2031 absent any changes to the status quo.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7283D42514C484DB5A42F3B685C9A51"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Over the next decade, roughly 1,200,000 new drivers will need to be hired to keep pace with increasing demand and the aging workforce.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFA15A6D47542469FB9DA91FDE931FD63"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Trucking is a crucial profession that links every component of the supply chain, and it offers diverse opportunities to workers, from over the road to local and regional trucking, and fulfilling careers with family-sustaining salaries, all without the debt that often accompanies a college degree.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA289FAC693E44A3ACA9335C603C8947"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Regulatory barriers prevent motor carriers from offering these pathways to 18- to 20-year-olds who may otherwise want to pursue a career in trucking, resulting in the loss of these individuals to other professions.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC2E6AA71167346CBB1B048AF0E043422"><enum>(7)</enum><text>To address these barriers and confront the driver shortage, Congress included section 23022 in the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act, which requires the Secretary of Transportation to create a pilot program for commercial drivers between the ages of 18 and 20.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD67A1D7BD8274FE08D6B8DFB28DC1672"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act was based on bicameral bipartisan legislation, the <quote>Developing Responsible Individuals for a Vibrant Economy Act</quote> or the <quote>DRIVE-SAFE Act</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H37633FCF63BB4C0DA7A6E2E840D134BA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>To meet the requirements of section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act, the U.S. Department of Transportation established the Safe Driver Apprenticeship Pilot Program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H342BE0CCFBE645709332D3D3AFBEB251"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The 3-year pilot program included in the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act was the result of a carefully crafted bipartisan compromise by the Senate Commerce Committee.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB5919C05266447B289A40468079ED814"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The pilot program enables 18- to 20-year-old drivers to receive rigorous training as professional truck drivers and drive in interstate commerce, much as they are able to do in intrastate commerce in 49 States plus the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9371ED06B81435ABFDB1E769890D0A8"><enum>(12)</enum><text>For purposes of the pilot program, section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act defined the term <term>apprentice</term> as an individual who is under the age of 21 and holds a commercial driver’s license.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5A47B089880B46FC8A34CA2A65EF17D2"><enum>(13)</enum><text>As directed by section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act, this pilot program requires advanced safety equipment and hours of supervision that go significantly beyond the requirements that 18- to 20-year-olds must fulfill in order to receive a commercial driver’s license to operate in intrastate commerce in those 49 States plus the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD23ABD9059424682800A1D0D74E5A3C7"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Through this pilot program, modeled in part on graduated drivers licensing concepts that have been found to improve the safety of new drivers, the U.S. Department of Transportation is able to collect data demonstrating that individuals who receive rigorous training and develop good habits early in their career can safely operate motor vehicles in interstate commerce.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8AFC496850734037BB55E465F319DF68"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Congress supports the successful implementation of the Safe Driver Apprenticeship Pilot Program and should consider actions to ensure that program requirements not specified in the statute do not limit or inhibit participation in the pilot program or the ability to collect sufficient and credible data.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H62C0F69193374027B9B9AFFF30FDF9F7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on apprenticeship program</header> <subsection id="H628C4151979644B7A0F73F1136805D91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration begins accepting applications from motor carriers to participate in the apprenticeship pilot program under section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31315">49 U.S.C. 31315</external-xref> note), and quarterly thereafter, the Secretary of Transportation shall provide to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report on the status of the Safe Driver Apprenticeship Pilot Program.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HEAEDD6FF769C4DD0B9B649265623FDBC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H5D7425BB24BA4D6E8A42EDFE77796F3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of motor carriers that have applied to participate in the apprenticeship pilot program and the number of motor carriers approved by the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration to participate in the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2779F0D996BF438F9CB1FB7B3145DF94"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of motor carriers that are prequalified but have not provided the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration with a valid registered apprenticeship number.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1EDBBC2B4194882A3C402351295E819"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of experienced drivers that have applied to participate in the program and the number of experienced drivers approved by the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration to participate in the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H09D5F6F228C34DF0997E76669046CC14"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of prospective apprentices that have applied to participate in the program and the number of apprentices approved by the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration to participate in the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF157CC3AA1E9491B852B28EEFCD7A906"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of apprentices currently participating in the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4383623840DD48B5A165809563408C5F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The number of apprentices who have been removed from the program, as well as an explanation for each removal.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H062A4140161541BF9E0D0A99FFA151AC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The number of apprentices who have withdrawn from the program, as well as an explanation for each withdrawal.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2AF57037AE294CFABDCEDCF65204F125"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The average number of days for the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration to process applications from motor carriers, experienced drivers, and prospective apprentices to participate in the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4104A89D83F84350B3991C0D21DDB083"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of any incidents in which the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration took longer than 30 days to approve or reject an application from a motor carrier, experienced driver, or prospective apprentice to participate in the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H431DB4B3674E41A392DE18D8F882A015"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A description of program requirements currently in effect that were not specifically mandated in section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31315">49 U.S.C. 31315</external-xref> note), including justifications for the inclusion of these program requirements as well as expected implications on motor carrier, experienced driver, and prospective apprentice participation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAF0D1C11912A480F8D1FC3CFD87CCD4A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Promotion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Transportation shall promote the apprenticeship pilot program under section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31315">49 U.S.C. 31315</external-xref> note) and, if necessary, remove requirements for participation in the program that go beyond section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31315">49 U.S.C. 31315</external-xref> note) in order to improve participation rates and collect sufficient data.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HE90CA79EDF6444739C5572972D12D00C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Apprenticeship program for commercial drivers under the age of 21</header>
<subsection id="H34324EE53A3B41968F37043A2326C733"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HCD75656F54B048A9A0BEF09086E5DC79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprentice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprentice</term> means an employee under the age of 21 who holds a commercial driver’s license required to operate a class of vehicles described in part 383 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4FD4B12564E048DBBCFCA1EFE333DA1D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commercial driver's license</header><text>The term <term>commercial driver's license</term> has the meaning given the term in section 31301 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D2E2415A8F747939F488CA7E4D27790" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commercial motor vehicle</header><text>The term <term>commercial motor vehicle</term> means a commercial motor vehicle that meets the definition under paragraph (1) or (4) of the definition of the term <term>commercial motor vehicle</term> in section 390.5 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H984EAC1C1D78403F8CA20A20687085A8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Driving time</header><text>The term <term>driving time</term> has the meaning given the term in section 395.2 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE462279B1D5844A79E45C4C0E2083296"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Employee</header><text>The term <term>employee</term> has the meaning given such term in section 31132 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0F8335FA8FA4475E933F8D48480275AA"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Employer</header><text>The term <term>employer</term> has the meaning given such term in section 31132 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23D86AED144547B79AF5ACE21A265D75"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Experienced driver</header><text>The term <term>experienced driver</term> means an individual who—</text>
<subparagraph id="H27CE1E2AA3134A878641E4B4C61AEBDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not less than 21 years of age;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9E39AEA0B7FC4F3394336FAE23403CEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has held a commercial driver’s license for the 2-year period ending on the date on which the individual serves as an experienced driver under subsection (c)(3)(B);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2169D43301CA4ED9B1ACDC3ED2B25540"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has had no preventable accidents reportable to the Department of Transportation or pointed moving violations during the 1-year period ending on the date on which the individual serves as an experienced driver under subsection (c)(3)(B); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8EFE16C2C2134FF7AF7427EB734295F4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a minimum of 2 years of experience driving a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H643DBA6CDBAB4A0D9264270EDECCAFC8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>On-duty time</header><text>The term <term>on-duty time</term> has the meaning given the term in section 395.2 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C58BE33CD3F4093A25B7894B1E72064"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Pointed moving violation</header><text>The term <term>pointed moving violation</term> means a violation that results in points being added to the license of a driver, or a similar comparable violation, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB7CF936533F941AB82A9A059181FE032"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H38A54CBC58314A26BA5F772D25F219CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Apprentice</header><text>An apprentice may—</text>
<paragraph id="HEBE39C1352674E9D8BC774FF13FB1351"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">drive a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce while taking part in the 120-hour probationary period under subsection (c)(1) or the 280-hour probationary period under subsection (c)(2), pursuant to an apprenticeship program established by an employer in accordance with this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H70B3AF686C9F4EE3B8A58ACB80039231"><enum>(2)</enum><text>drive a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce after the apprentice completes an apprenticeship program described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H183DCB57A6B544B19A3CC0B94BFAEC77"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An apprenticeship program referred to in subsection (b) is a program that consists of the following requirements:</text> <paragraph id="H0F962E9664A04DF68EBB7969DF76DC6D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>120-hour probationary period</header> <subparagraph id="HEC87AB76938840438E9EE27E761F8669"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The apprentice shall complete 120 hours of on-duty time, of which not less than 80 hours are driving time in a commercial motor vehicle.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4D007EDD75FA427A9DF199F871AC53D1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Performance benchmarks</header><text>In order to complete the 120-hour probationary period under subparagraph (A), an employer shall determine that the apprentice is competent in each of the following areas:</text> <clause id="H466FD2FFD28B4D2787C9891370BF1BCB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Interstate, city traffic, rural 2-lane, and evening driving.</text></clause>
<clause id="H53FE5BC4CFA8477FBC3654AC8A5912BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Safety awareness.</text></clause> <clause id="H8F9D0D82B3FE45F3BA169376152390B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Speed and space management.</text></clause>
<clause id="HAFCE1B2F233B4E2A85E63EF94915B42B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Lane control.</text></clause> <clause id="HB46C0BD3F47C49CA82B845C78C17FF8C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Mirror scanning.</text></clause>
<clause id="HCB7FC8C4BBDE42D2BF0E80F47C9246E9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Right and left turns.</text></clause> <clause id="HE3EF48F40A57428CB473EEBF084DF005"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Logging and complying with rules relating to hours of service.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC95BCAD4821D42C0BA85B0050AEA0380"><enum>(2)</enum><header>280-hour probationary period</header>
<subparagraph id="H77389F45911047759BC1DC5A83683EB7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After completing the 120-hour probationary period under paragraph (1), the apprentice shall complete 280 hours of on-duty time, of which not less than 160 hours are driving time in a commercial motor vehicle.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78C94860B9F54DBBBD242FD377D4A842"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Performance benchmarks</header><text>In order to complete the 280-hour probationary period under subparagraph (A), an employer shall determine that the apprentice is competent in each of the following areas:</text>
<clause id="HEB52F8C09127429DB4C362C613E6B097"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Backing and maneuvering in close quarters.</text></clause> <clause id="HBDF742D2F63C4F068E7F3F6B47D9726C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Pre-trip inspections.</text></clause>
<clause id="H6914209A25CB4D6AB56F0A7C8A776D8D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Fueling procedures.</text></clause> <clause id="H80D3887D34704B508DF26877958EDDC3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Weighing loads, weight distribution, and sliding tandems.</text></clause>
<clause id="H57001996D31A4C9A9F04C8860E151099"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Coupling and uncoupling procedures.</text></clause> <clause id="H52F6B3EFFFB847C3B30686427B5EDD0A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Trip planning, truck routes, map reading, navigation, and permits.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6948DC1AB92D46819EF94CC1F26170B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Restrictions for 120-hour and 280-hour probationary periods</header><text>During the 120-hour probationary period under paragraph (1) and the 280-hour probationary period under paragraph (2)—</text> <subparagraph id="H11B810DDA7964946A34AB0F08494FC86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the apprentice may only drive a commercial motor vehicle that has—</text>
<clause id="H00D4CC4A89A74C0FAC6C3BB4B52AA5ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">automatic manual or automatic transmissions;</text></clause> <clause id="H8046843A6B4145B38F187B9306B71CBC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>active braking collision mitigation systems;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0C09E89708BD492580916B21D38D76F5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>forward-facing video event capture; and</text></clause> <clause id="H93A7914E73624F90BF7B03824399C202"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>governed speeds of 65 miles per hour at the pedal and 65 miles per hour under adaptive cruise control; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HADED605E4BED48CE9C0AC88A7D96CA91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the apprentice shall be accompanied in the cab of the commercial motor vehicle by an experienced driver.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF69A28C74817425DA66FA8092CD91DDF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Records retention</header><text>The employer shall maintain records, in a manner required by the Secretary, relating to the satisfaction of the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (2)(B) by the apprentice.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFD4300D3365D4274979C92288516B3B9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reportable incidents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the apprentice is involved in a preventable accident reportable to the Department of Transportation or a pointed moving violation while driving a commercial motor vehicle as part of an apprenticeship program described in this subsection, the apprentice shall undergo remediation and additional training until the apprentice can demonstrate, to the satisfaction of the employer, competence in each of the performance benchmarks described in paragraphs (1)(B) and (2)(B).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC40D7CD7EFB44897B0D866667D533CC3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Completion of program</header><text>The apprentice shall be considered to have completed the apprenticeship program on the date on which the apprentice completes the 280-hour probationary period under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6DAE63EE026F4152B836E8677156DD8D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Minimum requirements</header>
<subparagraph id="HC593CB36582D42D79CDCCBCF47D820B4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this Act prevents an employer from imposing additional requirements on an apprentice taking part in an apprenticeship program established pursuant to this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49A5E31A259D4A819595D6F2ED6C00DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technologies</header><text>Nothing in this Act prevents an employer from requiring or installing additional technologies in a commercial motor vehicle in addition to the technologies described in paragraph (3)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE960F7FA244641E0A8FEC1139790F9C2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, not later than 1 year after the sunset of the apprenticeship pilot program under section 23022 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31315">49 U.S.C. 31315</external-xref> note), barring credible and sufficient data from a representative sample producing evidence that drivers participating in the pilot program are less safe than drivers operating a commercial motor vehicle in interstate or intrastate commerce on the day before the date of enactment of such Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall promulgate regulations for commercial drivers between the ages of 18 and 20, pursuant to this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H96BE749CEAEE4F4980C8BEBD59091B2F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No effect on license requirement</header><text>Nothing in this Act exempts an apprentice from any requirement to hold a commercial driver’s license in order to operate a commercial motor vehicle.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8ADF435B58B74F2BBE9D0C122CDB6572"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Employer responsibility</header><text>An employer shall not knowingly allow, require, permit, or authorize a driver under the age of 21 to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce unless the driver is participating in or has completed an apprenticeship program that meets the requirements of subsection (c). </text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

