<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H38BAEA5E5DDC43AD9DFAE788853431D3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3046 IH: Medical Student Education Authorization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3046</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230502">May 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish a grant program to award grants to accredited public institutions of higher education, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H30B50348593A46C8800857837C90BCB8" style="OLC"><section id="H39D5C135E98E407A84EB1D7E78B0F71A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medical Student Education Authorization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H47F06348D69640468ACC8C5C5F5C700C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Education program to support primary health care for medically underserved communities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title VII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/293">42 U.S.C. 293 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H259F9805EFA04D56B4B72053860096AE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H7AAA0DD3B9D34349ABC510A53AB94DAE"><enum>742.</enum><header>Education program to support primary health care for medically underserved communities</header><subsection id="HC1C56A77625D45BB8D897913EA77FCE2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, shall establish a grant program to award grants to accredited public institutions of higher education to carry out the activities described in subsection (d) for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="HBA1CD6515A46400A82D03E6196AE754E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanding and supporting education for medical students who are preparing to become physicians; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCA2143D9D4A41528F700B4672140F20"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">preparing and encouraging each such student trained by a grantee to serve in a Tribal, rural, or medically underserved community as a primary care physician after completing residency training.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8CFAD68F69A349B5B0C5E20B0DCBAD45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an accredited public institution of higher education shall—</text><paragraph id="HB8170170344F4E49A551561534A547E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be located in a State that is in the top quintile of States by a projected shortage of primary care physicians, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65D3013FD01C47AAA72E42F85D553D1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H2B7ECB184A2D4F38BEEDCD29EA0B22D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a certification that such institution will use amounts provided to the institution through the grant to carry out the activities described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC63B1347AD584653855F5D928771FF31"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of how such institution will carry out such activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C2FB87F803A4974A92CECE4D1854B15" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to accredited public institutions of higher education that meet the eligibility requirements of subsection (b) and—</text><paragraph id="H1B6C988DD63C431C95F83284D7FA60A7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are located in a State with not fewer than 2 Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations (as such terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H618590A15B1C42D1AD90DD83A367E093"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have established, or demonstrate plans to establish, a public-private partnership that supports the purposes described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE515C998DB8C45CA8128A1E3DC0B16F5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall, as appropriate, use the funds made available under such grant to carry out the following activities:</text><paragraph id="H0387709FCF3A4B33B9D8470190D3616D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Support or expand community-based and experiential training for medical students who will practice in or serve Tribal, rural, and medically underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2D710CE0CC344A98BB63E0A0AB072A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop and operate programs to train medical students in the provision of primary care services, which may include developing training programs and activities that—</text><subparagraph id="HEDB1D5B964214023B036C52A5C3266AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>emphasize care for Tribal, rural, or medically underserved communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2DF4500171B46B2ABC5D7549D2EFBCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are applicable to primary care practice with respect to individuals from Tribal, rural, or medically underserved communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7425A363B75D4C56A080828B08D807E6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support the use of telehealth technologies and practices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8869658AFE854D1898B4FA37D02D96C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">integrate mental health and substance use disorder care into primary care practice, including prevention and treatment of opioid use disorders and other substance use disorders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A893CEFD4214DC496029EBF5A3662A5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote interdisciplinary training.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0987E34EDBE748019FD7447D3D3E27C4" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Increase the capacity of faculty to develop and operate programs described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11673F029BA54540A006452122A6F5BF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop or expand strategic partnerships, such as public-private partnerships, to improve health outcomes for individuals from Tribal, rural, and medically underserved communities, which partnerships may include—</text><subparagraph id="H28090F7D7245483B8C9CE6704D2867BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">federally recognized Tribes, Tribal Colleges or Universities (as such term is defined in section 316 of the Higher Education Act of 1965), and Tribal organizations (as such term is defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD246259149A446E5A8BEC4D03EE04B4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federally-qualified health centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86E006BC433E4DBEA74DE6B5A2D37239"><enum>(C)</enum><text>rural health clinics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32432D0CDE474D37874F23161FF4504C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health facilities or programs operated by or in accordance with a contract or grant with the Indian Health Service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0481CADEFDE4BEAA69F827B4196064C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>primary care clinics.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9639A8C34FBB460D87AEB9C73C6B5517"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop a plan, as appropriate, for followup with graduates, including with respect to specialties, as applicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69BCE596E06645B58C6BBCBB87DA4A2A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Develop, implement, and evaluate methods to improve recruitment and retention of medical students from Tribal, rural, and medically underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C5C633352CD4BDD9E21EB89CE419827"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Train and support instructors to serve Tribal, rural, and medically underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18B537AE25B04060B6BBCA655AFF2AFD"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prepare medical students for transition into primary care residency training and future practice.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEB35E6D12D14F358E188D565B76C0E8"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide scholarships to medical students.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H83BFAF1A1D704923A3C3B16C4F4A4030"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant under this section shall be awarded for a period of not more than 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H43FC7E5078D44E1C9390E1F685FBEAFD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fiscal year, the amount of a grant made to an eligible entity under this section shall be not less than $1,000,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9A4BC8E9664C41008F078DA9578C7EDF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, as appropriate, require that an eligible entity receiving a grant under this section provide non-Federal matching funds, which may be in cash or in kind, in an amount equal to or greater than 10 percent of the total amount of Federal funds provided through the grant each fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0BC329D13D474DDCAA6C476B7F0D6F7B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $150,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2025.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

