<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA663D366960E4B95BD99613C81DDC529" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6541 IH: To provide for the liquidation or reliquidation of certain entries of steel and aluminum products retroactively approved for exclusion from certain duties.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6541</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231130">November 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the liquidation or reliquidation of certain entries of steel and aluminum products retroactively approved for exclusion from certain duties.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2BCF534A193142579F987978EAB12B54" style="OLC"><section id="H0F6C908EE0CB44578D2E1045CECB3E86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Reliquidation of certain steel and aluminum products retroactively eligible for exclusion from additional duties</header><subsection id="H14194210E1594A0F92C67BBA23B426E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 514 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1514">19 U.S.C. 1514</external-xref>) or any other provision of law, U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall liquidate or reliquidate each entry of a covered product on which duties under section 232 of the Trade Expansion Act of 1962 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1862">19 U.S.C. 1862</external-xref>) were paid before the date of the enactment of this Act without an assessment of such duties.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD6360ED6E46443D99FC5829A8094DBB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requests</header><text>A liquidation or reliquidation may be made under subsection (a) with respect to an entry of an article only if a request therefor is filed with U.S. Customs and Border Protection, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, that contains sufficient information to enable U.S. Customs and Border Protection—</text><paragraph id="HD6239BF90FE54B468A4E9860356A70DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to identify and reconstruct the entry, if necessary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3F285EBEB9345BA883BDFC35563EA85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to verify that the article is a covered product.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8FD76B919A3D4F9292EA745CDCFC5C4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Refunds</header><text>Any refunds owed by the United States pursuant to the liquidation or reliquidation of an entry under this section shall be paid, without interest, not later than 90 days after the date of the liquidation or reliquidation (as the case may be). </text></subsection><subsection id="H23287943A7264B89BF006C791CEB1518"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC7CE1900C3344684BEC31C837C93E8F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered product</term> means a product that—</text><subparagraph id="HADEBEC9F02134B5F89EF8232689C4C22"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is eligible for exclusion from additional duties imposed by the President under section 232 of the Trade Expansion Act of 1962 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1862">19 U.S.C. 1862</external-xref>) on imports of—</text><clause id="HCD461887C3D54900B194501CFA20F0D0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>steel articles classifiable under heading 9903.80.01 of the Harmonized Tariff Schedule of the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H80AD0F5B232A42F3A535A34F7CDC94D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>aluminum articles classifiable under heading 9903.85.01 of such Schedule; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H363DA42DD3BF4266A1CA784FB6EE57F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was granted such exclusion through an approval for retroactive application issued by the Department of Commerce during 2020 or 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F1BCA3E2BA346168162727EBD60A69C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enter; entry</header><text>The terms <term>enter</term> and <term>entry</term> include a withdrawal from warehouse for consumption. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

