<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H466EE728B5F44EFBBFB1A09D23A13447" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2610 IH: To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to specify certain registration statement contents for emerging growth companies, to permit issuers to file draft registration statements with the Securities and Exchange Commission for confidential review, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2610</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001156">Mr. McHenry</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to specify certain registration statement contents for emerging growth companies, to permit issuers to file draft registration statements with the Securities and Exchange Commission for confidential review, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA41A2354BCD34DDCADA43135BDE6DF7E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2E6E006E55A74AC6BB66502090B9EBC4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Registration statements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 12(b) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78l">15 U.S.C. 78l(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC3BAEB9EB7FC4B269E3690487FC233D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(K), by striking <quote>years,</quote> and inserting <quote>years (or, in the case of an emerging growth company, not more than the two preceding years),</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H562EB1FB06544B3099574E404BC540DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBAC1434FDB9E48B3BD237E520D218097" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">Any issuer may confidentially submit to the Commission a draft registration statement for confidential nonpublic review by the staff of the Commission prior to public filing, provided that the initial confidential submission and all amendments thereto shall be publicly filed with the Commission not later than 10 days before the issuer’s requested date of effectiveness of the registration statement. Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, the Commission shall not be compelled to disclose any information provided to or obtained by the Commission pursuant to this subsection. For purposes of section 552 of title 5, this subsection shall be considered a statute described in subsection (b)(3)(B) of such section 552. Information described in or obtained pursuant to this subsection shall be deemed to constitute confidential information for purposes of section 24.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

