<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H255DBCDDF36E44708D70608E73290DF7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2403 IH: Enhanced Background Checks Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2403</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001101">Ms. Clark of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Mrs. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000273">Ms. Leger Fernandez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000579">Mr. Ryan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, to strengthen the background check procedures to be followed before a Federal firearms licensee may transfer a firearm to a person who is not such a licensee.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H05BC75D479504732BABD3144B6365772" style="OLC"><section id="H9B7D938F94D74E288138B5123B9A86AC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Enhanced Background Checks Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H84E24741E2254D379B93E8F57C5D3D4C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening of background check procedures to be followed before a Federal firearms licensee may transfer a firearm to a person who is not such a licensee</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922(t) of title 18, United States Code is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8CA54DAD7748412FBDAB8C854B7A07EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H37FE0F4AE0284966A8FC91DD56F2C9DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking clause (ii) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H61941DC5811B41C28348661119F98A4B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HA1A252BBE68F426F9CF1C95760A3B65E" indent="up2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the event the system has not notified the licensee that the receipt of a firearm by such other person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of this section or State, local, or Tribal law—</text><subclause id="H4C194CF103554495B5A8FA4646BBA75F"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not fewer than 10 business days (meaning a day on which State offices are open) has elapsed since the licensee contacted the system, and the system has not notified the licensee that the receipt of a firearm by such other person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of this section or State, local, or Tribal law, and the other person has submitted, electronically through a website established by the Attorney General or by first-class mail, a petition for review which—</text><item id="H87E1FC904C734DCB9F2E1EC9F469210C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>certifies that such other person has no reason to believe that such other person is prohibited by Federal, State, local, or Tribal law from purchasing or possessing a firearm; and</text></item><item id="HCD8A954713D8472A8F4C047F50B3D83C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>requests that the system respond to the contact referred to in subparagraph (A) within 10 business days after the date the petition was submitted (or, if the petition is submitted by first-class mail, the date the letter containing the petition is postmarked); and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4B2DD3B88AA547848B94F9EEA278A340"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">10 business days have elapsed since the other person so submitted the petition, and the system has not notified the licensee that the receipt of a firearm by such other person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of this section or State, local, or Tribal law;</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5B5B3FA39FF4F8EBDF12120D8B68689"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><clause id="HBC3A4B4EBE49494DA59C6B5661E98012"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end of clause (i); and</text></clause><clause id="H4695D68A3F534EC9A5FFFC0A4DA96DEE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking clause (ii) and all that follows through the 2nd comma in clause (iii) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H35FAFF70931744BD974E06A140E3AB71" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H1A514D68A6AD4EB78E78855CFA93E44F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the transfer could be completed lawfully pursuant to subparagraph (B)(ii) if the person had attained 21 years of age</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3554D7DD82CA4C4297BA256BF9F46E53"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF8B4E5C98A0747308D88DE60469C81C5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HBA8D5414A6D74D14988049832694533F" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2B6EFE16AA3D4DA1A768F94E01D1EC08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prescribe the form on which a petition shall be submitted pursuant to paragraph (1)(B)(ii);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABAB4BC19B9041448EEA69DB7C265C6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the form available electronically, and provide a copy of the form to all licensees referred to in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70CBFA3BF8F74CBE98DDE6D26DD6F791"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide the petitioner and the licensee involved written notice of receipt of the petition, either electronically or by first-class mail; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4937524541ED4438992261FB52B9113B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>respond on an expedited basis to any such petition received by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D56B781B34441A3B7D28D04C282BF0F" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H72B264B1528F4A4BBDEB9CE28829E91E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>If, after 3 business days have elapsed since the licensee initially contacted the system about a firearm transaction, the system notifies the licensee that the transfer to, or receipt of, a firearm by such other person would not violate subsection (d), (g), or (n) (as applicable), or State, local, or Tribal law, the licensee may continue to rely on that notification for the longer of—</text><clause id="H02D295C257E04291B6350A3C509B0C33" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an additional 25 calendar days after the licensee receives the notification; or</text></clause><clause id="HBEA182F90061454B819917F4F4A5DB4A" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>30 calendar days after the date of the initial contact.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E81C5041E164015A6A238BD9FBFC1FA" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If such other person has met the requirements of paragraph (1)(B)(ii) or (1)(C) (as applicable) before the system destroys the records related to the firearm transaction, the licensee may continue to rely on such other person having met the requirements for an additional 25 calendar days after the date such other person first met the requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H03F39DD5EC9C49B3A65E38A1F3CDA36F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 103(l)(3) of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>, but in no case more than 10 business days,</quote>.</text></section><section id="H04D6F60E87E142AB972DB3A0038CAF95"><enum>4.</enum><header>GAO reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 90 days after the end of each of the 1-year, 3-year, and 5-year periods that begin with the effective date of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall prepare and submit to the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate a written report analyzing the extent to which, during the respective period, paragraphs (1)(B)(ii) and (7) of section 922(t) of title 18, United States Code, have prevented firearms from being transferred to prohibited persons, which report shall include but not be limited to the following—</text><paragraph id="H754E277645C5438B8741AB2122C9D6C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the overall implementation of such subsections, including a description of the challenges faced in implementing such paragraphs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF80D782E13F4F9B8731F8B37264EBD8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an aggregate description of firearm purchase delays and denials, with a description of denials, disaggregated by State and by the basis for the denial; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF78C5A73C7794992AA77973B018DFCFE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an aggregate analysis of the petitions submitted pursuant to such paragraph (1)(B)(ii).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF8747AC97E9A42A7B36FACBA83A97D14"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reports on petitions supporting firearms transfers not immediately approved by NICS System, that were not responded to in a timely manner</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation shall make an annual report to the public on the number of petitions received by the national instant criminal background check system established under section 103 of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act that were submitted pursuant to subclause (I) of section 922(t)(1)(B)(ii) of title 18, United States Code, with respect to which a determination was not made within the 10-day period referred to in subclause (II) of such section 922(t)(1)(B)(ii). The report shall include the following, which shall be disaggregated by State:</text><paragraph id="H8269A058284C4622BF3576A1E00B29BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of petitions submitted under such section that were received by the national instant criminal background check system established under section 103 of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2CA83E89F2D4622B656794092BFC18A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of petitioners who were discovered to be ineligible under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law during that 10-day period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78C809D6A6834631BB3C401B18B92455"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The number of petitioners who were discovered to be ineligible under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law after that 10-day period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0663BAB4D3214986A7FAE34A6A6ED602"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The basis of the ineligibility of the petitioners discovered to be ineligible under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law during that 10-day period, and the basis of the ineligibility of the petitioners discovered to be ineligible under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law after that 10-day period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE63BCD70F37548B4813D438E3517487F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of the petitioners whose petitions were denied and who, within 12 months after the denial, were prosecuted under Federal, State, or local law for receiving or attempting to receive a firearm.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HCC6F4E258E604808AFA9E60F53E4EB1B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report to the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 150 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Attorney General, in consultation with the National Resource Center on Domestic Violence and Firearms, shall submit to the Congress a report analyzing the effect, if any, of this Act on the safety of victims of domestic violence, domestic abuse, dating partner violence, sexual assault, and stalking, disaggregated by State, and whether any further amendments to the background check process, including amendments to the conditions that must be met under this Act for a firearm to be transferred when the system has not notified the licensee that such transfer would not violate subsection (d), (g), or (n) of section 922 of title 18, United States Code (as applicable), or State, local, or Tribal law, would likely result in a reduction in the risk of death or great bodily harm to victims of domestic violence, domestic abuse, dating partner violence, sexual assault, and stalking.</text></section><section id="H53C907E1DBC6450FA40BF998F4E1ED50"><enum>7.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect 210 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section><section id="H886CE63A735E4FC5A96D71FA4AB77BA3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Report on firearm transfers denied as a result of a NICS check</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Inspector General, Department of Justice, shall prepare and submit to the Congress a written report on the number of firearm transactions with respect to which the national instant criminal background check system established under the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act has determined that receipt of a firearm by the prospective firearm transferee would violate Federal, State, local, or Tribal law, and which have been referred to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives for investigation.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

