<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF1D15489D1ED4A458C69AF5F5C65CEF6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3329 IH: End Taxpayer Funding of Gender Experimentation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3329</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit taxpayer-funded gender transition procedures, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H61297B49C338407FAD11388B8133CC45" style="OLC"><section id="HA700C86819EE4CA28BFBF151B45678BC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="HE0CD5AC11FC44D5984E32CD2D7B5AD6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>End Taxpayer Funding of Gender Experimentation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF60F13C20129499BBDC87DD2AA07898A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act are as follows: </text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HA700C86819EE4CA28BFBF151B45678BC" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H76E631D5BB7046B49CE215DC1496E2D1" level="title">Title I—Prohibiting Federally Funded Gender Transition Procedures</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7E1ED13ED1974055B38EE06891C3D868" level="section">Sec. 101. Prohibiting taxpayer-funded gender transition procedures.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H10EA947347D649F09FC7583DAF7A9CD3" level="section">Sec. 102. Amendment to table of chapters.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9F51DAA595B94CFD9204EE2C96932585" level="title">Title II—Application Under the Affordable Care Act</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE0F7F2D301214EC3AF12F0BC483677B4" level="section">Sec. 201. Clarifying application of prohibition to premium credits and cost-sharing reductions under ACA.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><title id="H76E631D5BB7046B49CE215DC1496E2D1"><enum>I</enum><header>Prohibiting Federally Funded Gender Transition Procedures</header><section id="H7E1ED13ED1974055B38EE06891C3D868"><enum>101.</enum><header>Prohibiting taxpayer-funded gender transition procedures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title 1, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H3321B24C14FE4348BA4525E445426494" display-inline="no-display-inline"><chapter id="H1463938B114947A0B05B5A5C84DA9338"><enum>4</enum><header>Prohibiting Taxpayer-Funded Gender Transition Procedures</header><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">301. Prohibition on funding for gender transition procedures. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">302. Prohibition on funding for health benefits plans that cover gender transition procedures. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">303. Limitation on Federal facilities and employees. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">304. Construction relating to separate coverage.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">305. Construction relating to the use of non-Federal funds for health coverage.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">306. Construction relating to complications arising from gender transition procedures. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">307. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc><section id="HDA24051977F6476AA54698496FE74C7C"><enum>301.</enum><header>Prohibition on funding for gender transition procedures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No funds authorized or appropriated by Federal law, and none of the funds in any trust fund to which funds are authorized or appropriated by Federal law, shall be expended for any gender transition procedures.</text></section><section id="HB604499D4D3B48219A4EB70C087F4557"><enum>302.</enum><header>Prohibition on funding for health benefits plans that cover gender transition procedures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No funds authorized or appropriated by Federal law, and none of the funds in any trust fund to which funds are authorized or appropriated by Federal law, shall be expended for health benefits coverage that includes coverage of gender transition procedures.</text></section><section id="HCC0FB5EABD2D4885BA875123565EE760"><enum>303.</enum><header>Limitation on Federal facilities and employees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No health care service furnished—</text><paragraph id="H0F2B8FB7747F467588043895BA173A33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by or in a health care facility owned or operated by the Federal Government; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEE57491C3CE49B195D82ED8C513E8A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by any physician or other individual employed by the Federal Government to provide health care services within the scope of the physician’s or individual’s employment, </text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="section">may include gender transition procedures.</continuation-text></section><section id="HA572E1DEBFBD485CA7C2DF5E48A06B78"><enum>304.</enum><header>Construction relating to separate coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall be construed as prohibiting any individual, entity, State, or locality from purchasing separate coverage for gender transition procedures or health benefits coverage that include gender transition procedures so long as such coverage is paid for entirely with funds not authorized or appropriated by Federal law, and such coverage shall not be purchased using matching funds required for a federally subsidized program, including a State or locality’s contribution of Medicaid matching funds.</text></section><section id="HB04B0683E04248BF9B07A0A6E879F5E8"><enum>305.</enum><header>Construction relating to the use of non-Federal funds for health coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall be construed as restricting the ability of any non-Federal health benefits coverage provider from offering coverage for gender transition procedures, or the ability of a State or locality to contract separately with such a provider for such coverage, so long as only funds not authorized or appropriated by Federal law are used, and such coverage shall not be purchased using matching funds required for a federally subsidized program, including a State or locality’s contribution of Medicaid matching funds.</text></section><section id="HA02784DB586D4840B794D92DED639003"><enum>306.</enum><header>Construction relating to complications arising from gender transition procedures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to apply to the treatment of any infection, injury, disease, or disorder that has been caused by or exacerbated by the performance of a gender transition procedure.</text></section><section id="H3875ACE67E244D58A93135EA6BC38F62"><enum>307.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this chapter:</text><paragraph id="HF998ADD5BF1444DC86AD7D2D27B054CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Biological sex</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>biological sex</quote> means the biological indication of male or female in the context of reproductive potential or capacity, such as sex chromosomes, naturally occurring sex hormones, gonads, and non-ambiguous internal and external genitalia present at birth, without regard to an individual’s psychological, chosen, or subjective experience of gender.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6350F69E62F1497CB8B62DB6D46F321F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cross-sex hormones</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>cross-sex hormones</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA9AD77B7CCF54A27A98928DD3487933F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>testosterone or other androgens given to biological females at doses that are profoundly larger or more potent than would naturally occur in healthy biological females; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF29C193470FF447B84C2AE62B9533B5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">estrogen given to biological males at doses that are profoundly larger or more potent than would naturally occur in healthy biological males.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC811F8B4F2154000B19CD6ED493E9D87"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gender</header><text>The term <quote>gender</quote> means the psychological, behavioral, social, and cultural aspects of being male or female.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2951B29F62D84193B036DEFD1CE6DF1C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Gender transition</header><text>The term <quote>gender transition</quote> means the process in which a person goes from identifying with and living as a gender that corresponds to his or her biological sex to identifying with and living as a gender different from his or her biological sex, and may involve social, legal, or physical changes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F04DB2A962C4822AE11473389F08642"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Gender transition procedure</header><subparagraph id="H95A9E8217952428CBC0948F53E2123A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>gender transition procedure</quote> means any medical or surgical service, including physician’s services, inpatient and outpatient hospital services, or prescribed drugs related to gender transition, that seek to alter or remove physical or anatomical characteristics or features that are typical for an individual’s biological sex, or to instill or create physiological or anatomical characteristics that resemble a sex different from an individual’s birth sex, including, without limitation, medical services that provide puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or other mechanisms to promote the development of feminizing or masculinizing features (in the opposite sex), or genital gender transition surgery or nongenital gender transition surgery performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32376C1DB1DC4C809FB9906A6790B113"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>gender transition procedure</quote> does not include— </text><clause id="H358CD7C1F8F64EB882862AEDE493CF38"><enum>(i)</enum><text>services to those born with a medically-verifiable disorder of sex development, including a person with external biological sex characteristics that are irresolvably ambiguous, such as those born with 46 XX chromosomes with virilization, 46 XY chromosomes with undervirilization, or having both ovarian and testicular tissue; or services provided when a physician has otherwise diagnosed a disorder of sexual development, in which such physician has determined through genetic or biochemical testing that the person does not have normal sex chromosome structure, sex steroid hormone production, or sex steroid hormone action for a biological male or biological female; or</text></clause><clause id="H816FF7AD2F5243BD95F040CA83346339"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the treatment of any infection, injury, disease, or disorder that has been caused by or exacerbated by the performance of a gender transition procedure, whether or not such procedure was performed in accordance with State or Federal law, or whether funding for such procedure was permissible under this chapter.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6129215B94B4FF09BDF60575E415CF2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gender transition surgery</header><subparagraph id="HB446EB615FE142029BD6474DC6533563" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>gender transition surgery</quote> means any medical or surgical service that seeks to surgically alter or remove healthy physical or anatomical characteristics or features that are typical for an individual’s biological sex in order to instill or create physiological or anatomical characteristics that resemble a sex different from an individual’s birth sex, including, without limitation, genital gender reassignment surgery or non-genital gender reassignment surgery performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFABD93392944050B6451EE5B08D470A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Gender transition surgery does not include any procedure undertaken because the individual suffers from a physical disorder, physical injury, or physical illness that would, as certified by a physician, place the individual in imminent danger of death or impairment of major bodily function unless surgery is performed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H126BA8C2B86B49AA91522948B1CB5BF3"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Genital gender transition surgery</header><text>The term <quote>genital gender transition surgery</quote> includes surgical procedures such as penectomy, orchiectomy, vaginoplasty, clitoroplasty, or vulvoplasty for biologically male patients, or hysterectomy/ovariectomy, reconstruction of the fixed part of the urethra with or without a metoidioplasty or a phalloplasty, vaginectomy, scrotoplasty, or implantation of erection or testicular prostheses for biologically female patients when performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C5D8B20D83F4B469E9A5F9106B3C93B"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Non-genital gender transition surgery</header><text>The term <quote>non-genital gender transition surgery</quote> means surgical procedures including augmentation mammoplasty, facial feminization surgery, liposuction, lipofilling, voice surgery, thyroid cartilage reduction, gluteal augmentation (implants or lipofilling), hair reconstruction, or other aesthetic procedures for biologically male patients or subcutaneous mastectomy, voice surgery, liposuction, lipofilling, pectoral implants, or other aesthetic procedures for biologically female patients, when performed for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5CAAA5F4EE4423CB51DC5E8156D9765"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Puberty-blocking drugs</header><text>The term <quote>puberty-blocking drugs</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H0C2DD2F1480047D1A3022F79263408FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogues or other synthetic drugs used in biological males to stop luteinizing hormone secretion and therefore testosterone secretion;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C4F8BB3886E4102A7441C1E2A9D6481"><enum>(B)</enum><text>synthetic drugs used in biological females that stop the production of estrogen; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C35F33EFFBF4F87A90ACDAD6BBA860E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>progesterone when used to delay or suppress pubertal development in children for the purpose of assisting an individual with a gender transition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H10EA947347D649F09FC7583DAF7A9CD3"><enum>102.</enum><header>Amendment to table of chapters</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The table of chapters for title 1, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFEEA1F380AB498D8B0F87E0BDCE21B4" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><multi-column-toc-entry bold="on" level="section"><toc-enum>4. </toc-enum><level-header bold="on" level="section">Prohibiting taxpayer-funded gender transition procedures</level-header><target>301</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title id="H9F51DAA595B94CFD9204EE2C96932585"><enum>II</enum><header>Application Under the Affordable Care Act</header><section id="HE0F7F2D301214EC3AF12F0BC483677B4"><enum>201.</enum><header>Clarifying application of prohibition to premium credits and cost-sharing reductions under ACA</header><subsection id="H68AEF1B32CD04D9FAA8540AE7F8E35C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H10C5B7CD63E3439CABB8B27A02097909"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disallowance of refundable credit and cost-sharing reductions for coverage under qualified health plan which provides coverage for gender transition procedures</header><subparagraph id="H2B19B3BF777F4F39B684B455A3A6E44E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">Section 36B(c)(3)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>or any health plan that includes coverage for gender transition procedures (other than any procedure described in section 306 or 307 of title 1, United States Code)</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AFAA84B29C04DAC8777EA75B28A34CB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Option to purchase or offer separate coverage or plan</header><text>Section 36B(c)(3) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="HCE165429C1564B5FA69180DAA2A46231" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H45CB68147EEC4BC1A256BD54BF3CA724"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Separate coverage or plan for gender transition procedures allowed</header><clause id="HD9219D1DCB814024A9682D5CCEBEA057"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Option to purchase separate coverage or plan</header><text>Nothing in subparagraph (A) shall be construed as prohibiting any individual from purchasing separate coverage for gender transition procedures described in such subparagraph, or a health plan that includes such gender transition procedures, so long as no credit is allowed under this section with respect to the premiums for such coverage or plan.</text></clause><clause id="HA499FC68AF70430C88006876CC9E1A01"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Option to offer coverage or plan</header><text>Nothing in subparagraph (A) shall restrict any non-Federal health insurance issuer offering a health plan from offering separate coverage for gender transition procedures described in such subparagraph, or a plan that includes such gender transition procedures, so long as premiums for such separate coverage or plan are not paid for with any amount attributable to the credit allowed under this section (or the amount of any advance payment of the credit under section 1412 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94C1FEA41F9E4801A9F46E48190B16A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disallowance of small employer health insurance expense credit for plan which includes coverage for gender transition procedures</header><text>Subsection (h) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45R">section 45R</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H23E1E3C7F9474F338BE9655B7FA823E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Any term</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="HC56CC3384F234A1FB0BC494C5CDEDF63" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HDA24FBE7E97C4EE1B3602925DD341876"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any term</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C409087690142D9BB4E80BC19E54CE3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="HDA4A6E91F8554D28BF72D0362BE49581" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H6B4F77ACF9A14BCB8E78689BAC6C9CC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion of health plans including coverage for gender transition procedures</header><subparagraph id="HD1F8718DD2C0433195AEEFAB95930CEE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified health plan</quote> does not include any health plan that includes coverage for gender transition procedures (other than a procedure described in section 306 or 307 of title 1, United States Code).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD07D9FF3E5D4CA98370E9D4FA5996FA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Separate coverage or plan for gender transition procedures allowed</header><clause id="H3B805CD56101426AA2C656DFB4B90F21"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Option to purchase separate coverage or plan</header><text>Nothing in subparagraph (A) shall be construed as prohibiting any employer from purchasing for its employees separate coverage for gender transition procedures described in such subparagraph, or a health plan that includes such gender transition procedures, so long as no credit is allowed under this section with respect to the employer contributions for such coverage or plan.</text></clause><clause id="H8C06CADA460B452B9474D8AB5894FDEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Option to offer coverage or plan</header><text>Nothing in subparagraph (A) shall restrict any non-Federal health insurance issuer offering a health plan from offering separate coverage for gender transition procedures described in such subparagraph, or a plan that includes such gender transition procedures, so long as such separate coverage or plan is not paid for with any employer contribution eligible for the credit allowed under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H13DC33215CDD4FD094100CFB5C749ACA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application to multi-State plans</header><text>Section 1334(a) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18054">42 U.S.C. 18054(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H732E3B71F7B347209C17B11B04B8C5D2" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HA79DB076B7D14B0E9074A7026C05850D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Coverage consistent with federal policy regarding gender transition procedures</header><text>In entering into contracts under this subsection, the Director shall ensure that no multi-State qualified health plan offered in an Exchange provides health benefits coverage for which the expenditure of Federal funds is prohibited under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/1/4">chapter 4</external-xref> of title 1, United States Code.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF834CF15CC764CC5B153C9E709C29F01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H5FAAD58474C24DEFA705E37A8841E73E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date with respect to premium credits and cost sharing reductions</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply to taxable years after the date that is one year after the date of enactment of this Act, but only with respect to plan years beginning after such date.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16D0BCBC89564AD69F89EEC6582AD2CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date for application to multi-State plans</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (b) shall apply to plan years beginning on the date that is one year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

