<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3784857BDA884F7A82C39D5B90CFB456" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5523 IH: Financial Access Improvements Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5523</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230918">September 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 to include information in the International Narcotics Control Strategy Report on improvements by countries in combating narcotics-related money laundering, to require a report on the consistency of Bank Secrecy Act examinations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5A2831C6D3EE498C9C6E4D334E85960F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H64C140EA965B4B97936C6C899F6C73A5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Access Improvements Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HB814FC73EEF944D0B0B7C323C158B964"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements by countries in combating narcotics-related money laundering</header> <subsection id="H0CA8D040E00C47549D12A32A1DD4A53A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 489 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2291h">22 U.S.C. 2291h</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC74BEDD5557241EBB84599BD1C72B322"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(7)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE5FB6BE00C3046F2BA0F4613E2FA49DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter before subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>paragraph (3)(D)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (3)(C)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E04BFF5AE3D4AF78C6653ED8F4C207C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H88B4CFDC737A406ABBC68EF612B06BD5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H392F0927E96A4D3FB4CEAC441E935AEF"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Where the information is available, examples of improvements in each country related to the findings described in each of clauses (i) through (viii) of subparagraph (C), such as—</text> 
<clause id="H8B7F3CFEC9CC41EF9321EB28FF84F96B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>actions taken by the country due to each country’s adoption of law and regulations considered essential to prevent narcotics-related money laundering;</text></clause> <clause id="HB9CB18E667424A49A6F3ADD031394728"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhanced enforcement actions taken by the country, such as regulatory penalties, criminal prosecutions and convictions, and asset seizures and forfeitures;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H949E09FB917F4EC095D0422FC5893C6B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>status changes in international financial crime-related evaluations;</text></clause> <clause id="H6B1D5E9E6A574F9DB6A7CB59542787D0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other descriptions that are representative of efforts to enhance the prevention of narcotics-related money laundering; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D04FCAC10BD40BD8BC06EA8E7C57D88"><enum>(v)</enum><text>if applicable, bilateral, multilateral, and regional initiatives which have been undertaken to prevent narcotics-related money laundering.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HE964D0F359334B719A31F752E538EC27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional requirements for money laundering issues</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making each report required under section 489(a) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 as amended by subsection (a), the President shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H13DB4F7F7EF94C059D76AB904FD17375" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consult with the Secretary of the Treasury on any parts of the report relating to money laundering;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE12D1DBDFDBC4A32961282F15B9B2D42"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide each country identified pursuant to subsection (a)(3)(C) with an opportunity to provide comments on any parts of the draft report relating to money laundering in such country and, where appropriate, include such comments in the final report; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DC0A680C4CE4E65925BF0681F4B0F26"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prepare a separate volume of the report containing all items relating to money laundering, and submit a copy of such separate volume to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE321181400E147C0A0B904287A1147B3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on consistency of BSA examinations</header> <subsection id="H229E6D364BA446E3B089464E3249CFB1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE07108D8BF514D4A815FF5FB7D69021A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consult with the Federal banking agencies, the Financial Institutions Examination Council, and the Bank Secrecy Act Advisory Group to determine how to build more consistent Bank Secrecy Act exams across such agencies; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H626651BA21C94518B390DCF77C771296"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, a report that describes steps the Secretary of the Treasury is taking to build more consistent Bank Secrecy Act exams across such agencies based on the consultation required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H74F2D0E4090141CEAB548B6E1E1CFA24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal banking agency</header><text>The term <quote>Federal banking agency</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 3(q) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act.</text></subsection> </section> </legis-body></bill>

