<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H809C04162DA249C6821B32B9857B4A34" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4408 IH: Promising Pathway Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4408</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to establish a time-limited provisional approval pathway, subject to specific obligations, for certain drugs and biological products, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H718635D33828490BAF14CF16B0E30FD4" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H59AD3226EBB34006ABE7FBBCDDF1423E"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promising Pathway Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF3C2BC2D9DF349A5B859DB03DDE53ADB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Provisional approval of new human drugs</header> <subsection id="HE136E4253DAB4C94A69C9A9CCD8B3C06"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter A of chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/351">21 U.S.C. 351 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end of the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D32FD31A6AA4FF99BCB926BD565DA23">
<section id="HBAF1267584AD4DDCB18D0D4FD1CA8C2A"><enum>524C.</enum><header>Provisional approval of new human drugs</header>
<subsection id="HB117794203FE4617A4904F5A33705F4B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Priority review and evaluation of applications</header>
<paragraph id="H42E9007ACD6E4B52BC93DEBFA2B71AAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a priority review system to evaluate applications submitted under this section for provisional approval within 90 days of receipt of a completed application. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB5CE1D2B3CBA4D3FB7BACFC5705E03B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other designations</header><text>If a drug submitted for review under this section is eligible for a special designation by the Secretary under this Act, including as a drug for a rare disease or condition under section 526, all benefits of such other designation shall be available for use under provisional approval, including any tax credits and waiving of fees under chapter VII. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HE7C79A725305403B967C0C9CAC5CCF98"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>A drug may be eligible for provisional approval under this section if the Secretary determines that the drug is intended for the treatment, prevention, or medical diagnosis of a serious or life-threatening disease or condition for which there is a reasonable likelihood that premature death will occur without early medical intervention for an individual contracting or being diagnosed with such disease or condition.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H3D6C8331FD3447D59DEED57A3B76232B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Standard of review for provisional approval</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0DB179332D484660BA2B0BDBB7913AC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>An application for provisional approval under this section may be approved only if the Secretary determines that—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H852CBC1636E84EFBB767D1FDA6D3A6AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>there is substantial evidence of safety for the drug, such that there is evidence consisting of adequate and well-controlled investigations, including clinical investigations, by experts qualified by scientific training and experience to evaluate the safety of the drug involved, on the basis of which it could fairly and responsibly be concluded that the drug will have the effect it purports or is represented to have under the conditions of use prescribed, recommended, or suggested in the labeling or proposed labeling; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HD31CB8393CF54EE2A826969725BD3CFA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there is relevant early evidence based on adequate and well-controlled investigations, including early-stage clinical investigations, to establish that—</text>
<clause commented="no" id="H5F9DDC2FB4D745DBBD9D900C53AE3ADA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the drug provides a positive therapeutic outcome; and </text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HC1CDC69D54F54C93BE986A0871CC8546"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the outcome of the drug is consistent with or greater than currently marketed on-label therapies, with equal or fewer side effects, if there are currently marketed on-label therapies. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H00CC738D32C94532A5BE4ACF623A6903"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protocols</header><text>The Secretary shall promulgate rules that establish the appropriate protocols to enable rolling, real-time, mid-trial submission while preserving the integrity of the ongoing trial and without penalizing the sponsor for seeking provisional approval under this section. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HD27F3640555E4C1EBF7F3D5F5215CF27"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Real world evidence</header><text>The Secretary shall allow the use of real world evidence (as defined in section 505F(b)), including real world data used to generate real world evidence, to support an application for provisional approval under this section, and to fulfill the follow-up requirements and support applications for approval under section 505 or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, as applicable.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H5B667F8B71DB43498CB63842068A3307"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of scientifically substantiated surrogates</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H82C4FA9FEFB245B398AA5E05B9B11201"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The sponsor of an application for provisional approval under this section may use scientifically substantiated surrogates to support such application. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB8CFC3E3450C4E25B197E998E5440651"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In subparagraph (A), the term <term>scientifically substantiated surrogates</term> means surrogate endpoints to predict clinical benefit other than such endpoints previously validated by the Secretary, based on—</text>
<clause commented="no" id="H864C32265AFE4EADB848015B02A78F6C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>epidemiologic, therapeutic, pathophysiologic, or other evidence; or </text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H882B9BD455EE460882EE97E917F493CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an effect on a clinical endpoint other than survival or irreversible morbidity of interest.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H76B3B877192F42FDA4536B34C9F14249"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transparency and patient monitoring requirements</header>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HB090B28124954E0F99627A4AAC0E4734"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Registries</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H63BE58C3C428485D8F49736A5D7F1A77"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The sponsor of a drug provisionally approved under this section shall require that all patients who use such drug participate in an observational registry and consent to the sponsor’s collection, and submission to the registry, of data related to the patient’s use of such drug until such drug receives approval under section 505 or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, or the provisional approval is rescinded. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H21C1156F9271457F9E3CB92D074DE1C2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements for registries</header><text>An observational registry described in subparagraph (A) may be run by a third party, such as a government, for profit, or nonprofit organization, and shall track all patients who use the provisionally approved drug. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H594C670754B746AC9011D05ED8ABFCD0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Accessibility</header><text>An observational registry described in subparagraph (A) shall be easily accessible for—</text> <clause id="HC855E04F173949628BE04C76D6FD7A86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all patients who are participating in any registry related to a provisionally approved drug that allows for easy, unrestricted (or transparent) access for such patients to their patient data and related information regarding their usage of the provisionally approved drug; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H0EEBE7A6F3A0460490EE1C833CCC7486"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>approved researchers and medical professionals who may access data maintained in the registry, which access shall be for public health research and only in a de-identified, aggregated manner.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H2BB921DBFE8A4BEAA3CE1280EC33753D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>An observational registry under this subsection shall be maintained, as applicable—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H0EB34BF49B484161B69717215EB56F67"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by the sponsor of the drug provisionally approved under this section that is the subject of the registry; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H1D5FB0A0AC0A4BD48DC9575DBC8F7EE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by a third party, such as a government, for profit, or nonprofit organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HBAA1222E7E7D4B4AA9F1D8AB1445A4A1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sponsor requirements</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3E3C964D480B456283265A24F86FABBE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any drug application provisionally approved under this section, the Secretary shall notify the sponsor of the exact data such sponsor is required to submit to an observational registry.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HAB7F783F03384C188801C1943743A676"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual review of the registry; penalties</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an annual review of observational registries established under this subsection. If, at such an annual review, fewer than 90 percent of patients are participating in an observational registry with respect to a drug approved under this section, the Secretary shall issue to the sponsor of such drug a civil monetary penalty of not more than $100,000. If a violation of this section is not corrected within the 30-day period following notification, the sponsor shall, in addition to any penalty under this subparagraph be subject to a civil monetary penalty of not more than $10,000 for each day of the violation after such period until the violation is corrected. If application patient participation in an observational registry is not at or above 90 percent within 6 months of issuance of such penalty, the provisional approval shall be withdrawn.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H0C8F33FD98ED4892AA6BC9BA8E10EE69"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Annual report to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall submit an annual report to Congress on all drugs granted provisional approval under this section. Such report shall include—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H222394E4E4134B51A85A0E32F89715EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of patients treated with each such drug, and the number of patients tracked in an observational registry with respect to each such drug;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2A68CAD7AF434CD5A3F998299D67C283"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a discussion of the minimum amount of data required in the registries, including patient treatments and uses, length of use, side effects encountered, relevant biomarkers or scientifically substantiated surrogates, scan results, cause of death and how long the patient lived, and adverse drug effects; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H9F3701E6FA934FE28E35CD72712D08C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of all such drugs for which an application for approval under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, or an application for an extension of provisional approval under this section, has been submitted; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE7A34B302E8049AE94B40A984BA6F52E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a list of all applications denied provisional approval under this section, together with an explanation for the decisions to deny each such application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H28AEC54FFDBE48ADB321EB6574DE3A45"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Withdrawal of provisional approval</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB5544E613F7F4889989C217534BF2F0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall withdraw provisional approval under this section if there are a significant numbers of patients who experience serious adverse effects, compared to the other currently marketed on-label therapies that are available for the applicable disease or condition.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2F7CC1BB0F444F77822172FB72A1392E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of withdrawal</header><text>If a provisional approval is withdrawn under this subsection, the sponsor may not make the drug available to any new patients, but may be allowed to continue to make such drug available to patients who started taking the drug prior to the date of withdrawal, for as long a period as dictated by patient need, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HF3BE7F887A7D4610B9B92CCA509FBC31"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Transparency</header><text>Any scientific, medical, academic, or health care journal publishing an article explaining, releasing, conveying, or announcing research findings which were funded by the Department of Health and Human Services shall be prohibited from publishing such research unless—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HC27D9918C1CD475AAC2D1743C706073C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such article conveying research findings is made publicly available on the journal’s internet website without a paywall or charge not later than 3 months after the date on which such article was first provided to subscribers of such journal (or first made available for purchase); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HF9C2213BB8514BD49E9E09E030A979F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the article’s author or researcher or author’s institution (or, in the case of multiple authors, researchers, or institutions, all such authors, researchers, or institutions) received less than 30 percent of funding for such research from the Department of Health and Human Services throughout the period of time the research was conducted. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HA5F673965D20409F846C2D7FACF2FF78"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Informed Consent</header><text>Prior to receiving a drug provisionally approved under this section, the sponsor of the drug shall receive from each patient, or the patient's representative, informed consent, through a signed informed consent form, acknowledging that such patient understands that the drug did not undergo the usual process for approval of a drug by the Food and Drug Administration, and that such patient is willing to accept the risks involved in taking such drug. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H3643DBA42882472D99C00F2C9D23D2D9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Postmarket controls and labeling</header> <paragraph id="H21811992601E4B7CB01FD3AD2C464A13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>FDA annual review of registry data</header><text>The Secretary shall annually review the data made available through the observational registries under subsection (d) and make a determination regarding whether the side effect profile of any drug provisionally approved under this section does not support the benefit provided, or the data shows the benefit is less than the benefits offered through other, fully approved drugs. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB544C608B7094419B54E77FD18A1E1E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Labeling</header><text>The sponsor of the provisionally approved drug shall ensure that all labeling and promotional materials for the drug bear the statement <quote>provisionally approved by the FDA pending a full demonstration of effectiveness under application number ______</quote> (specifying the application number assigned by the Secretary in place of the blank). All promotional, educational and marketing materials for provisionally approved products shall be reviewed and approved by the Secretary before such materials are distributed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF5ACBDE30714740BC502586682B66FA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rescission of provisional approval</header><text>If the Secretary determines that the side effect profile of any drug included in such observational registries does not support the benefit provided by such drug, or that the data shows that the benefit is less than the benefits offered through other drugs approved under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, the Secretary shall rescind such provisional approval. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H52A519A1157548949BA22FD069B828DE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Duration of provisional approval; requirement To bring drug to market</header>
<paragraph id="H936AF69A606C4A5D87E1A0F004A79817"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duration; renewals</header><text>The provisional approval for a drug under this section is effective for a 2-year period. The sponsor may request renewal for provisional approval status for up to 3 subsequent 2-year periods. Provisional approval status with respect to a drug shall not exceed a total of 8 years from the initial date the sponsor was awarded provisional approval status.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D21341C8E4D4F81AC2755AC38FCFA09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Marketing requirement</header><text>If any drug that receives provisional approval under this section is not brought to market within 180 days of the provisional approval, such provisional approval shall be rescinded. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD373CC73EEF74C4DA1B8C22EDD2AB6C5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Limitation on liability</header><text>With respect to any claim under State law alleging that a drug sold or otherwise made available pursuant to a grant of provisional approval under this section is unsafe or ineffective, no liability in a cause of action shall lie against a sponsor or manufacturer, unless the relevant conduct constitutes reckless or willful misconduct, gross negligence, or an intentional tort under any applicable State law.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H978F5877304C495EA19547BB9298CA91"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Right To petition an advisory committee for approval</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC1EC99CA1C8E4351B6173875DC81FCF0"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The sponsor of a drug granted provisional approval pursuant to this section may request, at any time after provisional approval is granted under this section, a meeting with the appropriate advisory committee (or advisory committees) to present safety and efficacy data for the purposes of receiving a recommendation from such an advisory committee for approval under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act of the provisionally approved drug. Such a requested meeting shall be granted not later than 90 days after a request is made. Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to alter the processes and timeframes for recommendation for approval by such an advisory committee of the provisionally approved drug or for approval of the provisionally approved drug under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE31424A585294D62BFD9D9A11461F0A9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver of adequate and well-controlled study requirements</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55139E5AE2DA4BB9BD30C64D9F678345"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In considering whether to recommend a drug that was provisionally approved under this section for approval under section 505, the Director of the Center for Drug Evaluation and Research shall consider the option to waive requirements for adequate and well-controlled studies in accordance with the process described in section 314.126(c) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AFE75FCF34B4A728B07F89A7D770EFA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Biological products</header><text>In considering whether to recommend a biological product that was provisionally approved under this section for licensure under section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, the Director of the Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research may, and shall consider the option to, waive requirements, as applicable, for adequate and well-controlled studies for such biological product in accordance with the process described in section 314.126(c) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H883179ADB257408E9BF2C2B59BBA84A9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 505(a) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(a)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, or there is in effect a provisional approval under section 524C with respect to such drug</quote> before the period. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H96ABE7F39C05446F89715374316E5C2F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reimbursement</header> <paragraph id="H431F30F5EA0C442DB195106CFED4B6E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Private health insurers</header><text>Section 2719A of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-19a">42 U.S.C. 300gg–19a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3119AB69CB94AABAB93FA80030F265E">
<subsection id="HD469BAD46EB041A29108EE8BA2D84C87"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Treatment of certain drugs</header><text>A group health plan or health insurance issuer of group or individual health insurance coverage shall not deny coverage of any drug provisionally approved under section 524C of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act on the basis of such drug being experimental. In determining coverage under the applicable plan or coverage, a group health plan or health insurance issuer shall treat a drug provisionally approved under such section in the same manner as such plan or coverage would treat a drug approved under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act or section 351 of this Act. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require a group health plan or health insurance issuer to cover any specific drug provisionally approved under such section 524C.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H617F9394385547F5A9D915BC13318EF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal health care programs</header><text>The requirement under subsection (f) of section 2719A of the Public Health Service Act (as added by paragraph (1)) shall apply with respect to coverage determinations under a Federal health care program (as defined in section 1128B(f) of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1320a–7b(f))) in the same manner such requirement applies under such subsection (f). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEF27ECAC13CE4A0695FBF63E22F0A7EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1927(k)(2)(A)(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-8">42 U.S.C. 1396r–8(k)(2)(A)(i)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H92C8555324BE4B8B9527726DFE902661"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or which</quote> and inserting <quote>, which</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDE9CB08BFE4943A5A3822F6F70A324C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or which is provisionally approved under section 524C of such Act</quote> before the semicolon. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

