<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F3145B763F6424BA3C48713D370EEB6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 570 IH: Combating Racist Teaching in Schools Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 570</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the award of Federal funds to schools that promote certain race-based theories to students, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H52D61638C9E54A268FC363F8136E817A" style="OLC"><section id="H654F574640E84A41A17B72A7FFA76D46" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combating Racist Teaching in Schools Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CRT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7B790FD853614BED8FB8A7BBA008B394"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on award of Federal funds to certain schools</header><subsection id="HEB06B1D315444476A10FF289559272F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on award of funds to certain elementary and secondary schools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds received by a State or local educational agency may be allocated to an elementary or secondary school that promotes the race-based theories described in subsection (c) or compels teachers or students to affirm, adhere to, adopt, or process beliefs in a manner that violates title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD7A88B27DCF64CCDAA31742D7EED454E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on award of funds to certain institutions of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be awarded to an institution of higher education if such institution promotes the race-based theories described in subsection (c) or compels teachers or students to affirm, adhere to, adopt, or process beliefs in a manner that violates title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3A12BC0D89854E2AAD2F723CD8DB77EB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Race-Based theories described</header><text>The race-based theories described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H8045EDE668504D28B909CDE670079A7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any race is inherently superior or inferior to any other race, color, or national origin.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H076A685035384FB99EB77146290FF8C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States is a fundamentally racist country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9A188337A1048909471330E79126414"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Declaration of Independence or Constitution of the United States are fundamentally racist documents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE82EE2AC936B4EF4A8AEAA0905215EA0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual’s moral character or worth is determined by the individual’s race, color, or national origin.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C41919775BA4752913CCAB9922F982E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An individual, by virtue of the individual’s race, is inherently racist or oppressive, whether consciously or unconsciously.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6767AA560C84B058FFD34CE2690EC47"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual, because of the individual’s race, bears responsibility for the actions committed by other members of the individual’s race, color, or national origin.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDBC19F86641B4ABFAB19068159419B3D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><paragraph id="H5449FC0580454CEB8E098A79C953635B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Protected speech not restricted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to restrict the speech of a student, teacher, or any other individual outside of a school setting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB93D04C2FFE947AC892DDF743515BC1B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Access to materials for the purpose of research or independent study</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent an individual from accessing materials that advocate theories described in subsection (c) for the purpose of research or independent study.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB61DEE00E38A4A5CA58A549C39C04F73"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contextual education</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a covered school from stating theories described in subsection (c) or assigning materials that advocate such theories for educational purposes in contexts that make it clear the school does not sponsor, approve, or endorse such theories or materials.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H527E925F3F09455CAE22FB23125A5650"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H1E9AACC1EE4542F3B83562B118289E76"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered school</term> means an elementary school, a secondary school, or an institution of higher education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55F163DA69124C5CB33BAB636C5303CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESEA Terms</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <quote>State</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14B192757B4F46739767B8C46856DB2A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F05630CEEA540F9BD4DEDC05DBEAAE6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Promote</header><text>The term <term>promote</term>, when used with respect to a race-based theory described in subsection (c), means—</text><subparagraph id="H722B68F83849449DAE2ED2768AABF0D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to include such theories or materials that advocate such theories in curricula, reading lists, seminars, workshops, trainings, or other educational or professional settings in a manner that could reasonably give rise to the appearance of official sponsorship, approval, or endorsement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F36C5FF5B8F4FEDADD4CD0EEB49DAEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to contract with, hire, or otherwise engage speakers, consultants, diversity trainers, and other persons for the purpose of advocating such theories;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2697A56A0D224E85A5C18DBF8F9ACE46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to compel students to profess a belief in such theories; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF16B82F502F5419DA8A423F3AF00138F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to segregate students or other individuals by race in any setting, including in educational or training sessions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

