<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD948E4E8AC7B4AFAA3D1D2281BDB31E8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 555 IH: Securing America’s Vaccines for Emergencies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 555</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Defense Production Act of 1950 to ensure the supply of certain medical materials essential to national defense, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7A7675299DE8493A895F90CF8AB3423C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5E498A4D78B5490CA2F3261AC3D6E785" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing America’s Vaccines for Emergencies Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAVE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5DEC1E88023042A3BCBA80269699E4C4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Securing essential medical materials</header> <subsection id="HAF11DC0BA3844FC8B7C43AA21D358633"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>Section 2(b) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4502">50 U.S.C. 4502</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H71A49595484443D08EB59AF9CB8672D1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (3) through (8) as paragraphs (4) through (9), respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D51B2A9B72943C5967F36C0D38CDC98"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H11466F4C8A49420AB8DFEAE02185650B" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HFC3B65EA306547DEAE73C11A3A05FD80"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorities under this Act should be used when appropriate to ensure the availability of medical materials essential to national defense, including through measures designed to secure the drug supply chain, and taking into consideration the importance of United States competitiveness, scientific leadership and cooperation, and innovative capacity;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9DCE8B2CAB4940EC889CB838CAA71AB7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Strengthening domestic capability</header><text>Section 107 of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4517">50 U.S.C. 4517</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE4BFB5D76F84402FB910C36D895EFDED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by inserting <quote>(including medical materials)</quote> after <quote>materials</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDBF6CAEB85DA4EA2BC537F1448AE8AA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(1), by inserting <quote>(including medical materials such as drugs, devices, and biological products to diagnose, cure, mitigate, treat, or prevent disease that are essential to national defense)</quote> after <quote>essential materials</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8DBC68F5E6F24FE58918CAE8B5421223"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Strategy on securing supply chains for medical materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4511">50 U.S.C. 4511 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA780FD3374154F0D97B23A3706F06FC5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H992D08CBAFD0468FAEF5389997E7982E"><enum>109.</enum><header>Strategy on securing supply chains for medical materials</header> <subsection id="H12F4F25E13094B059D630024A280299B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the President, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and the Secretary of Defense, shall transmit a strategy to the appropriate Members of Congress that includes the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9E7BC0D28C7D427CA03BB24885C909C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed plan to use the authorities under this title and title III, or any other provision of law, to ensure the supply of medical materials (including drugs, devices, and biological products (as that term is defined in section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>)) to diagnose, cure, mitigate, treat, or prevent disease) essential to national defense, to the extent necessary for the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A3B8C4A8D604F85A0565C9E235E9197"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An analysis of vulnerabilities to existing supply chains for such medical materials, and recommendations to address the vulnerabilities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD18730B7EAD34FD3BEF6C604E61EE0C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures to be undertaken by the President to diversify such supply chains, as appropriate and as required for national defense.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB5DDF2959514E259B094B568EFAE282"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A discussion of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC47EB81906EC40F1985882C3ECCCDB79"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any significant effects resulting from the plan and measures described in this subsection on the production, cost, or distribution of biological products (as that term is defined in section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>)) or any other devices or drugs (as defined under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE4CC3E85D42848B4AE9116A7E8B0FA1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a timeline to ensure that essential components of the supply chain for medical materials are not under the exclusive control of a foreign government in a manner that the President determines could threaten the national defense of the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17135D5211E94A67B58EDE2E565EAC02"><enum>(C)</enum><text>efforts to mitigate any risks resulting from the plan and measures described in this subsection to United States competitiveness, scientific leadership, and innovative capacity, including efforts to cooperate and proactively engage with United States allies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H58745A2C12804FF1975FF6CD70FF158A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Progress Report</header><text>Following submission of the strategy under subsection (a), the President shall submit to the appropriate Members of Congress an annual progress report until September 30, 2025, evaluating the implementation of the strategy, and may include updates to the strategy as appropriate. The strategy and progress reports shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBCB946887BBF42199D8EC321ADAA1ADE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate Members of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate Members of Congress</term> means the Speaker, majority leader, and minority leader of the House of Representatives, the majority leader and minority leader of the Senate, the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, and the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H1C6F3AC79BD240FE954C6BD044A4951D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Investment in supply chain security</header> <subsection id="HB55015059B5142F3A990D93D105F75A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 303 of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4533">50 U.S.C. 4533</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="" id="H01CDED2D937C4024AEFE59D0B3E2CD31" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H800B8C21F73A44DF84652ABBB0B7D78B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Investment in supply chain security</header> 
<paragraph id="H519C2FD1513C4394B894C1973B4604EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to other authorities in this title, the President may make available to an eligible entity described in paragraph (2) payments to increase the security of supply chains and supply chain activities, if the President certifies to Congress not less than 30 days before making such a payment that the payment is critical to meet national defense requirements of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF673A6FE5334FD0BE722EC1F4B9D868"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>An eligible entity described in this paragraph is an entity that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF5E29B1E141B4675B3A086DA68743CD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EB3A32CE2014F27BBF8844D26A42367"><enum>(B)</enum><text>produces—</text> 
<clause id="H78708F6D68294E8A86670671589108F8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>one or more critical components;</text></clause> <clause id="H2F6383B4C73F48F9884BC0503710909B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>critical technology; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6C5B35EB2F2C47CB87D8F872C2B71B53"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">one or more products or raw materials for the security of supply chains or supply chain activities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EA7D9D78EB94A779297EC5F7DD63E54"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>supply chain</term> and <term>supply chain activities</term> have the meanings given those terms by the President by regulation.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H38F9117CFE0B44F793CB1146ABD9BE4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header> 
<paragraph id="H04ABEB58923F43C1A711B97D6D7B8FC5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall prescribe regulations setting forth definitions for the terms <term>supply chain</term> and <term>supply chain activities</term> for the purposes of section 303(h) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4533">50 U.S.C. 4533(h)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H962E008FCB3044E1BD1DC45606DBD442"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Scope of definitions</header><text>The definitions required by paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H55E4228FB59B438E845FC9A75F52219E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall encompass—</text> <clause id="H6108AB53D82C42CD8B041F8C1A3F16B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the organization, people, activities, information, and resources involved in the delivery and operation of a product or service used by the Government; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0C8269D428264939B34EA201E18F48B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>critical infrastructure as defined in Presidential Policy Directive 21 (February 12, 2013; relating to critical infrastructure security and resilience); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBDC5850A56834CF099E0BA847BA8F55C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include variations as determined necessary and appropriate by the President for purposes of national defense.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

