<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H251C7DE99E3241B193129E0A500ACDA5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4808 IH: Secure our Borders from the CCP Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4808</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Homeland Security to evaluate certain factors for aliens who submit a state sponsored Chinese immigration application or have been employed by the Chinese Communist Party.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB74DA50839404E2FA63B1AD4A22614D5" style="OLC"><section id="H74B2B464C55C45CFBAA62F8D61F6A101" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Secure our Borders from the CCP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HC2E56E954BD4412AB804F134F3EFFC72"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement to evaluate certain history for aliens</header><subsection id="H2379B3F8BDF54B95AC6EF7192FB09F93"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluation required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall evaluate the factors described in subsection (b) to determine if an individual submitting a covered application has any links, association, employment history, or association with the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China.</text></subsection><subsection id="H04723C88620C46C2BFEFB86D1A931F36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Factors described</header><text>The following factors shall be evaluated with respect to a covered application—</text><paragraph id="H03A020AAD6FF4AA08D0BB35BD32B26A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien’s employment or previous employment by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3D2B194F0D7449A87EEDAF50FEFCFD3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any immediate family relation of the alien who is employed by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19ECB6F1420E4A58AE8C5F4879EE56E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien’s participation in educational programs organized or sponsored by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2C3447231D64AD99B03E5D36A9C3136"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any grants awarded to an alien by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F508DAA4532463AA31610B39EC6AF08"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any public statements representing or supporting the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China by the alien;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE64689F36D9F4F74B8083DC55DB3073A"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien’s voter registration or party affiliation with the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H135B3E99BE1841B29EE6F9308F0AAC24"><enum>(7)</enum><text>any anti-capitalist or anti-American public statements made by the alien; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04D1A06FAD7849729F15947953B784D8"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any financial payments or any reimbursements to the alien made by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9D855E42EC114DC496B09879DB35D586"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Outcome of evaluation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that any of the factors described in subsection (b) exist with respect to a covered application the Secretary shall deny such application.</text></subsection><subsection id="H82BA743C76164C579B6BF9CF5C096B51"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an alien found to have lied on a covered application shall be subject to deportation and a fine of $5,000. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD878C148C1CA4459969AFD39DC74B6FF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA119BC034B32436AA1750B650CC81E99"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered application</header><text>The term <quote>covered application</quote> means an application submitted for immigration status by an individual as a result of their relationship with—</text><subparagraph id="H88DC7B59D27B4000A8B5803ABB1F66F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employer or institution of higher education that receives funding from the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4518EFFF59834E3F9705F1ED3F573D6A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an immediate family relation that is employed by or is associated with the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14B96D70412415B8EB36E05AC493267"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Immediate family relation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>immediate family relation</quote> means a mother, father, step-parent, brother, sister, cousin, uncle, or aunt. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

