<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0A64375A60224836977974042C9ED741" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5233 IH: To amend the Passport Act of June 4, 1920, to make certain improvements with respect to expenditure and other authorities, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5233</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Passport Act of June 4, 1920, to make certain improvements with respect to expenditure and other authorities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7C6E27218DC1474C9BBE51D748AEEB88" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2939BDDD97BB49D9BA6C67E74173EC0C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="H903E806B2E2648D7A3839735E682FF65"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2767916BCF00457CA10026AA5EECC0C2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of State.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5D060DB5CAD14380B734FCCF265F35FC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of State.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H71FE018D878A4D97AE31AA800DAF723E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Passport fee expenditure authority extension</header> 
<subsection id="H80DB4E333C7948E3BCFED4105F79B25E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Western hemisphere travel initiative fee</header><text>To make permanent the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative fee, section 1(b) of the Passport Act of June 4, 1920, (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/214">22 U.S.C. 214(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H905301B3F9754A1D8FFE28181D3DF499"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>(1)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4ABEE115FC9A4515AB1E0340D2C4232A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (2) and (3).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB1EA32918FF4867A735ABFBB22F9EAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Passport fees</header><text>Section 1(b) of the Passport Act of June 4, 1920, as amended by subsection (a), shall be applied through fiscal year 2028 by striking <quote>such costs</quote> and inserting <quote>the costs of providing consular services</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2218F3E61B9450ABEE5769A0DDC6FA5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Modernization of passport processing</header><text>A portion of the expanded expenditure authorities provided in subsections (a) and (b) shall be used—</text> <paragraph id="H28F727E7A7BD4369B2178F81F7951F25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to modernize consular systems, with an emphasis on passport and citizenship services; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2C1267E6C26744449614C7CE26759F9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>towards a feasibility study on how the Department could provide urgent, in-person passport services to significant populations with the longest travel times to existing passport agencies, including the possibility of building new passport agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H3F223B6FDF6C45B3A0BB7A4C6AD6AB62"><enum>3.</enum><header>Special hiring authority for passport services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">During the 3-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, without regard to the provisions under sections 3309 through 3318 of title 5, United States Code, may directly appoint candidates to positions in the competitive service (as defined in section 2102 of such title) at the Department in the Passport and Visa Examining Series 0967.</text></section> 
<section id="HBB6210358F6B4629B4B54D3ED9760D1F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Quarterly report on passport wait times</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and quarterly thereafter for the following 3 years, the Secretary shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that describes—</text> <paragraph id="HB67C9791659D45D8B80C5000CB681119"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the current estimated wait times for passport processing; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DDD0FD8F4E144EBA4CC8A5FB8643971"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the steps that have been taken by the Department to reduce wait times to a reasonable time;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A79A3A8332C4CC7A38FCA78F97E58F8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>efforts to improve the rollout of the online passport renewal processing program, including how much of passport revenues the Department is spending on consular systems modernization;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3BB743E7A0674DACAE89EA056710CC90"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the demand for urgent passport services by major metropolitan area;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1E4909AE87842DDB3E10E8D2F49010F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the steps that have been taken by the Department to reduce and meet the demand for urgent passport services, particularly in areas that are greater than 5 hours driving time from the nearest passport agency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1C2821739A6049438F056864ADB2CD8A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>how the Department details its staff and resources to passport services programs.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H1D64CBE3DCF545CABF7F17BD0506670B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Passport travel advisories</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Department shall make prominently available in United States regular passports, on the first 3 pages of the passport, the following information: </text> 
<paragraph id="H8D3EB8E6A7D54821A563C0A920C31D33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A prominent, clear advisory for all travelers to check travel.state.gov for updated travel warnings and advisories.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF30837E999E1402895F33CA60AE99478"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A prominent, clear notice urging all travelers to register with the Department prior to overseas travel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47F8BFB43F154264B7E02E0BAD28B2A5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A prominent, clear advisory—</text> <subparagraph id="H3454D933E8664E828B54E9551179BAEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>noting that many countries deny entry to travelers during the last 6 months of their passport validity period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DAB57C53A524CECB21D842D70885E5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>urging all travelers to renew their passport not later than 1 year prior to its expiration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HD98E8287405A45A98A19DCED77E3E5DC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Strategy to ensure access to passport services for all Americans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit a strategy to the appropriate congressional committees, the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives for ensuring reasonable access to passport services for all Americans, which shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF75A726A6CD5436F83787605D00969A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a detailed strategy describing how the Department could—</text> <subparagraph id="H6B7B6BF5133D43EDAB948B2A60165FF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by not later than 1 year after submission of the strategy, reduce passport processing times to an acceptable average for renewals and for expedited service; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H82E4B2C179794A4C9D568D62E4D25648"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by not later than 2 years after the submission of the strategy, provide United States residents living in a significant population center more than a 5-hour drive from a passport agency with urgent, in-person passport services, including the possibility of building new passport agencies; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD890214E2FC24ECD973EFD0734155B3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the specific resources required to implement the strategy.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HBD5244EF651D45CAA45641781A1403DD"><enum>7.</enum><header>Strengthening the national passport information center</header> 
<subsection id="H919975959FB0490086AE835951036669"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that passport wait times since 2021 have been unacceptably long and have created frustration among those seeking to obtain or renew passports.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H952B2C57E11347338A0A749CC8B8427C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Online chat feature</header><text>The Department should develop an online tool with the capability for customers to correspond with customer service representatives regarding questions and updates pertaining to their application for a passport or for the renewal of a passport.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2E2562DBA074EA9885124FA6AB964DA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Gao report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall initiate a review of NPIC operations, which shall include an analysis of the extent to which NPIC—</text> <paragraph id="HCE64B1CDD7A842B29C5226BE6F09EA8B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>responds to constituent inquiries by telephone, including how long constituents are kept on hold and their ability to be placed in a queue;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H16857027F956418F9D1627438238B064"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides personalized customer service;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29184AC13EAE4D8CABB125A0054AC7AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintains its telecommunications infrastructure to ensure it effectively handles call volumes; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5F5881AE9754D9182FFC4FB2926A1B9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other relevant issues the Comptroller General deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HCC5A176804BD4380B8851D1ABCDD6159"><enum>8.</enum><header>Strengthening passport customer visibility and transparency</header> <subsection id="H805D9C4FA34140B4978B3AA4671AD127"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Online status tool</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Department should modernize the online passport application status tool to include, to the greatest extent possible, step by step updates on the status of their application, including with respect to the following stages:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCE58DDE32DE44DFD9EB1674C63A8FD20"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Submitted for processing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H569C3EB82FEA4F8A989827A7DB2245E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In process at a lockbox facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H043A404060A4438C8CB1CCD802388361"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Awaiting adjudication.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H88200EF4A4B94805818413B68F62611C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In process of adjudication.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H025C26ABB20C4D728D8C9DDB34FA028F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Adjudicated with a result of approval or denial.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFB59FAB524D4EE8B622697EDA1FC2E8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Materials shipped.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H36D0DAFFB9A9446B82AC6ED240CD9773"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional information</header><text>The tool pursuant to subsection (a) should include a display that informs each passport applicant of—</text> <paragraph id="H299841FDD15E47CF92C096191CCC334D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which his or her passport application was received; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H760D2DACFE69432FBBEC78AA831C58D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the estimated wait time remaining in the passport application process.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4AFD29E5ADC44CEDA188E1D08E1FFDE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of State for Consular Affairs shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that outlines a plan for coordinated comprehensive public outreach to increase public awareness and understanding of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5487DF77EAD74B57B787ECCEDEC82534"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the online status tool required under subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC171BF066D284BE9915FF17B2DDE402A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>passport travel advisories required under section 4; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCF13CCD4C40401796B659FDD3FFABE5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>passport wait times.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

