<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H447C8B9FB8C04F6C947A473386C21CF1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6911 IH: Requiring Officials and Bureaucrats to Expeditiously Reliquinsh Testimony and Meaningful Answers about Lawbreaking and Locked out Employees Yesterday Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-01-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6911</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240102">January 2, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require heads of executive agencies to, upon request, submit to relevant congressional committees information regarding the furlough or indefinite suspension without pay of employees of such executive agencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B9DC02991244D259D24B1FF29FF6DF2" style="OLC"><section id="H77CA54C7D5E24ACD9CDCA0ABCEE34911" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Requiring Officials and Bureaucrats to Expeditiously Reliquinsh Testimony and Meaningful Answers about Lawbreaking and Locked out Employees Yesterday Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ROBERT MALLEY Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H662893DA32134CC3B033423164E576B4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HC31B236DACB64363A0D7BC3FAD131A7E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Government of the United States must be transparent with the American people and with Congress;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF592E031EF5D4F35A93C5302C71FCAB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the executive branch should never obstruct the right of Congress to investigate and conduct oversight;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9D2B1BA601A434FB35B0E011A60314B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>individuals that conspire with State Sponsors of Terror or foreign terrorist organizations should be held accountable to the fullest extent of the law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H062DB0EAB4AC45A1A42ECAD5517B44FD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>individuals that knowingly hire, or attempt to convince others to hire, intelligence assets for foreign nations are guilty of treason.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF88E0F2FD76E41F3971FED867DF859EA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Furlough and indefinite suspension explanations</header><subsection id="H10015E6EBC884A80BC779940116891EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the head of an executive agency receives a request from the Chairman or Ranking Member of an appropriate congressional committee for an explanation why an employee of such executive agency was furloughed or suspended indefinitely without pay, such head of an executive agency shall submit to the Chairman or Ranking Member making such request an explanation of the reasoning for such employee being furloughed or suspended indefinitely without pay, including any relevant information and evidence collected in the course of an investigation prior to intervention by a law enforcement agency.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD299953113FE46A0B5703230D27AB6DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to employees—</text><paragraph id="HF0F94C74D64140428B535B4F1F6ADD05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>suspended or furloughed pursuant to an action initiated under section 1215 of title 5, United States Code; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F43C290B79746F48A0060CA4DE0914C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>furloughed as a result of a lapse in appropriations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA7C6838BE930472294580F8B63C70270"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An explanation required by subsection (a) shall be in an unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCE67146055F64B1B936159E6372A2B3A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0DFC3200FB234D1A8173F24F8D83D9D7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB2FB97AC393F4EFDBCF8B13A48ECF7FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committees of the Senate and House of Representatives with jurisdiction over the executive agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H951529FCCB0C468A99C5CD82B423340B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H625EBE9A6FF14314AB3944E68A1E030B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B017E4F6A1F499EA6C5ED812C51F672"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>The term <term>executive agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

