<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H57F01E8C48A148F99F430CF2BB32423B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6622 IH: Clean Competition Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6622</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to create a carbon border adjustment based on carbon intensity, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H018D910B64064AF484B970AD807F577B" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HD102196F25064EFBB5FC0CED42E0F88C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clean Competition Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB2014D615E7C4E0890757597CA4F0D13"><enum>2.</enum><header>Carbon intensity charge</header> <subsection id="H6C6B08689C7D43DA9EF06A3E5456ACFF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/38">Chapter 38</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subchapter:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H691418E2FF4145F8BCF59F5EE4517D11"> 
<subchapter id="H41A615E3365B479D8E03B79648E1114F"><enum>E</enum><header>Carbon intensity charge</header> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H962F2B09CEDC43D9A70A6CCCB9187C4F">Sec. 4691. Calculation of carbon intensity. </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H03F1CCA0D46E4BF7908D6C2024DC57EE">Sec. 4692. Imposition of carbon intensity charge. </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H03C9E694EFBD4FAFBF62D4AF507E823C">Sec. 4693. Rebate. </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HEEC63E0F67E74097B56A3ED900216410">Sec. 4694. Definitions. </toc-entry></toc> 
<section id="H962F2B09CEDC43D9A70A6CCCB9187C4F"><enum>4691.</enum><header>Calculation of carbon intensity</header> 
<subsection id="HB70D30AAD9A74C7496DF890816262231"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text>Not later than June 30, 2026, and annually thereafter, any covered entity shall, for each eligible facility operated by such entity, report to the Secretary (and, for purposes of the information described in paragraphs (2) and (3), the Administrator) with respect to the following:</text> <paragraph id="H68B64450D52943DDA6735A6133F067C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any information required to be reported to the Administrator under the Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program (or which would be required to be reported notwithstanding any other provision of law prohibiting the implementation of or use of funds for such requirements) for the preceding calendar year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H007384ECAD06422DA3A3C7BEF24EF6FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The total amount of electricity used at such facility during the preceding calendar year, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HBAAC0225BB8945928ABA219DDD5EC049"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether such electricity was provided through the electric grid or a dedicated generation source, </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD57BB4512ED24232BF526E210390F61A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the terms of any power purchase agreements with respect to such facility, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H14AD4E9D8AAD473DA96906BCFCB0DB70"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to any electricity which was not provided through the electric grid, the greenhouse gas emissions associated with the production of such electricity, provided that such emissions are not reported pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2DB55614711C497481E64B166EE9A9A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The total weight (expressed in tons) of each covered primary good produced at such facility during the preceding calendar year.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H97E37715B9A84EE79F102151B4C50A67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Calculation</header> <paragraph id="H14983CE2E9CA43669EBCFC4DCCC67AAB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Carbon intensity</header> <subparagraph id="H28FDD863455B442CB27FB362BBFDF1C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Eligible facility</header><text>For purposes of this subchapter, for each calendar year, the carbon intensity with respect to any eligible facility shall be an amount equal to the quotient of—</text> 
<clause id="HEA6575BD70234D3AB9A4CDC3E7E5C34A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the covered emissions (as determined under paragraph (2)) with respect to such facility, divided by</text></clause> <clause id="HB7E4B9B3BA1B47F98D867D24BD691845"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total weight (expressed in tons) of covered primary goods produced at such facility during the preceding calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8FA7C0DE5D04B6F84DBC9C6A7D2BCC5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered national industry</header> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57B9FE03117844D095AFA39B0385CF2D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subchapter, the carbon intensity with respect to any covered national industry shall be an amount (as determined by the Secretary) equal to the quotient of—</text> <subclause id="H425D3F98296949B6BBF350292275CB3E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an amount equal to the sum of the covered emissions (as determined under paragraph (2)) with respect to all eligible facilities which produce covered primary goods which are included within such industry for calendar year 2025, divided by</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H82C42CE25CBC4068844CD507275607E7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total weight (expressed in tons) of covered primary goods within such industry which are produced at all such eligible facilities during such year.</text></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9335C01A53AD49988C71BBA11D4FA5BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the Secretary (in coordination with the relevant parties) may determine which types of eligible facilities (and any related covered primary goods) are included or excluded within a covered national industry, provided that such determination—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E72F1472E40463CBD8BCA3F616976E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitates a fair comparison of carbon intensities across similar eligible facilities (based on a comparison of the material inputs and outputs of such facilities), and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D4F0EB127E24F6DAF0DAB734F90CE6B"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not meaningfully reduce the scope of greenhouse gas emissions covered by this subchapter.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C7BAF645F034B559AA06E2BAE444900"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Excluded facilities</header><text>In the case of any eligible facility which, pursuant to clause (ii), is excluded from a covered national industry and is not included in any other covered national industry, such facility shall be deemed to not be included in any covered national industry.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H619ECD3C7E4F4785AC23363DB839481D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Petition for specific goods</header> <clause id="H10F35FA000FB4D57A48DEF5B4B734642"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any covered national industry which produces more than 1 covered primary good, a covered entity may file a petition with the Secretary to—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6BEA77DB18334F9E89763B3A3B696A60"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine the carbon intensity with respect to a specific covered primary good, and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABDC49A8924E4762A845C9277C311073"><enum>(II)</enum><text>determine a classification for defining such covered primary good for purposes of this subchapter, such as—</text> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D65C070D98A4324AAE72BA490D92A93"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the applicable 6-digit subheading of the Harmonized Tariff Schedule of the United States,</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9339DAEF6046445FB9B432816D557E96"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the relevant production process,</text></item> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6238E11187474A87848BF6EF4F97F741"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a set of material characteristics, or</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA9852D6716EB475DACD680059047D48A"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>any combination of the methods for classification described in items (aa) through (cc).</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HD43342F518B3481DA4F031DB34E03A6C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Review</header><text>With respect to any covered primary good which is included in a petition described in clause (i), the Secretary (in coordination with the Administrator and the Secretary of Energy) shall approve such petition if—</text> <subclause id="HA409D980B1B5469CBC72F05D01208F4F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the chemical, physical, or mechanical production processes for such good are substantially different as compared to other covered primary goods produced within the same covered national industry, </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3C9710DDF22D4E0CB5F879A86110E869"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the properties of such good are distinct such that its uses cannot be easily replaced by other covered primary goods produced within the same covered national industry, and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H938C62FC952B46CBAFC03A6A97AD0DC8"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the carbon intensity determined with respect to such good is at least 25 percent greater than the carbon intensity determined for other covered primary goods produced within the same covered national industry.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H6E9720D848564FD8A488ADA3DEEE0643"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Recalculation</header><text>In the case of any petition described in clause (i) which is approved by the Secretary pursuant to clause (ii), the Secretary (in coordination with the Administrator) shall redetermine the carbon intensity with respect to the covered national industry which includes production of the covered primary good which is the subject of such petition by excluding any covered emissions associated with the production of such good for purposes of the determination made under subparagraph (B) for such industry.</text></clause> <clause id="H5DA0C6E86354418FAD91C4937D4A6F65"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Goods-level data</header><text>In the case of any petition described in clause (i) which is approved by the Secretary pursuant to clause (ii), the Secretary (in coordination with the Administrator) shall use a methodology for determining the carbon intensity of the covered primary good (as determined using the eligible facility information reported under subsection (a)), and shall publish the methodology and the results of such determination, in a manner which—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB1A08CB68B148DDB794AEC83866D748"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is compatible with existing Federal carbon accounting rules and standards,</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78C68B85DD994C42824CACAE6C225B58"><enum>(II)</enum><text>includes the related chemical, physical, or mechanical production processes responsible for differences in carbon intensity and covered emissions, and</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3BC55C25AC4487689C9C14C49E75755"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritizes ease of administration and compliance.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDACCE803E48D4A42A043F82BF4C1CF9D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>Any determination of carbon intensity under this paragraph shall be made by the Secretary in coordination with the Administrator and the Secretary of Energy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB1704C8AC544787A0F63977B55E0111"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered emissions</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA259B44E19984DD899DB4D4C0EDEA78F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, for each calendar year, the amount of covered emissions with respect to any eligible facility shall be an amount (as determined by the Secretary, in coordination with the Administrator) equal to—</text> <clause id="H82F6B6E19DEC420E904F021BB60AB5F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount equal to the sum of—</text> 
<subclause id="H63C11C3BC05246C69058D680B61C3144"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the total greenhouse gas emissions associated with the production of covered primary goods at such facility during the preceding calendar year (as reported pursuant to subsection (a)), plus</text></subclause> <subclause id="H74B4303C39764F4DABEEC1175140A205"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total greenhouse gas emissions associated with any electricity used at such facility for the production of such goods during the preceding calendar year, minus</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H7AD74874D4CC488483E7873977940DF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total greenhouse gas emissions which are captured and disposed of in secure geological storage (in compliance with the regulations established under section 45Q(f)(2)) during the preceding calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDE402AF4280448E09C599038877ADFAE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Direct air capture</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii), in the case of any greenhouse gas emissions which are captured directly from the ambient air, the operator of the facility which captured such emissions may apportion such emissions amongst any eligible facilities which are under common control of such operator.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0CFF52E24EC44BF68FD1CFE6F6AEA36A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Emissions for electricity used</header> 
<clause id="H9405422A85C741F49B887404FC515C7B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(i)(II), the amount of greenhouse gas emissions associated with electricity provided through the electric grid shall be determined based on the average carbon intensity for the regional grid in which the eligible facility is located for the preceding calendar year.</text></clause> <clause id="HA5EA559BC6364D6085F4780D0365DEB5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>In the case of an eligible facility which is subject to a power purchase agreement (or its foreign equivalent) which guarantees that any electricity provided under such agreement is generated not less than 15 minutes prior to use by such facility and within the same regional transmission zone (or its foreign equivalent) as such facility—</text> 
<subclause id="H6C7CCBC15AEF4793B0ACFDC0DBAB0953"><enum>(I)</enum><text>clause (i) shall not apply, and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0A49F7A60E5146A1A80F119C273E67DA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the amount of greenhouse gas emissions associated with such electricity shall be determined based on the average carbon intensity of the electricity provided under such agreement.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5AA8A46749754F04916B764E861D90EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Imported goods</header> 
<subparagraph id="H14EB7269E9DD45839D9F4A923721397B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any covered primary good which is imported into the United States, the carbon intensity with respect to such good shall be determined by the Secretary (in coordination with the relevant parties) based on—</text> <clause id="HEF1AEECE3BB44298832141750BADC574"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the carbon intensity of the general economy of the country of origin of such good, or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB541F10C96849728B14670205552CCA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the Secretary (in coordination with the relevant parties) determines that transparent, verifiable, and reliable information is available with respect to any covered national industry in the country of origin of such good and that such country of origin is a transparent market economy in which inter-firm resource shuffling is unlikely to occur, the carbon intensity of the covered national industry in such country which includes production of such good.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7457B8314A6348E39D7FACE9A3198F10"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Petition</header> <clause id="H9F0B52B4096F4C64BA8A788AB69F195B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any entity which imports a covered primary good for which the carbon intensity can be determined under subparagraph (A)(ii), such entity may file a petition with the Secretary to determine the charge under section 4692, if any, based on the average carbon intensity with respect to the production of such good by the manufacturer within the country of origin.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2197834153E5406CAD15262E96AC10F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Aggregation rule</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the average carbon intensity with respect to the production of a covered primary good shall be determined based upon greenhouse gas emission and production data from all facilities which produce such good which are under common control of the manufacturer of such good, including any subsidiary, parent company, or joint venture of such manufacturer within the country of origin.</text></clause> <clause id="H8DA27BD528BC493586F9E83617733C58"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Data provision</header><text>In the case of an entity which files a petition described in clause (i), such entity shall provide the Secretary with an environmental product declaration containing—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DF8B237BFF24946A6D1FF038F179825"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any information which would otherwise be required to be reported under subsection (a) if the facilities which produced the covered primary good to which the petition applies were subject to the reporting requirements under the Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program, and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H14F676B90F2B4ABC85E271A8D2DB13AF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other information which is necessary (as determined by the Secretary, in coordination with the relevant parties) to calculate the carbon intensity of the covered primary good in accordance with any relevant methodologies for allocating the carbon intensity of the covered primary good under paragraph (1)(C)(iv).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C1B115A5E4F485AA79019834BBDF638"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inputs</header><text>With respect to any covered primary good which is imported into the United States and for which other covered primary goods (other than petroleum, natural gas, or coal) were used as inputs by the manufacturer in the production of the imported covered primary good, any greenhouse gas emissions associated with the production of the covered primary goods used as inputs shall be included in the determination of the greenhouse gas emissions associated with production of the imported covered primary good.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB07C0FD2A44B431B8BAFCF34F4AA0C4C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Carbon intensity of the general economy</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, with respect to any country, the carbon intensity of the general economy of such country shall be an amount equal to the quotient of—</text> 
<clause id="H2B44A7341C224154A436DB474560E768"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the greenhouse gas emissions of such country for the most recent year for which the Secretary determines there is reliable information, divided by</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B9E39332D3B4161B4047FFDCB0E9365"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the gross domestic product of such country for the year described in clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB5A191022CB046DE99446D5F89B94811"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Exclusion</header> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F94250501D3419FB39196149004B672"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to clause (ii), in the case of any covered primary good (including any covered primary good which is a component part of a finished good) which is imported into the United States and was produced in a relatively least developed country (as described in section 124 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151v">22 U.S.C. 2151v</external-xref>)), this paragraph shall not apply.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E2A6D31D580422594DDF72EC0E7D296"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply if the country described in such clause produces at least 3 percent of total global exports by value of the covered primary good.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A4E2F5A33C94B35A812247FE4EF4A49"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Inter-firm resource shuffling</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>inter-firm resource shuffling</term> means any buying, selling, trading, exchanging, or other transfer of control of production facilities between entities based on the carbon intensity of such facilities for the purpose of creating entities with relatively lower carbon intensity and entities with relatively higher carbon intensity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1DBB934D392D4AADBA6686BFD15477E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Secretary (in coordination with the relevant parties) shall—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8EC2CD21510C4D939FFCAF0C8A204306"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">annually publish any carbon intensity which has been determined under subsection (b) with respect to any eligible facility, covered national industry, covered primary good, foreign manufacturer, or country of origin, and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3F90170BF6824F14B367361758894540"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publish (and update, as appropriate) a list of—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4D14027202C40F1AB175B9C5A74F72E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each covered primary good, as categorized by the covered national industry in which such good is included, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB0719E2C4BE54E77981FFC4B99E86670"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any covered primary good for which a petition described in clause (i) of subsection (b)(1)(C) has been approved by the Secretary pursuant to clause (ii) of such subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H03F1CCA0D46E4BF7908D6C2024DC57EE"><enum>4692.</enum><header>Imposition of carbon intensity charge</header> 
<subsection id="H043D6BCDE1B0452ABF101CFD0EAE6245"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<paragraph id="H15A2AC5A83FF4160B187DC3E90E073A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Importation of goods</header> 
<subparagraph id="H59B758C6EEB84907AEF4B9477806B1D6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<clause id="HF7A36E2420A64A2CAF2BDCD4EC1B02E6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Covered primary goods</header><text>In the case of any covered primary good imported into the United States during any calendar year beginning after December 31, 2024, there is hereby imposed a charge in an amount (rounded to the nearest dollar) equal to the product of—</text> <subclause id="H8B105A7318184B81A319912B6DC6BF22"><enum>(I)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDA7B368D132E4793A874127821274E42"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a good for which the carbon intensity is determined under section 4691(b)(3)(A)(i), the amount (if any) by which the amount determined under clause (iii) with respect to such good exceeds an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the relevant carbon intensity for such good, or</text></item> 
<item id="H7C63BE8E753341508F55F63620C62A7A" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a good for which the carbon intensity is determined under subparagraph (A)(ii) or (B) of section 4691(b)(3), the amount (if any) by which the carbon intensity determined under such subparagraph with respect to such good exceeds an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the relevant carbon intensity for such good, multiplied by</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HE3F16B60D7044EF9A64F86608545D5BE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total weight (expressed in tons) of the good imported into the United States, multiplied by</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H407E9F52AA394CC8B1F7D1127B36268F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the carbon price.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H47B2167C9458498A94BB4C8B9A13497C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Finished goods</header> <subclause id="H084C20E551204406B6DECFAA3A8818A9"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any finished good which is imported into the United States during any calendar year beginning after December 31, 2026, there is hereby imposed a charge in an amount equal to the sum of the amounts determined under subclause (II) with respect to each covered primary good which is a component part of such finished good.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5BB9D77C37B0490D877CBE6A3B76E0AB"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Components</header><text>The amount determined under this subclause with respect to any covered primary good which is a component part of a finished good is an amount equal to the product of—</text> <item id="H2E4A42B7C6D94946B68D73B3D5D2303E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount (if any) determined under clause (i)(I) if such clause were applied with respect to such good, multiplied by</text></item> 
<item id="HABD1922F1B23497B853724BDAFD8868D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the total weight (expressed in tons) of the covered primary good, multiplied by</text></item> <item id="H0B23EA72A58243A787F5D9C35E66CDFE"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the carbon price.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H38CC0D95438545D2B65ED20F255D8473"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Calculation for certain foreign goods</header><text>For purposes of clause (i)(I)(aa), the amount determined under this clause with respect to any covered primary good shall be equal to the product of—</text> <subclause id="H35DA03A3F41F4EF4A1433FFD58ACA236"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an amount equal to the quotient of—</text> 
<item id="H589258003C1B49F7A28E1512D7E0AD0D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the carbon intensity of the general economy (as determined under section 4691(b)(3)(D)) of the country of origin of such good, divided by</text></item> <item id="H95EB9B978E3C4FA58A4ECA9DBB737284"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the carbon intensity of the general economy (as so determined) of the United States, multiplied by</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7ED54267C6254BD4A95294100FF2CD09"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the relevant carbon intensity for such good.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8FFEE7DB08A348ADAB88A168805E377B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Charge due</header><text>The charge imposed under this paragraph with respect to any goods imported during any calendar year shall be paid by the entity which imported such goods not later than September 30 of the calendar year subsequent to such year.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H708CF734D46A44E0927851422B32E5E5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusion</header> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDBD89CCE03F64CC8A628045946F6E7E1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to clause (ii), in the case of any covered primary good (including any covered primary good which is a component part of a finished good) which is imported into the United States and was produced in a relatively least developed country (as described in section 124 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151v">22 U.S.C. 2151v</external-xref>)), this paragraph shall not apply.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36780A274F5B4DE0BE81BB14DD579CD6"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply if the country described in such clause produces at least 3 percent of total global exports by value of the covered primary good.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H261D7E2793D7459483F0004C478D9C21"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Carbon clubs</header><text>If the Secretary (in coordination with the relevant parties) determines that a foreign country has implemented policies which impose explicit costs on the emission of greenhouse gases which are materially similar to the charges imposed pursuant to the provisions of this subchapter, the charge (or a percentage of the charge which is equivalent to the costs imposed by the foreign country) which would otherwise be imposed under this section with respect to covered primary goods produced in such foreign country may be waived.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDBCF44EC33874407912EF1FE5B5063C2"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Relevant carbon intensity</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>relevant carbon intensity</term> means, with respect to any covered primary good—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3406C89EDB14F4392540F3FFE9FCA97"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as provided in clause (ii), the carbon intensity (as determined under section 4691(b)(1)(B)) for the covered national industry which includes such good, or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32FE0271CCEE43A0934EBBBFF83709E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any covered primary good which is included in a petition described in clause (i) of section 4691(b)(1)(C) which is approved by the Secretary pursuant to clause (ii) of such section, the carbon intensity of such good as determined under such section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0F351D260E6A4D7EB8F8B69C83C44E61"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Domestic production of covered primary goods</header> 
<subparagraph id="HC7840E166BE94CF0AB811495EFCE9765"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any eligible facility, for each calendar year beginning after December 31, 2024, there is hereby imposed a charge in an amount (rounded to the nearest dollar) equal to the product of—</text> <clause id="H3D464F62F266465B9F190D3966462258"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount (if any) by which the carbon intensity of such facility (as determined under subparagraph (A) of section 4691(b)(1)) exceeds—</text> 
<subclause id="HBA47353201E84FE89804011C67DDFCCD"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the carbon intensity for the covered national industry (as determined under subparagraph (B) of section 4691(b)(1)) which includes any covered primary good produced by such facility, or </text></subclause> <subclause id="HB0EE70CF5D094EF981BE7B9CE3AE1298"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a covered primary good produced by such facility which is subject to an approved petition under subparagraph (C) of such section, an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the carbon intensity determined with respect to such good, multiplied by</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HBDE67B1A3E72496CB2CB69D0C854513F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total weight (expressed in tons) of any covered primary goods produced by such facility during such calendar year, multiplied by</text></clause> <clause id="H0666850A114A4BE3917268E71D43A92E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the carbon price.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H984A2AE0A92A46FE81095D0777C219D6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Charge due</header><text>The charge imposed under this paragraph with respect to any calendar year shall be paid by the covered entity not later than September 30 of the calendar year subsequent to such year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H950C6893CC804DCBB07637C252421679"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of paragraphs (1)(A) and (2)(A) of subsection (a), the applicable percentage shall be—</text> 
<paragraph id="H817DB575FC124899BD46A4461489EB64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for calendar year 2025, 100 percent,</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCC0567104A7742A0B599F7E0EE57CBB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for calendar years 2026 through 2029, the applicable percentage for the preceding calendar year, reduced by 2.5 percentage points, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H038FDA149E9842ECAD39C21DBF8829B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for any calendar year subsequent to calendar year 2029, the applicable percentage for the preceding calendar year, reduced by 5 percentage points (but not less than zero).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF3C54FAFE4F54FA89C3D32C0B2953B81"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Carbon price</header> <paragraph id="H0E81BD72F7DA455EA54936279BA58D39"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of paragraphs (1)(A) and (2)(A) of subsection (a), the carbon price shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC1C4F1AB1A4D4E9B868161893655AA09"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for 2025, $55, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06E1EA0A1794427FB18CCDFF770ECD3D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each calendar year subsequent to the calendar year described in subparagraph (A), an amount equal to the sum of—</text> 
<clause id="H2BE79DA6FE924757B6EDFB8ADC8C57FA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the carbon price for the preceding year, plus</text></clause> <clause id="H5BEEA8C474654EE6AB81AD5769D6A828"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an amount equal to—</text> 
<subclause id="H016A12FA2E724F00832876055459B6EC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount described in clause (i), multiplied by</text></subclause> <subclause id="H336475D2EACC400A86C342840C225568"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the percentage by which the CPI for the preceding calendar year exceeds the CPI for the second preceding calendar year, increased by 5 percentage points.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HA6C1B98A9F934851929C6D39B55BA2F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CPI</header><text>Rules similar to the rules of paragraphs (4) and (5) of section 1(f) shall apply for purposes of this subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H816F9D9E9A3E4342B8DF490D3C51199D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>Any applicable amount determined under this subsection which is not a multiple of $1 shall be rounded to the nearest dollar. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H03C9E694EFBD4FAFBF62D4AF507E823C"><enum>4693.</enum><header>Rebate</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F0B8A8C3B714FB5977C1458CC0EB83B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exportation of covered primary good</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a person who exports any covered primary good from the United States which was produced in an eligible facility for which a charge has been imposed under section 4692, a refund shall be allowed to such person in the same manner as if it were an overpayment of the charge imposed by such section in an amount equal to the charge that would be imposed under subsection (a)(1)(A)(i) of such section with respect to such good if the carbon intensity with respect to such eligible facility were determined under section 4691(b)(1)(A) by substituting <quote>all eligible facilities by the covered entity which produced the covered primary good described in section 4693(a)(1)</quote> for <quote>such facility</quote> each place it appears in such section.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB54F5AF2F534AE1ABD9A616A7208F7B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exportation of finished good</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a person who exports any finished good from the United States for which a charge has been imposed under section 4692 on such finished good or any of its components, a refund shall be allowed to such person in the same manner as if it were an overpayment of the charge imposed by such section in an amount equal to the charge that would otherwise be imposed under such section with respect to such finished good (as determined pursuant to subsection (a)(1)(A)(ii) of such section).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEEC63E0F67E74097B56A3ED900216410"><enum>4694.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this subchapter—</text> <paragraph id="H5DD2B93745FE4B06B00A530BB7F9C509"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HF3CB865F41B846B2B4639A50F16E32B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>C02-e</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H106A7201A5A8400A96E7B667923DA55F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the term <term>CO2-e</term> means, with respect to a greenhouse gas, the quantity of such gas that has a global warming potential equivalent to 1 metric ton of carbon dioxide, as determined pursuant to table A–1 of subpart A of part 98 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of the enactment of this subchapter.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC650132EE2414A5C87621EC580615B35"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Methane</header><text>In the case of methane, the term <term>CO2-e</term> means the quantity of methane that has the same global warming potential over a 20-year period as 1 metric ton of carbon dioxide, as determined by the Administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H469F01CB835147089F9E6DEF1369199B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term> means any entity which—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B71114F662B40AC8E6D0A2F866E53CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>produces any covered primary good, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HADF6EBFDAA0F43F5840C23512F2145D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is required to report emissions of greenhouse gases under the Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program (or would be required to report such emissions notwithstanding any other provision of law prohibiting the implementation of or use of funds for such requirements).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H75A0D02BAC834A268574C68F4F8839F2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered national industry</header> <subparagraph id="H0A2CF3BBE39A4B95B38357475B75C71D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided under section 4691(b)(1)(B)(ii), the term <term>covered national industry</term> means any industry which is assigned a 6-digit NAICS code which is included in any of the following clauses:</text> 
<clause id="H458D141569AA4EA0ADEC1A25241CE106"><enum>(i)</enum><text>211120 (petroleum extraction).</text></clause> <clause id="HCF460BF9D9154835A71821EC7C38FFC1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>211130 (natural gas extraction).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFB664958EE044135A3CF81DB59CD7E9D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>212114 (surface coal mining).</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3F0CD6A8721E4BF58932465B1ADE95E6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">212115 (underground coal mining).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H45D338A590284B939C9A1221F4811B90"><enum>(v)</enum><text>322110 (pulp mills).</text></clause> <clause id="H211216738AA64AE5B14CD8AD5314688C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>322120 (paper mills).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6F79A8FE0E7B4300AE22E4EAEF53F113"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>322130 (paperboard mills).</text></clause> <clause id="H67AAE7C173EF40D68090021D12BCA829"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>324110 (petroleum refineries).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9784FCE5EEFC489FB8311CEAC02A6512"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>324121 (asphalt paving mixture and block manufacturing).</text></clause> <clause id="HED0A803522B24C37876DA01704EA34F3"><enum>(x)</enum><text>324122 (asphalt shingle and coating materials manufacturing).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFF2A02EC6A854C4293316F765BCC04BF"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>324199 (all other petroleum and coal products manufacturing).</text></clause> <clause id="H2DA320184BF74F6DAF34453CC2E575F3"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>325110 (petrochemical manufacturing).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD20C4AC0DE07490C854AE6E96A5F09D9"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>325120 (industrial gas manufacturing).</text></clause> <clause id="HC0A58C4305F1495AA3A7EA5579A81083"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>325193 (ethyl alcohol manufacturing).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD1B5666682F245F7B0ED6E80B81491E0"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>325199 (other basic organic chemical manufacturing).</text></clause> <clause id="HE9DBAE0E621E4538AA911D889C52D9DC"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>325311 (nitrogenous fertilizer manufacturing).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9D3ADA2D77D24C69946778338A1137FF"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>327211, 327212, 327213, or 327215 (glass).</text></clause> <clause id="HA90516239CB243F1904154F5B578D3C6"><enum>(xviii)</enum><text>327310 (cement).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB0871086AE7D496885B8AB929FE823C7"><enum>(xix)</enum><text>327410 or 327420 (lime and gypsum product manufacturing).</text></clause> <clause id="H8D6730B73375420A86C912475380A2F5"><enum>(xx)</enum><text>331110 (iron and steel).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE9FC54C032A6442A922A70A3B129AF68"><enum>(xxi)</enum><text>331313 or 331314 (aluminum).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1EB2BE9CEC2746C1AEAD9A5AE7BB3B14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <clause id="H3854CB6B89AB476DB8845C55B7399FF2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Industrial gas manufacturing</header><text>Subparagraph (A)(xiii) shall apply only with respect to the production of hydrogen.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDCFCF913BC944E83B413C3680409E979"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other basic organic chemical manufacturing</header><text>Subparagraph (A)(xv) shall apply only with respect to the production of adipic acid.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE3E9F724D58046F398E72929F777511B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered primary good</header><text>The term <term>covered primary good</term> means any good which is produced as part of a trade or business operating within a covered national industry, and includes (except as otherwise provided under section 4691(b)(1)(C)) any good classifiable under the same 6-digit subheading of the Harmonized Tariff Schedule of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C6D1C52F9DE42F7850CEE53A97BE593"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible facility</header><text>The term <term>eligible facility</term> means any facility (as such term is defined for purposes of the Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program) which is—</text> <subparagraph id="HC1436228BC694B3994263A0290C52B04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operated by a covered entity for the production of any covered primary good, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9686A31D00414D87A572757D97FFB913"><enum>(B)</enum><text>located within the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A3914D927F54761A97BE7F7A8219643"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Finished good</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD26A6EFA9744E97B33ADDF45B4E3F36"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>finished good</term> means any good which—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D6631024558442FA01A55F7512B02D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for calendar years 2027 and 2028—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E553A346A9B48EA9B2796EF776B56A9"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contains greater than 500 pounds of any combination of any covered primary goods, or</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05010418498148A8A39DA5D2CC4A45B6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>was produced from inputs of any combination of covered primary goods, the value of which comprise more than 90 percent of the total value of the material inputs involved in the production of such good,</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HDC5AE71CA4C743BD9A816E02A425827E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for calendar years 2029 and 2030—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA02CA962E9540A5888E28C0570B77AB"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contains greater than 100 pounds of any combination of any covered primary goods, or</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17CFFBAFC7EB40F59BBED38D8B1FFC4B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>was produced from inputs of any combination of covered primary goods, the value of which comprise more than 75 percent of the total value of the material inputs involved in the production of such good, and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H387C122BAC524943B212B152C7AC1CB6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any calendar year after calendar year 2030—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12285A05D1074EA0AE6C88FD91F20111"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contains greater than such amount as is determined by the Secretary (as determined in coordination with the relevant parties, and which shall not be greater than 100 pounds) of any combination of any covered primary goods, or</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H289808E4CD7C485B850ABA26E35252B9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>was produced from inputs of any combination of covered primary goods, the value of which comprise more than such percentage as is determined by the Secretary (as determined in coordination with the relevant parties, and which shall not be greater than 75 percent) of the total value of the material inputs involved in the production of such good.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45FC577B9A5E4BBDB519A7D50029488D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception </header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>finished good</term> shall not include any waste or scrap product which is imported or exported.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H534EAC1BBCB0496F954564FD59A3AE2F"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Greenhouse gas</header><text>The term <term>greenhouse gas</term> has the meaning given such term under section 211(o)(1)(G) of the Clean Air Act, as in effect on the date of the enactment of this subchapter.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E77B72B548C4B07A7D5B2699BE5BB67"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Greenhouse gas emissions</header><text>The term <term>greenhouse gas emissions</term> means the amount of greenhouse gases, expressed in metric tons of CO2-e, which were emitted to the atmosphere. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H11730614457842B7B02919918E8D0F17"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program</header><text>The term <term>Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program</term> means the Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program established under part 98 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BC5752B6E314D14B85B6B4C5156A98F"><enum>(11)</enum><header>NAICS</header><text>The term <term>NAICS</term> means the North American Industrial Classification System.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71E691A9EA074D4F82AB31FF21D641D3"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Regional grid</header><text>The term <term>regional grid</term> means the smallest defined region of interconnected power grid (including power generation assets) from which a facility draws power that accounts for the total power supplied to the facility by the grid and for which there is reliable data.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6320F56B33364DC7BC19325201CC6334"><enum>(13)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Relevant parties</header><text>The term <term>relevant parties</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H76E3A68F8078411BB4017865A80F270A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Administrator,</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBAC2E3B37F684690BCB83B81ADEA2CC3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy,</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB60E9F8F9C33475EAA324F5FEE719986"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce,</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC62CC979800A45AC909F52E0DD2F51D8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the United States Trade Representative, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA3C88E5B93CE40D19CB8CEF5F41FFB9E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Chair and Vice Chair of the United States International Trade Commission. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HFD9722E4AFD74CC68BB5DCC86DFB88CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of subchapters for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/38">chapter 38</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end thereof the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H75279FAC257B4AC3B55023133BC5F4A9"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">Subchapter E—Carbon intensity charge</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H14045EE0ADD74EA59365F225406C4A7C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant program</header> 
<paragraph id="H4187137F2B0346119629D11D1E224FFB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For fiscal year 2026 and each subsequent fiscal year, there are appropriated, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, to the Department of the Treasury amounts equal to applicable amount for the preceding fiscal year, with such amounts to be used by the Secretary, in conjunction with the Secretary of Energy and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, to establish a competitive grant program to award grants to eligible entities for investments in new technology—</text> <subparagraph id="H0EE5AD7A21C24873B3949A3A194BB10D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of an existing eligible facility, to reduce their carbon intensity, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFDC3545F065E4C948E2DC8CB6C310B66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a proposed eligible facility, to ensure best-in-class carbon intensity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74EF2D4853B6424B83EF75BB28FE13A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Modeled on Diesel Emissions Reduction Act</header><text>For purposes of the program described in paragraph (1), such program shall be administered in a manner similar to the national grant program of the Environmental Protection Agency under subtitle G of title VII of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16131">42 U.S.C. 16131 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H948DD43301214B0EA65B6514B4456ED4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Awarding of grant amounts</header><text>For purposes of awarding grants under the program described in paragraph (1), the Secretary (in conjunction with the Administrator and the Secretary of Energy) shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H0858025584BD4916AB08D8754D58AA06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>give preference to proposed investments—</text> 
<clause id="HAD5A433716874665B742468D2309DBF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that would result in the greatest decrease in carbon intensity, </text></clause> <clause id="H640CEC219EB74D35BD87EEB14B02304A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for facilities located in economically distressed communities that have experienced a loss of manufacturing jobs,</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8E894EEBF2CD49528B77F43F489E6F28"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that would maximize improvement in local air quality, or</text></clause> <clause id="H223D4575DB4B47D1B227E1F5D4F463AC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>for facilities located in communities with high cumulative pollution burdens (as determined by the Administrator), and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8F86B74BEED14139923A15C5D607528D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>allocate grant funds to eligible facilities and proposed eligible facilities which produce covered primary goods that are included within a covered national industry in approximate proportion to the share of total greenhouse gas emissions for which such industry is responsible for emitting.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51F24D10960D4E68A2A7507E42E497E0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Recapture</header><text>In the case of any eligible entity which has been awarded a grant under the program described in paragraph (1) with respect to any eligible facility or proposed eligible facility, if such entity fails to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H29DDB2AFB4A9416EB660FF0323EB5EDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>within 3 years of the awarding of such grant, complete the proposed investments in new technology at such facility, or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8EC91A6FB73348D5B98C7396BE4DDF39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the 10-year period after such investments are placed in service—</text> 
<clause id="HFC0F79DBE81544F48871A549209A3569"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of an existing eligible facility, achieve and maintain the reduction in carbon intensity proposed in the application for such grant, or</text></clause> <clause id="H23C8423439704A99AEC066BDD794EF26"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a proposed eligible facility, achieve and maintain the best-in-class carbon intensity proposed in the application for such grant, </text></clause></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">the Secretary shall recapture, pursuant to such regulations or other guidance issued by the Secretary, the amount of the grant awarded with respect to such facility.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAA48FC2CF93B42E89980C93FF89693F0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Applicable amount</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>applicable amount</term> means, with respect to any fiscal year, an amount equal to 75 percent of the increase in revenues to the Treasury during such fiscal year by reason of the application of subchapter E of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/38">chapter 38</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by subsection (a)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59CBD3966A4E4651AA9143F32E1B380D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H55010E7E13224553B9700433C8044EA8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The terms <term>covered national industry</term>, <term>eligible facility</term>, and <term>covered primary good</term> shall have the same meaning given such terms under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4694">section 4694</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by subsection (a)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC381796A48D2424D934C0C334873ACCD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Best-in-class carbon intensity</header><text>The term <term>best-in-class carbon intensity</term> means, with respect to any proposed eligible facility, that the carbon intensity of such facility would be not greater than the carbon intensity of the existing facility with the lowest carbon intensity within the relevant covered national industry (as determined of the date of the application for a grant under the program described in paragraph (1)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3005EB1A846402CB4EA1407F785BE9A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means any person which operates an eligible facility or will operate a proposed eligible facility.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7A1DF38356464E4A824C593CE11A92D1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary's delegate).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5B0142F3D28148859EB9BB70750AD243"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Economic Support Fund of Department of State</header> 
<paragraph id="H2AB10B04D831489A94DCF0827B86433D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For fiscal year 2026 and each subsequent fiscal year, in addition to amounts otherwise available, there are appropriated, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, to the Department of State an amount equal to the applicable amount for the preceding fiscal year, with such amount to be made available for bilateral and multilateral assistance to support climate and clean energy programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD23AF90BB36F444B8B596A2198B7E24F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable amount</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>applicable amount</term> means, with respect to any fiscal year, an amount equal to 25 percent of the increase in revenues to the Treasury during such fiscal year by reason of the application of subchapter E of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/38">chapter 38</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by subsection (a)).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

