<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H71E7B5CEF2814A5B8550235FE3CA47EB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2449 IH: Taiwan Protection and National Resilience Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2449</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a strategy for countering the People’s Republic of China.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAFE1342D249448829BD386E4562F81E3" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H303FD0384C754F87A138EE54287D9C07"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan Protection and National Resilience Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB20A53B87DFD4A2D967ECEF635A361BC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strategy for countering the People's Republic of China</header><subsection id="H39B0939C61E146A6A0D3AFAD1C8C0E93"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Identification of vulnerabilities and leverage</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Director of the Office of Federal Procurement Policy, and the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that identifies—</text><paragraph id="H4300BD2467344BA3BED2C9124BA7280C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>goods and services from the United States that are relied on by the People’s Republic of China such that that reliance presents a strategic opportunity and source of leverage against the People’s Republic of China; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42353399FEC440A198FA0070C959DC31"><enum>(2)</enum><text>procurement practices of the United States Armed Forces and other Federal agencies that are reliant on trade with the People’s Republic of China and other inputs from the People’s Republic of China, such that that reliance presents a strategic vulnerability and source of leverage that the Chinese Communist Party could exploit.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD04220F774F24372A2800A53E9AEB1CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Strategy To respond to coercive action</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB274FCABFC9E4794B4CDB3C6CA9FCB20"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the submission of the report required by subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of the Defense, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of State, the Director of the Office of Federal Procurement Policy, and the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report, utilizing the findings of the report required by subsection (a), that describes a comprehensive sanctions strategy to advise policymakers on policies the United States and allies and partners of the United States could adopt with respect to the People’s Republic of China in response to any coercive action, including an invasion, by the People’s Republic of China that infringes upon the territorial sovereignty of Taiwan by preventing access to international waterways, airspace, or telecommunications networks.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC659B72B5D0B45539D82EB9E16522640"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall include policies that—</text><subparagraph id="HD2058558A44F4CCA8C3D56AC6103C29F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>restrict the access of the People’s Liberation Army to oil, natural gas, munitions, and other supplies needed to conduct military operations against Taiwan, United States facilities in the Pacific and Indian Oceans, and allies and partners of the United States in the region;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2722A5BF86B4A1BB96EB515EFF17089"><enum>(B)</enum><text>diminish the capacity of the industrial base of the People’s Republic of China to manufacture and deliver defense articles to replace those lost in operations of the People’s Liberation Army against Taiwan, the United States, and allies and partners of the United States; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA8926E666BA4FB7A1FD1F681976DBF8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>inhibit the ability of the People’s Republic of China to evade United States and multilateral sanctions through third parties, including through secondary sanctions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H290D0C0AA5A742CC98127354A7955563"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identify specific sanctions-related tools that may be effective in responding to coercive action described in paragraph (1) and assess the feasibility of the use and impact of the use of those tools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H204CDB8101E64308A5CA47C4306E2721"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Recommendations for reduction of vulnerabilities and leverage</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the submission of the report required by subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of State, the Director of National Intelligence, the United States Trade Representative, the Director of the Office of Federal Procurement Policy, and the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that—</text><paragraph id="HAEDB5931ECAA4208B39B49DB42A3B6BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies critical sectors within the United States economy that rely on trade with the People’s Republic of China and other inputs from the People’s Republic of China (including active pharmaceutical ingredients, rare earth minerals, and metallurgical inputs), such that those sectors present a strategic vulnerability and source of leverage that the Chinese Communist Party could exploit; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C048A6CC16E48E88A726B0D6540BDA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>makes recommendations to Congress on steps that can be taken to reduce the sources of leverage described in paragraph (1) and subsection (a)(1), including through—</text><subparagraph id="H4FB8133F06884D31AF48E8624AC82BE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provision of economic incentives and making other trade and contracting reforms to support United States industry and job growth in critical sectors and to indigenize production of critical resources; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB559FD44396B4EB788A9C915E3BE4CF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>policies to facilitate <quote>near- or friend-shoring</quote>, or otherwise developing strategies to facilitate that process with allies and partners of the United States, in other sectors for which domestic reshoring would prove infeasible for any reason.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7652D548CC474AED83904B110C5BCC4B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The reports required by subsections (a), (b), and (c) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="HED35DE8CC8234A1F9CEB29111B9EB70D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of congress defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H2D62039C29A6407D888771FF6B1207A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Armed Services, the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Finance, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5419BDB63CBA4F5CB476859E810AF48E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

