<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC3240C80D1544C3DB41D673E270C2757" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5045 IH: Chesapeake National Recreation Area Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5045</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Chesapeake National Recreation Area as a unit of the National Park System, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA7D4C4C1B32B4A3B9626BACFBA9D9656" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H9B6A3A3412964EA59FF4CC2DFFD8D764"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Chesapeake National Recreation Area Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5BB043E932604A2B8F31E80CAA0C28E7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HB55AB83E8D8F496DB0043A17449DD8AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisory Commission</header><text>The term <term>Advisory Commission</term> means the Chesapeake National Recreation Area Advisory Commission established under section 11(a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FE7538EDF654CC1A374DE8D3AE6DAD0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bay</header><text>The term <term>Bay</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBED903C89FFF4A68A0DB587768186FD3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Chesapeake Bay watershed; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF71ABCEB8264670B5B9A60B37DBB62C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any tidal segment of a tributary of the Chesapeake Bay in any State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6233052C9F8241038BFE784947B03887"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Bay Program</header><text>The term <term>Bay Program</term> means the Chesapeake Bay Program authorized under section 117 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1267">33 U.S.C. 1267</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13225C30D4034E62A78FAF81BAFB1DA3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chesapeake Gateways</header><text>The term <term>Chesapeake Gateways</term> means the Chesapeake Bay Gateways and Watertrails Network authorized under section 502 of the Chesapeake Bay Initiative Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/54/320101">54 U.S.C. 320101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/312">Public Law 105–312</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF5169ABE7AAC48F1B34A813056DDC835"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>Map</term> means the map entitled <quote>Chesapeake National Recreation Area Proposed Boundary</quote>, numbered P99/189631, and dated June 2023. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H554492958809442ABAEC003309B5B190"><enum>(6)</enum><header>National Park Service Site</header><text>The term <term>National Park Service site</term> means a unit of the National Park System that is—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5A9BE124DF4B4A08B7A4BF73BF1D015C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>directly associated with the Bay; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2BF3485CEDEE4C168E0BBC02F922C1AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>located in 1 or more of the States in the Bay watershed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3CBD7F339067464BAFF5BA172F5FDA04"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Partner site</header><text>The term <quote>partner site</quote> means land that is subject to a partner site agreement under section 8(b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BA334C8C3F84DE1AB6280530C4E3280"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Recreation area</header><text>The term <term>Recreation Area</term> means the Chesapeake National Recreation Area established by section 4(a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4591FD8F63964F5483E05B41B3B7AE9F"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H619B9F325FDE4A6C994BDCED2A4FE012"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Youth representative</header><text>The term <term>youth representative</term> means a member of the Advisory Commission who—</text>
<subparagraph id="HAE990485DCB44209BDE08337ED662BFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has not attained the age of 22 as of the date on which the member is appointed or reappointed; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8493D4CDC75B4C96A62DDDF4F823AE01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is tasked with representing the interests of children and young adults in the State from which the member is appointed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="H0F401FBB1BA6472194CA84BB61F3280E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text> <paragraph id="HCFDA5D0A1D3E47868F1889B021A0ECBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to recognize the ecological, cultural, and historic diversity of the region in which the Bay is located by promoting the national significance of the Bay and surrounding areas;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H774F26DBEF434F7E8B8A69FB9EC85422"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to conserve and protect the significant natural, recreational, historical, and cultural resources relating to the Bay;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5153728593DD4700909FF04C0B04A0F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to facilitate public access to the Bay for—</text>
<subparagraph id="H280832B6789449A68E76C689C6ADC9A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recreation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD20E88EBCA7444CE9D6AFA6B8E6D81A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>public enjoyment; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H11FABEDB98674453879CF27FDAB42090"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the enhancement of sustainable tourism that respects the health of the Bay;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FBBC18FB97E49DCA97E8B4AD4139FBD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to encourage engagement and cooperation with communities that neighbor the Bay and communities that include historically underserved and underrepresented populations that have traditionally lacked access to the Bay;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE59F98E58C6148408A543B4366AB1721"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to promote diversity, equity, and inclusion with respect to the Bay by emphasizing the vital economic, cultural, and ecological contributions of historic and current populations, including, at a minimum, by providing educational and interpretive services to increase public understanding of, and appreciation for—</text> <subparagraph id="H9735934A6E31435491889C0AE7B6B407"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the natural, historical, and cultural resources of the Bay; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD99B9F5E730748BBB0756DE5B0D79C36"><enum>(B)</enum><text>traditional practices of the individuals whose livelihoods have been dependent on the land and water resources of the Bay and the surrounding area;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAFE6A4E60D6C4BC7BB238D90BE359C60"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to facilitate the cooperative management and stewardship of the resources of the Bay; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB8627F3267494C8FAB140E50EAA3EF58"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to advance the conservation goals of Chesapeake Gateways and the Bay Program.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H0626F461D21F4019A5B494EE6B6B91ED"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment and boundaries of Chesapeake National Recreation Area</header> <subsection id="H2ABE1B34D6A34E60848C520D24B07916"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>To preserve, protect, interpret, and provide for the public enjoyment of the resources relating to the Bay and surrounding areas, there is established as a unit of the National Park System the Chesapeake National Recreation Area.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H93EDC1A6762944ACA6299547D4F605D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Boundary</header><text>The boundary of the Recreation Area shall be the boundary as depicted on the Map. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H4DADA95DA3534F989C6A09EBEBF38D94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administrative, interpretive, and visitor service sites</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of the establishment of the Recreation Area, the Secretary shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H22CC9C8CEAC042DB9FB1CCFAC15D3988"><enum>(1)</enum><text>seek to enter into a cooperative agreement for administrative, interpretive, and visitor service uses for the Recreation Area under section 8(a) or a partner site agreement under section 8(b) with the City of Annapolis, Maryland, for the use of the Burtis House;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1A0252D59064AE9B0F90A6C82F98AAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>acquire, lease, or enter into a cooperative management agreement with respect to real property for an additional administrative, interpretive, and visitor services center for the Recreation Area, which shall be located within or in the environs of the historic downtown area of the City of Annapolis, Maryland; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H75A0F94F39F74D5C8F73F13FF8453F40"><enum>(3)</enum><text>acquire, lease, or enter into a cooperative management agreement with respect to real property for an additional interpretive and visitor services center for the Recreation Area, which shall be located within or in the environs of Fort Monroe. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2E61217C37E44217997D87E2E9369636"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text>The Map shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE9CB6E3E9A564D6EA0FD7F9C23A26B3A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Revision of fort monroe national monument boundary</header>
<paragraph id="H2FE38ECD1EE341EE8DB59E7944B79A8A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The boundary of Fort Monroe National Monument, established by Proclamation 8750, dated November 1, 2011 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/54/320301">54 U.S.C. 320301</external-xref> note; 76 Fed. Reg. 68625), is revised to exclude all land and interests in land within the North Beach area of the Monument (as in existence on the day before the date of enactment of this Act) that are identified on the Map as part of the Recreation Area.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE03592CB5573421E80BE2DD85AFC60AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>Any reference in any law, regulation, document, record, map, or other paper of the United States to the land or interests in land described in paragraph (1) shall be considered to be a reference to the Recreation Area.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H41F9953570DC45F894A69A160E0EBF35"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transfer of administrative jurisdiction</header>
<subparagraph id="H1B4C133D38004DD0A70AF6F453CBBFF5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B) and until the date on which administrative jurisdiction over the land and interests in land are transferred to the Secretary, the Secretary of the Army shall continue to administer the land and interests in land described in paragraph (1) that were under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Army as of the day before the date of enactment of this Act in accordance with—</text> <clause id="H0F797AD15F164D91A173AC28DD781230"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the memorandum of agreement between the Secretary of the Army and the Secretary dated December 9, 2016; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HDB7EC629BA2442E3BF983B0943923CA3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC9C03FD245A347C5A408C4E68CD712E2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Secretary of the Army shall—</text>
<clause id="H16C4DB950FB9405EB0EB21D614E44EA9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consult with the Secretary; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6FA7CECD481C48C89A6B47234EECF286"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>administer the land and interests in land described in paragraph (1) in a manner consistent with this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HDF0B1202A1544574AC3193FBBFA8571E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Acquisition of land for the Chesapeake National Recreation Area</header>
<subsection id="HBB7D0FCF35C34F989376FBAD3C75F1E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Within boundary</header><text>Subject to subsection (c), the Secretary may acquire land or interests in land within the boundary of the Recreation Area only by—</text> <paragraph id="H4694D8CACABE43098D46FCE6D4EA974B"><enum>(1)</enum><text> donation; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE09678AA5E74BF4A44D965FD535DDF8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase from a willing seller with donated or appropriated funds;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H398E697F41394A3DA64798D09D58C285"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exchange; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7189FC62A4784C7EA96B3F46923323F9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>transfer from another Federal agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H51BA6444C899437AAA23B0CF860B07F9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Outside boundary</header> <paragraph id="HB10D492EBEDB4FCA820A35F205500E91"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subsection (c), the Secretary may acquire, using the methods described in subsection (a), land or interests in land located outside the boundary of the Recreation Area, in consultation with the Advisory Commission as described in section 11(b)(2)(B).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB38AA692F08843B7BCEEAB8D19B3201A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion in Recreation area</header><text>On acquisition of land or an interest in land under paragraph (1), the boundary of the Recreation Area shall be modified to reflect the acquisition.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H000AB4FC20D141269D6045ED502BE24A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Any land or interest in land owned by a State or a political subdivision of a State that is within the boundary of the Recreation Area or described in subsection (b)(1) may be acquired only by donation. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFA2DCBBEABAA4B63B9F01AC20F26C8EC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Condemnation</header><text>No land or interest in land may be acquired for the Recreation Area by condemnation unless the owner of the applicable land or interest in land consents to the condemnation. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HE570CD6490D14FE0A90FED768982FB52"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Environmental quality standards</header><text>Prior to the acquisition of land or an interest in land under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that the land or interest in land meets all applicable environmental quality standards.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H34AE37E6CBDF4C6CA3F701AFA5B410EB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Boundary adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As the Secretary determines to be necessary, the Secretary may make minor revisions of the boundary of the Recreation Area by publishing a revised map or other boundary description in the Federal Register.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H97EBC10202734C9AA57C57CFDCC9E92C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Acquisition of land-based resources for the Chesapeake National Recreation Area</header> <subsection id="H6A58080056604A8794D9E7FCE41A0BC5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subsection (b), the Secretary may acquire land-based resources, including associated docks, piers, and structures extending into adjacent waters, within the boundary of the Recreation Area only by—</text>
<paragraph id="H431740A4BFEB4B28BF8D128972527D24"><enum>(1)</enum><text> donation; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D5C45BEE9DB43A2BCC8B9253B1B2A84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase from a willing seller with donated or appropriated funds;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9DA607A7D8164E24B8BB111083FFBD59"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exchange; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCC3ACED7289407F97F5805BADB8E781"><enum>(4)</enum><text>transfer from another Federal agency.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFA18302DEA8146C6B72B1C092292FF14"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Environmental quality standards</header><text>Prior to the acquisition of a land-based resource under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that the land-based resource meets all applicable environmental quality standards.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H532D7F5939714169840A06E2A7729FA5"><enum>7.</enum><header>Administration</header> <subsection id="H9551C01A897E4AF6AFC04E1680F52978"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall administer the Recreation Area in accordance with—</text>
<paragraph id="H190DE7569ACC442D9A38C2161508E4F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>this section; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26086AC114F04C8C989F62A0540D32C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text> the laws generally applicable to units of the National Park System, including title 54, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HBAA27618606D4B348946282CF1B60201"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Headquarters</header><text>To facilitate coordination of the Recreation Area with Chesapeake Gateways and the Bay Program, the headquarters of the Recreation Area shall be located at the Chesapeake Bay Office of the National Park Service of the Department of the Interior.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H93F83D17CFB34583A56142453CFBBB71"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Commercial and recreational fishing</header><text>Nothing in this Act impacts or otherwise affects statutory or regulatory authority with respect to navigation or regulation of commercial or recreational fishing activities or shellfish aquaculture in the Chesapeake Bay or tributaries of the Chesapeake Bay.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8D380DC2248C4477892B272802A3A026"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State jurisdiction</header><text>Nothing in this Act enlarges or diminishes the jurisdiction of a State, including the jurisdiction or authority of a State with respect to fish and wildlife management.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H599AA841F9154EF3B7E80E4BA25E6CDA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header> <paragraph id="H07A13DE75C5346B989AE0D149E6F05A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Consistent with the purposes of the Recreation Area, the Secretary shall seek to coordinate the programming and management of activities of the Recreation Area with the goals of Chesapeake Gateways and the Chesapeake Bay Agreement (as defined in section 117(a) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1267">33 U.S.C. 1267(a)</external-xref>)). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA424F83D28B04A7EA6DE93BEC752D30C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination with National Park Service Sites and partner sites</header><text>As a component of the management plan required under section 10, the Secretary shall, to the maximum extent practicable, coordinate the development of an implementation plan for onsite interpretation of resources and other means of enhancing public understanding of the Bay at participating National Park Service sites and partner sites to tell the story of the outstanding, remarkable, and nationally significant resources of the Bay.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDB30031873FC404AA9BCD1424A991ABF"><enum>8.</enum><header>Agreements and matching funds</header> <subsection id="H378DA610DCCC4CD69624E6495EBDDB34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header> <paragraph id="H0F70136FF58F4A43A745AE57C8799BA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To accomplish the purposes of the Recreation Area, the Secretary may enter into cooperative agreements with a State, a political subdivision of a State, an educational institution, a Tribal government, a nonprofit organization, or other interested party that contributes to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4455BEB88AAD4D1DB06595F8DF4950EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development of the Recreation Area; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD41531CC909B4BB4A91E7E68355C09CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the implementation of the management plan for the Recreation Area prepared under section 10(a). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5767C3EBD17E4704827B473D75CAE50D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matching funds</header>
<subparagraph id="H60CBE6B712AB4C14B76FC8AE0BBED212"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall require that any Federal funds made available under an agreement entered into under paragraph (1) shall be matched on a 1-to-1 basis by non-Federal funds.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2DF37082F8D43C896609A6C0C5B6217"><enum>(B)</enum><header>In-kind contribution</header><text>With the approval of the Secretary, the non-Federal share required under subparagraph (A) may be in the form of property, goods, or services from a non-Federal source, fairly valued. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2509C03EC3954A6AA74ADB275491917E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Nothing in this subsection affects any existing cooperative agreement authority applicable to Chesapeake Gateways.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC59FBEA7DFAD4C529C677D80BFD71EF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Partner site agreements</header> <paragraph id="H2143B9DA012A461F9DFB64E690772F64"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, under such terms and conditions as the Secretary considers to be appropriate, may enter into a partner site agreement with an eligible entity described in paragraph (2) that owns or manages an eligible site described in paragraph (3), which shall provide for the inclusion of the partner site in the Recreation Area.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H072E443FCBE146BA9FF23BF7140247A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Description of eligible entity</header><text>An eligible entity referred to in paragraph (1) is—</text> <subparagraph id="HFBE626BBBB884F22AD86D65D5C2D0475"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Federal entity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9F8A08F547504FD79208369A152BF429"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State or local government; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2A53E4E85D614DF1BB50E9279FAA16E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a Tribal government;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB4540A4DD5947FFB5E588F2066DC045"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a private nonprofit organization; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA02EBA7718C4B278663633794235E76"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a private landowner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H88256442E6F443B8B984BE7888A690B3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Description of eligible site</header><text>An eligible site referred to in paragraph (1) is land that the Secretary has determined—</text> <subparagraph id="H83F79178163242518B769DC4FF833225"><enum>(A)</enum><text>contains a nationally significant natural, recreational, historical, or cultural resource;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA8349B67C0C3490A95441000C215429C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensures public access to the applicable resource; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2B618A23D39E46C997445B2A2FC721D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>meaningfully contributes to the purposes of the Recreation Area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC9408FF94CAB40B99F71F050183A30B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Criteria for inclusion in the recreation area</header><text>On the establishment of the Advisory Commission, the Secretary shall, establish any additional criteria for inclusion of partner sites in the Recreation Area, taking into consideration the recommendations of the Advisory Commission under section 11(b)(2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAC2FB17E2BAA4EFB8435AEC7B2AC5CCF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Cooperative management of partner sites</header><text>Under a partner site agreement entered into paragraph (1), the Secretary may acquire from, and provide to, the owner or manager of the partner site goods and services to be used in the cooperative management of the applicable partner site.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4707999793B2421A8FA187E2FB1C138B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>The Secretary may not transfer administrative responsibilities for the Recreation Area to the owner or operator of a partner site.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H488A3A3A7EDE42609B97883F4CD6A328"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Terms and conditions of agreements</header><text>Any agreement entered into under subsection (a) or (b) may include any terms and conditions that are determined to be necessary by the Secretary to ensure that—</text>
<paragraph id="HE4BF40E7DB8E4790A1F066547186D78F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of an agreement relating to a partner site, the partner site complies with the terms and conditions of the applicable agreement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA761378B5F64641B5B4353C293AA29C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary has the right of access at all reasonable times, and as specified in the applicable agreement, to all public portions of the properties covered by the agreement or grant for the purposes of—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBFE67120161E40178A7D6DFC6AEDA06B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducting visitors through the properties or providing public recreational access;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74A9BF3957964F8789C6EA1D7BF51555"><enum>(B)</enum><text>interpreting the properties for the public; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA56CC216001347EB8294AB2EA2FCB04E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>research, inventory, monitoring, and resource management;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF733036D80FC47ACA41279369F4E8668"><enum>(3)</enum><text>no changes or alterations may be made to any properties covered by an agreement entered into under subsection (a) or (b) unless the Secretary and the other party to the agreement agree to the changes or alterations; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9502D319743F41E6AE6040F40236F498"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any conversion, use, or disposal of a project for purposes contrary to the purposes of this Act, as determined by the Secretary, shall entitle the United States to reimbursement in an amount equal to the greater of—</text> <subparagraph id="HDC01A96382694425A3C65448115B148A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amounts made available to the project by the United States; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3A9A57E2D5A946A4B270BF3B50EF9448"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the portion of the increased value of the project attributable to the amounts made available under this subsection, as determined at the time of the conversion or disposal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA44EC88F21334297BC2D93D170CF1B43"><enum>9.</enum><header>Chesapeake gateways</header> <subsection id="HCC587FD0F4AB4B71A55B3508E7C66DCB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary (acting through the Superintendent of the Chesapeake Bay Office of the National Park Service) shall administer Chesapeake Gateways in coordination with the Recreation Area.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H594ECA8AD9984589B82C4FC867C79A69"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Permanent authorization</header><text>Section 502(c) of the Chesapeake Bay Initiative Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/54/320101">54 U.S.C. 320101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/312">Public Law 105–312</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>to carry out this section $3,000,000</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>to carry out activities authorized under this section $6,000,000 for each fiscal year.</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H68BE7DA157FE4C90BFF08412F2AFD3C4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Nothing in this section or an amendment made by this section modifies the eligibility criteria developed under section 502(b)(2) of the Chesapeake Bay Initiative Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/54/320101">54 U.S.C. 320101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/312">Public Law 105–312</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HB13CC125847547BDB67DD3216B45F544"><enum>10.</enum><header>Management plan</header>
<subsection id="HCA6EDD3BCF334D3EB53D284ECB901D53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date on which funds are first made available for the preparation of a management plan for the Recreation Area, the Secretary, in consultation with the Chesapeake Executive Council (as defined in section 117(a) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1267">33 U.S.C. 1267(a)</external-xref>)) and the Advisory Commission, shall prepare a management plan for the Recreation Area, in accordance with—</text> <paragraph id="H6E6BF74840CF4DCFB183DF0B5A61CA05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 7(e)(2); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2179413AC340424582854023C2B12888"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 100502 of title 54, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H42553140A1D84E2C954EA846FABB9466"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transportation planning</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59F07588473141628CBC1E47E92ADB24"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial sites</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Transportation and State transportation agencies, shall conduct transportation planning in accordance with section 100502(3) of title 54, United States Code, with respect to the initial sites depicted on the Map, to minimize traffic burden on the surrounding community by—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0B363A84B41D4ACB8DB15E9D6F94CE53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing an evaluation of the transportation systems needs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C36F4A76EE44F0EBDEBB05EB6B3A492"><enum>(B)</enum><text>using strategies to effectively manage the transportation system;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE14558EEDEAB47519CDDF0C2547CC197"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subject to section 7(c), prioritizing water and trail access to Recreation Area sites; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2C18E456CB9E42F6926117C820DB0982"><enum>(D)</enum><text>collecting community feedback on traffic.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3AAD8242FCF64829836A018142F162AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Future sites</header><text>The Secretary may, in accordance with paragraph (1), conduct additional transportation planning, as determined to be necessary by the Secretary, for any future sites included in the Recreation Area.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7A4CEE28D7CC4CD0B17AFDD7D2F78D2A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cost share</header><text>The management plan prepared under subsection (a) shall address costs to be shared by the Secretary and partner sites for necessary capital improvements to, and maintenance and operations of, the Recreation Area.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA1E788185D00489D9C8EDE2FD4D7BFB6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Submission to congress</header><text>On completion of the management plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit the management plan to—</text> <paragraph id="H4BB40D4023AC416CAA9DA5D7831DD607"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF618BE4F930046F9B21534DCC15D9F40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H132C3701652F4C8D8D4B600FCFFC9F70"><enum>11.</enum><header>Chesapeake national recreation area advisory commission</header> <subsection id="H44527568345F4106B1CD230AC4BB6F2E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish an advisory commission, to be known as the <quote>Chesapeake National Recreation Area Advisory Commission</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H6C8A1E0D0D714259B60B89988F9A2AE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Commission shall—</text> <paragraph id="HBA99E855ABDD473487B74FEF0705F00F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advise the Secretary on the development and implementation of the management plan required under section 10; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15F1649A1B404AA196F6275A4FBB2C3B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>after consultation with the States and other interested parties, recommend to the Secretary criteria and specific recommendations on the Bay for—</text> <subparagraph id="HB38F10ED5AA94173BFA0600A503A6B32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>partner sites; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAAC454A9262F438B875CD1507B8538EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>properties to be added to the boundary of the Recreation Area to be managed by the Secretary, including properties located outside of the existing boundaries of the Recreation Area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H386872CB8312442399AC855D9B3954EB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, the Advisory Commission shall be subject to—</text>
<paragraph id="H1A8C522D3B3A478A92581B95A9216118"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) (except section 14(b) of that Act); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H62151AE26B214EA7894CD48A3E977E3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>all other applicable laws (including regulations).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC97C7B5066FB4C5C9890CB65D283D1CD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<paragraph id="H1E45335CBFE94612A1634C6480D9A144"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Advisory Commission shall be composed of 19 members, appointed by the Secretary, of whom—</text> <subparagraph id="H9F770091E25849EEBCB073A7C60CB139"><enum>(A)</enum><text>9 shall be appointed to represent the State of Maryland, of whom—</text>
<clause id="HD64E37D5A24D4FED9F66AFEE479FEF2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>4 shall have knowledge of environmental, recreational, cultural or historic resources, environmental justice, grassroots organizing, education, or interpretation;</text></clause> <clause id="H5CF7ABC1AAE1405497FE6D210A6FA77E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall represent commercial fishing interests on the Bay;</text></clause>
<clause id="H9A774358A89940EB807F327623FDEB76"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>1 shall represent agricultural interests in the watershed of the Bay;</text></clause> <clause id="H1A6E0DDFF30447C0856752DA42A55212"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>1 shall be a youth representative;</text></clause>
<clause id="H9E3A6EA8736445C9ACE96D2E5B94971C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>1 shall be selected from among individuals recommended by the Governor of the State of Maryland; and</text></clause> <clause id="H2A42D29A54054812AD503A29539D240A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>1 shall be a representative of a federally recognized Indian Tribe or State-recognized Indian Tribe that is traditionally associated with the Bay;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0D9FA5FE76A449B5A0681F212F0844A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>9 shall be appointed to represent the Commonwealth of Virginia, of whom—</text> <clause id="H34A47C0E84EA404EB6CE0CFAD8CDAC57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>4 shall have knowledge of environmental, recreational, cultural or historic resources, environmental justice, grassroots organizing, education, or interpretation;</text></clause>
<clause id="H8388B51293BF41EBA21BCCC0814BEB4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall represent commercial fishing interests on the Bay;</text></clause> <clause id="H30DB85DF63574D3AB08D6E956B1870C0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>1 shall represent agricultural interests in the watershed of the Bay;</text></clause>
<clause id="H56451BD8F0194919B6ED73388401D67D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>1 shall be a youth representative;</text></clause> <clause id="HEC670D095CCD419696E708DAADF44BE5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>1 shall be selected from among individuals recommended by the Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H77D33D4FAF1C4157956DC100CE94ED5B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>1 shall be a representative of a federally recognized Indian Tribe or State-recognized Indian Tribe that is traditionally associated with the Bay; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4AF093E3692645EA8DE55CED88A9BEB8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 shall be the Executive Director of the Chesapeake Bay Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1E9D8A5D275949AD95C9DEF6C2264E38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In appointing the members described in subparagraphs (A)(i) and (B)(i) of paragraph (1), the Secretary shall seek to ensure the broadest practicable representation of the areas of knowledge described in those subparagraphs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2D277A1A4F0147879F78C345C06DFAEA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Terms</header> <paragraph id="H58F15A38A20F483890BCDC0E82BB1CCC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A member of the Advisory Commission shall be appointed for a term of 3 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05E8509FB4324682A66D6A6103555D30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Succession and reappointment</header><text>On expiration of the term of a member of the Advisory Commission, the member—</text> <subparagraph id="H8B69865E5729457F83D014D82A1EBFFF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall continue to serve until a successor is appointed; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H531FF35881DA4CDDBA1977F0C9B01877"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be reappointed to serve an additional 3-year term.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HADD79C36220D4183A5EEFB5278C3F36A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy on the Advisory Commission shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2BA0BCF4E22E4232AA7A9DBBE14F06EE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Elected positions</header>
<paragraph id="HA3B908CE45A845B192BD717B4BFDDF43"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Advisory Commission shall have a Chairperson who shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H84E0452E94F94695A148707C4818CE8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be elected by the Advisory Commission; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H169FB49352CE4AF9BBC76BE26A0CA062"><enum>(B)</enum><text>serve for a term of 1 year, unless reelected pursuant to procedures established by the Advisory Commission under subsection (h)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3BD07ADCB7B498AB04092F5B4E4B539"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vice chairperson</header><text>The Advisory Commission shall have a Vice Chairperson who shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB39316ED542E4875928B1FAD52C8FD9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be elected by the Advisory Commission;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H15A45C180EB147AC8A83DFE2D357DF82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>serve for a term of 1 year, unless reelected pursuant to procedures established by the Advisory Commission under subsection (h)(1); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE56DFD526CEB430A8194017417756451"><enum>(C)</enum><text>serve as Chairperson in the absence of the Chairperson.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H57D028A4033348E7BF5909539120D8D9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Other positions</header><text>The Advisory Commission may establish other positions and elect members to serve in those positions as the Advisory Commission determines to be appropriate, subject to subsection (h).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8C354AC350C54767B49682C6B86EA7AB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Procedures</header>
<paragraph id="H883A13C1E815408DB77D2B1B8A8A153D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraphs (2) through (6) and any applicable laws (including regulations), the Advisory Commission may establish such rules and procedures for conducting the affairs of the Advisory Commission as the Advisory Commission determines to be necessary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D0C62983522416C880329D79A58B856"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Advisory Commission shall meet at the call of—</text>
<subparagraph id="HFDB4D66BDABC43D8AD6B8C09E4080337"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Chairperson; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF785AC43195142F8ACB4D1955E88551C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a majority of the appointed members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H048C3E2EFCB64D58BF42F0EACE2286A2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A quorum shall consist of not less than 11 of the members of the Advisory Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H075A7CECD23C469F89EA9D7CF2545AB5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Actions of the advisory commission</header><text>Any action of the Advisory Commission shall require a majority vote of the members present at any meeting.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5A0368F160D44700A93450ED7598C608"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Virtual meetings</header>
<subparagraph id="HD54B8EDB437A4DBF83DAFCFFE37EFA2F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Meetings of the Advisory Commission may be conducted virtually, in whole or in part.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEBCBA26F87A0470EA8F632444801DDB4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Request</header><text>Any member of the Advisory Commission may request permission from the Chairperson of the Advisory Commission to participate virtually in—</text>
<clause id="H9263AB2289054E6F8D6FCE1737E11FE1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a meeting; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBFC0ED289DDE4FE8AF1C0BC8F3E08F01"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>all activities for that meeting.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF71D548343D04D1B90D795C3CF37C006"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Elections</header><text>Not less than <fraction>3/4</fraction> of the members of the Advisory Commission must be present, virtually or in-person, for elections carried out under subsection (g).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H324A23BB45274CDCB82FB01E504D8FD9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Advisory commission personnel matters</header> <paragraph id="HBA6F862BDD3E4376A6FCB9A4E208E13D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Compensation of members</header> <subparagraph id="HD83E6489C92A413C8747EDF7871BA0B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Members of the Advisory Commission shall serve without compensation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H53BE29ED65DF4187A2E84E487DADA886"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Members of the Advisory Commission shall be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, at rates authorized for an employee of an agency under subchapter 1 of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, while away from the home or regular place of business of the member in the performance of services for, or the duties of, the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H721AE7302B7642C2A1862B54E4467CCF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Staff</header> <subparagraph id="H569FCAB139E249B3A864A1F0120D628D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may provide the Advisory Commission with any staff or technical assistance that the Secretary, after consultation with the Advisory Commission, determines to be appropriate to enable the Advisory Commission to carry out the duties of the Advisory Commission.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D9CF2C6ECE64077A908E9021D855E91"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Detail of employees</header><text>The Secretary may accept the services of personnel detailed from a State or any political subdivision of a State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFF8DD0DBCE784008B155EE32FD870777"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination</header> <paragraph id="H930F12F9A92E49DA8B3D8FB32C60B8DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Unless extended under paragraph (2), the Advisory Commission shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB6D811AA0E09443FAB5C298A410BE203"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extension</header>
<subparagraph id="H22CDC6903873431D92D8F2232CEBE082"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Recommendation</header><text>Not later than 8 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Advisory Commission shall make a recommendation to the Secretary as to whether the Advisory Commission is still necessary to advise on the development of the Recreation Area.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46DF6153AA444187A2949FDF8798F26F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determination</header> <clause id="H7E8DCEA6975440888BEEBAE332D7DE03"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, based on a recommendation under subparagraph (A), the Secretary determines that the Advisory Commission is still necessary, the Secretary may extend the existence of the Advisory Commission for a period of not more than 10 years beyond the date described in paragraph (1).</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H120E9F990DB9466C8CB81B2549094473"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The Secretary shall make a determination to extend the existence of the Advisory Commission under clause (i) not later than 180 days before the date described in paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2A146A34B5F240448ED89A107CBB01F0"><enum>12.</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as provided in section 4(e), nothing in this Act enlarges or diminishes the authority of any official at, or transfers the administration or management of, any National Park Service site or any partner site to the Recreation Area.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

