<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8921026B0EE94151A068543C2F656E20" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2722 IH: Providing Child Care for Police Officers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2722</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230419">April 19, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To establish a grant pilot program to provide child care services for the minor children of law enforcement officers to accommodate the shift work and abnormal work hours of such officers, and to enhance recruitment and retention of such officers.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HBFFB23AEC4224B46823CECF5A1078BC3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6404E983FEF04BA2B557F81C490B49F5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providing Child Care for Police Officers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H173188F5DE9741DB9AEAF0346A86A725"><enum>2.</enum><header>Child care grant program to support law enforcement</header> <subsection id="H3920E706919546B089DC6E78F76598A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish a program to award grants to States, on a competitive basis, to assist States in providing funds to encourage the establishment and operation of child care programs to obtain child care services for the minor children of law enforcement officers during the shift work and abnormal work hours of such officers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HADC93A8C365043DE9D684FCE1D4FE2DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a State shall prepare and submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including an assurance that the funds required under subsection (e) will be provided.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4C99CF585E4945E5BDF89F71EC82C2E3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Period of grant</header><text>The Secretary shall make the grant for a period of 3 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H81E7688883B9408F961D85D0F4066C53"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Set-Aside</header><text>Of the amount appropriated to carry out this Act for a fiscal year, not less than 20 percent shall be used to make grants to eligible units of State and local government that employ fewer than 200 full-time law enforcement officers.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0BC8DB7FC4BF457F819878874AF71612"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> <paragraph id="HCAD89DCFF97D4EC7952A75AD55CFE15A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State shall use amounts provided under a grant awarded under this section to provide assistance to law enforcement agencies (or consortia formed in accordance with paragraph (3)) located in the State to enable the small businesses (or consortia) to establish and operate child care programs. Such assistance may include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H149CF339F24740829D5754E21498CF40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>technical assistance in the establishment of a child care program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE2A4DF6AB6A0487F9CAD0D20E0EA57F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assistance for the startup costs related to a child care program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA10F8F6EC3A14F988946D86178C164E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assistance for the training of child care providers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3A206FF5AE614ED19F81ACFA5814573D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>scholarships for families;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD5AE06A41FB14AAAB10C0B3163A836DF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the provision of services to care for sick children or to provide care to school-aged children;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5413BD59BA7541A38F5B7EE5AD4C6D1B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the entering into of contracts with local resource and referral organizations or local health departments;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC90CEF4C19CF4FB4AC66E29C75EC0176"><enum>(G)</enum><text>assistance for care for children with disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H226F8968ACB949419211F4D9742913B4"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assistance to maintain nonstandard hours for expanded hours of child care;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H639E323748BB4680A50EE1183FB880E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>payment of expenses for construction, renovation or operation of a child care facility, notwithstanding section 658F(b) of the CCDBG Act; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1B06C783C315498A915745E5685ED04F"><enum>(J)</enum><text>assistance for any other relevant activity determined appropriate by the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBF4904A21DFC480A92D9EEA27297C5A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>In order for a law enforcement agency or consortium to be eligible to receive assistance from a State under this section, the law enforcement agency or unit of local government involved shall prepare and submit to the State an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the State may require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF758A3512669479E879EAD2D3745C881"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>With respect to grant funds received under this section, a State may not provide in excess of $3,000,000 in assistance from such funds to any single applicant.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0834B3E4AD4D40D8A38BC1AD136495D7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a State shall provide assurances to the Secretary that, with respect to the costs to be incurred by a covered entity receiving assistance in carrying out activities under this section, the covered entity will make available (directly or through donations from public or private entities) non-Federal contributions to such costs in an amount equal to—</text> <paragraph id="HE504EF8A62AD4988B75578DB1AE70E42"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for the first fiscal year in which the covered entity receives such assistance, not less than 10 percent of such costs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H12469B95486F4649B20729C89CE08288"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for the second fiscal year in which the covered entity receives such assistance, not less than 25 percent of such costs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0724EACE1D242259FE15CD27C1BE2CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for the third fiscal year in which the covered entity receives such assistance, not less than 33<fraction>2/3</fraction> percent of such costs.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1ADB10049B474294A9C078A5FDA1E97B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Requirements of providers</header><text>To be eligible to receive assistance under a grant awarded under this section, a child care provider—</text> <paragraph id="HF2CAFE55AFBD48CE88349EBBB8DC9F54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>who receives assistance from a State shall comply with all applicable State and local licensing and regulatory requirements and all applicable health and safety standards in effect in the State; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H893D85BD7B844527A3CF7A8110361CAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>who receives assistance from an Indian tribe or tribal organization shall comply with all applicable regulatory standards.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFE15F99A55594D42A0342546EDF8DE49"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Administration</header> <paragraph id="HFE5A35F4BE364E62A5D55AFFAE89ACDA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State responsibility</header><text>A State shall have responsibility for administering a grant awarded for the State under this section and for monitoring covered entities that receive assistance under such grant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8342427ACB9C4CE1B54D53257D914332"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Audits</header><text>A State shall require each covered entity receiving assistance under the grant awarded under this section to conduct an annual audit with respect to the activities of the covered entity. Such audits shall be submitted to the State.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE284A775C39C4173B97FEAD2798C574B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Misuse of funds</header> <subparagraph id="H9897BAAABE4043898ECC82056693E4C6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Repayment</header><text>If the State determines, through an audit or otherwise, that a covered entity receiving assistance under a grant awarded under this section has misused the assistance, the State shall notify the Secretary of the misuse. The Secretary, upon such a notification, may seek from such a covered entity the repayment of an amount equal to the amount of any such misused assistance plus interest.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B6042316BF24835A4699219B874E21E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appeals process</header><text>The Secretary shall by regulation provide for an appeals process with respect to repayments under this paragraph.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H27955C8E8C054A068014A861A5C64FFF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header> <paragraph id="HE1FF98C061E14C2F9CA4C3535AE7FDB3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>2-year study</header> <subparagraph id="H4C7436CB38C54EA4BA0A89285731C8C2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Secretary first awards grants under this section, the Secretary shall conduct a study to determine—</text> 
<clause id="HA74F540B4219466CA50D8821383639AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the capacity of covered entities to meet the child care needs of communities within States;</text></clause> <clause id="H9F67F628241F4B9EA85555E03D42AB1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the kinds of consortia that are being formed with respect to child care at the local level to carry out programs funded under this section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA8D2F8007CEC46ECAD60416F453742B9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>who is using the programs funded under this section and the income levels of such individuals.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9881E3AACEC64A7F884743DD63390612"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 28 months after the date on which the Secretary first awards grants under this section, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the results of the study conducted in accordance with subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H84353DC9AF0E4EACAD025DB7A0C60A20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>4-year study</header> 
<subparagraph id="H93B9250D44B34A0598895EABD50BA456"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date on which the Secretary first awards grants under this section, the Secretary shall conduct a study to determine the number of child care facilities that are funded through covered entities that received assistance through a grant awarded under this section and that remain in operation, and the extent to which such facilities are meeting the child care needs of the individuals served by such facilities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE48D5086B86F4843BF5A2BD4F811C5D5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 52 months after the date on which the Secretary first awards grants under this section, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the results of the study conducted in accordance with subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFF95E9A703384B8BAB305BF73220C35D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HD787F7FAE9534F09890F2BB0687861DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Career law enforcement officer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term “career law enforcement officer” means a person employed by a State or local public agency on a permanent basis who is authorized by law to engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, or investigation of violations of criminal laws.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6F9B8BC94EE4594A5BDDDC00258A694"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consortia</header><text>The term <quote>consortia</quote> means a law enforcement agency and may also include a unit of local government, a child care provider, or a foundation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD42FB1D1CBC8417CAA9269CF9D2DB16F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means a law enforcement agency or a consortium formed in accordance with subsection (d)(3).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAC6D1795AC554DA0BE0E0D6098A0F167"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian community</header><text>The term <quote>Indian community</quote> means a community served by an Indian tribe or tribal organization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F2AEB398D484A6B8622D26EA98B9A46"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Indian tribe; tribal organization</header><text>The terms <quote>Indian tribe</quote> and <quote>tribal organization</quote> have the meanings given the terms in section 658P of the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858n">42 U.S.C. 9858n</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC2A251EC8B74C61B618D3A373BB614D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Law enforcement agency</header><text>The term <quote>law enforcement agency</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2503 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10533">34 U.S.C. 10533</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H604DB405AF19427780ACA3001874C724"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 658P of the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858n">42 U.S.C. 9858n</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H89DEFCC7C7B1450AAA226281954C8103"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Application to indian tribes and tribal organizations</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HCBDB2794FB2E4E3C86E1F6B848C1E484"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (f)(1), and in paragraphs (2) and (3), the term <quote>State</quote> includes an Indian tribe or tribal organization.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H39D4BBCE6C0144CAAF6421CF69DD4A33"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Geographic references</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> includes an Indian community in subsections (c) (the second and third place the term appears), (d)(1) (the second place the term appears), (d)(3)(A) (the second place the term appears), and (i)(1)(A)(i).</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H36384E69EC46455DB5952C3358278DB2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State-level activities</header><text>The term <quote>State-level activities</quote> includes activities at the tribal level.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H53E0F6D2239B47BEAFBBF5CDC414976C"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> 
<paragraph id="HC258E0A7EA574BF1969D8073F2E46D9D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section, $24,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2024 to 2028.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80194E8EA67A4B9BAA8E45048284E479"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Studies and administration</header><text>With respect to the total amount appropriated for such period in accordance with this subsection, not more than $2,500,000 of that amount may be used for expenditures related to conducting studies required under, and the administration of, this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0D699882D19342278D9472E55D165010"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Termination of program</header><text>The program established under subsection (a) shall terminate on September 30, 2028.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

