<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0195276CF6C34BA2B3492EC2E35EB3F1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1305 IH: Saving Us from Pandemic Era Resistance by Building a Unified Global Strategy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1305</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000369">Mr. Amodei</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Secretary of State, to formulate a strategy for the Federal Government to secure support from foreign countries, multilateral organizations, and other appropriate entities to facilitate the development and commercialization of qualified pandemic or epidemic products, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3F84919FDB4846319925F0272AA3AE12" style="OLC"><section id="H2F846DFE9866455CBBD8916011285312" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Saving Us from Pandemic Era Resistance by Building a Unified Global Strategy Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SUPER BUGS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB74AAD1FD83043DCBB6EA34138B40AD6"><enum>2.</enum><header>International strategy for development of qualified pandemic or epidemic products</header><subsection id="H5A8B91EE71C5427B961CBCD0BAC489C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy</header><paragraph id="H6555B20BFDA545609FD76C4B027FEF85"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall—</text><subparagraph id="HA983A4BBB815452C81BE719819559A31"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">formulate a strategy for the Federal Government to secure support from foreign countries, multilateral organizations, and other appropriate entities to facilitate the development and commercialization of qualified pandemic or epidemic products, including such products to address antimicrobial resistant pathogens—</text><clause id="H8185459EE4FB4085AF3A65294BDD972D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with pandemic potential; or</text></clause><clause id="HA7BB971E8E14407CB9C5B757609CD766"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that are priority pathogens; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE05190576B484B8387849456A5CCD0D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit such strategy to the appropriate committees of Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H28F816F27A0244E88CD485CDB06F99D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The strategy under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H77FD2EA66B854102B02141EF0FE05B9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for the process the Federal Government would use to enter into arrangements with foreign countries, multilateral organizations, and other appropriate entities in certain circumstances;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48093F266CD7426F814189B8ED859D5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strive to secure equitable contributions among participating countries, organizations, and entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09D7573CF47544568A1ED92DD1FE2AF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">focus on global priorities but allow participating countries, organizations, and entities to emphasize national or regional issues of importance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0C9CACEC5994AA280A211C2D68C2FE1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seek to ensure such arrangements are harmonized with each other and with other relevant arrangements to prevent duplication of effort and to efficiently distribute funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD40701B463B94EF2883B566AF71AF3DD"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for collaboration so as to allocate joint or individual responsibility across participating countries, organizations, and entities for the development and commercialization of particular qualified pandemic or epidemic products, where such collaboration is spelled out beforehand in such arrangements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F380F7BA79D4CD892ED125E545B5C22"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for the stewardship of qualified pandemic or epidemic products developed pursuant to the strategy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D51AD7C02184873B25184B2C218D5CE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>define criteria so that scarce funds are allocated to advance qualified pandemic or epidemic products that can achieve the greatest positive impact on human health, including unprecedented approaches to preventing, treating, and diagnosing infectious diseases;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05C873886A5D4E01A3893D3EBBE70510"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider approaches including securing contracts with the private sector, entering into public-private partnerships, implementing alternative payment models, and streamlining regulatory approval processes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF45FEA9FEF25413892276865F0DF0FE8"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be synchronized with United States pandemic preparedness priorities, such as the U.S. National Action Plan for Combating Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria (CARB).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7FD9FE223FC24E5293502B1712E5AD15"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Arrangements with foreign countries and multilateral organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall seek to enter into arrangements with foreign countries, multilateral organizations, and other appropriate entities to implement the strategy under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD3DC6FA1E0C74971B79F500815DC20C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H209F33BF739442A8B36C70557A05DE1F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>priority pathogens</term> means pathogens identified in the latest Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Antimicrobial Threats Report, the World Health Organization Global Priority Pathogens List, or a successor report or list.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75D1C7C3CFFD466FB5F75375AA5F79FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>qualified pandemic or epidemic product</term> has the meaning given to such term in section 319F–3 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6b">42 U.S.C. 247d–6b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

