<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCBEECE43B3F94AB6ABD96F1EF3F8A872" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1216 IH: Know Before You Owe Federal Student Loan Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1216</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230227">February 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To revise counseling requirements for certain borrowers of student loans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H656239BFDF17490F98B5D7AC885387B1" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HB0C63E1BDD3C47A8BC01ED78BA5E0C59"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Know Before You Owe Federal Student Loan Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC0754F9B78204B68B3B9EBEA044B53B1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pre-loan counseling and certification of loan amount</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 485(l) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1092">20 U.S.C. 1092(l)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC182616051904F69950C5F6AE2FC74E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Entrance Counseling</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Pre-Loan Counseling</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EA2F8997029499290027EA507D8B9FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A)—</text><subparagraph id="HB905E106876542CD8842E72F3D233FDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>a disbursement to a first-time borrower of a loan</quote> and inserting <quote>the first disbursement of each new loan (or the first disbursement in each award year if more than one new loan is obtained in the same award year)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FDCD8FF00084A3CB889E5DC2CFAE562"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (ii)(I), by striking <quote>an entrance counseling</quote> and inserting <quote>a counseling</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA021EF56F44F45AE9727343ADA75A200"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="H09A2807D96D444799BCA6829181EBBBD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (G) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1F443EC2DA1421DB39CB00A5BAEFB84"><subparagraph id="H6D6F681F368B40FE851F5E78BBBB4061"><enum>(G)</enum><text>An estimate of the borrower's monthly payment amount compared to the borrower's estimated monthly income after taxes, after living expenses (using Consumer Expenditure Survey data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics), after estimated health insurance costs, and after any other relevant expenses, based on—</text><clause id="H0AED9DB53D234FD8AC533CA8C4130A66"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the best available data on starting wages for the borrower's program of study, if available; and</text></clause><clause id="H854CB795E5B84E6BAE4454BC9F19544E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the estimated total student loan debt of the borrower, including—</text><subclause id="HED3D7093059545DC8D5D7BEEBFF94787"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Federal debt;</text></subclause><subclause id="H518BEE2F01EF491C8B26A4B79EDBE3AB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the best of the institution's knowledge, private loan debt already incurred; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H57114D80962C450BA9C192562D203A57"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the estimated future debt required to complete the program of study.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC67C927E52AB4AA8942A6AD6602D57E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBFFB45313AE042AC830784E18AEBBC44"><subparagraph id="HE6770A7B1CE4467A85006F9877E810D2"><enum>(L)</enum><text>A statement that the borrower should borrow the minimum amount necessary to cover expenses and that the borrower does not have to accept the full amount of loans for which the borrower is eligible.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H726F31F3967D4444AB82CD7370C68085"><enum>(M)</enum><text>A warning that the higher the borrower’s debt-to-income ratio is, the more difficulty the borrower is likely to experience in repaying the loan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0BFEAE255694C1C90CDD05BD198BC78"><enum>(N)</enum><text>Options for reducing borrowing through scholarships, reduced expenses, work-study, or other work opportunities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BF5CE444AC34E7C9760520A594AA254"><enum>(O)</enum><text>An explanation of the importance of graduating on time to avoid additional borrowing, what course load is necessary to graduate on time, and information on how adding an additional year of study impacts total indebtedness.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FDC6DE1B24D43CFB08218CD55E90CC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7CDD6A48D4114D0CAE33187D08387E7C"><paragraph id="H00EE54310FD345BA950D5A3A939D15CD"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD751B18702DF479391A39E24E98EC9BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In addition to the other requirements of this subsection and in accordance with subparagraph (B), each eligible institution shall ensure that the student manually enter, either in writing or through electronic means, the exact dollar amount of Federal Direct Loan funding under part D that such student desires to borrow.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB467AD6C28934A4BAE532FDA6FBA2B3A" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The eligible institution shall ensure that the student carries out the activity described in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H082BFE4CBECF41DB83300A3399BC587C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the course of the process used by the institution for students to accept a student loan award;</text></clause><clause id="H6B80131E6C984196AB350AB49BF19780"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prior to the institution certifying a Federal Direct Loan under part D for disbursement to a student (other than a Federal Direct Consolidation Loan or a Federal Direct PLUS loan made on behalf of a student); and</text></clause><clause id="H46F936C7505E492F8F80AEA2640D4FA3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>after ensuring that the student has completed all of the pre-loan counseling requirements under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H1AE0B3F7D50D4A2F876233F10500AAE7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required periodic disclosures during periods when loan payments are not required</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 433 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1083">20 U.S.C. 1083</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE52DA0552571451DB8F685A0F1DF1F59"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A7BF0A21B4A48B3895D2A041E5DF8EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subsection (e) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB078B130BE664C07B078648856D88E6C"><subsection id="H63326824ACC44EB38649E5E53879D4EC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Required periodic disclosures during periods when loan payments are not required</header><text>During any period of time when a borrower of one or more loans, made, insured, or guaranteed under this part or part D is not required to make a payment to an eligible lender on the borrower's loan from that eligible lender, such eligible lender shall provide such borrower with a quarterly statement that includes, in simple and understandable terms—</text><paragraph id="H572071F1829742B28718B3AE320A2C2B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the original principal amount of each of the borrower's loans, and the original principal amount of those loans in the aggregate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31788AA186DC4F18A9FB22EC78F5DF0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the borrower's current balance, as of the time of the statement, as applicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF75F07B8F18A46DCBF692BCA96AA49DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the interest rate on each loan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED2CCC30F1ED473091485242695D2871"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the total amount the borrower has paid in interest on each loan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC347CA370C1A4BEFAA16ACCC5084FC06"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the aggregate amount the borrower has paid for each loan, including the amount the borrower has paid in interest, the amount the borrower has paid in fees, and the amount the borrower has paid against the balance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69FB02F8FEF34EB688CCA315AE59971F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the lender's or loan servicer's address, toll-free phone number, and webpage for payment and billing error purposes, including information about how a borrower can make voluntary payments when a loan is not in repayment status;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EFF3D5C34B04183A70F3073D884D61B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an explanation—</text><subparagraph id="HC9D0B5CBF05B4F719EC6680F5EBAC047"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that the borrower has the option to pay the interest that accrues on each loan while the borrower is a student at an institution of higher education or during a period of deferment or forbearance, if applicable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2DFECE780D54F83A30F81D510F1ADC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the borrower does not pay such interest while attending an institution or during a period of deferment or forbearance, any accumulated interest on the loan will be capitalized when the loan goes into repayment, resulting in more interest being paid over the life of the loan;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D7832E70E3D4A56931110FCD6B60566"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the amount of interest that has accumulated since the last statement based on the typical installment time period and the aggregate interest accrued to date; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H392FFA17D29E4E7B93DED58E33DC0248"><enum>(9)</enum><text>an explanation that making even small payments of any unspecified amount while the borrower is a student at an institution of higher education, or during a period of deferment or forbearance, if applicable, can help to offset interest accrual over the life of the loan.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H0BF04F9049EC4AE3BCB143D4EC831E83"><enum>4.</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><subsection id="H7A0A771E82044BF797EE5707D900BA6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program participation agreements</header><text>Section 487(e)(2)(B)(ii)(IV) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(e)(2)(B)(ii)(IV)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBE3B410FB442455286767DB523BDC406"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Entrance and exit counseling</quote> and inserting <quote>Pre-loan and exit counseling</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBECEF88067DD48E3A98992A4E51A257A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>entrance and exit counseling</quote> and inserting <quote>pre-loan and exit counseling</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD8CB7D9628A4D72B4807148F85DB90A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulatory relief and improvement</header><text>Section 487A of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094a">20 U.S.C. 1094a</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>entrance and exit interviews</quote> and inserting <quote>pre-loan and exit interviews</quote> each place the term appears.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

