<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC5DB99FEDD7048408F7F867832532D9A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5859 IH: Transportation Assistance for Individuals with Disabilities Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5859</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish a program to provide grants to protection and advocacy systems to advocate for individuals with disabilities to access transportation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB12DA2B72B9840778BB675E09B10416D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HECC14A3BF7D44FB2B8CFDB57088081C1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transportation Assistance for Individuals with Disabilities Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H31F1AD5C527A426A94FA315A66129D33" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEE1B329C634B42DCA64CE72C650B3DFB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Transportation is significantly more difficult for Americans with disabilities. According to the Bureau of Transportation Statistics, 3.6 million Americans with travel-limiting disabilities do not leave their homes because of a lack of accessible transportation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AA3E39E71FB42EEA4903046D0F16E1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the American Association of People with Disabilities, people with disabilities are twice as likely to struggle with procuring transportation than those who are not disabled, which limits access to medical care, employment, and everyday activities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54F1599A393649228013639025C84D96"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (in this section referred to as the <quote>DD Act</quote>) assures that <quote>individuals with developmental disabilities and their families participate in the design of and have access to needed community services, individualized supports, and other forms of assistance that promote self-determination, independence, productivity, and integration and inclusion in all facets of community life</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B8A9E01AA2F4182A55FFD5D7688F630"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The DD Act requires States and territories to establish a protection and advocacy system that protects and advocates the rights of individuals with disabilities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HACC612F0554C422F8E424A7ABD21D485"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Even though the Americans with Disabilities Act requires all State and local governments to make public services accessible for people with disabilities, protection and advocacy systems continuously receive reports of ineffective and inadequate services from county and city paratransit services. These systems work to address these issues by providing legally based advocacy resources for those impacted.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H69D697B0780147F6875727E07353A7B6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2017, protection and advocacy systems received over 550 individual transportation related cases and in 2020 received over 2000 individual cases.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE259502C4FA473B92364173384EDDA3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Currently, there are 9 established protection and advocacy programs administered by several Federal agencies, including the Department of Education, the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Social Security Administration.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H851909F26FAD428687B2FB791FAEA94D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>There is currently no similar program administered by the Department of Transportation to ensure that protection and advocacy systems have dedicated funding to serve individuals who face issues related to transportation access.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HAC96986FD90640E49B0712AF5F234EBA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of grant program to improve access to transportation</header> 
<subsection id="H8D2EC0CD0CEC41AF8A85D5B101097329"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation shall establish a program to award grants to protection and advocacy systems to advocate for individuals with disabilities to access transportation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCD320919D7F249119FF8E77D02143490"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header> <paragraph id="H8F971C5DF3D9480B99F774DFA8A15162"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Award</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall select 10 protection and advocacy systems to receive a grant under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD87D8CB00AC942F7A8316A91A4F78B49"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grant term</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term of a grant awarded under this section shall be 5 fiscal years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB1E3FB22C8F149979EF5F170E6B9BE3B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>During the 5-year term of a grant awarded under this section, the Secretary shall distribute $110,000 for each fiscal year to the recipient of such grant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H058655E15E4F4874B3B3DD015B544D8F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Carryover</header><text>Any amount distributed under paragraph (3) to a grant recipient for a fiscal year that remains unobligated at the end of a such fiscal year shall remain available to such recipient for obligation during the subsequent fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC22959986C264ED18ABCC250AC130B39"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sunset; termination of grants</header> <paragraph id="H9BEDDCE7A1724E7D93E28A0AB90D175A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority of the Secretary to award grants under this section shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7B050F6C509E448BA1DC4823E6ADB152"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination of grants</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE400AA07332D4C0DB7F0875B7156CD03"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may terminate a grant awarded under this section before the end of the grant term under subsection (b)(2) if the Secretary determines there is good cause to terminate such grant, including—</text> <clause id="H75456F4087CA43838E19AD6C86A99B8E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>misuse of grant funds; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H041F3F7E1B0845348B6C1E6EDB5B41BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">redesignation of the recipient of such grant pursuant to section 143(a)(4) of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H27BBD29AF20642B5B62A2B2CF18B75DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Award of new grant</header><text>If the Secretary terminates a grant under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall award a new grant under this section to a different protection and advocacy system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4A25A675A52C4589AF4B61E5F68251BC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A protection and advocacy system that receives a grant awarded under this section shall have the same authorities, including access to records, as such system would have under subtitle C of title I of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15041">42 U.S.C. 15041 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H740685D7BD0746B781E22209E41DF147" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting the protection and advocacy systems to receive grants under this section, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H72D2365E08314DCA8375CD340916BE8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">select at least 3 protection and advocacy systems located in States in which at least 1 persistent poverty county (as defined by the Secretary of the Treasury) is located; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFAE6302D9E31410C9F572E02ABBCD03F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>select at least 3 protection and advocacy systems that are located in States in which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0F157CE993074276BC35B065C7C08C87" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the percentage of individuals aged 65 or older is greater than 18 percent; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA9359C5F73E4092AE4E69871DE55E8A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of individuals with a disability is greater than 16 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H29E21996734340F4AF536FBE14D3D889"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Each recipient of a grant under this section shall submit to an office designated by the Secretary an annual report documenting the work such grant recipient has done to address the barriers to accessing transportation for individuals with disabilities. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HC38AA5DF61984AE5901F6D055B99A9E5" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Program income</header><text>Any income generated from advocating for individuals with disabilities to access transportation with a grant under this section for a fiscal year shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9E09B9E89423415FA2F934A8226FBB0B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>remain available to the grant recipient until expended and be considered an addition to the grant; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H05A0039DF9B54CB19C57008CF8DEDC05" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>only be used to provide advocacy to enable individuals with disabilities to access transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3FD320CA065541B3993DA69B3726900D" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Training grant</header> 
<paragraph id="H8C0103A5A31A49A0B0B5A98C22E2D245" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>During each fiscal year in which a protection and advocacy system advocates for individuals with disabilities to access transportation with a grant under this section, the Secretary shall award a grant to 1 eligible organization to provide training and technical assistance to such protection and advocacy system.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29A66A666E06420E8761650113C8E7C7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each grant awarded under paragraph (1) shall be in the amount of $100,000.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H24094E037D0048B2A73DE9D76293FEC8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible organization defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>eligible organization</quote> means a national organization with extensive knowledge of protection and advocacy systems.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB399E7B11C544F5856240F6308E9E4D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this Act $1,200,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H48249CFD70D64B1ABBFA01682E70DAF0"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HF68CDB7D93324C4E8C97E965B961DF4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Protection and advocacy system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>protection and advocacy system</quote> means a protection and advocacy system established under subtitle C of title I of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15041">42 U.S.C. 15041 et seq.</external-xref>) that has—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD5D7CEF0417A4C6C87B21B7B89FF24A5" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrated monitoring experience; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H446C26905A2A427F8F464F02C3760272" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrated knowledge of accessibility barriers facing individuals with disabilities in accessing transportation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H11F0B9D431CC4129AC688D7EA49F6E3A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>State</quote> means the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

