<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H955600678B8849C780CBB986C9D3D1F4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 155 IH: Citizen Legislature Anti-Corruption Reform of Congress Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 155</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit a single bill or joint resolution presented by Congress to the President from containing multiple subjects and to require the equal application of laws to Members of Congress.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4B22F03FD37B43ADB554DAA8BC3ED267" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF6A2C979E1BB4313BE77D08B6BE4B3E6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Citizen Legislature Anti-Corruption Reform of Congress Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CLEAN Congress Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDE2E4C0ACC984F8598651CEDFF05182F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting multiple subjects in single bill</header> <subsection id="H090CD8AFCCA947A8BD27FEF6C4A42967"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each bill, order, resolution, or vote submitted by Congress to the President under section 7 of article I of the Constitution of the United States shall embrace no more than one subject, and that subject shall be clearly and descriptively expressed in the title of the bill, order, resolution or vote.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC2070CCF4124BDBA53412BEFF88978C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Subsection (a) shall apply with respect to the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress and each succeeding Congress.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE03B4FDFD7DD4F0AB0684A8676C83B1F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requiring equal application of laws to Members of Congress</header> <subsection id="H8199E3BD79FA4159BE98CB33D1D73BFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any provision of law that provides an exception in its application to a Member of Congress or an employee of the office of a Member of Congress shall have no effect.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1AF5F9726A1A45DBB07D4A5FD8CFE280"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification relating to exercise of official or representational duties</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not be construed to apply to provisions of law or rules which permit Members of Congress or employees of offices of Members of Congress to carry out official duties that are tied directly to lawmaking, including provisions or rules permitting Members and employees to enter and use the United States Capitol, the United States Capitol grounds, and other buildings and facilities.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC8732906258B4C45A3F4EAA4151DF2A7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Member of Congress</term> means a Senator or a Representative in, or Delegate or Resident Commissioner to, the Congress.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

