<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56E079EE9CA84C34A68F4F67E90C4FD4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6066 IH: HATIKVAHH Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6066</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit funding to international organizations that provide resources or other support to foreign terrorist organizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H65064F6C0893430C97A1A30001400CDF" style="OLC"><section id="H8588EB5754EE4E1CB1C625E47F3E58D0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Halting Appropriations for Terrorist-supporting Institutions that Knowingly provide Valued Assets to Hamas and Hezbollah Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>HATIKVAHH Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="HA1A75470292940D3804510FD6FBB18F5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certification</header><subsection id="H0E2BCBBE83634431BA0CD260FED6C001"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the Secretary of State shall, with respect to each international organization operating in Gaza or Judea and Samaria to which the United States Government provides funding, submit to the appropriate congressional committees a written certification of whether the organization complies with each of the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H489961D50E644C1A96F81FD98F55E5DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The organization does not provide resources or other support to a specified foreign terrorist organization or its members, directly or indirectly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF97B99ABB9C4D989F48220184196680"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The organization does not cooperate or work with a specified foreign terrorist organization or its members, directly or indirectly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8540BE1AA84D4991B18BB0805FC75937"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The organization does not employ or contract with a member of a specified foreign terrorist organization, directly or indirectly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDCF6C661FD942D9BAFD1968CB0BFAF5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The organization does not openly support or celebrate a specified foreign terrorist organization or a member of a foreign terrorist organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5397CA4B66A46D6828D468290E465AB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>No official, employee, consultant, contractor, subcontractor, representative, or affiliate of the organization—</text><subparagraph id="H002DE91997F7409EAEED37BC9B0C89BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a member of, is affiliated with, or has any ties to a specified foreign terrorist organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCED87D789E054031982A38A622D77689"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has advocated, planned, sponsored, or engaged in any terrorist activity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF06C724C8E48478AAF6B7B5C3518B62B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has called for violence against Americans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD57CD6F0B7DC419A952D87EB5FEDAA5F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>No infrastructure or resources of the organization are being used by a specified foreign terrorist organization or any member thereof—</text><subparagraph id="HAFE70FBFA0B34B3AB328CA6042616A02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for terrorist activities, such as operations, planning, training, recruitment, fundraising, indoctrination, communications, sanctuary, storage of weapons or other materials; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA039D63B37440D0B5D1C7A328883EE3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>as an access point to any underground tunnel network, or any other terrorist-related purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD97E70C771C247BB910C24EF1D67CF0B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The organization is subject to comprehensive financial audits by an internationally recognized third-party independent auditing firm that has implemented an effective system of vetting, as determined by the Secretary of the Treasury, and oversight to prevent the use, receipt, or diversion of any resources by any foreign terrorist organization or members thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08F838EBF0064210B12E54D67436FAC3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The organization does not provide funds or loans to another organization that is—</text><subparagraph id="H85704E9372E7409AAC1F728EA0CDE594"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a member of, is affiliated with, or has any ties to a specified foreign terrorist organization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8F05B680FE64BC8AFF69BE46550D5BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>otherwise engaged in terrorist activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H79D86FE0A8404D95A8B6839EBFFEF9CE"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The organization does not hold an account or other affiliations with financial institutions that the United States considers or believes to be complicit in money laundering or terrorist financing.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4608DDEAD3604513AC70997324C1708E" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notifications; suspension of funding</header><paragraph id="HDF72B134DC7549D5AAF6C33537C2E097"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of State submits a written certification to the appropriate congressional committees under subsection (a) with respect to an international organization indicating that the Secretary has determined that the organization is not complying with the requirements described in paragraphs (1) through (9) of subsection (a), the Secretary of State shall provide a written notification thereof to the organization which shall include the reasons for such determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36FE4E600B11426FB08734CE24154434"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Suspension of funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of State submits a second consecutive written certification to the appropriate congressional committees under subsection (a) with respect to an international organization described in paragraph (1) indicating that the Secretary has determined that the organization is not complying with the requirements described in paragraphs (1) through (9) of subsection (a), the United States Government shall suspend providing further assistance to the organization until such time as the Secretary submits a subsequent written certification to the appropriate congressional committees indicating that the organization is complying with such requirements.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25350199D94C4AD485CDECF149322978"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication in Federal Register</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall publish in the Federal Register a notification with respect to the suspension of funding to any international organization under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3C6D411C364249B3AC55D30FE6ED4875"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report describing the actions being taken to implement a comprehensive plan for urging other countries to withhold funds to any international organization that is prohibited from receiving funding from the United States by reason of the limitation provided for in section 2(b).</text></section><section id="HA432CC0A3F0D45CBA9B373A85F798653"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall consider each United Nations agency to be a separate international organization for purposes of applying the provisions of this Act.</text></section><section id="HA86F8E53BBED4D27B21CC32DF9098939"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text><paragraph id="HA9C891AEE7E04317BCDA93608470C8B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H62CC822C5B354821B8C7B4184F2BF11F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA56544E44E0942818087549D65D6FC6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A2D14C6058C454EAC9D990FC22EB983"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>specified foreign terrorist organization</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H05F962861F324F27A755A9CB9D998876"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hamas, Hezbollah, Palestinian Islamic Jihad, Palestine Liberation Front, Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, or the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EE1F64E36564B62B3D0770C9B197063"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other organization—</text><clause id="HF7771F70D9434473AB90EE7CCECD88F8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>designated as a foreign terrorist organization by the Secretary of State in accordance with section 219(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189(a)</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="H2AFFA27F88864BD9B1304320A20E0875"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operating in Gaza or Judea and Samaria.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

