<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3C56B61A31A74C8E87B4F9C43D2F57A7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6731 IH: Finding Orphan-disease Remedies With Antifungal Research and Development Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6731</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231212">December 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001165">Mr. McCarthy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To support endemic fungal disease research, incentivize fungal vaccine development, discover new antifungal therapies and diagnostics, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB148D06C616B41519B77CE37C383711A" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF0A8F151B0AE42A29EEC720C3A7C1825"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header> 
<subsection id="HE8E0DBB6A79A4843BC36B1A0AF8C30D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Finding Orphan-disease Remedies With Antifungal Research and Development Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FORWARD Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H99EE2700C3964D05BE13AEF518B3A0CD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF0A8F151B0AE42A29EEC720C3A7C1825">Sec. 1. Short title.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H91B209D420A144A8B3BF79274C937DC5">Sec. 2. Continuing support for research on endemic fungal diseases.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HCCB6DA7909AB4C6CA1ABB44AE3FF51D0">Sec. 3. Endemic fungal disease working group.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H3AA704F927EA4EB0856DA81EE8C866E6">Sec. 4. Expanding tropical disease product priority review voucher program to encourage prevention and treatment of coccidioidomycosis.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF7D878F87EA44CCEB9A20F6C72AE088E">Sec. 5. Combating antimicrobial resistance biopharmaceutical accelerator program.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="H91B209D420A144A8B3BF79274C937DC5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continuing support for research on endemic fungal diseases</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 447D of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/285f-5">42 U.S.C. 285f–5</external-xref>) the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17BA8133C47C4FAEAAB9BC516AF67CF9"> <section id="H173439290A6145ED9F73BF4BC2E1B205"><enum>447E.</enum><header>Endemic fungal diseases</header> <subsection id="H14B6F37584354B30A124771157C69819"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Institute shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAF95E77AB2334F47984C81D9182A032C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>continue to conduct or support basic, translational, and clinical research related to fungal diseases found in the United States, including coccidioidomycosis (commonly known as and referred to in this section as <quote>Valley Fever</quote>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D845F3039C646F7837514DCFB0D4E27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subject to the availability of appropriations, make grants to, or enter into contracts with, public or nonprofit private entities to conduct such research.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H565B5FD4FD8A45F1959950711090984B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Director of the Institute shall ensure that each triennial report under section 403 includes information on actions undertaken by the National Institutes of Health to carry out subsection (a) with respect to such fungal diseases, including coccidioidomycosis.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC599BF4A128A40748544F027418AC9E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to other amounts available for the purposes of carrying out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 for such purpose.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HCCB6DA7909AB4C6CA1ABB44AE3FF51D0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Endemic fungal disease working group</header> 
<subsection id="H3D165A196AA94198BE29C4F62691760E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a working group, to be known as the Endemic Fungal Disease Working Group (referred to in this section as the <quote>Working Group</quote>), comprised of representatives of appropriate Federal agencies and other non-Federal entities—</text> <paragraph id="H60ABF5A5F6774C61908CF76640364743"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to provide expertise and to review all efforts within the Department of Health and Human Services related to fungal disease in the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8168A854CA14BD7BA1471810470814D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to help ensure interagency coordination and minimize overlap with respect to such disease; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8F35520A0264B17B0DD05B847126CDF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to examine research priorities with respect to such disease.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB2B8840F29F2420D8580D21777CA4A46"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Working Group shall—</text> <paragraph id="HE32BDF2A980D4221A767C131C009BE5A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make recommendations to the Secretary, including an updated strategy related to development of therapeutics and vaccines for endemic fungal diseases, that shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA2B476B67AB04F95B650A0911D6BB4CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take into account ongoing fungal disease research, including for animals, that may be adapted for human use;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE894FC12DF604B1880F3845925CD2341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify gaps in endemic fungal disease research, including basic, clinical, and translational research related to the pathogenesis, prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of such diseases; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4EBFE2EE96DB449C8825FAA9108B6425"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include recommendations for congressional action to spur additional research and product development for fungal diseases; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H697EEDDB17EC4D4F9BD2B8AC907423A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in implementing this subsection, solicit input from States, Tribes, localities, and nongovernmental entities, including organizations representing patients, health care providers, researchers, and industry regarding scientific advances, research questions, and surveillance activities.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3B01608CEB074F7DA4E0788330540A67"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The members of the Working Group shall represent a diversity of scientific disciplines and shall be composed of the following members:</text> <paragraph id="HD518B5746EFF464FB2D85A4CC29C83E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal members</header><text>Seven Federal members, consisting of one or more representatives of each of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H02C04106CE694893BDD74920D40BE49C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Office of the Assistant Secretary for Health, who shall serve as Chair.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE91EF664170E4D5B80201BD5ABB9F35A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Food and Drug Administration.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBD99155473AB4170B17F9D56F40FC2D3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79DA294AE8224C22BCC0BC8CBF86F118"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The National Institutes of Health, who shall serve as Vice Chair.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H44985AD7DB784732AFC87B20EF43D286"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Such other agencies and offices of the Department of Health and Human Services as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H20A250920B954D29ABAE42920557E8CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-Federal public members</header><text>Seven non-Federal public members, consisting of representatives of the following categories:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H34A90B7DDD48426983206378A261FB5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Physicians, veterinarians, and other medical providers with experience in diagnosing and treating endemic fungal disease.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H509DC36789C847CAAAE644E1512182EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Scientists or researchers with expertise in endemic fungal disease.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98C40A1D368244EB99BDB2954432B9B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Patients who have been diagnosed with an endemic fungal disease and family members or caregivers of such patients, as applicable.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEFE48933F3E44094B042425F14DD2B0E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Nonprofit organizations that advocate for patients with respect to endemic fungal disease.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE53519583C3433EA8BCE4F31D690BED"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Other individuals whose expertise is determined by the Secretary to be beneficial to the functioning of the Working Group.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD7C9F23CFA8B4296A1DB46C762BEE59B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Working Group shall meet not less frequently than annually.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF945BE7388F4453DA2223A064E1FF945"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until termination of the Working Group pursuant to subsection (g), the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H765C49FF4BF14295A740F5ED4832774F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit a report on recommendations received under subsection (b)(1) to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19066473DAE445969E900039E8752556"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make such report publicly available on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEEBB9FB2933841A9A87D8662F5393CB3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Applicability of FACA</header><text>The Working Group shall be treated as an advisory committee subject to chapter 10 of part I of title 5, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Federal Advisory Committee Act</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H45A337119DB042FF912D3E7B62B14DEB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The Working Group under this section shall terminate 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8EA88E68DE62450084A33F16DC7143F6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Endemic fungal disease defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>endemic fungal disease</term> means blastomycosis, coccidioidomycosis, histoplasmosis, and sparotrichosis.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H3AA704F927EA4EB0856DA81EE8C866E6"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expanding tropical disease product priority review voucher program to encourage prevention and treatment of coccidioidomycosis</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 524(a)(3) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360n">21 U.S.C. 360n(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H9E4D528FB4A345A8AAB6589E6C311A88"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (S) as subparagraph (T); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB3388F4E995E42BBB6CD05D96B42E9CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (R) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD92462CA8884443A93FFFBADE1BA4514"> <subparagraph id="H4E6874E4C6E24380AAEF59FED576914F"><enum>(S)</enum><text>Coccidioidomycosis.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF7D878F87EA44CCEB9A20F6C72AE088E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Combating antimicrobial resistance biopharmaceutical accelerator program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of section 319L(c) of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 247d–7e(c)) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33744A7DE0BC4D988738C1BE1F2DC6FC"> <subparagraph id="H7DE3DD655DD044D6991A953C63DA1F0E"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Combating antimicrobial resistance biopharmaceutical accelerator program</header> <clause id="H7BF61DB1837844B799B154FFCE4ACDF1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of BARDA, shall implement strategic initiatives, to be known as the Combating Antimicrobial Resistance Biopharmaceutical Accelerator Program, including by building on existing programs and by awarding contracts, grants, and cooperative agreements, or entering into other transactions—</text> 
<subclause id="HC4F075BCCBE54505B19CE8A6AB21C144"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to optimize the use of antimicrobials in human health settings;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5E65EA23F45248FAB22EBADE55F23960"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to support innovative candidate products in preclinical and clinical development that reduce antimicrobial resistance; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3D3D4437B4B34C0CBC3CB41A2D1A9051"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to support research with respect to infection prevention and control to slow the spread of resistant bacteria, fungi, and viruses.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H47EB07137B104F568B6CAB37ACD15C4C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>References</header><text>Except as otherwise specified, any reference to the Combating Antibiotic Resistant Bacteria Biopharmaceutical Accelerator or the CARB-X program in any statute, Executive order, rule, regulation, directive, or other Federal document is deemed to be a reference to the Combating Antimicrobial Resistance Biopharmaceutical Accelerator Program under this subparagraph.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBFAB7ABF9C0746308078D29F35A9E2F1"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> 
<subclause id="H0E319410ADA5433894A3120D1C00DF9B"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To carry out the program under clause (i), there is authorized to be appropriated $500,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF575E5FB311149D6BAE5E6838AC0BC45"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Of the amounts made available to carry out the program under clause (i) for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, not less than 20 percent shall be used to support antifungal product development.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

