<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4665289FC06546CD8C989A989C7580D2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>105 HR 6146 IH: No CCP Consultants Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6146</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit certain contractors who have previously consulted for certain foreign entities or who fail to make disclosures relating to conflicts of interest that relate to national security or foreign policy from receiving contracts from the Department of State, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCF447C6893EE4758B09F937065DF413E" style="OLC"><section id="H0FC09BB45C7B477195AF7DE6767F0BF0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No CCP Consultants Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7786487034D74AE0BB03786A851E2070"><enum>2.</enum><header>Organizational conflict of interests relating to national security and foreign policy</header><subsection id="H9BD81BBCC786411993CA9AC5A41E0CC4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition related certain contracts or grants</header><paragraph id="H6B1FE88715D04FF59F02C01637A40116"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may not, after the date of the enactment of this Act, enter into, renew, or extend a contract with, or award a grant to, a covered consultancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB0FB3D48525464DA4473229150AB558"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure</header><text>Any individual or entity that submits an offer or bid for a contract to provide consulting services to the Department of State shall disclose in such offer or bid any information relevant to the individual or entity with respect to the prohibition under paragraph (1), including—</text><subparagraph id="H9C6EA686A2A1489B8625902D30C3C413"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether the individual or entity has entered into a contract with, or received grants or other financial awards from a covered entity in the five years prior to submitting the offer or bid; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94A3A4D5BF9B47D2985B41BA612DF94B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at the time the contract to provide consulting services to the Department will be entered into, whether—</text><clause id="HD86F5CAC64D949C9B370351EB2A5920E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any contract entered into by the individual or entity with a covered entity will still be in effect; and</text></clause><clause id="H1D86E886948F407BBEF3E8DF310F04FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the individual or entity will be receiving funds from, or have any unobligated or unexpended funds received under, any grant or other financial award from a covered entity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9587A4FED88C49C08B80C83B4278AC28"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Penalties</header><subparagraph id="H7FB2D2CC33284E9D956FF0BF9433D361"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a contractor of the Department failed to make the disclosure required by paragraph (2), the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H108EC6AC2C204367B2B3B2DD8837BEC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>terminate the applicable contract for cause; and</text></clause><clause id="H072964670E064765B944188F69325600"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>initiate a suspension and debarment proceeding with respect to the contractor.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H533D7C704A0543A3AEA9E957580669C6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum length of debarment</header><text>The maximum length of debarment of a contractor under this paragraph shall be a period of 5 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26A7C9BDA7A24DC9B9DC24D07056EBD2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><paragraph id="H7EA52B7719044A5EA94E02CCBD02CC67"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After a determination by the Secretary that a company is a covered consultancy, such company may submit to the Secretary a written and signed certification that—</text><subparagraph id="H39C581FF91B44C9FB6DAFC9F5D895FC0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the consultancy is no longer—</text><clause id="H6B959FE3C3704DDE8E571CF8C29D5419"><enum>(i)</enum><text>performing under a contract with a covered entity;</text></clause><clause id="H5E68BDB83E7943BC8180544E63A7BD89"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carrying out activities under a grant received from a covered entity; or</text></clause><clause id="H655233CC1B034DAFA32965943FFC08B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>receiving funds, or have any unobligated or unexpended funds received from a covered entity; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4839EA7AF2E942F09BAA5885B03D89E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>will not receive or pursue a contract with a covered entity or a grant or other financial award from a covered entity—</text><clause id="H205D3AEC94AB4C8BAA1547A636A9EB15"><enum>(i)</enum><text>during the term of a contract with the Department of State; or</text></clause><clause id="H23B446501F414EF7B7A5C78DE9511312"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>while receiving funds from the Department of State or obligating or expending any such funds.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H913B37A047CB4A6EADCE68B321088940"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Status change</header><text>Upon the approval by the Secretary of a certification submitted under paragraph (1), a company is deemed to not be a covered consultancy until the expiration of the certification under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E76F5D9C9242C898D2C78355F1CF94"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expiration</header><text>A certification submitted by a company under paragraph (1) shall expire on the earlier date on which the company, after submitting such certification enters into, extends, renews, or performs under a contract with a covered entity for consulting services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA97B9EB6D4544C72955CDBDD5E791156"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Director of National Intelligence, the Attorney General, the Secretary of Defense, and the heads of such other Executive agencies (as such term is defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code) as determined appropriate by the Secretary, shall issue procurement policies for the Department of State as follows:</text><paragraph id="HDE26DEFDCCBF4210AB9DFC3A9C58AC7E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Policies to implement the prohibition under subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B29E9DC588340DA9222AFDB3F86E740"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Best practices to avoid becoming covered consultancies under this section and for covered consultancies to end their status as such.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC5CF7DF8E91494691C705CF73037B0D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A policy containing the exact provisions and terms relating to the requirements of paragraphs (2) and (3) of subsection (a) to be included in solicitations, contracts, and grants of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD21069F4EE7246F9AABF4DE60A90202A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revision of department of state acquisition regulation</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall revise the acquisition regulations of the Department of State to implement this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2A8F05131824494E8ACC29C282C598A2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF1D297475E7A4B758453DD380B3B4B6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consulting services</header><text>The term <quote>consulting services</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>advisory and assistance services</quote> in section 2.101 of the Federal Acquisition Regulation, except that—</text><subparagraph id="HA5FB3FFAA0904FDB8ADCA3A0650A394B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term does not include the services described in paragraph (3) of such section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5CC5B6F455E4B29B774085D84DC6FEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each instance of the term <quote>Federal</quote> is replaced with <quote>client</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H561A0FF2A23D45318BE73FF7D38A098A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered consultancy</header><text>The term <quote>covered consultancy</quote> means a company that, itself or any subsidiary or affiliate thereof, in immediately preceding one year period entered into, extended, renewed, or performed under a contract with a covered entity for consulting services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CC08AC922BA4B07AB1FC802CF2CC8B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF1A12CBD216B46F3BDCE2DE49BB8C4C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Government of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93E0FAF6BDF04619B74FDE9FC1478A09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Chinese Communist Party.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EAF6534B43E4EA09B8613D1DB77AE16"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The People’s Liberation Army, the Ministry of State Security, or other security service or intelligence agency of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H519F96B61A124087A5BE6FC2676376B5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any entity on the Non–SDN Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies List (NS–CMIC–List) maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury under Executive Order 14032 (86 Fed. Reg. 30145; relating to addressing the threat from securities investments that finance certain companies of the People’s Republic of China), or any successor order.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5C4FC2A61D04C4C9CD68465DA89C3D7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any Chinese military company identified by the Secretary of Defense pursuant to section 1237(b) of the Strom Thurmond National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/261">Public Law 105–261</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83E373AE58EA47B79B3DFCA378DC8707"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Any Chinese state-owned entity or other entity under the ownership, or control, directly or indirectly, of the Government of the People’s Republic of China or the Chinese Communist Party that is engaged in one or more national security industries.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB59C52206D8C417EAD8CEA6419E44C0B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Government of the Russian Federation, any Russian State-owned entity, or any entity sanctioned by the Secretary of the Treasury under Executive Order 13662 titled <quote>Blocking Property of Additional Persons Contributing to the Situation in Ukraine</quote>(79 Fed. 5 Reg. 16169).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FC8420D298D434AA4A58D96A27552E4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The government or any State-owned entity of any country if the Secretary of State determines that such government has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism pursuant to—</text><clause id="H20578765E3F247CF81D1D141C0C01977"><enum>(i)</enum><text>section 1754(c)(1)(A) of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4318">50 U.S.C. 4318(c)(1)(A)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H5FFC2B7268FA454D885BC833BFC18A2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H0F76A6CAE96C4BCBB3C9DB90307B6912"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="HB91B927C583A4193BD2BD257BD3B2E90"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other provision of law.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87D5AB867EFE40EFA22D7DF58A65D949"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Any entity included on any of the following lists maintained by the Department of Commerce—</text><clause id="H078D99D7EF38444B9B91D624AFB80A69"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Entity List set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations;</text></clause><clause id="H4DCD24EA462A4E31BF94FF0B77BFA438"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Denied Persons List as described in section 764.3(a)(2) of the Export Administration Regulations; and</text></clause><clause id="H909D839310B648069E173E308B338DEC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Unverified List set forth in Supplement No. 6 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E27B94CC4414EE4B805CA9AA9393BEF"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Military End User List set forth in Supplement No. 7 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF75D5A914B11465BABD7CD71562307BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Export administration regulations</header><text>The term <quote>Export Administration Regulations</quote> means the regulations set forth in subchapter C of chapter VII of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB28542E1CF34DD3B73C61A2D1067EA4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>National security industry</header><text>The term <quote>national security industry</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB51D9CFA0ED34E078FA716F305390653"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a military-related industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC655EB79D054C3CA90DFD0060F2E4EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>semiconductor production;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2686CE1B60C54940A2354D101BB6C626"><enum>(C)</enum><text>researching or commercializing quantum computing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E63D058121546AF88D877801A383576"><enum>(D)</enum><text>producing products or services that use artificial intelligence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45302138EA594E1294B5580411FC2895"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the biotechnology industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBE888D810E04F84B5F97B0B092F6F15"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the cybersecurity industry; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75F2D82D9F9248849DB68815212A6C18"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the mining, processing, or refining of critical minerals (as such term is defined in section 7002(a) of the Energy Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/1606">30 U.S.C. 1606(a)</external-xref>)) for use by a covered entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AF8DE429F0A42C3A56605C7C79941CC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

