<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H972E26A806D5449F9DF853CA566F43C5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3234 IH: To authorize the immediate expulsion of inadmissible aliens attempting to enter the United States by fraud or without a necessary entry document, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3234</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the immediate expulsion of inadmissible aliens attempting to enter the United States by fraud or without a necessary entry document, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD8BF647350F1418AA875B83052644C96" style="OLC"><section id="HCC61143606554380814DA93ACF2D5FB0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Temporary expulsion of inadmissible arriving aliens</header><subsection id="H8D4FEC700E2341CC8356F0CC3A734E05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during the 2-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, an immigration officer who determines that an alien who is arriving in the United States at or along the border between the United States and Mexico is inadmissible under section paragraph (6)(C) or (7) of section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>), shall, subject to sections 2 and 3, process the alien for expulsion from the United States without further hearing or review.</text></subsection><subsection id="H12A97C6A27A34F0BA5DA6E2086B4D3CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Detention pending expulsion</header><text>An alien subject to expulsion under subsection (a) shall be detained pending expulsion.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE419D59C7A6C437B9164AC2E5AA3A6AF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Countries to which aliens may be expelled</header><subsection id="H23F66BA2A90C41A4AF49209AA4B09FE0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), an alien who is processed for expulsion pursuant to section 1(a) shall be expelled to Mexico.</text></subsection><subsection id="H379184E5BBFA444AB1580FC0AFC366FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Alternative countries</header><text>If the Government of Mexico is unwilling to accept an alien subject to expulsion under section 1(a) into the territory of Mexico or if the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that expulsion to Mexico would not be in the national interest of the United States, such alien shall be expelled, as directed by the Secretary, to—</text><paragraph id="H8EB23998EA8E460AB08AC8C6C35E0794"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the country of which such alien is a citizen, subject, or national;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4CCB137DD6E4BD6B3D897218F54CFB5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the country in which such alien was born;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FFD7481DAB245B9B263B5766D0DA8E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the country in which such alien has a residence; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F9E56B600F474C8F4DAD9238CBA722"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a country with a government that will accept such alien into its territory if expulsion to each country described in paragraphs (1) through (3) is impracticable, inadvisable, or impossible.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1FBE5A7846A4D7FBD6ADA8D9BF91F30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Restriction on expulsion to a country where an alien would be threatened with persecution or torture</header><paragraph id="H51FF4643A38F48B282ABCD5BD7806F33"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding subsections (a) and (b), and except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary of Homeland Security may not expel an alien to a country if—</text><subparagraph id="HCCD73ABBFB5D4C7C9FE288D008CF2995"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the alien’s life or freedom would be threatened in such country because of such alien’s race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group or political opinion; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3668FF5FBFD405DACA25087BA374664"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there are substantial grounds for believing that such alien would be in danger of being subjected to torture if expelled to such country.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7D6ECE5AB6A42699382C7AE3934E396"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply—</text><subparagraph id="HB62ABDF32C4744BCB2D53FB7D0BACA9D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to an alien who is deportable under section 237(a)(4)(D) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)(4)(D)</external-xref>); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56663B2224484BE1A7E2BAFD23F693F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that—</text><clause id="HC8922C6F774340BF8D6E1EA425AEF7BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the alien ordered, incited, assisted, or otherwise participated in the persecution of an individual because of the individual’s race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion;</text></clause><clause id="HA7AAC29B3C554F49A58C6D5CC7BD7575"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien, having been convicted by a final judgement of a particularly serious crime, is a danger to the citizens of the United States;</text></clause><clause id="HAC786F43FC714146AC232FD5B753A625"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>there are serious reasons to believe that the alien committed a serious nonpolitical crime outside the United States before the alien arrived in the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H69DFDF3CDB9C42CDA9628F153B4E6F4A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>there are reasonable grounds to believe that the alien is a danger to the national security of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4447A9133FF9423C8CB85D2CCD2165BA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determinations</header><subparagraph id="HB4FB3F7DF10742FA886033D7EF49009C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Particularly serious crime</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (2)(B)(ii), an alien who has been convicted of an aggravated felony or felonies for which the alien has been sentenced to an aggregate term of imprisonment of not less than 5 years shall be considered to have committed a particularly serious crime. Notwithstanding the previous sentence, the Secretary of Homeland Security may determine that an alien sentenced to an aggregate term of imprisonment of less than 5 years has been convicted of a particularly serious crime. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62057A16F8484A2C8C600AA9B2875C3B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Danger to national security</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (2)(B)(iv), an alien who is described in section 237(a)(4)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)(4)(B)</external-xref>) shall be considered to be an alien with respect to whom there are reasonable grounds for regarding as a danger to the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB009F83E13FD4801BA61CD1AD412A226"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Referral to asylum officer</header><subparagraph id="H2DB35FFC79A943708F8E835500053D82"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Referral</header><text>If an alien expresses to an immigration officer a fear that such alien’s life or freedom would be threatened in the country to which such alien will be expelled or that the alien would be in danger of being subjected to torture in such country, the immigration officer shall refer the alien for an interview by an asylum officer employed in the Refugee, Asylum and International Operations Directorate of U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services for a determination pursuant to paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H047A983E98604A96B959BCBF87B795B8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Burden of proof; credibility</header><text>In determining whether an alien has demonstrated that such alien’s life or freedom would be threatened for a reason described in paragraph (1)(A) or whether the alien would be subjected to torture described in subparagraph (1)(B), the asylum officer shall—</text><clause id="HC146DB7D6D5945A8922D3B60BFAA4193"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine whether the alien has sustained the alien’s burden of proof; and </text></clause><clause id="H786DD419EB0F4F14B5D146A9E66AE153"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>make credibility determinations, in the manner described in clauses (ii) and (iii) of section 208(b)(1)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE039C3A196B7430B9AADB4C0B62A5167"><enum>3.</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><subsection id="H27AFA2F86E4C43F5B3D38022B8D7D4E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Office of Field Operations Port Director (referred to in this subsection as <quote>Director</quote>) for each land port of entry situated on the border between the United States and Mexico shall coordinate with the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection to determine the maximum number of aliens per day that the Office of Field Operations staff at such port are capable of—</text><paragraph id="HE9E7E4BF1D594C508CE835AC939264C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>safely processing through such port of entry; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B063D1A13D0418684D314AA59565976"><enum>(2)</enum><text>placing with nongovernmental organizations to provide short-term shelter and services. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35D31A4A3BB84EF5AE8F3FD72CF98B30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Strategy</header><text>At the time of a determination under subsection (a), the Director shall develop a strategy to safely and humanely identify eligible individuals in the United States, giving priority to individuals who—</text><paragraph id="HA9578474A7DE457C8712FE79F836A765"><enum>(1)</enum><text>have a disability or an acute medical condition;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1528D97770E14C4E9D3C0B0C4B0CA831"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are in need of advanced medical care that cannot be obtained in their current location; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42B3E1A830004DEFA6540F5AB8F39DFB" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>are described in section 2(c)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE52A8677DC554446BE5253C77D5CC754"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An immigration officer, after approval from the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, may, on a case-by-case basis, except an alien from expulsion based on the totality of the circumstances, including consideration of significant law enforcement officer, public safety, humanitarian, and public health interests. An alien who has been excepted from expulsion under this subsection shall be processed in accordance with the immigration laws (as defined in section 101(a)(17) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(17)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

