<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="appropriations" dms-id="H19576D7C32A2405689CA21BAABADFDF1" key="H" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5893 IH: Commerce, Justice, Science, and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5893</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000395">Mr. Rogers of Kentucky</sponsor> introduced the following bill;</action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Referred to the Committee on Appropriations, and in addition to the Committee on the Budget, for a period to subsequently determined by the speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned </action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">Making appropriations for the Departments of Commerce and Justice, Science, and Related Agencies for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2024, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H99E499D5B225432BA0705970E769CC13" style="traditional-inline" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"> 
<section display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H45B7384833E443E88059B48E80F6CD33" section-type="undesignated-section"><text>That the following sums are appropriated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2024, and for other purposes, namely:</text></section> <title id="H8EC288C9C47746A2BC830E2458B6FA46" style="appropriations"><enum>I</enum><header display-inline="no-display-inline">DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE</header><appropriations-intermediate id="H77C8E1639CD940708D505796E072D2DD"><header>International trade administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H7ADA0324A9B045F9B760DFE7A2B71AE2"><header>OPERATIONS AND ADMINISTRATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for international trade activities of the Department of Commerce provided for by law, to carry out activities associated with facilitating, attracting, and retaining business investment in the United States, and for engaging in trade promotional activities abroad, including expenses of grants and cooperative agreements for the purpose of promoting exports of United States firms, without regard to sections 3702 and 3703 of title 44, United States Code; full medical coverage for dependent members of immediate families of employees stationed overseas and employees temporarily posted overseas; travel and transportation of employees of the International Trade Administration between two points abroad, without regard to section 40118 of title 49, United States Code; employment of citizens of the United States and aliens by contract for services; rental of space abroad for periods not exceeding 10 years, and expenses of alteration, repair, or improvement; purchase or construction of temporary demountable exhibition structures for use abroad; payment of tort claims, in the manner authorized in the first paragraph of section 2672 of title 28, United States Code, when such claims arise in foreign countries; not to exceed $294,300 for official representation expenses abroad; purchase of passenger motor vehicles for official use abroad, not to exceed $45,000 per vehicle; not to exceed $325,000 for purchase of armored vehicles without regard to the general purchase price limitations; obtaining insurance on official motor vehicles; and rental of tie lines, $570,000,000, of which $85,000,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2024: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That $12,000,000 is to be derived from fees to be retained and used by the International Trade Administration, notwithstanding section 3302 of title 31, United States Code: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, of amounts provided under this heading, not less than $16,400,000 shall be for China antidumping and countervailing duty enforcement and compliance activities: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the provisions of the first sentence of section 105(f) and all of section 108(c) of the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2455">22 U.S.C. 2455(f)</external-xref> and 2458(c)) shall apply in carrying out these activities; and that for the purpose of this Act, contributions under the provisions of the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 shall include payment for assessments for services provided as part of these activities.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HA10CD9B16F474ABBBCB8EC0B1B533CBE"><header>Bureau of industry and security</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H45CCCBD9CCF945519306401C32A94DE6"><header>OPERATIONS AND ADMINISTRATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for export administration and national security activities of the Department of Commerce, including costs associated with the performance of export administration field activities both domestically and abroad; full medical coverage for dependent members of immediate families of employees stationed overseas; employment of citizens of the United States and aliens by contract for services abroad; payment of tort claims, in the manner authorized in the first paragraph of section 2672 of title 28, United States Code, when such claims arise in foreign countries; not to exceed $13,500 for official representation expenses abroad; awards of compensation to informers under the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (subtitle B of title XVII of the John S. McCain National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/232">Public Law 115–232</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 2208; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4801">50 U.S.C. 4801 et seq.</external-xref>), and as authorized by section 1(b) of the Act of June 15, 1917 (40 Stat. 223; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/401">22 U.S.C. 401(b)</external-xref>); and purchase of passenger motor vehicles for official use and motor vehicles for law enforcement use with special requirement vehicles eligible for purchase without regard to any price limitation otherwise established by law, $191,000,000, of which $76,000,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the provisions of the first sentence of section 105(f) and all of section 108(c) of the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2455">22 U.S.C. 2455(f)</external-xref> and 2458(c)) shall apply in carrying out these activities: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That payments and contributions collected and accepted for materials or services provided as part of such activities may be retained for use in covering the cost of such activities, and for providing information to the public with respect to the export administration and national security activities of the Department of Commerce and other export control programs of the United States and other governments. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HF4F1D34A18A642619A1B4728E1EDA956"><header>Economic development administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H5FF302019B6F422F99CD4E219EEADE28"><header>ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE PROGRAMS</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For grants for economic development assistance as provided by the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965, for grants authorized by sections 27 and 28 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3722">15 U.S.C. 3722</external-xref>, 3722a, 3722b, and 3723), as amended, $211,000,000 to remain available until expended, of which $50,000,000 shall be for grants under section 27 and $41,000,000 shall be for grants under section 28: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any deviation from the amounts designated for specific activities in the report accompanying this Act, or any use of deobligated balances of funds provided under this heading in previous years, shall be subject to the procedures set forth in section 505 of this Act. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H011FD6837C064302822BF8F9EF6E191B"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of administering the economic development assistance programs as provided for by law, $43,500,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That funds provided under this heading may be used to monitor projects approved pursuant to title I of the Public Works Employment Act of 1976; title II of the Trade Act of 1974; sections 27 through 30 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3722">15 U.S.C. 3722–3723</external-xref>), as amended; and the Community Emergency Drought Relief Act of 1977.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H11C77A67B2A8448B8FBB35D53C80515A"><header>Minority business development agency</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H77868E17BB95418AB38E68B3EEA89946"><header>MINORITY BUSINESS DEVELOPMENT</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Minority Business Development Agency in fostering, promoting, and developing minority business enterprises, as authorized by law, $55,000,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H8230F236BE334DA79EE2D790BF8A8630"><header>Economic and statistical analysis</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HFBD49E57177246D8902F5A79493D5EA6"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, as authorized by law, of economic and statistical analysis programs of the Department of Commerce, $116,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H298EA662919A418F9C7CD808F1D156A8"><header>Bureau of the census</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H38C78DBADAAD44AAB0204B9881F802B3"><header>CURRENT SURVEYS AND PROGRAMS</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for collecting, compiling, analyzing, preparing, and publishing statistics, provided for by law, $300,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, from amounts provided herein, funds may be used for promotion, outreach, and marketing activities. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H454E121283504FF29714794B12D1706C"><header>PERIODIC CENSUSES AND PROGRAMS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H800A6A106A6C4656B3CAA2744AAF3380"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for collecting, compiling, analyzing, preparing, and publishing statistics for periodic censuses and programs provided for by law, $1,054,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, from amounts provided herein, funds may be used for promotion, outreach, and marketing activities. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H4D37A941A5B844E0860C4B342618AB1D"><header>National telecommunications and information administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H6BF3C3932EE04F09BC6443D7208BB32D"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, as provided for by law, of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration (NTIA), $54,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic></italic><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/1535">31 U.S.C. 1535(d)</external-xref>, the Secretary of Commerce shall charge Federal agencies for costs incurred in spectrum management, analysis, operations, and related services, and such fees shall be retained and used as offsetting collections for costs of such spectrum services, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Secretary of Commerce is authorized to retain and use as offsetting collections all funds transferred, or previously transferred, from other Government agencies for all costs incurred in telecommunications research, engineering, and related activities by the Institute for Telecommunication Sciences of NTIA, in furtherance of its assigned functions under this paragraph, and such funds received from other Government agencies shall remain available until expended.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H39C7A98D0F354E02A8846AEF431287DA"><header>PUBLIC TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITIES, PLANNING AND CONSTRUCTION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the administration of prior-year grants, recoveries and unobligated balances of funds previously appropriated are available for the administration of all open grants until their expiration. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H7A5F4F651FCC4B389E66D837F430B1DD"><header>United states patent and trademark office</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H592AD94F10E742A8B8134F0806284C26"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2593B6DA9D8943E3B3711625701F3ABA"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFERS OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the United States Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO) provided for by law, including defense of suits instituted against the Under Secretary of Commerce for Intellectual Property and Director of the USPTO, $4,195,799,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the sum herein appropriated from the general fund shall be reduced as offsetting collections of fees and surcharges assessed and collected by the USPTO under any law are received during fiscal year 2024, so as to result in a fiscal year 2024 appropriation from the general fund estimated at $0: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That during fiscal year 2024, should the total amount of such offsetting collections be less than $4,195,799,000, this amount shall be reduced accordingly: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any amount received in excess of $4,195,799,000 in fiscal year 2024 and deposited in the Patent and Trademark Fee Reserve Fund shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Director of USPTO shall submit a spending plan to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate for any amounts made available by the preceding proviso and such spending plan shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any amounts reprogrammed in accordance with the preceding proviso shall be transferred to the United States Patent and Trademark Office <quote>Salaries and Expenses</quote> account: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the budget of the President submitted for fiscal year 2025 under section 1105 of title 31, United States Code, shall include within amounts provided under this heading for necessary expenses of the USPTO any increases that are expected to result from an increase promulgated through rule or regulation in offsetting collections of fees and surcharges assessed and collected by the USPTO under any law in either fiscal year 2024 or fiscal year 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That from amounts provided herein, not to exceed $13,500 shall be made available in fiscal year 2024 for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That in fiscal year 2024 from the amounts made available for <quote>Salaries and Expenses</quote> for the USPTO, the amounts necessary to pay (1) the difference between the percentage of basic pay contributed by the USPTO and employees under section 8334(a) of title 5, United States Code, and the normal cost percentage (as defined by section 8331(17) of that title) as provided by the Office of Personnel Management (OPM) for USPTO's specific use, of basic pay, of employees subject to subchapter III of chapter 83 of that title, and (2) the present value of the otherwise unfunded accruing costs, as determined by OPM for USPTO's specific use of post-retirement life insurance and post-retirement health benefits coverage for all USPTO employees who are enrolled in Federal Employees Health Benefits (FEHB) and Federal Employees Group Life Insurance (FEGLI), shall be transferred to the Civil Service Retirement and Disability Fund, the FEGLI Fund, and the Employees FEHB Fund, as appropriate, and shall be available for the authorized purposes of those accounts: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any differences between the present value factors published in OPM's yearly 300 series benefit letters and the factors that OPM provides for USPTO's specific use shall be recognized as an imputed cost on USPTO's financial statements, where applicable: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding any other provision of law, all fees and surcharges assessed and collected by USPTO are available for USPTO only pursuant to section 42(c) of title 35, United States Code, as amended by section 22 of the Leahy-Smith America Invents Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/29">Public Law 112–29</external-xref>): <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That within the amounts appropriated, $2,450,000 shall be transferred to the <quote>Office of Inspector General</quote> account for activities associated with carrying out investigations and audits related to the USPTO. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HA6A78037A95E4224A812B10B4EF46C19"><header>National institute of standards and technology</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HDB89D1911EEE4563867D5296B7AE0E3D"><header>SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNICAL RESEARCH AND SERVICES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2622F7E2CEE14B5D99E12D93D4D48C65"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), $1,019,948,000, to remain available until expended, of which not to exceed $9,000,000 may be transferred to the <quote>Working Capital Fund</quote>: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the amounts appropriated under this heading, $118,511,000 shall be for scientific and technical research projects, which shall be for the purposes, and in the amounts, specified for <quote>DOC-NIST STRS</quote> in the table entitled, <quote>Community Project Funding</quote> in the report accompanying this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the amounts made available for the projects referenced in the preceding proviso may not be transferred for any other purpose: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $5,000 shall be for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That NIST may provide local transportation for summer undergraduate research fellowship program participants. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2CC581164080443086A6FFF06CDC327E"><header>INDUSTRIAL TECHNOLOGY SERVICES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for industrial technology services, $237,000,000, to remain available until expended, of which $200,000,000 shall be for the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership, and of which $37,000,000 shall be for the Manufacturing USA Program. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H7AD56D30A45746C49173FDE40FE44236"><header>CONSTRUCTION OF RESEARCH FACILITIES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For construction of new research facilities, including architectural and engineering design, and for renovation and maintenance of existing facilities, not otherwise provided for the National Institute of Standards and Technology, as authorized by sections 13 through 15 of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278c-278e">15 U.S.C. 278c–278e</external-xref>), $220,000,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the Secretary of Commerce shall include in the budget justification materials for fiscal year 2024 that the Secretary submits to Congress in support of the Department of Commerce budget (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code) an estimate for each National Institute of Standards and Technology construction project having a total multi-year program cost of more than $5,000,000, and simultaneously the budget justification materials shall include an estimate of the budgetary requirements for each such project for each of the 5 subsequent fiscal years. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H8FD3431A4AE149CFB3A9C5CCD89040FB"><header>National oceanic and atmospheric administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HC3C7E13DAE154AEB9E04D98A8E603E72"><header>OPERATIONS, RESEARCH, AND FACILITIES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H16E62C2B2F81482EA7494314EA5B0CFA"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of activities authorized by law for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), including maintenance, operation, and hire of aircraft and vessels; pilot programs for State-led fisheries management, notwithstanding any other provision of law; grants, contracts, or other payments to nonprofit organizations for the purposes of conducting activities pursuant to cooperative agreements; and relocation of facilities, $3,726,628,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, of which, $5,000,000 is for necessary expenses of designing and deploying the near real-time monitoring and mitigation program for threatened or endangered cetaceans authorized by section 11303 of the James M. Inhofe National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1391">16 U.S.C. 1391</external-xref>): <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may not amend or withdraw the North Atlantic right whale vessel strike reduction rule contained in section 224.105 of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations, in effect in Fiscal Year 2022 until such Administrator has fulfilled the requirements of section 11303(e) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1391">16 U.S.C. 1391(e)</external-xref>): <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That fees and donations received by the National Ocean Service for the management of national marine sanctuaries may be retained and used for the salaries and expenses associated with those activities, notwithstanding section 3302 of title 31, United States Code: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That in addition, $355,081,000 shall be derived by transfer from the fund entitled <quote>Promote and Develop Fishery Products and Research Pertaining to American Fisheries</quote>, which shall only be used for fishery activities related to the Saltonstall-Kennedy Grant Program; Fisheries Data Collections, Surveys, and Assessments; Observers and Training; Fisheries Management Programs and Services; and Interjurisdictional Fisheries Grants: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $50,000,000 shall be for payment to the <quote>Department of Commerce Working Capital Fund</quote>: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the $4,104,709,000 provided for in direct obligations under this heading, $3,726,628,000 is appropriated from the general fund, $355,081,000 is provided by transfer, and $23,000,000 is derived from recoveries of prior year obligations: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amounts appropriated under this heading, $56,999,000 shall be used for Coastal Zone Management projects, which shall be for the purposes, and in the amounts, specified for <quote>DOC-NOAA CZM</quote> in the table entitled, <quote>Community Project Funding</quote> in the report accompanying this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the amounts made available for the projects referenced in the preceding proviso may not be transferred for any other purpose: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any deviation from the amounts designated for specific activities in the report accompanying this Act, or any use of deobligated balances of funds provided under this heading in previous years, shall be subject to the procedures set forth in section 505 of this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That in addition, for necessary retired pay expenses under the Retired Serviceman's Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plan, and for payments for the medical care of retired personnel and their dependents under the Dependents' Medical Care Act (10 U.S.C. ch. 55), such sums as may be necessary.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HE2EEB6CB31E84417AF59717B4BF9ECB7"><header>PROCUREMENT, ACQUISITION AND CONSTRUCTION</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HAE244F672DE84D6CB9C5D7FFAB1B2D34"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For procurement, acquisition and construction of capital assets, including alteration and modification costs, of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, $1,653,630,000, to remain available until September 30, 2026, except that funds provided for acquisition and construction of vessels and aircraft, and construction of facilities shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the $1,666,630,000 provided for in direct obligations under this heading, $1,653,630,000 is appropriated from the general fund and $13,000,000 is provided from recoveries of prior year obligations: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any deviation from the amounts designated for specific activities in the report accompanying this Act, or any use of deobligated balances of funds provided under this heading in previous years, shall be subject to the procedures set forth in section 505 of this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Secretary of Commerce shall include in budget justification materials for fiscal year 2024 that the Secretary submits to Congress in support of the Department of Commerce budget (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code) an estimate for each National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration procurement, acquisition or construction project having a total of more than $5,000,000 and simultaneously the budget justification shall include an estimate of the budgetary requirements for each such project for each of the 5 subsequent fiscal years. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H07BE4CDBA0314408A58D9A0FE74EB26B"><header>PACIFIC COASTAL SALMON RECOVERY</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses associated with the restoration of Pacific salmon populations, $65,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, of the funds provided herein, the Secretary of Commerce may issue grants to the States of Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Nevada, California, and Alaska, and to the federally recognized Tribes of the Columbia River and Pacific Coast (including Alaska), for projects necessary for conservation of salmon and steelhead populations that are listed as threatened or endangered, or that are identified by a State as at-risk to be so listed, for maintaining populations necessary for exercise of Tribal treaty fishing rights or native subsistence fishing, or for conservation of Pacific coastal salmon and steelhead habitat, based on guidelines to be developed by the Secretary of Commerce: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That all funds shall be allocated based on scientific and other merit principles and shall not be available for marketing activities: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That funds disbursed to States shall be subject to a matching requirement of funds or documented in-kind contributions of at least 33 percent of the Federal funds.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HAC5AAD306C114162A20D66C35EE7F57F"><header>FISHERMEN'S CONTINGENCY FUND</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For carrying out the provisions of title IV of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/372">Public Law 95–372</external-xref>, not to exceed $349,000, to be derived from receipts collected pursuant to that Act, to remain available until expended. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HFBF141A9E4934BADA109E0F67EE79038"><header>FISHERIES FINANCE PROGRAM ACCOUNT</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subject to section 502 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974, during fiscal year 2023, obligations of direct loans may not exceed $24,000,000 for Individual Fishing Quota loans and not to exceed $100,000,000 for traditional direct loans as authorized by the Merchant Marine Act of 1936. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H83528D107EDA46EEABE0BC4CB2639667"><header>Departmental management</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HEE7924B64B3D47A7AC307AAAF8446345"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for the management of the Department of Commerce provided for by law, including not to exceed $4,500 for official reception and representation, $80,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That no employee of the Department of Commerce may be detailed or assigned from a bureau or office funded by this Act or any other Act to offices within the Office of the Secretary of the Department of Commerce for more than 180 days in a fiscal year unless the individual's employing bureau or office is fully reimbursed for the salary and expenses of the employee for the entire period of assignment using funds provided under this heading: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That amounts made available to the Department of Commerce in this or any prior Act may not be transferred pursuant to section 508 of this or any prior Act to the account funded under this heading, except in the case of extraordinary circumstances that threaten life or property. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HE5CC8E94B1934FDC863DA3099FA88070"><header>OFFICE OF INSPECTOR GENERAL</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of Inspector General in carrying out the provisions of the Inspector General Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App.), $49,598,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H2E9E94CA343C4CBC8D2E033BB7B0A227"><header>General provisions—Department of commerce</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H33BF7069662D4B3B90642C427E004F51"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header></appropriations-small> <section id="HFC71DE05C9EC494F962E784EA19718F4"><enum>101.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the current fiscal year, applicable appropriations and funds made available to the Department of Commerce by this Act shall be available for the activities specified in the Act of October 26, 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1514">15 U.S.C. 1514</external-xref>), to the extent and in the manner prescribed by the Act, and, notwithstanding <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/3324">31 U.S.C. 3324</external-xref>, may be used for advanced payments not otherwise authorized only upon the certification of officials designated by the Secretary of Commerce that such payments are in the public interest. </text></section> 
<section id="H2102570F7670488BB58F04F857E5EAA7"><enum>102.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the current fiscal year, appropriations made available to the Department of Commerce by this Act for salaries and expenses shall be available for hire of passenger motor vehicles as authorized by 31 U.S.C. 1343 and 1344; services as authorized by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/3109">5 U.S.C. 3109</external-xref>; and uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by law (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5901">5 U.S.C. 5901–5902</external-xref>). </text></section> <section id="HE2721E9A1A6C43CC8C3265F638542021"><enum>103.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not to exceed 5 percent of any appropriation made available for the current fiscal year for the Department of Commerce in this Act may be transferred between such appropriations, but no such appropriation shall be increased by more than 10 percent by any such transfers: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to this section shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Secretary of Commerce shall notify the Committees on Appropriations at least 15 days in advance of the acquisition or disposal of any capital asset (including land, structures, and equipment) not specifically provided for in this Act or any other law appropriating funds for the Department of Commerce. </text></section> 
<section id="H527BE8B6CA9D467985DAA9CA90F900C9"><enum>104.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements set forth by section 105 of the Commerce, Justice, Science, and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/55">Public Law 112–55</external-xref>), as amended by section 105 of title I of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/6">Public Law 113–6</external-xref>, are hereby adopted by reference and made applicable with respect to fiscal year 2024: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the life cycle cost for the Joint Polar Satellite System is $11,322,125,000, the life cycle cost of the Polar Follow On Program is $6,837,900,000, the life cycle cost for the Geostationary Operational Environmental Satellite R-Series Program is $11,700,100,000, and the life cycle cost for the Space Weather Follow-On Program is $692,800,000.</text></section> 
<section id="H79742DAE4A294850A61A44AF9E299F26"><enum>105.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Commerce may furnish services (including but not limited to utilities, telecommunications, and security services) necessary to support the operation, maintenance, and improvement of space that persons, firms, or organizations are authorized, pursuant to the Public Buildings Cooperative Use Act of 1976 or other authority, to use or occupy in the Herbert C. Hoover Building, Washington, DC, or other buildings, the maintenance, operation, and protection of which has been delegated to the Secretary from the Administrator of General Services pursuant to the Federal Property and Administrative Services Act of 1949 on a reimbursable or non-reimbursable basis. Amounts received as reimbursement for services provided under this section or the authority under which the use or occupancy of the space is authorized, up to $200,000, shall be credited to the appropriation or fund which initially bears the costs of such services. </text></section> <section id="H932FB61376C647B08A5EF042E11CE27A"><enum>106.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this title shall be construed to prevent a grant recipient from deterring child pornography, copyright infringement, or any other unlawful activity over its networks. </text></section> 
<section id="HE4D95CCAAC624BC9B24BBC2682ED0C95"><enum>107.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration is authorized to use, with their consent, with reimbursement and subject to the limits of available appropriations, the land, services, equipment, personnel, and facilities of any department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States, or of any State, local government, Indian Tribal Government, Territory, or possession, or of any political subdivision thereof, or of any foreign government or international organization, for purposes related to carrying out the responsibilities of any statute administered by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></section> <section id="HCE8386A80484498BB35A28DAC05C8500"><enum>108.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Technical Information Service shall not charge any customer for a copy of any report or document generated by the Legislative Branch unless the Service has provided information to the customer on how an electronic copy of such report or document may be accessed and downloaded for free online. Should a customer still require the Service to provide a printed or digital copy of the report or document, the charge shall be limited to recovering the Service's cost of processing, reproducing, and delivering such report or document. </text></section> 
<section id="H9272278FC02343E38FB66C556B2DA394"><enum>109.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out the responsibilities of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), the Administrator of NOAA is authorized to: (1) enter into grants and cooperative agreements with; (2) use on a non-reimbursable basis land, services, equipment, personnel, and facilities provided by; and (3) receive and expend funds made available on a consensual basis from: a Federal agency, State or subdivision thereof, local government, Tribal Government, Territory, or possession or any subdivisions thereof: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That funds received for permitting and related regulatory activities pursuant to this section shall be deposited under the heading <quote>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration—Operations, Research, and Facilities</quote> and shall remain available until September 30, 2024, for such purposes: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That all funds within this section and their corresponding uses are subject to section 505 of this Act.</text></section> 
<section id="H47E9DE0924654B8A915D640EEDA59B9C"><enum>110.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts provided by this Act or by any prior appropriations Act that remain available for obligation, for necessary expenses of the programs of the Economics and Statistics Administration of the Department of Commerce, including amounts provided for programs of the Bureau of Economic Analysis and the Bureau of the Census, shall be available for expenses of cooperative agreements with appropriate entities, including any Federal, State, or local governmental unit, or institution of higher education, to aid and promote statistical, research, and methodology activities which further the purposes for which such amounts have been made available. </text></section><appropriations-small id="H3F7AC59E09634082BE0A8C8A99869BA3"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Department of Commerce Appropriations Act, 2024</quote>. </text><pagebreak/></appropriations-small></title> <title id="H746DB72252C54840918ABF2BE40BE4C3" style="appropriations"><enum>II</enum><appropriations-major id="H7B282C45B3BA4EBDBC5746576748347D"><header>DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="HDF1C396A258F4A149010EE9CDBD39D19"><header>General administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H45455B29DBFD4675B55338B394C2758E"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary for the administration of the Department of Justice, $113,000,000, of which $4,000,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2024, and of which not to exceed $4,000,000 for security and construction of Department of Justice facilities shall remain available until expended.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HABD07B974E6E43C39C51D4BCA3BF291C"><header>JUSTICE INFORMATION SHARING TECHNOLOGY</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HFCC75A66C9D34EF292B6B34CBB1A9687"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for information sharing technology, including planning, development, deployment and departmental direction, $38,000,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the Attorney General may transfer up to $40,000,000 to this account, from funds available to the Department of Justice for information technology, to remain available until expended, for enterprise-wide information technology initiatives: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the transfer authority in the preceding proviso is in addition to any other transfer authority contained in this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to the first proviso shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HA802137A6D6B4E3B8365DDD864AF497D"><header>Executive office for immigration review</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HE6EC878E84F7455BBD11F538D3B8002F"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary for the administration of immigration-related activities of the Executive Office for Immigration Review, $760,000,000, of which $4,000,000 shall be derived by transfer from the Executive Office for Immigration Review fees deposited in the <quote>Immigration Examinations Fee</quote> account: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $50,000,000 of the total amount made available under this heading shall remain available until September 30, 2027, for build-out and modifications of courtroom space: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the Executive Office for Immigration Review shall implement case performance metrics that are linked to performance evaluations for individual immigration judges.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HB56B49770A18463AABF36D9AE0647233"><header>Office of inspector general</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of Inspector General, $142,000,000, including not to exceed $10,000 to meet unforeseen emergencies of a confidential character: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $4,000,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2024. </text></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-intermediate id="H79B24BC7122C43FD868BE7BBB427BD7B"><header>United states parole commission</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H0700F4F676F84DDFA7CAE9737D615F8F"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the United States Parole Commission as authorized, $14,238,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding any other provision of law, upon the expiration of a term of office of a Commissioner, the Commissioner may continue to act until a successor has been appointed. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H5F1EB6717F3A4B48A1F8C2620AB0B5B2"><header>Legal activities</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H4E34C9CB8C0448A4BED34D5589364A2C"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES, GENERAL LEGAL ACTIVITIES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HDA9646E5A63B4C01933BF723DED34304"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary for the legal activities of the Department of Justice, not otherwise provided for, including not to exceed $20,000 for expenses of collecting evidence, to be expended under the direction of, and to be accounted for solely under the certificate of, the Attorney General; the administration of pardon and clemency petitions; and rent of private or Government-owned space in the District of Columbia, $938,500,000, of which not to exceed $50,000,000 for litigation support contracts and information technology projects, including cybersecurity and hardening of critical networks, shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the amount provided for INTERPOL Washington dues payments, not to exceed $685,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the total amount appropriated, not to exceed $9,000 shall be available to INTERPOL Washington for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the total amount appropriated, not to exceed $9,000 shall be available to the Criminal Division for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding section 205 of this Act, upon a determination by the Attorney General that emergent circumstances require additional funding for litigation activities of the Civil Division, the Attorney General may transfer such amounts to <quote>Salaries and Expenses, General Legal Activities</quote> from available appropriations for the current fiscal year for the Department of Justice, as may be necessary to respond to such circumstances: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to the preceding proviso shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amount appropriated, such sums as may be necessary shall be available to the Civil Rights Division for salaries and expenses associated with the election monitoring program under section 8 of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10305">52 U.S.C. 10305</external-xref>) and to reimburse the Office of Personnel Management for such salaries and expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That of the amounts provided under this heading for the election monitoring program, $3,390,000 shall remain available until expended.</text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In addition, for reimbursement of expenses of the Department of Justice associated with processing cases under the National Childhood Vaccine Injury Act of 1986, $31,738,000, to be appropriated from the Vaccine Injury Compensation Trust Fund and to remain available until expended.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HA67D819DAB7B4F9F94F234AEBF2854C4"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES, ANTITRUST DIVISION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary for the enforcement of antitrust and kindred laws, $192,776,000, to remain available until expended, of which not to exceed $5,000 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding any other provision of law, not to exceed $192,776,000 of offsetting collections derived from fees collected for premerger notification filings under the Hart-Scott-Rodino Antitrust Improvements Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/18a">15 U.S.C. 18a</external-xref>), regardless of the year of collection, shall be retained and used for necessary expenses in this appropriation, and shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the sum herein appropriated from the general fund shall be reduced as such offsetting collections are received during fiscal year 2024, so as to result in a final fiscal year 2024 appropriation from the general fund estimated at $0.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2F926AA7BCAC417CB607C5C230513834"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES, UNITED STATES ATTORNEYS</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Offices of the United States Attorneys, including inter-governmental and cooperative agreements, $2,312,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the total amount appropriated, not to exceed $19,600 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $40,000,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That each United States Attorney shall establish or participate in a task force on human trafficking. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HE2BA5FF307C54F7D88E86116944C3BE4"><header>UNITED STATES TRUSTEE SYSTEM FUND</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the United States Trustee Program, as authorized, $239,000,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding any other provision of law, deposits of discretionary offsetting collections to the United States Trustee System Fund and amounts herein appropriated shall be available in such amounts as may be necessary to pay refunds due depositors: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding any other provision of law, fees deposited into the Fund as discretionary offsetting collections pursuant to section 589a of title 28, United States Code (as limited by section 589a(f)(2) of title 28, United States Code), shall be retained and used for necessary expenses in this appropriation and shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That to the extent that fees deposited into the Fund as discretionary offsetting collections in fiscal year 2024, net of amounts necessary to pay refunds due depositors, exceed $255,000,000, those excess amounts shall be available in future fiscal years only to the extent provided in advance in appropriations Acts: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the sum herein appropriated from the general fund shall be reduced (1) as such fees are received during fiscal year 2024, net of amounts necessary to pay refunds due depositors, (estimated at $230,000,000) and (2) to the extent that any remaining general fund appropriations can be derived from amounts deposited in the Fund as discretionary offsetting collections in previous fiscal years that are not otherwise appropriated, so as to result in a final fiscal year 2024 appropriation from the general fund estimated at $9,000,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2804957459244F72B1F785510EE80269"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES, FOREIGN CLAIMS SETTLEMENT COMMISSION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary to carry out the activities of the Foreign Claims Settlement Commission, including services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, $2,504,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H1E94217D0BDE42D5B36F26BA783A3F26"><header>FEES AND EXPENSES OF WITNESSES </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For fees and expenses of witnesses, for expenses of contracts for the procurement and supervision of expert witnesses, for private counsel expenses, including advances, and for expenses of foreign counsel, $270,000,000, to remain available until expended, of which not to exceed $16,000,000 is for construction of buildings for protected witness safesites; not to exceed $3,000,000 is for the purchase and maintenance of armored and other vehicles for witness security caravans; and not to exceed $35,000,000 is for the purchase, installation, maintenance, and upgrade of secure telecommunications equipment and a secure automated information network to store and retrieve the identities and locations of protected witnesses: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That amounts made available under this heading may not be transferred pursuant to section 205 of this Act. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HFD79148E33D44BCA8B2AE201119A0FA4"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES, COMMUNITY RELATIONS SERVICE</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H9257E5F3D5DC402BBF0FBEFEDD9C4A8E"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Community Relations Service, $10,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding section 205 of this Act, upon a determination by the Attorney General that emergent circumstances require additional funding for conflict resolution and violence prevention activities of the Community Relations Service, the Attorney General may transfer up to $8,000,000 to the Community Relations Service, from available appropriations for the current fiscal year for Salaries and Expenses, General Legal Activities, as may be necessary to respond to such circumstances: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to the preceding proviso shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H375E7D3B3654428FAA2F31043CBBB71E"><header>ASSETS FORFEITURE FUND</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses authorized by subparagraphs (B), (F), and (G) of section 524(c)(1) of title 28, United States Code, $20,514,000, to be derived from the Department of Justice Assets Forfeiture Fund. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H638F8520F0954068A7F51EAFB316678D"><header>United states marshals service</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HA6F385BD0F5A49D987C3C3E5AF3C7373"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the United States Marshals Service, $1,715,700,000, of which not to exceed $20,000 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses, and not to exceed $25,000,000 shall remain available until expended. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H01E502A42E214700B4E1DAEDBAF2DFF2"><header>CONSTRUCTION </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For construction in space that is controlled, occupied, or utilized by the United States Marshals Service for prisoner holding and related support, $15,000,000, to remain available until expended. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HA77CA2DC83A54979B6478E6BE5F58B1F"><header>FEDERAL PRISONER DETENTION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses related to United States prisoners in the custody of the United States Marshals Service as authorized by section 4013 of title 18, United States Code, $2,125,724,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $20,000,000 shall be considered <quote>funds appropriated for State and local law enforcement assistance</quote> pursuant to section 4013(b) of title 18, United States Code: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the United States Marshals Service shall be responsible for managing the Justice Prisoner and Alien Transportation System. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HD73D77E85D10497A8CF14D505606BA26"><header>National security division</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H69BEEE8FC874482487051022537648E6"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H12F2F98917CC46D5822BFEDB6B63623D"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For expenses necessary to carry out the activities of the National Security Division, $120,681,000, of which not to exceed $5,000,000 for information technology systems shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding section 205 of this Act, upon a determination by the Attorney General that emergent circumstances require additional funding for the activities of the National Security Division, the Attorney General may transfer such amounts to this heading from available appropriations for the current fiscal year for the Department of Justice, as may be necessary to respond to such circumstances: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to the preceding proviso shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H9C8BD4BE04884C709774D3E0383F732A"><header>Interagency Law Enforcement</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HD152BF3ECFF34CD5A42DBAD0E7F68773"><header>ORGANIZED CRIME AND DRUG ENFORCEMENT TASK FORCES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H690FF0FB88DB450BA2F395D12676DC0A"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for the identification, investigation, and prosecution of individuals associated with the most significant drug trafficking organizations, transnational organized crime, and money laundering organizations not otherwise provided for, to include inter-governmental agreements with State and local law enforcement agencies engaged in the investigation and prosecution of individuals involved in transnational organized crime and drug trafficking, $555,458,000, of which $50,000,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any amounts obligated from appropriations under this heading may be used under authorities available to the organizations reimbursed from this appropriation. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H100BD00269C64715A6369FE19ECE333F"><header>Federal bureau of investigation</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HF2FA369138674942BE5882C1FC223097"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for detection, investigation, and prosecution of crimes against the United States, $10,276,000,000, of which not to exceed $216,900,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $284,000 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0B821BFA6C8C41D8A61953B82C64D5E4"><header>CONSTRUCTION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, to include the cost of equipment, furniture, and information technology requirements, related to construction or acquisition of buildings, facilities, and sites by purchase, or as otherwise authorized by law; conversion, modification, and extension of federally owned buildings; preliminary planning and design of projects; and operation and maintenance of secure work environment facilities and secure networking capabilities; $30,000,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That such amount shall be used for a second DNA laboratory: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That, notwithstanding any other provision of law, unobligated balances from prior year appropriations made available under Federal Bureau of Investigation, Construction, for a new headquarters, may only be used to sustain use of the Federal Bureau of Investigation J. Edgar Hoover headquarters building. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H34F654F29A6048248FBBD57FD1470704"><header>Drug enforcement administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H5FA2CA87729C4F4B87DD79AB83D8873C"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H1846CE5DDD584F089B577EE025B2D91B"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Drug Enforcement Administration, including not to exceed $70,000 to meet unforeseen emergencies of a confidential character pursuant to section 530C of title 28, United States Code; and expenses for conducting drug education and training programs, including travel and related expenses for participants in such programs and the distribution of items of token value that promote the goals of such programs, $2,760,924,000, of which not to exceed $75,000,000 shall remain available until expended and not to exceed $90,000 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, notwithstanding section 3672 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/310">Public Law 106–310</external-xref>, up to $10,000,000 may be used to reimburse States, units of local government, Indian Tribal Governments, other public entities, and multi-jurisdictional or regional consortia thereof for expenses incurred to clean up and safely dispose of substances associated with clandestine methamphetamine laboratories, conversion and extraction operations, tableting operations, or laboratories and processing operations for fentanyl and fentanyl-related substances which may present a danger to public health or the environment: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That $50,000,000 shall be transferred to and merged with <quote>Community Oriented Policing Services Programs</quote> for competitive grants to State and local law enforcement agencies for the purpose of investigating illicit activities related to the distribution of methamphetamine, heroin, fentanyl and fentanyl analogues, and the unlawful distribution of prescription opioids. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H5716E3F8F07348898A8CB832A02C0C0F"><header>Bureau of alcohol, tobacco, firearms and explosives</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HD17319BA8015456AB533E15BE08EFE0B"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives, for training of State and local law enforcement agencies with or without reimbursement, including training in connection with the training and acquisition of canines for explosives and fire accelerants detection; and for provision of laboratory assistance to State and local law enforcement agencies, with or without reimbursement, $1,531,071,000, of which not to exceed $36,000 shall be for official reception and representation expenses, not to exceed $1,000,000 shall be available for the payment of attorneys' fees as provided by section 924(d)(2) of title 18, United States Code, and not to exceed $25,000,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That no funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to transfer the functions, missions, or activities of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives to other agencies or Departments: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso> That not more than 40 percent of the amounts made available under this heading may be obligated unless processing times for National Firearms Act applications do not exceed 120 days in the case of paper applications and 60 days in the case of electronic applications.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H5FB644BD57634606B9F17D629FC0EDC5"><header>Federal prison system </header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HFDDA6A1A6AE24A129BB1EF29616254F0"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H5755490993FE48FB853A76893660F66C"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Federal Prison System for the administration, operation, and maintenance of Federal penal and correctional institutions, and for the provision of technical assistance and advice on corrections related issues to foreign governments, $8,492,588,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not less than $409,483,000 shall be for the programs and activities authorized by the First Step Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/391">Public Law 115–391</external-xref>), of which not less than 2 percent shall be transferred to and merged with the appropriation for <quote>Office of Justice Programs–Research, Evaluation and Statistics</quote> for the National Institute of Justice to carry out evaluations of programs and activities related to the First Step Act of 2018 (<quote>First Step Act</quote>): <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Attorney General may transfer to the Department of Health and Human Services such amounts as may be necessary for direct expenditures by that Department for medical relief for inmates of Federal penal and correctional institutions: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Director of the Federal Prison System, where necessary, may enter into contracts with a fiscal agent or fiscal intermediary claims processor to determine the amounts payable to persons who, on behalf of the Federal Prison System, furnish health services to individuals committed to the custody of the Federal Prison System: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $5,400 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $50,000,000 shall remain available until expended for necessary operations: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, of the amounts provided for contract confinement, not to exceed $20,000,000 shall remain available until expended to make payments in advance for grants, contracts and reimbursable agreements, and other expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Director of the Federal Prison System may accept donated property and services relating to the operation of the prison card program from a not-for-profit entity which has operated such program in the past, notwithstanding the fact that such not-for-profit entity furnishes services under contracts to the Federal Prison System relating to the operation of pre-release services, halfway houses, or other custodial facilities: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That no amounts under this heading available for programs and activities related to the First Step Act may be transferred, or otherwise made available, to or for administration by the Department of Labor. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HB8E32AE473C94B889BFA6A22FEDFD6E8"><header>BUILDINGS AND FACILITIES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For planning, acquisition of sites, and construction of new facilities; purchase and acquisition of facilities and remodeling, and equipping of such facilities for penal and correctional use, including all necessary expenses incident thereto, by contract or force account; and constructing, remodeling, and equipping necessary buildings and facilities at existing penal and correctional institutions, including all necessary expenses incident thereto, by contract or force account, $273,000,000, to remain available until expended, of which $135,000,000 shall be available only for costs related to reconstruction and major repairs to facilities with geological and seismic deficiencies: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That labor of United States prisoners may be used for work performed under this appropriation. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H2A60EC24295B45CD98D2D9648E1BD7EB"><header>FEDERAL PRISON INDUSTRIES, INCORPORATED</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Prison Industries, Incorporated, is hereby authorized to make such expenditures within the limits of funds and borrowing authority available, and in accord with the law, and to make such contracts and commitments without regard to fiscal year limitations as provided by section 9104 of title 31, United States Code, as may be necessary in carrying out the program set forth in the budget for the current fiscal year for such corporation. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H7F5A9E9B1E0B4768975F65776EE387F4"><header>LIMITATION ON ADMINISTRATIVE EXPENSES, FEDERAL PRISON INDUSTRIES, INCORPORATED</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not to exceed $2,700,000 of the funds of the Federal Prison Industries, Incorporated, shall be available for its administrative expenses, and for services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, to be computed on an accrual basis to be determined in accordance with the corporation's current prescribed accounting system, and such amounts shall be exclusive of depreciation, payment of claims, and expenditures which such accounting system requires to be capitalized or charged to cost of commodities acquired or produced, including selling and shipping expenses, and expenses in connection with acquisition, construction, operation, maintenance, improvement, protection, or disposition of facilities and other property belonging to the corporation or in which it has an interest. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HB2185C59C9E445E19AAC3DE00951E0D1"><header>State and local law enforcement activities</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-intermediate id="HB55E25FDDED444E7A54C18F8EBE32748"><header>Office on Violence Against Women</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HED4716D179C34AE18A55B111704D950C"><header>VIOLENCE AGAINST WOMEN PREVENTION AND PROSECUTION PROGRAMS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H4AFCE6E233C94ED2822BD7577DC6A5BC"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For grants, contracts, cooperative agreements, and other assistance for the prevention and prosecution of violence against women, as authorized by the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1968 Act</quote>); title II of the Civil Rights Act of 1968 (commonly known as the <quote>Indian Civil Rights Act of 1968</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/90/284">Public Law 90–284</external-xref>) (<quote>the Indian Civil Rights Act</quote>); the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/322">Public Law 103–322</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1994 Act</quote>); the Victims of Child Abuse Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/101/647">Public Law 101–647</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1990 Act</quote>); the Prosecutorial Remedies and Other Tools to end the Exploitation of Children Today Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/21">Public Law 108–21</external-xref>); the Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/11101">34 U.S.C. 11101 et seq.</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1974 Act</quote>); the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/386">Public Law 106–386</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2000 Act</quote>); the Justice for All Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/405">Public Law 108–405</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2004 Act</quote>); the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/162">Public Law 109–162</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2005 Act</quote>); the Violence Against Women Reauthorization Act of 2013 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/4">Public Law 113–4</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2013 Act</quote>); the Justice for Victims of Trafficking Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/22">Public Law 114–22</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2015 Act</quote>); and the Abolish Human Trafficking Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/392">Public Law 115–392</external-xref>); the Prison Rape Elimination Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/79">Public Law 108–79</external-xref>) (<quote>PREA</quote>); and the Violence Against Women Act Reauthorization Act of 2022 (division W of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2022 Act</quote>); and for related victims services, $700,000,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the amount provided—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF7A8AEBAB9D944449F4A69EE7082965B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$255,000,000 is for grants to combat violence against women, as authorized by part T of the 1968 Act, and any authorized, applicable incentive funding amounts with respect to such grants;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF3DCADB38854DBA96DEC123D399E0C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$46,000,000 is for transitional housing assistance grants for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, stalking, or sexual assault as authorized by section 40299 of the 1994 Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C3CBE07F45A452EBA8854A90492C1DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$17,000,000 is for a grant program to provide services to advocate for and respond to youth victims of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking; assistance to children and youth exposed to such violence; programs to engage men and youth in preventing such violence; and assistance to middle and high school students through education and other services related to such violence, of which $3,500,000 is to engage men and youth in preventing domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That 10 percent of the total amount available for this grant program shall be available for grants under the program authorized by section 2015 of the 1968 Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the definitions and grant conditions in section 40002 of the 1994 Act shall apply to this program;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96888FF2578D4C4089432A25B743D029"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$60,500,000 is for grants to encourage arrests and otherwise improve the criminal justice response to domestic violence as authorized by part U of title I the 1968 Act, of which $8,000,000 is for an initiative to promote effective policing and prosecution responses to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking, including evaluation of the effectiveness of funded interventions (<quote>Policing and Prosecution Initiative</quote>); and $1,000,000 is for an initiative to enhance prosecution and investigation of online abuse and harassment (<quote>Prosecution and Investigation of Online Abuse Initiative</quote>): <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That subsections (c) and (d) of section 2101 of the 1968 Act shall not apply to the Policing and Prosecution Initiative or the Prosecution and Investigation of Online Abuse Initiative;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD14FA8E9E2D24A128A9F9185FC99BD24"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$78,500,000 is for sexual assault victims assistance, as authorized by section 41601 of the 1994 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H599DDC78A3734F6195FE051A2C30B496"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$15,500,000 is for grants to protect inmates and safeguard communities as authorized by section 6 of PREA: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That such funds may be transferred to <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote> for administration by the Office of Justice Programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1FA1A22988A24934BEBDD2090A9C5B67"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$2,000,000 is for a National Deaf Services Line to provide remote services to deaf victims of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That the definitions and grant conditions in section 40002 of the 1994 Act shall apply to this service line; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1ABB5F90BDC6455A9D948CF1B575138E"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$50,000,000 is for rural domestic violence and child abuse enforcement assistance grants, as authorized by section 40295 of the 1994 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H014063E28C82407CBD3E7F0C636564B8"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$25,000,000 is for grants to reduce violent crimes against women on campus, as authorized by section 304 of the 2005 Act, of which $12,500,000 is for grants to Historically Black Colleges and Universities, Hispanic-Serving Institutions, and Tribal colleges and universities;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E922A4430544637BD38237E4F06368E"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$50,000,000 is for legal assistance for victims, as authorized by section 1201 of the 2000 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB59D5FCBAA646199AC944CE6608AFC8"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$22,000,000 is for grants to support families in the justice system, as authorized by section 1301 of the 2000 Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H15E3E2521EDA45B3865F6648603309B3"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$9,000,000 is for enhanced training and services to end violence against, and abuse of, women in later life, as authorized by section 40801 of the 1994 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4F6DEF4544D34C118001D96FB9822B68"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$12,000,000 is for education and training to end violence against, and abuse of, women with disabilities, as authorized by section 1402 of the 2000 Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6C5620CCA054EC2AEB321C97CDBD970"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$2,500,000 is for research, evaluation, and statistics of violence against women and related issues addressed by grant programs of the Office on Violence Against Women, of which, $1,000,000 is for analysis and research on violence against Indian women, including as authorized by section 904 of the 2005 Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That such funds may be transferred to <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote> for administration by the Bureau of Justice Statistics and National Institute of Justice;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H25518F2C0573404395F517CCFB0C9F17"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$1,000,000 is for the National Resource Center on Workplace Responses to assist victims of domestic violence, as authorized by section 41501 of the 1994 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H583B193BD15B481592015926AFA0A64C"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$500,000 is for a national clearinghouse that provides training and technical assistance on issues relating to sexual assault of American Indian and Alaska Native women;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H956A0A98ED5C414A8C11588CEF7EDD66"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$11,000,000 is for programs to assist Tribal Governments in exercising special Tribal criminal jurisdiction, as authorized by section 204 of the Indian Civil Rights Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That the grant conditions in section 40002(b) of the 1994 Act shall apply to grants made under such programs: <proviso><italic>Provided further, </italic></proviso>That $3,000,000 is for an initiative to support cross-designation of Tribal prosecutors as Tribal Special Assistant United States Attorneys: <proviso><italic>Provided further, </italic></proviso>That the definitions and grant conditions in section 40002 of the 1994 Act shall apply to such initiative; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9DF40E2D39B4DC89751147B55B88AF9"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$2,500,000 is for the purposes authorized under title IV the 2015 Act (the <quote>Rape Survivor Child Custody Act</quote>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H255B24A90A584498936F1C09CBEDC5B3"><enum>(19)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000 is for the purposes authorized under section 205 of division W of the 2022 Act (the <quote>Abby Honold Act</quote>); </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5A6F695F5FE241ADA0FC68C868539050"><enum>(20)</enum><text>$5,000,000 is for grants to State and Tribal courts to implement protection order pilot programs; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D55609B6EB44C81AB3748E885214394"><enum>(21)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for grants to support access to sexual assault nurse examinations, as authorized by section 304 of title III of the 2004 Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That the grant conditions in section 40002 of the 1994 Act shall apply to this program; and for regional sexual assault investigative training academies; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5900B5FC7314462F8FB081B96920DF9A"><enum>(22)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$10,000,000 is for local law enforcement grants for prevention, enforcement, and prosecution of cybercrimes against individuals, as authorized by sections 1401 and 1402 of the 2022 Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That the grant conditions in section 40002 of the 1994 Act shall apply to this program.</text></paragraph></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HFC473CDAD119407B964A447426BF483F"><header>Office of Justice Programs</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H5ACD3082855443199868DB64457CFF4E"><header>STATE AND LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT ASSISTANCE</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H251EF1A6CAF24FFEB3A8F7B99B20070F"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For grants, contracts, cooperative agreements, and other assistance authorized by the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/322">Public Law 103–322</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1994 Act</quote>); the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/90/351">Public Law 90–351</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1968 Act</quote>); the Justice for All Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/405">Public Law 108–405</external-xref>); the Victims of Child Abuse Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/101/647">Public Law 101–647</external-xref>) (<quote>the 1990 Act</quote>); the Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/164">Public Law 109–164</external-xref>) (<quote>the TVPRA of 2005</quote>); the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/162">Public Law 109–162</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2005 Act</quote>); the Adam Walsh Child Protection and Safety Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/248">Public Law 109–248</external-xref>) (<quote>the Adam Walsh Act</quote>); the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/386">Public Law 106–386</external-xref>) (<quote>the Victims of Trafficking Act</quote>); the NICS Improvement Amendments Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/180">Public Law 110–180</external-xref>); subtitle C of title II of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/296">Public Law 107–296</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2002 Act</quote>); the Second Chance Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/199">Public Law 110–199</external-xref>); the Prioritizing Resources and Organization for Intellectual Property Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/403">Public Law 110–403</external-xref>); the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/98/473">Public Law 98–473</external-xref>); the Mentally Ill Offender Treatment and Crime Reduction Reauthorization and Improvement Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/416">Public Law 110–416</external-xref>); the Violence Against Women Reauthorization Act of 2013 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/4">Public Law 113–4</external-xref>) (“the 2013 Act”); the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>) (<quote>CARA</quote>); the Justice for All Reauthorization Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/324">Public Law 114–324</external-xref>); Kevin and Avonte’s Law (division Q of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>) (<quote>Kevin and Avonte’s Law</quote>); the STOP School Violence Act of 2018 (title V of division S of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>) (<quote>the STOP School Violence Act</quote>); the Fix NICS Act of 2018 (title VI of division S of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>); the SUPPORT for Patients and Communities Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/271">Public Law 115–271</external-xref>); the Second Chance Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/391">Public Law 115–391</external-xref>); the Matthew Shepard and James Byrd, Jr. Hate Crimes Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/84">Public Law 111–84</external-xref>); the Ashanti Alert Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/401">Public Law 115–401</external-xref>); the Missing Persons and Unidentified Remains Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/277">Public Law 116–277</external-xref>); the Violence Against Women Act Reauthorization Act of 2022 (division W of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>) (<quote>the 2022 Act</quote>); and other programs, $2,477,910,000, to remain available until expended, of which— </text> <paragraph id="HD286257B5B134C9EB76F8816CF847078"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$35,000,000 is for criminal justice statistics programs, as authorized by part C of title I of the 1968 Act; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8DC6938391E4D869C6E1D4C89DE6DA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$25,000,000 is for research, development, and evaluation programs, of which $8,000,000 is for Research and Development in Forensic Science for Criminal Justice Purposes grants;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5CB274759A284109B1FCBDE6E404A6C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$670,510,000 is for the Edward Byrne Memorial Justice Assistance Grant program as authorized by subpart 1 of part E of title I of the 1968 Act (except that section 1001(c), and the special rules for Puerto Rico under section 505(g), of title I of the 1968 Act shall not apply for purposes of this Act), including grants authorized by section 502(b)(1), of which, notwithstanding such subpart 1— </text> 
<subparagraph id="HE4A81B255DA4497ABD9FD9F3B408AB7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$30,000,000 is for the Patrick Leahy Bulletproof Vest Partnership Grant Program, as authorized by section 2501 of title I of the 1968 Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That $1,500,000 shall be transferred directly to the National Institute of Standards and Technology’s Office of Law Enforcement Standards for research, testing, and evaluation programs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H04B25539DC1547ED8F24E2E6D2144E4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for a competitive matching grant program for purchases of body-worn cameras for State, local, and Tribal law enforcement; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H011588FC259F4120B0A1F660D7F6BF9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$214,463,000 is for Byrne Justice projects to assist State, local, and Tribal law enforcement efforts to enforce laws, address violent crime, increase prosecutions, improve the criminal justice system (including the correctional system), provide victims’ services, and other related activities, which shall be for the purposes, and in the amounts, specified for <quote>DOJ-OJP Byrne</quote> in the table entitled, <quote>Community Project Funding</quote>, in the report accompanying this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That such amounts may not be transferred for any other purpose;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H801CD6EF44BF430CBA669E3086EEDC3A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$234,000,000 is for the State Criminal Alien Assistance Program, as authorized by section 241(I)(5) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 1231(I)(5)); </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3B2693AACE974AC18FFE5EE66F326E0B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$95,000,000 is for victim services programs for victims of trafficking, as authorized by section 107(b)(2) of the Victims of Trafficking Act, by the TVPRA of 2005, or programs authorized under <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/4">Public Law 113–4</external-xref>, of which, $4,000,000 is for grants to prevent the trafficking of girls;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8ED3D6BBA8F6493E88417D94F737E0EE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$95,000,000 is for grants to States to upgrade criminal and mental health records for the National Instant Criminal Background Check System, of which no less than $25,500,000 shall be for grants made under the authorities of the NICS Improvement Amendments Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/180">Public Law 110–180</external-xref>) and Fix NICS Act of 2018;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFF55FB4C9C749F3A47948E4ADFFB94C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$195,000,000 is for DNA-related and forensic programs and activities, of which— </text> 
<subparagraph id="H3C99BC3348CF4251A63E2F53041CB574"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$130,000,000 is for the purposes authorized under section 2 of the DNA Analysis Backlog Elimination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/546">Public Law 106–546</external-xref>) (the Debbie Smith DNA Backlog Grant Program): <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That up to 4 percent of funds made available under this paragraph may be used for the purposes described in the DNA Training and Education for Law Enforcement, Correctional Personnel, and Court Officers program (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/405">Public Law 108–405</external-xref>, section 303); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBD7D343372624D32B92F33C67070ACF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$55,000,000 is for community-based grant programs to improve the response to sexual assault and assistance for investigation and prosecution of related cold cases;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47A84823AE304222A5411455A1BEA6A5"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for grants for wrongful conviction review and for the purposes described in the Kirk Bloodsworth Post-Conviction DNA Testing Grant Program (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/405">Public Law 108–405</external-xref>, section 412);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H17566263A7664AD6A88A13EC2BBC367E"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$35,000,000 is for Paul Coverdell Forensic Sciences Improvement Grants under part BB of title I of the 1968 Act; of which $2,500,000 is for grants to strengthen the medical examiner-coroner system;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17F68EF89A5A4587BAF0983751AC8717"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$80,000,000 is for assistance to Indian Tribes, of which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3EBAA4D5D7F84E7C81450993B33B2EC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$31,500,000 is for improving Tribal law enforcement, including hiring, equipment, training; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEB2BD0D1C74045758264BB2EBD5825F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$14,000,000 is for a Tribal Youth Program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAF871F6E8AB94D4F8179C3107B0AED84"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$3,000,000 is to support the Tribal Access Program;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA6744D7A5D04415C98B737A93E448E0F"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$115,000,000 is for offender reentry programs and research, as authorized by the Second Chance Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/199">Public Law 110–199</external-xref>) and by the Second Chance Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/391">Public Law 115–391</external-xref>), without regard to the time limitations specified at section 6(1) of such Act, of which— </text> 
<subparagraph id="H583B36A110D44841BEB275C8E41C12F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$19,000,000 is for the justice reinvestment initiative, as implemented in fiscal year 2014, for activities related to criminal justice reform and recidivism reduction: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That no funds are used to support initiatives that promote the closing and repurposing of youth detention facilities; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1E5850B5996C412FA951B86F70F858A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$10,000,000 is for a grant program for crisis stabilization and community reentry, as authorized by the Crisis Stabilization and Community Reentry Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/281">Public Law 116–281</external-xref>); and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7746F62C01DD45888DC6342B2EFC42FA"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000 is for grants to enhance and maintain parental and family relationships for incarcerated parents as a reentry or recidivism reduction strategy;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6633B030F26C40D994E8C660776995DD"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$445,000,000 is for comprehensive opioid use reduction activities, including as authorized by CARA, and for the following programs, which shall address opioid, stimulant, and substance use disorders consistent with underlying program authorities, of which— </text> <subparagraph id="H2E47A32571EB4803BB98AB20F7728A40"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$95,000,000 is for Drug Courts, as authorized by section 1001(a)(25)(A) of title I of the 1968 Act;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA03229FCA7B44907AEBEC97E788084C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$45,000,000 is for mental health courts and adult and juvenile collaboration program grants, as authorized by parts V and HH of title I of the 1968 Act, and the Mentally Ill Offender Treatment and Crime Reduction Reauthorization and Improvement Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/416">Public Law 110–416</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9F20963E8E464ED0AC18AA72DBCCDD8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$45,000,000 is for grants for Residential Substance Abuse Treatment for State Prisoners, as authorized by part S of title I of the 1968 Act;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0027D8D174964114AED66F7FE5CDFAAB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$35,000,000 is for a veterans treatment courts program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9AA344FD3E64092A278B88E853F9899"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$35,000,000 is for a program to monitor prescription drugs and scheduled listed chemical products; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H370F992C797D4158BE53976F7449E8A7"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$190,000,000 is for a comprehensive opioid, stimulant, and substance use disorder program, of which— </text> <clause id="HE82AADAEC8DF43B98CF918315CE37E7E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for grants for local and regional efforts to prevent substance use and misuse: <proviso><italic>Provided, </italic></proviso>That priority is given to non-profit organizations implementing comprehensive approaches to combatting substance abuse, including investigations, treatment, and education;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6F786DE5DBD9424BA0171C343CC16A86"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$17,000,000 is for forensic support for opioid and synthetic drug investigations; and</text></clause> <clause id="H38BE8951276B4DF581715D4ACEC4A61B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$12,500,000 is for an initiative relating to youth affected by opioids, stimulants, and substance use disorder; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B43D8ACDC5540FB8BF1706332C113F6"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$82,000,000 is for grants to be administered by the Bureau of Justice Assistance for purposes authorized under the STOP School Violence Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FFF03D13AA14203AFD38F645943A043"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$3,000,000 is for grants to State and local law enforcement agencies for the expenses associated with the investigation and prosecution of criminal offenses involving civil rights, as authorized by the Emmett Till Unsolved Civil Rights Crimes Reauthorization Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/325">Public Law 114–325</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H577F00D3F2BE43E393D4D60FF740B754"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$55,000,000 is for formula grants authorized by section 221 of the 1974 Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2FAF29BBCF1A447D96DA8BAD5BA550C8"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$107,000,000 is for youth mentoring grants;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6CFDB50A249947D3ACD5E18C3057F94F"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$41,000,000 is for programs authorized by the Victims of Child Abuse Act of 1990, of which $4,000,000 is for grants to improve the judicial system’s handling of child abuse and neglect cases, as authorized by section 222 of the 1990 Act; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6FD6033589754BCBB2EA49689BABE7A7"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$15,000,000 is for the court-appointed special advocate program, as authorized by section 217 of the 1990 Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC830EBBE3A2E4765BCBE065727548D97"><enum>(19)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$130,400,000 is for missing and exploited Americans programs, of which—</text> <subparagraph id="HE9501EB13B054CDFAC8190746BA35B96"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$42,000,000 is for missing and exploited children activities, as authorized by sections 404(b) and 405(a) of the 1974 Act (except that section 102(b)(4)(B) of the PROTECT Our Children Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/401">Public Law 110–401</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this Act);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6D674E2E02BD42E2B480DC5A4F630FAA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$52,000,000 is for Internet crimes against children task forces, as authorized by the PROTECT Our Children Act of 2008;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD8D3399A4B5740639770667487A911E7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$18,000,000 is for sex offender management assistance, as authorized by the Adam Walsh Act, and related activities, of which $1,000,000 for the National Sex Offender Public Website;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H54F47A4F97344524AFDBB901CDC74C9F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$6,000,000 is for the operation, maintenance, and expansion of the National Missing and Unidentified Persons System;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCD305527DA5F4ABC98BE7EAE7BB73EFF"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000 is for grants authorized under the Missing Persons and Unidentified Remains Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/277">Public Law 116–277</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCBD154F6C35A49DFA16C43422649DB2E"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$2,000,000 is for the Missing Americans Alert Program (title XXIV of the 1994 Act), as amended by Kevin and Avonte’s Law; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H436B7C31CFCF4E62ADBD870410FB2BE9"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$1,000,000 is for the purposes of the Ashanti Alert Communications Network as authorized under the Ashanti Alert Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/401">Public Law 115–401</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="appropriations-small"> 
<proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That, if a unit of local government uses any of the funds made available under this heading to increase the number of law enforcement officers, the unit of local government will achieve a net gain in the number of law enforcement officers who perform non-administrative public sector safety service: 
<proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That in the spending plan submitted pursuant to section 528 of this Act, the Office of Justice Programs shall specifically and explicitly identify all changes in the administration of competitive grant programs for fiscal year 2024, including changes to applicant eligibility, priority areas or weightings, and the application review process. </continuation-text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H26DC3A4C69494342B26BC48F3BC6DBA5"></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H6C0A62A0ADE44E21A20DFC8BF7A7AB5D"><header>PUBLIC SAFETY OFFICER BENEFITS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H80716F21230148B69A3648AF19970ED7"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For payments and expenses authorized under section 1001(a)(4) of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968, such sums as are necessary (including amounts for administrative costs), to remain available until expended; and $34,800,000 for payments authorized by section 1201(b) of such Act and for educational assistance authorized by section 1218 of such Act, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding section 205 of this Act, upon a determination by the Attorney General that emergent circumstances require additional funding for such disability and education payments, the Attorney General may transfer such amounts to <quote>Public Safety Officer Benefits</quote> from available appropriations for the Department of Justice as may be necessary to respond to such circumstances: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to the preceding proviso shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HBCC6A872876B49998B7055B277CD830D"><header>Community oriented policing services</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H9EFD139D190948079A2B972629E580D9"><header>COMMUNITY ORIENTED POLICING SERVICES PROGRAMS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H97C67B03440C472A9C806679052DD8D3"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For activities authorized by the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/322">Public Law 103–322</external-xref>); the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<quote>the 1968 Act</quote>); the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/162">Public Law 109–162</external-xref>) (“the 2005 Act”); the American Law Enforcement Heroes Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/37">Public Law 115–37</external-xref>); the Law Enforcement Mental Health and Wellness Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/113">Public Law 115–113</external-xref>) (<quote>the LEMHW Act</quote>); the SUPPORT for Patients and Communities Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/271">Public Law 115–271</external-xref>); the Project Safe Neighborhoods Grant Program Authorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/185">Public Law 115–185</external-xref>); and the Supporting and Treating Officers In Crisis Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/32">Public Law 116–32</external-xref>) (<quote>the STOIC Act</quote>), $670,606,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any balances made available through prior year deobligations shall only be available in accordance with section 505 of this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amount provided under this heading—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5D94D99641F24E269FC1553374CF4911"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$330,950,000 is for grants under section 1701 of title I of the 1968 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10381">34 U.S.C. 10381</external-xref>) for the hiring and rehiring of additional career law enforcement officers under part Q of such title notwithstanding subsection (i) of such section: <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That, notwithstanding section 1704(c) of such title (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10384">34 U.S.C. 10384(c)</external-xref>), funding for hiring or rehiring a career law enforcement officer may not exceed $125,000 unless the Director of the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services grants a waiver from this limitation: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amounts appropriated under this paragraph, $100,000,000 is for grants for law enforcement activities associated with the presidential nominating conventions;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4110E01699074D438CF122A5F92881B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$50,000,000 is for regional information sharing activities, as authorized by part M of title I of the 1968 Act, which may be transferred to and merged with <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote> for administration by the Office of Justice Programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC1BFCFE0A92544A6A6135A7BAAA36431"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$10,000,000 is for training, peer mentoring, mental health program activities, and other support services as authorized under the LEMHW Act and part W of title I of the 1968 Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7A96B8299FDE41B89906B41EB58F7430"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for a grant program for State and local law enforcement to provide officer training on responding to individuals with mental illness or disabilities and for co-responder teams and an Officer Robert Wilson III memorial initiative on Preventing Violence Against Law Enforcement and Ensuring Officer Resilience and Survivability (VALOR);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE040920120D4608B143795794853FEC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$12,890,000 is for activities authorized by the POLICE Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/199">Public Law 114–199</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE897A4717AA43D1841DA1FA25529B5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$53,000,000 is for competitive grants to be administered by the Community Oriented Policing Services Office for purposes authorized under the STOP School Violence Act (title V of division S of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5FB7AC2432AC4E908D19B497F1F17A31"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000,000 is for grants authorized under the Project Safe Neighborhoods Grant Authorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/185">Public Law 115–185</external-xref>), which may be transferred to and merged with <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote> for administration by the Office of Justice Programs, of which, $8,000,000 is for a rural violent crime initiative, including assistance for law enforcement; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4A2632EC5EA647FD94C915084168A024"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$173,766,000 is for a law enforcement technologies and equipment grant program, which shall be used for the projects, and in the amounts, specified for <quote>DOJ-COPS Tech</quote> in the table entitled, <quote>Community Project Funding</quote>, in the report accompanying this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That such amounts may not be transferred for any other purpose: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That grants funded by such amounts shall not be subject to section 1703 of title I of the 1968 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10383">34 U.S.C. 10383</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H3CDA4FE4924042D293288919474F5C8F"><header>General provisions—Department of justice</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H5332F301E6CB4FC7A364E55636D5AFE2"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header></appropriations-small> 
<section id="H7DD4B1FC191949C9BF5194908551C79D"><enum>201.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to amounts otherwise made available in this title for official reception and representation expenses, a total of not to exceed $50,000 from funds appropriated to the Department of Justice in this title shall be available to the Attorney General for official reception and representation expenses.</text></section> <section id="H25D564C0DE9647D394910C00A90932B6" commented="no"><enum>202.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated by this title shall be available to pay for an abortion, except where the life of the mother would be endangered if the fetus were carried to term, or in the case of rape or incest: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That should this prohibition be declared unconstitutional by a court of competent jurisdiction, this section shall be null and void.</text></section> 
<section id="H4BFF5D99093C4D598BB5A7BBBAB97037"><enum>203.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated under this title shall be used to require any person to perform, or facilitate in any way the performance of, any abortion.</text></section> <section id="HEAE42A4134C64C0AAF5EE14CF9B08EC8"><enum>204.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in the preceding section shall remove the obligation of the Director of the Bureau of Prisons to provide escort services necessary for a female inmate to receive such service outside the Federal facility: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That nothing in this section in any way diminishes the effect of section 203 intended to address the philosophical beliefs of individual employees of the Bureau of Prisons. </text></section> 
<section id="H5739A3CD9C064DB2B918FFE3CA85F768"><enum>205.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not to exceed 5 percent of any appropriation made available for the current fiscal year for the Department of Justice in this Act may be transferred between such appropriations, but no such appropriation, except as otherwise specifically provided, shall be increased by more than 10 percent by any such transfers: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to this section shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That this section shall not apply to the following—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9FCB6846C1684182B9E4BAA2A64690AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>paragraph (23) under the heading <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36BEB83F0B3D4E418A1A59AE216D0A37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>paragraph (4) under the heading <quote>Community Oriented Policing Services Programs</quote>. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H797481AB4C7A489B965D3F9FE2A0BF1A"><enum>206.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this title may be used by the Federal Bureau of Prisons or the United States Marshals Service for the purpose of transporting an individual who is a prisoner pursuant to conviction for crime under State or Federal law and is classified as a maximum or high security prisoner, other than to a prison or other facility certified by the Federal Bureau of Prisons as appropriately secure for housing such a prisoner. </text></section> <section id="HED5C836BC5124489B270FC2245AFED85"><enum>207.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC55735A3DE3041979C99EDE475D7BC57"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated by this Act may be used by Federal prisons to purchase cable television services, or to rent or purchase audiovisual or electronic media or equipment used primarily for recreational purposes.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H798768EFC3FD48119D0FDC08D1FC2096"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Subsection (a) does not preclude the rental, maintenance, or purchase of audiovisual or electronic media or equipment for inmate training, religious, or educational programs. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H303EC273A0194EABBDA373F6BB093213"><enum>208.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this title shall be obligated or expended for any new or enhanced information technology program having total estimated development costs in excess of $100,000,000, unless the Deputy Attorney General and the investment review board certify to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate that the information technology program has appropriate program management controls and contractor oversight mechanisms in place, and that the program is compatible with the enterprise architecture of the Department of Justice. </text></section> 
<section id="H27B2281A3C234D5993A2BD4EC0EC6A01"><enum>209.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The notification thresholds and procedures set forth in section 505 of this Act shall apply to deviations from the amounts designated for specific activities in this Act and in the report accompanying this Act, and to any use of deobligated balances of funds provided under this title in previous years. </text></section> <section id="H13C09D44A0784F60BE0517F7B8F91AE8"><enum>210.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated by this Act may be used to plan for, begin, continue, finish, process, or approve a public-private competition under the Office of Management and Budget Circular A–76 or any successor administrative regulation, directive, or policy for work performed by employees of the Bureau of Prisons or of Federal Prison Industries, Incorporated. </text></section> 
<section id="H6B91C06E29A649F0B7B3836F6DB6E156"><enum>211.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no funds shall be available for the salary, benefits, or expenses of any United States Attorney assigned dual or additional responsibilities by the Attorney General or his designee that exempt that United States Attorney from the residency requirements of section 545 of title 28, United States Code.</text></section> <section id="H3114C48867ED40058279CC865C24E202"><enum>212.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1694E4FA31C345B5BEFD94AECCB7C1EF"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Subject to subsection (b), with respect to funds made available under this title for grant or reimbursement programs under the headings <quote>Office on Violence Against Women</quote>, <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote>, and <quote>Community Oriented Policing Services</quote>—</text> 
<paragraph id="HABB5F1DC81144552BE637FC0BA687FCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>up to 1 percent of funds may be transferred to and merged with funds provided to the National Institute of Justice and the Bureau of Justice Statistics, to be used for program evaluation purposes; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE7217D5241DE4B64AD16CF19A99FDBD1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not less than 0.4 percent of funds shall be transferred to the Office of Inspector General and remain available until expended for oversight and auditing purposes associated with programs administered under such accounts. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H54C6E777BC2642EA802CF426BCFA38CD"><enum>(b)</enum><text>This section shall not apply to—</text> <paragraph id="H103EB25973E74E2DA88356E20E37E787" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>paragraph (3)(C) under the heading <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote>; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB831640758F947C4A6AA223DC605F167" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>paragraph (8) under the heading <quote>Community Oriented Policing Services</quote>; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC5DC63419B4B48BFA95BC8948775881A" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any program for which funds are otherwise available, or authorized to be made available, by law for the purposes designated in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H46423B425EAD45D3B46ACB64C126F84F"><enum>213.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon request by a grantee for whom the Attorney General has determined there is a fiscal hardship, the Attorney General may, with respect to funds appropriated in this or any other Act making appropriations for fiscal years 2021 through 2024 for the following programs, waive the following requirements:</text> <paragraph id="HF879D41068CB4D358C4D33F20BD15365"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For the adult and juvenile offender State and local reentry demonstration projects under part FF of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10631">34 U.S.C. 10631 et seq.</external-xref>), the requirements under section 2976(g)(1) of such part (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10631">34 U.S.C. 10631(g)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F0FC96BFF8749BD91D078B814BD623A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For grants to protect inmates and safeguard communities as authorized by section 6 of the Prison Rape Elimination Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/30305">34 U.S.C. 30305(c)(3)</external-xref>), the requirements of section 6(c)(3) of such Act.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H13D37D585974411CA21705437FEC7F84"><enum>214.</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, section 20109(a) of subtitle A of title II of the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12109">34 U.S.C. 12109(a)</external-xref>) and section 506(b)(1) of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10157">34 U.S.C. 10157</external-xref>) shall not apply to amounts made available by this or any other Act.</text></section> 
<section id="H63613F3D46BF40F78A82FF66D90B0DEA"><enum>215.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this Act, other than for the national instant criminal background check system established under section 103 of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901</external-xref>), may be used by a Federal law enforcement officer to facilitate the transfer of an operable firearm to an individual if the Federal law enforcement officer knows or suspects that the individual is an agent of a drug cartel, unless law enforcement personnel of the United States continuously monitor or control the firearm at all times. </text></section> <section id="HFA3D436AB23D48338FB972338FCA57AE"><enum>216.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H13684B11DDD5450BA696FFBAE48BCD6E"><enum>(a)</enum><text>None of the income retained in the Department of Justice Working Capital Fund pursuant to title I of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/140">Public Law 102–140</external-xref> (105 Stat. 784; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/527">28 U.S.C. 527</external-xref> note) shall be available for obligation during fiscal year 2024, except up to $12,000,000 may be obligated for implementation of a unified Department of Justice financial management system.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC06A3C207A7E4778B431396FACC01A74"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Not to exceed $30,000,000 of the unobligated balances transferred to the capital account of the Department of Justice Working Capital Fund pursuant to title I of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/140">Public Law 102–140</external-xref> (105 Stat. 784; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/527">28 U.S.C. 527</external-xref> note) shall be available for obligation in fiscal year 2024, and any use, obligation, transfer, or allocation of such funds shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD945ADA1DF78484498BFCCD1264BB67C"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Not to exceed $10,000,000 of the excess unobligated balances available under section 524(c)(8)(E) of title 28, United States Code, shall be available for obligation during fiscal year 2024, and any use, obligation, transfer or allocation of such funds shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HAB409C3DB3EA4AD19A31D0E8B5544084"><enum>217.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate quarterly reports on the Crime Victims Fund, the Working Capital Fund, the Three Percent Fund, and the Asset Forfeiture Fund. Such quarterly reports shall contain at least the same level of information and detail for each Fund as was provided to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate in fiscal year 2022.</text></section> <section id="H5CDB516BCBBC434A9338784B55D58B19"><enum>218.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this Act may be used to conduct, contract for, or otherwise support, live tissue training, unless the Attorney General issues a written, non-delegable determination that such training is medically necessary and cannot be replicated by alternatives.</text></section> 
<section id="HE200682D0BF34799AB8DFB920CDC1A57"><enum>219.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0E3A836BCE3D42F89A204162FA693D97"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall issue—</text> <paragraph id="H6648CFAD40DE459ABF4AEF97F7B011B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an Environmental Impact Statement and Record of Decision for the proposed Federal Bureau of Prisons facilities in Letcher County, Kentucky, substantially in the form of the Record of Decision issued by the Federal Bureau of Prisons on April 12, 2018; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD6F6B50A911842219336711210833BF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>all studies, statements, and other authorizations that are necessary for the construction, operation, and maintenance of the proposed Federal Bureau of Prisons facilities in Letcher County, Kentucky, substantially in the form approved in the Record of Decision of the Federal Bureau of Prisons dated April 12, 2018.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H214735D7C0ED42389D400C2C4342BBC9"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The actions of the Attorney General and Director of the Federal Bureau of Prisons that are necessary for the construction and operation of the proposed Federal Bureau of Prisons facility in Letcher County, Kentucky shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></subsection></section><appropriations-small id="H6C3E965044954AC3A7A1CFA4B31664E1"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Department of Justice Appropriations Act, 2024</quote>. </text><pagebreak/></appropriations-small></title> <title id="H9C4280D4D6644795900F6D118F1516A6" style="appropriations"><enum>III</enum><appropriations-major id="H1509CB0ECECF43FB907D0E746FD824E8"><header>SCIENCE</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="HEA4340EC37D749C2841AFD7FFD80EC6B"><header>Office of science and technology policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, in carrying out the purposes of the National Science and Technology Policy, Organization, and Priorities Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6601">42 U.S.C. 6601 et seq.</external-xref>), hire of passenger motor vehicles, and services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, and rental of conference rooms in the District of Columbia, $5,544,000.</text></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-intermediate id="HC0C2575E7D7D4C36B7CBAB8A61C941DA"><header>National space council</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the National Space Council, in carrying out the purposes of title V of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/100/685">Public Law 100–685</external-xref> and Executive Order No. 13803, hire of passenger motor vehicles, and services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, not to exceed $2,250 for official reception and representation expenses, $1,865,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding any other provision of law, the National Space Council may accept personnel support from Federal agencies, departments, and offices, and such Federal agencies, departments, and offices may detail staff without reimbursement to the National Space Council for purposes provided herein. </text></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-intermediate id="H2FF7E66582E84C49A5FFD60E5AABBE6E"><header>National aeronautics and space administration</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H3A6449824DEF413580C489A94775C9DA"><header>SCIENCE</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of science research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $7,380,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H687764AA706B450A8940E554A74EB726"><header>AERONAUTICS</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of aeronautics research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $945,800,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H60167B5511DB46119DC3F8F028DEB2FC"><header>SPACE TECHNOLOGY</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of space technology research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $1,205,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That $227,000,000 shall be for On-orbit Servicing, Assembly, and Manufacturing 1: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That $110,000,000 shall be for the development, production, and demonstration of a nuclear thermal propulsion system, of which not less than $45,000,000 shall be for reactor development, not less than $45,000,000 shall be for fuel materials development, and not less than $20,000,000 shall be for non-nuclear systems development and acquisition planning: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, not later than 180 days after the enactment of this Act, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall provide a plan for the design of a flight demonstration.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HB45DD70CFF2143C097C1A8D0F60BF287"><header>EXPLORATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of Artemis Campaign Development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $7,971,091,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not less than $1,225,000,000 shall be for the Orion Multi-Purpose Crew Vehicle: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That not less than $2,506,100,000 shall be for the Space Launch System (SLS) launch vehicle, which shall have a lift capability not less than 130 metric tons and which shall have core elements and an Exploration Upper Stage developed simultaneously to be used to the maximum extent practicable, including for Earth to Moon missions and Moon landings: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amounts provided for SLS, not less than $600,000,000 shall be for SLS Block 1B development including the Exploration Upper Stage and associated systems including related facilitization, to support an SLS Block 1B mission available to launch in 2025 in addition to the planned Block 1 missions for Artemis I through Artemis III: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That $794,200,000 shall be for Exploration Ground Systems and associated Block 1B activities, including up to $501,800,000 for a second mobile launch platform: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall provide to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate, concurrent with the annual budget submission, a 5-year budget profile for an integrated system that includes the SLS, the Orion Multi-Purpose Crew Vehicle, and associated ground systems that will ensure a crewed launch as early as possible, as well as a system-based funding profile for a sustained launch cadence that contemplates the use of an SLS Block 1B cargo variant with an 8.4 meter fairing and associated ground systems: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That $3,234,900,000 shall be for Artemis Campaign Development. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H27D192AEE6C8455C94A03761105EC725"><header>SPACE OPERATIONS</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of space operations research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support and services; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities, including operations, production, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $4,344,609,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H3FAA9C4512A949CF855746C4E930D7FA"><header>SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY, ENGINEERING, AND MATHEMATICS ENGAGEMENT</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of aerospace and aeronautical education research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $89,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, of which $29,000,000 shall be for the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research and $60,000,000 shall be for the National Space Grant College and Fellowship Program. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H21C773EF583744F587B354236CE58F08"><header>SAFETY, SECURITY AND MISSION SERVICES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses, not otherwise provided for, in the conduct and support of science, aeronautics, space technology, exploration, space operations and education research and development activities, including research, development, operations, support, and services; maintenance and repair, facility planning and design; space flight, spacecraft control, and communications activities; program management; personnel and related costs, including uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; travel expenses; purchase and hire of passenger motor vehicles; not to exceed $63,000 for official reception and representation expenses; and purchase, lease, charter, maintenance, and operation of mission and administrative aircraft, $3,135,451,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That if available balances in the <quote>Science, Space, and Technology Education Trust Fund</quote> are not sufficient to provide for the grant disbursements required under the third and fourth provisos under such heading in the Department of Housing and Urban Development-Independent Agencies Appropriations Act, 1989 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/100/404">Public Law 100–404</external-xref>) as amended by the Departments of Veterans Affairs and Housing and Urban Development, and Independent Agencies Appropriations Act, 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/327">Public Law 103–327</external-xref>) up to $1,000,000 shall be available from amounts made available under this heading to make such grant disbursements: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That of the amounts appropriated under this heading, $36,261,000 shall be used for the projects, and in the amounts, specified for <quote>NASA-SSMS</quote> in the table entitled, <quote>Community Project Funding</quote>, in the report accompanying this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the amounts made available for the projects referenced in the preceding proviso may not be transferred for any other purpose. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H333D5103D4234DC59DFA229131DC3545"><header>CONSTRUCTION AND ENVIRONMENTAL COMPLIANCE AND RESTORATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for construction of facilities including repair, rehabilitation, revitalization, and modification of facilities, construction of new facilities and additions to existing facilities, facility planning and design, and restoration, and acquisition or condemnation of real property, as authorized by law, and environmental compliance and restoration, $247,900,000, to remain available until September 30, 2029: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That proceeds from leases deposited into this account shall be available for a period of 5 years to the extent and in amounts as provided in annual appropriations Acts: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That such proceeds referred to in the preceding proviso shall be available for obligation for fiscal year 2024 in an amount not to exceed $25,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That each annual budget request shall include an annual estimate of gross receipts and collections and proposed use of all funds collected pursuant to section 20145 of title 51, United States Code. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H8A02F6C0729E41C5874CA5D37696FCDC"><header>OFFICE OF INSPECTOR GENERAL</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of Inspector General in carrying out the Inspector General Act of 1978, $47,600,000, of which $500,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H1749B84D850B4B5793127B60A0F378A9"><header>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0A104E6C05BA47A5828639B169C53337"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFERS OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Funds for any announced prize otherwise authorized shall remain available, without fiscal year limitation, until a prize is claimed or the offer is withdrawn.</text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not to exceed 5 percent of any appropriation made available for the current fiscal year for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in this Act may be transferred between such appropriations, but no such appropriation, except as otherwise specifically provided, shall be increased by more than 10 percent by any such transfers. Any funds transferred to <quote>Construction and Environmental Compliance and Restoration</quote> for construction activities shall not increase that account by more than 15 percent and any funds transferred to or within <quote>Exploration</quote> for Exploration Ground Systems shall not increase Exploration Ground Systems by more than $49,300,000. Balances so transferred shall be merged with and available for the same purposes and the same time period as the appropriations to which transferred. Any transfer pursuant to this provision shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not to exceed 5 percent of any appropriation provided for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration under previous appropriations Acts that remains available for obligation or expenditure in fiscal year 2023 may be transferred between such appropriations, but no such appropriation, except as otherwise specifically provided, shall be increased by more than 10 percent by any such transfers. Any transfer pursuant to this provision shall retain its original availability and shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The spending plan required by this Act shall be provided by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration at the theme, program, project, and activity level. The spending plan, as well as any subsequent change of an amount established in that spending plan that meets the notification requirements of section 505 of this Act, shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section. </text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not more than 20 percent or $50,000,000, whichever is less, of the amounts made available in the current-year Construction and Environmental Compliance and Restoration (CECR) appropriation may be applied to CECR projects funded under previous years’ CECR appropriations. Use of current-year funds under this provision shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section.</text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Of the amounts made available in this Act under the heading <quote>Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics Engagement</quote> (<quote>STEM Engagement</quote>), up to $5,000,000 shall be available to jointly fund, with an additional amount of up to $1,000,000 each from amounts made available in this Act under the headings <quote>Science</quote>, <quote>Aeronautics</quote>, <quote>Space Technology</quote>, <quote>Exploration</quote>, and <quote>Space Operations</quote>, projects and activities for engaging students in STEM and increasing STEM research capacities of universities, including Minority Serving Institutions. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HB63E51C8B5C04950ACBDE6EF0AEAE201" commented="no"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not to exceed $18,162,000 made available for the current fiscal year in this Act within <quote>Safety, Security and Mission Services</quote> may be transferred to the Working Capital Fund of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Balances so transferred shall be available until expended only for activities described in section 30102(b)(3) of title 51, United States Code, as amended by this Act, and shall remain available until expended. Any transfer pursuant to this provision shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H096CADA542224943832D9413A92F6DC7"><header>National science foundation</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H696776AFE993437E8DFAD72CE84CE83C"><header>RESEARCH AND RELATED ACTIVITIES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses in carrying out the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1861">42 U.S.C. 1861 et seq.</external-xref>), and <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/86/209">Public Law 86–209</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1880">42 U.S.C. 1880 et seq.</external-xref>); services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code; maintenance and operation of aircraft and purchase of flight services for research support; acquisition of aircraft; and authorized travel; $7,866,646,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, of which not to exceed $680,000,000 shall remain available until expended for polar research and operations support, and for reimbursement to other Federal agencies for operational and science support and logistical and other related activities for the United States Antarctic program: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That receipts for scientific support services and materials furnished by the National Research Centers and other National Science Foundation supported research facilities may be credited to this appropriation. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H5F4495C13AF64A8ABFB103C83E378CC7"><header>MAJOR RESEARCH EQUIPMENT AND FACILITIES CONSTRUCTION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses for the acquisition, construction, commissioning, and upgrading of major research equipment, facilities, and other such capital assets pursuant to the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1861">42 U.S.C. 1861 et seq.</external-xref>), including authorized travel, $254,000,000, to remain available until expended. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H707713D6B3F3425F8D1BB6CBC97E2B75"><header>STEM EDUCATION </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses in carrying out science, mathematics, and engineering education and human resources programs and activities pursuant to the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1861">42 U.S.C. 1861 et seq.</external-xref>), including services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, authorized travel, and rental of conference rooms in the District of Columbia, $1,006,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H409ABC4B85F3442B95DD9592CA22DCBD"><header>AGENCY OPERATIONS AND AWARD MANAGEMENT</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For agency operations and award management necessary in carrying out the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1861">42 U.S.C. 1861 et seq.</external-xref>); services authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code; hire of passenger motor vehicles; uniforms or allowances therefor, as authorized by sections 5901 and 5902 of title 5, United States Code; rental of conference rooms in the District of Columbia; and reimbursement of the Department of Homeland Security for security guard services; $472,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $8,280 is for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That contracts may be entered into under this heading in fiscal year 2024 for maintenance and operation of facilities and for other services to be provided during the next fiscal year. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H79118D3AB36D4000A75D776A7863B9BB"><header>OFFICE OF THE NATIONAL SCIENCE BOARD</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses (including payment of salaries, authorized travel, hire of passenger motor vehicles, the rental of conference rooms in the District of Columbia, and the employment of experts and consultants under section 3109 of title 5, United States Code) involved in carrying out section 4 of the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1863">42 U.S.C. 1863</external-xref>) and <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/86/209">Public Law 86–209</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1880">42 U.S.C. 1880 et seq.</external-xref>), $4,600,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $2,500 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0B12E81C73BA48F3825C75F3A5279755"><header>OFFICE OF INSPECTOR GENERAL</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of Inspector General as authorized by the Inspector General Act of 1978, $26,810,000, of which $400,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2025. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H1A3D41BACB89414BAC401A811C33C0B5"><header>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HCD794DA8DD774C6DA39FB5988FFFFF17"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFERS OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not to exceed 5 percent of any appropriation made available for the current fiscal year for the National Science Foundation in this Act may be transferred between such appropriations, but no such appropriation shall be increased by more than 10 percent by any such transfers. Any transfer pursuant to this paragraph shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section.</text><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the National Science Foundation (NSF) shall notify the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate at least 30 days in advance of any planned divestment through transfer, decommissioning, termination, or deconstruction of any NSF-owned facilities or any NSF capital assets (including land, structures, and equipment) valued greater than $2,500,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H03DA3200574B4CD68B1847BACCE6C7C3"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Science Appropriations Act, 2024</quote>. <pagebreak/></text></appropriations-small></title> <title id="HA52469BA672B439B862A865CFDBD3AB5" style="appropriations"><enum>IV</enum><appropriations-major id="H0C211CC913534C8C8DF6764520FACDB1"><header>RELATED AGENCIES</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="H7BB07B698E4A4D9898D1A7F1E482E67F"><header>Commission on civil rights</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H5373871A4610412CAE6EEF475D86A5ED"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Commission on Civil Rights, including hire of passenger motor vehicles, $13,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That none of the funds appropriated in this paragraph may be used to employ any individuals under Schedule C of subpart C of part 213 of title 5 of the Code of Federal Regulations exclusive of one special assistant for each Commissioner: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That none of the funds appropriated in this paragraph shall be used to reimburse Commissioners for more than 75 billable days, with the exception of the chairperson, who is permitted 125 billable days: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Chair may accept and use any gift or donation to carry out the work of the Commission: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That none of the funds appropriated in this paragraph shall be used for any activity or expense that is not explicitly authorized by section 3 of the Civil Rights Commission Act of 1983 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1975a">42 U.S.C. 1975a</external-xref>).</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HF1CF79D34A774A6A8CBFD44134E31583"><header>Equal employment opportunity commission</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H662718D6180C4A468E074C4D6A3B6EC9"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission as authorized by title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967, the Equal Pay Act of 1963, the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, section 501 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, the Civil Rights Act of 1991, the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (GINA) of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/233">Public Law 110–233</external-xref>), the ADA Amendments Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/325">Public Law 110–325</external-xref>), and the Lilly Ledbetter Fair Pay Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/2">Public Law 111–2</external-xref>), including services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code; hire of passenger motor vehicles as authorized by section 1343(b) of title 31, United States Code; nonmonetary awards to private citizens; and up to $31,500,000 for payments to State and local enforcement agencies for authorized services to the Commission, $420,000,000: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the Commission is authorized to make available for official reception and representation expenses not to exceed $2,250 from available funds: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Commission may take no action to implement any workforce repositioning, restructuring, or reorganization until such time as the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate have been notified of such proposals, in accordance with the reprogramming requirements of section 505 of this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the Chair may accept and use any gift or donation to carry out the work of the Commission. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H5942CD3440C143B4A34F79BBEB6E35ED"><header>International trade commission</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HC6BAAFB2004C40469A999472D7AE05D7"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the International Trade Commission, including hire of passenger motor vehicles and services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, and not to exceed $2,250 for official reception and representation expenses, $122,400,000, to remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That none of the funds made available under this heading may be expended by the International Trade Commission to conduct Section 337 investigations asserting patent infringement, until the Commission implements a standing rule requiring each party to disclose the real parties in interest in all Section 337 patent litigation to ensure, inter alia, disclosure of any and all beneficial owners and investors in the litigation.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HEB4915A6D329411D99DEAF3BDA17C7E1"><header>Legal services corporation</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HF138002D606A4AE29EE587510E83E89F"><header>PAYMENT TO THE LEGAL SERVICES CORPORATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For payment to the Legal Services Corporation to carry out the purposes of the Legal Services Corporation Act of 1974, $489,000,000, of which $448,250,000 is for basic field programs and required independent audits; $6,000,000 is for the Office of Inspector General, of which such amounts as may be necessary may be used to conduct additional audits of recipients; $24,000,000 is for management and grants oversight; $4,500,000 is for client self-help and information technology; $4,250,000 is for a Pro Bono Innovation Fund; and $2,000,000 is for loan repayment assistance: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the Legal Services Corporation may continue to provide locality pay to officers and employees at a rate no greater than that provided by the Federal Government to Washington, DC-based employees as authorized by section 5304 of title 5, United States Code, notwithstanding section 1005(d) of the Legal Services Corporation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2996d">42 U.S.C. 2996d(d)</external-xref>): <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That the authorities provided in section 205 of this Act shall be applicable to the Legal Services Corporation: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, for the purposes of section 505 of this Act, the Legal Services Corporation shall be considered an agency of the United States Government. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HB60892AEE369472AA0859E3B54ADB952"><header>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISION—LEGAL SERVICES CORPORATION</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated in this Act to the Legal Services Corporation shall be expended for any purpose prohibited or limited by, or contrary to any of the provisions of, sections 501, 502, 503, 504, 505, and 506 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/119">Public Law 105–119</external-xref>, and all funds appropriated in this Act to the Legal Services Corporation shall be subject to the same terms and conditions set forth in such sections, except that all references in sections 502 and 503 to 1997 and 1998 shall be deemed to refer instead to 2023 and 2024, respectively. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HB9B4206531E1421AB61320BDC769CA66"><header>Marine mammal commission</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HC6A6C5336DA848B582792FBCAB2D36A9"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Marine Mammal Commission as authorized by title II of the Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1361">16 U.S.C. 1361 et seq.</external-xref>), $4,200,000.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H4506D5DE5549429689FD7A3E33129F2C"><header>Office of the united states trade representative</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H2ED38C79BC9A4D389E14B30541CADB25"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the Office of the United States Trade Representative, including the hire of passenger motor vehicles and the employment of experts and consultants as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, $56,000,000, of which $1,000,000 shall remain available until expended: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That of the total amount made available under this heading, not to exceed $124,000 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="HB5A26D46655744359053CBEA4A911268"><header>TRADE ENFORCEMENT TRUST FUND</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H4147B193081F4C71A869A755F89A61C0"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For activities of the United States Trade Representative authorized by section 611 of the Trade Facilitation and Trade Enforcement Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/4405">19 U.S.C. 4405</external-xref>), including transfers, $15,000,000, to be derived from the Trade Enforcement Trust Fund: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That any transfer pursuant to subsection (d)(1) of such section shall be treated as a reprogramming under section 505 of this Act. </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HB6C14389661C4AD4B636605CEAAFDBB5"><header>State justice institute</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H697162BB845440579C97EAF3C74832FD"><header>SALARIES AND EXPENSES</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For necessary expenses of the State Justice Institute, as authorized by the State Justice Institute Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10701">42 U.S.C. 10701 et seq.</external-xref>) $5,971,000, of which $500,000 shall remain available until September 30, 2025: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That not to exceed $2,250 shall be available for official reception and representation expenses: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That, for the purposes of section 505 of this Act, the State Justice Institute shall be considered an agency of the United States Government. </text><pagebreak/></appropriations-small></title> 
<title id="H80EB71FD30614690A5EA26ABD06DA8DB" style="appropriations"><enum>V</enum><appropriations-major id="H8FF9F48678034A8EB790AE373B040BCA"><header>GENERAL PROVISIONS</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-small id="HD6400B6354EF4BE194729EDFF1B94B5C"><header>(INCLUDING RESCISSIONS)</header></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0C9BC16984FE49059226B43FC612802A"><header>(INCLUDING TRANSFER OF FUNDS)</header></appropriations-small> 
<section id="HC13B4022169E42679408DFF48696C1F5"><enum>501.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No part of any appropriation contained in this Act shall be used for publicity or propaganda purposes not authorized by the Congress. </text></section> <section id="HF19281F0C23F4422B96EA8B25311FD79"><enum>502.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No part of any appropriation contained in this Act shall remain available for obligation beyond the current fiscal year unless expressly so provided herein.</text></section> 
<section id="HE1C433D3399B4C3A93C01DE1BF8018ED"><enum>503.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The expenditure of any appropriation under this Act for any consulting service through procurement contract, pursuant to section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, shall be limited to those contracts where such expenditures are a matter of public record and available for public inspection, except where otherwise provided under existing law, or under existing Executive order issued pursuant to existing law. </text></section> <section id="HEFB84C9774DF4576B7179DAE5040799D"><enum>504.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any provision of this Act or the application of such provision to any person or circumstances shall be held invalid, the remainder of the Act and the application of each provision to persons or circumstances other than those as to which it is held invalid shall not be affected thereby. </text></section> 
<section id="H7D8AB44CEF3B4901A86504A35969C409"><enum>505.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds provided under this Act, or provided under previous appropriations Acts to the agencies funded by this Act that remain available for obligation or expenditure in fiscal year 2024, or provided from any accounts in the Treasury of the United States derived by the collection of fees available to the agencies funded by this Act, shall be available for obligation or expenditure through a reprogramming of funds that: (1) creates or initiates a new program, project, or activity; (2) eliminates a program, project, or activity; (3) increases funds or personnel by any means for any project or activity for which funds have been denied or restricted; (4) relocates an office or employees; (5) reorganizes or renames offices, programs, or activities; (6) contracts out or privatizes any functions or activities presently performed by Federal employees; (7) augments existing programs, projects, or activities in excess of $500,000 or 10 percent, whichever is less, or reduces by 10 percent funding for any program, project, or activity, or numbers of personnel by 10 percent; or (8) results from any general savings, including savings from a reduction in personnel, which would result in a change in existing programs, projects, or activities as approved by Congress; unless the House and Senate Committees on Appropriations are notified 15 days in advance of such reprogramming of funds. </text></section> <section id="HCC6F6C8654AA47839BABB4945366E4A7"><enum>506.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5A16C554044C41E6A04C6F90978661AA"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If it has been finally determined by a court or Federal agency that any person intentionally affixed a label bearing a <quote>Made in America</quote> inscription, or any inscription with the same meaning, to any product sold in or shipped to the United States that is not made in the United States, the person shall be ineligible to receive any contract or subcontract made with funds made available in this Act, pursuant to the debarment, suspension, and ineligibility procedures described in sections 9.400 through 9.409 of title 48, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCEAF87CC4E8E4AD4AE9BE6D9B1A03DC7"><enum>(b)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H64A3F5527B594B3FBD8F1A472114FF04"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To the extent practicable, with respect to authorized purchases of promotional items, funds made available by this Act shall be used to purchase items that are manufactured, produced, or assembled in the United States, its territories or possessions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48FD3A0774C447E19BFA5C4BF49B0FA8" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>promotional items</quote> has the meaning given the term in OMB Circular A–87, Attachment B, Item (1)(f)(3). </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE759C28943F24E9CBB15F8FE49D7DE2F"><enum>507.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H32B2C593A67D457B807025DAA8010331"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Departments of Commerce and Justice, the National Science Foundation, and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall provide to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate a quarterly report on the status of balances of appropriations at the account level. For unobligated, uncommitted balances and unobligated, committed balances the quarterly reports shall separately identify the amounts attributable to each source year of appropriation from which the balances were derived. For balances that are obligated, but unexpended, the quarterly reports shall separately identify amounts by the year of obligation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9A8BC41B28ED43D78197684BA7CF1745"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The report described in subsection (a) shall be submitted within 30 days of the end of each quarter.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9316D8D60C7040D0BD96F08145AC1632"><enum>(c)</enum><text>If a department or agency is unable to fulfill any aspect of a reporting requirement described in subsection (a) due to a limitation of a current accounting system, the department or agency shall fulfill such aspect to the maximum extent practicable under such accounting system and shall identify and describe in each quarterly report the extent to which such aspect is not fulfilled. </text></subsection></section> <section id="HCBAC4A1B76D645D7916E8FF7CC98118F"><enum>508.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any costs incurred by a department or agency funded under this Act resulting from, or to prevent, personnel actions taken in response to funding reductions included in this Act shall be absorbed within the total budgetary resources available to such department or agency: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That the authority to transfer funds between appropriations accounts as may be necessary to carry out this section is provided in addition to authorities included elsewhere in this Act: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That use of funds to carry out this section shall be treated as a reprogramming of funds under section 505 of this Act and shall not be available for obligation or expenditure except in compliance with the procedures set forth in that section: <proviso><italic>Provided further,</italic></proviso> That for the Department of Commerce, this section shall also apply to actions taken for the care and protection of loan collateral or grant property.</text></section> 
<section id="H92E2F39594774ACB8C44473965B9703C"><enum>509.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds provided by this Act shall be available to promote the sale or export of tobacco or tobacco products, or to seek the reduction or removal by any foreign country of restrictions on the marketing of tobacco or tobacco products, except for restrictions which are not applied equally to all tobacco or tobacco products of the same type. </text></section> <section id="HFD97F47DB58245D6A20EA77190371487"><enum>510.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, amounts deposited or available in the Fund established by section 1402 of chapter XIV of title II of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/98/473">Public Law 98–473</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20101">34 U.S.C. 20101</external-xref>) in any fiscal year in excess of $1,200,000,000 shall not be available for obligation until the following fiscal year: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That notwithstanding section 1402(d) of such Act, of the amounts available from the Fund for obligation: (1) $7,500,000 shall be transferred to the Department of Justice Office of Inspector General and remain available until expended for oversight and auditing purposes associated with this section; and (2) 5 percent shall be available to the Office for Victims of Crime for grants, consistent with the requirements of the Victims of Crime Act, to Indian Tribes to improve services for victims of crime. </text></section> 
<section id="HD441DA0EA0284CE0AC28B73B61208440"><enum>511.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available to the Department of Justice in this Act may be used to discriminate against or denigrate the religious or moral beliefs of students who participate in programs for which financial assistance is provided from those funds, or of the parents or legal guardians of such students.</text></section> <section id="HAEE4278823864B7FA011347222D4D747"><enum>512.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be transferred to any department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States Government, except pursuant to a transfer made by, or transfer authority provided in, this Act or any other appropriations Act. </text></section> 
<section id="H53F121AF38B848C886E0BC3CD75861FF"><enum>513.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H71ABB999F0CE4F608F0B3FED1578667D"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Inspectors General of the Department of Commerce, the Department of Justice, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the National Science Foundation, and the Legal Services Corporation shall conduct audits, pursuant to the Inspector General Act (5 U.S.C. App.), of grants or contracts for which funds are appropriated by this Act, and shall submit reports to Congress on the progress of such audits, which may include preliminary findings and a description of areas of particular interest, within 180 days after initiating such an audit and every 180 days thereafter until any such audit is completed.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1B3E364295FB43CA8F271B755D3EE25D"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Within 60 days after the date on which an audit described in subsection (a) by an Inspector General is completed, the Secretary, Attorney General, Administrator, Director, or President, as appropriate, shall make the results of the audit available to the public on the Internet website maintained by the Department, Administration, Foundation, or Corporation, respectively. The results shall be made available in redacted form to exclude—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBD1090C1A6CC497083EC11A7528D49B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any matter described in section 552(b) of title 5, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9205F6E608914F8994DAB3BF295ABD50"><enum>(2)</enum><text>sensitive personal information for any individual, the public access to which could be used to commit identity theft or for other inappropriate or unlawful purposes.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1A0CBC04247647B3B82BD96977D4944F"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Any person awarded a grant or contract funded by amounts appropriated by this Act shall submit a statement to the Secretary of Commerce, the Attorney General, the Administrator, Director, or President, as appropriate, certifying that no funds derived from the grant or contract will be made available through a subcontract or in any other manner to another person who has a financial interest in the person awarded the grant or contract.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6CE124C83B8F48A58BB7D062CB00E4B2"><enum>(d)</enum><text>The provisions of the preceding subsections of this section shall take effect 30 days after the date on which the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, determines that a uniform set of rules and requirements, substantially similar to the requirements in such subsections, consistently apply under the executive branch ethics program to all Federal departments, agencies, and entities. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEA41174C402E42648C93DED1D473DDC0"><enum>514.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE48CBFFA594046FC87A1BC21F3C04EEA"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available under this Act may be used by the Departments of Commerce and Justice, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, or the National Science Foundation to acquire a high-impact or moderate-impact information system, as defined for security categorization in the National Institute of Standards and Technology's (NIST) Federal Information Processing Standard Publication 199, <quote>Standards for Security Categorization of Federal Information and Information Systems</quote> unless the agency has—</text> <paragraph id="HB908934809644E968D43D4B9FCDB0508"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reviewed the supply chain risk for the information systems against criteria developed by NIST and the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) to inform acquisition decisions for high-impact and moderate-impact information systems within the Federal Government;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2C7156EB8924D1AA5D99C8EE0C8D461"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reviewed the supply chain risk from the presumptive awardee against available and relevant threat information provided by the FBI and other appropriate agencies; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1BB06A07F6844159BA333D4484BFEF0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in consultation with the FBI or other appropriate Federal entity, conducted an assessment of any risk of cyber-espionage or sabotage associated with the acquisition of such system, including any risk associated with such system being produced, manufactured, or assembled by one or more entities identified by the United States Government as posing a cyber threat, including but not limited to, those that may be owned, directed, or subsidized by the People's Republic of China, the Islamic Republic of Iran, the Democratic People's Republic of Korea, or the Russian Federation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1015D9D62CB448FBBFD26C953BF6FB5B"><enum>(b)</enum><text>None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available under this Act may be used to acquire a high-impact or moderate-impact information system reviewed and assessed under subsection (a) unless the head of the assessing entity described in subsection (a) has—</text> <paragraph id="H0AE19EC7747C458597615B041D99E100"><enum>(1)</enum><text>developed, in consultation with NIST, the FBI, and supply chain risk management experts, a mitigation strategy for any identified risks;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBA033A52B6824C54A279075DB8A0B873"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determined, in consultation with NIST and the FBI, that the acquisition of such system is in the national interest of the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2EEE701FE5B945A0A9D9EE43271C6A7B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>reported that determination to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate and the agency Inspector General. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H785909BB60A4418386EF1CBCC2D4ACD0"><enum>515.</enum><text>None of the funds made available in this Act shall be used in any way whatsoever to support or justify the use of torture by any official or contract employee of the United States Government. </text></section> <section id="HDC8D54AA26354BE180DF99C6CAC4E8F1"><enum>516.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be used to include in any new bilateral or multilateral trade agreement the text of—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCBC0E915DB6E4A6687C09E0D17CA4987"><enum>(1)</enum><text>paragraph 2 of article 16.7 of the United States–Singapore Free Trade Agreement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC60286254FD74420908B4A508AACAB29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>paragraph 4 of article 17.9 of the United States–Australia Free Trade Agreement; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H99C881B3609D40878A79D2E49CEC65D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>paragraph 4 of article 15.9 of the United States–Morocco Free Trade Agreement. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H86242395A0574E9E92A6D6F481A4652E"><enum>517.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be used to authorize or issue a national security letter in contravention of any of the following laws authorizing the Federal Bureau of Investigation to issue national security letters: The Right to Financial Privacy Act of 1978; The Electronic Communications Privacy Act of 1986; The Fair Credit Reporting Act; The National Security Act of 1947; USA PATRIOT Act; USA FREEDOM Act of 2015; and the laws amended by these Acts. </text></section> 
<section id="H70E9D868C220493EB0B9A8E688BA92D9"><enum>518.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If at any time during any quarter, the program manager of a project within the jurisdiction of the Departments of Commerce or Justice, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, or the National Science Foundation totaling more than $75,000,000 has reasonable cause to believe that the total program cost has increased by 10 percent or more, the program manager shall immediately inform the respective Secretary, Administrator, or Director. The Secretary, Administrator, or Director shall notify the House and Senate Committees on Appropriations within 30 days in writing of such increase, and shall include in such notice: the date on which such determination was made; a statement of the reasons for such increases; the action taken and proposed to be taken to control future cost growth of the project; changes made in the performance or schedule milestones and the degree to which such changes have contributed to the increase in total program costs or procurement costs; new estimates of the total project or procurement costs; and a statement validating that the project's management structure is adequate to control total project or procurement costs. </text></section> <section id="HCE25CF297A064C37BCF0CFCEAFA05453"><enum>519.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds appropriated by this Act, or made available by the transfer of funds in this Act, for intelligence or intelligence related activities are deemed to be specifically authorized by the Congress for purposes of section 504 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3094">50 U.S.C. 3094</external-xref>) during fiscal year 2024 until the enactment of the Intelligence Authorization Act for fiscal year 2024. </text></section> 
<section id="H69D0562824F6438A812674DAC494D6DF"><enum>520.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available by this Act may be used to enter into a contract in an amount greater than $5,000,000 or to award a grant in excess of such amount unless the prospective contractor or grantee certifies in writing to the agency awarding the contract or grant that, to the best of its knowledge and belief, the contractor or grantee has filed all Federal tax returns required during the three years preceding the certification, has not been convicted of a criminal offense under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, and has not, more than 90 days prior to certification, been notified of any unpaid Federal tax assessment for which the liability remains unsatisfied, unless the assessment is the subject of an installment agreement or offer in compromise that has been approved by the Internal Revenue Service and is not in default, or the assessment is the subject of a non-frivolous administrative or judicial proceeding. </text></section><appropriations-small id="HAB6C768F17CD4BA884DE391E7515E431"><header>(RESCISSIONS)</header></appropriations-small> <section id="H39A93F5F75C744FD94F60F330823DF29"><enum>521.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4A486579055E4EA88C9BE7446AA7B0CF"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Of the unobligated balances from prior year appropriations available to the Department of Commerce under the heading <quote>Economic Development Administration, Economic Development Assistance Programs</quote>, $25,000,000 are hereby permanently cancelled, not later than September 30, 2024.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1A9FA7CEF945443A9D43AF140DDF0499"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the unobligated balances from prior year appropriations available to the Department of Justice, the following funds are hereby permanently rescinded, not later than September 30, 2024, from the following accounts in the specified amounts—</text> <paragraph id="H495294795E0E4436A80C46807ACC8819"><enum>(1)</enum><text><quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Activities, Office on Violence Against Women, Violence Against Women Prevention and Prosecution Programs</quote>, $5,000,000;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2A772655481E489AB0781CA84D7CB594"><enum>(2)</enum><text><quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Activities, Office of Justice Programs</quote>, $120,000,000; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65C9052E69B649FBBE876952A6C1586A"><enum>(3)</enum><text><quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Activities, Community Oriented Policing Services</quote>, $15,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HADABAD5F94F246E59619A25D1A563682"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the unobligated balances available to the Department of Justice, <quote>Working Capital Fund</quote>, $82,572,000 is hereby permanently rescinded.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8156D97031DB4CED9EA922257DAF2371"><enum>(d)</enum><text>The Departments of Commerce and Justice shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report no later than September 1, 2023, specifying the amount of each rescission made pursuant to subsections (a), (b), (c) and (d).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H108E532355BB433C8D3EE71304FBD495"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the unobligated balances available in <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, $12,900,000,000 available under section 10301(1)(A)(ii) and $9,125,000,000 available under section 10301(1)(A)(iii) as of the date of the enactment of this Act are rescinded. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HBBDC681C8A774A9D9ED54F65FE0E320C"><enum>(f)</enum><text>The amounts rescinded in subsections (a), (b), (c) and (d) shall not be from amounts that were designated by the Congress as an emergency or disaster relief requirement pursuant to the concurrent resolution on the budget or the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDE287928D3404F588BC6A4720F3EA309"><enum>(g)</enum><text>The amounts rescinded pursuant to subsections (c) and (d) shall not be from amounts provided under—</text> <paragraph id="H794D6A4831564FBC81683E42F898DBC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>subparagraph (Q) of paragraph (1) under the heading <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Activities—Office of Justice Programs—State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance</quote> in title II of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84401B83876641F981D1E39ED640F637"><enum>(2)</enum><text>paragraph (7) under the heading <quote>State and Local Law Enforcement Activities—Community Oriented Policing Services—Community Oriented Policing Services Programs</quote> in title II of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4FB0712DCC32484CB31EAB38858B805E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subparagraph (Q) of paragraph (1) under the heading “State and Local Law Enforcement Activities—Office of Justice Programs—State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance” in title II of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBB8E298A9BE4A4196DF77BBCA6CEC84"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">amounts provided under paragraph (7) under the heading “State and Local Law Enforcement Activities—Community Oriented Policing Services—Community Oriented Policing Services Programs” in title II of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2DDE15819E154D66B7062C3A638B6ACB"><enum>522.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be used to purchase first class or premium airline travel in contravention of sections 301–10.122 through 301–10.124 of title 41 of the Code of Federal Regulations. </text></section> 
<section id="HF243331F6801444CBC395C5BFD239265"><enum>523.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be used to send or otherwise pay for the attendance of more than 50 employees from a Federal department or agency, who are stationed in the United States, at any single conference occurring outside the United States unless—</text> <paragraph id="H715297AD3D1D450CBAB93EF7D4EC9062"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such conference is a law enforcement training or operational conference for law enforcement personnel and the majority of Federal employees in attendance are law enforcement personnel stationed outside the United States; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF15A4937D2745468649F195B57F74FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such conference is a scientific conference and the department or agency head determines that such attendance is in the national interest and notifies the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate within at least 15 days of that determination and the basis for that determination. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H6C611EB5C4C642BABC215E4A4095BB8F"><enum>524.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall instruct any department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States receiving funds appropriated under this Act to track undisbursed balances in expired grant accounts and include in its annual performance plan and performance and accountability reports the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H58BF47ED3C14408C911C009646492B0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Details on future action the department, agency, or instrumentality will take to resolve undisbursed balances in expired grant accounts.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7E5F0E116144D15AFE14C1797A20F21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The method that the department, agency, or instrumentality uses to track undisbursed balances in expired grant accounts.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBBDDAD38806242919E3D899BA46F6032"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Identification of undisbursed balances in expired grant accounts that may be returned to the Treasury of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF68B0775D9B7416489A83C6B75A458C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the preceding 3 fiscal years, details on the total number of expired grant accounts with undisbursed balances (on the first day of each fiscal year) for the department, agency, or instrumentality and the total finances that have not been obligated to a specific project remaining in the accounts.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF225F7AA24E44824AD6B3E2A87A22074"><enum>525.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to move the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF) Canine Training Center or the ATF National Canine Division from Front Royal, Virginia, to another location.</text></section> <section id="H0428918D87A9473DA38DEB7687F902C4"><enum>526.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAAD443CC46A84C7F91E36E2191D021CF"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), the Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP), or the National Space Council (NSC) to develop, design, plan, promulgate, implement, or execute a bilateral policy, program, order, or contract of any kind to participate, collaborate, or coordinate bilaterally in any way with China or any Chinese-owned company unless such activities are specifically authorized by a law enacted after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF304775763724FC2B709E1F7417D511E"><enum>(b)</enum><text>None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to effectuate the hosting of official Chinese visitors at facilities belonging to or utilized by NASA.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCDAF85F3EBAA4EBC83F24D0CD999DE66"><enum>(c)</enum><text>The limitations described in subsections (a) and (b) shall not apply to activities which NASA, OSTP, or NSC, after consultation with the Federal Bureau of Investigation, have certified—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBA32BE062AFE41E7B6C9DBD884B3F5F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pose no risk of resulting in the transfer of technology, data, or other information with national security or economic security implications to China or a Chinese-owned company; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H06540A4D462C41F3A9AE4833348BDBC7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>will not involve knowing interactions with officials who have been determined by the United States to have direct involvement with violations of human rights.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5C0780C83F1942B18F34952520A71C3D"><enum>(d)</enum><text>Any certification made under subsection (c) shall be submitted to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and the Federal Bureau of Investigation, no later than 30 days prior to the activity in question and shall include a description of the purpose of the activity, its agenda, its major participants, and its location and timing.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H50CBFAA483244270B1691C3BB7769743"><enum>527.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5FFF334C05084ADF85283EA375445938"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available in this Act may be used to maintain or establish a computer network unless such network blocks the viewing, downloading, and exchanging of pornography.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5C48B15BEB7C418DA1EB453F68DB27B1"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Nothing in subsection (a) shall limit the use of funds necessary for any Federal, State, Tribal, or local law enforcement agency or any other entity carrying out criminal investigations, prosecution, adjudication, or other law enforcement- or victim assistance-related activity. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H512943054FD64198B3F9BEEC3B10BEF7"><enum>528.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Departments of Commerce and Justice, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the National Science Foundation, the Commission on Civil Rights, the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, the International Trade Commission, the Legal Services Corporation, the Marine Mammal Commission, the Offices of Science and Technology Policy and the United States Trade Representative, the National Space Council, and the State Justice Institute shall submit spending plans, signed by the respective department or agency head, to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate not later than 45 days after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></section> 
<section id="HD5E6D84BE5954E26984A8CC5AA99958D"><enum>529.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, none of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available by this Act may be used to pay award or incentive fees for contractor performance that has been judged to be below satisfactory performance or for performance that does not meet the basic requirements of a contract. </text></section> <section id="H03CA02D6DD274173BD4023EBB701830B"><enum>530.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used in contravention of section 7606 (<quote>Legitimacy of Industrial Hemp Research</quote>) of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/79">Public Law 113–79</external-xref>) by the Department of Justice or the Drug Enforcement Administration. </text></section> 
<section id="HE81B332CE56B47C49D8C37EE54F0AF05"><enum>531.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this Act to the Department of Justice may be used, with respect to any of the States of Alabama, Alaska, Arizona, Arkansas, California, Colorado, Connecticut, Delaware, Florida, Georgia, Hawaii, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, Nevada, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, North Carolina, North Dakota, Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah, Vermont, Virginia, Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin, and Wyoming, or with respect to the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, or Puerto Rico, to prevent any of them from implementing their own laws that authorize the use, distribution, possession, or cultivation of medical marijuana. </text></section> <section id="H311FEA775AA94EC782AAD2B3BDF93B06"><enum>532.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Commerce, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, and the National Science Foundation shall provide a quarterly report to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate on any official travel to China by any employee of such department or agency, including the purpose of such travel.</text></section> 
<section id="HFC6F7D49BA3E464F8C6C7733B01D3E56"><enum>533.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amounts made available by this Act, not less than 10 percent of each total amount provided, respectively, for grants authorized by section 27 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3722">15 U.S.C. 3722</external-xref>) shall be allocated for assistance in persistent poverty counties: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That for purposes of this section, the term <quote>persistent poverty counties</quote> means any county that has had 20 percent or more of its population living in poverty over the past 30 years, as measured by the 1993 Small Area Income and Poverty Estimates, the 2000 decennial census, and the most recent Small Area Income and Poverty Estimates, or any Territory or possession of the United States. </text></section> 
<section id="HAADA2B76181544F2AD7529FC88FC8680" commented="no"><enum>534.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H08419A710E6E4318AB8590114A84EFD4"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law or treaty, none of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available under this Act or any other Act may be expended or obligated by a department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States to pay administrative expenses or to compensate an officer or employee of the United States in connection with requiring an export license for the export to Canada of components, parts, accessories or attachments for firearms listed in Category I, section 121.1 of title 22, Code of Federal Regulations (International Trafficking in Arms Regulations (ITAR), part 121, as it existed on April 1, 2005) with a total value not exceeding $500 wholesale in any transaction, provided that the conditions of subsection (b) of this section are met by the exporting party for such articles.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBC7729073ECC48A489664D1B1B7ED196" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The foregoing exemption from obtaining an export license—</text> 
<paragraph id="H423F8E75600A42C9A52181627CB4AD38" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>does not exempt an exporter from filing any Shipper's Export Declaration or notification letter required by law, or from being otherwise eligible under the laws of the United States to possess, ship, transport, or export the articles enumerated in subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDD0525C7DEBA4F6ABD5DB749FF267573" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not permit the export without a license of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H65115200EC384A9696B3950562BD6D3E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fully automatic firearms and components and parts for such firearms, other than for end use by the Federal Government, or a Provincial or Municipal Government of Canada;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D238C7F45F14881904BF16FB7E15F0B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>barrels, cylinders, receivers (frames) or complete breech mechanisms for any firearm listed in Category I, other than for end use by the Federal Government, or a Provincial or Municipal Government of Canada; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB611D14B088146F7917827F1CF7D8A36" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>articles for export from Canada to another foreign destination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA1B0EF2A0AFC4D23AAAA6A5D0B9E1261" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with this section, the District Directors of Customs and postmasters shall permit the permanent or temporary export without a license of any unclassified articles specified in subsection (a) to Canada for end use in Canada or return to the United States, or temporary import of Canadian-origin items from Canada for end use in the United States or return to Canada for a Canadian citizen.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB429B7BC9EAE436C88A920DF31AE1259" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may require export licenses under this section on a temporary basis if the President determines, upon publication first in the Federal Register, that the Government of Canada has implemented or maintained inadequate import controls for the articles specified in subsection (a), such that a significant diversion of such articles has and continues to take place for use in international terrorism or in the escalation of a conflict in another nation. The President shall terminate the requirements of a license when reasons for the temporary requirements have ceased.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HCD41B58ADDC441ADBA36DFCB0C9FEAF3" commented="no"><enum>535.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter, no department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States receiving appropriated funds under this Act or any other Act shall obligate or expend in any way such funds to pay administrative expenses or the compensation of any officer or employee of the United States to deny, or fail to act on, any application submitted pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(b)(1)(B)</external-xref> and qualified pursuant to 27 CFR section 478.112 or .113, for a permit to import United States origin <quote>curios or relics</quote> firearms, parts, or ammunition. </text></section> 
<section id="HA2557CEA04F3475D80DD8B5738565B7F" commented="no"><enum>536.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter, none of the funds made available by this Act may be used to pay the salaries or expenses of personnel to deny, or fail to act on, an application for the importation of any model of shotgun if—</text> <paragraph id="HD7D377120DA34C44BA36D6C29A3A1158" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all other requirements of law with respect to the proposed importation are met; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H808EA4E88749433F848491E61CB32DA1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no application for the importation of such model of shotgun, in the same configuration, had been denied by the Attorney General prior to January 1, 2011, on the basis that the shotgun was not particularly suitable for or readily adaptable to sporting purposes.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HEA096E44A6344B5696E341926851AAAA"><enum>537.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to require a person licensed under section 923 of title 18, United States Code, to report information to the Department of Justice regarding the sale of multiple rifles or shotguns to the same person. </text></section> 
<section id="HFA7F6E39C151488EB1CB6D1B857422F2" commented="no"><enum>538.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be obligated or expended to implement the Arms Trade Treaty until the Senate approves a resolution of ratification for the Treaty. </text></section> <section id="HEAF6E05FEF87415E810631B9AE5B5FF1" commented="no"><enum>539.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available in this or any other Act may be used to transfer, release, or assist in the transfer or release to or within the United States, its territories, or possessions Khalid Sheikh Mohammed or any other detainee who—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD521332E720843A8B7DA42C793CD0BDC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not a United States citizen or a member of the Armed Forces of the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDADA925F4BF45A19824860201F2019B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is or was held on or after June 24, 2009, at the United States Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, by the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H068A3FB1625343E0A8270C152D247686" commented="no"><enum>540.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1750D81765FF4679956235D64189ACF0"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available in this or any other Act may be used to construct, acquire, or modify any facility in the United States, its territories, or possessions to house any individual described in subsection (c) for the purposes of detention or imprisonment in the custody or under the effective control of the Department of Defense.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFCE54F2608134E068DD7E2A4ED65D644" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The prohibition in subsection (a) shall not apply to any modification of facilities at United States Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA4C8A92AFD354A108EB617E49410D6FE" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><text>An individual described in this subsection is any individual who, as of June 24, 2009, is located at United States Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, and who—</text> <paragraph id="H7822B72EDD0847F185081D9B42E390E4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not a citizen of the United States or a member of the Armed Forces of the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8356E568EE5C4C2C880B4210A30F2A3A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is—</text> <subparagraph id="H37EEE7F68441473E97706B2DAE9EC076" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the custody or under the effective control of the Department of Defense; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1AE981F965D647B0AE47AF23604B4AA5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise under detention at United States Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HAB2FC2E99BF4491B96A6B06A075E540B"><enum>541.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB0DC4EE3B3E34E69A86C125230A50A8E"><enum>(a)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0526F4708C72442F9E872C8725B0890B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 45 days of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall allocate amounts made available from the Creating Helpful Incentives to Produce Semiconductors (CHIPS) for America Fund for fiscal year 2024 pursuant to paragraphs (1) and (2) of section 102(a) of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (division A of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>), including the transfer authority in such paragraphs of that section of that Act, to the accounts specified, in the amounts specified, and for the projects and activities specified, in the table titled <quote>Department of Commerce Allocation of National Institute of Standards and Technology Funds: CHIPS Act Fiscal Year 2024</quote> in the report accompanying this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF00281FAF28340F498DC11F8F1B5348D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 45 days of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Science Foundation shall allocate amounts made available from the Creating Helpful Incentives to Produce Semiconductors (CHIPS) for America Workforce and Education Fund for fiscal year 2024 pursuant to section 102(d)(1) of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (division A of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>), to the account specified, in the amounts specified, and for the projects and activities specified in the table titled <quote>National Science Foundation Allocation of Funds: CHIPS Act Fiscal Year 2024</quote> in the report accompanying this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4BC3725B57E24703AF198F8AC8AEC0A3"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Neither the President nor his designee may allocate any amounts that are made available for any fiscal year under section 102(a)(2)(A) of the CHIPS Act of 2022 or under section 102(d)(2) of such Act if there is in effect an Act making or continuing appropriations for part of a fiscal year for the Departments of Commerce and Justice, Science, and Related Agencies: <proviso><italic>Provided,</italic></proviso> That in any fiscal year, the matter preceding this proviso shall not apply to the allocation, apportionment, or allotment of amounts for continuing administration of programs allocated funds from the CHIPS for America Fund, which may be allocated only in amounts that are no more than the allocation for such purposes in subsection (a) of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7DB31FAFB38142E19966EC5A8CD9C8E5"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to prior consultation with, and the regular notification procedures of, the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and subject to the terms and conditions in section 505 of this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H4EE1CE8ED2184664B1D632698AACE87F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Commerce may reallocate funds allocated to Industrial Technology Services for section 9906 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref> by subsection (a)(1) of this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H770B9D78743E4FAA8B43677F4124DF4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the National Science Foundation may reallocate funds allocated to the CHIPS for America Workforce and Education Fund by subsection (a)(2) of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1075188403C64845942DAA708695B333"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concurrent with the annual budget submission of the President for fiscal year 2025, the Secretary of Commerce and the Director of the National Science Foundation, as appropriate, shall each submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate proposed allocations by account and by program, project, or activity, with detailed justifications, for amounts made available under section 102(a)(2) and section 102(d)(2) of the CHIPS Act of 2022 for fiscal year 2025. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEE2C94D06D654E44B17467585335396F"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Commerce and the National Science Foundation, as appropriate, shall each provide the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and Senate quarterly reports on the status of balances of projects and activities funded by the CHIPS for America Fund for amounts allocated pursuant to subsection (a)(1) of this section, and section 543(a)(1) of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>, the status of balances of projects and activities funded by the Public Wireless Supply Chain Innovation Fund for amounts allocated pursuant to section 543(a)(2) of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>, and the status of balances of projects and activities funded by the CHIPS for America Workforce and Education Fund for amounts allocated pursuant to subsection (a)(2) of this section and section 543(a)(3) of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>, including all uncommitted, committed, and unobligated funds.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE7F4EF1AA8F149A39883F44B017A2A08"><enum>542.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out a rule that includes area or time closures in the South Atlantic until data from the South Atlantic Great Red Snapper Count can be incorporated into the stock assessment.</text></section> 
<section id="HB006D1072C9841D989C03E26128626FE"><enum>543.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out Executive Order 14006, <quote>Reforming Our Incarceration System to Eliminate the Use of Privately Operated Criminal Detention Facilities.</quote></text></section> <section id="H3D98007A29894FA3A70B96E8B1A2A908"><enum>544.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, carry out, or defend any part of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives final rule entitled, <quote>Definition of <quote>Frame or Receiver</quote> and Identification of Firearms</quote> (87 Fed. Reg. 24652; published April 26, 2022).</text></section> 
<section id="HC324A2749FC542E9A7D68A304907ABAF"><enum>545.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out Executive Order 14092, <quote>Reducing Gun Violence and Making our Communities Safer.</quote></text></section> <section id="H1D6A2E58AE8F46D2B32F91730E6004BF"><enum>546.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, carry out, or defend the joint Department of Justice and Department of Homeland Security interim final rule entitled, <quote>Procedures for Credible Fear Screening and Consideration of Asylum, Withholding of Removal, and CAT Protection Claims by Asylum Officers</quote> (87 Fed. Reg. 18078; published March 29, 2022).</text></section> 
<section id="HAB93F7B4B96F43CC9077F6B4BD8B7C35"><enum>547.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used by the Department of Justice to promulgate a regulation regarding asylum law and process or regarding administrative closure of cases in immigration court.</text></section> <section id="H47807430A1B54EEBAA75A13CDE261754"><enum>548.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out section 19 (establishing accreditation standards) or section 20 (supporting safe and effective policing through grantmaking) of Executive Order 14074, <quote>Advancing Effective, Accountable, Policing and Criminal Justice Practices to Enhance Public Trust and Public Safety.</quote></text></section> 
<section id="HA4B8CEE9E08A476BBCB129533EA804B1"><enum>549.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out any regulation issued by the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives issued or finalized on or after January 21, 2021.</text></section> <section id="H8B97B00B565642CF8510B2689374BA1A"><enum>550.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, carry out, or defend of any part of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives final rule entitled, <quote>Factoring Criteria for Firearms with Attached <quote>Stabilizing Braces</quote></quote> (88 Fed. Reg. 6478; published January 31, 2023).</text></section> 
<section id="H27426CDCC31749848D2E07FE0253B6A9"><enum>551.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out the Attorney General’s October 4, 2021, memorandum entitled, <quote>Partnership Among Federal, State, Local, Tribal, and Territorial Law Enforcement to Address Threats Against School Administrators, Board Members, Teachers, and Staff.</quote></text></section> <section id="HFE7CC88C578C439483BACF22909E14FF"><enum>552.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out the Office of Science and Technology Policy’s August 25, 2022, Memorandum to Executive Departments and Agencies entitled, <quote>Ensuring Free, Immediate, and Equitable Access to Federally Funded Research.</quote></text></section> 
<section id="H04CB6E3A3E994EE7B112E00BE4F96A89"><enum>553.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used—</text> <paragraph id="H4ECD188D9035406BAB88A5D87D8548E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H19FCEE9B1C6A4406AD98F1F934E9E086"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Department of Commerce—</text> <clause id="HFCE1E02C30D34BC990DD43D42DB69E37"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Equity (DEIA) Council;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB75AD2798D6A47EE96030E66CE632141"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Institute of Standards and Technology Diversity, Equity, Inclusion and Accessibility Initiative;</text></clause> <clause id="HB1ADEA89E89041528DB241A214650C64"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration—</text> 
<subclause id="H7B75DB249DE64DF8BC749AAB8F1DC964"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Office of Inclusion and Civil Rights;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3A15E10BD80A4311B71867F29BEBE58D"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Diversity and Inclusion Advisory Management Council;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE1E66DC816F14A998066F160E3CC898D"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">NOAA Diversity and Professional Advancement Working Group;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FBC0789B1A54E21ACC63AEF6FDB3233"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Department of Justice—</text> 
<clause id="H5861E5C2C269446F91A5B8B79808906F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chief Diversity Officer;</text></clause> <clause id="H5B672DB216A64889A586AA553A0DB866"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives Diversity and Career Impact Program;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB812025D9CEE480A9A9CC989F4136C91"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal Bureau of Investigation Office of Diversity and Inclusion;</text></clause> <clause id="HAF6A1570018148C7816500D04B71A721"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Antitrust Division Diversity Committee;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H91BC699E11A048CC94CC88F3B03A5B55"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Resource Center for Justice-Involved LGBTQ+ and Two-Spirit Youth;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H17DBB1F609584DEF804406AE63E82054"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Aeronautics and Space Administration Office of Diversity and Inclusion;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H66EF624CBFD5477C9E9BC61790190058"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Science Foundation—</text> <clause id="HB217661D6B934BF391E7DCB4AB8EA040"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Office of Equity and Civil Rights;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H36619DF379B14AC6981491C07CFF4F81"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) Program;</text></clause> <clause id="H24B0E1D393E0475386F84ABFECD8C558"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP);</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H68B09D2C3D2445258DE5C47CF8D973A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out—</text> <subparagraph id="HC94A0044EF754332AC7D0DD680621A5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 13985 of January 20, 2021, “Advancing Racial Equity and Support for Underserved Communities Through the Federal Government” (86 Fed. Reg. 7009);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13FA91736FAC41579048E0630BBABF6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 14091 of February 16, 2023, “Further Advancing Racial Equity and Support for Underserved Communities Through the Federal Government” (88 Fed. Reg. 10825); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4D70ED6FE295447A94D37B01E25AF396"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 14035 of June 25, 2021, “Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, and Accessibility in the Federal Workforce” (86 Fed. Reg. 34593); or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F12563CCEB04B558209913FBDBFDA52"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to conduct any diversity, equity, inclusion, or implicit bias training.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H1DC832662B4944B29E7D6CEACAD94323"><enum>554.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCC057BA6E6D546DB91C98B0C0F6EA294"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by the—</text> <subparagraph id="HF6204C373E264A01A0E762211AEDC786"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Department of Commerce for—</text> 
<clause id="H90EA5759CF7F447FB6F930F34EC744D7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the National Institute of Standards and Technology Center of Excellence in Climate Change; or</text></clause> <clause id="H3500EDD382B840BD8986426722095C88"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">climate change fisheries research;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68D2C6BB37D841A6AC876CBEFA0F8BA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">National Science Foundation for the—</text> <clause id="H2FA8EE10529348E1AD8ECA0A90776BF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">U.S. Global Change Research Program (USGCRP); or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB264847EC36845129DA87E6D16595C96"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clean Energy Technology program; or</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F1541423BCF4CD4A13F4B86B23EB941"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to implement, administer, apply, enforce, or carry out Executive Order 14008 of January 27, 2021, <quote>Tackling the Climate Crisis at Home and Abroad</quote> (86 Fed. Reg. 7619).</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HA1B105B942FD4EAA9DE6F022776D374A"><enum>555.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to develop or implement guidance related to the valuation of ecosystem and environmental services and natural assets in Federal regulatory decision-making, as directed by Executive Order 14072 (87 Fed. Reg. 24851, relating to strengthening the Nation’s forests, communities, and local economies).</text></section> <section id="H6068CAEBBE75448D8B22D89AF5589319"><enum>556.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to provide legal representation to any alien in a removal proceeding. </text></section> 
<section id="H9BA47109DACE419080C98F17C63FC927"><enum>557.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to incentivize any immigration judge to close or dismiss any case without adjudicating the merits of the case.</text></section> <section id="H471537C995A44F5E90803B918604BC9E"><enum>558.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available for the State Criminal Alien Assistance Program may be used in contravention of section 642 of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996.</text></section> 
<section id="HEA9970B173AB411F8FE313CFDAD307E3"><enum>559.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to allow the United States Census Bureau to include aliens who are unlawfully present in the United States in rendering apportionment determinations in subsequent decennial censuses.</text></section> <section id="HC4B312CB925B40D68335D7C0A0ECEEC9"><enum>560.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to pay a compromise settlement in relation to a civil action brought by an alien who is inadmissible under section 212(a)(6)(A) or (7)(A)(i)(I) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(6)(A)</external-xref> or (7)(A)(i)(I)), or who entered the United States in violation of section 275(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1325">8 U.S.C. 1325(a)</external-xref>), in connection with conduct described in such section 275(a), unless expressly authorized by law.</text></section> 
<section id="H91B7C03D4DB14A0C8F317BA01F3591A8"><enum>561.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement a limit on reimbursement available to a local law enforcement jurisdiction under the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program for the purpose of paying overtime pay to a law enforcement officer who engages in eradication efforts against unlicensed or unregistered cannabis grown in a State wherein production or sales of cannabis is lawful.</text></section> <section id="H5CFEEA7A3DFA40949F10C542470E8FDE"><enum>562.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to review, process, or approve applications for Federal grants, contracts, cooperative agreements, or other agreements by any individual or organization that educates or otherwise trains or informs Federal employees about diversity, equity, inclusion, critical race theory, implicit bias, unconscious bias, or culturally relevant teaching.</text></section> 
<section id="H2D027CE5C61C4439BA573CA8FFA801FD"><enum>563.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to provide any education, training, or professional development that utilizes, promotes, or teaches Critical Race Theory, any concept associated with Critical Race Theory, or that teaches or trains any idea or concept that condones an individual being discriminated against or receiving adverse or beneficial treatment based on race or sex, that condones an individual feeling discomfort, guilt, anguish, or any other form of psychological distress on account of that individual’s race or sex, as well as any idea or concept that regards one race as inherently superior to another race, the United States or its institutions as being systemically racist or sexist, an individual as being inherently racist, sexist, or oppressive by virtue of that individual’s race or sex, an individual’s moral character as being necessarily determined by race or sex, an individual as bearing responsibility for actions committed in the past by other members of the same race or sex, or meritocracy being racist, sexist, or having been created by a particular race to oppress another race.</text></section> <section id="HF72788C5D844418FA4EE371CE2438616"><enum>564.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to promote or contribute to environmental, social, and corporate governance (also known as environmental, social, and governance (ESG)) investments.</text></section> 
<section id="H80246A75BC2B4729AAD0C5CD3B985500"><enum>565.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to investigate, litigate, or advocate against any person or recipient, as currently defined at section 106.2 of title 34, Code of Federal Regulations, for defining <quote>sex</quote> as currently used in, inter alia, section 1681 of title 20, United States Code, and sections 106.21, 22, 23, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 37,39, 40, 41, 44, and 45 of title 34, Code of Federal Regulations, to mean biological sex, male or female, as determined by the type of gamete an individual produces; and for defining <quote>boys and girls</quote> to mean only biological boys, whose DNA consists of one X sex chromosome and one Y sex chromosome, and biological girls, whose DNA consists of two X sex chromosomes.</text></section> <section id="H3199FC9195854A02BA9448F255CE6B00"><enum>566.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used for gun buyback or relinquishment programs.</text></section> 
<section id="H855DA96AD16C4A90BA5DCD54918479A9"><enum>567.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to implement any statute, rule, policy, or interpretive guidance or to disburse any grants or funding that would have the effect of creating, utilizing, supporting, or implementing a law or procedure which could result in the confiscation of any firearm without, in all cases, providing the gun owner with notice and opportunity to participate in a hearing.</text></section> <section id="H41C58A935E7B4D91BDB5D8439221477B"><enum>568.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to fund or implement any red flag or extreme risk protection order laws.</text></section> 
<section id="H048299273D714B31990EAAAA0AD05592"><enum>569.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act, or provided from any accounts in the Treasury of the United States derived by the collection of fees available to the agencies funded by this Act, may be available for obligation or expenditure to study, prepare, propose, or adopt any rule, regulation, administrative order or secretarial or executive action for the purpose of restricting the production, purchase, sale or transfer of any firearm unless expressly authorized by Congress.</text></section> <section id="H5044CF57D4174B208CF73B5A5E861357"><enum>570.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to create, operate, or maintain a Federal firearms registry.</text></section> 
<section id="H6447ED051A84477DB0A5EEE9BFEE1B82"><enum>571.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to pay the salaries or expenses of personnel to facilitate, advise, promote, or otherwise support any civil actions to which the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, and Firearms is not a named party against any licensee or other person purported to be subject to the regulation and oversight of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, and Firearms.</text></section> <section id="H1CA30096E1154D329814D549A85933EC"><enum>572.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used for the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF) Demand 2 program unless the ATF modifies the Demand 2 reporting thresholds such that the threshold criteria of the Demand 2 program is a percentage of traces relative to a licensee’s average number of firearm sales for the preceding three years as reported on such licensee’s Federal firearms license renewal applications.</text></section> 
<section id="H22388344CD104CA5806BC773B9DD7A10"><enum>573.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to—</text> <paragraph id="HAE024022549942A280D32D3A5796EF65"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">classify, tax, or register any firearm with an attached <quote>stabilizing brace</quote> or other similar brace or rearward attachment, notwithstanding any extended additional contact surface rearward or use outside of its original design or use as a buttstock or use to enable shoulder fire, as a <quote>rifle,</quote><quote>short-barreled rifle,</quote> or <quote>short-barreled shotgun</quote> under the Gun Control Act of 1968, the National Firearms Act of 1934, or any other such act of Congress; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B0997C831C849CF9CDC7BA72D06C6DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">direct any other law enforcement or regulatory entity to conduct any of the activities described in paragraph (1) on the ATF’s behalf.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA6C240E23E6B4FBDA0E87155E2CC9446"><enum>574.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be made available to support, directly or indirectly, the Wuhan Institute of Virology, or any laboratory owned or controlled by the governments of the People’s Republic of China, the Republic of Cuba, the Islamic Republic of Iran, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea, the Russian Federation, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela under the regime of Nicolás Maduro Moros, or any other country determined by the Secretary of State to be a foreign adversary. </text></section> 
<section id="H212AB3334AE34A118570CDD8BF2BE08B"><enum>575.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to engage in any formal or informal negotiations, regardless of subject, with leadership or representatives of the Islamic Republic of Iran.</text></section> <section id="H99510E82417247FA99115D607CBC3A48"><enum>576.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to recruit, hire, promote, or retain any person who either has been convicted of a Federal or State child pornography charge, has been convicted of any other Federal or State sexual assault charge, or has been formally disciplined for using Federal resources to access, use, or sell child pornography.</text></section> 
<section id="H7AF32286C7FB4E0FA8EF18D1F277D9C1"><enum>577.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to recruit, hire, promote, or retain any person based in whole or in part on such person’s race, national origin, sex, or religion.</text></section> <section id="H0B0680B89CC4478EB22DC4B32FE7F7A2"><enum>578.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to fund any sex-altering surgical procedures in either a Federally owned facility or a private facility leased or used by the Federal Government.</text></section> 
<section id="H98450F51AE71450A9BD34F4A6B4D0613"><enum>579.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used for the Department of Justice’s Reproductive Rights Task Force.</text></section> <section id="H524528640E7740288E4E7EEDEB31501F"><enum>580.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to sue any State or local government over their abortion laws, or to intervene or file an amicus brief in such a case.</text></section> 
<section id="H500C862E5A594D52B3677B7242485BF6"><enum>581.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to sue any State or local government over any law relating to transgender issues, or to intervene or file an amicus brief in such a case.</text></section> <section id="H8E20FD4D1EBC4F358E62A0F00EA86B65"><enum>582.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to sue any State over its redistricting plans, or to intervene or file an amicus brief in such a case.</text></section> 
<section id="HFDC0920B68494DE99C45EF65812CCBBC"><enum>583.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H16391DEBE6F04345BE4816809DF8A058"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general.—Notwithstanding section 7 of title 1, United States Code, section 1738C of title 28, United States Code, or any other provision of law, none of the funds provided by this Act, or previous appropriations Acts, shall be used in whole or in part to take any discriminatory action against a person, wholly or partially, on the basis that such person speaks, or acts, in accordance with a sincerely held religious belief, or moral conviction, that marriage is, or should be recognized as, a union of one man and one woman.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H310C79846B884C9E9FCBC1094ADB4D59"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Discriminatory action defined.—As used in subsection (a), a discriminatory action means any action taken by the Federal Government to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H01A76CC4C6964CD7AA4970072623F165"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">alter in any way the Federal tax treatment of, or cause any tax, penalty, or payment to be assessed against, or deny, delay, or revoke an exemption from taxation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 of, any person referred to in subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFCECD7CDD8B45E49A8E2CC87E95EA9D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disallow a deduction for Federal tax purposes of any charitable contribution made to or by such person;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H02A31CFF67D04C7596E3BE0FF684D970"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">withhold, reduce the amount or funding for, exclude, terminate, or otherwise make unavailable or deny, any Federal grant, contract, subcontract, cooperative agreement, guarantee, loan, scholarship, license, certification, accreditation, employment, or other similar position or status from or to such person;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41CD73614A6543D28A771FCE49275D05"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">withhold, reduce, exclude, terminate, or otherwise make unavailable or deny, any entitlement or benefit under a Federal benefit program, including admission to, equal treatment in, or eligibility for a degree from an educational program, from or to such person; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA39BDAACD5C4E1AB9A3F7F3CB6B05A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">withhold, reduce, exclude, terminate, or otherwise make unavailable or deny access or an entitlement to Federal property, facilities, educational institutions, speech fora (including traditional, limited, and nonpublic fora), or charitable fundraising campaigns from or to such person.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7FA1DDBF4F604F77B049A98680962CB0"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Accreditation; Licensure; Certification.—The Federal Government shall consider accredited, licensed, or certified for purposes of Federal law any person that would be accredited, licensed, or certified, respectively, for such purposes but for a determination against such person wholly or partially on the basis that the person speaks, or acts, in accordance with a sincerely held religious belief or moral conviction described in subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HFFFF9D4F55C64A3E9C0E837BD85C9082"><enum>584.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used by any agency to enforce section 19.17 of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement or Article 18 of the United States-Japan Digital Trade Agreement or to negotiate similar language in future trade agreements.</text></section> <section id="H0824A23ED9EF4E7CAD8B2E9A3CF48AB3"><enum>585.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1B46E90F2AE0415A9E98B77D5BEEE014"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to facilitate, permit, license, or promote exports to the Cuban military or intelligence service or to any officer of the Cuban military or intelligence service, or an immediate family member thereof or any agency or entity owned or partially owned or operated on behalf of the previously listed.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H499C5F6F580D4DBCB792E4ACB71D8B25"><enum>(b)</enum><text>This section does not apply to exports of goods permitted under the Trade Sanctions Reform and Export Enhancement Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7201">22 U.S.C. 7201 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5774BB7A53B34175A98471C7E19045B6"><enum>(c)</enum><text>In this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="H86B52A0A74CF4559BAFAD4E56A6FB655"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>Cuban military or intelligence service</quote> includes the Ministry of the Revolutionary Armed Forces, and the Ministry of the Interior, of Cuba, and any subsidiary of either such Ministry; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4E1C9A4128C64605868C3ABB87C44963"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>immediate family member</quote> means a spouse, sibling, son, daughter, parent, grandparent, grandchild, aunt, uncle, niece, or nephew.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC555A3C3EFB24DE3BB14A79CAE615C6C"><enum>586.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act or any other Act may be used for an Office of Environmental Justice.</text></section> <section id="H4E4DC768CC144381AFA00ECCD3A33769"><enum>587.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to enforce the Department of Commerce rule entitled, “Procedures Covering Suspension of Liquidation, Duties and Estimated Duties in Accord With Presidential Proclamation 10414” (87 Fed. Reg. 56868).</text></section> 
<section id="HCBD63B6149CB447E84F426D44C1F1114"><enum>588.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to pay the salaries and expenses of personnel of the Department of Justice to negotiate or conclude a settlement with the Federal Government that includes terms requiring the defendant to donate or contribute funds to an organization or individual.</text></section> <section id="HDC5258F3AE894BA5BFE0885590FA0658"><enum>589.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this or any other Act may be used to pay the salary, benefits, bonuses, or expenses of any Federal officer or employee who fails to comply with a duly issued and valid congressional subpoena, including any circumstances in which a Federal officer or employee does not produce documents in unredacted form by a date certain provided in a congressional subpoena.</text></section> 
<section id="HB14B699FD071455686063DB258456B24"><enum>590.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDE452EE5FCC148E790AB2157187926E4"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to conduct a politically sensitive investigation until the Department of Justice establishes a policy requiring non-partisan career staff to oversee such investigations.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5570140593184790B7A075180CA6C2BD"><enum>(b)</enum><text>For the purpose of this section, the phrase <quote>politically sensitive investigations</quote> includes investigations of elected officials or their family members, political candidates or their family members, political organizations, religious organizations, and members of the media.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H99205460B993483D8CF47C66C3CC77A9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>591.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to pay the salary, benefits, bonuses, or expenses of a Department of Justice employee who is found to have retaliated against a whistleblower or suppressed an employee’s constitutional rights under the First Amendment.</text></section> <section id="H2589473F34C44BB38B5ADF9750D56CA9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>592.</enum> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H64915CE648D74BAA856C60EF5DF9798A"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to conduct an interview in connection with an investigation of a Federal offense, or an investigation in which the agency is assisting a State, local or Tribal law enforcement agency, unless such interview is recorded using electronic audio recording equipment.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD931505156294CD39D12782D45075BC4"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Subsection (a) shall apply with respect to custodial and noncustodial interviews, but shall not apply with respect to—</text> <paragraph id="HD1245FE83BD248CB925D30135C6CEF2D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">communications with confidential informants; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDDDDF51BD11D4D1C8B6EF20430DFD79A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">interviews of non-United States persons conducted outside the United States. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3CDF999949BF4A2C9FA628A6FD98E5A0"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Recordings of such interviews shall be retained for 10 years. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H837C2D04C626440681B596D1EEA5DF3A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>593.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to discourage, or implement a policy that serves to discourage, United States Marshals Service employees or personnel from fully enforcing section 1507 of title 18, United States Code.</text></section> <section id="H25EB461817E44F3A8926665930EE5D1C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>594.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used be used, or transferred to another Federal agency, board, or commission to be used in furtherance of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7A917D3A19464B10B75B1226A918EDA8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any modification or publication of revised Merger Guidelines without the express authorization of Congress;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H573622A3704C4EBF9581F15963929A38"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the European Commission’s Digital Markets Act or in support of such Act; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F2A2821A0464DD389B9ABB5D2E0C1E5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the hiring of any new employees to the Antitrust Division, other than to replace retired or departed employees, unless expressly authorized by Congress.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HCA54D12329B74F018277643F8C7295EA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>595.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to fund the operations or expenses of any Federal employee union.</text></section> 
<section id="H7CD624872CDD4A21AD2EAB9CABF740A4"><enum>596.</enum> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8BDF4700FB5B4AC2A5ADD7811204556A"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 507(d) of title 11, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>excluding subparagraph (F)</quote> after <quote>(a)(8)</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H382324DABC9C4B8B9FA7553BA32BAD27"><enum>(b)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE351C4A026FA4FC69F82B6A62A1997A7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendment made by in section (a) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD60364D781E24C52910AD719ACC719F7" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to cases commenced under title 11 of the United States Code before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HF8B9E8AD2E854789ACDE121FFB1F74F3"><enum>597.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated or otherwise made available by this Act may be made used to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H30A5FBC56A0946AA9B101955CEC4C2ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">classify or facilitate the classification of any communications by a United States person as misinformation, disinformation, or malinformation; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA6728A8545E74239B71ABE36785391A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>partner with or fund nonprofit or other organizations that pressure or recommend private companies to censor lawful and constitutionally protected speech of United States persons, including recommending the censoring or removal of content on social media platforms.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H1921F6E466E84C3589E11FCA8648122D"><enum>598.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available by this Act may be used to enforce any COVID-19 vaccine mandates or passports.</text></section><appropriations-small id="HEB3A1175E8784EAD8290B620C4757152"><header>SPENDING REDUCTION ACCOUNT</header></appropriations-small> <section id="HBDFDFE7EB06249F88079E2CCDDD81776"><enum>599.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$0</text></section><appropriations-small id="HDD65C7B2891D4689893D8D7547B3CB02"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Commerce, Justice, Science, and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></appropriations-small></title> </legis-body> </bill> 

