<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0D88C23E320245299E2F8E3F1396DCFD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1753 IH: To ensure that certain members of the Armed Forces who served in female cultural support teams receive proper credit for such service.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1753</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that certain members of the Armed Forces who served in female cultural support teams receive proper credit for such service.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFBBBB01E5F4C4398803AF3ACDFFC729B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD9143274DB9844AC92361C331B6A8041" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Credit for certain members of the Armed Forces who served in female cultural support teams</header> 
<subsection id="H362FF4B910574481A95D4178183A5A73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="HE05B77DC3F98486FA8AFB83CE70C3BAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2010, the Commander of United States Special Operations Command established the Cultural Support Team Program to overcome significant intelligence gaps during the Global War on Terror.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD324C212833498A9D0E03A9446EC563"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From 2010 through 2021, approximately 310 female members, from every Armed Force, passed and were selected as members of female cultural support teams, and deployed with special operations forces.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41389EE98F8F44399EA608F5584B9C3E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of female cultural support teams served honorably, demonstrated commendable courage, overcame such intelligence gaps, engaged in direct action, and suffered casualties during the Global War on Terror.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4D00456E8BE43488D9CCE83032F18A5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Government has a duty to recognize members and veterans of female cultural support teams who volunteered join the Armed Forces, to undergo arduous training for covered service, and to execute dangerous and classified missions in the course of such covered service.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H391900AA5F054A11A433EE6C0C7A59D9"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members who performed covered service have sought treatment from the Department of Veterans Affairs for traumatic brain injuries, post-traumatic stress, and disabling physical trauma incurred in the course of such covered service, but have been denied such care.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4DA7F3991DD745D89CA08D2A6E144B39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the Sense of Congress that individuals who performed covered service performed exceptional service to the United States. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HFA5399586DF74E30B717D6D8F6659C75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Military service: records; calculation of retired pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall ensure that the performance of covered service is included in—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9758E0F8A0E347E88C91C9BB1BDFF15C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the military service record of each individual who performed covered service; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4CAF1DBC89E54C75B218D3187A409E85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the computation of retired pay for each individual who performed covered service.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H96C2082FEA5741A7A1CF65321553A264"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Claims for veterans benefits arising from covered service</header> 
<paragraph id="HC3EFFAAE4A634CDC82D50FC480A822FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination of service connection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the filing of a claim by an individual described in paragraph (3)(C) for service-connected disability or death incurred or aggravated in the course of covered service, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall determine whether such disability or death was service-connected.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAC8772704BEA4F9E9C506CF5DD406161" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of covered service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the consideration of a claim under this subsection, the Secretary shall treat covered service as engagement in combat with the enemy in the course of active military, naval, air, or space service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD5D4078D8B6E4D38929B214DD0A6C9C6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date of award</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE39D783BB3A24720886EDA1EDD3E8293" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided by subparagraph (B), the effective date of an award under this subsection shall be determined in accordance with section 5110 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4B80B99B3F484020BDAC04792C60DDAF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (g) of such section, the Secretary shall determine the effective date of an award based on a claim under this subsection for an individual described in subparagraph (C) by treating the date on which the individual filed the initial claim specified in clause (i) of such subparagraph as the date on which the individual filed the claim so awarded under this section.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9DEC9E17DB674FECA314B452EF1DED1D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Eligible individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual described in this subparagraph is an individual who performed covered service, or a survivor of such an individual—</text> <clause id="HF19CBF6C8B1A4C09AFE4DDC46492F3E4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who, before the date of the enactment of this Act, submitted a claim for service-connected disability or death of such individual;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5689119178614F1E92B813838168F3C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whose such claim was denied by reason of the claim not establishing that the disability or death was service-connected; </text></clause> <clause id="HDD0525AB1ABB471C8D99993E3C1EDC8F" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who submits a claim during the period of three years beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, for the same condition covered by the prior claim under clause; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H04B84D0A6AE046E39A5A53E4228B7901"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>whose such claim is approved pursuant to this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H06CC99ABD6FD446C9F816A55CDEFDF56"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Processing of claims</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, shall improve training and guidance for employees who may process a claim under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA70C34E204A46C08FBB3CE1904CE3BB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Outreach</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct outreach to inform individuals who performed covered service (and survivors of such individuals) that they may submit supplemental claims for service-connected disability or death incurred or aggravated in the course of covered service. Such outreach shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HC347C7544B48438B82FCA0E6B8B42A54" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall publish on the internet website of the Department a notice that such individuals may elect to file a supplemental claim.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H154A454EE050410D9FFBC31925865E16" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall notify, in writing or by electronic means, veterans service organizations of the ability of such individuals to file a supplemental claim.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HF60882C718814BE5A92E3F7BC3782348"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H2CC4FC2A422246369AA717D6EEE2159D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered service</quote> means service—</text> <subparagraph id="HA2F3353E5375455E9C69427BFFF809DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as a member of the Armed Forces;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBEB32E165D9B40528F1B2B14DB8BC531"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a female cultural support team; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F9729369C2845BEBE73330D01938440"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the personnel development skill identifier of R2J or 5DK; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8719B69CEA254E9E97E5A7B7DD078F71"><enum>(D)</enum><text>during the period beginning on January 1, 2010, and ending on August 31, 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E240F8241F647989CF72CD6A51C96CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <quote>active military, naval, air, or space service</quote> and <quote>service-connected</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6DF8FAC5A04242788AC49256009F944D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>Secretary concerned</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

