<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H09978399F5584C6399F00ECB246E4588" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5175 IH: Providing Essential Temporary Shelter Assistance For Emergencies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5175</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230808">August 8, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency to establish a pilot grant program for mobile pet shelters during emergencies and major disasters.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE41BBD5D6E7D49A08313FDA58A7391CE" style="OLC">
<section id="H20E85A7CDA784EE49024C5CA2FF4163B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providing Essential Temporary Shelter Assistance For Emergencies Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PETSAFE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9E4995FC1DCA479B8F33DE31C03CE597" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text>
<paragraph id="HB3C0134CB9644438AE15DBE4CA962047"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BDAAD1CA60E48819EA8A6DB645A69BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emergency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>emergency</quote> means an emergency declared by the President under title V of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5191">42 U.S.C. 5191 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA4CB7D81C21844468BBB64DCC9FEF448"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Major disaster</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>major disaster</quote> means a major disaster declared by the President under title IV of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F93EA814ACA43AD8E98B232DEF35FE0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Common household pet</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>common household pet</quote> means an animal, including a dog, cat, bird, rodent, rabbit, or turtle, that is kept in the home as a companion animal rather than for commercial purposes.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H781724367AB5447DAE1B25D6D9882968"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pilot program</header>
<subsection id="HD17294AC340646C99950B91A84AD2E83"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President, acting through the Administrator, in coordination with State, local, and Tribal governments, shall establish and conduct a pilot program to provide grants for equipping mobile pet shelter sites for use during emergencies and major disasters.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H21D6FA9E2BB949C1914BA042CD4C98E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administration</header> <paragraph id="H24FE4C1B9B8E4073ABD47E5DFA566870"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of the pilot program under this section, the Administrator may provide funds to State, local, and Tribal governments to establish a new pet shelter site that is a mobile unit, which may be a companion animal mobile equipment trailer, to be used in the case of evacuation due to emergencies and major disasters.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8A54FE6F710C4149BF9335B142B99D32"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The duties of such mobile unit shall be to—</text> <subparagraph id="H7261123117DB4071A945B43A4B902035"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide—</text>
<clause id="H941BA977C59F47D8B7AB98C63C3F12CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>immediate and temporary shelter to common household pets in the case of government directed or ordered evacuation at embarkation sites in the impacted jurisdiction or shelters or reception sites within the impacted jurisdiction or a host jurisdiction; or </text></clause> <clause id="H2D5BF05FFFCC41AFA1C16789254E5A52"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide safe transport of common household pets that require shelter during evacuations and relocate pets to a safe location; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H96CFA263F17D423983E07EF0462AFAB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitate the reunification of common household pets, including return transport, if necessary, with the owners of such pets not later than 3 weeks after all evacuation warnings are lifted and disaster-caused congregate shelters operation transition and close.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1036B25925D6475BBE766B2A9E18B7D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header> <subparagraph id="H0DFA6DC0CF9F45909E0CDDA647628773"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report on the effectiveness of the pilot program.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8737A5B2DDC446C9B2F87B9BFDCEE527"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall include in the report required under subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="H21836767555E4657A735F8B765AB35C5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the effectiveness of the pilot program under this section, including consultation with State, local, and Tribal governments and private nonprofit organizations with responsibility for care and sheltering of household pets;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0278AA5C97E94E4EA6FAE5295C99CB3C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an assessment of cost savings to State, local, and Tribal governments and any benefits to individuals and households who housed a common household pet with a mobile shelter under the pilot program;</text></clause> <clause id="HF0E2A68A5270463FA2F3BBD6DAB300BB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">findings and conclusions of the Administrator with respect to the pilot program;</text></clause>
<clause id="H848C3FB3FF8740FF8056C636D11A6F86"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of additional authorities needed to aid the Agency in its mission of providing disaster assistance to individuals and households with pets, either under the pilot program under this section or other potential programs; and</text></clause> <clause id="H25858564154E4746B0C7081CE77DBB31"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any recommendations of the Administrator for additional authority to continue or make permanent the pilot program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H415D732BB7CF4DBD8DAC68343CC2CD3A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Pilot program project approval</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The authority of the Administrator to approve a project under this section shall cease on January 1, 2029. </text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

