<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBA0BBE6C115040889B2CA75B0FAAB1C5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3764 IH: Weather Innovation for the Next Generation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3764</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title IV of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 to research the impact of obstructions on radar detection and prediction capabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC46A8C51B3DB4624AA49519A94EE5D3D" style="OLC"><section id="HD99C371025394223B3B0767A3D409A6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Weather Innovation for the Next Generation Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>WING Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE15403485A8F419394E4517EEA0E8665"><enum>2.</enum><header>Radar obstruction Research, Development, Test, and Evaluation Program</header><subsection id="HB5E0706D6088412DB23BF8B21110D5D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Radar obstruction research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title IV of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8514">15 U.S.C. 8514 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H18D774F76E4E44C488F10295FA340088" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5E88310D4B3745859078967B8979F288"><enum>415.</enum><header>Radar obstruction Research, Development, Test, and Evaluation Program</header><subsection id="HF908683F22B04572B66F469CBD056798"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Weather Service, in coordination with the Assistant Administrator for Oceanic and Atmospheric Research, shall establish a Research, Development, Test, and Evaluation Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to ensure the continued performance of weather radar detection and prediction capabilities with physical obstructions in the line of sight of such radar.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5A572AE4D012433F844D8852F0C37E34"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Program, the Director, in consultation with the Interagency Council for Advancing Meteorological Services, shall—</text><paragraph id="H1751BD04070443849F63B21C54A74DDD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>partner with industry, academia, Federal, State, and local government entities, and any other entity the Director considers appropriate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DAC5A474E2144589C24E4684063270B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and test existing or near-commercial technologies and solutions that mitigate the potential impact of obstructions on weather radar;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H040D0AAD1E7048A3B7E581EFE5350C29"><enum>(3)</enum><text>research additional solutions that could mitigate the effects of an obstruction on weather radar, including—</text><subparagraph id="H4C326E31E90044A59A3B8EE6FFEB59BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>signal processing algorithms;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAF95F0B9B604694B85CA3867E292541"><enum>(B)</enum><text>short-term forecasting algorithms to replace contaminated data; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD46D22B2E2574459B521CB49A878A382"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the use of dual polarization characteristics in mitigating the effects of wind turbines on weather radar; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CB4762A0BE54FCD88B7659812CE3007"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop commercially viable technical mitigation solutions for obstructions to weather radar capabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H744BBC67BD7E4F879FB56F2FFC2E54FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the requirements described in subsection (b), the Director shall prioritize consideration of the following technology-based mitigation solutions:</text><paragraph id="H34F2727729404922A7A08606E6E3B1C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Multifunction phased array radar.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H819AEEDDC3B84C10AF62B2D1CE85F253"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The replacement of contaminated data with commercial radar data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H370507D7584341BFB8E1EA2B8CE73C9F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The utilization of data from private-sector-associated meteorological towers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFFA111EBE6B4F84B5BA9FB7232A1986"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Providing wind farm boundaries and consolidated wind farm areas to display on local forecasting equipment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H860152C8270346DD89D8F9233B85EA51"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Installing and providing access to rain gauges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35104618CD5E4ACEB6EB4C0CAD2EEE92"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any other technology-based mitigation solution the Director determines could overcome beam blockage or ghost echoes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H401BD8A7E3D54D6499BCDC678A705AE7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The authority of the Director to carry out the Program shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="HB9E6D1066BC440519DD223DBDB3E136E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>September 30, 2028; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C8EB164EB18482CA671E0C2ADB69000"><enum>(2)</enum><text>one year after date on which the final recommendation required by subsection (e)(2) is submitted by the Director.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H32D5ED55AC394538AD12ACAFAF1439DB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report; recommendation</header><paragraph id="H128D048B02E54480ABB8CCD5B5B4E5D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this section and annually thereafter until the Program terminates pursuant to subsection (d), the Director shall submit to Congress a report on the implementation of the Program, including an evaluation of each technology-based mitigation solution identified for priority consideration pursuant to subsection (c), and a recommendation regarding additional identification and testing of new technologies based on such consideration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3374FBFF50CC426E87686286FEDDA2B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final recommendation</header><text>Not later than five years after the date of the enactment of this section, the Director shall provide to Congress a recommendation on whether additional research, testing, and development through the Program established under subsection (a) is needed, and a determination of whether a cessation of field research, development, testing, and evaluation is appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDED345E9CB347C58DA2F76098BA0BEC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H47C893929F5448828F623296C01303D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Beam blockage</header><text>The term <term>beam blockage</term> means a signal that is partially or fully blocked due to an obstruction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35231C8B6D054616B76010B41F192058"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Weather Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4327E8B25EB34DD1B982D2DBA515E2D1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ghost echo</header><text>The term <term>ghost echo</term> means radar signal reflectivity or velocity return errors in radar data due to the close proximity of an obstruction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC88F5C5F5ECA431D9DFCBED0AF633953"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Obstruction</header><text>The term obstruction includes—</text><subparagraph id="H62469795871840B1A4020851128B3A4F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a wind turbine that could limit the effectiveness of a weather radar system; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD88F6F7BCE404FAA9C4B0061BC0B4E4A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any building that disrupts or limits the effectiveness of a weather radar system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H228870914CC5400AB2F29090EE3F22D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections in section 1(b) of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 414 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H737C58D78DD546B7B3F143735BBE152D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">415. Radar obstruction Research, Development, Test, and Evaluation Program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

