<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE13B0D3392A14C009AE60DC994CB8820" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 6384 IH: Expanding Capacity in Quantum Information Science, Engineering, and Technology Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6384</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand capacity in quantum information science, engineering, and technology, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD85E0AF6501E47D7B4A7613AD479112C" style="OLC"><section id="H2ECE729FFC6447E8B06200FF3380670D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Capacity in Quantum Information Science, Engineering, and Technology Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Expand QISET Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H766DEE385D1C47CBBA1F9CB7DE58E1C9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expanding capacity in quantum information science, engineering, and technology (QISET)</header><subsection id="H066F2E9F2C1D4BB7A30562EABC738D43"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Science Foundation, in consultation with the heads of Federal agencies the Director considers appropriate, shall make awards on a competitive, merit-reviewed basis to eligible institutions of higher education or eligible nonprofit organizations (or consortia thereof) to increase research capacity, education and infrastructure capacity, and broaden participation in quantum information science, engineering, and technology and related disciplines, including by—</text><paragraph id="H99EB1A785D2242728EB326519348552A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting curriculum development in quantum information science, engineering, and technology as described in section 301(d) of the National Quantum Initiative Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8841">15 U.S.C. 8841(d)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC45CB266B1784FE786BF5D16E37155AF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">building upon the activities carried out under the Next Generation Quantum Leaders Pilot Program authorized under section 10661(f) of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19261">42 U.S.C. 19261(f)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21FDFBF5481C4AD28290A57E8F00F35C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>leveraging the readiness for the involvement of local research and education communities to secure a talent pipeline in quantum information science, engineering, and technology to meet the workforce needs of industry, government, and academia.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CFFF3C9024F4EB28A26F8BBA50A263A" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Collaborations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A collaboration receiving an award under this subsection may include institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, and private sector entities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5E1DAB4CF6347649BA72F96248A85E8" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible institution of higher education defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>eligible institution of higher education</quote> means an institution of higher education, that, according to the data published by the National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics, is not, on average, among the top 100 institutions in Federal research and development expenditures during the 3-year period prior to the year of the award.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC451AA057FFE417F9D5B5287DD485E2D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>To receive an award under this section, an eligible institution shall submit to the Director of the National Science Foundation an application that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HA29810CAD06A4A42B729C17F6678611B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A plan to sustain proposed activities beyond the duration of the award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DCDA3D899D9479DAE2107249687CB03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Proposed quantum information science, engineering, and technology disciplines and focus areas the eligible institution is prepared to engage in to significantly build up its quantum information science, engineering, and technology research and education capacity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC016302D0734697AC74880C9AEF2268"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A plan for education and workforce development, which may include K–12 and post-secondary education programs and activities, workforce training and career and technical education programs and activities, undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral education, and informal education programs and activities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDDBC7D41FEC458797DDB7F5853129FF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Awards under this section to support research and related activities may include the activities relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="H981C23D7B56A47AABB47C1F52F37A636"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Development or expansion of research programs in disciplines and focus areas specified in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ABEEEFA378342049B06DE4FC0BCB725"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Faculty recruitment and professional development in disciplines and focus areas specified in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6941DCFC42664548A4D1FEDE44D46959" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Bridge programs focused on preparing post-baccalaureate students for graduate programs in quantum information science, engineering, and technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H502694057FBD4C8B98245BAA5BC9A59B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To build research capacity and infrastructure at an eligible institution in disciplines and focus areas specified in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99BC6ACFD4114CA6B5B43715502E3D78" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An assessment of capacity-building and research infrastructure needs identified in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94FEF15E2CA8490784D30E49DBDB83CA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Administrative research development support.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFECB9AE646D64D57A758C98D909C3984"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Other activities necessary to build research capacity in quantum information science, engineering, and technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE6D05A934BB744BB9E2A63D94D4A6653"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional considerations</header><text>In making awards under this section, the Director of the National Science Foundation may also consider the following:</text><paragraph id="HEDAF0BC155EF4526925A057E44EA93D6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The extent to which the eligible applicant will support students from diverse backgrounds, including first-generation undergraduate students.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H526A17D0DD3D4C199F28741D7224F2FB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The geographic and institutional diversity of eligible applicants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H338633AB1F2849868302EC5C311783EE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How the eligible applicant can leverage public-private partnerships and existing research partnerships with Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H309265AF13D546B5B02D3C4A5C21797C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Duplication</header><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation shall ensure awards made under this section are complimentary to and not duplicative of existing programs.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

