<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDAECC496236543B8B7C89786151B482E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3360 IH: National Infrastructure Investment Corporation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3360</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a Government corporation to provide loans and loan guarantees for infrastructure projects, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H25C9714C253A475DB37603FAAD9C7D2A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF30D36D48F754C2CACF4426B2D9357D0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Infrastructure Investment Corporation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC87FB1D286CE4087AA2FE7B94321015D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB8271417FFD041FF922397BB41BCA123"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the American Society of Civil Engineers 2017 Infrastructure Report, the current condition of the infrastructure in the United States earns a grade of D+ and an estimated $4,500,000,000,000 is needed by 2025 to make conditions adequate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD81BF74EF87C4BCCA52956C4589D9AB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Current and foreseeable demands on traditional funding for infrastructure expansion exceed the resources to support much-needed infrastructure programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H70DAA3D7E9A841D89FC4A8B8782313C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As of April 19, 2019, the top 50 strategic infrastructure projects, including transportation, water and wastewater, ports and waterways, and telecommunications, totaled $289,370,000,000 in unmet needs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1DAA9B7273504CEDAACE7403DC9D9BF4"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Infrastructure needs are not limited to traditional roads and bridges but include a wide sector of basic, physical, and organizational structures and facilities that are needed for the effective and productive operation of society.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E059C7B0CFC4F8CB80A8B52F9B57CC7"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Investment in infrastructure not only creates jobs and economic growth and is a key component of maintaining a global competitive edge but is also fundamental to enhancing and preserving quality of life.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8844D6770CD34B3586653F3746A6D1D5"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The establishment of a Government corporation that provides loans supported by pension funds to finance qualified infrastructure projects would attract needed supplemental capital for infrastructure development.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD0DB2F3FC953486ABDD8DFDA9B35113A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is established a corporation to be known as the <quote>National Infrastructure Investment Corporation</quote> (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Corporation</quote>), which shall be a Government corporation as defined in section 103 of title 5, United States Code, whose purpose shall be to finance infrastructure projects that are beyond the financing capabilities of States and cities, including—</text> <paragraph id="H77C2E6A69DC3465CAC873A3C3B588D0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritizing projects in a fair and efficient manner; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B055E64882D4AEAA4344F6E03628C50"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">minimizing financial costs to the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H2B740D31934244EBBB23DE9649D3BCC5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Board of Directors and Inspector General</header> <subsection id="H9DBE35E71FA449A4961FAB28DA4D5E88"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The management of the Corporation shall be vested in a board of directors (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Board</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H745F62BDEC484E48A5D572001E222350"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall be composed of 7 members that meet the qualifications under subsection (c), consisting of—</text> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H705210E3791C4A27A19A74172B610A1B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">3 members appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46E703A2CC8D41B99246ACDB0E87FAEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>1 member appointed by the majority leader of the Senate;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4959377CD4064B9E904743142EA6A559"><enum>(3)</enum><text>1 member appointed by the minority leader of the Senate;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6FF6EE31760A473B9A7A4B6BF0C1767A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>1 member appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC418C824BA2540F9B36AAA9E0DF72F95"><enum>(5)</enum><text>1 member appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4C1788919EAF49AFA45D43D6AD878BE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>Each member of the Board shall—</text> <paragraph id="H3666C605E3A041B198D389AE19D31A53"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be a citizen of the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H762D86E6B7B1432C99F7348332B4DF74"><enum>(2)</enum><text>have significant demonstrated experience or expertise in—</text> <subparagraph id="HF3629C301C804C7B8727C054E6A951A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>infrastructure, and with respect to infrastructure, experience or expertise in—</text> 
<clause id="H1BED47F4789642F78D67576D0F024698"><enum>(i)</enum><text>heavy construction;</text></clause> <clause id="HF150D673A0364D55B5867D6C564D061B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>labor; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBE419417A7384A6FA00416AFA6D60DF9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>government policy;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB904EB06FBD54769B00060536236B062"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the financing, development, or operation of infrastructure projects, including the evaluation and selection of eligible projects; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF03CE911F0046908865CDC2D8E41E1E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the management and administration of a financial institution that provides financing for infrastructure projects; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H730548CAAA5E41A2AFF14996F69FC8BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>represent different geographic regions of the United States to ensure rural areas and small communities are represented.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3483F947E8C5432AB45C647B2ABACB09"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Initial appointments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President and congressional leadership shall appoint the members of the Board in accordance with subsections (b) and (c).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H16EB0C8361E142B4B907B2C8A8513ECF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Chair of the Board shall be designated by the President from among the members appointed under subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0071FCB4AD7145CF9746BCD3A1F7E8BD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>Each member of the Board shall hold office for a term of 5 years, except as provided in the following paragraphs:</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H225F9DAA95E5470A913E971CC46F6773"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Terms of initial appointees</header><text>As designated by the President and congressional leadership at the time of appointment—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H7CF61807C54143F6B19630E45954B022"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Chair shall be appointed for a term of 5 years;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H35CA28FEB9D443B2B73C6B9361C4CBC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the 4 members appointed by congressional leadership shall be appointed for a term of 4 years; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H20F942DDC36149F28E994589C4A72655"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 2 members appointed by the President shall be appointed for a term of 2 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E0491D38EEC4F2099A66BDFC1C711DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Vacancies shall be filled according to the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5A4DF61656A44F23929417A96CB43E87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A vacancy shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53A822E2273B4D84A00762F2B6324E9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any Board member elected to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the direct predecessor of the member was appointed shall be appointed only for the remainder of that term.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H91C489B0E4DE4F769A4D542F7C65377B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with subparagraph (B), a Board member may serve after the expiration of the term of the direct predecessor of the Board member until a successor has taken office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE13E488DB6154DF4BC4AE7EBAAE3F4AE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Responsibilities of the Board</header><text>The responsibilities of the Board are as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H09BE3AC2FA484AADA026951FAB8DB272"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide low-cost loans and loan guarantees to eligible applicants under section 5.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51DA64397B544ED8B80EFABC2D256612"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Develop strategic goals for the Corporation based on the purpose of the Corporation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD65670695DD44AFC9431DE16DB130A6D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Monitor and assess the effectiveness of the Corporation in achieving such strategic goals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE23E8458D2AB4D5A915487E9A4FF584C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Review and approve the annual business plans, annual budgets, and long-term strategies of and for infrastructure projects financed through the Corporation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B2C0C36804A469ABD4A08CD4963C886"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Develop, review, and approve annual reports for the Corporation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7AC2922B42124DA1BA1FB9A951A738E9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Employ at least 1 external auditor to conduct an annual audit of such infrastructure projects.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC3B75358D70945E7A1AD26234695361F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Employ individuals as necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BB203850CD74E948DE379F7119A2394"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Determine the operations and internal policies of the Corporation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2E3E754700744E7AE1357D2F9248EB7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Inspector General</header><text>The Board shall appoint an employee of the Corporation to be known as the <quote>Inspector General</quote> whose duties shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="HB5B3A7E6B52F4BE8BA276B277C000D98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Conduct audits under section 6(b).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9D5AE5FEFD9943FFA011962EF15970BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Carry out, with respect to the Corporation, duties and responsibilities established under the Inspector General Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App.).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97EE6D7410DE4151B89B77F79B0C5BF7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Establish, maintain, and oversee such audits as the Inspector General considers appropriate under this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE0A692F534ED4EC0A2240B51217104D5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Loans, loan guarantees, and bonding</header> 
<subsection id="H2673CAAB444748DBAAC698DC8509776A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Corporation shall provide loans, loan guarantees, and bonds to eligible applicants for infrastructure projects in the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H81DBBB7EFDF340E28065F70B1F4260BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility requirements</header><text>An applicant is eligible for a loan, loan guarantee, or bond under this section if the applicant—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7E240BC6C4774DAA90900182E0DBFAF0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits a detailed letter of interest to the Corporation that—</text> <subparagraph id="H59FBE9FD50444915BEAD2D13C00D8F66"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describes the infrastructure project and the location, purpose, and cost of the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE9A8815C7A8D4EC2B334C58E3245EEF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">outlines the proposed financial plan with respect to such project, including the requested loan, loan guarantee, or bond amount and the proposed obligor;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80DF86AA6E0F43D9BBB8857C1D001D8B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides a status of environmental review; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1C5336B5A5F544C7810C9455B85EF171"><enum>(D)</enum><text>summarizes the geographic area affected by such project;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1389CBD2BD8F413DBABD0AACCB523B94"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets the prerequisites for assistance and conditions for assistance described in subsections (g) and (h) of section 502 of the Railroad Revitalization and Regulatory Reform Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/45/822">45 U.S.C. 822(g)</external-xref> and (h)).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFC0DFD12F76047A48D72ED8BA61C717F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible uses</header><text>Loans, loan guarantees, and bonds provided under this section may be used only for eligible project costs (as defined in section 601(a)(2) of title 23, United States Code) for infrastructure projects, including transportation, energy, environment, and telecommunications.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1998A1D359554764971840B0AF9EAE12"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prior to approving a loan, loan guarantee, or bond under this section, the Corporation shall require the applicant to consult with any member of the House of Representatives or member of the Senate whose district or State, respectively, is affected by the infrastructure project to ensure that such project is meritorious and to avoid any problems that may arise with respect to such project.</text></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB2E373FABFEC47EBB8C58D8B4CD879CA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>A loan or bond provided under subsection (a) shall be structured with respect to the expected timing and duration of the construction and utility of an infrastructure project.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H40DE95862EB74AFFA32C98F2EB225277"><enum>(f)</enum><header>TIFIA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as inconsistent with this Act, the Corporation shall provide for loans, loan guarantees, and bonds under this section in the same manner and subject to the same requirements as the Secretary of Transportation enters into loans and loan agreements under section 602 of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/6">chapter 6</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, with respect to the TIFIA program (as defined in section 601 of such title).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8E26522A2D8F474F943CEB8F8DB66E61"><enum>6.</enum><header>Audits and reports</header> 
<subsection id="H1FB20A3C946846B5A606528B9C2EE2C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Board shall submit to Congress a report on the activities of the Corporation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAADD9667950F4BE18A0D8CD827DE57AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual audit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Inspector General of the Corporation shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H89359F67E57C473CBA1FBC26E652348B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct an account audit of the Corporation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AFC5784BB33408EADE36BF84B95B33B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conduct, supervise, and coordinate investigations of the business activities of the Corporation;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8078688321C4E2CA60949A11CBCE6AA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensure that the Corporation is acting consistent with this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H788BD1A045734A20ACE1E42A7C447A44"><enum>(4)</enum><text>submit the results of such audit to Congress.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA36913445C2F41B8BB823C5BD4A162F4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO audit and report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 5 years thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text> <paragraph id="H5033526FCFC44F2DB6DF1CBAD8B46FDF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct an evaluation of the activities of the Corporation from the previous 5 fiscal years; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB68646EBBA834050B2A5DF48C6A72EB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report containing the results of such evaluation, which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H40395960E5B946F389475899D4E0E280"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the impact and benefits of each infrastructure project financed through the Corporation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF95400EFCE224FE4BA5A39939DA0DA6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a review of the effectiveness of such infrastructure project in accomplishing the goals of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCB14ACE7233F47729AD522B18F63CCAB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application waiting period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before any loan or loan guarantee is awarded under this Act, the Corporation shall submit to Congress a report describing the application for such loan or loan guarantee. The Corporation may not award the loan or loan agreement before the end of the 60-day period following the submission of such report to Congress. The Corporation may award the loan or loan agreement after such period unless Congress enacts a joint resolution disapproving the application with an explanation for such disapproval.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCB7629B3898A4A4EB476BDD3EF38DF6D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rejected applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An application that is rejected under subsection (d) shall not be resubmitted to the Corporation unless the basis for the disapproval of the application has been addressed by the resubmitted application.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HB9866827864242D28CED5F72B34A3178"><enum>7.</enum><header>Funding</header> <subsection id="H24A5658053844369BCD7B873AF019A40"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pension fund loans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paying for the administrative costs of the Corporation and to provide loans and loan guarantees for eligible infrastructure projects, the Board may accept loans during fiscal years 2024 through 2028 from pension funds.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBB7D9E3770074056A3A1E1DD7825D1C2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board may not accept more than $5,000,000,000 in loans under subsection (a) during any single fiscal year.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H855B36F833A846CEBED2567443517C0B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual percentage rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a loan described under subsection (a), the Board may not pay an annual percentage rate of less than 3 percent or more than 4 percent.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

