<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H11312A93B7424B4181879D5963601361" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1777 IH: United States-Israel Future of Warfare Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1777</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230324">March 24, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000579">Mr. Ryan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a fund for the conduct of collaborative defense projects between the United States and Israel in emerging technologies, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H7E5410A5701842D2A082CD07B1CBB500" style="OLC">
<section id="HC0156ABCD1C5443FB47056FC78B5C2B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Israel Future of Warfare Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF7E0F98B32ED4451BBB194A9773F8AC2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Fund for conduct of collaborative defense projects between United States and Israel in emerging technologies</header> <subsection id="H0D40C3E0967E4F478D0A005DBA8EE389"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H16B2782222434B36BEDC58D168B68456"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The strategic partnership between the United States and Israel is mutually beneficial, reinforcing shared moral values and security interests while promoting peace and regional stability.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE24C852B511D4B0A9A2B8BC479C7A1D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A strong strategic relationship between the United States and Israel, and enhanced bilateral cooperation between such countries in defense, homeland security, cybersecurity, space, and other key areas, ensure both countries can confront current and future emerging defense challenges.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEE0B67ED7D0A405EB4D90A153586ED12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Israel is a global leader and innovator in the development of defense technology and is one of the closest foreign defense partners of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA6C4A800826461AB7A04BF63671888B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>On September 14, 2016, the United States and Israel signed a 10-year memorandum of understanding reaffirming the importance of continuing annual United States military assistance to Israel (and other defense programs in areas such as missile defense, counter tunneling, and counter-unmanned aircraft systems) in a way that enhances the security of Israel and strengthens the bilateral relationship between the two countries.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC824842DFF224BA18530F0213CE82256"><enum>(5)</enum><text>On July 12, 2022, President Joe Biden and former Israeli Prime Minister Yair Lapid committed to elevating the strategic partnership between the United States and Israel to new heights by launching the Strategic High-Level Dialogue on Technology, tasked with establishing a technological partnership between the United States and Israel with respect to critical and emerging technologies and solutions to global challenges.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB83B8FB9E0FE4C6BB9321789B0D95AFD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On July 14, 2022, President Joe Biden and former Israeli Prime Minister Yair Lapid signed a joint declaration titled the <quote>Jerusalem U.S.-Israel Strategic Partnership Joint Declaration</quote> reaffirming the steadfast commitment of the United States to strengthen the self-defense capability of Israel and to <quote>move forward the U.S.-Israel defense partnership through cooperation in cutting-edge defense technologies such as high energy laser weapons systems to defend the skies of Israel and in the future those of other U.S. and Israel security partners</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD52D4B99A74D4E4492CEBC89F72FB91A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Since 2016, Congress has appropriated $320,000,000 for counter-tunneling cooperation between the United States (specifically the Irregular Warfare Technical Support Directorate of the Department of Defense) and Israel, resulting in the development of counter-tunnel technology that enhances the capability of the United States and Israel to deal with tunnel threats at the borders of such countries and elsewhere.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FE6F66843C4465BBE32EA6E7CF00D3C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since 2020, Congress has appropriated $88,000,000 for counter-unmanned aircraft systems cooperation between the United States (specifically the Irregular Warfare Technical Support Directorate of the Department of Defense) and Israel, resulting in the co-development of counter-unmanned aircraft systems for use by the United States Armed Forces, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and the United States Secret Service.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF8176A9D218A4AE9BF6CFB44F7E09CC3"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In January 2023, the Irregular Warfare Technical Support Directorate of the Department of Defense awarded Israel Aerospace Industries a multi-million dollar contract to rapidly develop and deliver a loitering munition known as <quote>ROC–X</quote> to provide ground-based tactical forces with more precise capabilities and improve the safety and security of United States warfighters.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA169E8D56BF541ED8F5A203A2508CF35"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Over the last few years, the Irregular Warfare Technical Support Directorate of the Department of Defense and the Directorate of Defense Research and Engineering of the Ministry of Defense of Israel hosted a competition known as the <quote>MOSAIC Challenge</quote>, seeking cutting-edge hardware and software solutions to address some of the challenging and longstanding technological gaps concerning remote autonomous indoor maneuverability.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD7C8D6EF207C4A52BC7992F438444C2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States to support and encourage further defense collaboration with Israel in areas of emerging technologies capable of enabling the warfare capabilities of both the United States and Israel to meet emerging defense challenges, including with respect to the areas of artificial intelligence, cybersecurity, directed energy, and automation. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H89AAD8C0B8DD4D58AA7A1E632A78BA36"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment of fund</header> <paragraph id="HB9243770E84B4F8F9B0CE71830C8009C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall establish a fund, to be known as the <quote>United States-Israel Future of Warfare Research and Development Fund</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBFB8370965384165A95FC889B08750B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text>Amounts in the Fund shall be available for the conduct of collaborative defense projects between the United States and Israel in areas of emerging technologies (including artificial intelligence, automation, cybersecurity, and directed energy) for the purpose of enabling the Armed Forces of the United States and of Israel, respectively, to meet emerging defense challenges.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB2EE392523C414793C278B2239B51FA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Fund $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


