<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D6CBA2BE3714E6CA89E9B2B2028756C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5909 IH: Caring for Grieving Families Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5909</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act to limit cost sharing for prenatal services in certain circumstances.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7E6E992305274180AEC607F05C7CEECA" style="OLC"><section id="H54D7A396B03545E0A09EA9DDEDDD6471" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Caring for Grieving Families Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9DF8FC1240984ABC9002882C50D17BEE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limiting cost sharing for prenatal services in certain circumstances</header><subsection id="H6D0B499454224F2AB0A4516D60CF5E2B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart II of part A of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-11">42 U.S.C. 300gg–11 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0DE6CE53603241059319F722F472B0FF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H37E93DE91DC346D9A405666F8825CDF3"><enum>2730.</enum><header>Limitation on cost sharing for prenatal services in certain circumstances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In the case of a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage that pays for items and services furnished to an individual relating to the birth of a child as part of a bundled payment and that includes payment for prenatal services (such as imaging tests and office visits) as part of such bundled payment, if such individual experiences a miscarriage or stillbirth and such bundled payment is not made, such plan or coverage may not impose any cost sharing requirement (including deductibles, coinsurance, and copayments) on such prenatal services furnished prior to such miscarriage or stillbirth in an amount that exceeds the cost sharing requirement that would have been applicable to such bundled payment had such miscarriage or stillbirth not occurred.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H156D93E6E2A54EACB4E6FF8A695CA35F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

