<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H69D99C31FE6449B7BD829B5CA03D7443" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6260 IH: Federal Oversight of Construction Use and Safety Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6260</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for certain reviews of the use and safety of Federal buildings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H51F9EA6BF1694E789086C58185F7127F" style="OLC"><section id="H43DF4DF412864EBDBCDC367176484DBF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Oversight of Construction Use and Safety Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FOCUS Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1BD6E7C6B27C4B709C45798D48237A04"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eliminating project escalations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3307(c) of title 40, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Administrator shall notify, in writing, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate of any increase of more than 5 percent of an estimated maximum cost or of any increase or decrease in the scope or size of a project of 5 or more percent. Such notification shall include an explanation regarding any such increase or decrease. The scope or size of a project shall not increase or decrease by more than 10 percent unless an amended prospectus is submitted and approved pursuant to this section.</quote>.</text></section><section id="HF7D8FB0BEE06441787D28887475B077E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Public safety at Federal buildings</header><subsection id="H0524356BE93A44919F1EA322B6B8B6BC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Data collection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of General Services shall collect data from tenant Federal agencies reports of any safety incidents as a result of criminal or other activity impacting public safety in and around public buildings, as defined in section 3301 of title 40, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7C3B0ADF9EDA4E7BA242190C1D53D5F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report that—</text><paragraph id="H8BBA15AD36DF4FF9BB43E81236D479B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>contains the data collected under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H309392CF7C2E436295099A73A8B6EE4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describes any actions taken or planned, if necessary, to improve building management and operations to address such incidents.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2DF4F9A8E3434EDD80C4668F6453D2B2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reducing waste in new projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3307(b) of title 40, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE5E3116B04C84E7387776A6E72E5F737"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (7) by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7B60222950A45D2BC7A8A59200FA865"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (8) by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDEF5D7E2D514FEB92D053BED0AE045A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HEBD02925606944BDB520F3CEB2E085AD"><paragraph id="H997FC8E430C146F7988928EF43A94AAE"><enum>(9)</enum><text>information on any space occupied by the relevant agency in the geographical area of the proposed facility, including uses, utilization rates, any proposed consolidations, and, if not proposed to be consolidated, a justification for such determination; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA8B7491E23D4898AC84EC9C467D4B18"><enum>(10)</enum><text>details on actual utilization rates, including number of personnel assigned to the facility, number of personnel expected to work in-person at the facility and whether all personnel identified reflect filled and authorized positions.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H8984BAB729584305A393EC1B31E0AD27"><enum>5.</enum><header>Review of special use space</header><subsection id="HE63D5DA495314D44B20A0F7AFB89972D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall review the use of special use spaces in Federal buildings, including conference centers, fitness centers, and similar spaces to determine levels of utilization, opportunities for sharing, collocating, and other efficiencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5D368EAB19BA4408BA0AEAE69E7CC591"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report containing the review under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H060E0453083044DD90B61D812B0E39F4"><enum>6.</enum><header>Interagency space coordination</header><subsection id="H228B192A45404FC48E67E77F72B94B8B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/33">Chapter 33</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H7F23FE5FB04C488E9E56961CE4CE9C0C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HA2AA12F4B4C54BA484A2A018BA3A9DF1"><enum>3319.</enum><header>Interagency space coordination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Unless a Federal agency specifically restricts the sharing of the information described in this section for national security purposes, the Administrator of General Services shall share with tenant Federal agencies pursuing new or replacement office space information on any other Federal agencies located in the same geographical area for purposes of determining opportunities for consolidations, collocations, or other space sharing to reduce the costs of space and maximize space utilization.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H421EFE66E009489BABDA0F85EE5D4A66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H136416200EEC4888911E24425DC643CA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">3319. Interagency space coordination.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

