<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H28837B09E5794EE1A313E0F70C1B02B4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2786 IH: Climate Change Relief for Urban Areas Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2786</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Cooperative Forestry Assistance Act of 1978 to prioritize urban and community forestry assistance for areas with low tree equity scores, to establish a grant program to enhance public elementary and secondary school rooftop gardens, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE4A242ECAD394F2A98E9C43901F0949A" style="OLC"><section id="H9F731786E8164A61B1CA7ED3F515CF3D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Climate Change Relief for Urban Areas Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H872553D05C7445D189973C5349719F71"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prioritization of urban and community forestry assistance to areas with low tree equity scores</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 9 of the Cooperative Forestry Assistance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2105">16 U.S.C. 2105</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H96E28D9EF3F64A66A4D9B256E10B139E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following: <quote>In carrying out this section, the Secretary shall give priority to providing assistance to State foresters or equivalent State officials serving areas with the lowest tree equity scores, as determined by the Secretary</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18C934C1C4B14A74B288295D1EFE06EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (h)—</text><subparagraph id="HA77C913F779B4ECF970871AB4F63DC48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36E25D97B54845AC90D57062F365DDCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking the period and adding <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33121F72430746A9A2690161A59034FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H06E7DD2588CB438CA7238B5F1F27554D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H720BD327A9764D69A6EF516D176A3803"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>tree equity score</term> means a tree equity score, as determined by the Secretary, that is—</text><subparagraph id="HBF5620E5DC3E4DE5B82E12DD23BB7C3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>either—</text><clause id="HBDDCA8FC5EB748ABA5297B29240FA052"><enum>(i)</enum><text>substantially similar to the tree equity score established by American Forests (or a successor tree equity score developed by such conservation organization or other similar organization); or</text></clause><clause id="HD02A9A08B7F2440E8F37E32E1B08C530"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a tree equity tool that the Secretary determines is most appropriate for the communities served by such tool; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C6C16DD077C4E86BAB96808495DC3E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on how the tree canopy and surface temperature of an area align with income, employment, race, age, and health factors of that area as determined by consulting with community representatives or community-based organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE04B09B2B19C4674A958D420E5FD9173"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (i), by striking <quote>fiscal years 1991 through 1995</quote> and inserting <quote>fiscal years 2023 through 2028</quote>. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HB14ABEC920E9435D8EEB91681D27E2DB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pilot grant program to public elementary and secondary school rooftop gardens</header><subsection id="H34BEE22352EB4FB282950EF654B4BCD0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program established</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a competitive grant program under which the Secretary shall make grants to eligible entities to establish or expand rooftop gardens. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFB349D45C93B4C7BBBF8C8EA3D3FD987"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including the square feet of the proposed rooftop garden (or expansion of such rooftop garden).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC9AFC1D64AD546D6A9F0E258FA31D79C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to the eligible entities that have the lowest garden equity score, as determined by the Secretary based on, with respect to the area in which the eligible entity is located, the population density, racial composition, incidence of respiratory illness, number of urban gardens, food sovereignty, and average surface temperature. </text></subsection><subsection id="HF5397C6691A94DB79C5C59BD5AE4C8D6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out each of the following:</text><paragraph id="HB24A7CE8F137449FBD3665E802AEAC73"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assessing (including through architectural analysis) if the area identified for purposes of establishing or expanding a rooftop garden can support such garden or expansion and the construction thereof. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D2B38F35F524A7E8E92E6D0073BE247"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Applying for permits with respect to such rooftop garden.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H827F4E3B2A98470F94BA22D6390D63B4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Establishing a financial plan with respect to the establishment or expansion of such rooftop garden.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE99D05B896AE4250BAC48541411F9A4C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Designing a rooftop garden—</text><subparagraph id="HAB66EEE229704F599C6FB72E74E20024"><enum>(A)</enum><text>of which at least 20 percent is comprised of native plants, fruits, or vegetables;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H510FF82B779C451D9179575FDB597F27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that does not include plants identified by the State in which such garden is located as invasive species;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H235FEA22C0DD47C0ADB001EE88D1525B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>using best practices to reduce risk of contaminants (such as using cleaning soil in raised garden beds); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H046186613E1E4418A27E864C07697301"><enum>(D)</enum><text>either—</text><clause id="HD37D0CE29A484FFFB2D6DA8D7AF38B90"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a strategy for increasing energy efficiency and increasing the surface ability of a building to reflect sunlight and absorb less solar energy; or</text></clause><clause id="HE1016D96E80646B69B1DDCDF5070F4BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the strategy in clause (i) is not feasible, a strategy to increase habitat and food availability for pollinators, manage rainwater, or provide other benefits to the community.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D739BF2ECDB4A93A3DCBB78A92D6696"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Incorporating into the science curriculum of the entity—</text><subparagraph id="HF412D35C323B45DCB752FDF8B3453B3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an urban agriculture lesson plan; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC02B2BCB616E430FBDB6BEE4152E98DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a lesson plan on pollinator habitat, green infrastructure for heat or stormwater management, or remediation of soil and water contaminants by plants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEE8695521504467DA32360BE70C43842"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Organic requirement</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may only use organic farming methods with respect to a rooftop garden established or expanded by such grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C36B8DE07384D4FAD3FBF6367605705"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Routine inspections</header><paragraph id="HEA9021BEFD7945C5991897743B3BF188"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall inspect each rooftop garden for which a grant is awarded under this section once each year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD34FE9A81FC142BC95B28F0AC7F3144B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><text>The Secretary may enter into contracts with appropriate entities to carry out the inspections required under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D60AE5152B64F8CAD3987625BEB884C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA51B82F8F2AD49E2A78C2E8F235445F2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a public elementary school or secondary school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7AA585A756B46D29239BB0BA7990804"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term> and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EB75C4F0BDA42ABB633DD3A833576A5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9B38AD02E4B4A4EB9F39CE8132F2110"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

