<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H317FCC575F7D4D74AC7D88A429424CB6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 2409 IH: Expand eXpertise in China Education and Language Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2409</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve hiring authorities available to the Secretary of State with respect to expertise on the People’s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC4B4F6DA6B99448FA50B8DF06FEFB7E0" style="OLC"><section id="H787BFCA4358A479D8E5D5BF181D58D03" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expand eXpertise in China Education and Language Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EXCEL Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H663DA2D3D0074299B2C3039AE5D8A912"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H34AF027A710F4661B28CE3A5B9BE1243"><enum>(1)</enum><text>strategic competition with the Government of the People’s Republic of China (PRC) and the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) is the most significant geostrategic challenge the United States faces in the 21st century;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA75F457DF4BF44228E654A310062E66B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States Government needs to further invest in relevant linguistic, cultural, and regional expertise to effectively engage in strategic competition with the PRC; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE07B0CA158D94E5D8341727CCCD4BD64"><enum>(3)</enum><text>existing hiring authorities across the executive branch are not being adequately utilized to bring in necessary expertise to win the strategic competition against the PRC, and agencies may benefit from additional flexibility to recruit, hire, and retain talent.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE1C1E4BEB5A74B9D894A5BAABC585153"><enum>3.</enum><header>Hiring additional expertise at the Department of State</header><subsection id="HA84873A9F6944DCAB918F3389F52D361"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Direct hire authority</header><paragraph id="H7E24A0D5999B4A74AC1ADF404D39DEFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall appoint directly to positions in the competitive service, as defined in section 2102 of title 5, United States Code, without regard to the provisions of sections 3309 through 3318 of that title, not fewer than 31 candidates with linguistic, cultural, or regional expertise relevant to strengthening United States understanding of and ability to compete with the PRC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DA85472D4FA4365AD71336D39178AEC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The authority provided under paragraph (1) shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60C773CE0FC44B97A694CB293949611F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Long-Term and short-Term contracts</header><paragraph id="HC14DF7EFD93B481E98C33E453CB1A9B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Training</header><text>The Secretary of State shall train Foreign Service and civil service employees who hold positions relevant to advancing United States policies toward competition with the PRC in the topics described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FD64996E43A4B6DAA61F7D0628D02FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Topics covered</header><text>The training referred to in paragraph (1) shall cover the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5786EF67BC9049499102784B70E5AC13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The domestic and foreign policy objectives of the PRC and the CCP, as demonstrated through publicly available speeches and PRC and CCP documents.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76723052555C480C939A2942E47E2953"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The tools the PRC and the CCP use to achieve those objectives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C37D0FA292E45CB9D8AEC25A18A5E57"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The role of ideology in shaping CCP policies and outlook.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAEE086DB51714F288E675CAF668D81A5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Other topics deemed relevant by the China Strategic Advisory Board, established by section 4(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A12D66226474093B1E6F00286C8AB80"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contracts and grants for training</header><text>In providing the training referred to in paragraph (1), the Secretary of State may obtain assistance from knowledgeable persons by—</text><subparagraph id="H19BEF5034B4A4EC7A5381C87573A27C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>entering into short-term and long-term contracts for such assistance, including contracts for the temporary or intermittent services of experts and consultants under section 3109 of title 5, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA971DF02424844E8AE2C529BB9C81E9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>making grants to the persons providing such assistance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00048BB7BAF545B8B415CF45F87A8001"><enum>(C)</enum><text>taking other appropriate measures, as the Secretary of State deems necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7345030E3E204F2AA4AECA1EA3327C6A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Providing enduring strategic advice via the China Strategic Advisory Board</header><subsection id="H35F1A8D8B890415AAEC86743B82A1077"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established an advisory board to be known as the <quote>China Strategic Advisory Board</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Advisory Board</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H32022B543D3E4593B520D911D0D71E95"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties and responsibilities</header><text>The Advisory Board shall—</text><paragraph id="HA3F3DB074507487FBE216B8270B8DC56"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide advice and expertise to the Secretary of State, and continuity, in United States foreign policy matters pertaining to strategic competition with the PRC;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83EBCAD0EB7A44329529DB4437162B62"><enum>(2)</enum><text>review recruitment, training, and retention of Foreign Service and civil service members with the expertise and experience necessary to support United States policy toward the PRC; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7933710DB33849E685C04231495C08CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide guidance on programs across regional and functional bureaus intended to respond to strategic competition with the PRC, including the Countering Chinese Influence Fund established by section 7043(c)(2) of the Department of State, Foreign Operations, and Related Programs Appropriations Act, 2020 (division G of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/94">Public Law 116–94</external-xref>; 133 Stat. 2896).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD80F144A1E149C0AAE3508EFEEC6926"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="HAE482386FAF94F51BBF5DE4136FD5425"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Advisory Board shall consist of at least 18 and not more than 24 members, who each should have a demonstrable record of substantial experience pertaining to issues related to United States strategic competition with the PRC. No sitting officer or employee of the United States Government may be appointed to the Advisory Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A473370EE0244CE8FDFE7D0A80C96D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appointments</header><subparagraph id="H31A6DCC4769A4F3EA409469753223350"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appointments by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and Senate leader of same party</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the leader that is of the same party in the Senate (if any), in consultation with the Chair and Ranking Member of the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate, shall jointly appoint 3 members.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46EE31A3123240C98DA2181E24F0E376"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointments by minority leader of the House of Representatives and Senate leader of same party</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The leader of the minority party of the House of Representatives and the leader of the same party in the Senate (if any), in consultation with the Chair and Ranking Member of the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives, shall jointly appoint 3 members.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD2F9767FEE74A78AB2E7FD59821D8F3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appointments by the President</header><clause id="H0AF9035B027E438BAD468B415A86758E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Number</header><text>The President shall appoint 6 members.</text></clause><clause id="H226FCF39B9F5436F8EFDF246E34E71B8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>At least 2 of the members appointed under clause (i) shall be between 30 and 50 years of age (inclusive) at the time of appointment.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8847636C1CB54834B03A355AB5B2083F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Appointments by Secretary of State</header><clause id="H40EFA0134944441B8C81E2BE76E191FD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Number</header><text>The Secretary of State shall appoint at least 6 but not more than 12 members.</text></clause><clause id="H122220E68A0F452EBE190E3C1A1E2343"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>The appointments made under clause (i) shall meet the following criteria:</text><subclause id="H50B857953E5F4194893A409A261E28C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>At least 1 member who is not described in subclause (II) or (III) shall be between 30 and 50 years of age (inclusive) at the time of appointment.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC55CD668218B478BA7043876797DAD60"><enum>(II)</enum><text>At least 1 member who is not described in subclause (I) or (III) shall be able to credibly represent the views of the United States business community.</text></subclause><subclause id="H0B8ED42C7B9D47388F12E0B1A2FB3506"><enum>(III)</enum><text>At least 1 member who is not described in subclause (I) or (II) shall have demonstrable experience as a United States diplomat.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF43FBF22FCD4BC1B11A7904777FE0A6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline for initial appointments</header><text>Each appointing authority referred to in paragraph (2) shall make all initial appointments required by such paragraph not later than January 1, 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A3C774379244CE1B55973B927CC50CA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which a vacancy on the Advisory Board occurs, the vacancy shall be filled in the same manner as specified for the original appointment under paragraph (2), and the individual so appointed shall serve the remainder of the unexpired term.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64524A388BE74CBE817F6EEC353EC611"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Replacement appointments</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the term of a member of the Advisory Board expires, the appointing authority that appointed such member shall appoint the member’s replacement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96F2B32A50674AA9A99D5C8894D62B36"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Terms</header><paragraph id="HA8EA595B82EA4EA9B5A76DD6D1FC641D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), all members appointed to the Advisory Board shall have a term of 6 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5A5FEA2DED24D4394AA809E1EAD234F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial terms</header><subparagraph id="H510D59B0C6A94450A7134ABF5D30B73A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appointments by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and Senate leader of same party</header><text>Of the initial members appointed under subsection (c)(2)(A), 1 shall have a term of 2 years and 1 shall have a term of 4 years, as designated by the Speaker and leader referred to in such subsection at the time of appointment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE98188CDD9D4FBAA1F5692F9DBCB720"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointments by minority leader of the House of Representatives and Senate leader of same party</header><text>Of the initial members appointed under subsection (c)(2)(B), 1 shall have a term of 2 years and 1 shall have a term of 4 years, as designated by the leaders referred to in such subsection at the time of appointment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB382BED65B8340E2BA683DA2F4A24F8E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appointments by the President</header><text>Of the initial members appointed under subsection (c)(2)(C), 2 shall have a term of 2 years and 2 shall have a term of 4 years, as designated by the President at the time of appointment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB22C60F6583A4987B23516EA12369CC9"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Appointments by Secretary of State</header><text>Of the initial members appointed under subsection (c)(2)(D), at least <fraction>1/3</fraction> shall have a term of 2 years and at least <fraction>1/3</fraction> shall have a term of 4 years, as designated by the Secretary of State at the time of appointment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FE8FF98A29B46F3B6538C9DCF5EE6C5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional terms</header><text>A member of the Advisory Board may be reappointed to not more than 1 additional term but may not be appointed to a different seat on the Board.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB0D76F7FC17E41DFBAC910C934E691C2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the sitting members of the Advisory Board shall constitute a quorum but a lesser number may hold hearings.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3583DC044F8544E1BE23039B41621F21"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Chairperson and Vice Chairperson</header><text>The Advisory Board shall elect, from among its members, a Chairperson and Vice Chairperson. The terms of office of the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson shall be 1 year, and the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson may be reelected to subsequent terms.</text></subsection><subsection id="H74DA20B3E2B0478180F1FBF40732B0EA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Board meetings</header><paragraph id="H4EE13B7F254548A3B1716ACE8CC98EE9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text>The Advisory Board shall meet, at the call of the Chairperson or a majority of its members, at least once every 3 months and as frequently as may be necessary to carry out its duties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB28B90417D95407DB277C5D8655B057C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subcommittees</header><text>The Advisory Board may be divided into subcommittees that meet separately from the whole Board.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H71D3D3F0BB004D40B4F4A15D76395DEA"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Briefings with officials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than annually, the Advisory Board shall collectively provide to the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development a briefing on—</text><paragraph id="H22D82F2086C64359A8BBBCD091D92643"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the findings made by the Advisory Board in fulfilling its duties and responsibilities under subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA26B900C2A4A41099013E4A9379483F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Advisory Board for future legislative or administrative action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E87D250DD2A416A9E435B6BFA4D3D1E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Congressional briefings</header><text>On a semiannual basis, the Advisory Board shall provide to each of the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on—</text><paragraph id="HEC98765721744290857B5F241CE9DCEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the findings made by the Advisory Board in fulfilling its duties and responsibilities under subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23A7E07EAB024034BDE93D00D57E711A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Advisory Board for future legislative or administrative action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4AD9EE4821047F19B678706446B266E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Security and access to information</header><paragraph id="HEAA8D7F3C07C49479D24CB7CD266878E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Security clearances</header><text>The appropriate departments and agencies of the executive branch shall cooperate with the Advisory Board to expeditiously provide to the members of the Advisory Board the appropriate security clearances necessary to carry out the duties and responsibilities of the Advisory Board, subject to the standard procedures and requirements for granting such clearances.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78A98479558749C4B32D518A7C93D04B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Need to know</header><text>For purposes of any law or regulation governing access to classified information, a member of the Advisory Board seeking access to a record or material to fulfill the duties and responsibilities of the Advisory Board shall be deemed to have a need to know the contents of the record or material.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H937CA284CDD14B7FA8A3D2E1C46AD952"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Access to information</header><text>The Secretary of State shall ensure that members of the Advisory Board have access to all appropriate information to fulfill the duties and responsibilities of the Advisory Board.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8F2062A33F54943A1A7A5C997D1A3A6"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>Members of the Advisory Board shall—</text><paragraph id="H6C14FDD621464EACA7338CBF9880D33B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>receive compensation at a rate not to exceed the daily equivalent of the annual basic pay payable for positions at GS–15 of the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code, for each day such member is engaged in the actual performance of services of the Advisory Board; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2B5433F108746E5854422FC6FC1DF35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence at rates authorized for employees of agencies under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, while away from their homes or regular places of business in the performance of services of the Advisory Board.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4B29B958EFCF46D7BE0E3EE601086EAD"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The Chairperson may appoint and fix the pay of personnel as the Chairperson considers appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D8CB91B74DB41678FF27853C0612532"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Section 1013(a)(2) of title 5, United States Code, (relating to the termination of advisory committees) shall not apply to the Advisory Board.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD560095FF889405CA06CDBD0345FCB8F"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Review and report by Comptroller General</header><paragraph id="H2753CBEF740E442E9782CB04403FC1E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a review that analyzes the progress of the Advisory Board on fulfilling the duties and responsibilities referred to in subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0E287D6879743348EDCFD528EA1A29E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report detailing—</text><subparagraph id="H2C396BEE92F04355926AC42F46B0855F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the review referred to in paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D11553BD5894A7189CED679BFB03C97"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations for legislative or administrative action to improve the functioning of the Advisory Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5724D014827E4595B8743F25E0DB9E3B"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $100,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDEE089AAE8A44EFB8A6130312DC9A51F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Identifying long-term solutions through the Government Accountability Office</header><subsection id="H14FB2B8852DE4BE59CC36070F3C7E845"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on the personnel capacity and capability of the Department of State and the United States Agency for International Development (in this section referred to as <quote>USAID</quote>) to support United States strategic competition with the PRC and on available mechanisms to address any identified gaps.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0BD75CC14B364927BD3227B2731F0B2C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H1BF9CC88CC654377867E4C1AA71E0651"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report detailing the results of the study referred to in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13068187F1EA4AC9926C9FB2C937AAC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report referred to in paragraph (1) shall contain the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8791B74FF4AD4410AE9D9A7062C13B59"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The percentage of Foreign Service positions and civil service positions in the Indo-Pacific region that are vacant, as compared to the same vacancy rates for such positions in all other regions globally.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE91E8F47210D46D4BCD95F7425FE187D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A qualitative assessment of the gaps in understanding of the PRC among the Foreign Service, civil service, and intelligence community (as that term is defined in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>)) and how these perceived gaps hamper their work, which the Comptroller General of the United States shall compile after consulting with directors and deputy directors within the Department of State and USAID that the Comptroller General deems appropriate for informing United States policies on competition with the PRC.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0616D46638E94684B253B3C612D4441C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A recommendation of actions that Congress, the Executive Office of the President, and the Department of State can take to address the gaps referred to in subparagraph (B), disaggregated by whether such actions can be taken within a 1-, 5-, or 10-year period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4D9E431E10341F3BE45E2043E7D0B41"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report referred to in paragraph (1) may be submitted in classified or unclassified form and shall have an unclassified summary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBEA9E1443D934CB5B24C46B5574A1220"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Congressional briefings</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter until the submission of the report required by subsection (b)(1), the Comptroller General of the United States shall provide the appropriate congressional committees an interim briefing on the progress of the study referred to in subsection (a), including any preliminary observations, interim findings, and barriers to completing the work.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB013A5B3AB394ED3A2376BCFAB12E253"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4A5E052C5CA94D4DADCD573AD35893CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H0819AE203E734695A8A80C3E100D8E16"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD55D7F570FA147BE8C69CBD438BA2094"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED37F02786FC4B03A2BB56046CB5F1E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CCP</header><text>The term <term>CCP</term> means the Chinese Communist Party of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00F2F3C5B89F47E89E566C94E8B31B12"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Civil service</header><text>The term <term>civil service</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2101 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB36BD3A7DD264396B0A8986DD19100B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign Service</header><text>The term <term>Foreign Service</term> means the Foreign Service of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D35ABDC80C948C98D80A653B746A786"><enum>(5)</enum><header>PRC</header><text>The term <term>PRC</term> means the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

