<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAAAE9E6125524EFA918136EA57077AA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2932 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to report on the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2932</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to report on the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFD2FD5D51B264C43BAAAA2E386678BE9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H06123EEA35C74E299B31D85169CD93BB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Reporting on the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefits Administration</header>
<subsection id="H426C05736EC24F24B8BFF41B19894AE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports required</header>
<paragraph id="H42A5F79B9A594B79846875A00344C7A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on WARTAC.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE1A85B731774455B95A061FF0C0AF9D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>One year after the submission under paragraph (1) and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to such Committees a report that contains the elements under paragraphs (1) and (3) of subsection (b) with regards to the preceding year.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5D317E0DC5BC430481C23461D100F2D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Subject to subsection (a)(2), the reports under this section shall include the following elements:</text> <paragraph id="H507A68D85C894853BD9C2D8BA94ADB1E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Best TAP practices</header><text>With regards to TAP practices of WARTAC—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE9F651D560FC4CA9B9271ACD6C5C8561"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how many covered members have applied to participate in WARTAC;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9912835BB7747918FC8ED30ADF1F4B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how many covered members have participated in WARTAC;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HED118AF4A3AE4407B88990D90FA5D815"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the Secretary provides training to covered members during TAP;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H89BBC42F26AB4777BD61208F6D525A47"><enum>(D)</enum><text>how many covered members have completed WARTAC; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H40EF73CAD30245BFA7361B0E55E9F4B0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other information the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H357B9FB208114E9AAC1108522575A489"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost savings</header><text>With regards to cost savings of WARTAC—</text>
<subparagraph id="H718C1286EE1A454A814E789E7379F700"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how much money the Secretary determines WARTAC saves the United States each fiscal year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0BE9426F64AA487CB6A3DE4E45752350"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how much money the Secretary determines WARTAC has saved the United States since its establishment; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H79FC7A8C741043C6BD11CE4A5E0AEEDF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the determination of the Secretary whether other Federal agencies may save money by establishing a program similar to WARTAC.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDD1232425817404786D10E5DA7219B9C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Hiring</header><text>With regards to hiring covered members who complete WARTAC—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB76384D55CD14D0880B8560A56175E77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the Secretary identifies positions in the Department of Veterans Affairs for which such covered members may qualify;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2A5F9D656DD4CABAC049F9E4AD07E83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the grades of such positions on the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H473FF4282A894BC885233BBF812883D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how many such covered members the Secretary has hired to such positions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB822C4FF48D54F84A76387A0AA8320E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>Not later than 30 days after submitting the report under subsection (a)(1), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall transmit a copy of the report under this section to each head of a Federal agency.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HED6632D315154E1A839153E4399F91BC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H44F3D2CA8FF84406839C3A26DCA68049"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered member</term> means a member of the Armed Forces participating in TAP.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4B74B7A6771F4D33A374E9FD2241EB24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>TAP</term> means the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense under sections 1142 and 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C6DBE0613E64CD9A1DAD7E40F8D8695"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>WARTAC</term> means the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefits Administration, in which the Secretary provides training to covered members so such covered members may qualify for certain employment in the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

