<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H70EACB139E1E4386A42E3DC1EB0ECBDB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6705 IH: Effective Screening and Testing for Tuberculosis Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6705</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to treat certain tests for tuberculosis as breakthrough devices eligible for expedited development and priority review, to require certain establishments that perform donor screening or testing to screen or test for active and latent tuberculosis, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7922851DD1854066BCA1DB4FD1DE2E0A" style="OLC"><section id="H191362F184214C1180D36568B6AD3B28" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Effective Screening and Testing for Tuberculosis Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H03662EF3F94A4C22B78B0506C8BC23F8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of certain tests for tuberculosis as breakthrough devices</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall treat a device as a breakthrough device eligible for expedited development and priority review under section 515B of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360e-3">21 U.S.C. 360e–3</external-xref>) if it is a new and innovative donor screening test with heightened sensitivity to effectively screen human cell, tissue, and cellular and tissue-based product donors for evidence of active or latent tuberculosis infection.</text></section><section id="HDA493359B37748108C4267D30F11E4F4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requiring certain establishments that perform donor screening or testing to screen or test for active and latent tuberculosis</header><subsection id="H8D44BC926E4F45B1A7CE38AD0C67D7B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall promulgate regulations revising part 1271 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, including sections 1271.75 and 1271.85, and any other applicable regulations, to require—</text><paragraph id="H5651CC0E861543958BDAF62721C17879"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an establishment that performs donor screening to screen for active and latent tuberculosis; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDFFD580072E43AC8C6D35D0A03348E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an establishment that performs donor testing to test for active and latent tuberculosis.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08C2C96CF44B45D590A6ABCE7E7C56AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><paragraph id="HDD9675073B5F439C9AA2F33089EED568"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, propose the regulations required by subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCAAC1AD8D75426BB7DC8A2FBCE5DA11"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 3 months after the close of the comment period for such proposed regulations, promulgate such regulations as final; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4CA9CE240644A4A91C1BD74C8D4D34D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than 6 months after the date such regulations are promulgated as final, begin implementation of such regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21D83957ED0C4E0CACD84090986DD421"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <term>establishment that performs donor screening</term> and <term>establishment that performs donor testing</term> have the meanings given to such terms under part 1271 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4C7B09F1A61D4A73805010C5E7EADAE9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Guidance on current good tissue practice and additional requirements for manufacturers of human cells, tissues, and cellular and tissue-based products</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, and in coordination with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall—</text><paragraph id="H5EDAA962E5D743A1B892AAA29965EA29"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review the guidance titled <quote>Guidance for Industry—Current Good Tissue Practice (CGTP) and Additional Requirements for Manufacturers of Human Cells, Tissues, and Cellular and Tissue-Based Products (HCT/Ps)</quote> (December 2011); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H836759CB4B514BA5939510079DBBBFF1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue an updated version of such guidance.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6048DFB4F580432A9FEAF8FDDB278B93" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Compliance with CUTGO</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act, and this Act shall be carried out using amounts otherwise available for such purpose. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

