<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBEACBEF5AA3F43CABFC48FFAB6DA2D96" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6682 IH: Prohibiting Nationalization of American Companies and Investments Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6682</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit funding for the Government of Ukraine for the nationalization of strategic assets.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0A85A2ADBDB640C389B36A0501F36F0E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBD6326B57D9F456BAC021B72B320DBCB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prohibiting Nationalization of American Companies and Investments Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7FD5723DA39D417F9D6D234272CBE66E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of funds by the Government of Ukraine for the nationalization of United States assets</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No amounts appropriated or otherwise made available by a law enacted before, on, or after the date of the enactment of this Act, may be used by the Government of Ukraine for the nationalization, expropriation, forced liquidation, seizure, or imposition of any restrictions on shareholders rights to execute governance over, assets or property in Ukraine that is owned directly or indirectly by United States investors, including shareholder interests in any publicly traded company.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

