<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBC37CFB7C15348E383EE186A1E4BCC75" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6336 IH: Protect Veteran Students, Job Seekers, and Entrepreneurs Housing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6336</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act to ensure that certain education and workforce development benefits administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs are treated as income by landlords evaluating the ability of a servicemember, veteran, or a spouse or child of a servicemember or veteran, to pay rent, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5E0233AF6EB54EE18C53610223571650" style="OLC"><section id="H983B7997F730499C80EF9957BA556DB4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Veteran Students, Job Seekers, and Entrepreneurs Housing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5ADD6B83738546D98C75484655E7CD7C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of certain Department of Veterans Affairs benefits in determining income for purposes of entering into residential leases</header><subsection id="HCE5252114DA84397A99716638C0BFFFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3951">50 U.S.C. 3951 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section (and conforming the table of contents at the beginning of such Act accordingly):</text><quoted-block id="H4D659D623C64412CBA1DF073FDEEF04A" style="OLC"><section id="H19E2C786F3EC4FBC9D2143AFCAEC8E19"><enum>309.</enum><header>Treatment of certain Department of Veterans Affairs benefits in determining income for purposes of entering into residential leases</header><subsection id="H0238868CB390447C80A2D21837D9C8DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Protection</header><text>In determining whether a covered individual has an income sufficient to enter into a lease of premises for a residential purpose, the landlord (or other person with paramount title) of the premises shall treat any educational assistance received by the covered individual under any of chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, or 36 of title 38, United States Code, or chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10, United States Code, as income.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB7E09A449546410D8335DBDA88C3FC3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Lease period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When entering into a lease of premises for a residential purpose with a covered individual pursuant to subsection (a), the landlord (or other person with paramount title) shall guarantee that the period of the lease does not exceed the number of months of entitlement the individual has for the educational assistance described in such subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="H599745A78A734BBEBECFA1C02E07B7D6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H859693DCDF2D43E4A675E6020FC0B9AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A landlord (or other person with paramount title) who knowingly takes an action contrary to this section, or attempts to do so, may not participate in a covered Federally assisted rental housing program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5FDD3228A5C43BF9DECFDE30F3F5BB3" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A person who knowingly takes an action contrary to this section, or attempts to do so, shall be fined as provided in title 18, United States Code, or imprisoned for not more than one year, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H470F76B439A64357997DA020954383B9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA15CA48889624153BE9AA42E95F92664"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means a servicemember, veteran, or a spouse or child of a servicemember or veteran, who is entitled to educational assistance under chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, or 36 of title 38, United States Code, or chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD76C61CD425E428985E99D44FA82B4E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered Federally assisted rental housing</term> means a residential dwelling unit that is made available for rental and for which assistance is provided, or that is part of a housing project for which assistance is provided, under any program administered by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs (other than stipends made in connection with educational assistance), the Secretary of Agriculture, or the Secretary of the Treasury, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8815225B2607480380F98A650FB2B520"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the public housing program under the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437">42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFD3A847B020412CB255E929117294C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the program for rental assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C87DB05D70F4690A60F244A8402FA8F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the HOME Investment Partnerships program under title II of the Cranton-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12721">42 U.S.C. 12721 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0F9FAE453754EE69780A7D127E1AB61"><enum>(D)</enum><text>title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BF28194B3A24E06958F8B7FC6040B16"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">housing assistance for homeless veterans under section 2041 of title 38, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63207C5C458B4E34B3018E8E43075CC2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Housing Trust Fund program under section 1338 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4568">12 U.S.C. 4568</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A2C389982334B04ACE3BA57415EF073"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for the elderly under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2033CE174CD44C03AF0A115477E43E40"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for persons with disabilities under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29ED9310055F4F94B82A3FB1C081F433"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the AIDS Housing Opportunities program under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE73750E407F84785B6CAF8B36BA9E7DF"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the program for Native American housing under the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4101">25 U.S.C. 4101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H447BC37F36BD467087C4EA2E37974B5A"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the program for housing assistance for Native Hawaiians under title VIII of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4221">25 U.S.C. 4221 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DBC634A849A47039E5C3A1F201C3FDC"><enum>(L)</enum><text>the programs for assistance for rural rental housing under title V of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1471">42 U.S.C. 1471 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18936ADEF3E3469E859A9C67AD57383F"><enum>(M)</enum><text>the low-income housing tax credit program under section 42 of the Internal Revenue Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF3F20126759244B59EA6E8A1A776690C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extended grace period To maintain benefits</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/36">Chapter 36</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section (and conforming the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter accordingly):</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H22861825058542E8B2C68A734CEE35D4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFBCA785C962A4939BDFE3E61B9CB28B0"><enum>3699C.</enum><header>Grace period for individuals to maintain benefits</header><subsection id="H1353BFAD0EA94D41840D67E2571EB374"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary determines that a covered individual is not eligible for educational assistance described in subsection (b)(1) by reason of the covered individual failing to fulfill a single program requirement, the Secretary may not terminate the individual from using such assistance until—</text><paragraph id="HEBEC571BC73645E28AFC3ABC8A0FF60B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary notifies the individual of such failure; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE74605FA42A4EAA96E8BBA09C7B3EC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a period of 60 days has elapsed following such notification.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB6C0D83FD3DD425381172294CE5A3847"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H250906D5CB5A4DB4BC88B9785E72EE9C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual who is entitled to educational assistance under chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, or 36 of this title or chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AD8E2F4298B4354924B1B771B8FD357"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>program requirement</term> means a requirement to participate in educational assistance described in paragraph (1) relating to any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HB6CF5298132342CFB9853E117AA8E58D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Missing a recertification appointment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA65AB2DE2EA409BBE10C19693739805" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Withdrawing from a class.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEECF83AFAC704A958A33EC868D6D8E14"><enum>(C)</enum><text>With respect to a dependent, the death of the veteran.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82952C3F20E3432284F15898ADED8971"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Loss of employment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FF90B6D803B42658E8E23AC8C3B3C8C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any other requirement the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

