<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H747BBEC14694459E9A45F5DB2A406FE3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3286 RH: Securing Open Source Software Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 127</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3286</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–160, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on May 15, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to establish the duties of the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency regarding open source software security, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HHM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H4D9356FBD6B44326B75F0FC85C7E8F40"><section section-type="section-one" id="H346DE95C12F6455286E37CD6589D58EE"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Open Source Software Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HF6199CE68040454BB27D28AF67F2CE98"><enum>2.</enum><header>Open source software security duties</header><subsection id="HE977E238AC86438F981279E2502B7919"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title XXII of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H9F5CBF5E8DE941BD90AB022E22F22E1B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 2200 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H98437C60C19D470DA68E8400AE18B142"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (22) through (28) as paragraphs (25) through (31), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDC7305C1A6840268C77320A1D63A72C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (21) the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4AA2A2FD61704B05B1B53F82C68E555E" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><paragraph id="HD7F32FCC2D4A410DA532EBA31EADB6D7" commented="no"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Open source software</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>open source software</term> means software for which the human-readable source code is made available to the public for use, study, re-use, modification, enhancement, and re-distribution.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6227D39FA6F044398D9A3EAC0CE906A5"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Open source software community</header><text>The term <term>open source software community</term> means the community of individuals, foundations, nonprofit organizations, corporations, and other entities that—</text><subparagraph id="H9B353FCCFF3D4CD7BE95CCAA118C88E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop, contribute to, maintain, and publish open source software; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73405F29872B4B9CA5EB4C814F1673BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>otherwise work to ensure the security of the open source software ecosystem.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE89A56DF66324D999BE1D38E74553498"><enum>(24)</enum><header>Open source software component</header><text>The term <term>open source software component</term> means an individual repository of open source software that is made available to the public.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H722C0A9120DD444D9CB3EF9325BB14D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 2202(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/652">6 U.S.C. 652(c)</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H65CEC5DD2F7D43598171C6257F2B299C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (13), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A65744328CE4BC79BF47D24074A0E05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (14) as paragraph (15); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE90604261F4C405A87BCBC829CF5D0C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (13) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3393BE474BA4AFA84D69FF249D8760B" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><paragraph id="HDFF942E9068747FE9C12506656810D12" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><text>support, including by offering services, the secure usage and deployment of software, including open source software, in the software development lifecycle at Federal agencies in accordance with section 2220F; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B45C2955F274421992CF9F408CBAA58"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF83CB9C7635E4E83B15C6DF069AB8B82" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><section id="H35E95E92FD6248928C8BA7E98E2F4383"><enum>2220F.</enum><header>Open source software security duties</header><subsection id="H0EC281830D8F497CA8923AD89EB45DAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>software bill of materials</term> has the meaning given such term in the Minimum Elements for a Software Bill of Materials published by the Department of Commerce, or any superseding definition published by the Agency. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB8374BAF1E1A40F284080E5817EB91E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Employment</header><text>The Director shall, to the greatest extent practicable, employ individuals in the Agency who—</text><paragraph id="HC9A2E40FF91D47BEBDE88B3BB50649E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>have expertise and experience participating in the open source software community; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBC82DF67F954996BE90202CC1952965" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>perform the duties described in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3068B6E85A34BE3943FD24FC27F8D40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties of the Director</header><paragraph id="H0257ABA1A79840EEAB6DD23F728AF244"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="HF2FEB8D263994901AACCD0289F77D6CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>perform outreach and engagement to bolster the security of open source software;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8F3362BF29C41B086A66B87EB5689EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support Federal efforts to strengthen the security of open source software;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB787BC337E94592B92AB21BD5809411"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordinate, as appropriate, with non-Federal entities on efforts to ensure the long-term security of open source software;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15045532AA394F8FBEB2D0CDACC9038F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>serve as a public point of contact regarding the security of open source software for non-Federal entities, including State, local, Tribal, and territorial partners, the private sector, international partners, and open source software communities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H754DFE4C9FC84C63A5173FEE41A29505"><enum>(E)</enum><text>support Federal and non-Federal supply chain security efforts by encouraging efforts to bolster open source software security, such as—</text><clause id="H86AF02AD2FC34110AD5F5120BF0EDD8E"><enum>(i)</enum><text> assisting in coordinated vulnerability disclosures in open source software components pursuant to section 2209(n); and</text></clause><clause id="H7E18C378E6DD4CFD8F4B3E42DE4A2D5D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supporting the activities of the Federal Acquisition Security Council.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A881BF1210743DE9AA79C960EAC36FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment of critical open source software components</header><subparagraph id="H7539FD21E33F4317BC63578772CBBA64" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Framework</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Director shall publicly publish a framework, incorporating government, private sector, and open source software community frameworks and best practices, including those published by the National Institute of Standards and Technology, for assessing the risk of open source software components, including direct and indirect open source software dependencies, which shall incorporate, at a minimum, the following with respect to a given open source software component:</text><clause id="H88E9A76D338D4989A24FCEBF29F62445" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The security properties of code, such as whether the code is written in a memory-safe programming language or successor language.</text></clause><clause id="HF2BAC59B7414445984FD4036945DF0C0" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The security practices of development, build, and release processes, such as the use of multi-factor authentication by maintainers and cryptographic signing of releases.</text></clause><clause id="HF166F44029A745C7869D3636FC7792B6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The number and severity of publicly known, unpatched vulnerabilities.</text></clause><clause id="HE3803540625144CDABD52C57CC8C1B11" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The breadth of deployment.</text></clause><clause id="H01B030D3CF5D4111BC711FD006E024C5" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The level of risk associated with where such component is integrated or deployed, such as whether such component operates on a network boundary or in a privileged location.</text></clause><clause id="H3E066D5BC77849F1949DB096A109D43C" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The health and sustainability of the open source software community, including, where applicable, the level of current and historical investment and maintenance in such component, such as the number and activity of individual maintainers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF208890A002414BBE435CEA0A6C5605"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updating framework</header><text>Not less frequently than annually after the date on which the framework is published under subparagraph (A), the Director shall—</text><clause id="H4D4CE3FB477842779D850EB222DCA97D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine whether updates are needed to such framework, including the augmentation, addition, or removal of the elements described in clauses (i) through (vi) of such subparagraph; and </text></clause><clause id="H109DABDB3E804E7C93E7CF5D3B90E99C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the Director so determines that such additional updates are needed, make such updates.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF76AC2AF0DE24903A8D39ED066861817"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Developing framework</header><text>In developing the framework described in subparagraph (A), the Director shall consult with the following:</text><clause id="HF5A032CF41C647E68E1E4F6E991B28A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Appropriate Federal agencies, including the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></clause><clause id="HFFFF45DF6CB64B4B83256742BBA19D4C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The open source software community.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B5665FFECB544659288B31084C1F5FB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Usability</header><text>The Director shall ensure, to the greatest extent practicable, that the framework described in subparagraph (A) is usable by the open source software community, including through the consultation required under subparagraph (C).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7431EEAAB2744AEABDE5CE38C5199375"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Federal open source software assessment</header><text>Not later than one year after the publication of the framework under subparagraph (A) and not less frequently than every two years thereafter, the Director shall, to the greatest extent practicable and using such framework—</text><clause id="H82A51358319E469784A6134AAD5306B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perform an assessment of each open source software component deployed on high value assets, as described in Office of Management and Budget memorandum M-19-03 (issued December 10, 2018) or successor guidance, at Federal agencies based on readily available, and, to the greatest extent practicable, machine readable, information, such as—</text><subclause id="H1E522B2F0E464E7E9D1DB36583BAED15"><enum>(I)</enum><text>software bills of material that are, at the time of the assessment, made available to the Agency or are otherwise accessible via the internet; </text></subclause><subclause id="HE8CA7BB6D565484681BD4C47E752067C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>software inventories, available to the Director at the time of the assessment, from the Continuous Diagnostics and Mitigation program of the Agency; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0CE94246D4994DE1AA55D9AFE04440A9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>other publicly available information regarding open source software components; and </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H505E3C02640B4EB7BD7F28F8D339EF0F" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop, in consultation with the Federal agency at which an open source software component is deployed, one or more ranked lists of components described in clause (i) based on such assessment, such as ranked by the criticality, level of risk, or usage of the components, or a combination thereof.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCC906708DDB405A9AD3BAB270AF4B25"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Automation</header><text>The Director shall, to the greatest extent practicable, automate the assessment performed pursuant to subparagraph (E).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E2ABE7E09744EDC8BFE4BEED0963B15"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Director shall publicly publish and maintain any tools developed to perform the assessment under subparagraph (E) as open source software.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H52B6D02EA1EE4547901ABBFB89141001"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Sharing</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AF817A1A50F4A4FA085A582D8307B59"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director, to the greatest extent practicable, and taking into account the sensitivity of the information contained in the assessment performed pursuant to subparagraph (E), shall facilitate the sharing of the results of each assessment under subparagraph (E)(i) with appropriate Federal and non-Federal entities working to support the security of open source software, including by offering means for appropriate Federal and non-Federal entities to download the assessment in an automated manner. </text></clause><clause id="HA0D579AB127B4D1F9816BE5D3C073952"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Datasets</header><text>The Director may publicly publish, as appropriate, any datasets or versions of the datasets developed or consolidated as a result of an assessment under subparagraph (E)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3248DCD1A3F54F91B4E12C22093A42E2"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure assessment study and pilot</header><clause id="H6E32260C0CE9463EB05CB82BF1750371"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Not later than two years after the publication of the framework under subparagraph (A), the Director shall conduct a study regarding the feasibility of the Director conducting the assessment under subparagraph (E) for critical infrastructure entities.</text></clause><clause id="HBFE005C68E1C4136888824780A7A2748"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Pilot</header><subclause id="H82DA82F4589D4F52AAE06A29EADE8175"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Director determines that the assessment described in clause (i) is feasible, the Director may conduct a pilot assessment on a voluntary basis with one or more critical infrastructure sectors, in coordination with the Sector Risk Management Agency and the sector coordinating council of each participating sector.</text></subclause><subclause id="HBB1CC20178494E49B879BE037D980A62"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>If the Director proceeds with the pilot assessment described in subclause (I), such pilot assessment shall terminate not later than two years after the date on which the Director begins such pilot assessment.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE57DB135A8104BA9A035911D3BD6D374"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Reports</header><subclause id="H6099B80C69EA4B4C9317EEE6452F922A"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the Director completes the study conducted under clause (i), the Director shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text><item id="HC5A6A3DB6789415588C25F53BC96C617"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>summarizes the study;</text></item><item id="H5EEB36F6A7A0493F844B49BE609E0F02"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>states whether the Director plans to proceed with the pilot assessment described in clause (ii)(I); and</text></item><item id="HA072CB7275754250842D7A40813491FA"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>if the Director proceeds with such pilot assessment, describes—</text><subitem id="H8F75468495C94A018311F9EEF49C5DAF"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the methodology for selecting the critical infrastructure sector or sectors to participate in the pilot; and</text></subitem><subitem id="H857413935ED04F07B924841DE3E910F6"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the resources required to carry out the pilot.</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="HEA27FBDCDFB440588DF6AECC3863FE36"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Pilot</header><text>If the Director proceeds with the pilot assessment described in clause (ii), not later than one year after the date on which the Director begins such pilot assessment, the Director shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes the following:</text><item id="HECDB443636214006B2E40C51E9D644F5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>A summary of the results of such pilot assessment.</text></item><item id="H6204663892A04E97840D4070CB5AABC6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>A recommendation as to whether the activities carried out under such pilot assessment should be continued after the termination of such pilot assessment in accordance with clause (ii)(II). </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC4B2F6887DD4F7A846DDAD8F8F135EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation with National Cyber Director</header><text>The Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="H1BDFEFC8D933448EA8189D3CB6341C97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>brief the National Cyber Director on the activities described in this subsection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB034FDF8EEDF4EBFAC55ED2AA821A48A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consult with the National Cyber Director regarding such activities, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88EDE0E4D6CD4DC799E5BD6F5EA572F0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports</header><subparagraph id="H9470825343844CB0BE66501D782C9B14" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section and every two years thereafter for the following six years, the Director shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes for the period covered by each such report the following:</text><clause id="H0308D5DDFE3B4834BE25EF96C9FA743F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A summary of the work on open source software security performed by the Director, including a list of the Federal and non-Federal entities with which the Director interfaced.</text></clause><clause id="H3F6D70C5A4544F10B195FE905F07B4D0" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The framework under paragraph (2)(A) or a summary of any updates to such framework pursuant to paragraph (2)(B), as the case may be.</text></clause><clause id="H50BBC5FC6C3947FABCEB54CB9B2FE476" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A summary of each assessment under paragraph (2)(E)(i).</text></clause><clause id="H334469EC921E4DA194E3BA9D52FCFDC2" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A summary of changes made to each such assessment, including overall security trends.</text></clause><clause id="HEDABDAC5E58A4CED9327400133CEA949" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A summary of the types of entities with which each such assessment was shared pursuant to paragraph (2)(H), including a list of the Federal and non-Federal entities with which such assessment was shared.</text></clause><clause id="HB6E02A33E61C453494267A1E661473AC" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Information on resources, including staffing, allocated to the Director’s open source software responsibilities under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D714EAC8D6B406A88BB1D803DC11874"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Director submits each report required under subparagraph (A), the Director shall make a version of each such report publicly available on the website of the Agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBEA48E8D970B4A1EBBAAF531667F0E7D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 2220E the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BBBE7A00A244D36A280DE6026E46439" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 2220F. Open source software security duties.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H73CA6B75F1DC4536BF3C8DBC94173120"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Software security advisory subcommittee</header><text>Section 2219(d)(1) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/665e">6 U.S.C. 665e(d)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC639EE521B9E49EBB1F40937A1BE8D34" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00"><subparagraph id="HDC8B1CCA07F44E58A1A998BAEDD032D5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Software security, including open source software security.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD00D1AA88EBF43429C2227EA1E5ADFD7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act or the amendments made by this Act may be construed to provide any additional regulatory authority to any Federal agency described therein.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HHM00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

