<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7D243D3276774B53AD3BDF83D320769F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6692 IH: Students and Young Consumers Empowerment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6692</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 to establish the position of the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, to establish the Office for Students and Young Consumers of the Bureau, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5C52FCD40C6B489B89271B0C174CBA43" style="OLC"><section id="H6016C116EDEE4BBDBD820185AA6A3213" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Students and Young Consumers Empowerment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDA6369A2C2AD44B785621934C3D62F57"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate</header><subsection id="H49F76A3475EC4C4F9AABEF6BB7EAD62A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1035 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5535">12 U.S.C. 5535</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4CD2B6A3D7DA49E6A76BDCAC07E8B15D" style="OLC"><section id="H4B73A9DFADA84297BFAC0C4D7EAC7E64"><enum>1035.</enum><header>Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate</header><subsection id="HDE3FAA146CB74E698B328DD36083F8ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the position of Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate, who shall be appointed by the Director.</text></subsection><subsection id="H769577C1C9A54086ACA5EA3317FEB20A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate shall—</text><paragraph id="H346699051DE0475D9410A2E13B8F6106"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve as the head of the Office for Students and Young Consumers established under subsection (e);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C2477D293524FCEA62F7CD56577E15D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this section, enter into a memorandum of understanding with the Secretary of Education, the Chief Operating Officer appointed under section 141(d) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1018">20 U.S.C. 1018(d)</external-xref>), and the Student Loan Ombudsman appointed under section 141(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1018">20 U.S.C. 1018(f)</external-xref>) that—</text><subparagraph id="H64D9ABC81CB44678BCAED4CE49B2BC4F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures coordination in providing assistance to and serving borrowers seeking to resolve complaints related to their private education or Federal student loans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE09D2B0BEF254F5786F4F0B491572AA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>authorizes the Bureau to access all relevant Department of Education information systems, records, and data, including any relevant information systems, records, or data maintained by contractors of the Department of Education;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFA0B197261B4ED9B8593D0504B67AE9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">accept and attempt to resolve complaints from borrowers with both private education loans and Federal student loans, including complaints against lenders, servicers, and debt collectors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB48830BCD54C44D29FD83F4027BE2AA3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carry out such other duties as the Director may determine appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E7EF7703C1D4F2F89CA5D98E5184F15"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notification to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall provide written notice and an explanation to the appropriate congressional committees, if—</text><paragraph id="HAD19ACF53447478BBE2F1D559B363CD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the position of the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate has been vacant for a period of 60 days or more; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B74D36253A549E3A480675CF389B404"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the memorandum of understanding required under subsection (b)(2) has lapsed for a period of 60 days or more.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81AE6993EBDB4AE6A6253AFEAC800BD5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HFF109265351141B1B646D9672E846327"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual report on the student loan marketplace</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE62366AFC3604DFAB35EB350BE371658"><enum>(A)</enum><text>compile and analyze complaints from borrowers with Federal student loans or private education loans;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0477694576D24E26B2E49F376714DD6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than once per year, submit a report to Congress summarizing the activities of the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate in the previous year and including an independent evaluation of risks to consumers posed by policies and practices in the student loan marketplace; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8758E983D37C429C938B8D322CEB1DA3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as part of each report submitted in accordance with subparagraph (B), and any other time deemed prudent by the Student Loan Borrower Advocate, make recommendations to the Director, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Education, and the appropriate congressional committees to address risk to student loan borrowers and strengthen the student loan marketplace.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1910517050D348F7BEA6B249812C11D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report on campus banking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than once per year, the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate shall issue a report to the appropriate congressional committees analyzing the use of consumer financial products and services by students enrolled at institutions of higher education, including an evaluation of contracts and other financial arrangements between institutions of higher education and providers of consumer financial products and services, including an evaluation of revenue sharing provisions, marketing provisions, and fees assessed to students who use such products and services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23C5F099E2EB4E59BF16DA0D5FEB7CE2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report on risks to young consumers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than once per year, the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate shall issue a report to the appropriate congressional committees containing an analysis of complaints submitted to the Bureau by young consumers during the previous year and offering an independent evaluation of risks to consumers posed by policies and practices in the marketplace for consumer financial products and services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC58EC93D6BEC40848EDA5EA864EB0181"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Office for Students and Young Consumers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established an Office for Students and Young Consumers, which shall be responsible for developing and implementing initiatives for students, young consumers, and their families intended to—</text><paragraph id="H05B1152398814716852985731914E8DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>educate and empower students, young consumers, and their families to make better informed decisions regarding consumer financial products and services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB6EE30DE4CF406A8ACEB7B14F77D8C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate efforts among Federal and State agencies, as appropriate, regarding consumer protection measures relating to consumer financial products and services offered to, or used by, students, young consumers, and their families.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB44C445A4FE4880A82B92C3296125E7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Collection of information; market monitoring</header><paragraph id="H492FA60AFDB54B69B048BE38FCC4215B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate shall have the authority to gather information from time to time regarding the organization, business conduct, markets, and activities of covered persons and service providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CC231050E0F43CBAAAA9B49F0A539C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sources of information</header><text>In gathering information described under paragraph (1), the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate may gather and compile information from a variety of sources, including examination reports concerning covered persons or service providers, consumer complaints, voluntary surveys and voluntary interviews of consumers, surveys and interviews with covered persons and service providers, and review of available databases.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E01B3BEBDCF455DAC52DE239B236C1C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority to require reports and other information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall, upon the recommendation of the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate, require covered persons and service providers participating in consumer financial services markets to file with the Bureau, under oath or otherwise, in such form and within such reasonable period of time as the Bureau may prescribe by rule or order, annual or special reports, answers in writing to specific questions, or other information described under section 1022(c)(4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6FDA5F2F46F4C5D81FB468B88C5911D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Bureau may not use its authorities under this subsection to obtain records from covered persons and service providers participating in consumer financial services markets for purposes of gathering or analyzing the personally identifiable financial information of consumers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA931ADFCE744304B860CF35C50FD7B8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="H9F65E2CE0A2142D3B4C8839A4E03A91C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committees on Education and the Workforce and Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1EB56FAB8234535AE4AD02F4B98DFE8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Truth in Lending Act terms</header><text>The terms <term>private education loan</term> and <term>institution of higher education</term> have the meanings given those terms, respectively, under section 140 of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1650">15 U.S.C. 1650</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7D12A0493BC04A278EC6FCC8EA1B817F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents under section 1(b) of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act is amended, in the item relating to section 1035, by striking <quote>Private Education Loan Ombudsman</quote> and inserting <quote>Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5B6EF065B02144F2A05D2D77F4811D3C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Duties of the Department of Education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title I of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1018">20 U.S.C. 1018 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6242E2ADAAC8459281F2FFBA2CB9A564" style="OLC"><section id="H342EC08CB71C473997C1FB0D34D32FD9"><enum>144.</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding with the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Education, the Chief Operating Officer appointed under section 141(d), and the Student Loan Ombudsman appointed under section 141(f) shall enter into a memorandum of understanding with the Assistant Director and Student Loan Borrower Advocate of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection that—</text><paragraph id="H3453EE25E342461E8128EEF110859DE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensures coordination in providing assistance to and serving borrowers seeking to resolve complaints related to their private education loans or loans made, insured, or guaranteed under title IV; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF29C935BF27C4F53959F1BCDB1591685"><enum>(2)</enum><text>authorizes the Bureau to access all relevant Department information systems, records, and data, including any relevant information systems, records, or data maintained by contractors of the Department.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

