<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H58663768F2974417826DBD0241448A9E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1412 IH: Digital Equity Foundation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1412</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the Foundation for Digital Equity, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H87BC5EC79B6647CBB7589904E33D2582" style="OLC">
<section id="H9BB98CEBCB97416BB70FC6F224AF5176" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Digital Equity Foundation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H731FB3FBA8DB4F55A3D2FE5D1165CDB6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Foundation for digital equity</header> <subsection id="H092DDE1B55524CF1B68456E845B7D560"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H1388BFC150D240B59B28C8CFC222B830"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistant secretary</header><text>The term <term>Assistant Secretary</term> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF94D70C0596453A9483896AE9639C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Board</header><text>The term <term>Board</term> means the Board of Directors described in subsection (d)(1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22AE613920984E6483723F390AEB2247"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Business incubator</header><text>The term <term>business incubator</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Native American Business Incubators Program Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5802">25 U.S.C. 5802</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4F1BC79488BF4AA5913FD881956D0950"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8CE2660A1B8D4A138E2C5B914DC4A348"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Committee</header><text>The term <term>Committee</term> means the Committee for the Establishment of the Foundation for Digital Equity established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABF7F61F03574937AB8669635032E728"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Community anchor institution; covered household; covered populations</header><text>The terms <term>community anchor institution</term>, <term>covered household</term>, and <term>covered populations</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 60302 of the Digital Equity Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1721">47 U.S.C. 1721</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4856B8B33B3B41249635B96DDED52821"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Commerce.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3389B16B4C594656A8AE0B5A95061950"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Digital equity</header><text>The term <term>digital equity</term> means the condition in which individuals and communities have the information technology capacity that is needed for full participation in the society and economy of the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3409E69B39254639BB31F1A5ADF3E0A1"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Digital inclusion</header><text>The term <term>digital inclusion</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="HC2D838C3EFED42BC99BA1C4780FA168E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the activities that are necessary to ensure that all individuals in the United States have access to, and the use of, affordable information and communication technologies, such as—</text>
<clause id="HB619BFD5A6A847F2A6BD9A2656FB0738"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reliable fixed and wireless broadband;</text></clause> <clause id="H107C0F14CD4943EB84F4B82FF0A02C28"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>internet-enabled devices that meet the needs of the user for telehealth, remote work, remote schooling, or other purposes; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB5548B5170DF42C1ABCAFAC6AF5AF77E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>applications and online content designed to enable and encourage self-sufficiency, participation, and collaboration; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H659FE032F22E4A00BDE7D2095269C11A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text>
<clause id="HFA7D0A499446469285A982778EDD7BEB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>obtaining access to digital literacy training;</text></clause> <clause id="HBE10E293ED5D4D23BFAD9EB24CDEF4C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the provision of quality technical support; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB2D55308EDA54623902BF1D7B67E5897"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>obtaining basic awareness of measures to ensure online privacy and cybersecurity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB979179E4784831A1B1B73C47A1F819"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Digital literacy</header><text>The term <term>digital literacy</term> means the skills associated with using technology to enable users to find, evaluate, organize, create, and communicate information.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80BE31F466EE48A0AB9E50A577046FB1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Executive director</header><text>The term <term>Executive Director</term> means the Executive Director of the Foundation described in subsection (f)(1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1CCD7212D7F843E9BB566E84E2D352FD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Foundation</header><text>The term <term>Foundation</term> means the Foundation for Digital Equity established under subsection (c). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3F2023239EDB4E7395F59247E44430A2"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HB358FEBD303A499C80D3D2FF11557FF5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education, as that term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3A66BB2E3F1846E896781398E6560247" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a postsecondary vocational institution, as that term is defined in section 102(c) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002(c)</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBEC8E9AD4E042778D1408F3DAF0A3CE"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Minority-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Minority-serving institution</term> means an institution described in any of paragraphs (1) through (7) of section 371(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067q">20 U.S.C. 1067q(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A0E0FE29381479EB8A2B18CE376FD90"><enum>(15)</enum><header>NTIA</header><text>The term <term>NTIA</term> means the National Telecommunications and Information Administration.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4561303C4B0B476485350646ED762073" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Older individual</header><text>The term <term>older individual</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3001">42 U.S.C. 3001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H46F568F7EC1E43488F06A612B8EBE7DF"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce. </text></paragraph> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HA01F99537E9146C88431B0C339E82D15"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Small business investment company</header><text>The term <term>small business investment company</term> has the meaning given the term in section 103 of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/662">15 U.S.C. 662</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HBE84686B2F334D9A8E690ED3D0D93DB9"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Startup</header><text>The term <term>startup</term> has the meaning given the term <term>start-up business</term> in section 362(f)(5)(C) of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6322">42 U.S.C. 6322(f)(5)(C)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H1BEB1C1BD02741328DE40F1D9E8A2931"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Tribal Broadband Connectivity Program</header><text>The term <term>Tribal Broadband Connectivity Program</term> means the program established pursuant to section 905(c) of division N of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1305">47 U.S.C. 1305</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE64655E660E94B63BA88975FAA3AA5EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Committee for the Establishment of the Foundation for Digital Equity</header>
<paragraph id="H33E4F1670B6C4D19B5B1DDCB59066F36"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish the Committee for the Establishment of the Foundation for Digital Equity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C74DAA8850747548D62C94502C58508"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Members</header><text>The Committee shall be composed of 5 members—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA0205A1B16494517B73286DA9AECF864"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who shall be appointed by the officials described in subsection (d)(2)(B)(i);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBDF8608E5BF944379CE14E03B75FC770"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each of whom shall be a voting member of the Committee; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H52EBF9A063E547A8A10C201809990122"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not fewer than 3 of whom shall have broad and general experience in matters relating to digital equity, digital inclusion, or digital literacy; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0810989B4ABE42779E72AE0774F0F41C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>not less than 1 of whom shall have broad and general experience in working with private nonprofit organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9A30846835884F23A5574C19790287B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The functions of the Committee are as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="HF9D6347FBDC644E5B75567B67D7DE2A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To carry out such activities as may be necessary to incorporate the Foundation under the laws of a State, including by— </text>
<clause id="HA47754E251B54DA88C2ACC3B43068AA9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serving as the incorporators for the Foundation; and</text></clause> <clause id="H07081878A4C4456780918E1075672C72"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensuring that the articles of incorporation for the Foundation require that the Foundation is operated in accordance with the requirements of this section.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6D755215273149DDBEC684FE46776127"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To ensure that the Foundation qualifies for and (during the period in which the Committee is in existence) maintains the status described in subsection (c)(4).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F7C128C2EF941F2A145411AA189546B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To provide for the initial operation of the Foundation, including by ensuring that the Foundation has adequate facilities, equipment, and staff.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBEB4D23F60FC46398674866B48C3A43C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To appoint initial voting members of the Board who satisfy the requirements under subsection (d)(2)(C) and have such other qualifications as the Committee determines appropriate with respect to those members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CF9956967F649E5BBC04716C85722EB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Committee shall, from among the members of the Committee, designate a member of the Committee to serve as Chair of the Committee.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H19E9FE766F174C9DB1D88BF6611CC74C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Term</header>
<subparagraph id="H60AD31C8C1B544D2A23EF687516F553D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member of the Committee shall serve for the duration of the Committee.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E96415406234F1F8A4859A5D75A8B18"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header> <clause id="H41975E01BC5F47E68888242B1BF8B71F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>No effect on authority</header><text>A vacancy in the membership of the Committee shall not affect the authority of the Committee to carry out the functions of the Committee.</text></clause>
<clause id="HDAA520361B5C474784DA8F2096078AB4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Replacement</header><text>If a member of the Committee does not serve for the duration of the Committee, the individual appointed to fill that vacancy shall be appointed by the ex officio members of the Board for the remainder of the applicable term.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3CD0F2BD60494EFFABB5AAF9CCF74F1F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>A member of the Committee— </text>
<subparagraph id="H21625A4296774BF98259604120A56395"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not receive compensation for service on the Committee; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC63DC03DC4A14C0CA7AD309917DA1221"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be reimbursed for travel, subsistence, and other necessary expenses incurred in carrying out the functions of the Committee.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4A2CB4EF0C844CBC985413FF3DECCE43"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Committee shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H1015B433C92C43B4BE77061AD8EE6AE0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete the functions of the committee described in paragraph (3) not later than 180 days after the date on which the Secretary establishes the Committee under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1817E9CE39164B2E9282414899795AC9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>terminate on the date that is 30 days after the date on which the Secretary determines that the Committee has completed the functions described in paragraph (3). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H21C554F260044719A5812CCC3A0E44B9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="H22A5DECA84764C538298311C66B87117"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a nonprofit corporation to be known as the <quote>Foundation for Digital Equity</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7613AC7016AD4B9DB77BAD1F57227E86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Foundation shall be—</text> <subparagraph id="H51F709CDEB5C4D5FA34BBBDEECFAD1EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to supplement, but not supplant, the work of the NTIA and the Commission in promoting the benefits of technological development in the United States, and of high-capacity, affordable broadband connectivity in particular, for all users of telecommunications and information facilities; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4B878453CB7C4233917B0761BAAFE51B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to raise, leverage, or match funding from other entities, including philanthropic organizations, the private sector, and State and local governments, to promote digital literacy, digital inclusion, and digital equity for communities with low rates of adoption of broadband;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6E5AA04273094EE2ABA3858C538B204D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to develop programs and partnerships to—</text>
<clause id="HB9BD9B6706B445A1BAF9273778B2A663"><enum>(i)</enum><text>spur greater rates of adoption of broadband among covered populations;</text></clause> <clause id="H1D3096E868B74A7696CF04CDEC33D52A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>collaborate with State, local, and Tribal governments, Minority-serving institutions, other anchor institutions, and stakeholders in the communications, education, business, and technology fields;</text></clause>
<clause id="H608DC6CEE8654D0583E93F56992A799A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>publicize and incentivize the adoption of evidence-based programs;</text></clause> <clause id="H8893BF17090441EFA8A3A4C85B1E8744"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>convene organizations and partnerships with related goals and interests to establish problem-solving processes;</text></clause>
<clause id="H79AEE68B70E5488EAB9F26868132F8B5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>strengthen and share best practices relating to—</text> <subclause id="H75A688EFD1334A0DBF86A8BAE60AE756"><enum>(I)</enum><text>projects promoting digital inclusion, digital literacy, and digital equity; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H486AEC228C0845059077EBF714DECDB6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>regional economic development;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H59B6A37C81604357BC46A0AB57862939"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>support job creation and workforce development; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H9A5971D0B37A49B7B3447E1A3B5D93E9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>support the goals of the Tribal Broadband Connectivity Program; and </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H136F3A1E4AE14DB19D178D07F9FA92B8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to promote equitable access to, and the adoption of, broadband technologies and digital applications that support accessibility, telehealth, distance learning, and online access to governmental benefits and services, including by preventing, detecting, and remedying digital discrimination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCAB335DDD83D4EAD9BECC2AF4C4A4D2F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Foundation shall not be an agency or instrumentality of the Federal Government or any State or local government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23D1796C5ADA452FA9627760F9C08FED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tax-exempt status</header><text>The Board shall take all necessary and appropriate steps to ensure that the Foundation is an organization that is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of that Code.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6E46A5AE0D08483CB6B88CFEB5758192"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Board of directors</header>
<paragraph id="H220D9CD8086E4F948E66C0FD9BC08250"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Foundation shall be governed by a Board of Directors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0A5B2997B08A4DA7A73A1CDB08360AB2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header> <subparagraph id="H6099F1DFBB624644AC220677F01EE6F8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall be composed of the ex officio members described in subparagraph (B) and the appointed voting members described in subparagraph (C).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H82D3672ADDA749F09CC4BAFAC8EFFDB2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ex officio members</header>
<clause id="H5078523594DA4AA1AB870E0E167D1E97"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Members</header><text>The ex officio members of the Board shall be the following individuals (or designees of those individuals):</text> <subclause id="HC3F762CB5CA04409BEFB5DF9E0B78ADA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Secretary.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC4723359C7784A7991F11DECC8C8FF2F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HED0E0AC227DA47918250C715469B0739"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The Chairman of the Commission.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1EA8C6027CCC4C298F9DDAD4045CD921"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Treasury.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5B53953F701B4C2FA21ECD423F831DED"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of Agriculture for Rural Development.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H5A7096A219B6435CA5B2F8CD38E256E0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Nonvoting members</header><text>The ex officio members of the Board shall be nonvoting members of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4195071530544B2EA3942C395B091D38"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appointed members</header> <clause id="HAA2503F2D2264F8AA9040CF60DA0A542"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>The appointed members of the Board shall reflect a broad cross-section of stakeholders from academia, industry, nonprofit and civil rights organizations, community-based practitioners of efforts to promote digital inclusion, State or local governments, local school districts and libraries, other community anchor institutions, and the philanthropic community.</text></clause>
<clause id="HD4AC7DBDB7AD41439E972ED39A55CDB5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Experience</header><text>Each appointed member of the Board shall—</text> <subclause id="H7F3C64B872AC4911A51114CD94724E9A"><enum>(I)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H23AA5E079DCE415688F5F5E312DA8D8A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>have experience promoting digital equity, digital inclusion, and digital literacy;</text></item>
<item indent="up1" id="HB6D60DBB31E746AF922606FE4744B9C8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>have experience in the technology sector; </text></item> <item indent="up1" id="H6CBCC71F1A8D428F964DE9ACF390A9C7"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>have experience in the telecommunications and broadband sector; </text></item>
<item indent="up1" id="H5AD11162314D4C3B94AC69228B9D45CD"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>have direct experience working with covered populations; or</text></item> <item indent="up1" id="HB12074E917054400803C31FD06F7A4FF"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>have research experience in foundation operations; and </text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="HEDBC2A4A546645D6A241B34D3828F778"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, represent diverse regions, sectors, and the communities corresponding to the covered populations that are the focus of the activities of the Foundation.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H577D8E94B3E74EE79155FFB1CEF510A6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chair and vice chair</header> <subparagraph id="H9932C55E4EF4455CAD0821DDD4775716"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall designate, from among the appointed members of the Board—</text>
<clause id="HA0A48AED21B74A2AAC5AC3F444A9A4E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an individual to serve as Chair of the Board; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4647555ADF864D4D8A7D38FBAE7C93C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an individual to serve as Vice Chair of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H99DC63351CBD40BD9089DF9CCE884FCA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>The term of service of the Chair and Vice Chair of the Board shall end on the earlier of—</text> <clause id="H7511B1BB58944C27981C87F05C6FC01F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date that is 3 years after the date on which the Chair or Vice Chair of the Board, as applicable, is designated for the position; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HCEBB8286D0974551B3DA295232100985"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the last day of the term of service of the member, as determined under paragraph (4)(A), who is designated to be Chair or Vice Chair of the Board, as applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H63ACBA6702F542CF91209E77471BEF13"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>The Chair and Vice Chair of the Board—</text>
<clause id="HD20CA062A3334C988ED94000F9F33240"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not be representatives of the same area of subject matter expertise, or entity, as applicable, under paragraph (2)(C)(ii); and</text></clause> <clause id="HE3FE926781C84405AC61D76AB044467A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be representatives of any area of subject matter expertise, or entity, as applicable, represented by the immediately preceding Chair and Vice Chair of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9A0F373CC6404DCCB6CCC96C8900477F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terms and vacancies</header>
<subparagraph id="HD560EE3C64844C97A73189833AB3553B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Terms</header>
<clause id="HD352E32410344FDD9854E71D19C8CA89"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term of service of each appointed member of the Board shall be not more than 5 years.</text></clause> <clause id="HA9BD3C531C9744BCB8324B444A5DF682"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Initial appointed members</header><text>Of the initial members of the Board appointed under subsection (b)(3)(D), <fraction>1/2</fraction> of the members shall serve for 4 years and <fraction>1/2</fraction> of the members shall serve for 5 years, as determined by the Chair of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB52F9F7EA343462EB3AC5C6D679B43A4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the membership of the appointed members of the Board—</text> <clause id="HEE872BDDF1F9418EABD941C3FB49C4B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be filled by a majority vote of the appointed members of the Board in accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation;</text></clause>
<clause id="HE669FC68B563409B953C50C3BFE9894D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not affect the power of the remaining appointed members to execute the duties of the Board; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCAC9842C9DEA45299A5994F8FF956667"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall be filled by an individual selected by the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F848B178118438EA770565FE8C6A311"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Meetings; quorum</header>
<subparagraph id="H11957474443445CC9C524D6BF517A081"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial meeting</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which all of the members of the Board have been appointed, the Secretary shall convene a meeting of the ex officio and appointed members of the Board to establish the bylaws of the Foundation in accordance with paragraph (7).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD9A44236F3B44F7F8C656B3211E3D2CA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the appointed members of the Board shall constitute a quorum for purposes of conducting the business of the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H79BAD8243EA04B4D88BA5688D8616BEC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Board shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H486A32EE88A143F18778DEC0DBB75B50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide overall direction for the activities of the Foundation and establish priority activities;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0060A508E0334C6C8B8DB1000BED6823"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide guidance to the Executive Director such that the Executive Director may carry out any other necessary activities of the Foundation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5C61963B57F4405CBFE8639D0588F280"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evaluate the performance of the Executive Director; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9EECBD7413EF490B98E31EEAE85B38D6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>actively solicit and accept funds, gifts, grants, devises, or bequests of real or personal property to the Foundation, including from private entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4307688CF75B472696914E59B3EECA5D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Bylaws</header> <subparagraph id="H8E17A8B236AB40A09519545BA1A18430"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The bylaws established under paragraph (5)(A) may include—</text>
<clause id="H4403697F32A640C396685752839458AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>policies for the selection of Board members and officers, employees, agents, and contractors of the Foundation;</text></clause> <clause id="H20585453DBC1416FA92F7748CEF95043"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>policies, including ethical standards, for—</text>
<subclause id="H017FF134CA0F401EADC1C9568931AB43"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the acceptance, solicitation, and disposition of donations and grants to the Foundation, including appropriate limits on the ability of donors to designate, by stipulation or restriction, the use or recipient of donated funds; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9BFDA4A607E9475AB67B2822FBAA800E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the disposition of assets of the Foundation;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HC867057E0E97409AA7CF00BA57B88470"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>policies that subject all employees, fellows, trainees, contractors, consultants, and other agents of the Foundation (including ex officio and appointed members of the Board) to conflict of interest standards; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA805BD53D59545F197D33557048D0CA2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the specific duties of the Executive Director.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF3EB4E15F6954C999CDD042328468ADB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Board shall ensure that the bylaws of the Foundation and the activities carried out under those bylaws shall not—</text> <clause id="H89BC21B1A2F54A4A870E9E8F42B43909"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reflect unfavorably on the ability of the Foundation to carry out activities in a fair and objective manner; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H91858110110C49688A5C759AEA98578E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>compromise, or appear to compromise, the integrity of any Federal agency or program, or any officer or employee employed by, or involved in, such an agency or program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H73CFB032F6534751B4170D9A41819317"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Compensation</header> <subparagraph id="H407F9036AE2848B5B62C7BAF8A21C90B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No member of the Board shall receive compensation for serving as a member of the Board.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1DCD5703AAD040929982AA2782D45D68"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reimbursement of certain expenses</header><text>In accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation, members of the Board may be reimbursed for travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, and other necessary expenses incurred in carrying out the duties of the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA73C6477D26E44CBB1F44F61299FB1B2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Activities</header> <paragraph id="H7B1C320429F9454A984C67DD6A68900C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Studies, competitions, and projects</header><text>The Foundation may conduct and support studies, competitions, projects, and other activities that further the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H997C3D61477F477E8E3DEFEA606CB55A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header>
<subparagraph id="HC136ADAA2F9E413899539C8AD5CF5C5D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation may award grants for activities relating to digital equity, digital inclusion, or digital literacy.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9CE5E3CC0CC34A398CEC199E9B702E8E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>In selecting a recipient for a grant awarded under subparagraph (A), the Foundation—</text>
<clause id="HBE52AA70C2B84431AB84A3BE1E20E633"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall make the selection based on the comparative merits of— </text> <subclause id="H4F34AB0A064D4A739CCD6E8895D5B3DC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the proposed project of the potential recipient; </text></subclause>
<subclause id="HD2F331617F4F4444B382AD8A29DDC80B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the impact of the project described in subclause (I) on promoting digital equity in local communities; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA25C49DD5F9C4B6782B1326F4F63CD85"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the alignment of the project described in subclause (I) with— </text>
<item id="H2BEB1CE10B6C43D6A2EB6BBECF14CB6D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the overall goals of the Foundation relating to diversity on the basis of geography;</text></item> <item id="H4AAD0E1CE8A04C55A6BB19F566CBA16C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the type of need addressed by the project; and</text></item>
<item id="HD5707C6BB6E64219ADF764B40E18CF9F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>other factors specified in the strategic plan and grant guidelines of the Foundation; and</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H88F7A8E2FDD24753813704EC73AFDCEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may consult with a potential recipient regarding the ability of the potential recipient to carry out various projects that would further the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H79883A2B49BC4A0994BFBC9CA3E7DE7A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Accessing facilities and expertise</header><text>The Foundation may work with the Secretary and the Commission—</text> <subparagraph id="H4ADD17F7680D4E1DBF2FD2167D144234"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to leverage the capabilities and facilities of the Department and the Commission; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF126C85737C34FC4B332B7BEDEED6592"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to assist with resources, including by providing information on assets of the Department and the Commission that may enable the promotion of digital equity, digital inclusion, or digital literacy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8DC14C78B3BE49558BDBF66444E0C407"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Training and education</header><text>The Foundation may support programs that provide training to researchers, scientists, and other relevant personnel at the Department, the Commission, and institutions of higher education to help promote digital equity, digital inclusion, and digital literacy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8436E281801C45FCAC144ED172A44AC0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Stakeholder engagement</header><text>The Foundation shall convene, and may consult with, representatives from the Department, the Commission, institutions of higher education, the private sector, public interest stakeholders, and commercialization organizations to develop programs for the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2) and to advance the activities of the Foundation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB70F95B5DC5743C5A682F4A4FB74F572"><enum>(6)</enum><header>For-profit subsidiaries</header> <subparagraph id="HD8F144C1A9304399845DE0335E3C5938"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation may establish 1 or more for-profit subsidiaries, including an impact investment fund—</text>
<clause id="H2BF2E3CF59364BE38A5A21F4F3A75D77"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to stimulate economic development activities relating to the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2); and</text></clause> <clause id="H5BF1B4E17BB149D182347E966C9CFB37"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to attract for-profit investment partners for digital equity, digital inclusion, and digital literacy activities.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H741BFBC1810C4F6EBDCB4A74FEB30D9B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authorities of the for-profit subsidiary</header><text>A for-profit subsidiary established under subparagraph (A) may—</text> <clause id="HC8306E84AC1C4C1C95C0E8F96436242A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enter into a partnership with an economic development corporation, including a business incubator or small business investment company;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD4E5021902DC487989626DFFABFD75A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>pay for the cost of building and administering a facility, including a business incubator, to support the activities of the Foundation described in this subsection; and</text></clause> <clause id="HEFE339BEFAFE4BC49B12C06DA11E43A6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provide funding to a startup.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFB2F2B08A4704B5EB1AD5B706C07EFAC"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Supplemental programs</header><text>The Foundation may carry out supplemental programs—</text> <subparagraph id="HC6234D2B63054AA1BBC8FF3CBE2E820B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to conduct and support forums, meetings, conferences, courses, and training workshops consistent with the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE20CB0A3D7634FD1BED5D8F2C4B750E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to support and encourage the understanding and development of—</text> <clause id="HCFA2D29BBF8242DEA423FF5A10C9D680"><enum>(i)</enum><text>data collection that provides clarity with respect to inequities and community needs in order to promote digital equity, digital inclusion, and digital literacy; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H1336D85EFD47485CA07046E220A53C59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>policies that make regulation more effective and efficient by leveraging the data collection efforts described in clause (i) for the regulation of relevant technology sectors;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA27BB0174AD940DCBD11A82810175F87"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for writing, editing, printing, publishing, and selling books and other materials relating to efforts carried out by the Foundation, the Department, or the Commission; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7EBB26CF13814F759D040F7A2668DE95"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to conduct other activities to carry out and support the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H15414501933944DB92C665CF0493C498"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><text>The Foundation shall support the development of an evaluation methodology, to be used as part of any program supported by the Foundation, that shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H93023B21601D40AE9E8013DF2D9057B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consist of qualitative and quantitative metrics; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49959BAF095344C3BBC72FFCDB7109BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include periodic third party evaluation of the programs and other activities of the Foundation; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7280C30502D74A308F12CAB276D79C4D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be made publicly available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H35244B424E9C4672B9EE9660C09A5E7B"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Communications</header><text>The Foundation shall develop an expertise in communications to— </text>
<subparagraph id="H126A00EE981443359F404A6326B3DEC6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disseminate awareness of funding opportunities among community-based organizations that serve covered populations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C82E2A61EC84381AC959DA211893F51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promote the work of grant and fellowship recipients under paragraph (2), the successes of the Foundation, opportunities for partnership with the Foundation, and other activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3A23EAADD6F74CF48212DA00C5182DA2"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Tribal Broadband Connectivity Grants</header><text>The Foundation may support a grant made under the Tribal Broadband Connectivity Program if there are not adequate appropriations to support such a grant.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H84FFE229E67B4576BE841E35B8241156"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Administration</header> <paragraph id="HB52600FCEBFE425FB6467EAC1C52173B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive director</header><text>The Board shall appoint an Executive Director of the Foundation, who shall serve at the pleasure of the Board.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05A9E2912F9E4338B2A3004363C13698"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative control</header><text>No member of the Board, any officer or employee of the Foundation, any officer or employee of any program established by the Foundation, or any participant in a program established by the Foundation may exercise administrative control over any Federal employee.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3696C94EA4AC4060B8FC797169A0759C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Foundation shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a strategic plan that, incorporating the input of the community advisory committee convened under subsection (g)(1), contains—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBF3C10F6A3BD47078D3F99ECC358E08E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the initial focus areas of, and primary purposes for, each program, grant, or award opportunity that the Foundation plans to implement during the 2-year period beginning on the date on which the strategic plan is submitted;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H902B0A4F322A4A23A6A685B601483123"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the efforts that the Foundation will take to be transparent in the processes of the Foundation, including processes relating to—</text>
<clause id="HC4CB00594C3E4803B32D352743426C5F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>grant awards, including selection, review, and notification with respect to those awards; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC2DF3BFE958C4705A84AEA00AD275A72" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>communication of past, current, and future digital equity priorities;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3FF390BE249148B7A25C672232A8D366"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the financial goals and benchmarks of the Foundation for the 10-year period beginning on the date on which the report is submitted; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6E67689E84EA46278E5D8050021226CC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of the efforts undertaken by the Foundation to ensure maximum complementarity and minimum redundancy with investments made by the Secretary and the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD72AC9CE6F0B48AC9E992584B10B5826"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Recurring report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Foundation is established, and once every 2 years thereafter, the Foundation shall make publicly available, and shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Commerce and Energy of the House of Representatives, and the Secretary, a report that, for the period covered by the report—</text> <subparagraph id="H25A88C2C5FFC4E1EBFF66AB35000BD89"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes the activities of the Foundation and the progress of the Foundation in furthering the mission of the Foundation described in subsection (c)(2);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H35AEEFE561F04A7D8DFBF2F27421D809"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides a specific accounting of the source and use of all funds made available to the Foundation to carry out the activities described in subparagraph (A) to ensure transparency in the alignment of the missions of the Department and the Commission; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H09F99E80DF1A4495B61722A2E81F5DE3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes a summary of each evaluation regarding the decision to award a grant that is conducted under the requirements of subsection (e)(2)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2D819EADAF5F4C97A52812DED6E525C3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Evaluation by comptroller general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date on which the Foundation is established, and once every 5 years thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives—</text> <subparagraph id="HACABD480B5334372A204DED207E9AF0F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an evaluation of—</text>
<clause id="HBEC048F781284E5D9FF59D6E0976AEB3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the extent to which the Foundation is achieving the mission of the Foundation; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC8A76A1F1B454649BC45A19B7A8FF9F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the operation of the Foundation; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H51E2C8F1269A448C98E27F996AFBE477"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations regarding how the Foundation may be improved.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H35B88B66686F4BCDA1F61A9E899904F4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Audits</header><text>The Foundation shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H856EDB96FB9D4B03A08E7CD1FEA7C9A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide for annual audits of the condition of the Foundation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB9532F7E13D46B78A49AF9553AAF893"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the audits, and all other records, documents, and papers of the Foundation, available to the Secretary and the Comptroller General of the United States for examination or audit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H11311C74202041C6A1967A95D67CD7B6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Integrity</header>
<subparagraph id="H18BA38F6782E486696F2ABE3CECDEE64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To ensure integrity in the operations of the Foundation, the Board shall develop and enforce procedures relating to standards of conduct, financial disclosure statements, conflicts of interest (including recusal and waiver rules), audits, and any other matters determined appropriate by the Board.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H59A65A9E9E78457C81D89A8113B903C9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Financial conflicts of interest</header><text>An individual who is an officer, employee, or member of the Board may not participate in deliberations by the Foundation regarding a matter that would directly or predictably affect any financial interest of—</text>
<clause id="HD63CD1F123064BC6B7CBCC4B2582E140"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the individual;</text></clause> <clause id="H4983EAF36B654297B2AF007C2EABCC28"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a relative (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-act" parsable-cite="usc-act/Ethics in Government Act of 1978 /109">section 109</external-xref> of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App.)) of that individual; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H007131C02DF741D79915DA0398573A9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a business organization or other entity in which the individual has an interest, including an organization or other entity with which the individual is negotiating employment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BCF7729E32E40298916F810D6080C96"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Intellectual property</header><text>The Board shall adopt written standards to govern the ownership and licensing of any intellectual property rights—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9F5E0419C1CA4996A9CDF77D01855C3D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>developed by the Foundation through activities funded by a for-profit subsidiary established under subsection (e)(6); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D8F1E99A0EC45D78E6F81BC0D1EC2E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>otherwise derived from the collaborative efforts of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H319F591680BE4A4B84390685A81C90E0"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Liability</header>
<subparagraph id="H8C165CDD8BE94D0A8F347312FA32E3F0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The United States shall not be liable for any debt, default, act, or omission of—</text> <clause id="H49266045A73544C1906B47C77C33B9ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Foundation; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H1DFB3C95389040DE9C21C34A138A4D03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a Federal entity with respect to an agreement of that Federal entity with the Foundation.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57B339E1BF99438CB5427998CF2DF918"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Full faith and credit</header><text>The full faith and credit of the United States shall not extend to any obligations of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3E861B16765644AD83BC397BC8907DF1"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of faca</header><text>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Foundation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5DBE9F2485D7456CB9C1E6FC5FD646EF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Community advisory committee and report</header> <paragraph id="H9B27227DC7FB4A34B1A97B4EC1D539E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header> <subparagraph id="H90371E979FF9438594E02E0741FF24FC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later 90 days after the date on which the Foundation is established, the Board shall convene an advisory committee comprised of community members from covered populations and experts with experience providing essential products and service to covered populations.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H809569E205B34AC5BB1B38BFC9868FB4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Stakeholders represented</header><text>To the extent practicable, the Board shall ensure that members appointed to the advisory committee under subparagraph (A) represent diverse regions, sectors, and communities, including not less than 1 member who is affiliated with, or has experience working with, all of the following:</text> <clause id="HE4B6E11C585745DABF1C6157078240A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Digital inclusion practitioners.</text></clause>
<clause id="H6C6961239A004B84B3C3C386490D2CC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Rural-focused programs.</text></clause> <clause id="H3248C0B45DF642349F9C73587D536D31"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Members of Indigenous communities.</text></clause>
<clause id="HEB48952A009E494DB5B63A319374D95A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Civil rights advocates.</text></clause> <clause id="HB27DF4AF3BEF4D658419EC1EA31D39D0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Consumer advocates.</text></clause>
<clause id="H43F6199BA649416A9D7001C6888698F8"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Libraries.</text></clause> <clause id="H695822625E904B72899785922D4E199C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>School systems or education technology specialists.</text></clause>
<clause id="H0625B4B4524F4EF69D3C98A0DB12FA86"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Accessibility advocates or experts.</text></clause> <clause id="H77CDEFDB96B542AC83FA628BA4CB5E30"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Retired or older individuals.</text></clause>
<clause id="HC9DAB7D568E445E2B1965DCD9677B317"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Private sector internet service providers.</text></clause> <clause id="H623961D0C5314877A370EF659C352E24"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Other relevant groups with experience addressing the access, adoption, and affordability of broadband services.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H35C01B31930A4DECB74945073937926B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Foundation is established, and annually thereafter, the Board shall direct the community advisory committee convened under paragraph (1) to submit to the Board a written report that includes recommended changes, if any, to the Foundation and any other matter the Board considers appropriate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD1AEEE952414814B8BEA1EDCA337E8C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reimbursement for certain expenses</header><text>In accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation, members of the community advisory committee convened under paragraph (1) may be reimbursed for travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, and other necessary expenses incurred in carrying out the functions of that advisory committee.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD8E20C5C1DCE43CCA2399DB218737358"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Support services</header><text>The Secretary shall provide facilities, utilities, and support services to the Foundation if the Secretary determines that the provision of those items is advantageous to the programs of the Department.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3C16D59F8893428B876077A02336DDF7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Anti-Deficiency act</header><text>Section 1341(a)(1) of title 31, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Anti-Deficiency Act</quote>), shall not apply to any Federal officer or employee carrying out any activity of the Foundation using funds of the Foundation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDF23C17885074F2BA4C610976D4DB2E7"><enum>(j)</enum><header>No preemption of authority</header><text>This section shall not preempt any authority or responsibility of the Secretary under any other provision of law.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5F7C29EBC8AD47A1A61DFC9265CF4493"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Transfer funds</header><text>The Foundation may transfer funds to the Department, which shall be subject to all applicable Federal limitations relating to federally funded research.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H9DC9A889537F470FA5F07BEF9FDD5835"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary— </text> <paragraph id="HF89E7298460248ED99D09A726F89E461"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the Secretary for fiscal year 2023 to establish the Committee;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6523F69614BE4E89A785761D0692C3C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the Foundation for fiscal year 2024 to carry out the activities of the Foundation; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED03170563FC45AFA97E1BC3E12EF488"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to the Foundation for fiscal year 2025, and each fiscal year thereafter, for administrative and operational costs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


