<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H282D2AB6E3BE41099D02C0CE523A1F97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3696 IH: To name the Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Lynchburg, Virginia, as the “Private First Class Desmond T. Doss VA Clinic”.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3696</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To name the Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Lynchburg, Virginia, as the <quote>Private First Class Desmond T. Doss VA Clinic</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6E46511321EF42038438BCE5DD4BD450" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5DB8C7885EE84FB9AD92173A4D26908F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Name of Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic, Lynchburg, Virginia</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Lynchburg, Virginia, shall after the date of the enactment of this Act be known and designated as the <quote>Private First Class Desmond T. Doss VA Clinic</quote>. Any reference to such clinic in any law, regulation, map, document, record, or other paper of the United States shall be considered to be a reference to the Private First Class Desmond T. Doss VA Clinic.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

