<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H144FCCA351794AEAB89F315894E8CF11" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4653 IH: Protecting U.S. Business Sovereignty Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4653</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Securities and Exchange Commission to conduct a study on the detrimental impact of the Directive on Corporate Sustainability Due Diligence and the Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive on United States companies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H60B1625BE5DF47B3BF43FCC211F39424" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC9AF39E4593E4278A7F3D5718FA00931" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting U.S. Business Sovereignty Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H086CB0DB6CB14A789C9F2999EC2F4AB7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on detrimental impact of the Directive on Corporate Sustainability Due Diligence and Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive</header> <subsection id="H16216F672CA4498AB346607443C5ED8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall conduct a study to examine and evaluate—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBD76470AF7BD4EF8AECF14886931E411"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the detrimental impact and potential detrimental impact of each of the Directives on—</text> <subparagraph id="H3DF0F7BC89DD4DC6A884880B8F245293"><enum>(A)</enum><text>United States companies, consumers, and investors; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA1DD36D5D8FC4A04A8AC4771D20211B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the economy of the United States;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FEAE40B17AD4B7BB8DBCB770C1388CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which each of the Directives aligns with international conventions and declarations on human rights and environmental obligations; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HECAD5DF2B1264FA09CA493B6E5AD793F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the legal basis for the extraterritorial reach of each of the Directives.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA5C11D5DD4124A97ACD2E4A4A76A211C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Securities and Exchange Commission shall submit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Commerce, and the United States Trade Representative a report that includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="H47FA5C007BA64E4984FC037C67355467"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the study conducted under this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H789DC9959118492F93929425A94594CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations for policymakers and relevant stakeholders on potential mitigating measures, alternative approaches, or modifications to each of the Directives that would address any concerns identified in the study.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1C439747CB2845D4AC134A7A3618435D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Access to information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission may request from private entities such relevant data and information as the Securities and Exchange Commission determines necessary to carry out the study required under this section and such private entities shall provide such requested data and information to the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H34A246E036744B5981DF0D28102BAA77"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Directives defined</header><text>In this section the term <term>Directives</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEDB55218E2D24DB6940A9680CB9A7F30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the proposed directive entitled <quote>Corporate Sustainability Due Diligence</quote> adopted by the European Commission on February 23, 2022; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD51F96C2037243C88152B97F512A024D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive of the European Commission effective January 5, 2023. </text></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

