<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H268CD7A7617F45ADA955E0A283CCAD37" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3760 IH: To amend title VII of the Public Health Service Act to strengthen the mental health workforce, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3760</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title VII of the Public Health Service Act to strengthen the mental health workforce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD6C6A9D093834634A3399035F84060F9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB183D10600904D52AD5660A63C855AF0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Strengthening the mental health workforce</header> 
<subsection id="HE0D73CB85D824836AD89B66A0F6EA82A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part B of title VII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/293">42 U.S.C. 293 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6E050A22ACEB4248850F7FA0B48C26E8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H38B8926CAF2A4179B705FFA9D0CEDCAE"><enum>742.</enum><header>Strengthening the mental health workforce</header> <subsection id="H580F1E6559194AE7969E99BE83334D70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><italic></italic>The Secretary shall establish and carry out a mental health provider loan deferment and forgiveness program under which the eligible individual agrees to be employed full-time for a period of at least 5 years (beginning on the date on which the individual graduates from medical school) in providing mental and behavioral health care, including substance abuse prevention and treatment services—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEA07F8B898F6429B90C2164B3D1BDC8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as a solo practitioner—</text> <subparagraph id="H15D17C751CB446A58324CF45C648B91F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 30 percent of the patients of which are individuals receiving medical assistance under a State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (or a waiver of such plan); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6AC65503879B455F8EC3C237AC912C95"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 50 percent of the patients of which are members of a racial and ethnic minority group (as defined in section 1707); or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H670F0EE3C3574B63AC6805CBC2AFFF5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at an institution that accepts patients described in paragraph (1)(A) and at which at least 50 percent of the patients served by the institution are members of a racial and ethnic minority group (as defined in section 1707).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE2F65E2DFB884881AF75F32547B3B513"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Through the program established under this section, the Secretary shall enter into contracts with eligible individuals under which—</text> <paragraph id="H55BA08BE34F94E108B57DE8F651716DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such eligible individuals will agree to provide mental and behavioral health care services as described in subsection (a); </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78E3C02207D24DA9BDA4B6BD574CF267"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary agrees that periodic installments of the principal of an eligible loan need not be paid, but interest shall accrue and be paid, during any period during which the borrower is employed as described in subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A04C33ABE4842F9AC2FEAC4AD9C3260"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary, through the holder of the loan, will assume the obligation to repay the lesser of 100 percent or $200,000 of the total amount of principal and interest of an eligible loan, that are outstanding as of the day immediately preceding the first day of the first year of service (as described in subsection (a)), for an eligible individual, who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD6F7FEF703384273A209D26ABDBA7422"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has been employed as described in subsection (a) for 5 consecutive years; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9905F005A9584E01A5AB561E48E07D94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not in default on a loan for which the individual seeks forgiveness. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDA196E3C101D4382BFA31D26881E4FDB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H85ECAF7EA59740BB8AD186CC1E926DEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>eligible individual</quote> means an individual who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2A1411B42CCC4AD8A54E862B67EFA5CD"><enum>(A)</enum>
<clause id="H8CAA6DE8AB4E4723B37817A8DDFB4C56" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has been accepted for enrollment, or be enrolled, as a student in a minority-serving institution eligible to receive funding under section 371 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 in a course of study or program leading to a mental or behavioral health professions degree or certificate; or</text></clause> <clause id="HBFB14F05BF3B4873A6B32F2284562D9E" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is completing training hours under clinical supervision for purposes of obtaining such a degree or certificate; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3377DDEE8ADB40829E0B0EADEE151370"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has accepted employment as described in subsection (a), to commence upon graduation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1B8E1852154B4E13A26A2B4A518FB216"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>eligible loan</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7E5ED2BCABE443D4BA9154DF2756201E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any loan for education or training for mental and behavioral health care, including substance abuse prevention and treatment, employment; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4C6B08D71CC44BBAEE313AEBDCEC4F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any Federal Direct Stafford Loan, Federal Direct PLUS Loan, Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan, or Federal Direct Consolidation Loan (as such terms are used in section 455 of the Higher Education Act of 1965);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCE3F82809DB94207B6C70C1B1E378E78"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any Federal Perkins Loan under part E of title I of the Higher Education Act of 1965; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA1EB8DDB6B3A417091C4E7CAB0263DFB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other Federal loan as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

