<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7706B55EBF1B4AF9822C7E1781E1906F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5964 IH: Methane Emissions Reduction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5964</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231017">October 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reduce methane emissions from flaring and venting natural gas during oil and natural gas production activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE1520FDD3C6E49269A51099A7B578D57" style="OLC"><section id="H17B6427E060049D7A105CB13B75B0842" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Methane Emissions Reduction Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H550B697E28D447B18374A5119357843C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Methane emissions</header><subsection id="H4A0029F29D484CC9A0BA13733E9FD4B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy shall carry out a comprehensive program to reduce methane emissions from flaring and venting natural gas during oil and natural gas production activities, recognizing that States are the primary regulators of oil and natural gas production activities and emissions on State and private lands, including by—</text><paragraph id="H8B89E69449D34A1DB34600BA823EEE00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>providing technical assistance to State and public utility commissioners and officials, representatives from the energy industry, and other stakeholders from State, local, and Tribal organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0636052E8EB49DF92B10F1862FBEB4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>accelerating the development and application of technologies and practices to reduce flaring and venting of natural gas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1A5C4480F5946A5AA8622E856FD413F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintaining a database that summarizes the relevant flaring and venting regulations in each of the oil and gas producing States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4E420037C034AC6B18DC6C21B8A5389"><enum>(4)</enum><text>informing the States and other stakeholders of potential options available to economically capture and utilize natural gas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BDC472C1B9147E0AB711B2651EEBD7F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report describing—</text><paragraph id="HC7FE7BD3E936456ABD569D8A9C3180E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Federal, State, and local policies and regulations relating to natural gas flaring and venting;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4437F30E3C6048809D41FD84B052C093"><enum>(2)</enum><text>initiatives to accelerate technology solutions to reduce natural gas flaring and venting;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31B2A2F795604DB78641FECD1D9BD3F5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>barriers to the development and commercial application of technologies to capture natural gas that would otherwise be flared or vented; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H919D7AA238B34D1E846FFC1226BEA7C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations to reduce barriers described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F2583FD1A454040B82C28052F9B919D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical conference</header><text>In preparing the report under subsection (b), the Secretary of Energy shall solicit input from States and local governments and representatives of the energy industry, including by convening a technical conference and providing an opportunity for submission of written comments on a draft report.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

