<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H30FE955C007F421883BD586A50762C49" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6559 IH: All Participating in Process Reaching Informed Solutions for Everyone Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6559</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231201">December 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to ensure that certain aviation roundtables may appoint technical representatives, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6EB36CAD52134FAFA05AC40B3FEBECBE" style="OLC"><section id="H54C06715F11E48CFBA6A06527ADFF792" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>All Participating in Process Reaching Informed Solutions for Everyone Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>APPRISE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAE464CC54D734FC1A1A7F6BEEDC18736"><enum>2.</enum><header>Performance-based navigation implementation process</header><subsection id="H73A03A523C0341BB90ECC79F5F09796B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the implementation process for NextGen performance-based navigation (as described in FAA Order JO7100.41A, or any subsequent similar order), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall ensure that any covered aviation roundtable or community highly impacted by aviation noise may appoint a technical representative or consultant to participate as member of the core working group or the full working group of such process on the same terms and conditions as a representative of the industry, an airport, or a participating proponent of a procedure.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE506CF15DD6C440BAEB9CC2CB8AE4699"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered aviation roundtable defined</header><text>The term <quote>covered aviation roundtable</quote> means an aviation roundtable—</text><paragraph id="H74AEE934DF15460CAE72C2624FCB36ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that is the actual or de facto proponent of a proposed new or modified performance-based navigation flight procedure; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BB0C96810104AC6BBC9AD2AF60F7A85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for which the modified procedure path to be implemented in the process described in subsection (a) is within 5 miles of the jurisdictional area of the aviation roundtable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H122E8145932A43AC9919A5261084CA80"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the progress made toward implementing the requirements under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

