<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H54085AEDA8724E3C8AA7EE562179B352" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2973 IH: Maritime Architecture and Response to International Terrorism In the Middle East Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2973</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense to develop, in cooperation with allies and partners in the Middle East, an integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction capability, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H3AA0AE34AA234CC28027B7ED101B6DBF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEA96B66C7BA041208765A2ACB18F25DF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maritime Architecture and Response to International Terrorism In the Middle East Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MARITIME Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4921F21A0E534FDD81417E1D67EFBCBC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Middle East integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction capability</header> <subsection id="HD9E4321736D744B68F54B52C629278AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall seek to build upon the historic opportunities created by the Abraham Accords and the incorporation of Israel into the area of responsibility of the United States Central Command to develop a Middle East integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction capability for the purpose of protecting the people, infrastructure, and territory of such countries from—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5B7F07C878ED40A792E17329FA4BCE11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>manned and unmanned naval systems, undersea warfare capabilities, and anti-ship missiles of Iran and groups affiliated with Iran; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5168BB37971E4CF09C06098AB79CE4F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>violent extremist organizations, criminal networks, and piracy activities that threaten lawful commerce in the waterways within the area of responsibility of the United States Naval Forces Central Command.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCFB8AE99274344038BB1720138A6612A" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Strategy</header> 
<paragraph id="HFFED374887814D8BA9D696D5CDF018F2" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a strategy for the cooperation described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23814FE2467E4AB6A5B890516A4E88A0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters to be included</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3896CB714E554C428E3E6CA035595F41" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An assessment of the threats posed to ally or partner countries in the Middle East by—</text> <clause id="HBD17074E124E487FAF5D0AAFE62DA0FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>manned and unmanned naval systems, undersea warfare capabilities, and anti-ship missiles of Iran and groups affiliated with Iran; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4F60CFA7180F4C778CB633FCF09CE1C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>violent extremist organizations, criminal networks, and piracy activities that threaten lawful commerce in the waterways within the area of responsibility of the United States Naval Forces Central Command.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46E0F89CF3FE455A8AAF0F82A904F475"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of existing multilateral maritime partnerships currently led by the United States Naval Forces Central Command, including the Combined Maritime Forces (including its associated Task Forces 150, 151, 152, and 153), the International Maritime Security Construct, and the Navy's Task Force 59, and a discussion of the role of such partnerships in building an integrated maritime security capability.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9443FA6741494255A9DD6DBC84EAEBFA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of progress made in advancing the integration of Israel into the existing multilateral maritime partnerships described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA3687CF0CDE4189A4427FCDF9389DE7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of efforts among countries in the Middle East to coordinate intelligence, reconnaissance, and surveillance capabilities and indicators and warnings with respect to the threats described in subparagraph (A), and a description of any impediment to optimizing such efforts.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE7B251FBC3954BA78DB970F32305F86E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of the current Department of Defense systems that, in coordination with ally and partner countries in the Middle East—</text> <clause id="HEE1E7B9CF6134925B85DF12270D95A27"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide awareness of and defend against such threats; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H4978DBFA943A4FFB83A85B74AF93F350"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>address current capability gaps.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F6FFB0EFD9A48A8A57C474240EA73C5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>An explanation of the manner in which an integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction architecture would improve collective security in the Middle East.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3299386F583E4F4F92561A4F5BCEF784"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A description of existing and planned efforts to engage ally and partner countries in the Middle East in establishing such an architecture.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DF13109250A446BBCC6889347289818"><enum>(H)</enum><text>An identification of the elements of such an architecture that may be acquired and operated by ally and partner countries in the Middle East, and a list of such elements for each such ally and partner.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0668C3BD2B4E47168C5EB5A9FC529DDD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>An identification of the elements of such an architecture that may only be provided and operated by members of the United States Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA9FB7D32278E437FB8DABA084049026E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>An identification of any challenge to optimizing such an architecture in the Middle East.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3715BE254534E25AAB9ECC0E1608054"><enum>(K)</enum><text>An assessment of progress and key challenges in the implementation of the strategy required by paragraph (1) using the metrics identified in accordance with paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC01BB8DEFAB34248B3F3008D93755DFA"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Recommendations for improvements in the implementation of such strategy based on such metrics.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF10CD7CCD75542A8B859272AA502B82C"><enum>(M)</enum><text>An assessment of any capabilities or lessons from the Navy’s Task Force 59 that may be leveraged to support an integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction capability in the Middle East.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H32DD54EC6C9A45E5871F6964FDFA4D97"><enum>(N)</enum><text>Any other matter the Secretary of Defense considers relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EECBC40AEE14254B80CB9755E03E782" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall identify metrics to assess progress in the implementation of the strategy required by paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02DC8C6261D54318BE320A40C1AFFC6F" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Format</header><text>The strategy required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H68BFB634671F4484813480331E746AF6" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Feasibility study</header> 
<paragraph id="H249EBEA2475A4A059B3CF1DB05BF4DB9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall conduct a study on the feasibility and advisability of establishing a fund for an integrated maritime domain awareness and interdiction capability to protect the people, infrastructure, and territory of ally and partner countries in the Middle East from—</text> <subparagraph id="H8C72E52198A24F93A780E1C8F171DC91"><enum>(A)</enum><text>manned and unmanned naval systems, undersea warfare capabilities, and anti-ship missiles of Iran and groups affiliated with Iran; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB66170B5678C4212817ADA57DBD2566E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>violent extremist organizations, criminal networks, and piracy activities that threaten lawful commerce in the waterways of the Middle East.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC456235DCE2A4911A737CCA68AAC7466"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Element</header><text>The study required by paragraph (1) shall include an assessment of funds that could be contributed by ally and partner countries of the United States. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H3BD57A9BD14943C48F3BDFC4434BBD75"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9E2A3D8FCAAA4AB2AC78942513C0BBAE" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Protection of sensitive information</header><text>Any activity carried out under this section shall be conducted in a manner that appropriately protects sensitive information and the national security interests of the United States. </text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H2B358CE0C3544935BA7FD7D10B83D3AA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H169558FA90B4484A99FDE7FB6E7ECF2A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE6B276705E6441E98FF16CE2F8B9713" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

