<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0C730A002DF04FC2A42A5F5DAC8A6E13" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6371 IH: Provider Reimbursement Stability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6371</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for certain adjustments to the physician fee schedule under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA2F7AC948DE34682996F272851CDA124" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H21B17F0C8F624CDA88C18A57B2905305" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Provider Reimbursement Stability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAC1A80DAED1542FA93F29160C8ABAA3B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Updating the budget neutrality threshold</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B)(ii)(II) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)(ii)(II)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBEBDF744E7684F4B90137F177584E551" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Subject to</quote> and inserting the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAAF060CE93AD4091BBC34B51593C4F30"> <item id="HD20B5643078B4ACCA206B323A4E79E4C"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to</text></item><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E9339B73D094C61960DF613435B9B0A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in item (aa), as inserted by subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>$20,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>the amount specified in item (bb) for such year</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF38640C5B94147DF9C3F1A7086F85A45"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new items:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H183621E5BEC447A88CACEC9BE51B4ADD"> 
<item id="H6D44BC4ED40641AEBE51EB85C0469E88"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Amount specified</header><text>For purposes of item (aa), subject to item (cc), the amount specified in this item is—</text> <subitem id="H45E80F522C7844289BFB43D81F81C0F7"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>for years before 2025, $20,000,000;</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="H785BB0DB4EAC46849D76C0E0D5B7DC2E"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>for 2025, $53,000,000; and</text></subitem> <subitem id="H6FF570F947D44F1DA356CDAE6DFD27DA"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>for 2026 and each subsequent year, the amount specified in this item for the preceding year.</text></subitem></item> 
<item id="H6DE4932D8D6A42DF9FAAADC77A061EB0"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Indexing limitation on annual adjustments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For 2030 and every subsequent fifth year, the Secretary shall increase the amount specified in item (bb) for such year by the cumulative increase in the MEI (as defined in section 1842(i)(3)) applicable to physicians’ services over the 5-year period ending on the last day of the preceding year.</text></item><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HD0AEE152CB1C4B6CA5C21BE363809F7E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Budget neutrality corrections for overestimates and underestimates in utilization</header> <subsection id="H6A31AE259DA34978964EA2BE1232C404"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H643A407A9B1549D2A3AA4EFA2ED01EB7" style="OLC"> 
<clause id="H847A5B0D6CF745B5A82BB4939A3FB2D6"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Budget neutrality corrections for overestimates and underestimates in utilization</header> 
<subclause id="H42A3A28A9E7A474286ADA514CD01FD12"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a budget neutrality adjustment applied pursuant to clause (ii)(II) for an adjustment application year (as defined in clause (viii)(I)) beginning with 2025, with respect to an adjustment to relative value units made under clause (ii)(I), that is determined using estimated utilization (as defined in clause (viii)(III))—</text> <item id="HCC89572589044C80BFE60166559D9679"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Secretary shall, by not later than September 1 of the subsequent year—</text> 
<subitem id="HD75CF1142C794D1988D72768339E0FDC"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>compare such estimated utilization to actual utilization occurring during such adjustment application year with respect to the adjustment to the relative value units made under clause (ii)(I); and</text></subitem> <subitem id="HA5D3A82A21F948AFB63D0738D2838BCF"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>if applicable, determine the extent to which, if any, the difference between the estimated utilization and such actual utilization affected the amount of such budget neutrality adjustment applied for such adjustment application year; and</text></subitem></item> 
<item id="HFB2FCE56892943998E7D50343D58AD7C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in the case that the Secretary determines under subclause (I)(bb) that the difference between the estimated utilization and such actual utilization affected the amount of the budget neutrality adjustment applied for such adjustment application year, the Secretary shall adjust the amount of payment made under this section for services furnished during the adjustment correction period (as defined in clause (viii)(II)) with respect to such year by such amount as determined necessary by the Secretary to reconcile the difference (which may be positive or negative) between—</text> <subitem id="H91CDDE5314C34C42B85C4916BFCBA25A"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the budget neutrality adjustment that had been applied for such application adjustment year, using the estimated utilization; and</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="HBD6B2E0043EB4348B0B46E1D7FEA9C78"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the budget neutrality adjustment that would have been applied for such year if such adjustment had been calculated using such actual utilization.</text></subitem></item></subclause> <subclause id="HAC87B3F076D04B70B142E2A7D483717C"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this clause:</text> 
<item id="H1D9CEF1B35574203995624893A49A6FC"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Adjustment application year</header><text>The term <quote>adjustment application year</quote> means, with respect to an adjustment to relative value units made under clause (ii)(I) for which a budget neutrality adjustment under clause (ii)(II) is required, the year for which such adjustments are applied.</text></item> <item id="H72182FF652F541C78813D8C680D6AB59"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Adjustment correction period</header><text>The term <quote>adjustment correction period</quote> means, with respect to an adjustment application year, the second year beginning after such adjustment application year.</text></item> 
<item id="H3EFE9F75EC9B4A84A877D0C3F3EA7EBA"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Estimated utilization</header><text>The term <quote>estimated utilization</quote> means, with respect to an adjustment to relative value units made under clause (ii)(I), an estimate of utilization associated with such adjustment used for purposes of applying clause (ii)(II).</text></item></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H6ED7630DC20C454FA92C29C0A5893227"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nonapplication of budget neutrality to reconciliation adjustments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE242AEFAAD004612BA335E0A1FB23D51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (iv)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE46C4269EE9D4F2B90FC2083647F5A4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (V), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0D254F61D65F45808B4399CCD4701B6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subclause (VI), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCA5DD43266A54C72BF91F16E3E9D42B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB07D12CF141C4192B4B251C0EDFCC767" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subclause id="H3103180C79D54DCBA1239B7DDA5A9AF5"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">clause (vii)(I)(bb) for an adjustment correction period shall not be taken into account in applying clause (ii)(II) with respect to such period.</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA672432F7D3B4344A98E731356E54AB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (v), by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4EAD65FF910840CA9336E4310DB1952C" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subclause id="HE44E0FF2B0E8425BB6D248230826013C"><enum>(XII)</enum><header>Reductions attributable to an adjustment correction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For an adjustment correction period, reduced expenditures attributable to application of clause (vii)(I)(bb) with respect to such period.</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H612390044E84469C9B01D948120005DD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Timely updates to direct costs used to calculate practice expense RVUs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>), as amended by section 3, is further amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H062D2D143AE8437EB13B20A0A81EA36D" style="OLC"> 
<clause id="H526E7AACA2144209989D0FB0A747B309"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Timely updates to direct costs used to calculate practice expense relative value units</header> 
<subclause id="H86490FBDB70D433CB8BDD75175A49B13"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Simultaneous updates to direct cost inputs at least once every 5 years</header><text>The Secretary shall, not less often than every 5 years, update the prices and rates, as applicable, for each of the direct costs inputs described in subclause (II) used in the methodology for calculating the practice expense relative value units under this subsection for physicians’ services. Updates made pursuant to the previous sentence shall be made in the same year for all direct cost inputs described in such subclause.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2FE04B2B7CEC439F92180B9B9BD7F3FE"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Direct costs input categories described</header><text>For purposes of this clause, the direct costs inputs described in this subclause are clinical staff wage rates, prices of medical supplies, and prices of equipment.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H98109588F2934AEFB3E0EC98134426E7"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In making the updates under this clause, the Secretary shall consult with relevant stakeholders, including physician specialty societies.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HF9CCDB8643E24613AF28F588E3040CE3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Limitation on year-to-year conversion factor variance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>), as amended by sections 3 and 4, is further amended— by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE455941E25074E478F8FB323EF747BD5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H4D8F6FDE7BBD45058BB2BAF849BA2666"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Limitation on conversion factor variance</header> 
<subclause id="H7057458314DD400F8017B19EEAF6478D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that application of clause (ii)(II) for a year (beginning with 2025) would result in a conversion factor established under subsection (d) for such year, not taking into account any adjustment provided under such subsection, to vary by more than 2.5 percent compared to such factor so established for the preceding year (in this subclause referred to as the <quote>preceding year’s conversion factor</quote>), the Secretary shall—</text> <item id="H730D565EF34D431DA620D67B81C0CBA4"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such application would result in a decrease in such conversion factor, modify any budget neutrality adjustment applied to such conversion factor pursuant to such clause such that such conversion factor is decreased by 2.5 percent, not taking into account any adjustment provided under such subsection, compared to the preceding year’s conversion factor; and</text></item> 
<item id="HA638BA97CC6C4AF1ABC869CB04E65019"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such application would result in an increase in such conversion factor, modify any budget neutrality adjustment applied to such conversion factor pursuant to such clause such that such conversion factor is increased by 2.5 percent, not taking into account any adjustment provided under such subsection, compared to the preceding year’s conversion factor.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HC64F18C536BA40CA9E72217ECECE8ACF"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Special rule for 2025</header><text>In applying subclause (I) with respect to the conversion factor established under subsection (d) for 2025, in determining whether the application of clause (ii)(II) for such year would result in such conversion factor varying by more than 2.5 percent compared to such factor so established for 2024, the Secretary shall take into account the increase to such conversion factor so established for 2024 provided under subsection (t).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0A3E9E8AE97A46BD975CBA855598DD39"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Clarification relating to transition to multiple conversion factors</header><text>For 2026, in applying subclause (I) with respect to the qualifying APM conversion factor (as described in subsection (d)(1)(A)) and the nonqualifying APM conversion factor (as so described) established under subsection (d) for such year, each reference in such subclause to the <quote>preceding year’s conversion factor</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to <quote>the single conversion factor (as described in subsection (d)(1)(A)) so established for 2025</quote>.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

