<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2A46234320D241EC83D04C99DA221E47" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4214 IH: MEZr Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4214</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish and implement a comprehensive system for analyzing and addressing nonconformities in the aftermath of all Class A Mishaps, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1735FD918F00431EA88CA7A7556EF84C" style="OLC"><section id="HC5B7233FAE714F358F5B972011C223E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military Equipment Quality and Safety Reform Act</short-title></quote> or <quote>MEZr Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="H98883CC427B94AA2AB5F5F6E7002E188"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H03DD6563C8FE43D1805EBEA6FD29AC3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Defense lacks a comprehensive system for addressing nonconformities that may have contributed to Class A Mishaps.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H208B7D65686E4814993E6E432463F19E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This lack of a system can result in a failure to identify and address underlying issues, which can increase the risk of similar incidents occurring in the future.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0A370E3E701A433EAACDEEB4A3B3A8C5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Defense system for analysis of nonconformities contributing to Class A Mishaps</header><subsection id="H2505E295F64E4D71BA41ED32507BCB4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>System required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall establish and implement a comprehensive system for analyzing and addressing nonconformities in the aftermath of all Class A Mishaps. Such system shall include each of the following capabilities:</text><paragraph id="H707E4297A04543C9B25D6430D5C05C5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The analysis of processes, work operations, and material for nonconformities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1BED41A21D548349DC623C064CDD7CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The investigation of the causes of nonconformities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA869801AE8704C0EB8E0D7FEBB0B5765"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identification of the actions needed to correct and prevent the recurrence of nonconformities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H119BADEDF9BB4EC7A259E53584ED7D6C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The implementation and documentation of changes in methods and procedures to correct and prevent identified nonconformities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96056856699E486DB7E3075DDCECAEFC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The verification or validation of corrective and preventive actions to ensure that such actions are effective and do not adversely affect the overall system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06712851539744D19A78B7ACB0A13B48"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensuring that information related to nonconformities including corrective and preventive actions and their effectiveness is disseminated to the individuals who are directly responsible for assuring the quality of related processes, and made available for public release.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47261E7C3EAC4BF8B344C1F25AD8A7FB"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The submission to the Joint Safety Counsel established under section 184 of title 10, United States Code, of relevant information on identified nonconformities, as well as corrective and preventive actions and their effectiveness.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4DDAE549C2FC4A8F922016016B591E7B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidelines and procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall establish guidelines and procedures for compliance with the requirements of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB1C68CD5DAAC4C7AB284D3B14634DD70"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph id="H448A7EE438404F3D9E44D00CF5173CBB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Penalties for noncompliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense may establish penalties for noncompliance with the requirements of the system established under subsection (a), which may include fines, suspension or revocation of contracts, and other appropriate measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71BB3B9249A0499283AA2BE8AC55A98B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Auditing and monitoring</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish auditing and monitoring processes to ensure compliance with the requirements of the system established under subsection (a), which may include regular audits of nonconformities and corrective and preventive actions taken.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA44904F76E24E6FA657EA4B89FB0A42"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the establishment of the system under subsection (a). Such report shall include information on identified nonconformities, corrective and preventive actions taken, and the effectiveness of the system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H67D5DE3086B74055BFA08FF1411F1868"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8BF8BE3907734F6BAB794BECB48C6504"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Class A Mishap</quote> means any mishap involving aircraft, missile, spacecraft, nuclear weapon, or submarine, resulting in—</text><subparagraph id="H7940EA4477F54B36BCB6773DD706CCB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a fatality or permanent total disability; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3323AFF374F7445A938496BC11A329D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>property damage of $2,000,000 or more.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF264B9A5A2846FF8355DAF2114B2AD6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>nonconformity</quote> means any failure to fulfill a specified requirement or standard.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

