<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA73FDC7B2E4849449ECD81A4CBAEE324" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 632 IH: Ensuring Accurate and Complete Abortion Data Reporting Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 632</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230130">January 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000609">Mr. Palmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act and Public Health Service Act to improve the reporting of abortion data to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H55BF2FB1EA5D4AB1A9841201FE35360F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H06FC862D136C495F87FEF8030E82370A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Accurate and Complete Abortion Data Reporting Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE20B056F112A48B2A8B8DBE3E5E8297D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD2F94230E1CA467D9000F9444D392EFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reporting abortion data has been voluntary in the past, which has not resulted in complete data being submitted to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H375120DE14C8499984FEF9D848C32BA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>While the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention requests specific data points from each State and the District of Columbia, there is a great variety in the information collected and published by the States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85DF706D55644EACAE33DFD9E0ACFBF3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In fact, there is not a single abortion data point publicly reported for all fifty States and the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4D397E356E247E5879D69055F914B7C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Even more alarming, three States that together account for 15 percent of the United States population of women of childbearing age do not report any abortion data to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57F7111A4C2B471083D013D28D55FD21"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Accurate statistical data regarding abortion and those who survive abortion attempts is critical to public health and policy analysis.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H265E4B747A4940D3AA7D9185943E8F29"><enum>3.</enum><header>Medicaid payments for certain family planning services and supplies contingent on submission of abortion data to CDC</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1903 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H32236BE13E8A4E78802CD507D6EA7DA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(5), by inserting before <quote>an amount equal to</quote> the following: <quote>subject to subsection (cc),</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA7B7230D63D84C2897CEB96017759490"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C099CABAE3E481F84A1DDC07AC90D57" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H6401A9115F204DA8BFBF7479C7028D13"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Annual reports on abortion data</header> 
<paragraph id="H3CDD0B83E8AF4B64AF7180BE89F76B19"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), as a condition of receiving payment under subsection (a)(5) with respect to any amount expended during a year (beginning with the year following two years after the date of the enactment of this subsection) for family planning services and supplies described in section 1905(a)(4)(C) furnished to an individual described in section 1902(ii) or an individual whose medical assistance under this title is limited to such services and supplies furnished pursuant to a waiver granted under section 1115, each State shall, by not later than December 31 of the previous year, submit to the abortion surveillance system of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, with respect to the year before the previous year, at least abortion data regarding the mandatory questions described in section 317W(a)(3)(A) of the Public Health Service Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C31FC156FC9401990A02A3D2F8A2F59"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Late submission of reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a year, in the case of a State that does not submit by December 31 of the previous year the abortion data required under paragraph (1) with respect to the year before the previous year but submits such data by December 31 of the year, such State shall continue to receive payment, including retroactive payment, under subsection (a)(5) with respect to any amount expended during the year for family planning services and supplies described in section 1905(a)(4)(C) furnished to an individual described in such paragraph.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H40FADBE67DE54A8DB53D5FF5A2A74DD3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Certification of abortion data</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6ED288AD1E414C1FB3331A7FF019B6B4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each submission of abortion data under this subsection, a State shall certify to the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention that such data is accurate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD15F1397EA94139806267FB331FDC10"><enum>(B)</enum><header>False information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention determines that a State has knowingly provided false information with respect to a submission of abortion data under this subsection, such State may not receive payment under subsection (a)(5) with respect to any amount expended during the first full fiscal year following such determination for family planning services and supplies described in section 1905(a)(4)(C) furnished to an individual described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H61BDC00FE7474B75B0D6BBB635BF9C41"><enum>4.</enum><header>Collection of abortion data by CDC</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 317V of such Act the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H679D7D4F399D4461ADD0BA61AC20CC71" style="OLC"> <section id="H7F29A552545B46E8A0A6AF816D8A4B1B"><enum>317W.</enum><header>Abortion data</header> <subsection id="H88E95E27E5124922A2FDB763C51D7624"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>)—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9365D2FB4CFD4055954EC966AAAC9C2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall maintain a surveillance system to collect aggregate data in a standardized format on abortions in the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12F4B40583B44168A93BF1A8C9C12CC3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall, as part of such system, create a standard worksheet to collect data from States on abortions in the respective States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C91AE48FAE748AEA8F1C01B25E5A7C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in such worksheet—</text> <subparagraph id="HEFB0167E724F4718BFCBFAF74E0F3D21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall, at a minimum, include questions on the variables listed in subsection (b), to be treated as mandatory questions for purposes of section 1903(cc) of the Social Security Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H78902A49B5B44777814E9CCEA8B91638"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include such additional questions on abortion as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, to be treated as voluntary questions; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H93AF354ACFF146DA98940A4A45204B9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall, as part of such system, allow for cross-tabulation of the variables listed in subsection (b), including cross-tabulation of maternal age by gestational age; race and ethnicity by gestational age; type of abortion procedure by gestational age; race and ethnicity by maternal age; and race and ethnicity by marital status; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE5BDF6D38A1F43AE925E7D90A8C18699"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">periodically update the questions in the worksheet under paragraph (2) and the classification of such questions as mandatory or voluntary under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5D5BCB251A2C4B2FA53C56CBCCFB5B6D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Variables</header><text>The variables listed in this subsection are the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H8C59E9B2202B4F03AC473D6A7958C33B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Maternal age in years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE1B94D4A6A547779C0EBF6A440A2324"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Gestational age in completed weeks at the time of abortion.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE330884A781B40018402F843AAEADB36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Maternal race.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF14D78812F6F4465866B6AA8AFAC935E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Maternal ethnicity.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B3211E92E294A469FCF175D1521D0DD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Maternal race by ethnicity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE7DF756C0BD4FBDAEF6BCA7E755D4F7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The abortion method type.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57A286D04A2842A597D1FD59695B5650"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Maternal marital status.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF643AC8A0BC642C38BC15CB548F53164"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Previous pregnancies of the mother, including the number of previous live births, the number of previous induced abortions, and the number of previous spontaneous abortions.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H21B3A699EF704721975EB1D05F19E3B1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Maternal residence (State or county).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF766A7929A94CD98255411B54C84FBF"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Whether the child survived the abortion.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA8D11A013EF64C5DA7233C5181181A23"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide technical assistance to States to facilitate and improve the reporting of data to the system under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H54B4C37CB70C446AB3E3E6F899887C94"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual reporting</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H141988706F814616844738C90F1F9046"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include, for each calendar year, the data collected pursuant to this section in a report on abortion; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6CBAA75D1FC046D89ADEEF874C72D988"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publish such report not later than December 30 of the third calendar year following the calendar year covered by the report.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD67858E7554D458293E8F7DEB98F0CAB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the term <term>State</term> refers to the several States, the District of Columbia, and any territory of the United States.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

