<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA4820B53C5634701AB115C36252A6E10" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5038 IH: Housing Emergencies Lifeline Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5038</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To create a database of eviction information, establish grant programs for eviction prevention and legal aid, and limit use of housing court-related records in consumer reports, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1DAF786D397F4CAC896147AF8022360A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H91717CC80D6243FA93F1CB92371D1776" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Housing Emergencies Lifeline Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HELP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1933F0B037F243C9AB8432DE28354277"><enum>2.</enum><header>Congressional findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H82A9C99C8E774DEEA1EF7444D3C2F64E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">housing is fundamentally an issue of economic and racial justice and a critical determinant of health;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45474EFDDA3F49D88C3D9176C5F22810"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the 2008 financial crisis was a Great Depression-level event for Black Americans, wiping out decades of gains in Black homeownership, which has now fallen to its lowest rate since the passage of the Fair Housing Act in 1968;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC7501BC2BD1245208BD362CC7C020C23"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Black borrowers were 76 percent more likely to have lost their home to foreclosure than White borrowers during the foreclosure crisis;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5FC64FDB476F4A769DD209B1C0C7AC7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Black and Hispanic households continue to be about twice as likely as White households to rent their homes;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H73AC2D21F02A403FA16AF4C36A7C727E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in 2016, 58 percent of Black household heads and 54 percent of Hispanic household heads were renting their homes, compared with 28 percent of White household heads;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD32BDE6E86C245DCAD80250E86C5EBA8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>while cost burdens affect households of all races and ethnicities, Black and Brown renters are much more likely to be burdened, with 55 percent of Black renters considered to be rent burdened compared to only 43 percent of White renters;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FC89099F23A4530B8CF4D89B58CDF00"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Black households account for 12 percent of all households in the United States, but 19 percent of all renters and 26 of all renter households with extremely low incomes;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H05401CEAB2544272ADD37D3153447205"><enum>(8)</enum><text>prior to the coronavirus pandemic, it was estimated that around 3.7 million evictions are filed every year, a rate of about 7 every minute;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAC7BCE2209C24E06ABED5E2433B5BF91"><enum>(9)</enum><text>across the United States, one in 20 renters faces an eviction every year, but for Black renters, the number is one in 11;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85E3A8FD32C14CFE8AB95E12C2163F39"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the Department of Housing and Urban Development does not require the reporting or collection of eviction data, including among households in federally assisted housing, and should be required to do so;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H67A184A274A34430B6EB8D327A22B422"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the American Civil Liberties Union’s analysis of Eviction Lab data found that, on average, <quote>Black renters had evictions filed against them at nearly twice the rate of White renters</quote> and that Black women specifically were filed against for eviction at <quote>double the rate of White renters or higher in 17 of 36 [S]tates</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C1F33E06B414F6194FFAB9F4C49E9E7"><enum>(12)</enum><text>right to counsel is a matter of racial justice, equity, and ensuring equal protection under the law;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7134D66DDA2C4ECAAA422F21C9ED8B4D"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nationally, it is estimated that more than 81 percent of landlords are represented in housing court proceedings, compared to less than 3 percent of tenants in such proceedings;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H199996F00DDB41019E2CF6E8FEDACDB1"><enum>(14)</enum><text>a Massachusetts COVID–19 legal help project found that when providing full legal representation to low-income tenants, 90 percent of cases closed resulted in positive outcomes, with 70 percent of tenants remaining in their homes and 20 percent of tenants having more time to find a place to live; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2755E011A3674762B8203B53B021F348"><enum>(15)</enum><text>a California study of the Shriver Civil Counsel Program found that 91 percent of Shriver cases ended with the eviction record sealed, 81 percent with the eviction not reported to a credit agency, and 71 percent with a neutral reference provided by the landlord, tenants in such cases saved nearly $800 more in reduced rent and other fees while paying holdover damages or attorney’s fees only half as often, and 71 percent of represented clients that had been required to move had obtained a new rental unit, compared to 43 percent of unrepresented tenants.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HC2C9404F241946F1A06FC99D3FEBF21F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Database of eviction information</header> <subsection id="H5F0EF59586E1461A88E692F2E2158E8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports by housing providers</header> <paragraph id="H765E2FBDBA0042DDB8F27596FE45CFB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall require each State and local entity that receives covered housing assistance to submit to the Secretary annual reports under this section regarding evictions from assisted dwelling units of the covered housing occurring during the preceding year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F78C07DC4794EBA8F001290355730D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each report submitted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HE0F2A0000E894AED9063C6DF8691497F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each household subject to an eviction proceeding during the year which the report covers—</text> 
<clause id="HF53D5EDF21C24387BA1F1D467D40A8C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reason or reasons that the eviction proceeding was undertaken and, in the case of any eviction proceeding undertaken in whole or in part based on an arrearage in rent owed, the amount of such arrearage and the amount of the tenant's required contribution toward rent;</text></clause> <clause id="HABB3897AA51D405AB1F3BEFC3390CD01" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date on which the household was ordered to be evicted;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8353FF02F840463E8FFBFF9EA795C228"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the address of the dwelling unit from which the household was evicted;</text></clause> <clause id="H4EB02E233E794AFF9B45EEF8156FA633" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the household was represented by legal counsel in any eviction proceeding, if such information is available;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2B471F9C8423402798D801AF489F83C5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the number of days the household was given to vacate the dwelling unit, if such information is available; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3538550119BF47ADBCCFDEEAE9714BB6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>whether a writ of execution was issued in regards to the eviction; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA70CFAE6A1E44D8A91F3699B9391644B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each individual in any household subject to an eviction proceeding during the year which the report covers—</text> <clause id="H06ECFBED58274794A23E86C861B2B28C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the name of the individual;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H08A2F5830C3149EDA761959613599132" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the annual income of the individual in the fiscal year prior to the year during which the individual was evicted, if available;</text></clause> <clause id="H2DD37FDEE7FC41B087C2D016CBA3AAF7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the disability status of the individual evicted, if available;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBA678F32EF69402F893D69DA69635A6E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any available demographic information about the individual including race, ethnicity, age, and gender;</text></clause> <clause id="H35C41773A1364753BA5850BAF9122621"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any foster care history for the individual, if available;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H21CE129B98D84FE9A09609037CC001BD"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any serious physical health problems or serious mental illness of the individual, if such information is available;</text></clause> <clause id="HD4AE954F1AD148D198CEF2A229EC5B8C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any history of prior homelessness of the individual, if such information is available; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0C7CC4EB729E46A988A3445B682F68B0"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the individual has a criminal record, if such information is available.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D321EC837354DD8866A31234E3D61CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data requirements</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall develop requirements for States and local entities that receive covered housing assistance that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H61E1ABE960774B249562C19D3A4DC7DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide that the provision of the information being collected under this subsection shall be voluntary on the part of any individual or household who is or was a tenant in an assisted dwelling unit of covered housing;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H16F9AE44938F41269CFA744DB8F28C22"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide limitations on how long the information described in paragraph (2) shall be retained;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H893533DFCBFB443A8A5FE5C32401C7B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish data privacy and security requirements for the information described in paragraph (2) that include appropriate measures to ensure that the privacy of the individuals and households is protected and that the information, including any personally identifiable information, is collected and used only for the purpose of submitting reports under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23393A24440A4D60A88BB18D96646E85"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">confidentiality protections for data collected about any individuals who are survivors of intimate partner violence, sexual assault, or stalking.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDA4F58E214E74CFB94AD1DF9B5595F65" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Database</header> 
<paragraph id="H34EFF4958107433C9C83B70DBF12E0E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a database for collecting and maintaining information submitted in reports pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01F0BDE87DDB449D8EA66F76CD78D4FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent possible, such database shall be disaggregated by the smallest census tract, block group, or block possible for the data set, and by income, race, gender, disability, and all other protected classes under the Fair Housing Act. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE13EEF8732C643EA827831B44810AA55"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Privacy protections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish appropriate measures regarding information in the database to ensure that, subject to paragraph (4), the privacy of the individuals and households is protected and that any personally identifiable information is not disclosed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E194E257DE34A96BD8B3B3838E0AEE6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may make full and unredacted information available to academic institutions for the purpose of researching causes and solutions to evictions and adherence to civil rights protections.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H64C2C8391F96484CBE0E6FEA33C08EB0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Assistance for eviction related legal aid</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $10,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended, for assistance under the Emergency Solutions Grants program under subtitle B of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11371">42 U.S.C. 11371 et seq.</external-xref>), to be used only for—</text> <paragraph id="H7D78F827A6C745D691956B5AB8029EF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>providing legal counsel for tenants subject to or at risk of eviction with regard to any eviction-related legal proceeding; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1973FCFA5B914EB0973B5D0284CA48E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">costs of any court fees associated with an eviction-related legal proceeding for a tenant (excluding any attorneys fees for the attorney of the landlord of the tenant).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HE1D84267BCB84D419614682D91259C8B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Consumer reports</header> <subsection id="HAAC8464FD73B47ECBA04845E9975B064"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 605(a) of the Fair Credit Reporting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1681c">15 U.S.C. 1681c(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE70380E8C3754FE888C0699DA8E90694" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H743907AFEAE043A1B46E543AEE9EC38A"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eviction, or any information related to an eviction or a proceeding seeking eviction, of a consumer from a rental dwelling.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FC01F95FB574E9DA4ED5EADB8D49929"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Any adverse item of information related to rent or utility arrears.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF427443B8B9E41169ED859C79F9C8696"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to any consumer report (as defined in section 603 of the Fair Credit Reporting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1681a">15 U.S.C. 1681a</external-xref>)) issued on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HED7B6224987B4DF0B0459A72785AC32B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Eviction information</header> <subsection id="H4BC49BBBFCFB4ADCAD888D535BBBCC18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, issue rules that require each owner of a covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit to ensure that each tenant of such dwelling unit owned by such owner receives information, in writing—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA7D774BD7141431E9B2EBC0CC512BA9B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not less than once each year regarding—</text> <subparagraph id="H75780F3A575749E5AA9FE2F0E2B751BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rights and responsibilities of such owner with regard to eviction; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA64CAE0A1CA6446E8FF97F151F9C2A65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>local organizations and resources that can provide assistance in eviction-related matters; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1E2F1DB0B424A20AFA3EEC426BFB25D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">upon provision of any notice of eviction, stating the reason or reasons for the eviction.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H49CDCC30B2284D8B8EB5963AA49A5EB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Hotline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, establish a hotline to provide assistance with regard to eviction-related matters to tenants of covered federally assisted rental dwelling units.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC95773FB41DB4BB5B1E4D27264B4E2F7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header> <subsection id="HE23BBE6F42F04FE3BF9C118DD76B65BD"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBCCFCEDB89044589B91FFC7A24D7001D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>assistance</quote> means any grant, loan, subsidy, contract, cooperative agreement, or other form of financial assistance, but such term does not include the insurance or guarantee of a loan, mortgage, or pool of loans or mortgages.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDCA3723E4F24466F9ADD60FE416CEBA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit</quote> means a residential dwelling unit that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0EB2937104CA44E8A2064484AF5E2CF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is made available for rental; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF3C2A8659E34AEA827DCB093B5312D4"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H88A2C91030A348098D01BB4D05B9814C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for which assistance is provided, or that is part of a housing project for which assistance is provided, under any program administered by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, including—</text> 
<subclause id="H72DA5A19C2BE46AFAC40226D8D78104F" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the public housing program under the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437">42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4B8061DB0BF94F79A57053474BBAB756" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the program for rental assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8B988AEF158446A1B26E538B9DC19F84" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the HOME Investment Partnerships program under title II of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12721">42 U.S.C. 12721 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF507298893E448608BB06FD7C64385BC" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3836B8AD190B4A05BA2AE515AAB8DB84" indent="up1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the Housing Trust Fund program under section 1338 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4568">12 U.S.C. 4568</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB23135C76F724E6B93B936D216BE9C53" indent="up1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for the elderly under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HAF5CB4027D1B4AA79FC6EF3729C37F79" indent="up1"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for persons with disabilities under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3DE5F576207E488F9A738C1B6F900347" indent="up1"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>the AIDS Housing Opportunities program under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD73EC9A746EE48EDAC363E838C81C363" indent="up1"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the program for Native American housing under the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4101">25 U.S.C. 4101 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7EFBE040D9C3412285CB3B6236D2A139" indent="up1"><enum>(X)</enum><text>the program for housing assistance for Native Hawaiians under title VIII of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4221">25 U.S.C. 4221 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HB8B3F5E7FFF641EABE400397DD8B4986" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a property, or is on or in a property, that has a federally backed mortgage loan or federally backed multifamily mortgage loan, as such terms are defined in section 4024(a) of the CARES Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9058">15 U.S.C. 9058(a)</external-xref>). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7DE81D58F9644B80A630E437F00C2B73" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered housing</header><text>The term <quote>covered housing</quote> means a dwelling unit assisted with amounts made available, or a loan or mortgage made, insured, or guaranteed, under any of the following programs:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H418D69E7C8D84D07A984FD82E52E5DA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The programs for tenant- and project-based rental assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD986CC59720F4F7E8061D83A9143BE6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The program for public housing under the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437">42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8368ACFDDF84EF3981BEAD1CBB41CFB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The program for supportive housing for the elderly under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB8882804B4E4EBE9A9A4621E6438C52"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The program for supportive housing for persons with disabilities under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD822EF7183644C58E4DFFDC636DB12A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The community development block grant program under title I of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5301">42 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H895FF26F273E400890B3EFC645783AA8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The HOME Investment Partnerships program under titles I and II of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12704">42 U.S.C. 12704 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2524A3453E6E454DBC15FA982C5B949D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The program for housing opportunities for persons with AIDS under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H520A1CA36B03474BAF9F9AF003144869"><enum>(H)</enum><text> The programs for homeless assistance under title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11361">42 U.S.C. 11361 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84E9C8A382C94071B25F8C68143F4CF9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered housing assistance</header><text>The term <quote>covered housing assistance</quote> means assistance under any program specified in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E72B09F0794487E9D4BC86905724B48"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Legal counsel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>legal counsel</quote> means full representation by an attorney throughout proceedings in issue.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8AC5619A613A4868A69D49D4758F63F9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Owner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this Act, the term <quote>owner</quote> means any private person or entity, including a cooperative, an agency of the Federal Government, or a public housing agency, having the legal right to lease or sublease dwelling units.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04C4954F3B7A4FE8B0A9CF26577560DD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

