<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="HF6435A3B33D14479AC9E02300E58A1E6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5 EH: Parents Bill of Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>118th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 5</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To ensure the rights of parents are honored and protected in the Nation’s public schools. </official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H12E639DC09B840C6AED6696926382644" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3C79E5AB0E794A3CBB090E7BA6DA8015" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Parents Bill of Rights Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <title id="H487545E4D60B45DCA8AC2871D2FA5C34"><enum>I</enum><header>Amendments to the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</header> <section id="H0E3B28D0FD3B42E5A15C7057426B9707"><enum>101.</enum><header>State plan assurances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1111(g)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(g)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5E7A72A838D94F90B3F1194C63046D6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (M), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EA5B9D3F22A4BD4A509B2E926BA149E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (N), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC53D2F5A5438486F9A961E67678EF577" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HF5EA277350354A1DBF8D0E94E898CFCA" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H5C79DC5FFFE44BCBB95AC54941FAABD9" commented="no"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State will ensure that each local educational agency in the State—</text> 
<clause id="H310B76FD68AC466D8AC0F5B20AD2C32C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case in which the curriculum for an elementary or secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) grade level is freely and publicly available on the internet—</text> <subclause id="H234F6045C60E4DF1A0E132DB21EEB2B1" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>posts on a publicly accessible website of the agency, such curriculum; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HC71A6985E1394C33816C6B089BB28AF6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if such agency does not operate a website, widely disseminates to the public such curriculum; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HAB38213E9EA64A97965FB3CDF74AC392" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case in which the curriculum for an elementary or secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) grade level is not freely and publicly available on the internet—</text> 
<subclause id="H10D5F7E9F20F417F840B825321CA9108" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">posts on a publicly accessible website of the agency—</text> <item id="H3AFC3EB1C85F4FF582794AA9C99708EB" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a description of such curriculum; and</text></item> 
<item id="H9B8FF27784864934B5B396DA2A3DBA0C" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>information on how parents can review such curriculum as described in section 1112(e)(1)(A); or</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H8196A704C6F141B699C5C0EA1D732F44" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such agency does not operate a website, widely disseminates to the public the description and information described in items (aa) and (bb) of subclause (I); and </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H632E9778E64F4899AB3F5261BF9ECE31" commented="no"><enum>(P)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any revisions to the State’s challenging State academic standards (including any revisions to the levels of achievement within the State’s academic achievement standards), the State educational agency will post to the homepage of its website, and widely disseminate to the public, notice of such revisions and a copy of such revisions, except that the State educational agency shall not be required to submit such notice or such revisions to the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H4F2C332DFFD64C04A0F091745D6A4A65"><enum>102.</enum><header>Annual local educational agency report cards</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1111(h)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(h)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HC03EA6B3931546489CE8524C4819E85D" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H84EEB376D7A84833BC604082DC8CEAF0"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Budget</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each local educational agency report card shall include the budget for the school year for which such report card is being prepared (including all revenues and expenditures (including expenditures made to private entities)) for the local educational agency as a whole, and for each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by the local educational agency. In addition to the detailed budget information required under the preceding sentence, the agency shall include a separate fact sheet that summarizes such information in a clear and easily understandable format.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H0483E7CEC28448CAA8B478A7777188E2"><enum>103.</enum><header>Local educational agency plan assurances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1112(c) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6312">20 U.S.C. 6312(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H64EE4DE165984E9B976F8A7BEAE138E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC42C19797059466DAECC572A0780A437"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD0E2CB9402D4ADCAD3F1F06ED5F5D50"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block id="HFEFB1581DDF045D593599610F2D945B1" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HF99B60EC98044C98B43157AF983ABFED" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>meet the requirements described in section 1111(g)(2)(O);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H256AD1525F4444488F33366DB3EB4ADC" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">post on a publicly accessible website of the local educational agency or, if the local educational agency does not operate a website, widely disseminate to the public, the plan for carrying out the parent and family engagement described in section 1116 and all policies and procedures that result from such engagement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9357FD370A2469E9643D0050799B75F"><enum>(10)</enum><text>ensure that each elementary school served by the local educational agency notifies the parents of any student enrolled at such school when the student does not score as grade-level proficient in reading or language arts at the end of the third grade based on the reading or language arts assessments administered under section 1111(b)(2)(B)(v)(I)(aa) or another assessment administered to all third grade students by such school; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C4A9FD055074703AA2F78F21E570EF1"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by the local educational agency provides to the parents of students enrolled at such school, before a person speaks (in-person or virtually) to such students in a class, school assembly, or any other school-sponsored event, notice that includes the name of the speaker and the name of the organization or other entity being represented by the speaker.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H3E1DFF3287154297A80C20D6ABB31F88"><enum>104.</enum><header>Parents right-to-know</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1112(e) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6312">20 U.S.C. 6312(e)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1B6B512F92FD448FBF3F80AAB5901C20"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (1), (2), (3), and (4) as paragraphs (2), (3), (4), and (6), respectively;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE35AC07B4951435F8EB89AA471C6BC77"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting before paragraph (2) (as so redesignated), the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H302587AEA0C247D4A956617760EE75B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HBDEBC3A8D0444964A8EBF5EC1EEAC251"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice of rights</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency posts on a publicly accessible website of the school or, if the school does not operate a website, widely disseminates to the public, a summary notice of the right of parents to information about their children’s education as required under this Act, which shall be in an understandable format for parents and include, at minimum—</text> <subparagraph id="H1AA854FD989F49F08CDC5D5D3B42E9F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right (provided in accordance with the requirements of section 445(a)(2) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(a)(2)</external-xref>) with respect to such local educational agency) to review, and make copies of, at no cost, the curriculum of their child’s school;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H19133B2F7E104A1C86D30EC29D5158EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the right to know if the State alters the State’s challenging State academic standards;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F483CF5A2EB45FE9C96A46E17431873" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the right to meet with each teacher of their child not less than twice during each school year in accordance with paragraph (5)(A);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAF49D288CE6A44D6B75B58F98D8255A6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the right to review the budget, including all revenues and expenditures, of their child’s school;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9A397629A4264CF7BC5FE222D2BB6E80"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to—</text> 
<clause id="H3EE887B8C81B41D9B8F22E07B6AD4CB2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a list of the books and other reading materials available in the library of their child’s school; and</text></clause> <clause id="H84CDA998E4C34CFF98551D863CF5CF96"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>inspect such books or other reading materials;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA6B54D14B53C435C8C547ACA4A06BEA0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to information about all schools in which their child can enroll, including options for enrolling in or transferring to—</text> <clause id="HED7817085F2344C782BA5EDD769EB585"><enum>(i)</enum><text>other schools served by the local educational agency;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H71F1B3B9118147009D542BF0C21384F4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>charter schools; and</text></clause> <clause id="HFB6BC23C90324F209BA392ED93E37A4B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>schools served by a different local educational agency in the State;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4944687224CC41638873670150B5D2A3"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the right to address the school board of the local educational agency; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6BEF71E6F0A94249A623139E4B231C77"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the right to information about violent activity in their child’s school;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA9919C9047E4B039890D1E0C05AE75F"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to information about any plans to eliminate gifted and talented or college credit programs in the child’s school, including Advanced Placement and dual-enrollment classes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF45F3F322EF4369B674D379D60A3B18"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the right to review any professional development materials; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HADE6A022FEA44FE594A7897B2363CD1C"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to know if their child is not grade-level proficient in reading or language arts at the end of the third grade as described in subsection (c)(10); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7000AF631EB9402AA9AA0A78C8BC7FDA"><enum>(L)</enum><text>the right to know if a school employee or contractor acts to—</text> 
<clause id="HC31AC61BA2C14DCFAE789F9F123334E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">change a minor child’s gender markers, pronouns, or preferred name; or</text></clause> <clause id="H115360686103455892A090E96105F727"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allow a child to change the child’s sex-based accommodations, including locker rooms or bathrooms; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32FF6F1F557A4E828585A8B93032E83A"><enum>(M)</enum><text>the right to know if—</text> <clause id="H1693821EB40946F38355606A6FF1A451"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a school employee or contractor acts to—</text> 
<subclause id="HD3372AC3681F49B28A94390FF93B95A9"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address the cyberbullying of a student;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDB0D1D3097A44E81BA8F83DEBF4834F1"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address the bullying or hazing of a student;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H20AC14599592473DBB8DC6C19FD40733"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address a student’s mental health, suicidal ideation, or instances of self-harm;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H83D84924B24C44A5B06B5252852C5041"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address a specific threat to the safety of a student;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H000E1214A10445948B2CB7D50B3D3ACD"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address the possession or use of drugs and other controlled substances; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF45275D9039F4E72951E4C7188F390C3"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat, advise, or address an eating disorder; or</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HBDCC639550404559B57650BA48E575A0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a child brings a weapon to school; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5E76168B9BA4C22AC6406F8FCB7D213"><enum>(N)</enum><text>the right to the notice described in subsection (c)(11) before a person speaks (in-person or virtually) to their child in a class, school assembly, or any other school-sponsored event; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C27EE0CDA9042F6A8CC71FF797C09F3"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to be informed of the total number of school counselors in their child’s school; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H341697C452F04886829D99BDDDDADB8B"><enum>(P)</enum><text>the right to know if their child’s school operates, sponsors, or facilitates athletic programs or activities that permit an individual whose biological sex is male to participate in an athletic program or activity that is designated for individuals whose biological sex is female;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD930A338D0044539903F462F188F999"><enum>(Q)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to know if their child’s school allows an individual whose biological sex is male to use restrooms or changing rooms designated for individuals whose biological sex is female; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F8F5C6A207641518D0DBA0B5F945552"><enum>(R)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to timely notice of any major cyberattack against their child’s school that may have compromised student or parent information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB3BD798141674DA396436196B3C339CD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B) (as redesignated by paragraph (1))—</text> <subparagraph id="H2572A7BE7FEC432F84168342E2F6D51C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating clause (i) and clause (ii) as subclause (I) and subclause (II), respectively; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE32F58D4573A43BEB2DDD9B7D3CDF82F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(B) <header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Additional Information.—</header-in-text></quote> and inserting: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9BA07C59DE9449D091C4822688A6EC39" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HEA03AB47E4A0446AB151F6D484D66C58"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional information</header> <clause id="HD645F5211D4D4AEDA60C1A6DA1A28EB4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H67021D464231402DB324DC02B32D1768"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7A804A3BF1AA4750BF348601B6708CAB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H6BF344BACF604A8DB10DF67AA276B019" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>School library</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school—</text> <subclause id="H0EA21ED264194F339BD927B45B8753DD"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at the beginning of each school year, a list of books and other reading materials available in the library of such school; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H54A4DD1922994923B2355D4430427663"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the opportunity to inspect such books and other reading materials.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H4D15306B08564BD081419237EEBC7E54" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Violent activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school timely notification of any violent activity occurring on school grounds or at school-sponsored activities in which one or more individuals suffer injuries (including whether such agency is aware of videos or recordings of such violent activity), except that such notification shall not contain names or the grade level of any students involved in the activity.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H26278A43E2034B42967A931E8FA3C985" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Gifted and talented programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school timely notification of any plan to eliminate gifted and talented or college credit programs in such school, including Advanced Placement and dual-enrollment classes.</text></clause> <clause id="H2FE36B71319049449BD3461F7F93270C"><enum>(v)</enum><header>School counselors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school the information described in paragraph (1)(O).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H403A5DE9AC364CFC95DBC99910342842"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Enrollment options</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school the information described in paragraph (1)(F), including the enrollment and transfer options described in such paragraph.</text></clause> <clause id="HB5B87E8EB01D44F1B9726060E0DF9EED"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>School employee or contractor actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency notifies the parents of any child who is a student in such school if a school employee or contractor takes, with respect to such child, any action described in clause (i) or (ii) of paragraph (1)(L).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8709643445BE4E78BC22A35D62549E0A"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>School and Student Safety</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency notifies—</text> <subclause id="HB42BA77E49B54F0CAD06C473303B5EE9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the parents of any child who is a student in such school if a school employee or contractor takes, with respect to such child, any action described in clause (i) of paragraph (1)(M); and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7CD20A29ABB846DB9B42FEB2024BEE30"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the parents of each child who is a student in such school if any child takes the action described in clause (ii) of paragraph (1)(M).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H538056C38B1449CFA0829682746BBDC5"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Professional Development Materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school the opportunity to review professional development materials to ensure the parental right described in paragraph (1)(J).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCF5B9EA37FE44E85B8E7B3C08672F0AF"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Athletic programs or activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school the information described in paragraph (1)(O).</text></clause> <clause id="H07CD68C602FD48C3B8DA71C76817CF67"><enum>(xi)</enum><header>Accommodations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school the information described in paragraph (1)(O).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H73A7CD7D20444F8EB112EE251D6921DE"><enum>(xii)</enum><header>Cyberattacks</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall ensure that each elementary school and secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency provides the parents of each child who is a student in such school notifications described in paragraph (1)(O).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D5A495275EB475790B33BA373CD41B6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (4) (as redesignated by paragraph (1)) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HF141D71909B84F2AA5F840F65F89907B" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H4B962AF5C8B149268AD4C5FC8E4A5D00"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Transparency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving funds under this part shall provide the parents of each child who is a student in an elementary school or secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) served by such agency—</text> <subparagraph id="H224890DBB6454A35B1BD6E883A262C2C"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause id="H080BFF4FBF784FE7995A1F42B20110D5" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> the opportunity to meet in-person or virtually via videoconference with each teacher of such child not less than twice during each school year; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE956731E45194544946EF25FEFBA16AB" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a notification, at the beginning of each school year, of the opportunity for such meetings, including the option to attend such meetings virtually via videoconference; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD9504B79C5C94B6DA347DCEDEE5F9E65"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the opportunity to address the school board of such local educational agency on issues impacting the education of children in such agency and on any violations of the rights specified in paragraph (1). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H18228F1798FB413B9AAD6A5F6130E510"><enum>105.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on First amendment rights</header> 
<subsection id="H7C96C1B7C64F4A25BCCDDE6AC4E94EDA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VIII of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4E623B55BC344B45A585A6C0DE7C9515"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 8549C as section 8549D; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H56BC815173C84F1CA132F2297E929347"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 8549B the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2B7EFED68641464998CADE89F4A9FF68" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H1212CC224B254ECA904863B0E74481B6"><enum>8549C.</enum><header>Sense of congress on first amendment rights</header> <subsection id="HEA3C549C21E1405698CBB3347C770B6B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H065561B2CF334DD7ADEEC3BB934959C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The right of parents to educate their children is a pre-political natural right that the U.S. Supreme Court has recognized as <quote>beyond debate</quote> and rooted in the <quote>history and culture of Western civilization</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB30AF485E6F444A3ACAA91B059B9970E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Parents have a First Amendment right to express their opinions on decisions made by State and local education leaders.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF03F6831DA544D8903CE63A759A7A2A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>States and local educational agencies should empower parents to communicate regularly with Federal, State, and local policymakers and educators regarding the education and well-being of their children.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF00CA98BF11F47F799010BC4A14B18C9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Transparent and cooperative relationships between parents and schools have significant and long-lasting positive effects on the development of children.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE5517A28D48B46E7AFEDC43456E35D0C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Parents’ concerns over content and pedagogy deserve to be heard and fully considered by school professionals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8BEFD40BD44748AABCB1F2C16C377494"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Parent and other community input about schools that is presented in a lawful and appropriate manner should always be encouraged.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB963EF4838AB48C88724953BA14AA321"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Educators, policymakers, elected officials, Executive Branch officials and employees, and other stakeholders should never seek to use law enforcement to criminalize the lawfully expressed concerns of parents about their children’s education, but should never hesitate to contact public safety officials if there is a credible threat to the safety and security of students, parents, educators, policymakers, elected officials, executive branch officials or employees, or other stakeholders, school faculty, or staff.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1D538249A72C401F8B43BB26D9716A50" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0DAF8BB8F44C4928BBF95FA958945149"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the First Amendment guarantees parents and other stakeholders the right to assemble and express their opinions on decisions affecting their children and communities, and that educators and policymakers should welcome and encourage that engagement and consider that feedback when making decisions; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39C953995A2C415EBF97809871D2D01E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">parents have a fundamental right, protected by the U.S. Constitution, to direct the education of their children, and the strict scrutiny test used by courts to evaluate cases concerning fundamental rights is the correct standard of review for government actions that interfere with the right of parents to educate their children.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H741D5B61D4494112B9776CCC8FD98C80"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents in section 2 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8CCE24B7101D4107B8BDCADEA587DC0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the item relating to section 8549C; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4BFBC6DB95F347569DE6C837C84297D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 8549B the following: </text> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8549C. Sense of Congress on First Amendment Rights.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8549D. Technical assistance.</toc-entry></toc></paragraph> </subsection></section> <section id="HC456ABC13CFE415B94A6D72B4FFE1D6D"><enum>106.</enum><header>Definition of secondary career and technical education school</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8101 the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB21EED66ABCF4828AFD5E9F9C2DF8E52"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (45) through (52) as paragraphs (46) through (53), respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H62F2945DF4074F3792DAE75766DE5064"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (44) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7C831DC619134D06B154CAE9AFED2C1E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HE337A8BB53DD464DAEF92AEA43AEBE26"><enum>(45)</enum><header>Secondary career and technical education school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>secondary career and technical education school</quote> means a secondary school (including secondary career and technical education schools) that is an area career and technical education school described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (3) of section 3 of the <short-title>Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006</short-title> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2032">20 U.S.C. 2032(3)(A)</external-xref>; (B)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title> <title id="H32A99C0CC4D0434094E7E27E8B6B6ED7"><enum>II</enum><header>Amendments to FERPA and PPRA</header> <section id="HA783110F64E440F9812760B573DD1733"><enum>201.</enum><header>Amendments to the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</header> <subsection id="H1C982B8F93BF445B8047C9C4E02C5978" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 444(f) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>) (also known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g(f)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Secretary shall comply with the reporting requirement under section 445(e)(2)(C)(ii) with respect to the enforcement actions taken under this subsection to ensure compliance with this section.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1ED382C6939C4EC4B00117BC123675D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on educational agencies or institutions acting as an agent of a parent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>) (also known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H64DCB9D548434444973BB23E4D4E76C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H70A4B525F0314B47A5896CA6F184BC76"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Prohibition on educational agencies or institutions acting as agent of a parent for use of technology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An educational agency or institution may not act as the agent of a parent of a student in attendance at a school of such agency or at such institution for purposes of providing verifiable parental consent for the use of technology in the classroom for purposes of educating the student without providing notice and an opportunity for the parent to object to the use of such technology.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8E447F03AA2345538526D35232C9527D"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Prohibition on educational agencies or institutions acting as agent of a parent for vaccines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An educational agency or institution may not act as the agent of a parent of a student in attendance at a school of such agency or at such institution for purposes of providing verifiable parental consent for a vaccination.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HE635C7BFF8474A0ABEA7A02041E250CD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on sale of information for commercial purposes</header><text>Section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>) (also known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>), as amended by this section, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD94953793E184082A44BEB3048BDD106" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H1BE61354C6F645CB80ACF67F672F4A4D"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Prohibition on sale of information for commercial purposes</header> 
<paragraph id="H18DE7FC6FEDF46A9B8F30E82E3EC912F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), no educational agency or institution or authorized representative of such agency or institution may sell student information for commercial or financial gain.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA1A755063C14C26957D5A6601D1739F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibition described in paragraph (1) shall not apply to products sold to students by or on behalf of the educational agency or institution, such as yearbooks, prom tickets, and school pictures. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE921D35C961C498CA3B21027E36593AF" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Parental consultation</header><text>Section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>) (also known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>), as amended by this section, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9EE2AAA58ED840D79557EF7DD46BA423" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H6B6E74A0365C428D9FF99ECEF764DA4A" commented="no"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Parental consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing a privacy policy or procedure, an educational agency or institution shall engage meaningfully with parents of students in attendance at the schools served by such agency or institution.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H929EEF715C914617AD558276BDCAC9DB" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Disclosure of information</header><text>Section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>) (also known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>), as amended by this section, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HC6CE92FE80204EEAA9E7E6BD1D69A851" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H7A022B8976714D1482B1A1ABA8CCAFBB" commented="no"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Disclosure of information</header><text>An educational agency or institution or authorized representative of such agency or institution shall, upon request from a parent of a student, disclose to such parent the identity of any individual or entity with whom information is shared from the education record of the student or any response of the student to a survey.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCDDF93ADB5B44ED2B55EFDE4ACB13D08"><enum>202.</enum><header>Protection of pupil rights</header> 
<subsection id="H2DAF6A801C6B433BBE777475C023B698"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Availability for inspection by parents or guardians</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 445(a) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFB75A49484E34A8D99AD2EC2B40EDD79" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H503235C63E754CFCB07DA33B0DAB5E8A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Availability for inspection by parents or guardians</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency (as such term is defined in subsection (c)(6)(C)) that receives funds under any applicable program shall ensure the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9A87FB0F36794A1CA320037C5EC11752"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Information available</header><text>Each of the following shall be available for inspection by the parents or guardians of the children in attendance at the schools served by such agency, and the availability of each of the following for inspection shall not be conditioned on any requirement that such parents or guardians sign a nondisclosure agreement:</text> <subparagraph id="H9B50CE68D6E143F3B4BA7F7AA2AC7435"><enum>(A)</enum><text>All instructional materials, including teacher’s manuals, films, tapes, or other supplementary material which will be used in such school or in connection with any survey, analysis, or evaluation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EEB9CDF61AB4D0D9EF497C7733F4730"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any books or other reading materials made available to students in such school or through the school library of such school.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C229AA1961C4ADD865025008408B24A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any professional development materials.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1431E507EAC64145A839493295C4CA38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comment periods for parents</header> 
<subparagraph id="H228CEB3AFA9B448C92D623DAA19A98C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The agency shall provide comment periods during which parents or guardians of the children in attendance at the schools served by the agency may inspect and provide feedback on any of the materials referred to in paragraph (1) that—</text> <clause id="H146D84A31C034F9CA21D7CC7C440C3CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are expected to be used to teach such children during the three weeks following the comment period; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H23BF408561114E48B5AA92C33AEFD565"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">were used to teach such children during preceding portions of the school year.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2115824FCC6141C29F39931D28E6CBE5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Frequency and duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The comment periods described in subparagraph (A) shall be held not less frequently than once every three weeks during the school year and each comment period shall be not less than three school days in duration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H05DA3F772D8341A1848C40760191DF1C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Single issue notification</header><text>Section 445(b) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HDA5F949AB91E4AF9BBD9E1B51CEDACD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>prior consent of the student</quote> and inserting <quote>prior written consent of the student</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H393F07BF186443168BD28F7ECF78E801"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, which is provided specifically for such survey, analysis, or evaluation</quote> before the period at the end.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1EEF206C916349B994DB42B12E4851CA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development and adoption of local policies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 445(c) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEDEB14FBFC8046CD88725E21DC2E1588"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">physical</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">medical</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA61D4A3A72F14DF383FD97D17B9D3F2B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE2B7D78877F64D07BEDC5CE13CE45E76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>in consultation with parents</quote> and inserting <quote>in consultation with parents in accordance with paragraph (2)(A)</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9B3E9EAB05A14D0FB7E8E63A2C560815"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by amending clause (i) to read as follows: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H35D6BF209DF34253BECAEDD93218D25F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H2645437F7EFD4D90A6A239A502AD2ABC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The right of a parent of a student to inspect, upon the request of the parent, any instructional material used as part of the educational curriculum for the student, and any books or other reading materials made available to the student in a school served by the agency or through the school library; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE77D8AFC8E0F46AC8D5AC0DF29916229"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (D) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H57329A81B8B14FE1BEB71AC9EBF242EF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H3333807E2D8B487B99D84C2856FBFF05"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The administration of medical examinations or screenings that the school or agency may administer to a student, including—</text> <clause id="H0B332CB77BE0433391FB3F831A525AB9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prior notice to parents of such a medical examination or screening, and receipt of consent from parents before administering such an examination or screening; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H89660E02C6EF42F19E462964A4A34B7F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the event of an emergency that requires a medical examination or screening without time for parental notification and consent, the procedure for promptly notifying parents of such examination or screening subsequent to such examination or screening.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC09E3007189F410CBC13A986BB2DFA2D" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (E) to read as follows: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4E911536F43949DDBCA1534D47D0E6EF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HC702451A65024F718248B4DE680200CB" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibition on the collection, disclosure, or use of personal information collected from students for the purpose of marketing or for selling that information (or otherwise providing that information to others for that purpose), other than for a legitimate educational purpose to improve the education of students as described in paragraph (4), and the arrangements to protect student privacy that are provided by the agency in the event of such collection, disclosure, or use for such a legitimate educational purpose.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H88B67BD0856848C2BD802A7C296D845A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Parental notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of section 445(c) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFA9358C72C3D40A1A9396DA29EF5EBB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">consultation and</header-in-text></quote> before <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">notification</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H411CE2BC3540434380C90081CE5FEB13"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A) through (C) as subparagraphs (B) through (D), respectively;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBC2AEE8E3FBF49639700D0E40D6B9C0B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) (as so redesignated)—</text> <subparagraph id="H09ECC9F8268F4BDD8013E12FCED33ACC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC1A3EAE374324BBEA46C6AE46894AC18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFA3E386CA6AB4BDCB4752AF5848D0FB7" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H5E395A825E06499BB0579E6D32DC89F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of an activity described in clause (i) or (iii) of subparagraph (D), offer an opportunity and clear instructions for the parent (or in the case of a student who is an adult or emancipated minor, the student) to opt the student out of participation in such activity;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H10D383EEAC4A4DC58F1EF227E8B04B8C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H36C001FDC7F641D8A3F32487BB5D660D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H8B1ACB8ECFF547ACA0ADCC0BE4C8A8D9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an activity described in subparagraph (D)(i), a description of how such activity is for a legitimate educational purpose to improve the education of students as described in paragraph (4); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBBCA28FF1C8446A0A936F7F32C6C0377" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>not require a student to submit to a survey described in subparagraph (D)(ii) without the prior written consent of the student (if the student is an adult or emancipated minor), or in the case of an unemancipated minor, without the prior written consent of the parent, which is provided specifically for such survey.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE24E30656B954DFF91B3CA9D5A2D029F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting before subparagraph (B) (as so amended and redesignated), the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H89EC9E665A254E71B267A95B4B1DC5C6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H8FCB5D5BC7B34B0698DAA71B10327B1A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Parental consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The parental consultation required for the purpose of developing and adopting policies under paragraphs (1) and (3) by a local educational agency shall ensure that such policy is developed with meaningful engagement by parents of students enrolled in schools served by that agency. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B892C6D149B43B1AD59ECE1B8D2ADF4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D) (as redesignated by paragraph (2))—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H846233E6F62C4BD5A7C0D7A6ADDB709A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending clause (i) to read as follows: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H36BBAF0B990A4ABB82465FDD5E57E03A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H59C6A974DCE3493F9AC77C182ADF6A0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Activities involving the collection, disclosure, or use of personal information collected from students for a legitimate educational purpose to improve the education of students as described in paragraph (4).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6CEB1D164BC04142BB70C3B42485B81B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>invasive physical</quote> and inserting <quote>medical</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF4B01395AEDB4071AD69971C04899C08"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Updates to existing policies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of section 445(c) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(c)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2C18279C08474493AD72D502F12F1C43" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HB3B87B62AFB048E98D9095F1CC76C6AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Updates to existing policies</header> 
<subparagraph id="H660D6F76EC014C31BC79A924C45E3443"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the Parents Bill of Rights Act, a local educational agency that receives funds under any applicable program shall—</text> <clause id="H1A4F351B7B3D4A9DB324603562BA49C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>review policies covering the requirements of paragraph (1) as in effect on the day before such date of enactment; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H76A500E353EF4AADA493C289D4AF7073"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop and update such policies to reflect the changes made to paragraph (1) by the amendments made by the Parents Bill of Rights Act.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB168AE3B4074F9FBE382A55DC0660A1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation and notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing and updating the policies under subparagraph (A), the agency shall comply with the consultation and notification requirements under paragraph (2). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5D3A119A91C64F4FB2707EC2733C5E1D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (4)(A) of section 445(c) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(c)</external-xref>) is amended by amending the matter preceding clause (i) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBB668A2AE6A64FC0AF9459D61A47241C" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H152694FE70E8463FA54DDF4332ADE39C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Educational products or services</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)(E), the collection, disclosure, or use of personal information collected from students for a legitimate educational purpose to improve the education of students means the exclusive purpose of developing, evaluating, or providing educational products or services for, or to, students or schools, such as the following: </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5388386E3EC2437A8B5DA4284AC854BC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (6) of section 445(c) of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HE1BEC325FEC245FC969615072F36F824" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (B) to read as follows: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H55ECDF0588DF4B64865F784C59DD6800" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H4E2A7EE1FFCE49C79350009D1CFFAEB6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Medical examination or screening</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘medical examination or screening’ means any medical examination or screening that involves the exposure of private body parts, or any act during such examination or screening that includes incision, insertion, or injection into the body, or a mental health or substance use disorder screening, except that such term does not include a hearing, vision, or scoliosis screening, or an observational screening carried out to comply with child find obligations under the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1400">20 U.S.C. 1400 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A61D8F8170E427A808D6B73B1EE293C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (E)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1ACE313213874835957413ECF4709ECE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>or</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA21E5417C80A4E4CBCF31EC3816F6E73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6CB3106ED82048FF876F13775213FB0A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3587A12F01FC49FCB9F4DB2C8452FFEC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H22EF1DF1847F434E89046CDA980E05F2"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an email address.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3AA8BB0D2CA64132B2A4CBDD2986624E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Enforcement and reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 445 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232h">20 U.S.C. 1232h</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5EDD8BACFA5744378A83D76BAD80B912" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H5EC59F77F8064AB6A4DE862700E57F64"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement and reporting</header> <paragraph id="H47C4DC523DBF417998757079DCC90CAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>The Secretary shall take such action as the Secretary determines appropriate to enforce this section, except that action to terminate assistance provided under an applicable program shall be taken only if the Secretary determines that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBBDFB86F7C84494EB57D8E8E1E4662FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>there has been a failure to comply with such section; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42EE1A4140A3432486BA92FED0E64C9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>compliance with such section cannot be secured by voluntary means.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E11688EBB74466BBDF833DAB27A02A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting</header> 
<subparagraph id="H98E7263497A249D9B1876A039C9C6DB0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Local educational agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On an annual basis, each local educational agency (as such term is defined in subsection (c)(6)(C)) that receives funds under any applicable program shall—</text> <clause id="H486E6CE9A15A4D8DBC31C37BE369AA91"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">without identifying any personal information of a student or students, report to the State educational agency any enforcement actions or investigations carried out for the preceding school year to ensure compliance with this section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4455D00F55AE495E955F01D4F3A01534"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publish such information on its website or through other public means used for parental notification if the agency does not have a website. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB512A78AE96146E281F66E8B2F954C26"><enum>(B)</enum><header>States</header><text>On an annual basis, each State educational agency shall provide to the Secretary a report, with respect to the preceding school year, that includes all actions local educational agencies have reported under subparagraph (A), and a description of the enforcement actions the State educational agency took to ensure parents’ rights were protected. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7AB6EC1221B044D2BFCD7082EE77CE4B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the Parents Bill of Rights Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate—</text> <clause id="H0CE50DCBE1DC40BD965E11F84B658558"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reports received under subparagraph (B); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF8B5A45B6343497FB69B27830AD089B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the enforcement actions taken by the Secretary under this subsection and section 444(f) to ensure full compliance with this section and section 444, respectively.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></title> <title id="H156A0F94518F44D08712DC6E6C04F56B"><enum>III</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal involvement in curriculum</header> <section id="HC6014EFFAF5D42F9A3226758536E5939"><enum>301.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to authorize any department, agency, officer, or employee of the United States to exercise any direction, supervision, or control over the curriculum, program of instruction, administration, or personnel of any educational institution, school, or school system.</text></section></title>
<title id="HD45796B347C1470F84EDA3D45D9A9CD2"><enum>IV</enum><header>Gender markers, pronouns, and preferred names on school forms</header> 
<section id="HC6D0E3DAFDD245EEBEA3140FDD5A6EF6"><enum>401.</enum><header>Requirement related to gender markers, pronouns, and preferred names on school forms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As a condition of receiving Federal funds from the Department of Education, any elementary school (as such term is defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) or school that consists of only middle grades (as such term is defined in such section), that receives such Federal funds shall be required to obtain parental consent before—</text> <paragraph id="H1D9922469E824DD4BCB49BC21B488B95"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">changing a minor child's gender markers, pronouns, or preferred name on any school form; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89ED10C9A27542C18375862BB7DD7806"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allowing a child to change the child's sex-based accommodations, including locker rooms or bathrooms.</text></paragraph></section></title> <title id="HB8310E43BA9540EEA86BF165642CBF04"><enum>V</enum><header>Access to School Broadband</header> <section id="HBC45C0B22D2443629401178183E117AF"><enum>501.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that all public elementary and public secondary school (including public secondary career and technical education school) students should have access to broadband.</text></section></title>
<title id="HC5C08C2D6BFC48E3894FBCA04CDC6EA2"><enum>VI</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header> 
<section id="HDBB05E71F65442249EB31946B93AF8EB"><enum>601.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that all public elementary school and secondary school (including public secondary career and technical education school) students should have opportunities to learn the history of the Holocaust and anti-Semitism. </text></section></title> <title id="H59329094E6CC41498DF91B06FB6BA5C5"><enum>VII</enum><header>GAO Report</header> <section id="H141C1B75B77C46D3BEE8610E97BB7DDF"><enum>701.</enum><header>GAO report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report that evaluates and analyzes the impact of this Act, and the amendments made by this Act, on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9E06E348E2B3488E99A00D631F029F3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>protecting parents’ rights in the education of their children; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD71FB9D60CE24A2A9BA1281C5FB50D8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>costs to State educational agencies, local educational agencies, elementary schools, and secondary schools (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)). </text></paragraph></section></title>
<title id="H8169087F171945A7A494A3EC0C8DA40A"><enum>VIII</enum><header>Rule of Construction on Student Access to Books and Other Reading Materials</header> 
<section id="H3FCD5A436E344A6B80092C7CF5BD9849"><enum>801.</enum><header>Rule of construction on student access to books and other reading materials</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, shall be construed as authorizing or granting parents the right or ability to deny any student who is not their child from accessing any books or other reading materials that are otherwise available in the library of their child’s school. </text></section></title> <title id="H90193683A75E4E7BBD9F969A837BDCC9"><enum>IX</enum><header>Inapplicability to Non-Public Schools</header> <section id="HA8A474FE59C5466EBCAF5F1DCD40BCAC"><enum>901.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to impose any requirements on non-public elementary or secondary schools.</text></section> 
<section id="HE8FE4DEE1E22480E815603306E89193F"><enum>902.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that local educational agencies do not have the authority to exercise any direction, supervision, or control over the curriculum or program of instruction of non-public elementary or secondary schools.</text></section></title> </legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230324" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives March 24, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> <endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> </bill> 

