<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H89C6845280C04116BD625557C6CFC4C2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6084 IH: Expediting Disaster Recovery Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6084</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act to ensure that unmet needs after a major disaster are met.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H366CD41C212F4D50B200B291E460E644" style="OLC"><section id="H6FDE3B713C7A497EBC9C5407B041116A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expediting Disaster Recovery Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE73620F10A804C8F99903A6B8A8879C7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unmet needs assistance</header><subsection id="H4F10A650C05F4D04AA9289697E8659C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title IV of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H434597B57B8C4C4B9414054C7CBD3516" style="OLC"><section id="HF3CDDB82ACB6428FA576E23463B9C4E7"><enum>431.</enum><header>Unmet needs assistance</header><subsection id="HF6A5F4EB9FD749509DB9A89C0E538705"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After the declaration of a major disaster under section 401, the President may direct the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency to provide to a State assistance necessary for meeting unmet needs as a result of such disaster.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC1A4046DBB524947A93DA31B566CD11C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph id="H6698966AF36D4A1F942BD722ED57DD3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount of funding</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the President declares a major disaster under section 401, the President, acting through the Administrator, may allocate an amount that equals up to 10 percent of the estimated aggregate amount of the grants to be made pursuant to sections 406 and 408 for the major disaster in order to provide technical and financial assistance under this section and such amounts shall be considered to be related to activities carried out with assistance provided under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1953DCBA12524D89A066EB9D281BD2EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Estimated aggregate amount</header><text>Not later than 180 days after each major disaster declared pursuant to this Act, the estimated aggregate amount of grants for purposes of paragraph (1) shall be determined by the President and such estimated amount need not be reduced, increased, or changed due to variations in estimates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H761333AC8EB044AEAC1555DB2C3FEC37"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No reduction in amounts</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to reduce the amounts otherwise made available for sections 403, 404, 406, 407, 408, 410, 416, and 428 under this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D867498345A43FCBDB0F35B9F247354"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unmet needs</header><text>Financial assistance provided under this section may be used to provide assistance, in addition to other amounts made available under this Act, for the following unmet needs:</text><paragraph id="HC65ECEC385AA43D5814EC034898A1B0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Disaster-related home repair and rebuilding assistance to families for permanent housing purposes, including in conjunction with eligible expenditures under section 408.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCCED4D16D8C42A586EDE394BD124EDE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Disaster-related unmet needs of families who are unable to obtain adequate assistance from other sources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40155281908C427FA397883317DD78C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Other disaster-related services that alleviate human suffering and promote the well-being of disaster victims.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB9236A4C57D4F02BA8A3C74614A971A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Economic and business activities (including food and agriculture) after a disaster to implement post-disaster economic recovery measures, including planning and technical assistance for long-term economic recovery plans, infrastructure improvements, business or infrastructure financing, market or industry research, and other activities authorized under a comprehensive economic development strategy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HED706FAA301D4E33B2B4E574F284B4C2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Accounting and fiscal controls</header><paragraph id="H7DA85B91DC3E4F21B2D8C75988A02920"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after receipt of funds and every 6 months thereafter until all such funds are expended, each State receiving such funds shall submit to the Administrator a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HA934EC41433C40E094A1F1F2936CE380"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the criteria established for determining how the funds are spent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H430960FBC8594AF596CDA1D86FA4FAA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the allocation of such funds; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6ED11DC58FB41A380695D9AD1A77413"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the process for public notice and comment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02F87BCDDDB9439EA12848D47D735A1E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance</header><text>Section 312(b) shall apply to this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD20F21BDE9F43988957CBB01186157D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>A State that receives funds under this section may expend not more than 5 percent of the amount of such funds for the administrative costs of providing financial assistance to individuals and households in the State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H5D69C4DD9B8A43B5B32963E962EF4B56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall apply to funds appropriated on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7ABA96532D0743A6ACAB9CDFCD7B62D0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Further considerations for disaster declarations</header><subsection id="HA23510B9EEA64BBA81470390F9CC83DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making recommendations to the President regarding the declaration of a major disaster or emergency pursuant to section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) or the proposed non-Federal share of the cost of carrying out activities with assistance provided under such Act, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall give greater weight and consideration to severe local impact resulting from such disaster or emergency and, in the 5-year period preceding such disaster or emergency, whether multiple other disasters or emergencies have occurred in the affected area.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA9788A0084834AB7A25DE92BD74B612C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Revisions to guidance, policies, and regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall take such actions as are necessary to revise any policies, guidance, or regulations of the Agency to implement subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H62C1771B93324A66BBBABDD5521B7ACB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report on the implementation of this section and shall include in such report a description of—</text><paragraph id="H548341596B6F443983E3CADFE4DD3A3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>changes made to guidance, policies, or regulations pursuant to subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D276A96B28C4A06B9C1E23ADAB1901F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of major disasters and emergencies that have been declared pursuant to section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act based on the criteria described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2C2BBA918BA94A48BAB28455568E0562"><enum>4.</enum><header>Repair and rebuilding</header><subsection id="HBF7585302B684DE99A73D25EF0B2D503"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408(c) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5174">42 U.S.C. 5174</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HDB770B9DEE44427580133B1B3E6934E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="HAD209611C6CB4069832FF9C5A4F3139B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(i) by striking <quote>to a safe and sanitary living or functioning condition</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD427CF5383F64C92949837B9A9E92F9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause id="HFB06B0752E4C49CA96AD84F2EFE82B1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A recipient of</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4776F9DF813B4ADD980FB164B215961E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H36C0EF6D8BE84518B7CD99B7558CE211"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Evidence of other means of assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="HF63125ECBD134367B7604CC05A66BBF3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H4B4C80B7B6E043389B2BFE02720E5402" style="OLC"><clause id="H2F6A1CF46ADB475089B9B23E272387E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Coordination with other assistance</header><text>Assistance allowed under this paragraph may be used in coordination with other sources for the repair and rebuilding of an owner-occupied residence.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H736479C0063C4595843918DDBD2C9489"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4) by striking <quote>in cases in which</quote> and all that follows through the end of the paragraph and inserting <quote>if the President considers it a cost effective alternative to other housing solutions, including the costs associated with temporary housing provided under this section, and long-term rebuilding costs associated with section 431.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDFD6DD4E25B14343BD71CBB2C3B72EE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall apply to funds appropriated on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD21F9FB466F64C42AE2ED47F8A62A5CD"><enum>5.</enum><header>FEMA Emergency Home Repair Program</header><subsection id="H6ACDE30FC0644BA98C8AE952EB816A25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 403(a) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170b">42 U.S.C. 5170b(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H6C4BBDBA78E9462AB481C5D9BD8C68E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><subparagraph id="H67128CE19B974B9589011E0EE644422A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I) by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FF41E24A944429984581A08BBE0B1A2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J) by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFF00783B9F84236B8DA8BDCE2B870AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6542FA0279AD4F52B61FB122EC671311" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H82C0C53300744DA59DC37FBCAE5C0435"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">minor repairs up to habitability of owner-occupied homes damaged by the disaster in order for survivors to safely shelter in place.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB2BF789A6C2432CAAB9520D17B2764A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H847F879C98AE4A139A170A490D8795DA" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HB32CE401E52542DF94CC0A863EE5F485"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Duplication of benefit limitations</header><text>Notwithstanding section 312, any minor repairs up to habitability of owner-occupied homes may not be considered a duplication of any owner benefits. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56F7F9E8F4A94E9EA87A49C06651DDEB" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Sheltering and housing options</header><text>Not later than 15 days after a declaration of a major disaster, the Federal coordinating officer shall provide all sheltering and housing options available under this section to a State Governor, or the designated State coordinating officer. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E4CD5DB4AC74A55828CA328802C7E8F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>minor repairs up to habitability</quote> means the minimum standards for permanent housing described in section 576.403(c) of title 24, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAEBB926547294E96B82362A1F6590700"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall issue final regulations to implement the amendments made by this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H064D6C3DDC8D45B0839CCEC58EF1626E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Appeals of individuals and households program benefits</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator shall revise section 206.115 of title 44, Code of Federal Regulations, to require the Federal Emergency Management Agency to provide to any applicant who appeals a determination of eligibility of assistance—</text><paragraph id="H2A6DD3D9095B4353B9F7E8C73D30875E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any documentation used to make such determination, including any inspection documents that exist;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H610FE6EA607E4190BF437038A6681674"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of—</text><subparagraph id="HFF3CD1CF2F35408DA85AF2BB337A625F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the reasons for such determination; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB26BA7A18A9D471A9666EA460EB0BBA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommended steps that could be taken to remedy a determination of ineligibility, including, as applicable, a list of additional documentation that the applicant may provide; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7030127AEA714DBC8EE3319DAA8E9E73"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any inspection documents that exist not later than 10 days after the completion of the inspection.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H79015B97B6764B67A4153DE00E04ACEE" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Period of assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator shall revise section 206.115 of title 44, Code of Federal Regulations, to extend the period of assistance for Federal assistance to individuals and households to 24 months after the date of a major disaster declaration pursuant to section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="HFE8DC1F618054D9DA0052E195A3F5174" commented="no"><enum>8.</enum><header>Report to Congress on major disaster declarations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report containing the following information with respect to each major disaster declared pursuant to section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) during the 5-year period preceding such date of enactment:</text><paragraph id="H93C333972FE3415497F37998C2FC62D5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The process used by the Federal Emergency Management Agency to determine individual household need.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E46F2F72C2A43B9802CB23E172FDBC1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An itemization of the most common reasons for denial of individual and household assistance pursuant to section 408 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5174">42 U.S.C. 5174</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED5E7EA09F1041D095A312809639A1ED" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The rate of appeals of denial of such assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB19D24785E74AC1B09BDF1AD7C32799" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The amount of time the Agency takes to issue a decision regarding eligibility for individual assistance, disaggregated by each such major disaster.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EC3668820BF421B83A1D3F9B94B0661" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Information on the use of Disaster Legal Services and the number of applicants who were eligible for such services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0586E5BD616D4D249DF7646F6AA3E784" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The total number of Disaster Legal Services volunteers as of such date of enactment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F0753ACC38D4361A0E789116BA79947" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The number of such volunteers who were activated for each such major disaster.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91DEED99D30D4DB5B226B293D42C98FF" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of time taken after the declaration of each such major disaster to set up disaster recovery centers that provide access to individual assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5A8B35FC8B449C5B64B902F7DE4F29F" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The number of disaster recovery centers opened for each such major disaster.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2B58D9235014C3AA700D221B123CE5C" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The process used for selecting the location of such disaster recovery centers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB05C0941EA2D4ABF8FE06401A2D5139A" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The average amount of time disaster recovery centers remained open.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H440B273E23104C35AC0DBACF21AAC94E" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The average amount of time individual survivors spend at such centers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10DE97BD4B2041EE83EEA4852D8B5DA8" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of outreach efforts in low-income, rural, and underserved communities regarding the availability of assistance provided by the Federal Emergency Management Agency under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H554EE9881FFC4D939167953DA59A68FE" commented="no"><enum>9.</enum><header>Review by Comptroller General</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><paragraph id="H55441C6EE89C44259D8A79769BCF070C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a review of the fiscal controls of States that receive assistance under section 431 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act, as added by section 2; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA813D8297E8141868D16000131060834" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make recommendations regarding the program established under such section to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

