<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F934197D3154D338EB3AF524B86ED36" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 834 IH: Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 834</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to support rural residency training funding that is equitable for all States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H26436E783296443DBE7F9E34FC75EEC6" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6DA9A42C5DCE484DA6ACCB02DFADEB58"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFEFF743F31694B50B796EAE507DAD6D8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Elective rural sustainability per resident payment for residents training in rural training locations</header> <subsection id="HC2EE1583B7AF42D58F3099978FCBBFE1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1886 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8FF24428C8B490B8B12C25F3A799BAB">
<subsection id="H71D7C487CE4D43B8BEA74F43F5165845"><enum>(u)</enum><header>Elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount for residents training in rural training locations</header>
<paragraph id="H69A6BFE8D74F45E0A9BD51C9CFF105CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination of elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount</header>
<subparagraph id="H69FB82962C1347C68EC1BC738830FF91"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount determined under this subsection for an applicable hospital (as defined in paragraph (7)(A)) that makes an election under paragraph (2), with respect to each full-time-equivalent resident in an approved medical residency training program that receives training in a rural training location (as defined in paragraph (7)(C)), is an amount equal to the difference between—</text> <clause id="H6F8E3E44C2F94680AC886B5C902752BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total elective rural sustainability amount determined under subparagraph (B) (or, in the case of an applicable hospital not located in a rural area, the total elective rural sustainability amount or urban total elective rural sustainability amount, as applicable, determined under such subparagraph); and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="HD56C2CFC92ED4040A4743D148C72C281"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount (if any) the applicable hospital otherwise receives for direct graduate medical education costs under subsection (h) or section 1814(l), as applicable, with respect to each such resident.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52C52EDE4B1A482F8339486A4328FE0B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Total elective rural sustainability amount</header> <clause id="H5C1AD1E0F6604F22975DA65EBBE588D7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Establishment for initial cost reporting periods</header> <subclause id="H74FFED7DA9A747E78BCF5A10CFBAEBAF"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subclause (II), for cost reporting periods beginning during the first year beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall establish a total elective rural sustainability amount for time spent by each full-time-equivalent resident in an approved medical residency training program that receives training in a rural training location. Such amount shall be the amount that the Secretary determines is equal to the median national direct GME training costs per full-time-equivalent resident for 2015 described in table 9 on page 33 of the March 2018 GAO report on Physician Workforce (GAO–18–240), updated for each subsequent year through the first year beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this subsection, by the annual percentage increase in the consumer price index for all urban consumers (all items; United States city average). </text></subclause>
<subclause id="HEFCD4A616F7D440E9DF06A45722225F8"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Application to urban hospitals</header><text>For cost reporting periods beginning during the first year beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this subsection, in the case of an applicable hospital that is not located in a rural area—</text> <item commented="no" id="H7BFC909328A14B86BB874C1EA9F920E5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>with respect to such residents that receive training in a rural track or an integrated rural track, the total elective rural sustainability amount per resident shall be equal to the amount established under subclause (I); and</text></item>
<item id="H90555E98FE614925B9C8F01E3E4E6856"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>with respect to such residents that receive training in a rural training location and who are not participating in a rural track or an integrated rural track, the total elective rural sustainability amount per resident shall be equal to 50 percent of the amount established under subclause (I) (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>urban total elective rural sustainability amount</quote>).</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H6F14573AC8D14B269CA96E9FE371D40E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Updating for subsequent cost reporting periods</header><text>For each subsequent cost reporting period, the total elective rural sustainability amount under clause (i)(I) and clause (i)(II)(aa) and the urban total elective rural sustainability amount under clause (i)(II)(bb), respectively, are equal to such amounts determined under such clause for the previous cost reporting period updated, through the midpoint of the period, by projecting the estimated percentage change in the consumer price index for all urban consumers (all items; United States city average) during the 12-month period ending at that midpoint, with appropriate adjustments to reflect previous under- or over-estimations under this clause in the projected percentage change in the consumer price index for medical care services.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6EC3E6D5EEDE4612990B16D1B7022BF9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>The total elective rural sustainability amount, the urban total elective rural sustainability amount, and the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount determined under this paragraph shall not be discounted or otherwise adjusted based on the Medicare patient load (as defined in subsection (h)(3)(C)) of an applicable hospital or discharges in a diagnosis-related group.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA9AB4B5BA2BD4B558BFFD125099C7088"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Election</header><text>For cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, an applicable hospital may elect to receive the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount for each full-time-equivalent resident in an approved medical residency training program that receives training in a rural training location in accordance with this subsection. An applicable hospital may make an election under the preceding sentence regardless of whether the applicable hospital is otherwise eligible for a payment or adjustment for indirect and direct graduate medical education costs under subsections (d)(5)(B) and (h) or section 1814(l), as applicable, with respect to such residents.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0EE930C5E18C460F8D8E498520D233F5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The provisions of this subsection, or the application of such provisions to an applicable hospital—</text> <subparagraph id="H29B31FEBB6E246E589C3E2F50B5E0FCE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not result in—</text>
<clause id="HBE2F2FC3401841CB90856C080385FD0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the establishment of a limitation on the number of residents in allopathic or osteopathic medicine for purposes of subsections (d)(5)(B) and (h) with respect to an approved medical residency training program of an applicable hospital (or be taken into account in determining such a limitation during the cap building period of an applicable hospital); or</text></clause> <clause id="H07CAA093B1704544BD3291E390268605"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the counting of any resident with respect to which the applicable hospital receives an elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount under this subsection towards the application of the limitation described in clause (i) for purposes of subsections (d)(5)(B) and (h); and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H29CDB173B40D48BB9E34630FC4CCCEE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not have any effect on the determination of—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H07F072B0A7D948F89D263EDE06483EF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the additional payment amount under subsection (d)(5)(B); or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H4698EEF3EC6C4E8AA849888B52BFE51F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>hospital-specific approved FTE resident amounts under subsection (h).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H77E202941EA44BCE80AF8445AD09BD1A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Allocation of payments</header><text>In providing for payments under this subsection, the Secretary shall provide for an allocation of such payments between parts A and part B (and the trust funds established under the respective parts) as reasonably reflects the proportion of such costs associated with the provision of services under each respective part.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H73E62E3D7B974A7FBC0A2422E50BDBC8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligibility for payment</header>
<subparagraph id="H9EB20AC3638744F6B78CD04455CE4FFC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An applicable hospital shall be eligible for payment of the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount under this subsection for time spent by a resident training in a rural training location if the following requirements are met:</text> <clause id="HF30A283032E74E69AF10750E5D3EAD43"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The resident spends the equivalent of at least 8 weeks over the course of their training in a rural training location.</text></clause>
<clause id="H7D05992550E0453BB62819CC61232F25"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The hospital pays the salary and benefits of the resident for the time spent training in a rural training location.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB14785460156407E870D7204251E1C6B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of time spent in rural tracks or integrated rural tracks</header><text>An applicable hospital shall be eligible for payment of the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount under this subsection for all time spent by residents in an approved medical residency program (or separately defined track within a program) that provides more than 50 percent of the total residency training time in rural training locations, regardless of where the training occurs and regardless of specialty.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2924AC9089A44CD88723ADE636E6584E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Determination of full-time-equivalent residents</header><text>The determination of full-time-equivalent residents for purposes of this subsection shall be made in the same manner as the determination of full-time-equivalent residents under subsection (h)(4), but not taking into account the limitation under subparagraph (F) of such subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDCB81EEB123244708CFDED8EC99E906D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text>
<subparagraph id="H598BD82CD0E840F58C25E46DEC612A3F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Applicable hospital</header><text>The term <term>applicable hospital</term> means a hospital, critical access hospital, sole community hospital (as defined in subsection (d)(5)(D)(iii)), or rural emergency hospital (as defined in section 1861(kkk)(2)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5BF707AD8F7F4A4CA2F40C0160095316"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approved medical residency training program; direct graduate medical education costs; resident</header><text>The terms <term>approved medical residency training program</term>, <term>direct graduate medical education costs</term>, and <term>resident</term> have the meanings given those terms in subsection (h)(5).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H76BD2D53DFD84F46985310635EA7DED1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rural training location</header><text>The term <term>rural training location</term> means a location in which training occurs that, based on the 2010 census or any subsequent census adjustment, meets one or more of the following criteria:</text> <clause id="HCEE966FB382F41B18BB7FF9AE57DAF58"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The training occurs in a location that is a rural area (as defined in section 1886(d)(2)(D)).</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H8CC872C092214702958151790C03009B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The training occurs in a location that has a rural-urban commuting area code equal to or greater than 4.0.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H40D40CC68DBA461B92511437BC77579C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The training occurs in a sole community hospital (as defined in subsection (d)(5)(D)(iii)) or in a location that is within 10 miles of a sole community hospital.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H27E6947B2C414F54B475BEAB1546E314"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Budget neutrality requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that aggregate payments for direct medical education costs and indirect medical education costs under this title, including any payments under this subsection, for each year (effective beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this subsection) are not greater than the aggregate payments for such costs that would have been made under this title for the year without the application of this subsection. For purposes of carrying out the budget neutrality requirement under the preceding sentence, the Secretary may make appropriate adjustments to the amount of such payments for direct graduate medical education costs and indirect medical education costs under subsections (h) and (d)(5)(B), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HF70F0B10ABDE40A4B289637D86C5CF5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of critical access hospitals and sole community hospitals</header> <paragraph id="H4F0DA8A6407A4F9EA3CF3D0E53ACA951"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical access hospitals</header><text>Section 1814(l) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395f">42 U.S.C. 1395f(l)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4639E3D35D524246B17D5182DD992B61">
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2AC8945A91694CAD9B082A41C3F7E6F3" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>For cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the following shall apply:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HAAC4CB57FBB94597B5BF8F95499A7BC4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A critical access hospital may elect to be treated as a hospital or as a non-provider setting for purposes of counting resident time for indirect medical education costs and direct graduate medical education costs for the time spent by the resident in that setting under subsections (d)(5)(B) and (h), respectively, of section 1886.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HD1C74DFFD10943D485CB17A16D5C47FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Direct medical education costs shall not be considered reasonable costs of a critical access hospital for purposes of payment under paragraph (1), to the extent that the critical access hospital is treated as a non-provider setting of another hospital or another hospital receives payment for such costs for the time spent by the resident in that setting pursuant to subsection (d)(5)(B), subsection (h), or subsection (u) of section 1886.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F05CF430D2647FD988B5EACB07376F6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sole community hospitals</header><text>Section 1886(d)(5)(D) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(d)(5)(D)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H25805701AE76475EAC780503A4DE1997">
<clause id="HCFD4845FAB9847DDABC0CF5CC4D00936" indent="up3"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>For cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the hospital-specific payment amount determined under clause (i)(I) with respect to a sole community hospital shall not include direct medical education costs, to the extent that the sole community hospital receives payment for such costs for the time spent by the resident in that setting pursuant to subsection (u).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H994FBF528C104241B11D72E72C47EEDD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> <paragraph id="H81402BA6321644FBB0756D26CCF2AE9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 1886 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCF9BBD1ED21149B4814990ACC60C9E15"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(5)(B), in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>The Secretary</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subsection (u), the Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD8D4776447ED41B989F32302D0018D30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (h)—</text>
<clause id="H9E6A94D77B4B482F8EAB2ADA2C8FA849"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>subject to subsection (u)</quote> after <quote>1861(v),</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA066C6D84B95468C879F747E13F994FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), in the flush matter following subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>subsection (k)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (k) or subsection (u)</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HB1D665161AC34598B34DCDF793CD0E84"><enum>3.</enum><header>Supporting new, expanding, and existing rural training tracks</header>
<subsection id="H24FEB458E8964815AD38467B2AD58A27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Direct graduate medical education</header><text>Section 1886(h) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(h)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HDB8C2A9131414E9DB3A619CDCE81E2B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCB304BE563B94C98B367E2904DBF53DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F)(i)—</text> <clause id="HBE930D3EAC034E488A785A448F3B258C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>130 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>for cost reporting periods beginning on or after October 1, 1997, and before the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</short-title>, 130 percent</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H8F094A97C0A144FB92062D9E854C2F47"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>For cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</short-title>, such rules shall provide that any full-time-equivalent resident in an approved medical residency program (or separately defined track within a program) that provides more than 50 percent of the total residency training time in rural training locations (as defined in subsection (u)(6)(C)), regardless of where the training occurs and regardless of specialty, shall not be taken into account for purposes of applying the limitation under this subparagraph.</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2582F979C07453EAD305113DD854E34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H)—</text>
<clause id="H3C523534D7754977B33A0E8D59F1982C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), in the second sentence, by inserting the following before the period: <quote>, in accordance with the second sentence of clause (i) of such subparagraph</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H31DFA526C20540D5A0C7A8D6805655DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by inserting the following before the period: <quote>, in accordance with the second sentence of clause (i) of such subparagraph</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA385A57816334751813F0E6F3D78AFF2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84B8A27EE4084291BFC5FC3BBCF50E15"> <subparagraph id="HD7840765808544AF995765B8E1A00EFE"><enum>(L)</enum><header>Special rules regarding application of elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount</header><text>For special rules regarding application of the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount under subsection (u), see paragraph (3) of such subsection.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC9215F21D5D24A419CD5F6AC33006FC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Indirect medical education</header><text>Section 1886(d)(5)(B)(v) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H6A74E85FFE294D14A71DC75EDF63F96F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>130 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>for cost reporting periods beginning on or after October 1, 1997, and before the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</short-title>, 130 percent</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H057CAC0A633540C2A328B01218CA2A7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>For cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rural Physician Workforce Production Act of 2023</short-title>, such rules shall provide that any full-time-equivalent resident in an approved medical residency program (or separately defined track within a program) that provides more than 50 percent of the total residency training time in rural training locations (as defined in subsection (u)(6)(C)), regardless of where the training occurs and regardless of specialty, shall not be taken into account for purposes of applying the limitation under this subparagraph. For special rules regarding application of the elective rural sustainability per resident payment amount under subsection (u), see paragraph (3) of such subsection.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

