<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA1168C80AAE64C72A4666CA04BFCBDE9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 722 IH: Western Hemisphere Nearshoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 722</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230201">February 1, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To decrease dependency on People’s Republic of China manufacturing and decrease migration due to lost regional economic opportunities.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HB8C192277096460CB97448E96D19CB5F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA2555F5F4890489D94220F462C42709F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Western Hemisphere Nearshoring Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5DE1DE69ECA54519BF8C7388ECEC8089"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE9BE91406ADF45A0BF6B85E9EE88661D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Our neighbors in the Western Hemisphere play a vital role in ensuring peace, security, and democracy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1B4D801F479846F2B90714875D0A34C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Instability and lack of economic opportunities in the region are major drivers of migration in violation of the Immigration and Nationality Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6284CEC19664203BC77FA2FF9562BA7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the United States Census Bureau, in 2021 the United States exported $174.62 billion worth of goods to Central and South America, and imported $121 billion.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97B619D344A740D18E0E43AF84837434"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United States is a net exporter with Central and South America.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A5068BC0D5E4A788C902558C7D5EEB2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Economic growth and development of the Western Hemisphere brings essential strength and stability to the region.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48A10C437F1E4B6FB09E224074C9BB52"><enum>(6)</enum><text>There is significant opportunity to expand the free flow of goods and services in the Western Hemisphere.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BCE397E007542B6A0FABDC55925182B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Closer relations among the Americas through free trade agreements and trade liberalization would encourage further economic development and stability in the region.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07607411ED2944739B1D2F15529E70AB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States should exercise its influence to encourage privatization, free markets, and economic cooperation in the region.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC02E0967AC3D4B7AAF05739DA21120BE"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Countries in the region should combat corruption, strengthen the rule of law, reduce bureaucratic red tape, streamline permitting, and embrace free market principles to encourage further private sector investment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2380A704036144678C6929FD0D186046"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With cooperation from the United States, regional countries must take serious steps to curb migration in violation of the Immigration and Nationality Act. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE67DC0DCBB7341CBB0ABD8681C372AA8"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Western Hemisphere has supply chains that are vulnerable due to their over dependence on the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56A63635E9294AD39B4D49C73852D419"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Free trade and expanded commercial ties between the United States and Western Hemisphere partners will foster economic and commercial cooperation, increase investment opportunities, decrease migration in violation of the Immigration and Nationality Act, reduce our dependence on the People’s Republic of China, and create jobs for American workers.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF25A56E6EBE94593B8FB139D8D58B156" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Use of United States International Development Finance Corporation funds to finance moving expenses and necessary workforce development costs incurred by companies moving from the People’s Republic of China to Latin America or the Caribbean</header> 
<subsection id="H2DB3F3018D794418803B23792FBB2CE4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="HE46EEA39E26D4A69972E8F84DA5ADFE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States International Development Finance Corporation, in coordination with relevant Federal agencies (including the United States Trade and Development Agency, the Export-Import Bank of the United States, the United States Army Corps of Engineers, and the United States Agency for International Development) and the United States Executive Directors of relevant international financial institutions (including the World Bank Group, the Inter-American Development Bank, and the International Monetary Fund), shall use not less than 10 percent of the amounts made available to provide financing under section 1421 of the Better Utilization of Investments Leading to Development Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9621">22 U.S.C. 9621</external-xref>) for each fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act to finance the qualified moving costs and necessary workforce development costs of, and reduce the interest rate on any loan to be provided by the DFC to the interest rate described in paragraph (3) to, any qualified corporation that is eligible for, or a recipient of, assistance from the DFC, to the extent of qualifying applications for assistance under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD28FC0DD2D64429185E2BFCA892A7B34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of unused amounts</header><text>If the DFC does not use the entire amount described in paragraph (1) for a fiscal year described in such paragraph, such amount shall, to the maximum extent practicable, be made available to the DFC for the next fiscal year to carry out this section or other DFC programs for Latin American or Caribbean countries.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B3F6084387248EA9966396A645FECC7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interest rate described</header><text>The interest rate described in this paragraph is—</text> <subparagraph id="H9F98DA3EEB1D4F459A406BC75BC44BF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federal funds rate; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6285E1923C9B4990AA431EDDC7BDBAD5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the interest rate that is determined by reducing by not less than <fraction>1/2</fraction> of 1 percent and not more than 1 percent (but to not less than zero percent) the interest rate on the loan to be provided by the DFC to the qualified corporation, </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">whichever is the lesser. </continuation-text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2781991330B04487B090828396FB45AA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No negative effects on employment in the United States</header><text>The DFC shall not provide assistance under this section unless the Secretary of Commerce has determined that the provision of the assistance would not result in a negative effect on employment in the United States.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H02A8729D495245DF83FD2C672CD9F8E5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disposition of unused assistance</header><text>A corporation to which financing is made under this section shall remit to the DFC any portion of the assistance that is not expended within a period of time after the date the financing is made that is determined by the DFC on a case-by-case basis.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H65C35FE2366D4FF8B11C487E6A97FF79"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conditions on provision of loans</header><text>The DFC—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBFF9D4EF558D41F2AA770983AD46186A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may provide loans under this section to a corporation only if the loans are commercially viable, as determined by the DFC; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C4C552AA68044449328E7E4D5773F95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall determine an appropriate amount of time for repayment of loans under this section to a corporation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE19A3C85A8B04EDD8E5FBC6D1E4BC756"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the DFC shall develop and submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a plan to streamline the provision of assistance under this section, including to expedite the approval process for the provision of such assistance.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE8AF89014B3140FFBF5774A54D01046E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authority to provide duty-free treatment for goods and services of companies moving from the People’s Republic of China to Latin America or the Caribbean</header> <subsection id="HB060831881CC4431A275390DB8F504A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the President shall proclaim duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) for any good or service made or produced in a Latin American or Caribbean country by a qualified corporation that has received assistance under section 3, subject to such terms and conditions as the President determines to be appropriate.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2182043F4F8C45A39816C0D0AD565ABD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The President shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3C11D48C344243A6AF70D605F5500BAC" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective period</header> <paragraph id="HFE9B836E7D13423CA0C395ABC051CDAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (a) shall apply with respect to a good or service made or produced in a Latin American or Caribbean country by a corporation for the 15-year period beginning on the date on which the corporation begins operations in such country.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H136C9561AE504C7FBC76BE54C3538C2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to affect duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) for any good or service made or produced in a Latin American or Caribbean country by a qualified corporation after the 15-year period described in paragraph (1) if goods and services from such country are otherwise generally eligible for duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H239BF2C29CBB4A0DA15F279DF5E0B7B5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Additional conditions on receipt of assistance under section 3 and duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) under section 4</header> <subsection id="HD18D7586B72346239AF767E13FBCB463"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appropriate Federal agency may not provide assistance under section 3 or duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) under section 4 to a corporation unless—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0EBE07B18BE049B594166062639C67A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the agency determines that the corporation will create jobs in the Latin American or Caribbean country to which it moves operations in numbers determined by the agency to be commensurate with the assistance provided;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF37730CF2F624D55B6B97F517CC6A15E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the corporation makes a binding commitment to the agency that on and after the date the assistance is provided—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCE14E51210DA4A5F80C958F7D3633E3C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the corporation will not come under the ownership or control of the Government of the People’s Republic of China or the Chinese Communist Party, the Government of the Russian Federation, or any other foreign adversary; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEF7B9CE9EDDA4F70ABCD03D34B253396"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the corporation will not have its headquarters in the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, or any other foreign adversary;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84DFE92B093E46CEB76E16AA4A2E4F43"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">within 2 years after the date described in paragraph (2), and subject to an additional extension as determined appropriate by the agency, all assets of the corporation with respect to which the assistance is provided will have been moved from the People’s Republic of China to a Latin American or Caribbean country; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H86FDD4FE8B8341BDBFCA1BF1DF31AFD1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the corporation retains all assets of the corporation with respect to which the assistance is provided in a Latin American or Caribbean country after the date described in paragraph (2) or the last day of the extension described in paragraph (3), as the case may be.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H30443620572F41D798F035633990D02A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compliance determinations</header> 
<paragraph id="H70D9FB2CA3084B598A1B11AC77BC58DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The appropriate Federal agency, in coordination with the Department of State, shall make all determinations regarding compliance with the provisions of subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8C1C293FF1B424A8EB4CD14AB09B2EB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-compliance actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified corporation that has received assistance under section 3 or duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) under section 4 that is subsequently determined by the appropriate Federal agency not to be in compliance with the provisions of subsection (a) shall be subject to the following actions:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF3CCF285B9B547309F5F118EC791B36A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any good or service made or produced in a Latin American or Caribbean country by the corporation (other than a good or service made or produced in a free trade zone or which is subject to benefits under a free trade agreement) shall not be eligible for duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) under section 4. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40BC0106AE404F7D84E71FABB8269813"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The appropriate Federal agency shall adjust the interest rate on any loan to be provided by the agency to the corporation to the prevailing market interest rate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9F482CDB861141CA8B9D1DFDE1AE3FC0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate Federal agency defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate Federal agency</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H1627C7B26C314414AF31488F89BB1C65"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to actions relating to assistance under section 3, the DFC; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AFA2354E7CA4255A5D832363F13AC47"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to actions relating to duty-free treatment (or other preferential treatment) under section 4, the United States Trade Representative.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H36D083944C144CA1AFA8D783F158D7B9"><enum>6.</enum><header>Expenses paid for with tariffs collected from the People’s Republic of China</header> <subsection id="HB2AC9BF9DFF84086B0DFBAE6EDE10A89"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury of the United States a trust fund consisting of such amounts as are appropriated to such trust fund under subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H91AEEC9F5CDE4D7FAD44D0E1F8C3D96F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appropriations to trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are hereby appropriated to such trust fund amounts equivalent to the tariffs collected by the United States on goods manufactured in the People’s Republic of China.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H14EC418FFF2348E5A9E593EA00869BF4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriations from trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are hereby appropriated from such trust fund to the General Fund of the Treasury amounts equivalent to the reduction in revenue to such General Fund by reason of assistance provided by the DFC under this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B806AB49CD343E98B27FE474321C48D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Timing of transfers, etc</header><text>Rules similar to the rules of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/9601">section 9601</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall apply with respect to appropriations to and from such trust fund under subsections (b) and (c).</text></subsection></section> <section id="HF60945D717B44101888EC138C01FE4B2"><enum>7.</enum><header>Amendments to the BUILD Act of 2018</header> <subsection id="HFDC5FFCEBDA147FFB1926E575FCEAE72"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1411 of the Better Utilization of Investments Leading to Development Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9611">22 U.S.C. 9611</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4604FBE1FDB64A298BFCAB2FA9764221"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF46CDBA8204E4DCA8FC5DB4A39973771"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34C5409B33B04A778B2C98C2FEE3D25D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4674DA7CAA364097BE9E026B7A72DD71" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H0A8B6E0A41D646BDB5EEF530B08B660E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>to further United States economic growth by prioritizing United States-owned businesses in providing support under title II; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20D94F1EC1A64CD89D6F886DEEF12FE3"><enum>(10)</enum><text>to further United States national security by prioritizing the production of goods in critical industries, as determined by the Corporation, in consultation with the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1D2A011338274896BBDCB189D1427184" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on support for state-Owned enterprises</header> <paragraph id="H69B14C374F474042B78DCF75423983B0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title V of the Better Utilization of Investments Leading to Development Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9671">22 U.S.C. 9671 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H480E87C65B80462ABA9AF2E61EC631B8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HEF8B4D0C56784DD0B1BD8FAB26F5969E" commented="no"><enum>1455.</enum><header>Prohibition on support for entities owned or controlled by foreign governments</header> 
<subsection id="H7D1979F109DC4EA7A11AD047D1059D05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), the Corporation is prohibited from providing support under title II for an entity owned or controlled by a foreign government.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA0A42D3D0E5A42BF9B4CC653E8D54BF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header> <paragraph id="HF253B7A03D9F43A0A04EAB3BC3AC10D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation may provide feasibility studies and technical assistance under title II for an entity owned or controlled by a foreign government that is not a foreign adversary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85877D043CFA491EB3497E251AE96C99"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign adversary defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>foreign adversary</term> means a foreign government engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or security and safety of United States persons.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE9CDD67F1764E4A98A6BCB32A6C3F9C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1454 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4366C8F2DAC040309FFF06FF4F77CB1D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 1455. Prohibition on support for entities owned or controlled by foreign governments.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H91CB18DB0B18481987BE20EFD6551E9F"><enum>8.</enum><header>Trade negotiating authority</header> 
<subsection id="H162F8A9FF99D4427AFF533E687D064C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Trade Representative shall take action to initiate negotiations to obtain trade agreements with each Latin American or Caribbean country that as of the date of the enactment of this Act is not a party to a free trade agreement with the United States if the country meets the conditions described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H87EE2CC89D464A09BE73C71D1C982A64"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conditions described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The conditions described in this subsection are the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H69B4B1276DCC4C1882E1C412B9BE1A37"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The country is taking steps to reduce migration in violation of the Immigration and Nationality Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0F070AF08E1445BB93967CF9E608C419"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The country is taking steps to reduce economic dependence on the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC619662DE678416AA344CE2CAA3C4A7B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The country allows Taiwan to establish and maintain a commercial office in the country.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDC0EDF11FFEA438980D16C1A45D4C59B"><enum>9.</enum><header>Agreements for cooperation pursuant to section 123 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954</header> <subsection id="H49F4D30F50264910B7AB508F3A59CD00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President is authorized to take action to initiate negotiations with Latin American and Caribbean countries to obtain agreements for cooperation pursuant to section 123 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2153">42 U.S.C. 2153</external-xref>) to approve the sales of nuclear reactors to such countries, or to qualified corporations that receive assistance under this Act, but only if—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB238393F9F9440D892AB0609549A7EEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President determines that such sales will not threaten the national security of the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D47104897FF41BAA49BC2C5095160EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the countries or qualified corporations, as the case may be, meet the conditions described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of section 8(b).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC492B61741F64FADA2694FB9F2AFDFAB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical assistance and expertise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy and the DFC, may provide technical assistance and expertise in electrical grid and energy efficiency improvements related to sales under subsection (a), as appropriate.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC407888B8164452CAB7A7407018D17BE" commented="no"><enum>10.</enum><header>Temporary increased expensing for relocating manufacturing from the People’s Republic of China to a Latin American or Caribbean country</header> <subsection id="H8F050EA7F76246A8A6E785B81BAB26A8" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/168">section 168(k)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, in the case of any qualified relocated manufacturing property which is placed in service by a qualified manufacturer after the date of the enactment of this Act, and before January 1, 2038—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3C83E73294D64B1FA17056AAD435F14D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such property shall be treated as qualified property (within the meaning of such section),</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0897CEB8B4B41DBA442CFBF5BBD292D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the applicable percentage otherwise determined under section 168(k)(6) of such Code with respect to such property shall be 75 percent, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E4E4AC71DAB44B1859309DD71205574" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>paragraph (8) of such section shall not apply. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1488CCBBCF86477C9FDCB400A843D0CC" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified relocated manufacturing property</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1AA65BE8492C424FA7781FEF978AF367"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified relocated manufacturing property</term> means qualified property (within the meaning of section 168(k) of such Code) or nonresidential real property (as defined in section 168(e)(2)(B) of such Code) which is—</text> <subparagraph id="HF67613802E144C76A5E5E87998FBB57D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>placed in service in a Latin American or Caribbean country by a qualified manufacturer, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD2A8F3742BF4458BAF0FF76999960C5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is acquired by such qualified manufacturer in connection with a qualified relocation of manufacturing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D550B8414164179ACFBE2840B3E74A0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified relocation of manufacturing</header> <subparagraph id="HFD01DCB884BC4E9EA38E378EF021AF23" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified relocation of manufacturing</term> means, with respect to any qualified manufacturer, the relocation of the manufacturing of any tangible personal property from the People’s Republic of China to a Latin American or Caribbean country.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD45E5C2983164925AAC7B0D03B95AF05" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relocation of property not required</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), manufacturing shall not fail to be treated as relocated merely because property used in such manufacturing was not relocated.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A55652D92D44B47B60B61BE99E7AC5C" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Relocation of not less than equivalent productive capacity required</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), manufacturing shall not be treated as relocated unless the property manufactured in a Latin American or Caribbean country is substantially identical to the property previously manufactured in the People’s Republic of China and the increase in the units of production of such property in a Latin American or Caribbean country by the qualified manufacturer is not less than the reduction in the units of production of such property by such qualified manufacturer in the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9FFD999B694344D284490978F75F1A34" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualified manufacturer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>qualified manufacturer</term> means any person—</text> <paragraph id="H8E1AE59AE2A34ECBB9191805EED3852E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>which is engaged in the trade or business of manufacturing any tangible personal property,</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F8129AD45A3495B9A21F73C4D545E03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to which the Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary’s delegate) has made the determination described in section 5(a)(1), and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H503B925F6B36464A906AB06F016F0142"><enum>(3)</enum><text>which has entered into a binding agreement with such Secretary (or such delegate) to meet the requirements of section 5(a)(2) which is enforceable under terms similar to the terms of section 5(b).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H01FBF3824B0E4524A53B96185B179562" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>11.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H803E9F8D6D7B47FBBB888B0182AD7E05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>DFC</header><text>The term <term>DFC</term> means the United States International Development Finance Corporation. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAEADF3CF7BDB4C7E8D0AEDDF0D1EDDC4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified corporation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified corporation</term> does not include a State-owned enterprise.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8E41EABD4FC41569E87027C0C04CCCD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified moving costs defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified moving costs</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8815CE6546F341BF8A4200B0F7004C9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the costs of moving inventory, equipment, and supplies from the People’s Republic of China to a Latin American or Caribbean country; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HADF5441A045C47A4A55ED79292F9E53B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the costs of workforce development and construction of facilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CD21424BEC244FAB188AAE77C830D4A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Latin American or Caribbean country; Western Hemisphere</header> 
<subparagraph id="H481B0EE766B140278A79391C21F81DAE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The terms <term>Latin American or Caribbean country</term> and <term>Western Hemisphere</term>—</text> <clause id="H369F1225059C4F058592ACC4988880F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>mean a country in the Caribbean Sea, South America, or Central America, and Mexico; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDF1018C258FE4A3EADC06FD00E0FBADE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>except as provided in subparagraph (B), do not include Cuba or Venezuela.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B88D49073DD4AE2BD72E11252106CC2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Latin American or Caribbean country</term> shall include Cuba or Venezuela if the Secretary of State determines and certifies to Congress that—</text> 
<clause id="H173369C57B9543E59A0B5FA7FC01EEB7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the government of such country—</text> <subclause id="H49E344AE3E854579B52E88602B303DD5"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has held free and fair presidential and legislative elections, as determined by independent international observers, and subsequent elections are scheduled;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCC978B4708F04AEDB036B646F63D963F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>respects and upholds human rights;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC818F7C7B8504F1AAF618583BEC8E5B9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is taking significant steps to privatize its economy and institute a free market;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HFAFC7F878A7E4F199B157EA45EDF111E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">permits the international community to provide humanitarian, governance, and economic development assistance;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6835715782A74153839E0D57F1263C9B"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has freed all unlawfully detained United States citizens, legal permanent residents, and political prisoners; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE5572D53B04449CFAB3FC72A63CBB9B1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>has expelled all security services from foreign adversaries from the country; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HEB2ECDDA9B93496EAF4DC0463D234571"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the prior authorities of such country have renounced their illegitimate claim to power.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE81CAE8EAFB84FD38AB9DDBED5D418E8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federal funds rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal funds rate</term> means the discount window primary credit interest rate most recently published on the Federal Reserve Statistical Release on selected interest rates (daily or weekly), commonly referred to as the H.15 release.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

