<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC02B139766084D88B9DF1EAAE85C02DB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5718 IH: Nuclear Fuel Security Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5718</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Energy to establish a Nuclear Fuel Security Program, expand the American Assured Fuel Supply Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE54DB4C90CAC45819A755B04C1866563" style="OLC"><section id="HAAC7D027B32145CC84DB7F831D8F15F5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nuclear Fuel Security Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HF016B6B92AD142268CD3E779ED8C7B9D"><enum>2.</enum><header>U.S. nuclear fuel security initiative</header><subsection id="H7EE736350BE94EA09C958C50A02F7401"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HE9A58E3980624B689FC582BE197B52F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Department should—</text><subparagraph id="H8ED1E820804B46ACBE2C194B4CB6CB34"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support increased domestic production of low-enriched uranium; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8465DDAE8D4E4D07835A8F553B1A5E5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>accelerate efforts to establish a domestic high-assay, low-enriched uranium enrichment capability; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CDC4276EC8C46EFBE5EBB026AA23278"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if domestic enrichment of high-assay, low-enriched uranium will not be commercially available at the scale needed in time to meet the needs of the advanced nuclear reactor demonstration projects of the Department, the Secretary shall consider and implement, as necessary—</text><subparagraph id="HA1F0101082604815BBBBD4E78C772F70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all viable options to make high-assay, low-enriched uranium produced from inventories owned by the Department available in a manner that is sufficient to maximize the potential for the Department to meet the needs and schedules of advanced nuclear reactor developers, without impacting existing Department missions, until such time that commercial enrichment and deconversion capability for high-assay, low-enriched uranium exists at a scale sufficient to meet future needs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92EBCE3EE54841FA9CAF7E29B3926B0A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all viable options for partnering with countries that are allies or partners of the United States to meet those needs and schedules until that time.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4D29A12950E34AD1856FFDE22556B9E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Objectives</header><text>The objectives of this section are—</text><paragraph id="HC4EAF07D933C4DD3B3A1B43702A9B2A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support domestic production of low-enriched uranium;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBDF3A9B5F634FFB9109BA60978669C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to expeditiously increase domestic production of high-assay, low-enriched uranium by an annual quantity, and in such form, determined by the Secretary to be sufficient to meet the needs of—</text><subparagraph id="HB0011CCB6ADE4C04909DDBCFD6E66BFB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advanced nuclear reactor developers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H766C8579E06E4C31B9D55E8E211F4982"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the consortium;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7B534E4254344C5B87A6C65B853F4D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to ensure the availability of domestically produced, converted, enriched, deconverted, and reduced uranium in a quantity determined by the Secretary, in consultation with U.S. nuclear energy companies, to be sufficient to address a reasonably anticipated supply disruption;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H016BB6AA14A5449BB76C503A56E76C8C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to address gaps and deficiencies in the domestic production, conversion, enrichment, deconversion, and reduction of uranium by partnering with countries that are allies or partners of the United States if domestic options are not practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H488660C9AFB54D27863378A232F0E235"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to ensure that, in the event of a supply disruption in the nuclear fuel market, a reserve of nuclear fuels is available to serve as a backup supply to support the nuclear nonproliferation and civil nuclear energy objectives of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEE4DEBBF01F4B9BBC297CF6CDA3FCBC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to support enrichment, deconversion, and reduction technology deployed in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CBDA09B7607495AA371D0C6E5AFF44D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to ensure that, until such time that domestic enrichment and deconversion of high-assay, low-enriched uranium is commercially available at the scale needed to meet the needs of advanced nuclear reactor developers, the Secretary considers and implements, as necessary—</text><subparagraph id="H7330A37050EA4F2194764FEDC0CE09E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all viable options to make high-assay, low-enriched uranium produced from inventories owned by the Department available in a manner that is sufficient to maximize the potential for the Department to meet the needs and schedules of advanced nuclear reactor developers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA905D4765FDF44FF9C6BF21CE1B33AAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all viable options for partnering with countries that are allies or partners of the United States to meet those needs and schedules. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H098E4758E49541F5ABEB7DF327DC5425"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBA45B18899D7464ABB788C6BF3B8FD57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced nuclear reactor</header><text>The term <term>advanced nuclear reactor</term> has the meaning given the term in section 951(b) of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16271">42 U.S.C. 16271(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7524A25B189141E6B7EA23A6E6ED6C89"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Associated entity</header><text>The term <term>associated entity</term> means an entity that—</text><subparagraph id="H53E1E4F83CBD4E6D98D4110B2582A93F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is owned, controlled, or dominated by—</text><clause id="H6B74F162C6584785B559B6F486BB163C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the government of a country that is an ally or partner of the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H62F8106A84C845CFA2B6B7F9433BBD66" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an associated individual; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEF5514AAD354EA698BC0E1719E82AB0" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is organized under the laws of, or otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of, a country that is an ally or partner of the United States, including a corporation that is incorporated in such a country. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA19DD8475574F8A87893EF337CF406F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Associated individual</header><text>The term <term>associated individual</term> means an alien who is a national of a country that is an ally or partner of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DF3A6D331F04CAF8FCD16920405F417"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consortium</header><text>The term <term>consortium</term> means the consortium established under section 2001(a)(2)(F) of the Energy Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16281">42 U.S.C. 16281(a)(2)(F)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE907EC6029914FBEA5BD8497F66BD945"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB148A838AF3429FB8EFB3910CEE442D" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>High-assay, low-enriched uranium; HALEU</header><text>The term <term>high-assay, low-enriched uranium</term> or <term>HALEU</term> means high-assay low-enriched uranium (as defined in section 2001(d) of the Energy Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16281">42 U.S.C. 16281(d)</external-xref>)). </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H777BD091C9AB499588AAF15755F4DD31"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Low-enriched uranium; LEU</header><text>The term <term>low-enriched uranium</term> or <term>LEU</term> means each of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H10E4EAA38C34481BBCB69305DA92B8ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>low-enriched uranium (as defined in section 3102 of the USEC Privatization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2297h">42 U.S.C. 2297h</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H379FB26D59D3412CBD85957186009DFC" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>low-enriched uranium (as defined in section 3112A(a) of that Act (42 U.S.C. 2297h–10a(a))). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H74185DD4A73A4273A8E28477EFD152FA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Programs</header><text>The term <term>Programs</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HEC209BA7CA724DF19739F87ABFCEC4DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Nuclear Fuel Security Program established under subsection (d)(1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72397EC0B42F4E438ED74EFD821B2350"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the American Assured Fuel Supply Program of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF92B363619EB402482A13B36FC3F4699"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the HALEU for Advanced Nuclear Reactor Demonstration Projects Program established under subsection (d)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA56C42907B24978A36A9D2E3C0A8C0A"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A761CEF7BB34F38B720D4F77B163767" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>U.S. nuclear energy company</header><text>The term <term>U.S. nuclear energy company</term> means a company that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3AD0C648C38A44CCB728F0FAD0397C01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is organized under the laws of, or otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of, the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4CCAA4E1B47435E9BB3EEAE297D6944" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is involved in the nuclear energy industry. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8BA64C1D4FD4889A095F18DB9E61D3B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Establishment and expansion of programs</header><text>The Secretary, consistent with the objectives described in subsection (b), shall—</text><paragraph id="HDE8D9C06BD0F4A73857925EAFFB1BFCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a program, to be known as the <quote>Nuclear Fuel Security Program</quote>, to increase the quantity of HALEU and, if determined to be necessary after completion of a market evaluation, LEU produced by U.S. nuclear energy companies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H405425D51FE24A1688CC85762F3F8005"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expand the American Assured Fuel Supply Program of the Department to ensure the availability of domestically produced, converted, enriched, deconverted, and reduced uranium in the event of a supply disruption; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6538EA7DDFE94AFFB5ED54C75435E680"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establish a program, to be known as the <quote>HALEU for Advanced Nuclear Reactor Demonstration Projects Program</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H3555151715134E588DF6ED1BC78819A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to maximize the potential for the Department to meet the needs and schedules of advanced nuclear reactor developers until such time that commercial enrichment and deconversion capability for HALEU exists in the United States at a scale sufficient to meet future needs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H796536DEC4E848A995838D762D699A29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>where practicable, to partner with countries that are allies or partners of the United States to meet those needs and schedules until that time.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9ED9B42FD0AE4D25AFACCA21F1CE9E14"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Nuclear Fuel Security Program</header><paragraph id="H35781376DBEE48A382A92F54D747F116"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the Nuclear Fuel Security Program, the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H849BF2D778AB4CFD8DA35CFDF695AF47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall—</text><clause id="H7467B660B70C45B2BAE49CF5B93C493F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if determined to be necessary or appropriate based on the completion of a market evaluation, not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, take actions, including cost-shared financial agreements, milestone-based payments, or other mechanisms, to support commercial availability of LEU and to promote diversity of supply in domestic uranium mining, conversion, enrichment, and deconversion capacity and technologies, including new capacity, among U.S. nuclear energy companies;</text></clause><clause id="H6EEC735368224F56ABA93C99D56B8A7D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, enter into 2 or more contracts with members of the consortium to begin acquiring not less than 20 metric tons per year of HALEU by December 31, 2027 (or the earliest operationally feasible date thereafter), from U.S. nuclear energy companies;</text></clause><clause id="HD7D6940A0B854DA9888A6F40389146BA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>utilize only uranium produced, converted, enriched, deconverted, and reduced in—</text><subclause id="HE64C4F80ACF74075B7EAEF0D0AC9C1B2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the United States; or </text></subclause><subclause id="H567121DA51E2438A97C3B34E6721EAE2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if domestic options are not practicable, a country that is an ally or partner of the United States; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB339F84D9890433AA5FE15385022C3B0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, ensure that the use of domestic uranium utilized as a result of that program does not negatively affect the economic operation of nuclear reactors in the United States; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9303262EF8C14E7CBA3CE0E52793EF6B"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8F4AFA20ECA64CB3849473DA64FC4414"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may not make commitments under this subsection (including cooperative agreements (used in accordance with section 6305 of title 31, United States Code), purchase agreements, guarantees, leases, service contracts, or any other type of commitment) for the purchase or other acquisition of HALEU or LEU unless—</text><subclause id="HCDB5B92A583447E59507C3A9AECE53D3" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>funds are specifically provided for those purposes in advance in appropriations Acts enacted after the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="HA284EA24DF154EDB8E010A551A3935C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the commitment is funded entirely by funds made available to the Secretary from the account described in subsection (i)(2)(B); and</text></subclause></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H25DE70EDA64640A883C3D0D2FD05A506"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may make a commitment described in clause (i) only—</text><subclause id="H2A1AB4DCA0064BA79B347B374D6F8CC9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the full extent of the anticipated costs stemming from the commitment is recorded as an obligation at the time that the commitment is made; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H61ED1D09A90541B49938B221851A2964"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the extent of that up-front obligation recorded in full at that time.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C0E53277A884CB7BB2C05549188359B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1)(A)(ii), the Secretary shall consider and, if appropriate, implement—</text><subparagraph id="H04DB8BFEF8C9424C95C98BF6019CCC6E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>options to ensure the quickest availability of commercially enriched HALEU, including—</text><clause id="H31F92A8ECED5465EA22365E13F0D57A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>partnerships between 2 or more commercial enrichers; and</text></clause><clause id="H7A8F4333A57841F09DA1D52F177FF6FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>utilization of up to 10-percent enriched uranium as feedstock in demonstration-scale or commercial HALEU enrichment facilities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CFACE2660D44FC89ACFE101EBAC5944"><enum>(B)</enum><text>options to partner with countries that are allies or partners of the United States to provide LEU and HALEU for commercial purposes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5DD2F432503423B91854E8876C92889"><enum>(C)</enum><text>options that provide for an array of HALEU—</text><clause id="HC2461C34EB634AF19E6B39AE7501125A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enrichment levels;</text></clause><clause id="HDBC5D77530EB4625B45F6DF18F3A50AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>output levels to meet demand; and</text></clause><clause id="HDB2928732BA64BB4B57E370524C8F910"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>fuel forms, including uranium metal and oxide; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C694442955149BCA509D3A7B1384DC5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>options—</text><clause id="H79A9252745BC44FEA0A33B0ED539F0C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to replenish, as necessary, Department stockpiles of uranium that were intended to be downblended for other purposes, but were instead used in carrying out activities under the HALEU for Advanced Nuclear Reactor Demonstration Projects Program;</text></clause><clause id="H55BCA5D46414437981E0EE4DBB7CF198"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to continue supplying HALEU to meet the needs of the recipients of an award made pursuant to the funding opportunity announcement of the Department numbered DE–FOA–0002271 for Pathway 1, Advanced Reactor Demonstrations; and</text></clause><clause id="H2F9CBB12B9E34C099E35433D3ACE1D17"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to make HALEU available to other advanced nuclear reactor developers and other end-users.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10B970A5AC08464EB4E5C3CFB8603BA3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Avoidance of market disruptions</header><text>In carrying out the Nuclear Fuel Security Program, the Secretary, to the extent practicable and consistent with the purposes of that program, shall not disrupt or replace market mechanisms by competing with U.S. nuclear energy companies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H861F5215A1864E1CAD195A92DFD3B6DC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Expansion of the American Assured Fuel Supply Program</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with U.S. nuclear energy companies, shall—</text><paragraph id="H1C35137CF3E14D2FA5644B4FEC2F4542"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expand the American Assured Fuel Supply Program of the Department by merging the operations of the Uranium Reserve Program of the Department with the American Assured Fuel Supply Program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED0301ACEED24BC8B43B4012E4EA2757"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in carrying out the American Assured Fuel Supply Program of the Department, as expanded under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H6D5367A23D154D7A9AF19590DBF1AE3F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintain, replenish, diversify, or increase the quantity of uranium made available by that program in a manner determined by the Secretary to be consistent with the purposes of that program and the objectives described in subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2F0071055AD4A7A8BC73E69D14622EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>utilize only uranium produced, converted, enriched, deconverted, and reduced in—</text><clause id="HA5A02C040DF748F5829B03E525AB6933"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="HB5160CECC3C64876AF1417148FE0A648"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if domestic options are not practicable, a country that is an ally or partner of the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8043599547BF46E3AF0585F912489F53"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make uranium available from the American Assured Fuel Supply, subject to terms and conditions determined by the Secretary to be reasonable and appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7F13FD0C6CE4894B220590158503F31"><enum>(D)</enum><text>refill and expand the supply of uranium in the American Assured Fuel Supply, including by maintaining a limited reserve of uranium to address a potential event in which a domestic or foreign recipient of uranium experiences a supply disruption for which uranium cannot be obtained through normal market mechanisms or under normal market conditions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33DC55A01BDB4C799C74CB95C752B18D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>take other actions that the Secretary determines to be necessary or appropriate to address the purposes of that program and the objectives described in subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE47FC2A61D2F4F58A70926DCDAF10243"><enum>(g)</enum><header>HALEU for Advanced Nuclear Reactor Demonstration Projects Program</header><paragraph id="H70FA0ABA22F34D2685C8AAE5FE766A56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>On enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall immediately accelerate and, as necessary, initiate activities to make available from inventories or stockpiles owned by the Department and made available to the consortium, HALEU for use in advanced nuclear reactors that cannot operate on uranium with lower enrichment levels or on alternate fuels, with priority given to the awards made pursuant to the funding opportunity announcement of the Department numbered DE–FOA–0002271 for Pathway 1, Advanced Reactor Demonstrations, with additional HALEU to be made available to other advanced nuclear reactor developers, as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE008301167694865A3498ACBAF006C10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Quantity</header><text>In carrying out activities under this subsection, the Secretary shall consider and implement, as necessary, all viable options to make HALEU available in quantities and forms sufficient to maximize the potential for the Department to meet the needs and schedules of advanced nuclear reactor developers, including by seeking to make available—</text><subparagraph id="HD2910FA9D3EE42B69F3DC568BE09C072"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by September 30, 2024, not less than 3 metric tons of HALEU;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8812329BF3F344149697E2C148879242"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by December 31, 2025, not less than an additional 8 metric tons of HALEU; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15B942A65EA64F7B85191629EE399F26"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by June 30, 2026, not less than an additional 10 metric tons of HALEU.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB0E8CCD346E424DA689FDEBF76B1AC3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Factors for consideration</header><text>In carrying out activities under this subsection, the Secretary shall take into consideration—</text><subparagraph id="H2182A23601E941E3A499B68B8FAE2B37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>options for providing HALEU from a stockpile of uranium owned by the Department, including—</text><clause id="H13C4BCEC492144E08868B9BE64FBD0B7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>uranium that has been declared excess to national security needs during or prior to fiscal year 2023;</text></clause><clause id="H2C2827269B954B2EB65BFBB017E2DF00"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>uranium that—</text><subclause id="H1DB73557AED240078961966D27243B9F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly meets the needs of advanced nuclear reactor developers; but</text></subclause><subclause id="H8C9D97D093874EA59293022AB43AB1FB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has been previously used or fabricated for another purpose;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9D20CA7F4AAC4E57AE0C655AC6CB62B6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>uranium that can meet the needs of advanced nuclear reactor developers after removing radioactive or other contaminants that resulted from previous use or fabrication of the fuel for research, development, demonstration, or deployment activities of the Department, including activities that reduce the environmental liability of the Department by accelerating the processing of uranium from stockpiles designated as waste;</text></clause><clause id="H99237DD099E84B6BB10A88E9A2EB1F07"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>uranium from a high-enriched uranium stockpile, which can be blended with lower assay uranium to become HALEU to meet the needs of advanced nuclear reactor developers; and</text></clause><clause id="HFDD7CA7B1B19428C8A23CD09A550526F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>uranium from stockpiles intended for other purposes (excluding stockpiles intended for national security needs), but for which uranium could be swapped or replaced in time in such a manner that would not negatively impact the missions of the Department;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3EBE29EE44E45F7A9EE31AB61D1C6A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>options for expanding, or establishing new, capabilities or infrastructure to support the processing of uranium from Department inventories;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H976E661A296D48DDBDAB97FA9246F5CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>options for accelerating the availability of HALEU from HALEU enrichment demonstration projects of the Department;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H058C630437FD40C39742A92A154E9E94"><enum>(D)</enum><text>options for providing HALEU from domestically enriched HALEU procured by the Department through a competitive process pursuant to the Nuclear Fuel Security Program established under subsection (d)(1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H161FA8A816AD41B393A2EAA3B550B3C0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>options to replenish, as needed, Department stockpiles of uranium made available pursuant to subparagraph (A) with domestically enriched HALEU procured by the Department through a competitive process pursuant to the Nuclear Fuel Security Program established under subsection (d)(1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76788D47C42D4407A63AD36C3B5BCC33"><enum>(F)</enum><text>options that combine 1 or more of the approaches described in subparagraphs (A) through (E) to meet the deadlines described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H53FC8A16FD9541F6AFA2C56641261F48"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitations</header><subparagraph id="H6F9697C9E10A41A6AE9EF03B102CDAA9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Certain services</header><text>The Secretary shall not barter or otherwise sell or transfer uranium in any form in exchange for services relating to—</text><clause id="HC26A1059CD684E7FB392942FAB1FDD23"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the final disposition of radioactive waste from uranium that is the subject of a contract for sale, resale, transfer, or lease under this subsection; or</text></clause><clause id="H8D5AF63E2A77457B8FC25A5AA1630A53"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>environmental cleanup activities.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66871AB90CFD471199468611C79AFDE6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain commitments</header><text>In carrying out activities under this subsection, the Secretary—</text><clause id="HA4FF41A202A54C25AB709A5E1A84B5BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may not make commitments under this subsection (including cooperative agreements (used in accordance with section 6305 of title 31, United States Code), purchase agreements, guarantees, leases, service contracts, or any other type of commitment) for the purchase or other acquisition of HALEU or LEU unless—</text><subclause id="HCC13D6BB2F2C443DA3EE98D10669DE86"><enum>(I)</enum><text>funds are specifically provided for those purposes in advance in appropriations Acts enacted after the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HCB2B9D6467DB465FBD5A492527CF441C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the commitment is funded entirely by funds made available to the Secretary from the account described in subsection (i)(2)(B); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0CD9ED6319D048139B89A745C7F3392B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may make a commitment described in clause (i) only—</text><subclause id="H2F6BD75CAEEE476E99C823347F1B2448"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the full extent of the anticipated costs stemming from the commitment is recorded as an obligation at the time that the commitment is made; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H653BA46FFFF8445183CB803789396789"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the extent of that up-front obligation recorded in full at that time.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BA0565C5227447D9F07FD8701022617"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority of the Secretary to carry out activities under this subsection shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><subparagraph id="HDFB033C657FC40A49ACE512E46777DB2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date on which the Secretary notifies Congress that the HALEU needs of advanced nuclear reactor developers can be fully met by commercial HALEU suppliers in the United States, as determined by the Secretary, in consultation with U.S. nuclear energy companies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16D4CA59CE25407D89F61A31F758F06F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>September 30, 2034.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2C8912DDB2E4612B615DC58322EC244"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Domestic sourcing considerations</header><paragraph id="H350E5C2817AF4AFAAE5A9A612853E5B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary may only carry out an activity in connection with 1 or more of the Programs if—</text><subparagraph id="H4F49327AB9E845AFB9E711AFDE8213AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the activity promotes manufacturing in the United States associated with uranium supply chains; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C24C0A5D9CF4D27892B80521C14B6C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the activity relies on resources, materials, or equipment developed or produced—</text><clause id="H152E70FBB232413D9C8258E6CDDF0362"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H6F1B50E2AADC468A85C4079C79EC0BCA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in a country that is an ally or partner of the United States by—</text><subclause id="HE1BD0EA829224840B4BCEF88A09DB388"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the government of that country;</text></subclause><subclause id="H585C742213084BB896E7838E69A59730" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an associated entity; or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA1226B9B3DBE4EA1B73B39E5AFF044EB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a U.S. nuclear energy company.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C04988685E44B1395FD474EF3A95016"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirements of paragraph (1) with respect to an activity if the Secretary determines a waiver to be necessary to achieve 1 or more of the objectives described in subsection (b). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD5005D8D0494830960F9BFF7ADF5695"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reasonable compensation</header><paragraph id="H19CCA4E6CC364FC489C9FC9F212206E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out activities under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that any LEU and HALEU made available by the Secretary under 1 or more of the Programs is subject to reasonable compensation, taking into account the fair market value of the LEU or HALEU and the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF472A894C71466AA0F2CABFCAF64467"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of certain funds</header><subparagraph id="H913791EB9EC241F699D948096262ABCA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 3302(b) of title 31, United States Code, revenues received by the Secretary from the sale or transfer of fuel feed material acquired by the Secretary pursuant to a contract entered into under clause (i) or (ii) of subsection (e)(1)(A) shall—</text><clause id="H73A706BA02274F529F27048F5C5BC4CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be deposited in the account described in subparagraph (B);</text></clause><clause id="HF678BC3B04444FA3ACC9B5065D2C4987"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be available to the Secretary for carrying out the purposes of this section, to reduce the need for further appropriations for those purposes; and</text></clause><clause id="HB966C39712414578BEE15B08BE2DDD39"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>remain available until expended.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B75A0EF196344919D3E6CEC7CD0FAB8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revolving fund</header><text>There is established in the Treasury an account into which the revenues described in subparagraph (A) shall be—</text><clause id="H04348B12C8B84522BD697B99A2FC4BA5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>deposited in accordance with clause (i) of that subparagraph; and </text></clause><clause id="H7C4AC380E4F242BB972ABE81D443FC90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>made available in accordance with clauses (ii) and (iii) of that subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A5761E052924E21A5BDCCCD50BC78D0"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Nuclear regulatory commission</header><text>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission shall prioritize and expedite consideration of any action related to the Programs to the extent permitted under the <act-name parsable-cite="AEA54">Atomic Energy Act of 1954</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2011">42 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>) and related statutes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0898A0ED9D7C46F3B3F6B5B00AC0AECE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>USEC Privatization Act</header><text>The requirements of section 3112(d)(2) of the USEC Privatization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2297h-10">42 U.S.C. 2297h–10(d)(2)</external-xref>) shall not apply to activities related to the Programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAC9D350EFB5C48B5A58405E4477C9EDD"><enum>(l)</enum><header>National security needs</header><text>The Secretary shall only make available to a member of the consortium under this section for commercial use or use in a demonstration project material that the President has determined is not necessary for national security needs, subject to the condition that the material made available shall not include any material that the Secretary determines to be necessary for the National Nuclear Security Administration or any critical mission of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC412A0B3DF67415BB93D6E544921135B"><enum>(m)</enum><header>International agreements</header><text>This section shall be applied in a manner consistent with the obligations of the United States under international agreements.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

