<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H94C0279C26DB45D9A163A5620AF6AC42" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3674 IH: Providing Relief and Stability for Medicare Patients Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3674</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to increase the nonfacility practice expense relative value units for specified services furnished under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H151A20EC482A4DB7AB19DFB0A3EB4ED9" style="OLC"><section id="HBC6DBFC1DE6B4F19B4A2C1387EA8AB89" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providing Relief and Stability for Medicare Patients Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB9E2B4E0053C445E91DC78E16AA4C876"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increasing the nonfacility practice expense relative value units for specified services furnished under the Medicare program</header><subsection id="H63888298781D40AD8FCC1C54BB241236"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H63331F8D40EA479483F0CEDF2F819EA7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H079C4B9C57FB4B3098A84CA74B26BFAB"><enum>(P)</enum><header>Increase of nonfacility practice expense relative value units for specified services</header><clause id="HA9E5128CF5834C768662D81F5FE58F37"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall increase the nonfacility practice expense relative value units applied to a specified service (as defined in clause (ii)) furnished in—</text><subclause id="HE219B1357B6745BA89CDFCED43C9299F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>2024, by 10 percent of the number of nonfacility practice expense relative value units that would otherwise apply to such service furnished in such year without application of this clause; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC8289F4952A4444FAF0205F67401ADD7"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2025, by 15 percent of the number of nonfacility practice expense relative value units that would otherwise apply to such service furnished in such year without application of this clause.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCF93D487021E4899AF863D5D6D0EE5A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Specified service defined</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>specified service</quote> means, with respect to a service furnished in a year, a service with a nonfacility practice expense relative value unit that was calculated for such year (without application of this subparagraph) based on 65 percent or more of the service’s direct practice expense cost being attributed to equipment and supply costs.</text></clause><clause id="H7566BE3FE6D644C5B88866F074584E29"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be transferred from the General Fund of the Treasury to the Federal Supplementary Medical Insurance Trust Fund under section 1841 such sums as the Secretary determines are necessary for purposes of increasing payment amounts pursuant to this subparagraph, to remain available until expended.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4D4B0BDD9FF2414BAE87D718C21EFE53" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nonapplication of budget neutrality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1848(c)(2)(B)(iv) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(c)(2)(B)(iv)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE7A5C11C7DD749E28CDDE05C486F177D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subclause (IV), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F20D4EFC8A446FBA3BD02D730960F00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subclause (V), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95E7243C347542429B511CF493E87E8A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDE8C8B0FBE345E99EF7A2C3E92ED168"><subclause id="H4390B28B150A42BCA1D88A34583B371E"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subparagraph (P) shall not be taken into account in applying clause (ii)(II).</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F739D6E772641A2BAE8C1500229A6CA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the Medicare physician fee schedule and patient access, including—</text><paragraph id="H8F05F92B1E714B3293A391591AECF680"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of the number of health care providers furnishing specified services (as defined in section 1848(c)(2)(P) of the Social Security Act, as added by subsection (a)) in a nonfacility setting under the Medicare program over the 20 year period ending on such date of enactment, including a description of any changes in volume of such services furnished under such program and the availability of such services under such program and a description of wait-times, decreased hours, other factors that could impede a patient’s access to such services (such as increased cost sharing);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78FD64BD28C34F6DB8BB797C1114199A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of any change in the proportion of services payable under such schedule furnished in nonfacility settings compared to the proportion of such services furnished at other sites of service over such period, including an analysis of the impact of any such change on health system consolidation, underserved and rural populations, quality of care of Medicare beneficiaries, and increased cost to the Medicare program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB400E252E86647C489C500B7EF3B133C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of whether significant annual changes in provider reimbursement are a cause of any change described in paragraph (2), disruptions in patient access to services, and increased cost sharing; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE604AD8507394461BBEB3EFE68923E54"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">taking into account the analyses described in paragraphs (1) through (3), recommendations for improving Medicare patient access to specified services (as defined in section 1848(c)(2)(P) of the Social Security Act, as added by subsection (a)) and minimizing health system consolidation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

