<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H00AD2BC641884E31A70EF07D25A9E5B5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5878 IH: Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5878</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFCC709F71F564BFAA5A4430A78361B0A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2DDE561B198D49B89E41A8FC787DC2CB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H314EC6858DE64D7C8A4047CB372875DA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2628D5FE9CE44492A6D05E1DDEE5384E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the town of Quindaro was founded in 1857, in the Territory of Kansas, with the specific intent of aiding the Free-State movement in the struggle over whether to admit Kansas to the Union as a free State or a slave State;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BFAD9B2BFDD4B4B915F7A296CA8392E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as a result of the circumstances described in paragraph (1), the town of Quindaro played an important role in the history of Kansas and the broader debate over slavery in the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCCF7CE9EE10448594A81F523B8206B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the town of Quindaro was a key site during the conflict, known as the <quote>Bleeding Kansas</quote> conflict, serving as a safe port of entry into Kansas on the Missouri River for people opposed to slavery;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9F2F2996C35645C38777634053FA3F13"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the town of Quindaro also acted as an important piece of the Underground Railroad, allowing runaway slaves to escape to freedom in Kansas;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EA030D554DF4551BDF1FE1683D945B4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>since the first excavation of the Quindaro Townsite, the area has yielded a wealth of important artifacts that have contributed to the understanding of the town and the place of the town in history;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF838ECFD90EE470EBCCB48188D35DC04"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Quindaro Townsite maintains a high level of archaeological integrity, with the potential for additional discoveries at the townsite in the future;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF542D3C1E4D4AABA8219ACD2FAF8C46"><enum>(7)</enum><text>local government, private entities, and individual stakeholders in the area have invested time and resources to further the preservation of the physical remains of the town and the historical and cultural legacy of the town; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H855DD2813F9C433BBEC5AE465A0B4555"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Quindaro Townsite fits the requirements for National Historic Landmark designation of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2519CC1FE4F14894B06D15592FE1F369"><enum>(A)</enum><text>possessing exceptional value in illustrating the history of the United States; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA4DBFDA2F3B744A39D56C08012EA9EC2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing the potential to yield new information about the history of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HDC546467C2E94D289A9C7E01937A4847"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H323EA3BF43674EE2870AC6A6D82B64DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Landmark</header><text>The term <term>Landmark</term> means the Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark designated by section 4(a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDAB436F4220942FAAE35962D4B0C8A78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD726D6216A848E996AB488B4A35CDBE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means the State of Kansas.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H37C25B1DD8FF4015B5B5F7ADE3AF592D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark</header> 
<subsection id="H624694E771A3484EB6DDDDE8B9B201A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The Quindaro Townsite in Kansas City, Kansas, as listed on the National Register of Historic Places, is designated as the <quote>Quindaro Townsite National Historic Landmark</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4C261566133D4559B5201FB02F441AB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header> <paragraph id="HA7EAECE0DD8E4510888EB9CAD51593BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the State, Kansas City, Kansas, and affected subdivisions of the State, may enter into cooperative agreements with appropriate public or private entities, for the purposes of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H20D71445BCC4493995983B3A4F9C1E12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>protecting historic resources at the Landmark; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC708A06B18B436D8056BC82FE5F387D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing educational and interpretive facilities and programs at the Landmark for the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE64F737A4D3443189FECEF52D9C47F44"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical and financial assistance</header><text>The Secretary may provide technical and financial assistance to any entity with which the Secretary has entered into a cooperative agreement under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA528C3B5E65E409A909825768517C06E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No effect on actions of property owners</header><text>Designation of the Quindaro Townsite as a National Historic Landmark shall not prohibit any actions that may otherwise be taken by a property owner (including any owner of the Landmark) with respect to the property of the owner.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD1E5C47D440E431CA3DF91A3EB980A50"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No effect on administration</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the administration of the Landmark by Kansas City, Kansas, or the State.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

