<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7F910122DBCC4488B78ADBC7B59DDADF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2875 IH: Grid Reliability and Resiliency Improvements Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2875</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the North American Electric Reliability Corporation, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, Regional Transmission Organizations, and Independent System Operators, to submit a report to Congress on the reliability of the electric grid.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H478C97382169452FB12D9E17622C91D1" style="OLC"><section id="H151D58352CEC4CF48ED52B095F68154A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grid Reliability and Resiliency Improvements Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H944FC92E4546488CB5C62FC5B9188D92"><enum>2.</enum><header>Identifying and preventing risks to the long term reliability of electric grid and electricity generation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and every two years thereafter, the Electric Reliability Organization (as defined in section 215(a)(2) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824o">16 U.S.C. 824o(a)(2)</external-xref>)), in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, Regional Transmission Organizations, and Independent System Operators, shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that—</text><paragraph id="H996314851B4F4CC9938B83CA47801860"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies State and Federal policies that affect, or could affect, the retirement of facilities that generate electricity, including retirement of such facilities that may occur because the costs of compliance with such policies economically disadvantages such facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89EAEDFF4B6F46E5859612A4EFFA2CF4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describes the impact of electric utility-level environmental, social, and governance (ESG) commitments and policies on electric grid reliability and whether such commitments and policies contribute to the retirement of facilities that generate electricity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD9708FDE3CC4575A7D9A3B3FCCC8F99"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies the estimated number of facilities that generate electricity in the United States that will be retired, per calendar year, until 2030;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0F15E2D15C046DB9598A69A0D7BFC10" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>describes the estimated increase in demand for electricity until calendar year 2030, taking into consideration State and Federal economy-wide electrification efforts, and whether the estimated level of new electricity generation that will connect to the bulk-power system, including facilities and control facilities and control systems necessary for operating an interconnected electricity transmission network and electricity from generation facilities needed to maintain transmission system reliability, will meet such estimated increase in demand for electricity by calendar year 2030;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1040295B1D4B4BF3A5677B78BD332561" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">outlines whether the current pace of facilities that generate electricity from non-dispatchable variable energy resources connecting to the bulk-power system is sufficient—</text><subparagraph id="H689C8628243A415DB26B426C6B61661C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to exceed the pace of retirement of facilities that generate electricity from dispatchable, firm, or flexible resources; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7151B98ABBE346B799D3366C1270D4F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to meet the estimated increase in demand for electricity by calendar year 2030;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H56542970FFE94BDA9043DAE319E1949F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides recommendations to improve the reliability of the electric grid and to ensure that electricity generation can meet estimated demand for electricity by calendar year 2030, as well as anticipated reserve margins;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECD8A4D719DA4383BAC1B2399704313C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>identifies whether increased electricity generation from natural gas and increased natural gas transportation is essential to the reliability of the electric grid by calendar year 2030 and the importance of natural gas for electricity generation as a balancing, flexible resource; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D1C9295DF24DAC992736E6D11D7F8B" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>quantifies the benefits of generation of electricity using flexible resources that can dispatch on demand, are able to counter variations in electricity generation and demand, and balance generation of electricity using intermittent and non-dispatchable resources. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

