<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H89F510F677204DB6813173622F4F488E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5998 IH: America’s College Promise Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5998</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231019">October 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000273">Ms. Leger Fernandez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to establish grants for tuition-free community colleges, student success grants, and grants for Historically Black Colleges and Universities, Tribal Colleges and Universities, and Minority-Serving Institutions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5E6FE18FD3DC406CA7629675EE987B24" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H544C4193A9D043D7A1D5B1D3EFE2E421"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>America’s College Promise Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><title id="H5549334C804F4151A7CFF8DD76CD2057"><enum>I</enum><header>Grants for tuition-free community colleges</header><section id="H8817BDC46F2D4CF29B2D311DF7D67697"><enum>101.</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H242EF45473464B56BCA9DDE21CDFCC3F"><part id="HFEA58358EB74459BADAC286E05F1D04F"><enum>J</enum><header>America’s college promise Federal-State partnership</header><subpart id="H9E7A1E7258DC486CA63996253E9774E7"><enum>1</enum><header>Grants for tuition-free community college</header><section id="HF5C44591787D41E895DB997710EB2950"><enum>499A.</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 499G for any fiscal year, the Secretary shall award grants to eligible States and eligible Tribal Colleges and Universities to pay the Federal share of expenditures needed to carry out the activities and services described in section 499E.</text></section><section id="HAF64879B8324416ABA4AA3F8862915A4"><enum>499B.</enum><header>Federal share; non-Federal share</header><subsection id="H3D49AC4C41574EB192563B32B18DB41D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal share</header><paragraph id="H2AEE0DD03E8C45E08CC7BDE8BACA1C30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="H223B89148F67418E824B7643F04883B8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the amount of the Federal share of a grant under this subpart shall be based on a formula, determined by the Secretary, that provides, for each eligible student enrolled in a community college operated or controlled by the State or in an eligible Tribal College or University, a per-student amount that is equal to the applicable percent described in subparagraph (B) of—</text><clause id="H52FE017204EA42D9916EAB358247BAF0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the 2024–2025 award year, the average unweighted resident community college tuition and fees per student in all States for the most recent year for which data are available; and</text></clause><clause id="HF2F5332BC17D48518794CE4DA59708E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each subsequent award year, the amount determined under this paragraph for the preceding award year, increased by the lesser of—</text><subclause id="HD85C6D2C2FD14DFE9334F1755743FC4C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a percentage equal to the estimated percentage increase in the Consumer Price Index (as determined by the Secretary) since the date of such determination; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H3C683FB92BF641AAA4FB5BD5C0736049"><enum>(II)</enum><text>3 percent.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9EB33B082A147FB945170C7DFEE615A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicable percent</header><text>The applicable percent for a State receiving a grant under this subpart shall be—</text><clause id="H4A8EF01F4C4D414F984380DF3172E2DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the 2024–2025 award year, 100 percent;</text></clause><clause id="H87593C67D9364A6D8D3050CCB41B1F81"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for the 2025–2026 award year, 95 percent;</text></clause><clause id="HBE4B35260A254ADB8D9A0DFAA3AF11AF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for the 2026–2027 award year, 90 percent;</text></clause><clause id="H98182A52BC054384B5B3071F3CC76E39"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>for the 2027–2028 award year, 85 percent; and</text></clause><clause id="HCB24AB158BB74FE2B0F76CD88BD1390E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for the 2028–2029 award year and each subsequent award year, 80 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D10A893F20C4BCBA435AADEB29E6686"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tribal colleges and universities</header><text>The amount of the Federal share for an eligible Tribal College or University receiving a grant under this subpart shall be the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="H7B73431AA6544BBDB08DB712AABCB9D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>100 percent of the per-student amount determined in accordance with clause (i) or (ii) of paragraph (1)(A), as applicable, with respect to eligible students enrolled in such eligible Tribal College or University (based on full-time equivalent enrollment); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AD00A4F45A7470584231DD91D67537E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount that is 100 percent of the total amount needed to set tuition and fees to $0 for all eligible students enrolled in such eligible Tribal College or University for the 2023–2024 award year, increased by the percentage increase in the Consumer Price Index (as determined by the Secretary) between July 1, 2023, and the applicable award year, and adjusted to reflect the enrollment in such eligible Tribal College or University for such applicable award year. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5244143C28CB4E04B93DC403AC213998"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State share</header><paragraph id="H7EF0021652BE49CA89B4C0E3129548BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Formula</header><subparagraph id="H39989E4233B542D5B5C011B69E1AB012"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the State share of a grant under this subpart for each fiscal year shall be the amount needed to pay the applicable percent described in subparagraph (B) of the average unweighted resident community college tuition and fees per student in the 2024–2025 award year for all eligible students in the State for such award year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED6E8B1F958244F289F4844F1B12D096"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicable percent</header><text>The applicable percentage shall be—</text><clause id="HBB19FDD149CD492C90DE11BE27700324"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the 2024–2025 award year, 0 percent;</text></clause><clause id="H834022C941604FDCB94CCF691F8F6795"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for the 2025–2026 award year, 5 percent;</text></clause><clause id="H77245CF79C0D4B77BF72D40D78161D26"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for the 2026–2027 award year, 10 percent;</text></clause><clause id="H5FC302A560BA4A55BD030D0B1478E0AE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>for the 2027–2028 award year, 15 percent; and</text></clause><clause id="HA8933870B68545429DD27706998FE008"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for the 2028–2029 award year and each subsequent award year, 20 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7FFB2D3D9AB4E44B9C87BD25E154D86"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Obligation to provide share</header><text>The State shall provide the State share even if the State is able to set tuition and fees charged to eligible students attending community colleges operated or controlled by the State to $0 as required by section 499D without such State share.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22E21BF6E29246CDB70694DB8973178D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>No double counting funds</header><text>No funds that count toward the maintenance of effort requirement under section 499D(c) may also count toward the State share under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73683220BD1A42C7A9990563373479F3"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Special rule for outlying areas and territories</header><clause id="H2B89C93C392D4CB6820CD969EB1C028E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines that requiring an outlying area or territory to provide a State share in accordance with this subsection would represent a substantial hardship for the outlying area or territory, the Secretary shall reduce or waive the State share for such area or territory. If the Secretary so reduces or waives the amount of the State share of an outlying area or territory, the Secretary shall increase the applicable percent used to calculate the Federal share for such area or territory, in proportion to the reduction in the applicable percent used to calculate such State share.</text></clause><clause id="HFE686A7976C248DC9596CD7A6BBECCC8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For the purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>outlying area or territory</term> means the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the District of Columbia, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and the Freely Associated States.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E328099D44B4A88B81028419A52DE2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of State financial aid and local funds</header><text>In the case of a State that demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Secretary that community colleges operated or controlled by such State will not experience a net reduction in total per-student revenue (including revenue derived from tuition and fees) as compared to the preceding State fiscal year in such State, a State may include, as part of the State share—</text><subparagraph id="HDF134E0E87774534A8A4C43DABB95A34"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any financial aid that is provided from State funds to eligible students for such students’ cost of attendance that is not awarded predominantly on the basis of merit; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFB5CDF42B0B4069B901742BBDC84380"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any funds provided to community colleges by local governments in such State for the purpose of carrying out this subpart, including for the purpose of setting community college tuition and fees for eligible students to $0 as required under section 499D.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DE83E87D20C4BDDB26103BC570D7B45"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relationship to maintenance of effort</header><text>The inclusion of funds described in paragraph (2) as part of a State’s share shall modify the maintenance of effort requirements under section 499D(c) in accordance with the provisions of—</text><subparagraph id="HC590EA5730894F8EAF6FF882B9D63B20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 499H(12)(B)(iii) with respect to funds included under paragraph (2)(A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5F350DD1E6944888DE7FD67448384F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 499H(12)(B)(ii), with respect to funds included under paragraph (2)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA66D1A357BC14874BE8CAC701CFDE8D3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>No in-kind contributions</header><text>A State shall not include in-kind contributions for purposes of the State share described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD6770BF1A52C4C61B7F84FFC2D1DFCA3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determining number of eligible students</header><paragraph id="HFC9846E933BF447CAC457A9465082BBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a) and subsection (b), the Secretary shall develop and implement a formula for accurately estimating the number of eligible students and for making adjustments based on the number of eligible students enrolled in the community colleges operated or controlled by a State or in an eligible Tribal College or University on less than a full-time basis and the associated tuition and fees charged to such students in proportion to the degree to which each such student is not attending on a full-time basis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC6225B5392F447FBA1E48BDA6B889D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial determination</header><text>For the first year for which grants are awarded under this subpart, the number of eligible students in a State or eligible Tribal College or University shall be considered to be equal to the number of eligible students who were in the State or eligible Tribal College or University for the preceding school year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4469285EB8164A6B85EFF12CF93676FB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Adjustment of grant amount</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which a State or eligible Tribal College or University receives a grant under this subpart, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H1128C13918264AF49C48A2C8A171149B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in consultation with the State or eligible Tribal College or University concerned, determine whether the actual number of eligible students in the State or eligible Tribal College or University for the year covered by the grant is greater than the estimated number of such students that was used to determine the amount of the grant; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7029371CAFA3445CA3C9DA04BCC19025"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a determination under paragraph (1) that the actual number of eligible students in the State or eligible Tribal College or University is higher than such estimate, issue a supplementary grant payment to the State or eligible Tribal College or University in an amount that ensures that the total amount of the grant funds received by the State or eligible Tribal College or University under this subpart for the year covered by the grant accurately reflects the higher number of eligible students.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0AF2EED6359D447AB7DE4A0CCB8FB573"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Community colleges operated or controlled by State To include community colleges operated or controlled by local governments within the State</header><text>For purposes of this subpart, the term <term>community college operated or controlled by a State</term> shall include a community college operated or controlled by a local government within such State.</text></subsection><subsection id="H371464C7AD6A45F780511FF182837624"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inapplicability of State requirements to eligible TCUs</header><text>The Secretary may not apply any requirements applicable only to States under this subpart to an eligible Tribal College or University, including the requirements under subsection (b) and subsection (b) and (c) of section 499D. </text></subsection></section><section id="HAB87F4F5F26143508D1773240DBAE764"><enum>499C.</enum><header>Applications</header><subsection id="H399FB077C65A49DDB86724A8DD6E7CA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>In order to receive a grant under this subpart, a State or an eligible Tribal College or University shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9BC33A9FAD444EF5A792506EC9737965"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each application under subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H278A2FF3FAD4471FB77DEA4298E6079F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an estimate of the number of eligible students enrolled in the community colleges operated or controlled by the State or in the eligible Tribal College or University and the cost of waiving community college tuition and fees for all eligible students for each award year covered by the grant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF98B4917EA324392A6689AAC042F1471"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a State, a list of each of the community colleges operated or controlled by the State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7AA09F07F27489788C784E47D0387C5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an assurance that each community college operated or controlled by the State, or the eligible Tribal College or University, as applicable, will set community college tuition and fees for eligible students to $0 as required by section 499D(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A417C69AB7F455A98F3846C166DA4F8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of the promising and evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices to improve student outcomes, including transfer and completion rates, that have been or will be adopted by each such community college, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H755D90CC8C2249A7B664AC64E97D5B0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing comprehensive academic, career, and student support services (including mentoring, advising, case management services, and career pathway navigation), especially for low-income, first-generation, and adult students, and other students belonging to racial and other groups that are historically underrepresented in higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H179648B1BBE54285836D044F9D9D3D9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing direct support services, or assistance in applying for such services, such as—</text><clause id="HD353A5F1DDF941269B67CF45314E8349"><enum>(i)</enum><text>childcare, transportation, and emergency financial assistance;</text></clause><clause id="H246A8A12803E416C9B814AF8EF29446C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assistance in obtaining health insurance coverage and accessing health care services, including behavioral and mental health services;</text></clause><clause id="H024E1B28B67C4DF498F1BAE029574950"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>affordable housing;</text></clause><clause id="H9B9EE817638141C19F50F1BB913010A8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>nutrition assistance programs or free or discounted food; and</text></clause><clause id="H4ACDD6D5A0FB4C32814F7E0B532FDBCD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>means-tested Federal benefit programs, or similar State, tribal, or local benefit programs;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C9FD7C18B924D18A6BF6863988F811B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing accelerated learning opportunities, such as dual or concurrent enrollment programs, including early college high school programs, and reforming course scheduling and credit awarding policies to better meet the needs of students and shorten time to completion;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9018ABD575024154B0C238C5A61D5612"><enum>(D)</enum><text>strengthening and reforming remedial and developmental education, especially for low-income, first-generation, and adult students, and other students belonging to racial and other groups that are historically underrepresented in higher education, including through the use of multiple measures (such as a student’s college entrance examination score, grade point average, high school course list, or a placement examination) to identify students in need of remedial education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA01F16DD42EE403FBCF9B4020AFD6AD1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>utilizing career pathways, including through building capacity for career and technical education, as defined in section 3(5) of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302(5)</external-xref>), and programs of study, as defined in section 3(41) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302(41)</external-xref>), or degree pathways; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6952DB88884C46C58EFA0B164574E286"><enum>(F)</enum><text>providing expanded opportunities for participating in work-based learning, which may include apprenticeship programs, in students’ programs of study;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0685BC3142F14130B944AE5164BAAABE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a description of how the State or eligible Tribal College or University will ensure that programs leading to a recognized postsecondary credential meet the quality criteria established by the State under section 122(b)(1) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3152">29 U.S.C. 3152(b)(1)</external-xref>) or other quality criteria determined appropriate by the State or eligible Tribal College or University;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2C4D160881F47A2AECEFDF7295C1D92"><enum>(6)</enum><text>an assurance that each community college operated or controlled by the State or the eligible Tribal College or University, as applicable, has entered into a program participation agreement under section 487;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H509540884102453B8DE91C2F73BF9CA9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an assurance that the State or eligible Tribal College or University will assist eligible students in obtaining information about and accessing means-tested Federal benefit programs and similar, State, tribal, and local benefit programs that can provide financial assistance for any component of the student’s cost of attendance, as defined under section 472, other than tuition and fees;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CF672E9756A40A1A63E2390F816E989"><enum>(8)</enum><text>an assurance that, for each year of the grant, the State or eligible Tribal College or University will notify each eligible student of the student’s remaining eligibility for assistance under this subpart;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C53E80CFCBA4458B597A90BCC855BF9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>if the application is submitted by a State—</text><subparagraph id="HE30E2106B9164145BF4BFFA31994BE3D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the State will support the scaling and increased adoption of the reforms and practices described in paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0148443571D84EAF9C00D062160656BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assurance that the State will, to the extent practicable, consider changes to State law that will enable more community college students to be eligible for means-tested Federal benefit programs and similar State benefit programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF62EA6EF4EA14E3CB32B5930EAE95491"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assurance that the State will meet the requirements of section 499D(b)(1) relating to the alignment of secondary and postsecondary education; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6D79D9B79CB46E9AB487075DD2F4783"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an assurance that the State will meet the requirements of section 499D(b)(2) relating to the improvement of transfer pathways between institutions of higher education; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45DC4947A9F64F28A1825EC18637714E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>an assurance that the State or eligible Tribal College or University will clearly communicate to prospective students, including students with prior college experience who have not completed a postsecondary degree or credential, their families, and the general public—</text><subparagraph id="H33C43F35CF7246ED8694B720B48E0A3B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>plans to implement the program funded under this subpart; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5281C98E7EA4BF98538FB0D20C91450"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how eligible students can attend a community college operated or controlled by the State or eligible Tribal College or University without paying tuition and fees. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA7E262CBC4AB4C98B0B9CAF25DECF9AB"><enum>499D.</enum><header>Program requirements</header><subsection id="HFC12F5ECA855493EA76848908E5508DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General requirements</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this subpart, a State or eligible Tribal College or University shall meet the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H2627C5B7F7AF4402AAB2AE0122A265D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Ensure that the total amount of tuition and fees charged to an eligible student in the State or the eligible Tribal College or University shall be $0.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45106988C4184534B5270113658117C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For each year of the grant no amount of financial assistance for which an eligible student qualifies may be applied to such tuition or fees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0310145C56543A3B7609DCD6F6BE11A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The State or eligible Tribal College or University may not use any funds provided under this subpart for administrative purposes relating to such grant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H34A1962CEB9E4CCC9499A2525AF5EA67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State requirements</header><text>In addition to the requirements under subsection (a), as a condition of receiving a grant under this subpart, a State shall meet the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="HEE54A878EB5849979071F80BA128CAA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alignment of K-12 and higher education</header><subparagraph id="H4AFE10D9C4E04F658DAC13A44D9A3177"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The State shall—</text><clause id="H1E8030F780254D03BB44E2216EE0DDCB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit a plan to align the requirements for receiving a regular high school diploma from public schools in the State with the requirements for entering credit-bearing coursework at community colleges in such State; and</text></clause><clause id="HED873F988F7B4F72A917C57068CE16E8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 3 years after the date on which the State first receives a grant under this subpart, certify to the Secretary that such alignment has been achieved.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD27F0E3D24E84014AE8CB395C59A22A4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Failure to certify</header><text>If a State does not provide the certification required under subparagraph (A) by the date specified in such subparagraph, the State shall submit to the Secretary, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require—</text><clause id="H5A9105ADDF5A4DFDACC5EE2AA5FF202C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a written explanation for the delay in making the certification; and</text></clause><clause id="HA2B1AFBD93D8452DA23933AFF4363699"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a plan that will enable the State to make the certification by not later than 5 years after the date on which the State first received a grant under this subpart.\art.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD80DED83812F48D280E1F106F8432563"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer pathways</header><subparagraph id="H9F94FCAE74114A0893229931408B94D4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The State shall—</text><clause id="H05F673011B614A078CC030B4B164754A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit a plan, developed in collaboration with faculty from institutions of higher education in the State, to improve transfer pathways between institutions of higher education in the State, including by—</text><subclause id="H232CB7FCD59348688F01D21879A82D7D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>ensuring that associate degrees awarded by community colleges in the State are fully transferable to, and credited as, the first 2 years of related baccalaureate programs at public institutions of higher education in such State; </text></subclause><subclause id="HB0873285947D413680FB027214CB7CA1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>increasing the transferability of individual courses within the certificate or associate programs offered by community colleges in the State to related baccalaureate programs offered by institutions of higher education in such State to maximize the transferability of credits for students who transfer before completing an associate degree;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7ABC3A7ED9D74E96BBC312ECBA9FAFAD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>expanding the use of reverse transfer policies that allow institutions to—</text><item id="HDE1ACBBC32F1457B93A8E547A4663C1F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>implement the process of retroactively granting a certificate or associate degree to students who had not completed the requirements for such certificate or degree before they transferred; and</text></item><item id="HEBB70ACB045440608B67498D58EEC420"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>allow academic credits for coursework completed at a 4-year institution to be applied to a previously attended community college for the purpose of obtaining an associate degree or a certificate; and </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4AB4DD9A2F8949B1A130033DA37D28AD"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>ensuring that students attending community colleges in the State have access to comprehensive counseling regarding the process for transferring to a 4-year institution of higher education; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBB68605FD3B5469DAD43D6F1C35D5CA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 3 years after the date on which the State first receives a grant under this subpart, certify to the Secretary that the State is carrying out the plan submitted in accordance with clause (i) and is meeting the requirements of subclauses (I) through (IV) of such clause.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1616B8983A5146A79FBDF728E6BA5F01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Failure to certify</header><text>If a State does not provide the certification required under subparagraph (A) by the date specified in such subparagraph, the State shall submit to the Secretary, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require—</text><clause id="H94DD27369663424C90029D0037F4C108"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a written explanation for the delay in making the certification; and</text></clause><clause id="H54D5EF5C4ED64A36AD0A4F6DAFC54D03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a plan that will enable the State to make the certification by not later than 5 years after the date on which the State first received a grant under this subpart.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4427D830A2D447388C6EB99CB73D6E08"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The Secretary may not apply the requirements under this subsection to an eligible Tribal College or University.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D209F48EEC446B386948AB6CD47D9D1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State maintenance of effort</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State receiving a grant under this subpart shall be entitled to receive its full allotment of funds under this subpart for a fiscal year only if, for each year of the grant, the State provides—</text><paragraph id="HE2DC76D1537949EF851744A5EACB3207"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State fiscal support for higher education per full-time equivalent student at a level equal to or exceeding the average amount of State fiscal support for higher education per full-time equivalent student provided for the 3 consecutive preceding fiscal years;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58AE35A953E94BB4AA3BB981EB32FE5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>financial support for operating expenses (excluding capital expenses and research and development costs) for public 4-year institutions of higher education at a level equal to or exceeding the average amount provided for the 3 consecutive preceding State fiscal years; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEC84F13C7594A548DF14B1FF79EAC44"><enum>(3)</enum><text>financial support for need-based financial aid at a level equal to or exceeding the average amount provided for the 3 consecutive preceding State fiscal years. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE0D7E53774A4FC9A67EC3514AC31E1C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No additional eligibility requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or eligible Tribal College or University that receives a grant under this subpart may not impose additional eligibility requirements on eligible students other than the requirements under this subpart.</text></subsection><subsection id="H49CC2D7CB65F4249AD72DD7397DF891B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligibility for benefits</header><text>No individual shall be determined to be ineligible to receive benefits provided under this subpart (including tuition and fees set to $0 and other aid provided under this subpart) on the basis of citizenship, alienage, or immigration status. </text></subsection></section><section id="H4A410C7D92C346EC94FC20A580185272"><enum>499E.</enum><header>Allowable uses of funds</header><subsection id="H341EE83DD33A438783C4D023394505A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), a State or eligible Tribal College or University shall use a grant under this subpart only to ensure that the total amount of tuition and fees charged to an eligible student in the State or the eligible Tribal College or University shall be $0.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8F770169223F4F59B0403E27FF4A87D9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional uses</header><text>If a State or an eligible Tribal College or University demonstrates to the Secretary that the State or eligible Tribal College or University has grant funds remaining after meeting the demand for activities described in subsection (a), the State or eligible Tribal College or University may use those funds to carry out 1 or more of the following:</text><paragraph id="H16A0C782D1474F3BA45FFAE399C56CEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Providing need-based financial aid to students that may be used by such students to pay any component of cost of attendance, as defined under section 472.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4726D4CC8C924DF7A7EFA43F6D943AEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Improving student outcomes by implementing evidence-based institutional reforms or practices. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70C3606425F54B07B02347D393EE359F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Enhancing the quality and equity of public higher education to improve student outcomes, including transfer and completion rates and labor market outcomes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DDEA170CE3A47CB890F73C176FEC3EC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Investing in and diversifying the academic workforce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66B08088C9B146EE95D2EBD13FE2700F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Expanding the scope and capacity of high-quality academic and occupational skills training programs at community colleges, which may include collaboration with one or more industry or sector partnerships (as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3201">29 U.S.C. 3201</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2803C70F5244B938B50B57723B753E6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Improving postsecondary education readiness in the State, including through outreach and early intervention.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9380C6DFEF645FE97938DF142589ED0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Expanding access to dual or concurrent enrollment programs, such as early college high school programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4EA7224EE3A47478016D687CE4FBB77"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Reducing unmet need at public 4-year institutions of higher education.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A917779A1C144C691505251829D9936"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds for administrative purposes</header><text>A State or Tribal College or University that receives a grant under this subpart may not use any funds provided under this subpart for administrative purposes relating to such grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD5568CE383CE4862A6C509474CA1E10F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available under this subpart shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, tribal, and local funds that would otherwise be expended to carry out activities described in this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBD72A6BBB6C04F8490E469D741A06C60"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report requirements</header><paragraph id="HBAC4E3F4A4AF4A50876E5B49C70861AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reporting by States</header><text>A State receiving a grant under this subpart shall submit to the Secretary an annual report that shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H858B1BB5B9684EE5BDE3116D5727B825"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the uses of grant funds under this subpart;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A3B0BB469ED46F18D49359278492EE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the progress made in fulfilling the requirements of the grant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AB7AD30F57E4A489F7FDA5AE656D583"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the rates of transfer, graduation, and attainment of recognized postsecondary credentials at participating community colleges, disaggregated by race, income, and age; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H327932B31BEC4A319ED33FB173AC5149"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H19EB44D21ACF4E9486FAE2C2E525FCFA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting by Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall, on an annual basis—</text><subparagraph id="H152F4974F6564BFB9C58D5942CA2B5EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>compile and analyze the information described in paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6BC2F51CE044F689E5B362BFB042993"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prepare and submit to the authorizing committees a report containing—</text><clause id="HB9FC6B9BFDFB4D388E1D53CC7D54CF69"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the analysis described in subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H839B4E8B66FB4BA7A06A6DD940E7E6DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an identification of State and best practices for achieving the purpose of this subpart.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3518F576145641129C3F280485F8213D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide technical assistance to States and eligible Tribal Colleges and Universities concerning best practices regarding the promising and evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices to improve student outcomes and shall disseminate such best practices among such entities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C4C90BE53FF4C0AA1F747D0358A971B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Continuation of funding</header><paragraph id="HCE9625D758584D618FC107C6DFA3398D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), a State or an eligible Tribal College or University receiving a grant under this subpart for a fiscal year may continue to receive funding under this subpart for future fiscal years conditioned on the availability of budget authority and on meeting the requirements of the grant, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF258B6B79E04932A37906F02241B7D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Discontinuation</header><text>The Secretary may discontinue funding of the Federal share of a grant under this subpart if the State or eligible Tribal College or University has violated the terms of the grant or is not making adequate progress in implementing the reforms described in the application submitted under section 499C.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BE190516D7F46A68A80F4B778C884B6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding BIE funds</header><text>Nothing in this subpart shall be construed to impact the availability of funds from, or uses of funds provided by, the Bureau of Indian Education for Tribal Colleges and Universities.</text></subsection></section><section id="H60EF22390733459FA3422DA7F76BFC20"><enum>499F.</enum><header>Automatic stabilizers for America’s College Promise</header><subsection id="HF907416CE62F40B990D28DE97F87A875"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort relief</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (c) of section 499D, a State that meets the qualifying spending requirements may request a waiver of the requirements under such subsection (c). The Secretary shall waive the requirements of such subsection (c) for a State that makes a qualifying request under this subsection as follows:</text><paragraph id="HBC3670B4F86542A79063A921A0B364EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Tier I</header><text>With respect to each State eligible for relief under tier I, such requirements shall be waived for the fiscal year succeeding the fiscal year in which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47BB1BC615D549AA89E813C0B758D431"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tiers II through V</header><text>With respect to each State eligible for relief under tier II, III, IV, or V, such requirements shall be waived, in accordance with subsection (d), for—</text><subparagraph id="H087FDAC48EC5444FAE57936A63391300"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the fiscal year in which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H269FCEAFF45745CEA7EF5E40D02D1A2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fiscal year succeeding the fiscal year described in subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0716A31673BA4E289570060400E38CE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>both such fiscal years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H495B31820C0149AB991BD002BCA93CF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State share relief</header><paragraph id="HB6A5E4C03C56427A8D09A194CB8CA46E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State match relief</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b) of section 499B, a State that is eligible for relief under tier II, III, IV, or V may request relief with respect to the requirements of such subsection (b). The Secretary shall provide relief from the requirements of such subsection (b), for the applicable fiscal year or years, for a State that makes a qualifying request under this paragraph as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H36F0D2C0879C4890BFDD49E4512B2C91"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Tier II</header><text>With respect to a State that is eligible for relief under tier II, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H1A072E1972AE44B188886166270631A7" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>85 percent</quote> for <quote>80 percent</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H9A08AF6FB1CC4C8B98ABDDD4595E58B8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>15 percent</quote> for <quote>20 percent</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4094136AC6AC40DD86FC887875F6C11D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Tier III</header><text>With respect to a State that is eligible for relief under tier III, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H6C43627EDA914C7C9A361077F55D0EFA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>90 percent</quote> for <quote>80 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H3C430D586B5342528ADCE6689EA3DFFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>10 percent</quote> for <quote>20 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H9BBA49A5BD3346539F99283596ED3361"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>90 percent</quote> for <quote>85 percent</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H24CC94D548E8490BAC92BA5433D40B66"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>10 percent</quote> for <quote>15 percent</quote></text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H049C55DEF14D4E0BA240A55D457A1042"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Tier IV</header><text>With respect to a State that is eligible for relief under tier IV, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H88AC55A1CB1E4A38BFD3063976EB8667"><enum>(i)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(v) by substituting 95 percent’ for <quote>80 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H2BE9B172136C4189BA0A550742E151B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>5 percent</quote> for <quote>20 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H6D77A288D0624D0BBBEE47A53E79FC82"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>95 percent</quote> for <quote>85 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H79231CC422D9439A829354E87CEB7C47"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>5 percent</quote> for <quote>15 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H69C54B48B436406B82CAC4E3813872EC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(iii) by substituting <quote>95 percent</quote> for <quote>90 percent</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HB9C54602566448E182D769DDD6D3563E"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(iii) by substituting <quote>5 percent</quote> for <quote>10 percent</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HECE5B640552444A58587C0C5BDEA04D2"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Tier V</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a State that is eligible for relief under tier V, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H00478273808647B3924F26127DEA11F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(v) by substituting 100 percent’ for <quote>80 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HC9EF96D8BD154E83899F7539BF16F1F3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(v) by substituting <quote>0 percent</quote> for <quote>20 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HA138AACB8BBB486D91A5020CDE8D25AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>100 percent</quote> for ’85 percent’;</text></clause><clause id="H7F3E01A3BF6F4235AADBF7D7711880AD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(iv) by substituting <quote>0 percent</quote> for <quote>15 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H58357B1A2CF54EA3A4CDE1485D3E0BAF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(iii) by substituting <quote>100 percent</quote> for <quote>90 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H65DF2386520B46F591F171AF68510953"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(iii) by substituting <quote>0 percent</quote> for <quote>10 percent</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HAD33FCDF801D4539BDD956420F54111E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(a)(1)(B)(ii) by substituting <quote>100 percent</quote> for <quote>95 percent</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H77C31E521FD14C17BD70BB0E38ABEF60"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>apply section 499B(b)(1)(B)(ii) by substituting <quote>0 percent</quote> for <quote>5 percent</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BC9570E757E4D73BD3C02183CCE0E55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable fiscal years</header><text>With respect to each State eligible for relief under tier II, III, IV, or V, the Secretary shall provide the relief under paragraph (1), in accordance with subsection (d), for—</text><subparagraph id="H29C8605944E541098408C158134B86C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the fiscal year in which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DC2A175F012422E9B0EA979B3590A72"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fiscal year succeeding the fiscal year described in subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H589E9B100C1B44CBB154880322F356AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>both such fiscal years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22966EB48E2248C7B7D1E6522F90D0E9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State eligibility</header><text>A State’s eligibility for relief under this section shall be determined as follows:</text><paragraph id="H14574C2D87FA4EA9A622F4814F893500"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Tier I</header><text>A State shall be eligible for relief under tier I for a fiscal year in which—</text><subparagraph id="HDEDE9A35DE4D4B7CB9B40DE135BF55E2"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H900A6BC2C90742F5B73ED4FDF4ED38A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State was in an elevated unemployment period at any point in the fiscal year; or</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H8D58514B69BF4E0D98AE9FD65D138085"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Nation as a whole was in an elevated unemployment period at any point in the fiscal year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C5B1A445A1B493C839E88C89740F832"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State is not eligible for relief under any other tier.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC450782ECBDC407C9438CC3DAD77922D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tier II</header><text>A State shall be eligible for relief under tier II for a fiscal year in which—</text><subparagraph id="H375A7AA4F152417391055CB3D9DFE817"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA8448B4D65474B94A68EFA9970A77074"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State average unemployment rate was equal to or greater than 6.5 percent but less than 7.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; or</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H08E8CDA2067B467BA8C6809124C21A28"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the national average unemployment rate is equal to or greater than 6.5 percent but less than 7.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5BEA59153BD4122A52602364B520512"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State is not eligible for relief under tier III, IV, or V.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC446635827F642CFB221B8697B4AA3D9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tier III</header><text>A State shall be eligible for relief under tier III for a fiscal year in which—</text><subparagraph id="H1B212FBE1D3A44A8B7C3027BE2C545C2"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H64EBA104CB9C45269C7606FBEE0CA5CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State average unemployment rate was equal to or greater than 7.5 percent but less than 8.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; or</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H23F99E259F76407097C7F106BCD80807"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the national average unemployment rate is equal to or greater than 7.5 percent but less than 8.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD10E9A10104648CC9E53FE0F2B8E793D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State is not eligible for relief under tier IV or V.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H971655275F6B4EA7B08FB1B5936E59E3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tier IV</header><text>A State shall be eligible for relief under tier IV for a fiscal year in which—</text><subparagraph id="H650F03D7D16548FFBFCCDC718D801AF8"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF4BDCB54823D4CCEB558CCA06837D999"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State average unemployment rate was equal to or greater than 8.5 percent but less than 9.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; or</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H370FCE3A02914FF182F07ECDCC4899CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the national average unemployment rate is equal to or greater than 8.5 percent but less than 9.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75197706C6F148BD98C829258861F535"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State is not eligible for relief under tier V.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H930720254D3845C99C8419A18770AFFC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Tier V</header><text>A State shall be eligible for relief under tier V for a fiscal year in which—</text><subparagraph id="HF5DEA97A9E9B4B7CB19063E9E648FC09"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State average unemployment rate was equal to or greater than 9.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CCD5663C0114580A7E3A21C76802C41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the national average unemployment rate is equal to or greater than 9.5 percent at any point in the fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F37A0DDD9894A06BB2C20E77A234259"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Discretion in the provision of relief</header><text>In determining the fiscal years for which to provide relief in accordance with subsections (a)(2) and (b) to a State that is eligible under tier II, III, IV, or V, the Secretary shall take into account the following:</text><paragraph id="H528D0D2C43E74FB3A1C245C75CEE345F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a State that requests relief under subsection (a)(2), the fiscal years for which the State requests such relief, including—</text><subparagraph id="HD50E0D5E2AAE4210A50E3EEF82A8CAAE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the State requests such relief for the fiscal year for which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made, the amount by which the State is unable to meet the requirements of section 499D(c) for such fiscal year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73B13E4050E14556BB4471C82DF2B953"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the State requests such relief for the fiscal year succeeding the year described in subparagraph (A), the amount by which the State anticipates being unable to meet such requirements for such succeeding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5CF2B8F96F4C4083A1556E7FEA3B4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of a State that requests relief under subsection (b), the fiscal years for which the State requests such relief, including—</text><subparagraph id="HB71E43F63EAB447CA8AED30F0084F303"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the State requests such relief for the fiscal year for which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made, the extent to which the State is unable to meet the requirements of section 499B(b) for such fiscal year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D22788905484A56980C4F24ECA92B78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the State requests such relief for the fiscal year succeeding the year described in subparagraph (A), the extent to which the State anticipates being unable to meet such requirements for such succeeding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H13023E2C62D641749803E85C1BC58D7D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The actual or anticipated timing, severity, and duration of the unemployment rate increase during—</text><subparagraph id="H2F2B810267E347B7A0E11B717DA7DB39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the fiscal year for which the determination of the State’s eligibility for such relief is made;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB86A6AB64F44D6EADCFD718BE318AF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fiscal year succeeding the fiscal year described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1B04A8A490E4E2E81C265947DF05A84"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the fiscal year preceding the fiscal year described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BEA89F7A4E84682931D738AF139439F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Other factors determined to be relevant by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9F2AA211094A41A49D85DBAE10B96FF3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Continued payment to employees</header><text>A State that receives relief under subsection (a) or (b) shall, to the greatest extent practicable, continue to pay its employees of, and contractors with, public institutions of higher education in the State during the period in which the State is receiving such relief. </text></subsection><subsection id="HCE60BD315F6B4E9ABF9986143CF6A8BF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8B3247A7812D4F969F41CC6FDACEF7E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Elevated unemployment period</header><text>The term <term>elevated unemployment period</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H50F7D2248DA34BD3960B41AAC36F0829"><enum>(A)</enum><text>when used with respect to the Nation as a whole, means a consecutive, 3-month period in a fiscal year in which the national average unemployment rate is not less than 0.5 percentage points above the lowest national average unemployment rate for the 12-month period preceding such 3-month period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB807179FA8C498FB08FE01B231C09B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when used with respect to a State, means a consecutive, 3-month period in a fiscal year in which the State average unemployment rate is not less than 0.5 percentage points above the lowest State average unemployment rate for the 12-month period preceding such 3-month period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F94F943ABB3439C84BCB116AB5723FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifying spending requirements</header><text>The term <term>qualifying spending requirements</term> means the requirements that a State not disproportionately decrease spending for any of the categories described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of section 499D(c) relative to such State’s overall, average decrease in spending for the 3 consecutive preceding fiscal years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECF471B0EE0C4E71BAAA3832912C3E20"><enum>(3)</enum><header>National average unemployment rate</header><text>The term <term>national average unemployment rate</term> means the average (seasonally adjusted) rate of total unemployment in all States for a consecutive, 3-month period in a fiscal year, based on data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3543B230424B4D4AA41BFAC5E9E96F1E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State average unemployment rate</header><text>The term <term>State average unemployment rate</term> means the average (seasonally adjusted) rate of total unemployment in a State for a consecutive, 3-month period in a fiscal year, based on data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF474CADA18B14277A56791894867FE2C"><enum>499G.</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated, and there are appropriated to carry out this subpart (in addition to any other amounts appropriated to carry out this subpart and out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated), such sums as may be necessary for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></section><section id="H4167EF12700844DA9DD5ADB442059DAD"><enum>499H.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subpart:</text><paragraph id="HD69AA4DCA6B043778BE747902C1B1217"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprenticeship</header><text>The term <term>apprenticeship</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H183A565A0B894F60AAFC67D939E06A79"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Career pathway</header><text>The term <term>career pathway</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7F350A7F0184AC89F5CEFA067C68CAD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Community college</header><text>The term <term>community college</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H915123797400438396475BAC35C2C214"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a degree-granting public institution of higher education at which—</text><clause id="H208C9F97049E417AAB301EE5EC0C9588"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the highest degree awarded is an associate degree; or</text></clause><clause id="H4602D0FFF9C04533B24A4B4C86757E06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an associate degree is the predominant degree awarded;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD00D83DAB344C3C8C17DBF9206B95D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an eligible Tribal College or University;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE56468BFA48140B4AFEDA1B68A8F2787"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a degree-granting branch campus of a 4-year public institution of higher education if, at such branch campus—</text><clause id="HACCE450B7BB74C25AD46DF6A8F99F9A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the highest degree awarded is an associate degree; or</text></clause><clause id="H60C757AB53414128AE56869199794EE5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an associate degree is the predominant degree awarded; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBCD5E69B6D349B98E1138E730ACDE3F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>at the designation of the Secretary, in the case of a State that does not operate or control any institution that meets a definition under subparagraph (A) or (C), a college or similarly defined and structured academic entity—</text><clause id="HD7A24CB1B56B4994BEE1ABE726C77413"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that was in existence on July 1, 2021;</text></clause><clause id="HF30B11F27874457382F6E0113C6F4238"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>within a 4-year public institution of higher education; and</text></clause><clause id="HA4507529F2DF4A3A82F2F93B8FB6C8F5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at which—</text><subclause id="HFF335EC6AEFF412A8A574BC800C02C47"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the highest degree awarded is an associate degree; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HB00CAFFB971342CD82FBDB98949EB209"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an associate degree is the predominant degree awarded. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBCBA46E70324A108F43D19E1B19BD73"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Dual or concurrent enrollment program</header><text>The term <term>dual or concurrent enrollment program</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H406406B7BA1F4F17867D561129EE797C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Early college high school</header><text>The term <term>early college high school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H020DB418EC9D4B0F88F13E4539C94344"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible student</header><text>The term <term>eligible student</term> means a student who—</text><subparagraph id="H23B075813DE94CE78D22928CC5A9109C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is enrolled as an undergraduate student in an eligible program (as defined in section 481(b)) at a community college on not less than a half-time basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A94E1A13DC34F4287E7E07C9E88E3F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a student who is enrolled in a community college that charges different tuition rates on the basis of in-State or in-district residency, either—</text><clause id="HAD9F470940414FEB842841C907E8FB33"><enum>(i)</enum><text>qualifies for in-State or in-district resident community college tuition; or</text></clause><clause id="H308ABEDC4B524B2E9CE2EF961C0BD6CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>would qualify for such in-State or in-district resident tuition at such community college, but for the immigration status of such student; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB17A620B6E904862A18A57999E5B40DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has not been enrolled (whether full-time or less than full-time) for more than 6 semesters (or the equivalent) for which community college tuition and fees of the student were set to $0 pursuant to section 499D(a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H272069B8EC764162ABD86B966059E6E6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is not enrolled in a dual or concurrent enrollment program or early college high school; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6D19731440E4466BF4CF52456439637"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in the case of a student who is a United States citizen, has filed a FAFSA described in section 483 for the applicable award year for which the student is enrolled.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H82D75196546447BA85DD1E6250E9697E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Eligible Tribal College or University</header><text>The term <term>eligible Tribal College or University</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H3703C426CC2248E0AE0F7AC0A7CA9605"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a 2-year Tribal College or University; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H522B5D63DF5349B18EBBBE8F2D276C67"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a degree-granting Tribal College or University—</text><clause id="H5131CD5A3EC94490862C60AA0D734510"><enum>(i)</enum><text>at which the highest degree awarded is an associate degree; or</text></clause><clause id="HEA17FCECA1B3434394D344CA0223C4C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an associate degree is the predominant degree awarded.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EC0631A336D48518FAD6419C9693C32" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices</term> means practices or reforms that meet the criteria for <quote>evidence tier 1</quote> and <quote>evidence tier 2</quote> under section 4611(a)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, as determined by the Secretary in accordance with such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3AF9B55F8BD4786BF404A57460838BF"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA9A99A214042DDBEB939D7975BBF6B"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Means-tested Federal benefit program</header><text>The term <term>means-tested Federal benefit program</term> has the meaning given the term in section 479.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF20110C138A4BEDA447A7EF01BA7CB2"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Recognized postsecondary credential</header><text>The term <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H466207E3C0684D29B3A56509F5F38BA0"><enum>(12)</enum><header>State fiscal support for higher education</header><subparagraph id="HFA39A2D8D33F415598AB98F6291B7E86"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><clause id="H29656DED4ABA4CECA799997F8FE6D807"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the term <term>State fiscal support for higher education</term>, used with respect to a State for a fiscal year, means an amount that is equal to—</text><subclause id="H0AEB16A4F1D14C79B767DFEFA05CF562"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the gross amount of applicable State funds appropriated or dedicated, and expended by the State, including funds from lottery receipts, in the fiscal year, that are used to support institutions of higher education and student financial aid for higher education in the State; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H21A57C43EE99425E98565CEB13D76EB4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any funds described in clause (ii). </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6CB2486AF53748D6B10FBB3959050A06"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Local funds</header><text>In the case of a State that includes, as part of the State share under section 499B(b)(2)(B) for an award year, funds provided to community colleges by local governments in such State for the purpose of carrying out this subpart, local funds provided to community colleges operated or controlled by such State for operating expenses (excluding capital expenses and research and development costs) shall be included in the calculation of the State fiscal support for higher education for such award year under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EA70AB0272049149DBF3FB124F1AA4C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>State fiscal support for higher education for a State for a fiscal year shall not include—</text><clause id="H85217DB2D6554B4099AC6694B3F311C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>funds described in subparagraph (A)(i) that are returned to the State;</text></clause><clause id="HAF915817985F48B193E3A2F89022A637"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>State-appropriated funds derived from Federal sources, including funds provided under section 499B(b) and section 499J(b);</text></clause><clause id="H9AB2034C70FA4DBEB7DE1732B0718360"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>funds that are included in the State share under section 499B(b) (except as provided in subparagraph (A)(ii) of this paragraph), including funds included in the State share in accordance with paragraph (2)(A) of such section; </text></clause><clause id="H77EAD4CFC36C4DEDAB0AA1F784B94A49"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>amounts that are portions of multiyear appropriations to be distributed over multiple years that are not to be spent for the year for which the calculation under this paragraph is being made, subject to subparagraph (C);</text></clause><clause id="H69E004E887254FBD82FA3A6D74D0E57D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>tuition, fees, or other educational charges paid directly by a student to a public institution of higher education or to the State;</text></clause><clause id="H34FC410EA2534F6D9935C338B4348BB1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>funds for—</text><subclause id="HDF2AEB4C7E7442A6ABF8C0EE3DFC761C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>financial aid to students attending, or operating expenses of—</text><item id="HED037743D715451987C3BBEDC09E7718"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>out-of-State institutions of higher education;</text></item><item id="HA90B8B4914704C39956FE03BD0A0B857"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>proprietary institutions of higher education (as defined in section 102(b)); or</text></item><item id="H0ED6E1703FA246498DC10DEC5B8A0D27"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>institutions of higher education not accredited by an agency or association recognized by the Secretary pursuant to section 496;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H7D468BF0252F4159AA3B4FB6F4D34A16"><enum>(II)</enum><text>financial aid to students awarded predominantly on the basis of merit, including programs awarded on the basis of predicted or actual academic performance or assessment;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCE07E92D04184549A3805DC95A40197A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>research and development;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA0D2961E29654014BADAA3415982B064"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>hospitals, athletics, or other auxiliary enterprises; or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC34B832711CF4C1F978D55A81A5816BE"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">corporate or other private donations directed to 1 or more institutions of higher education permitted to be expended by the State; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H87EA65494EB54688A99F200083725B70"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any other funds that the Secretary determines shall not be included in the calculation of State fiscal support for higher education for such State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1365B41F448B44A9B4392D650D8BF076"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Adjustments for biennial appropriations</header><text>The Secretary shall take into consideration any adjustments to the calculations under this paragraph that may be required to accurately reflect State fiscal support for higher education in States with biennial appropriation cycles.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H21796B4B19BE450C98ED45CEF56B3887"><enum>(13)</enum><header>State fiscal support for higher education per full-time equivalent student</header><text>The term <term>State fiscal support for higher education per full-time equivalent student</term>, when used with respect to a State for a fiscal year, means, the amount that is equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H98EA2C2568BF448684ABEB3D216E7148"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State fiscal support for higher education for the previous fiscal year; divided by</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2270BEFC41284C8FB9431266F243AAC2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of full-time equivalent students enrolled in public institutions of higher education in such State for such previous fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8592186707C428F9760B658EC29DC7A"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Tribal College or University</header><text>The term <term>Tribal College or University</term> has the meaning given such term in section 316(b)(3).</text></paragraph></section></subpart></part><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title id="HE1DF8EA0B10947B49A5D979FFEBD9A12"><enum>II</enum><header>Student success fund</header><section id="HC0C0B580A5A641C48E179607E8571E48"><enum>201.</enum><header>Student success fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part J of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>), as added by section 101, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE26FD9D551224B5AB31BF007EB1CB289"><subpart id="HC0AF05E651604DAAAFA71FC57A0BC49B"><enum>2</enum><header>Student success fund</header><section id="HE951EC13EBC649009A10D63A809776F2"><enum>499I.</enum><header>In general</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCB852B829F6C4B658CBAFAE8B1AF3DAD"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 499O for any fiscal year, the Secretary shall carry out a grant program (to be known as the <quote>Student Success Fund</quote>) to make grants to eligible entities to carry out the activities and services described in section 499L.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBAA464CB19884A178097E70CFC8B68F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding funds under this subpart, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that propose to use a significant share of grant funds to improve enrollment, retention, transfer, or completion rates or labor market outcomes among students of color, low-income students, students with disabilities, students in need of remediation, first generation college students, student parents, and other underserved student populations. </text></subsection></section><section id="H8622AC27781C4FA2A15556473FF0F49F"><enum>499J.</enum><header>Federal share and matching funds</header><subsection id="H1695FC7209D94B5BA30FF27C198461B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal share</header><paragraph id="HD5FA44A5218E4BF6937D7371E5CB2B79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Formula requirements</header><text>The Federal share of a grant under this subpart shall be based on a formula, developed by the Secretary, that accounts for—</text><subparagraph id="H79D02860EB2F463C8DDE81574FF06AAC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State or Tribal College or University relative share of eligible students, as determined in accordance with section 499B(c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9218B1CA971A4186B44DB1B9FC80A9F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State or Tribal College or University relative share of Federal Pell Grant recipients; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2248A50BC8AF4577983BC9CD33BEB981"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the ratio between a State or Tribal College or University funding per full-time equivalent (FTE) student at public institutions of higher education and the average net price at public 4-year institutions of higher education, in such a way as to reward States and Indian tribes that keep net prices for students low while maintaining their fiscal support for higher education. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H288BB54B7FD3496D885D34C1CD37AB58"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Formula published before application deadline</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H19C39CF81A3141BD8500D8277DB82B60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop the formula described in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A52257FD16B4E3EBC7D6C8A3026E4AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>calculate estimated allotments for each eligible entity under such formula; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA3E8E509C5D47848B9EFEFEC6A1709D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>publish such formula and estimated allotments not later than the date of the notice soliciting applications for participation in the program under this subpart.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8622D7A471A481EB4265D8ABA59E341"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matching funds</header><paragraph id="HEF8F04742C4C46C1B6893461124B40E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), an eligible entity participating in the program under this subpart shall provide, from non-Federal sources, in cash or in-kind—</text><subparagraph id="H4FE04F96297647F6B96D1A838CA0877D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in each of the first, second, third, and fourth years of participation in the program, an amount equal to 25 percent of the amount such entity received under subsection (a) with respect to such year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1F8113225764DD19B34B23C8831ABF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in each of the fifth and sixth years of participation in the program, an amount equal to 50 percent of the amount such entity received under subsection (a) with respect to such year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5697BBAC08E84BC7A90AFC2C30CD543E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in each of the seventh and eighth years of participation in the program, an amount equal to 75 percent of the amount such entity received under subsection (a) with respect to such year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D2CBF3A78C143D7918C5CB975ACF949"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the ninth year and each subsequent year thereafter of participation in the program, an amount equal to 100 percent of the amount such entity received under subsection (a) with respect to such year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5A01A029A3A47BC8BD424E6A4C05215"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception for Tribal Colleges and Universities</header><text>The Secretary may modify or waive the matching fund requirements under paragraph (1) in the case of an eligible entity that is a Tribal College or University. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3CACBFC4EB74642AE0F33B34763BA03"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reallotment</header><text>If an eligible entity returns to the Secretary any portion of the grant amount provided to such eligible entity under this subpart for any fiscal year, or requests a grant amount that is less than the Federal share determined for such entity in accordance with subsection (a), the Secretary shall reallot such excess amount for the succeeding fiscal year, in addition to the amounts appropriated under 499O for such succeeding fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08F0A24B95634516BEFA5079F974E49B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Grant funds awarded under this subpart shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, tribal, and local funds that would otherwise be expended to carry out activities assisted under this subpart.</text></subsection></section><section id="H051DC0ADCDC3453B9E89392572E1BFAD"><enum>499K.</enum><header>Applications</header><subsection id="HC4CC262E96174650BEBBC4139588A404"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to participate in the program under this subpart, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text><paragraph id="HCA659342B76244EB85AEEA4165D320ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HFE2970C02C794020B4EE173FD5D200D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of funds requested by the eligible entity under this subpart and the intended use of such funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF3923F9326D4EEE938DE47728B144A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the eligible entity will use the requested funds to implement promising and evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices to improve student outcomes, including—</text><clause id="HDA1E9CA9EC1C48FE84AB868C4F6A5B5C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>implementation of the reforms and practices identified by such entity under section 499C(b)(4); and</text></clause><clause id="HF60FA92615AD4756801F46437052C9C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>annual implementation benchmarks that the entity will use to track progress in implementing such reforms and practices;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18B921814BAD47928C8B15C1DE60E4D4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if the eligible entity is a State, how such eligible entity will support the scaling of evidence-based and innovative initiatives system-wide;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9F511FBADD4432C8CD0816B0EAE4887"><enum>(D)</enum><text>how the eligible entity will meet its matching fund requirements under section 499J(b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41B52F77CAF54AE79D5189954EC9CA21"><enum>(E)</enum><text>if the eligible entity is a State, how such eligible entity will prioritize spending on the public institutions of higher education specified in paragraph (2)(B); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD768BB9D03984DB2913E32E802D63A55"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the improvements the eligible entity anticipates in student outcomes, including improvements in transfer rates or completion rates, or both; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B444A6DDBC34A36B1E1BF7C65E4C52D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the eligible entity is a State, an analysis that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H3C445424FF6D45A4B50C216D910BD6B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to each public institution of higher education of the eligible entity—</text><clause id="HC74622F9B3FE48708A1F8FBCBCAA25E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total per-student funding;</text></clause><clause id="H78E8554F9C6E4A019C01C82EF8E1DFAE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of per-student funding from State-appropriated funds;</text></clause><clause id="H41DE8F1E4C2F45309F6CC370D6738B1C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the student demographics (including data on race, income, disability status, and remediation); and</text></clause><clause id="HC52E68DFD895473D93F21FABB682B557"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>transfer and completion rates, including such rates among low-income students, students of color, students with disabilities, and students in need of remediation; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CF09CAF672E4C79A9E306A7288DD604"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether, of the public institutions of higher education of the eligible entity, the public institutions of higher education that received less funding on a per-student basis described in clause (i) or (ii), or both, of subparagraph (A), are serving disproportionately high shares of low-income students, students of color, students with disabilities, or students in need of remediation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H298F292F43E84512B368A4132F22FE79"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approval</header><paragraph id="H5C670B26A88A471088291136F58DE181"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after receiving a plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB06E74A4C5A04B7DB5E344935785B640"><enum>(A)</enum><text>approve the plan; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBCB6E638498415DA792D6CCDD540022"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require revisions to such plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H47335186AD2F423BA36CFC5C51EB9AC5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revisions required</header><text>An eligible entity shall make such revisions as required by the Secretary under paragraph (1)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0505D253253D4EFCB49B2B3BEFCB5A8F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Secretary shall make each plan approved under subsection (b)(1)(A) and each plan revised under subsection (b)(2) available to the public on the website of the Department.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3129A350AA17413A864DBAF4DBB462B5"><enum>499L.</enum><header>Program requirements</header><subsection id="H6DFFE8FCF13E455E883D458DA800DC7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General requirements</header><paragraph id="HAEBEE8B4843A439C96B41E90732D3D0D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report on demonstrated progress</header><text>For the third year in which an eligible entity participates in the program under this subpart, and every 2 years thereafter, the eligible entity shall submit a report to the Secretary, in such manner and containing such information as the Secretary may require, that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HCECF389BEEBC4737A7FABD88D90D87FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the progress in meeting the annual implementation benchmarks included in the application of such eligible entity under section 499K(a)(1)(B);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F8D2405FA084D41A29E4742BE5E4D0F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the progress in improving the student outcomes identified by the entity under section 499K(a)(1)(F); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA487D2093E6B4FB282095948AF308D2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to the 2 years after such report is submitted—</text><clause id="HF6F19778AE864DF6909434AC0B201075"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a plan for the use of funds under this subpart; and</text></clause><clause id="HBF4F7CE29E5A4F1095F996A7CB847C13"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of funds requested by the eligible entity under this subpart.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7186B9EFCA949D2A3812CCE7EFD0B8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Approval</header><text>Not later than 180 days after receiving a plan under paragraph (1)(C)(i), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H9EE2BB5B7E5C48C884479331154252AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>approve the plan; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H404A72C3B2F24B21B4F90D7C8E51E6D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require revisions to such plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9825EFF1B09409F9FCA4010BB88688E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Revisions required</header><text>An eligible entity shall make such revisions as required by the Secretary under paragraph (2)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0363B15159F745F797CB064BCCF5A05D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Failure To meet requirements</header><text>If an eligible entity does not meet the annual implementation benchmarks included in the application of such eligible entity under section 499K(a)(1)(B), as required to be reported under subsection (a)(1)(A), such eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require—</text><paragraph id="H663369D94F02469285D824F234FBE7F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a written explanation for the delay in meeting such requirements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE01F58CEA18B4EAB8CB95B560F76F35B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan that will enable such eligible entity to meet such requirements not later than 1 year after the date on which the eligible entity submitted the written explanation under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65FF4EE4E0994B32A7985B11179CC835"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Secretary shall make each plan approved under subsection (a)(2)(A), each plan revised under subsection (a)(3), and each plan submitted under subsection (b)(2) available to the public on the website of the Department.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD148DB5D91124BAB959EFA06AF50CC07"><enum>499M.</enum><header>Allowable uses of funds</header><subsection id="HFB602CE521DC4C6BA69F8C70E1786B6A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), an eligible entity shall use a grant under this subpart only to carry out the plan approved or revised for such year under section 499K.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA14851F00F78429784C12E356BFECC67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds for administrative purposes</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this subpart may use not more than 5 percent of such grant for administrative purposes relating to the grant under this subpart.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBC77CEFB42794EBAAC2A3D68D063B25F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibited uses of funds</header><text>No funds received under this section shall be used to—</text><paragraph id="HCDA434DCCB0347139B66CAA229803B44"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pay contractors for the provision of pre-enrollment recruitment activities through a revenue sharing agreement; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CB00DEB4CDA4BCA85AEF96B7896FF74"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fund endowments, athletics, sectarian instruction, or religious worship.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4A394DE8B27C46159229BB20DF88615D"><enum>499N.</enum><header>Eligible entity defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subpart, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a State or Tribal College or University that is a recipient of a grant under subpart 1.</text></section><section id="HC109D754CA6743D6BAB90056A4F7CF6C"><enum>499O.</enum><header>Appropriations</header><subsection id="HCFEBF0F8C7D445DDA03335B1913967CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization and appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated, and there are appropriated to carry out this subpart (in addition to any other amounts appropriated to carry out this subpart and out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated), $1,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H425CEA63FE8E4980B3BDF8AE183D8F7F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Funds appropriated under subsection (a) shall remain available to the Secretary until expended.</text></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title id="HDB07D8DCD55E45D08A72409B4DADF977"><enum>III</enum><header>Pathways to student success for Historically Black Colleges and Universities, Tribal Colleges and Universities, and Minority-Serving Institutions</header><section id="H10972160380645548E21C82DFBD1E9C0"><enum>301.</enum><header>Grants to Historically Black Colleges and Universities, Tribal Colleges and Universities, and Minority-Serving Institutions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part J of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>), as added and amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H568F8B26E93342C89897BCCDBB497ADE"><subpart id="H61192C0563FC41F08294AA1E0252A668"><enum>3</enum><header>Grants to historically Black Colleges and Universities, Tribal Colleges and Universities, and Minority-Serving Institutions</header><section id="HB63BB45B85F04E7EBA325CDB682E28BC"><enum>499P.</enum><header>Pathways to student success for Historically Black Colleges and Universities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 499U(a) for any fiscal year, the Secretary shall award grants to participating historically Black colleges or universities that meet the requirements of section 499S(a) to—</text><paragraph id="H43E98A596B624EF39725D428EDE80BF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encourage students to enroll and successfully complete a bachelor’s degree at such colleges and universities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87009D76291941E39FBB08368779D70A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide incentives to community college students to transfer to such colleges and universities through strong transfer pathways to complete a bachelor’s degree program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1746B64FEBE54D71853EB86DAADF7459"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support such colleges and universities to better serve new and existing students by engaging in reforms and innovations designed to improve completion rates and other student outcomes.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE29BC018CD094BA39BDF19F5B3E40E66"><enum>499Q.</enum><header>Pathways to student success for Tribal Colleges and Universities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 499U(a) for any fiscal year, the Secretary shall award grants to participating Tribal Colleges or Universities that meet the requirements of section 499S(a) to—</text><paragraph id="H30F783ED3F3B4CEBA032E13503062D7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encourage students to enroll and successfully complete a bachelor’s degree at such Colleges and Universities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE85D240C3BA431981ED0BB504C03284"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide incentives to community college students to transfer to such Colleges and Universities through strong transfer pathways to complete a bachelor’s degree program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90BBE9BE6F2342DE9F8A2611BBBA809D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support such Colleges and Universities to better serve new and existing students by engaging in reforms and innovations designed to improve completion rates and other student outcomes.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFF6C3FA7955145B4B1AAD220BA442EF6"><enum>499R.</enum><header>Pathways to student success for Alaska Native-serving institutions, Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institutions, Hispanic-serving institutions, Native American-serving nontribal institutions, Native Hawaiian-serving institutions, and Predominantly Black institutions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From amounts appropriated under section 499U(a) for any fiscal year, the Secretary shall award grants to participating Alaska Native-serving institutions, Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institutions, Hispanic-serving institutions, Native American-serving nontribal institutions, Native Hawaiian-serving institutions, and Predominantly Black institutions that meet the requirements of section 499S(a) to— </text><paragraph id="HC7DF239F91444D99A87914B203C2445D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encourage students to enroll and successfully complete a bachelor’s degree at such institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46CF2AF8451C443AB32C746BB51DDB46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide incentives to community college students to transfer to such institutions through strong transfer pathways to complete a bachelor’s degree program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C3C6E7DE40547819A93FF428CB632E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support such institutions to better serve new and existing students by engaging in reforms and innovations designed to improve completion rates and other student outcomes.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA8B239BD9BF34F1190B983AF7FB7B3A7"><enum>499S.</enum><header>Grant terms</header><subsection id="H95A9E50A8E3A4D3CA99B58112F5D03C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Institutional eligibility</header><text>An institution shall meet the requirements of this subsection if the institution—</text><paragraph id="HE4F76CCFC0FE425AA6D18736B756FF5A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in a public or nonprofit 4-year institution that has a student body of which not less than 35 percent are low-income students;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H946420EEF2DD4EDDBD8D03106E15FCEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>commits to maintaining or adopting and implementing promising and evidence-based institutional reforms and innovative practices to improve the completion rates and other student outcomes, such as—</text><subparagraph id="HF546B92111BD4E389172601282BE4603"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing comprehensive academic, career, and student support services (including mentoring, advising, case management services, and career pathway navigation), especially for low-income, first-generation, and adult students, and other students belonging to racial and other groups that are historically underrepresented in higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5FAFA0D9DD54C98AC7D0E5AF46FEC31"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing direct support services, or assistance in applying for such services, such as—</text><clause id="H84EE0A8175134FF89FFCAB867B32655B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>childcare, transportation, and emergency financial assistance;</text></clause><clause id="HA1250785340E4BB5953799B6BCC7746B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assistance in obtaining health insurance coverage and accessing health care services, including behavioral and mental health services;</text></clause><clause id="H6B3A0970497C4953A773F026AD5FF7E8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>affordable housing;</text></clause><clause id="H96D570556BB64DF9BB8C09C33311A815"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>nutrition assistance programs or free or discounted food; and</text></clause><clause id="H3755F18180CF4540A14DBC7A1E5124B2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>means-tested Federal benefit programs, or similar State, tribal, or local benefit programs;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1FBA4FB09F84515855FCF1A8127029A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing accelerated learning opportunities and degree pathways, such as dual or concurrent enrollment programs and pathways to graduate and professional degree programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7EDC8DA9D064123A305EA8363B0A6D5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>partnering with employers, industry, nonprofit associations, and other groups to provide opportunities to advance learning outside the classroom, including—</text><clause id="H74595E0DF45A49B5AAF932903DECFB74"><enum>(i)</enum><text>work-based learning opportunities (such as internships or apprenticeships); or</text></clause><clause id="HF200C0D3C0694ED7A1E5E63739EADEEE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>programs designed to improve inter-cultural development and personal growth (such as foreign exchange and study abroad programs); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H954D0F8B748C45E08D43FF80CAF5ABE8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>strengthening remedial education, especially for low-income, first-generation, and adult students, and other students belonging to racial and other groups that are historically underrepresented in higher education, including through the use of multiple measures (such as a student’s college entrance examination score, grade point average, high school course list, or a placement examination) to identify students in need of remedial education;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0A2192422594F7AB7353426D74AA6DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>sets performance goals for improving student outcomes for the duration of the grant; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CCCDCAAB3D64603BBF33D9B259866EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>if receiving a grant for transfer students, has a formal, statewide articulation agreement with community colleges in the State in which such institution operates that guarantees—</text><subparagraph id="H7B2362E2F7D6429EBA0A9510AE7D978B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that a student who earns postsecondary credit at any community college in such State shall be able to fully transfer such credit toward meeting related degree or certificate requirements at such institution; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H602F51B776284B65A344C4B663656553"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that associate degrees awarded by community colleges in the State are fully transferable to, and credited as, the first 2 years of related baccalaureate programs at such institution.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H645AD0AB9BEE446AA8EF1CB0C414EFA0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><paragraph id="H1E1D68FB0FE2468C992D3902099F9E19"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial amount</header><text>For the first year that an eligible institution participates in the grant program under this subpart and subject to paragraph (3), such eligible institution shall receive a grant in an amount based on the product of—</text><subparagraph id="H223EB727FFB04C078591A0ACAE3D66CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the actual cost of tuition and fees at the eligible institution in such year (referred to in this subpart as the per-student rebate); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C103E11D0934D66B5CD994CE14BB6F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of eligible students enrolled in the eligible institution for the preceding year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H42C72BCC249243C9B1B78B42EAA83E4B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent increases</header><text>For each succeeding year after the first year of the grant program under this subpart, each participating eligible institution shall receive a grant in the amount determined under paragraph (1) for such year, except that in no case shall the amount of the per-student rebate for an eligible institution increase by more than 3 percent as compared to the amount of such rebate for the preceding year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D1FC5E6EE3D4D02925A9D27A8C3E124"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations</header><subparagraph id="H53C15C4EE2B94650B0678028248CC3A3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Maximum per-student rebate</header><text>No eligible institution participating in the grant program under this subpart shall receive a per-student rebate amount for any year that is greater than the national average of annual tuition and fees at public 4-year institutions of higher education for such year, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13E162914E114E1CA298C42E49943551"><enum>(B)</enum><header>First-year tuition and fees</header><text>During the first year of participation in the grant program under this subpart, no eligible institution may increase tuition and fees at a rate greater than any annual increase at the eligible institution in the previous 5 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D55E736CC614A88A72046DB5E215D94"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Students enrolled less than full-time</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and implement a formula for making adjustments to grant amounts under this subpart based on the number of eligible students at each eligible institution enrolled less than full-time and the associated tuition and fees charged to such students in proportion to the degree to which each such student is not attending on a full-time basis.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66D6C869DC4C4B5B80AE5937C4ABEB12"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible institution that desires a grant under this subpart shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F4C31E7784B4990AA783EBC33EE077A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Funds awarded under this subpart to a participating eligible institution shall be used to waive or significantly reduce tuition and fees for eligible students by an amount not to exceed the annual per-student rebate amount. Such funds under this subpart may only be used to waive or reduce tuition and fees for the first 60 credits for which an eligible student is enrolled in the participating eligible institution.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE3FB8DAD99044CD0BA363D49B4FBA042"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Funds made available under section 499U to carry out this subpart shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, tribal, and local funds that would otherwise be expended to carry out activities under this subpart.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD56C8F8E43CA433A8B47355BC863995A"><enum>499T.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subpart:</text><paragraph id="H20C95F98DB194CFFBB08D63404FBBB25"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alaska native-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Alaska Native-serving institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 317(b). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A5843C5904E43E4B4EFCB9F0E69B119"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Asian american and native american pacific islander-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 371(c). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H138AB4124120462696CF123925152851"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible student</header><text>The term <term>eligible student</term> means a student, regardless of age, who—</text><subparagraph id="H0664D635FA6F4CBD9346B0096A8D465B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is enrolled in an eligible program (as defined in section 481(b)) at a participating eligible institution, on at least a half-time basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B625D59DAF54ECFB9B7B8CD41B0976C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is a low-income student;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C46AC2689C24815BED8C969A5B887E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has been enrolled at such participating eligible institution under this subpart for not more than 60 credits; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6136CFFEEF64CDBB04FA38FDEB2C530"><enum>(D)</enum><text>has not been enrolled (whether full-time or less than full-time) for more than 6 semesters (or the equivalent) for which the student received a benefit under this subpart.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59D6EAF76C07455FA72D58B9EB35591A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Hispanic-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Hispanic-serving institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 502.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D3C252B5B02402A8CCF9D75B92DBF5D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Historically Black college or university</header><text>The term <term>historically Black college or university</term> means a part B institution described in section 322(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86C754D9A9D449B5B677C005B8E3CF3E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Low-income student</header><text>The term <term>low-income student</term> shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HDA982B169B574B34BD14E9E11D6A06B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any student eligible for a Federal Pell Grant under section 401; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC41A0C798D2145C2BA786FE9EA1E336C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any student who meets the financial eligibility criteria for receiving a Federal Pell Grant under section 401, but who is ineligible to receive a Federal Pell Grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C7A20F164184682BA9B1C9C7C65D73A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Native American-serving nontribal institution</header><text>The term <term>Native American-serving nontribal institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 371(c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE424B0FF192044B6A46EAAE83149D9DA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Native hawaiian-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiian-serving institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 317(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AC67CF369F74F9B83F0E68D2374AF15"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Predominantly Black institution</header><text>The term <term>Predominantly Black institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 371(c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6206F507EC174529BEBB1707D26F9B43"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Tribal college or university</header><text>The term <term>Tribal College or University</term> has the meaning given the term in section 316(b)(3).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE06B8EF0E56C4FDB816A26136A5D0B8B"><enum>499U.</enum><header>Appropriations</header><subsection id="H01420B3389FF4B34AD40F2749F1B346F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization and appropriations for HBCU, TCU, and MSI grants</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this subpart there are authorized to be appropriated, and there are appropriated—</text><paragraph id="H7663B3C02E71490FB0BC965B7A4BF45E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$98,100,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFFEBBF50979456D86601E071041514A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$321,040,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H430CB25B7A4140A1B2C456BBB0CF1B67"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$1,912,010,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0577B37D3844038A47C310C2FAE89E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$1,988,710,000 for fiscal year 2027;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76F8F8100EEF485E93F8DB8DE99E33A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$2,068,960,000 for fiscal year 2028;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A98E989DD1A4A83A4FC95AD174C6330"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$2,151,010,000 for fiscal year 2029;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2B07D3C2D514AD89F990A7D21894E6D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$2,184,900,000 for fiscal year 2030;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8AD09A13EFE4638B229C55612C98D86"><enum>(8)</enum><text>$2,329,370,000 for fiscal year 2031;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36F71B5E4FD944F88C52CA2BE8A06664"><enum>(9)</enum><text>$2,423,910,000 for fiscal year 2032; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD9DC6B1752B4128A44E99DDD64B78B8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>$2,521,990,000 for fiscal year 2033 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H86ABF14BAC6E4532AAC24CF8E42B0F31"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Funds appropriated under subsection (a) for a fiscal year are to remain available to the Secretary through the two fiscal years following such fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE812314AE6F34DEC8E7EE01BEC2C4731"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Insufficient funds</header><text>If the amount appropriated under subsection (a) for a fiscal year is not sufficient to award each institution participating in the grant programs under sections 499P, 499Q, and 499R a grant under this subpart equal to 100 percent of the grant amount determined under section 499S(b), the Secretary may ratably reduce the amount of each such grant or take other actions necessary to ensure an equitable distribution of such amount appropriated under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

