<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDB01A38409CA4A5B8A8E1BCE3041EB58" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2845 IH: Enhancing K–12 Cybersecurity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2845</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency to establish a School Cybersecurity Improvement Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H36136511A691485F986A44F2029EE5F2" style="OLC"><section id="HFE9835F38B4D4BB4AE232B6F91E8CF05" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may cited as the <quote><short-title>Enhancing K–12 Cybersecurity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H710BA40808954654AF5CC2B30ADBE242"><enum>2.</enum><header>School cybersecurity information exchange</header><subsection id="H15C3EE4D62CA4FE1B2D77730A1F12D5A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency shall enhance existing information exchange efforts implemented through partnerships with one or more information sharing and analysis organizations to focus specific attention on the needs of K–12 organizations with regard to cybersecurity, including a new publicly accessible website (to be known as the <quote>School Cybersecurity Information Exchange</quote>) to disseminate information, cybersecurity best practices, training, and lessons learned tailored to the specific needs, technical expertise, and resources available to K–12 organizations in accordance with subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA2E94A5F35E4E5495AEF8993B732577"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the School Cybersecurity Information Exchange under subsection (a), the Director shall—</text><paragraph id="H0C770CB47FBC4868BF6DF51C23E04CE4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage appropriate Federal, State, local, and nongovernmental organizations to identify, promote, and disseminate information and best practices for local educational agencies, State educational agencies, and educational service agencies (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) with respect to cybersecurity, data protection, remote learning security, and student online privacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8B3E842B9934EB5AE87200BBBA30301" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintain a database for an elementary school, secondary school, local educational agency, State educational agency, and educational service agency to identify cybersecurity security tools and services funded by the Federal Government, as well as tools and services recommended for purchase with State and local government funding; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5789F7E897E048D69FACF57BCC932816"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide a searchable database for an elementary school, secondary school, local educational agency, State educational agency, and educational service agency to find and apply for funding opportunities to improve cybersecurity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE6B421189E194D108A7A485F88F18299"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the duties under subsection (b), the Director shall consult with the following:</text><paragraph id="H35451ED4071A417E9F99A03D0EA6D4D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22817336FD9C4C4194445721C67BE6DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55B04F904EE34F9C8192728047ECC075"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Federal Communication Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H401550592CDA4B57A4E362AF9A5522E8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCF1EE9B833E48EBA4FCD61AE3F0A05C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2492062C753B4DAAA9A7FD0C23C70149"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State and local leaders, including, when appropriate, Governors, employees of State government departments and agencies, members of State legislatures and State boards of education, local educational agencies, State educational agencies, representatives of Indian tribes, teachers, principals, other school leaders, charter school leaders, specialized instructional support personnel, paraprofessionals, administrators, other staff, and parents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0357030AEC36417189926CE70353ABBB"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When determined appropriate by the Director, subject-matter experts and expert organizations, including nongovernmental organizations, vendors of school information technology products and services, cybersecurity insurance companies, and cybersecurity threat companies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDA825A3DF6754A10A60B05E6C524BA9A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Cybersecurity incident registry</header><subsection id="HF842535BD7E745019B057EDCC853547F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency shall establish, through partnerships with one or more information sharing and analysis organizations, a voluntary registry of information relating to cyber incidents affecting information technology systems owned or managed by a covered entity, and determine the scope of cyber incidents to be included in the registry and processes by which incidents can be reported for collection in the registry<italic></italic>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDCF5C3AA351F49D88C653C8E7B822C58"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information in the registry established pursuant to subsection (a) may be used to—</text><paragraph id="H450230A914694A9AB4FAD38AD41A3A31" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve data collection and coordination activities related to the nationwide monitoring of the incidence and impact of cyber incidents affecting a covered entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16DA495A227845BD9D7AF2F4554D4383"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conduct analyses regarding trends in cyber incidents against such entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34FC9560E2B9467E9184BE70321DD949"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop systematic approaches to assist such entity in preventing and responding to cyber incidents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BA9906604994B44AC49A762B5C990C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>increase the awareness and preparedness of a covered entity regarding the cybersecurity of such covered entity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE74DA9959A84439DBBB7E8D7BF9F749D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify, prevent, or investigate cyber incidents targeting a covered entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52B438CB85CF45E1A3E2E8CAD5F0FE72"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Information collection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency may collect information relating to cyber incidents to store in the registry established pursuant to subsection (a). Such information may be submitted by a covered entity and may include the following:</text><paragraph id="HB564F39A4032472EB12941A15A09C5AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The dates of each cyber incident, including the dates on which each such incident was initially detected and the dates on which each such incident was first publicly reported or disclosed to another entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADDB8CC19F1A463B8C205DC649CEF7FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of each cyber incident, which shall include whether each such incident was as a result of a breach, malware, distributed denial of service attack, or other method designed to cause a vulnerability.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H819823DD54CB45499B394FEEE79576CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effects of each cyber incident, including descriptions of the type and size of each such incident.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C9F25E332B940228C9B7CA8252B1C46"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other information determined relevant by the Director.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1FDA125F75C94EEFBDB1038827C11A87"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency shall make available on the School Cybersecurity Information Exchange established under section 2 an annual report relating to cyber incidents affecting elementary schools and secondary schools which includes data, and the analysis of such data, in a manner that—</text><paragraph id="H1E90AF5A15FC4EF98184760CE1E1C3D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is—</text><subparagraph id="H56AFA61D86864DA29A89B048609EFD38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>de-identified; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5335DA9FC44D48EBA329E0DEB87F31B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>presented in the aggregate; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A2B2E651398465F919423823BCF69B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at a minimum, protects personal privacy to the extent required by applicable Federal and State privacy laws.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H461189D454C7471ABA41EA182E37E0B3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Covered entity defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered entity</term> means the following:</text><paragraph id="HBB3F69CBBD9540DD960C73E65EC6C0DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An elementary school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H777DCBC058C642EC94A51CF010AE8CF4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A secondary school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E4003F0449E4CCD9D0A7086A5F474A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A local educational agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16593134C232445385E35ACCF538AC5F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A State educational agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3543784974B049ECA44580588EDBFA04"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An educational service agency.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H89D55C66401A467F9FC9AF1A52E6FAAD"><enum>4.</enum><header>K–12 Cybersecurity Technology Improvement program</header><subsection id="H23D753046C524A2A9292BB5C2B4643E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, shall establish, through partnerships with one or more information sharing and analysis organizations, a program (to be known as the <quote>K–12 Cybersecurity Technology Improvement program</quote>) to deploy cybersecurity capabilities to address cybersecurity risks and threats to information systems of elementary schools and secondary schools through—</text><paragraph id="HBE9D70D4906048949376B932EAC97492"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing cybersecurity strategies and installation of effective cybersecurity tools tailored for K–12 schools;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H128AF05366EF4BC29EB974D58D73BB77"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">making available cybersecurity services that enhance the ability of K–12 schools to protect themselves from ransomware and other cybersecurity threats; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB770D31C87E344DFB0DB5D2755DFF5E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">continuing training opportunities on cybersecurity threats, best practices, and relevant technologies for K–12 schools.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6BC3AF19EA4F4EC8A1281E387207EB6A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency shall make available on the School Cybersecurity Information Exchange established under section 2 an annual report relating to the impact of the K–12 Cybersecurity Technology Improvement Program, including information on the cybersecurity capabilities made available to information technology systems owned or managed by elementary schools, secondary schools, local educational agencies, State educational agencies, and educational service agencies, the number of students served, and cybersecurity incidents identified or prevented.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2DF7EA876FC14309BF2CEEBE6D322E53"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025.</text></section><section id="H254797474A40491DA0A4E35ADE50B88C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H5975982581B64F149DB99FFF6FEF5EDA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Educational service agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>educational service agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF045E8EDD93432785909A37811416F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elementary school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>elementary school</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0741D1712D0D487CA8C6F61924F6164C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information sharing and analysis organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>information sharing and analysis organization</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2200 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF375F53F9ECA412FB02A8DF75DEBFB30"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9919A79E66F046F8B6FDE657EF4B43D5" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State educational agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD36E0C719BE142D48D858A98A02F57B1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secondary school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>secondary school</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

