<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H5260434A423E47F48444CD77B0CF67FC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1690 RH: Orderly Requirements Designed to Enforce and Regulate Latin American Migration Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 30</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1690</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–46, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HFA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 22, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of State to negotiate regional immigration agreements, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HFA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H204DA4A9B35F49B6A5E01BBE87B98448"><section id="HBDD90D7020524F1AB5D59C7EE4BF0B24" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Orderly Requirements Designed to Enforce and Regulate Latin American Migration Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ORDER Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H65415C0BEB724E5FA4D9F40A71BF8194"><enum>2.</enum><header>United States Policy regarding Western Hemisphere cooperation on immigration and asylum</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to enter into agreements, accords, and memoranda of understanding with sovereign countries in the Western Hemisphere, the purposes of which are to advance the interests of the United States by reducing costs associated with illegal immigration and to protect the human capital, societal traditions, and economic growth of other sovereign nations in the Western Hemisphere. It is further the policy of the United States to ensure that humanitarian and development assistance funding aimed at reducing illegal immigration is not expended on programs that have not proven to reduce illegal immigrant flows in the aggregate.</text></section><section id="HD5C16366904542D79A55AED98F7DB69B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Negotiations by Secretary of State</header><subsection id="H8A6591A18B99415CA831D9CD1185D4F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization to negotiate</header><text>The Secretary of State shall seek to negotiate agreements, accords, and memoranda of understanding between the United States, Mexico, Honduras, El Salvador, Guatemala, and other countries in the Western Hemisphere with respect to cooperation and burden sharing required for effective regional immigration enforcement, expediting legal claims by aliens for asylum, and the processing, detention, and repatriation of foreign nationals seeking to enter the United States unlawfully. Such agreements shall be designed to facilitate a regional approach to immigration enforcement and shall, at a minimum, provide that—</text><paragraph id="H1DB5BF880E4A484AB7DF0348FE88FFB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Government of Mexico authorize and accept the rapid entrance into Mexico of nationals of countries other than Mexico who seek asylum in Mexico, and process the asylum claims of such nationals inside Mexico, in accordance with both domestic law and international treaties and conventions governing the processing of asylum claims;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC60396BF70074345B266428EA93A3D42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Government of Mexico authorize and accept both the rapid entrance into Mexico of all nationals of countries other than Mexico who are ineligible for asylum in Mexico and wish to apply for asylum in the United States, whether or not at a port of entry, and the continued presence of such nationals in Mexico while they wait for the adjudication of their asylum claims to conclude in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5871280098B94567954F32B59C6D8971"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Government of Mexico commit to provide the individuals described in paragraphs (1) and (2) with appropriate humanitarian protections;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5043AC38C4B4427A5DDE4A9FC879D10"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Government of Honduras, the Government of El Salvador, and the Government of Guatemala each authorize and accept the entrance into the respective countries of nationals of other countries seeking asylum in the applicable such country and process such claims in accordance with applicable domestic law and international treaties and conventions governing the processing of asylum claims;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC54F28431634616BE55B393D5B8D2D7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Government of the United States commit to work to accelerate the adjudication of asylum claims and to conclude removal proceedings in the wake of asylum adjudications as expeditiously as possible;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7488D7E898264637B6861E1F627CCFE7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Government of the United States commit to continue to assist the governments of countries in the Western Hemisphere, such as the Government of Honduras, the Government of El Salvador, and the Government of Guatemala, by supporting the enhancement of asylum capacity in those countries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA803194BD24494FBC79CAEF5B5ADFD2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Government of the United States commit to monitoring developments in hemispheric immigration trends and regional asylum capabilities to determine whether additional asylum cooperation agreements are warranted.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2BB789B20E414E0F92914AB8C00D1C60"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification in accordance with Case-Zablocki Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall, in accordance with section 112b of title 1, United States Code, promptly inform the relevant congressional committees of each agreement entered into pursuant to subsection (a). Such notifications shall be submitted not later than 48 hours after such agreements are signed.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCA7CB50AEF1E4A1C8AC20A19C9317CCE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Alien defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>alien</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="H25D2CB845B764031B41D90F18F7C2B98" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>4.</enum><header>Mandatory briefings on United States efforts to address the border crisis</header><subsection id="H6FB7961140274EF5A99B159C21FF6E72"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Briefing required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and not less frequently than once every 90 days thereafter until the date described in subsection (b), the Secretary of State, or the designee of the Secretary of State, shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees an in-person briefing on efforts undertaken pursuant to the negotiation authority provided by section 3 to monitor, deter, and prevent illegal immigration to the United States, including by entering into agreements, accords, and memoranda of understanding with foreign countries and by using United States foreign assistance to stem the root causes of migration in the Western Hemisphere.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1288CC010D51443C98CAB59FA9C54C78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination of mandatory briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The date described in this subsection is the date on which the Secretary of State, in consultation with the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, determines and certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that illegal immigration flows have subsided to a manageable rate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H03931B65769A4F33B7240DFD7C5CCBAF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HFA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

