<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HD9E8E7A40A2E4356948DE16C99ECCB0B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2868 RH: Association Health Plans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 87</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2868</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–112]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor> and <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on April 25, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 to clarify the treatment of certain association health plans as employers, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HED00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H4BBA25E1286C44BFA81AE249DA6F39C7"><section id="H7BD15B5A28DF4409B737ED025DE17A5B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Association Health Plans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAC8932A658734F2B8CF052CCF1A9CA2E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of group or association of employers</header><subsection id="HD775412242B844BAB82C7694421569CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(5) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1002">29 U.S.C. 1002(5)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC3AD14F3868D4F5CB023C48C7B9B2F09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The term</quote> and inserting <quote>(A) The term</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H856D2105565A4205B965BEDF8697DFED"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3BB5696080E84AE68A2D6A72F3400200" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><subparagraph id="H6E7F2E5FF78049CB83A011DFA3B99C8C" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), a group or association of employers shall be treated as an <quote>employer</quote>, regardless of whether the employers composing such group or association are in the same industry, trade, or profession, if such group or association—</text><clause id="H39545B50B60441F5A3B3612C3E395B4A"><enum>(i)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAC1605FD858D466C9233585C19089975"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has established and maintains an employee welfare benefit plan that is a group health plan (as defined in section 733(a)(1));</text></subclause><subclause id="HCC05A7651E294F9488C8888B96C2CEF1" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides coverage under such plan to at least 51 employees after all of the employees employed by all of the employer members of such group or association have been aggregated and counted together as described in subparagraph (D);</text></subclause><subclause id="HE2D02FCC8F1949659CF6929350A64F77" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has been actively in existence for at least 2 years prior to establishing and maintaining an employer welfare benefit plan that is a group health plan (as defined in section 733(a)(1));</text></subclause><subclause id="H4CD0543CF5554F9EB609E13613280EE0" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has been formed and maintained in good faith for purposes other than providing medical care (as defined in section 733(a)(2)) through the purchase of insurance or otherwise;</text></subclause><subclause id="H75AAB49467D144E7BB6075BC11D41E1B" indent="up1"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not condition membership in the group or association on any health status-related factor (as described in section 702(a)(1)) relating to any individual;</text></subclause><subclause id="HFEACEB5E911A40D8999C823BA35A9E23" indent="up1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes coverage under such plan available to all employer members of such group or association regardless of any health status-related factor (as described in section 702(a)(1)) relating to such employer members;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3523D1533DF84F3C8BDDE545AA0E7067" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>does not provide coverage under such plan to any individual other than an employee of an employer member of such group or association;</text></subclause><subclause id="HDAE83CC03582417F9A5131CD0BEC04D5" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has established a governing board with by-laws or other similar indications of formality to manage and operate such plan in both form and substance, of which at least 75 percent of the board members shall be made up of employer members of such group or association participating in the plan that are duly elected by each participating employer member casting 1 vote during a scheduled election;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1B5F8D82B9DB4FA3A70477D8A1A12497" indent="up1"><enum>(IX)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not a health insurance issuer (as defined in section 733(b)(2)), and is not owned or controlled by such a health insurance issuer or by a subsidiary or affiliate of such a health insurance issuer, other than to the extent such a health insurance issuer—</text><item id="HE7CB50105FBF486F9A809DD7E1345888"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may participate in the group or association as a member; and</text></item><item id="HE36FD9E67A914F20AC5AFB983AF81072"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>may provide services such as assistance with plan development, marketing, and administrative services to such group or association;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H0C648E297F3C4DEAA47CE12D03B18B10"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets any set of criteria to qualify for such treatment in an advisory opinion issued by the Secretary prior to the date of enactment of the <short-title>Association Health Plans Act</short-title>; or</text></clause><clause id="H30C99BAB71B049059E0D3258E75A5E01" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>meets any other set of criteria to qualify for such treatment that the Secretary by regulation may provide.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7DE502729D84EF9A4F1F5D1DED6F1DC" indent="up2"><enum>(C)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2E4014AF67744DC39EE7592E6C719FC7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (B), a self-employed individual shall be treated as—</text><subclause id="H64432D26B0C6414489E70B5A3F7F54C6" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employer who may become a member of a group or association of employers;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF7930DE73D8B433B8D9BCE3A7BC3CBAF" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employee who may participate in an employee welfare benefit plan established and maintained by such group or association; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA58F7A985EB64140AF3409B173779745" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a participant of such plan subject to the eligibility determination and monitoring requirements set forth in clause (iii).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H76FD25DFF12E4D6B95446B50854EC75E" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>self-employed individual</quote> means an individual who—</text><subclause id="H188D6888F03342C8A888AFB94BC93A25" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>does not have any common law employees;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1593F962D2894A4495DBCE13397468DE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has an ownership right in a trade or business, regardless of whether such trade or business is incorporated or unincorporated;</text></subclause><subclause id="H84B7049E586747279690109E10C6E6EE"><enum>(III)</enum><text>earns wages (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/3121">section 3121(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) or self-employment income (as defined in section 1402(b) of such Code) from such trade or business; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9A00294AE4144CD9BE4C49B4C3BB6E3D"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>works at least 10 hours per week or 40 hours per month providing personal services to such trade or business.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H115B2CC7450C4A0FB2D90838EA6BB88D" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The board of a group or association of employers shall—</text><subclause id="HBBCB166DC14B415195C166E82F7E80ED" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">initially determine whether an individual meets the requirements under clause (ii) to be considered a self-employed individual for the purposes of being treated as an—</text><item id="H68DB9239E2484FA48004CB482FF9FE5D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text> employer member of such group or association (in accordance with clause (i)(I)); and</text></item><item id="HF956B4AA2DF84864881FD1BC44E5227C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>employee who may participate in the employee welfare benefit plan established and maintained by such group or association (in accordance with clause (i)(II));</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HD69A0DC01D6C4283967A8E6815C034C2"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">through reasonable monitoring procedures, periodically determine whether the individual continues to meet such requirements; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD20B1F78100E49DDBE6B237392518CA0" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the board determines that an individual no longer meets such requirements, not make such plan coverage available to such individual (or dependents thereof) for any plan year following the plan year during which the board makes such determination. If, subsequent to a determination that an individual no longer meets such requirements, such individual furnishes evidence of satisfying such requirements, such individual (and dependents thereof) shall be eligible to receive plan coverage.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DF4D71D9002426BADB72B35DE9E7820" indent="up2"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (B), all of the employees (including self-employed individuals) employed by all of the employer members (including self-employed individuals) of a group or association of employers shall be—</text><clause id="HA7003A731D30466EBDDB8CDC5297A8D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treated as employed by a single employer; and </text></clause><clause id="H1B9371E52E044D288C314CE8D5A40C45"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aggregated and counted together for purposes of any regulation of an employee welfare benefit plan established and maintained by such group or association.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43B7F40552A9495A9B385FC910DCAD0F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination of employer or joint employer status</header><text>The provision of employee welfare benefit plan coverage by a group or association of employers shall not be construed as evidence for establishing an employer or joint employer relationship under any Federal or State law.</text></subsection></section><section id="H8F6CEA7CC0A3421CA37690827635D71F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rules applicable to group health plans established and maintained by a group or association of employers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part 7 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1181">29 U.S.C. 1181</external-xref>, et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD0A00067C3C941C7B3EECD0E5E2D2640" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><section id="H98F51C94F0C543B9A42C453526825E60"><enum>736.</enum><header>Rules applicable to group health plans established and maintained by a group or association of employers</header><subsection id="H4A1B043B57A24F4F8673829C94E4EA39" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Premium rates for a group or association of employers</header><paragraph id="HA3036DB70A354459AEB999782B3979FB" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8F9E3DE7C9B4402BAB41A5DF3AFD2E2A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In the case of a group health plan established and maintained by a group or association of employers described in section 3(5)(B), such plan may—</text><clause id="HD14D95BA8F2D49F8A287E158D87C1B66" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish base premium rates formed on an actuarially sound, modified community rating methodology that considers the pooling of all plan participant claims; and</text></clause><clause id="H5C477B99080948938083B3BEA67457CB" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilize the specific risk profile of each employer member of such group or association to determine contribution rates for each such employer member’s share of a premium by actuarially adjusting above or below the established base premium rates.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16A04AEBDE7942468A74FEDF6C4D19BE" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <quote>employer member</quote> means—</text><clause id="H7492CB6114784B8284454AE28CDA3856" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employer who is a member of such group or association of employers and employs at least 1 common law employee; or</text></clause><clause id="HBEDF2CB6B3564B0B877A2B8FA6FB6546" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a group made up solely of self-employed individuals, within which all of the self-employed individual members of such group or association are aggregated together as a single employer member group, provided the group includes at least 20 self-employed individual members.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD542755E78714B4790C4D3C1501BE5DE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the event a group or association is made up solely of self-employed individuals (and no employers with at least 1 common law employee are members of such group or association), the group health plan established by such group or association shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5511122B57644990ADCDD18AE2E06C9C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat all self-employed individuals who are members of such group or association as a single risk pool;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19DC81FD71DC4A60BBF0EF00AF8CA39D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pool all plan participant claims; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H973C07128C2C47D4AFC8ABA247F74E16" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">charge each plan participant the same premium rate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BFBFAD3A4D742E9B277CEE25927C62D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Discrimination and pre-existing condition protections</header><text>A group health plan established and maintained by a group or association of employers described in section 3(5)(B) shall be prohibited from—</text><paragraph id="H37CE6985799F4864B99AC4007647C726"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establishing any rule for eligibility (including continued eligibility) of any individual (including an employee of an employer member or a self-employed individual, or a dependent of such employee or self-employed individual) to enroll for benefits under the terms of the plan that discriminates based on any health status-related factor that relates to such individual (consistent with the rules under section 702(a)(1));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDF49D6C553841C185460EB84EA16BC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>requiring an individual (including an employee of an employer member or a self-employed individual, or a dependent of such employee or self-employed individual), as a condition of enrollment or continued enrollment under the plan, to pay a premium or contribution that is greater than the premium or contribution for a similarly situated individual enrolled in the plan based on any health status-related factor that relates to such individual (consistent with the rules under section 702(b)(1)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8765AF09290B453F9E84A19B3906D69A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>denying coverage under such plan on the basis of a pre-existing condition (consistent with the rules under section 2704 of the Public Health Service Act).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H89C66FD167EC4582B1FCE630F7BD7861"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to exempt a group health plan which is an employee welfare benefit plan offered through a group or association of employers from the requirements of part 7 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (29 U.S.C. 1181 et. seq.), including the provisions of part A of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act as incorporated by reference into this Act through section 715.</text></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date>June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

