<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H16CA709EBC034C5FBE5D04FA763A6828" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3205 IH: Project Precursor Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3205</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To disrupt the international fentanyl supply chain, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HCB12A80646B04139B010695A48FA67C0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4C517DD7E6144B199828FA48F9F54CAE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="H0E8D54E7171941CA9D0683CF692A19CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Project Precursor Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H11AEB7A8EBFA48FCAB29FB3914DFFFE0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="H4C517DD7E6144B199828FA48F9F54CAE" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title and table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6C72029BDF4A476E81A8C03FD934DD8C" level="title">Title I—Department of State Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, Bureau of Global Public Affairs, and Bureau of Intelligence and Research</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H306256713F474AC19CC2C59E251E80A7" level="section">Sec. 101. Authorizations to strengthen Mexican law enforcement capacity to disrupt fentanyl supply chains.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H58AE89C63CC14993BD96C327DE74D964" level="section">Sec. 102. Public diplomacy as a weapon to delegitimize cartels and disrupt criminal recruitment.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HED2EE69A27384A00838CF1A83812B5A1" level="section">Sec. 103. Chinese operations in Mexico.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFAAC20DDF30646B6AFCE14D26D30A0AF" level="section">Sec. 104. Relevant congressional committees defined.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0E4E6A1468DE47AE8DB411AB6389A45C" level="title">Title II—Chemical Weapons Convention</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9A018535E4B742F594F97F2EAD2C74FE" level="section">Sec. 201. Actions to seek to amend the chemical weapons convention to include covered fentanyl substances on schedule 1, 2, or 3 of the annex on chemicals to the chemical weapons convention.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H81137E5FDF224AEBBEF2CD390C4390A1" level="title">Title III—Sanctions and other penalties </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6FC1C50E78B3452B95E1C548093BB9F4" level="subtitle">Subtitle A—Modification and extension of Fentanyl Sanctions Act</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H2308ADBA5BB746EEBC14884322317C04" level="section">Sec. 301. Determination and report on additional foreign opioid traffickers.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFA113CA9AA8B406684AC691E6CBEE19E" level="section">Sec. 302. Termination.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9CDC22AE138644F286A012C84A48B1FD" level="subtitle">Subtitle B—Sanctions with respect to transnational criminal organizations</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H1834FE7452D44EE9B1D9DFC72A3F16C7" level="section">Sec. 311. Imposition of sanctions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H724756157D504322BFF0AC8D2EA556DB" level="section">Sec. 312. Sanctions described.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFC68BF27E2214178A7B077DCCE3CCA1C" level="section">Sec. 313. Penalties; waivers; exceptions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8BD7550FA9BC451CAF85FF977E9CDB7A" level="section">Sec. 314. Report required.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H3ACE464F80354B97819A1C475D2FCEE5" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Definitions</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H5A875B49AFD149F4B3F7A3E93F80CF74" level="section">Sec. 321. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<title id="H6C72029BDF4A476E81A8C03FD934DD8C"><enum>I</enum><header>Department of State Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, Bureau of Global Public Affairs, and Bureau of Intelligence and Research</header> 
<section id="H306256713F474AC19CC2C59E251E80A7"><enum>101.</enum><header>Authorizations to strengthen Mexican law enforcement capacity to disrupt fentanyl supply chains</header> 
<subsection id="HA7D815F9FD5F4ABB92330D1C3A0C01CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of program</header><text>Notwithstanding section 660 of the Foreign Affairs Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2420">22 U.S.C. 2420</external-xref>), the Secretary of State, acting through the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, is authorized to carry out a program to build the capacity of Mexican law enforcement agencies to prevent the transit, trafficking, and distribution of fentanyl and its precursor chemicals and analogues into the United States from Mexico.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HED00F149B44448C6A76258F589C67998"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program elements</header><text>The program authorized by subsection (a) shall include projects and activities, at a minimum, that address—</text> 
<paragraph id="H74CEE3A6F23C47E280E60D00B42AB5C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>canine unit support for drug detection;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65BF762FD7BC4E048B7480B7E8768BE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>disrupting fentanyl trafficking in express consignment, as well as in postal, shipping, and transportation operations conducted by the Government and private business sectors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA63AF9241E13426199922B8638EC5CDD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>forensic chemist information exchanges, equipment, and drug profiling;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D736429D1724F3EBCB9E48E95B51D1E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>efforts meant to increase Mexican Federal and state laboratory forensic accreditation to identify fentanyl and other drugs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF4FD48EF420F4B17953ED41B9EBBF271"><enum>(5)</enum><text>efforts to increase the number of handheld synthetic drug detection devices;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26BDABB2E411425CAF70307C19A68F96"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the provision of equipment and training related to identifying and dismantling clandestine laboratories that produce synthetic drugs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF274BE0CD5E74933942F6B55FECFC0D2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>efforts proven to reduce diversion of precursor chemicals from licit to illicit purposes;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A83955387E34574A05F0DD059C3AF85"><enum>(8)</enum><text>precursor chemical information sharing between governments and among various agencies;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5AF370DA1BF046C9B6976FFEFC7D58FA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>maritime interdiction of synthetic drugs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FC4650E1D1D4ED0B7479314568D09C8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>cargo container control and inspection; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B62A011C5954AFCB095FAB91861A7D1"><enum>(11)</enum><text>chemical industry mapping.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE14413360F594021A27BC49C5767E720"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $64,000,000 to carry out the programs described in subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD81970A3B7BD4B5D9C041B7EAD8D13A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prioritization of Mexico in efforts To combat international fentanyl trafficking</header><text>The Secretary of State, acting through the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, shall prioritize Mexico in all efforts of the Department of State to combat international trafficking of fentanyl and other synthetic drugs by carrying out programs and activities in Mexico and throughout the greater Latin American region, in consultation with the Government of Mexico and other relevant governments, with respect to the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0C351EFB652B40ED88A7EBF44EF6E87A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Providing technical assistance and equipment, as appropriate, to strengthen the capacity of Mexican law enforcement agencies with respect to combating the trafficking of fentanyl and other synthetic drugs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCADF39DCED2F4311976B2621CC3E175E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Carrying out exchange programs for governmental and nongovernmental personnel, such as programs conducted at the International Law Enforcement Academy in El Salvador and at other locations in the United States and Mexico, to provide educational and professional development on disrupting fentanyl supply chains, interdicting fentanyl and precursor chemicals used to produce fentanyl, and other synthetic drugs at seaports and on land and permanently dismantling transnational drug trafficking organization operations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCE187D3669114D14BE014E3AD303B7E4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report on law enforcement cooperation and obstruction in Mexico</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs shall submit to the relevant congressional committees an unclassified report, that may include a classified annex, detailing—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4F6040940EAC473DAAB87A7EE67E1F30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>efforts taken by the various law enforcement agencies in Mexico to disrupt the flow of fentanyl and its precursor chemicals; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5148FACD79974B119BDEC4C2CAF0BB85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which any part of the Government of Mexico has refused to work with the United States, or otherwise obstructed, paused, or unnecessarily delayed bilateral security cooperation with respect to disrupting the flow of fentanyl and its precursor chemicals.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE449D0228FF140AEA29C4DBBBF51E09C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>United States death toll as chief monitoring and evaluation metric</header> 
<paragraph id="H8E07D02A76D541878A240430B0097989"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Metrics to evaluate efforts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Knowledge Management of the Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs shall use monthly and yearly statistics indicating the number of United States citizens who die from the consumption or ingestion of fentanyl and other illicit narcotics—</text> <subparagraph id="HEDDECDF7C52D4E8088E7CC64A4C50495"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as the primary monitoring and evaluation metric of the efforts led by such bureau in Mexico; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB699DCAE8BE40FD9E73BEA98F96F5A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to gauge whether bilateral efforts to disrupt synthetic drug production and precursor chemical transit throughout Mexico are achieving measurable desired impacts, with a rising number of United States deaths indicating a failure to achieve such impacts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2108D9E3B3B24DFEB3631331F6F2721F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Improper use of data</header><text>The Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, in its monitoring and evaluation practices, may not use data related to drug seizures or clandestine laboratory raids in Mexico as a substitute for the data described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD133E680BF484E8C811AA35E0487D148"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report on progress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the Secretary of State, acting through the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs, shall submit a report to the relevant congressional committees indicating whether, based on the statistics described in paragraph (1), its Mexico programs (including projects and activities under the program authorized by subsection (a)) are achieving desired outcomes, including a ranking of all such programs from most effective to least effective.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H58AE89C63CC14993BD96C327DE74D964"><enum>102.</enum><header>Public diplomacy as a weapon to delegitimize cartels and disrupt criminal recruitment</header> <subsection id="HAAC16530EC474E06A8BCBFFBA2E66C5E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of Global Public Affairs, in consultation with the United States Ambassador to Mexico and other diplomatic and consular posts in Mexico, as well as with the United States entertainment and media industries and private and government actors in Mexico, shall formulate and deploy a public relations campaign, the goal of which is to delegitimize and humiliate, in the Mexican and the United States social consciousness, Mexican transnational criminal organizations involved in illicit fentanyl trafficking, as well as to permanently disrupt and cripple such organizations’ ability to recruit new members.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H94ACD156252F4AE3B32A5EA567325579"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Bureau of Global Public Affairs shall brief the relevant congressional committees on the implementation of this provision.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H207E0673F0E8495D8F3E539169D82436"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Bureau of Global Public Affairs shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a report detailing the implementation of subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HED2EE69A27384A00838CF1A83812B5A1" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>103.</enum><header>Chinese operations in Mexico</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a classified report describing the operations and geographic footprint of all Chinese state- and non-state actors inside Mexico that are involved in the illegal importation, production, transport, or trafficking of fentanyl or its precursor chemicals into or through Mexico.</text></section> <section id="HFAAC20DDF30646B6AFCE14D26D30A0AF"><enum>104.</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title, the term <quote>relevant congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate. </text></section></title> 
<title id="H0E4E6A1468DE47AE8DB411AB6389A45C"><enum>II</enum><header>Chemical Weapons Convention</header> 
<section id="H9A018535E4B742F594F97F2EAD2C74FE"><enum>201.</enum><header>Actions to seek to amend the chemical weapons convention to include covered fentanyl substances on schedule 1, 2, or 3 of the annex on chemicals to the chemical weapons convention</header> 
<subsection id="H06EA88BAB4A646E5BA98E0CA7CBF7976"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Attorney General, shall use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States at the Conference of the States Parties to the Chemical Weapons Convention to seek to amend the Chemical Weapons Convention to include each covered fentanyl substance on schedule 1, 2, or 3 of the Annex on Chemicals to the Chemical Weapons Convention.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H028BE85B48BC4105A56E9BFFB76DF17D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to Congress a report on the implementation of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE33A4FA4DC484D5FA645BF867CEA1CFA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HD38BF78825354D9E8495E93D79C6C124"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>Chemical Weapons Convention</quote> means the Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, Production, Stockpiling and use of Chemical Weapons and on their Destruction, done at Paris, January 13, 1993 (commonly known as the <quote>Chemical Weapons Convention</quote>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7A9278BC32E443CEBA2AB6108B5E8C7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered fentanyl substance</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HEF940BD35FB8457E910EB163035F978C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fentanyl, including its isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of isomers, esters, and ethers, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation (as such terms are used in the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801 et seq.</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCA24973341F34E81AEBE5048DCCC9D66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any controlled substance analogue of fentanyl (as the term <quote>controlled substance analogue</quote> is defined in section 102(32) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802(32)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H399A82097823467F952A14A646459247"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any immediate precursor (as defined in section 102(23) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802(23)</external-xref>) of fentanyl.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="H81137E5FDF224AEBBEF2CD390C4390A1"><enum>III</enum><header>Sanctions and other penalties </header> 
<subtitle id="H6FC1C50E78B3452B95E1C548093BB9F4"><enum>A</enum><header>Modification and extension of Fentanyl Sanctions Act</header> 
<section id="H2308ADBA5BB746EEBC14884322317C04"><enum>301.</enum><header>Determination and report on additional foreign opioid traffickers</header> 
<subsection id="HEF173A10E91D4020B62A6C226F7379AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fentanyl Sanctions Act (title LXXII of division F of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/2301">21 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding after section 7217 the following: </text> <quoted-block id="H2FDC80CC2419477681C010EC6C5717C6" style="OLC"> <section id="H68E4C3A18AD645C583BB0CD1F804B1B6"><enum>7218.</enum><header>Determination and report on additional foreign opioid traffickers</header> <subsection id="H803C31061E824FD1A8FB0B2F636A7265"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Determination</header> <paragraph id="H1232670F01DE4A448BC88DBFB46ACF98"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall make a determination as to whether any of the foreign persons described in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCD35565ECA9045118FA2BEAF85CCD529"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a foreign opioid trafficker; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB6B4E904AA0744D69D906CF9800C740F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is engaging in any of the conduct described in Executive Order 14059 (86 Fed. Reg. 71549; relating to imposing sanctions on foreign persons involved in the global illicit drug trade) or has engaged in any such conduct in the prior 365 days.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84F69B6429654767841F84F45A7EB148"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign persons described</header><text>The foreign persons described in this paragraph are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H17899F32ECBA4E3587B4C26667CE1AA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Any foreign bank (as such term is defined in section 1(b) of the International Banking Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3101">12 U.S.C. 3101(b)</external-xref>)) that operates in—</text> 
<clause id="H1E2997DBB58643E1AAEC898D388D5041"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the People’s Republic of China; or</text></clause> <clause id="H54F9A5F91B9D46ADB8CF3E55B06A9D1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Mexico.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7E624D0E8B3F40B293F894998641DD5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any money transmitting business that processed more than $25,000,000 in transactions in—</text> <clause id="HC7F42428A03B4B668955C64DC41B5E08"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any of the 5 calendar years preceding the date of enactment of the Project Precursor Act;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2A13D0CF58324EA48C3C750615676A2D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the calendar year in which the Project Precursor Act is enacted; or</text></clause> <clause id="HE2DA31BC67F844C8A891598C92CF2D44"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any calendar year after the calendar year described in clause (ii).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68E5FA4CF50F4BDEB68398468CEAF250"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any transnational criminal organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC47718536CB741E19EF7DE455FD83845"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the Project Precursor Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report containing—</text> 
<paragraph id="H44AA990F812C4BB4B552E0C446E10209"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a list of all foreign persons that the President has determined to be foreign opioid traffickers pursuant to subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63986C5D655E479C9ED26340D727A5EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each foreign person identified on the list required by paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3590493E4F89444C96AE86B369383A65"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether the President has imposed any or all of the relevant sanctions described in section 7213 or Executive Order 14059 with respect to the foreign person; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF0FC36D73B6F4B049376FDDE6C43E10F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to which any of the sanctions described in section 7213 or Executive Order 14059 have been waived or determined not to apply due to an exception or an exercise of discretion, a description of the specific legal grounds for the waiver, exception, or exercise of discretion.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE09BCCC374E64E01AC4D2F9CF1997ACB" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header> 
<paragraph id="H69520FA84D304A14A1C0044D60B8F9F3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The report required by subsection (b) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex if necessary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD36324F6CE843C6AA38D00CC82AD0D1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The unclassified portion of the report shall be made available on a publicly available internet website of the Federal Government. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H049E81C16A5D4AE29C27147535DC264E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H1C42D75765484A0E9E5E751D351F463B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>money transmitting business</quote> means a foreign person who engages in the activities described in section 5330(d)(1)(A) of title 31, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2417EE5220204123AEFA02B83369748A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>transnational criminal organization</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 431 of the Project Precursor Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H6FAA2228898A44E09450E7E9DE07C6C8" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The table of contents in section 2(b) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref> and the table of contents in title LXXII of division F of such Public Law are each amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7217 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5C5EF99B517843C28F422E34BAF6B80E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 7218. Determination and report on additional foreign opioid traffickers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="HFA113CA9AA8B406684AC691E6CBEE19E"><enum>302.</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7233 of the Fentanyl Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/2301">21 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>7 years after the date of the enactment of the Project Precursor Act</quote>.</text></section></subtitle> <subtitle id="H9CDC22AE138644F286A012C84A48B1FD"><enum>B</enum><header>Sanctions with respect to transnational criminal organizations</header> <section id="H1834FE7452D44EE9B1D9DFC72A3F16C7"><enum>311.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President shall impose the sanctions described in section 312 with respect to any foreign person the President determines is knowingly involved in—</text> 
<paragraph id="H11F1CAAC530345B79D41AC401ADBB6EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the trafficking of fentanyl, fentanyl precursors, or other related opioids by a transnational criminal organization; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A065215338F4F98BDCCDA043D4D17BE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the activities of a transnational criminal organization relating to the trafficking of fentanyl, fentanyl precursors, or other related opioids.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H724756157D504322BFF0AC8D2EA556DB"><enum>312.</enum><header>Sanctions described</header> 
<subsection id="H0F8C25E1060F494094DAC50CE26081D1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>The President shall, pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>), block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of a foreign person described in section 311 if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF39122F80E5E48539B158054DA2B9C52"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header> <paragraph id="HC613EA2805394A0F8C4BEB0A40180FD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Visas, admission, or parole</header><text>An alien described in section 311 shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7FA24DFB99274F259AFE5F0708478CBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53250FA48F95498FADCE8BDF5E0D5E30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H23407F2970E24E478630CBAFDEA61FAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA066CC5FAC3F47FB94C250FF1F8E70EA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header> <subparagraph id="H72A481B10075437C94D7B3839C8D33CF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The visa or other entry documentation of any alien described in section 311 is subject to revocation regardless of the issue date of the visa or other entry documentation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFBE6E4AB5D0B4D40872CF3C53808D2D1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Immediate effect</header><text>A revocation under subparagraph (A) shall in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1201">8 U.S.C. 1201(i)</external-xref>)—</text> <clause id="HA29A884B5420439DA3F1BB1D0FFEEFF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>take effect immediately; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6411901051034503BEB893C6038745BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the possession of the alien.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HFC68BF27E2214178A7B077DCCE3CCA1C"><enum>313.</enum><header>Penalties; waivers; exceptions</header> <subsection id="HCA83479BF9674677A0853CB03B30D3F0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this subtitle or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out this subtitle shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 20 1705) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA1A4EFE769A24A90935F66F37E46FDF6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header> 
<paragraph id="H12FD07CEA0124A1894D5C4CEADBC76E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President may waive the imposition of sanctions under this subtitle if the President determines, and reports to the appropriate congressional committees, that—</text> <subparagraph id="H71C298C9620B430798D2C6B515B57E88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the waiver is needed for humanitarian purposes; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98D7783C88D842D4ABEEE95959A79D09"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the national emergency described in Executive Order 14059 (86 Fed. Reg. 71549; relating to imposing sanctions on foreign persons involved in the global illicit drug trade) has ended.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5E0900D66EBC49AE998F6EC57C634D6A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National security waiver</header><text>The President may waive the application of sanctions under this subtitle with respect to a foreign person if the President determines that the waiver is in the national security interest of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE5D6CF0B24A54EBF92780D1164AC407E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> 
<paragraph id="HBF162A6332774F9AA04F2D606BC0E180"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exception for intelligence activities</header><text>This subtitle shall not apply with respect to activities subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any authorized intelligence activities of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H44AF6FC78FF04C8DBC645379CA7EB174"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception for compliance with international obligations and law enforcement activities</header><text>Sanctions under this subtitle shall not apply with respect to an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H87046B164E0F44A69768B1A4733791ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success on June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations of the United States; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H942E5B54699244BF8706ABEB5C85FC39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to carry out or assist law enforcement activity of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64DC6457ED094D46B44DD5A918EAEBBB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception to comply with USMCA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions under this subtitle shall not apply in a case in which such sanctions would conflict with provisions of the USMCA (as defined in section 3 of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement Implementation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/4502">19 U.S.C. 4502</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD317B08DFF64D30A767752B11828762"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Humanitarian exemption</header><text>The President may not impose sanctions under this subtitle with respect to any person for conducting or facilitating a transaction for the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices or for the provision of humanitarian assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8BD7550FA9BC451CAF85FF977E9CDB7A"><enum>314.</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on actions taken by the President with respect to the foreign persons identified under section 311.</text></section></subtitle> <subtitle id="H3ACE464F80354B97819A1C475D2FCEE5"><enum>C</enum><header>Definitions</header> <section id="H5A875B49AFD149F4B3F7A3E93F80CF74"><enum>321.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE92DE50D00FD45B9AF35E26A60FC017F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H951C6465BD9947FDBE861FCA1A70470E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86875E90651641D6A5A7FC8D1808D787"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB511D6B75E6140AF96DD75D6726601F8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>foreign person</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 7203 of the Fentanyl Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/2302">21 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7595A8B120674EEDB51F568BDC158D65"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>knowingly</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 7203 of the Fentanyl Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/2302">21 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC27CC8AA74ED4F1185A9AD8263861739"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>trafficking</quote>, with respect to fentanyl, fentanyl precursors, or other related opioids, has the meaning given the term <quote>opioid trafficking</quote> in section 7203 of the Fentanyl Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/2302">21 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H964CEDA622D84202918179460C7982CD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <quote>transnational criminal organization</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="H2A1D44F33779496AB0C68F0187D06A28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any organization designated as a significant transnational criminal organization under part 590 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE153BF466CB74EB9AE68338A08150C95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text> <clause id="H2C12AA522E1C47BD8CF2C54F726118F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any of the organizations known as—</text> 
<subclause id="H5BEE760F426A4873AFF0FC94200E5F6F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Sinaloa Cartel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAA95FB31B43144C58EC8F1B1E99F6ACF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Jalisco New Generation Cartel;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB2A237894DDE4875B74FB7FD38143A9F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the Gulf Cartel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H93D37DEEE0E34366B5CA2E43A14535EC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the Los Zetas Cartel;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H94E5D457ED534B9EA9D2EBB68047472E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the Juarez Cartel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HEC3300FCD50C446AA92746AF7AFC6E80"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the Tijuana Cartel;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEBF645A4AE634ABFAB1C23416735E532"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the Beltran-Levya Cartel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD3D4C6009B2644D1AADA4AAA789A3741"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>La Familia Michoacana, also known as the Knights Templar Cartel; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H89FF856A5F1941A285257D991A3A174C"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>La Nueva Familia Michoacan; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H10E92946DEFB4A06A2A8947EE3ADC975"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any successor organization to an organization described in clause (i) or as otherwise determined by the President; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D6CACA094B04A0AA4613E2FD0562AD2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H3B6BA8AD6CE5422EAF9A018779C3D1C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H305636FFA20C4CBE9D05683F6744E20D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD569580029D447BD93F0B69B0319A609"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></subtitle></title> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


