<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAFC7EAB94649407FB875BA48F68BA78D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2820 IH: Justice for Jana Elementary Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2820</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide financial assistance to schools impacted by radioactive contaminants, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF645944148D54EB381E3EB2D3CE974B0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H421C6E8D4DB948EBBEDD2E2BF2C68970" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justice for Jana Elementary Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA44BAC3B87EC406491766A02760F3B9A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6AC095DEF1A24DC6A92F0114B6F4DE18"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered school</header><text>The term <term>covered school</term> means a school that is part of the Hazelwood School District in the State of Missouri. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF6109B307AD94EC9800452292669ADD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fund</header><text>The term <term>Fund</term> means the Radioactive School Assistance Fund established under section 4(a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40944E77DD7F47ACA62AE6EDCB664585"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Impacted school</header><text>The term <term>impacted school</term> means a public elementary school or secondary school—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28ADB174EA56449FA07E2AE10E863C4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that closed on or after January 1, 2020; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5732223A5A1B414F8B7902FCAEF7414F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">where the Formerly Utilized Sites Remedial Action Program of the Corps of Engineers detected radiation above background levels—</text> <clause id="HABF55513F588443BA669CA095641EF22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on school property; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H84ECC27D778C45B0AADD42BD524002EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>otherwise, within 1000 feet of a building containing classrooms or other educational facilities of the school.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BB7533C1C8548BD8CF379A1D6B772D2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Jana Elementary School</header><text>The term <term>Jana Elementary School</term> means the school located at 405 Jana Drive in Florissant, Missouri.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB9E6EAD6A58F45DB83520C51C12F1337" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBBBF6C3E80A4BD5BA95D0F7AC5C31BD"><enum>(6)</enum><header>National Contingency Plan</header><text>The term <term>National Contingency Plan</term> means the National Contingency Plan—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5DB1357BDECC466BA6A790632499033C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prepared and published under section 311(d) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1321">33 U.S.C. 1321(d)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB1850FE8A9CB49BE9F2CDFBA07646509" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>revised under section 105 of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9605">42 U.S.C. 9605</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HADDAE85907B347EFB20CF71D55162C30"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the Radioactive School Assistance Program established in accordance with section 4(b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBE5C79FE52B44FCBB640DFF95A561D4"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9AC8BA5C7A549BF96D45620DEC9B5E9"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Vicinity property</header><text>The term <term>vicinity property</term> has the meaning given the term in the Engineer Regulation ER 200–1–4 of the Corps of Engineers entitled <quote>Formerly Utilized Sites Remedial Action Program</quote> and dated August 29, 2014 (or a successor document). </text></paragraph></section> <section id="HCE77DBF610694EED969C44CF855AA3BD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Remediation of Jana Elementary School</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Consistent with the requirements and obligations under the Formerly Utilized Sites Remedial Action Program of the Corps of Engineers, the Secretary of the Army shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB63906146DF94778A79E7EDC6C4EF393"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, establish new remediation goals for Jana Elementary School that will result in the removal of all radioactive contamination at Jana Elementary School such that no portion of the site is subjected to radiation above background levels; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H643D64E8CB574DE493B1E839ECFB3EBE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>after establishing remediation goals under paragraph (1), carry out activities necessary to achieve those goals. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD0C521D3086B41C69FF676A490AE8A5E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Financial assistance for schools with radioactive contamination</header> 
<subsection id="H26D89FEB9DF34D25BBD0FFB9F9DCB7AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Radioactive School Assistance Fund</header> 
<paragraph id="H600742AD256442F1AF307334171154A9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury of the United States a fund to be known as the Radioactive School Assistance Fund to carry out the reimbursement program described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7109639C1D9C4606B6D49D559BC15A66"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>The Fund shall consist of amounts appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under section 7.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC01EEB7508DB4A1DAFBDEAEE2CB7A27E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Radioactive School Assistance Program</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish and implement a program to be known as the <quote>Radioactive School Assistance Program</quote> to provide financial assistance in accordance with subsection (c) to local educational agencies that have been financially impacted by the presence of radioactive contaminants stemming from the atomic energy activities of the United States Government.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD49831756F974C368542FF5F7490F104"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications for financial assistance</header> <paragraph id="H48E2A3DE2F2C46A28B9746C858F6689C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reimbursement for testing</header> <subparagraph id="H96E503AC52414E93B1B177B7A6E6FA12"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall provide financial assistance to each local educational agency that submits to the Secretary an application that includes—</text> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H3DCD573E1DB343529ED50CBB736679A8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a certification that the local educational agency incurred expenses while testing for radioactive contaminants at an impacted school; </text></clause> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H817675ED360C4C84A269BD4A501833CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>proof of such expenses; and</text></clause> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HBCC0C973A01D49ED858D3D3DFA982DBD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>proof that such testing—</text> <subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HC95AD98FDF904D60B09BE1D72447C490"><enum>(I)</enum><text>led to further testing under the Formerly Utilized Sites Remedial Action Program of the Corps of Engineers; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H94C734FF63534B9899DDA7EC15D4B12A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>was undertaken following testing by a private entity that found radioactive contamination.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HE8EA629E4732428D8887235E379173CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Financial assistance provided to a local educational agency under this paragraph shall not exceed the amount expended by such local educational agency to test for radioactive contamination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD7FF3EF7858542D5817BA69794F76E09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding for construction</header> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H0934073EFBBA411AAAF6DED094CF925E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall provide financial assistance for the construction of a new school building to each local educational agency that submits to the Secretary an application that includes the following:</text> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H3076AD1B5CCE42FC8F23A878B5DDAB86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A plan for the construction of a new school building.</text></clause> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HFCA99B4FFA404A8896F3FED5F13B0B2A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Documentation that a school under the jurisdiction of the local educational agency is an impacted school.</text></clause> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HEB4D9C66D1D447D28E0B54606D22ABC6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A budget for the construction of a new school building.</text></clause> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H80BF21E9153249A795B8C386467019E8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A certification that the local educational agency shall only use financial assistance provided under this paragraph for 1 or more of the following purposes:</text> <subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H6811335DD4864E289EF6FBF61AA90858"><enum>(I)</enum><text>To purchase land for the construction of a new school building.</text></subclause> 
<subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H38FD63C066A741C196F6E262FB7E7440"><enum>(II)</enum><text>To construct a new school building to replace an impacted school.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD62D5E9740BD4AB2B9D7D1727EEB84AD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitations</header> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H8AE7972887E4451AB0D45DA8D6F502BE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Amount of funding</header><text>Financial assistance provided to a local educational agency under this paragraph shall not exceed $20,000,000 for each impacted school.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB13E3A223F0544C0A6FDBB2FA601101C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A local educational agency that receives financial assistance under this paragraph may only use such financial assistance for 1 or more of the following purposes:</text> <subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HAEC61C159C4B4C18B33EFDC762D739BE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>To purchase land for the construction of a new school building.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5BCB5F8C9AEE4CBBB47ADAC66419E40F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(II)</enum><text>To construct a new school building to replace an impacted school. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HF7F26D55849F4FA69EC20B60A57BFC17"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>The Secretary may not reject an application submitted by a local educational agency for financial assistance under this subsection due to prior remediation by the Corps of Engineers or any other relevant Federal agency of an impacted school under the jurisdiction of such local educational agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H557E430590EE419F857481D7C3BCB872"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the Program, which shall include—</text> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H8E88971E0BB74CAFB55EF96583F406F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the number of applications submitted under this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H4F27AC3F14944F2EA7022311015106E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the amount of financial assistance provided to local educational agencies under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE46BD78382D748278E37CFFEECB08492"><enum>5.</enum><header>Investigation of schools in Hazelwood School District for contaminants</header> <subsection id="H9FC63C72D2434657B850375B06AB40E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, each covered school shall be designated as a vicinity property of the St. Louis Airport Site of the Formerly Utilized Sites Remedial Action Program of the Corps of Engineers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71A95CA681324D1C8047387936F7F44A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investigation</header> 
<paragraph id="H44A321A2453E441CB7487ACC518217B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Army shall investigate and characterize each covered school in accordance with the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9601">42 U.S.C. 9601 et seq.</external-xref>) and the National Contingency Plan, including, at a minimum, carrying out a preliminary assessment and site inspection of each covered school.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E569FA6784A4B7CBB6E0BB0FE2B8DBE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>An investigation of a covered school under paragraph (1) shall include on-site investigatory efforts and sampling in accordance with section 300.420(c)(2) of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8FF58CACC24E4990B2714EC992A1AC5D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary of the Army shall develop and make available to the public, for each covered school, a report that includes the results of the investigation under subsection (b), including—</text> <paragraph id="H15287FA1CC60432EAE738B6093E08E13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the on-site investigatory efforts;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94B7880A6E034E78AF6C1CF6B6DB4ECC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a summary of the results of sampling under paragraph (2) of that subsection for contaminants of concern, including the average and highest detected levels of each contaminant of concern; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H259F3AC15D5946CFA958E9150E69AA0D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an evaluation of the danger posed to students and employees of the covered school by the levels of contamination.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H91DEB745788E48B9A1BAF74490D773DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Community relations</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary of the Army shall comply with all applicable requirements relating to community relations and public notification under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9601">42 U.S.C. 9601 et seq.</external-xref>), section 311 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1321">33 U.S.C. 1321</external-xref>), and sections 300.415, 300.430, and 300.435 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></subsection></section> <section id="HAC5F1DB0571744E38D8BED04513072D0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Review and report of radioactive testing at Jana Elementary School</header> <subsection id="HBFCC63C06C06460399108336F09D05AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall review the methodology and results of all tests for radioactive contaminants conducted at Jana Elementary School, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA889D993A7D640838E57B1474DBE3800"><enum>(1)</enum><text>tests conducted by the Corps of Engineers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H742954C3819A44E1AC504CE885324C41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>tests conducted by Boston Chemical Data Corporation; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4681C466D274436DA4330A69144A188B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>tests commissioned by the Hazelwood School District in the State of Missouri.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDC59303D2F2D4CEAAC777F4424F1C5B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="HE74AA2DC07584AB69DADAFBED0CDB0E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the review required by subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF0D53810B7AF4C128FAF44E2E7E603EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H4B0F00FB64154C93AE162FF632E731B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for each test described in subsection (a), an evaluation of—</text> 
<clause id="H80C01323F6F848EEAB75D5AE31A6FC0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reliability of the methodology used—</text> <subclause id="H939D3890A4E94E0F857F2F8B281C7D4C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to conduct such test; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1AA912DFEAE14B3C971FBCCEBED9FA58"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to evaluate the results of such test; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HF72B49C40F0040ECBF68078DB4E8D8A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the reliability of the opinions contained in any report summarizing the test; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H23412290B84B43149AAC8DEEC586E31B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an evaluation of the danger posed to children by any radioactive contaminants found at Jana Elementary School.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H6C4CB7AA09D849E499B5D9CA52C1D381"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for fiscal year 2023 $25,000,000 to carry out this Act.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


