<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3969583FE8544CE69ACDFA1A14F75F87" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6791 IH: Artificial Intelligence Literacy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6791</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Digital Equity Act of 2021 to facilitate artificial intelligence literacy opportunities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H97E33FAFC3C94470B69C810811AC24F0" style="OLC"><section id="H0C18191B81694D97AF539064488A56BF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence Literacy Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7CD87016BCAA4B2B888234A093032137"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H88A08E8C54224856809A58BD623FC621"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Artificial intelligence (AI) is a transformative technology that affects nearly every aspect of the United States economy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEBAA124C4444C3ABCB2C40EB8718CC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As AI becomes increasingly ubiquitous, AI literacy will become as important as digital literacy is today.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF01CF1336A1744448C1B0D7DF670395E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Technological leadership in AI is an economic and national security imperative. Maintaining this leadership requires a sufficient workforce to research and develop AI capabilities. Such a workforce must contain both technical talent, such as computer engineers and data scientists, and nontechnical talent, such as product managers and sales engineers, who understand AI.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC935685FA9894AB986D25BC5A895F229"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Effective AI literacy initiatives encompass not only technical training but also include comprehensive education about the potential benefits and risks associated with AI technologies. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF70F406FDD314D2C9CE1CAAB43D86819"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Informed developers and consumers of AI technologies can help mitigate potential risks and biases often found in systems that utilize AI.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC74C7CF39DB478BA8531D2104AA4FB1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Basic AI literacy is critical to ensuring that Americans have the tools and knowledge needed to navigate the economy and digital world. With AI being increasingly adopted by consumer-facing companies and widely used tools on the internet, Americans of all ages and occupations should have the skills and tools needed to understand AI and its limitations at a basic level as well as skills to identify when AI is being employed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1329D8A697949D6AABDC2ABC6023254"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Successful AI literacy initiatives will prepare Americans of all ages and technical backgrounds to safely navigate AI tools and AI-enabled technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H057601D3928340C8A4555BD95BD2B8A0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Communities most often negatively impacted by AI-enabled technologies often have the least access to AI education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H962218514C354B09AD66A347CBBB0B39"><enum>(9)</enum><text>AI literacy initiatives must engage stakeholders and communities in all stages, and specific outreach efforts should be made for communities disproportionately impacted by the digital divide, including minority and rural communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB7E9BFD7E0C4B038F26C23E6D539FE1"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to a survey of adults commissioned by Jobs for the Future, a non-profit organization with a focus on workforce development and education, 58 percent believe that learning opportunities around AI should be offered to workers, 53 percent believe that such opportunities should be available to learners, and 54 percent believe that they would feel more prepared for the future impact of AI if they were given learning tools for it.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H112FE04C21224B169420C3FED3A5DE4D"><enum>(11)</enum><text>As of 2018, the United States AI workforce stood at about 14,000,000 workers, or about 9 percent of total employment. From 2019 to 2029, demand for AI occupations is projected to grow twice as fast as for all occupations in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5979B53DAC64F75BD30DCCF51668CAE"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In 2021, Black students made up only 7.5 percent of AI-related bachelor’s degrees despite making up 14 percent of the population. While women account for 60 percent of college graduates, they constitute only 40 percent of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics graduates and 25 percent of graduates in AI fields. Efforts in AI literacy can help to bridge stark differences in attainment across demographic groups.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08557AC50E554D5D98267FEE03494C7A"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The need for a strong workforce of AI workers, as well as an AI-literate population, requires investment in AI literacy education.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H51329190CA4D44C89E9C10D42C72A431"><enum>3.</enum><header>Digital literacy, artificial intelligence, and competitive grant program</header><subsection id="H769DB7D4EDA24B2BB95DEB89122355B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Digital literacy with respect to artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 60302 of the Digital Equity Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1721">47 U.S.C. 1721</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7D829395340D4CBAA9747808AA1CBFD3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (12) by inserting <quote>, including the skills associated with artificial intelligence literacy</quote> before the period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C178EB51F8A4D2E8480C9259B8D6499"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (5) through (23), as amended by paragraph (1) of this subsection, as paragraphs (6) through (24), respectively, and inserting after paragraph (4) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H32B65DDC6138464BAED0C6D9AF427664" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H993200E5D408424A927E69D7D0AEE80A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence literacy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>artificial intelligence literacy</quote> means the skills associated with the ability to comprehend the basic principles, concepts, and applications of artificial intelligence, as well as the implications, limitations, and ethical considerations associated with the use of artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3EC3DF9D457E491BA329635A1B15FF0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Sections 60304 and 60305 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1723">47 U.S.C. 1723</external-xref>, 1724) are amended by striking <quote>60302(8)</quote> and inserting <quote>60302(9)</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD7245C81DA374009A068701666BD9B34"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence literacy in the digital equity competitive grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 60305(d)(2)(A) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1724">47 U.S.C. 1724(d)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by redesignating clause (vi) as clause (x) and inserting after clause (v) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B339FF9EF0F4A16AD68AFA2D9847B59"><clause id="HEA0251E3F9EB429FB7296902363F9AF7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a grant made to increase artificial intelligence literacy in public elementary and secondary schools—</text><subclause id="H8FB1279EB4634F9C808E441795007A5F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to provide teachers training and certification to support artificial intelligence literacy efforts in schools;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB6E7F86F661D4099BE9399A412B7842A"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to facilitate the attendance of teachers at professional development courses, workshops, and conferences related to artificial intelligence education, including professional development related to artificial intelligence course design and fee-based professional development;</text></subclause><subclause id="H22E867C0EDD94445B1B45B0E66DC6690"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to schools without resources for computer science education, to use best practices to develop and design computer science course materials needed for artificial intelligence education;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAE0C9986FB4C43BA8FCE81AD69A9954D"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>to support partnerships with the private sector to facilitate artificial intelligence education;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF077909D4F904A15A023670D4DE22369"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to equip schools with labs to provide students hands-on artificial intelligence learning experiences; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HF5F468FD990A44E299C4C27FE747A44A"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>to develop virtual learning platforms that facilitate remote and individualized artificial intelligence education opportunities.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H47EE26F152D34021B635DE83ECECCF1F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a grant made to increase artificial intelligence literacy in community colleges—</text><subclause id="HD25F974F1F8F4E578364A7156CC2980F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to develop and implement an interdisciplinary literacy program with respect to artificial intelligence for non-traditional learners, including through partnerships with non-profit educational organizations;</text></subclause><subclause id="H8F445B533553486DB5A3E83B35172ABA"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to develop labs to provide students hands-on artificial intelligence learning experiences; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HFC760EB77AE147168C25CE1A0F237BE3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to develop virtual learning platforms that facilitate remote and individualized artificial intelligence education opportunities.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0BC7342A01EF4EADB0E42E72C73346BC"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a grant made to increase artificial intelligence literacy in institutions of higher education—</text><subclause id="H24F3C9F52F6C478CB5B8EB5CC3682812"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to develop labs to provide students hands-on artificial intelligence learning experiences;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD50487F2D9FF44EF82AFC8E49FEBA799"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to develop virtual learning platforms that facilitate remote and individualized artificial intelligence education opportunities; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H7100BAFEBACE4391A401202BB107A2F1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to develop programming and pedagogical tools with respect to artificial intelligence education and instruction for the benefit of elementary school and secondary school teachers and community educators.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H76E468024AD24679913F839AD93FC815"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>In the case of a grant made to a community anchor institution, other than a school, community college, or institution of higher education, to increase artificial intelligence literacy in covered populations—</text><subclause id="H240AB9EAE68C4EC78CD11FFF559A40B5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to provide training and certification with respect to artificial intelligence education and instruction to employees of the community anchor institution; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H69A419D2339144C7813069F95440557A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to develop and implement artificial intelligence learning experiences and educational programming to the community served by the community anchor institution.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA10C9E41D46046BAA5CCB72631480E90"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Section 60305 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1724">47 U.S.C. 1724</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1CE81B53355D45E5B4EA383FFFB53913" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HE42121C0FB3741E986FC43A82EF48CB7"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Annual report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each year of the 4-year period described in subsection (d)(2)(D), the Assistant Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a written report—</text><paragraph id="HA3AA33E4E74A415ABE6B0AF322011DB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>summarizing and analyzing the reports submitted to the Assistant Secretary pursuant to subsection (h) for that year; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD93E5B8FC0D4069A560F0D7BADFBFEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifying any specific use described by a report submitted pursuant to subsection (h) that the Assistant Secretary recommends for expansion or modification to benefit greater populations.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

