<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCA03ED8FB730480AA2351AB2C9F9823D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2384 IH: Complete American Pipelines Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2384</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To lower energy costs by ending judicial review for legacy projects and providing jurisdiction to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H71C658C72EE543D0BE449F61CBAFAAD8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7D3A93C234A841A28D2BDBFD1E0F3A0D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Complete American Pipelines Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H350E37D5D16342648F56EA50CCB54089"><enum>2.</enum><header>Legacy projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for any project that, prior to January 1, 2018, has been granted a certificate of public convenience and necessity by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission pursuant to section 7(c) of the Natural Gas Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/717f">15 U.S.C. 717f(c)</external-xref>), and where such certificate of public convenience and necessity is still in effect—</text> 
<paragraph id="H14AC6C05210E4818AA3AD30146E0593B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such project shall be constructed expeditiously in the location and form specified in such certificate of public convenience and necessity or any amendment or authorization issued pursuant thereto, and consistent with other applicable permits;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7A0C7CCF00BE408B9046C062FA710A67"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such certificate of public convenience and necessity and any amendment, extension of time, or other authorization issued pursuant to or related thereto, and any order or action of a Federal agency or State administrative agency acting pursuant to Federal law for such project that is required to complete construction of such project, issued prior to or subsequent to the enactment of this section, shall not be subject to judicial review in any court, and any action (including any action pending in a court as of the date of enactment of this section) seeking judicial review of such an agency order or action shall not be filed or maintained in any court and shall be promptly dismissed; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F18D690F750403E9EF9C7753AEDE5DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit shall have original and exclusive jurisdiction over any claim alleging the invalidity of this section or that an action is beyond the scope of authority conferred by this section.</text> </paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

