<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDAD92EEED9004B57A0DAA6A4E3D125F6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1825 IH: Right to Try Clarification Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1825</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230328">March 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To clarify that the Federal Right to Try law applies to schedule I substances for which a phase I clinical trial has been completed and to provide access for eligible patients to such substances pursuant to the Federal Right to Try law.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H91D76BA888824E23B71A46CA8D877F49" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0181FA8569DF4F608E7757086BD2184C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Right to Try Clarification Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA51148CE982B4419B0E8E56F63C89201"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="H26109D04EE81435589FE96CEC0B9298C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Trickett Wendler, Frank Mongiello, Jordan McLinn, and Matthew Bellina Right to Try Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/176">Public Law 115–176</external-xref>) was enacted in 2018. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF95D899BE804345862011AEC22D1453"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 561B of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb-0a">21 U.S.C. 360bbb–0a</external-xref>), as added by the Act described in paragraph (1) (referred to in this section as the <quote>Federal Right to Try law</quote>), does not exclude from the application of such law schedule I substances for which a phase I clinical trial has been completed. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD0C59A569BC04174A00093ECA86B6DF3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Multiple schedule I drugs have progressed through phase I clinical trials and have been designated by the Food and Drug Administration as breakthrough therapies under section 506 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/356">21 U.S.C. 356</external-xref>) because of preliminary clinical evidence indicating that such drugs demonstrate substantial improvement over existing therapies, but eligible patients have not been permitted access to these drugs pursuant to the Federal Right to Try law.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H12CF8BE14629468E96A9D727C2371845"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendment to Federal Right to Try law</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 561B(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (21 U.S.C. 360bbb–0a(b)) is amended by inserting <quote>any provision of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801 et seq.</external-xref>) that prohibits the unauthorized use, possession, distribution, dispensation, or transportation of an eligible investigational drug,</quote> before <quote>and parts</quote>. </text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

