<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9E7673B5084C475AAA2C1EC8F8944A62" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 659 IH: Forbidding Airlines from Imposing Ridiculous Fees Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 659</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit air carriers from imposing fees that are not reasonable and proportional to the costs incurred by the air carriers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H21D0CE7023F849B593DBAD362F72ADDF" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HB586AD5436CE495C9A6A67AF2739AF2B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Forbidding Airlines from Imposing Ridiculous Fees Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAIR Fees Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H653615842203426AA22B7B3EEBB23039"><enum>2.</enum><header>Regulations prohibiting the imposition of fees that are not reasonable and proportional to the costs incurred</header><subsection id="H38DA41E044D342B5A0EF03D29FEAAB56"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall prescribe regulations—</text><paragraph id="HCE743B37E5ED45BF890C2F82C6C27E75"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prohibiting an air carrier from imposing fees described in subsection (b) that are unreasonable or disproportional to the costs incurred by the air carrier; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD47B45A270B146B78842BBF374281154"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing standards for assessing whether such fees are reasonable and proportional to the costs incurred by the air carrier.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22B20971115D44B089D867835C849252"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fees described</header><text>The fees described in this subsection are—</text><paragraph id="HF1ED0AE8B2CE480793E220AD11C60570"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any fee for a change or cancellation of a reservation for a flight in passenger air transportation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA335D54DA9E04D6F884106A91CAB2EC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any fee relating to checked or carry-on baggage to be transported on a flight in passenger air transportation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE4350EEFB32473AABE8CF81E597C51C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any fee relating to the choice or assignment of seats on a flight in passenger air transportation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58509EDE00414E11B2BFBDD5E3614638"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other fee imposed by an air carrier relating to a flight in passenger air transportation. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1B0C2E5AB174995A5E7BB2CC8C09195"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In establishing the standards required by subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall consider—</text><paragraph id="H5C06EA716C99470CA20C53AAE249F0A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to a fee described in subsection (b)(1) imposed by an air carrier for a change or cancellation of a flight reservation—</text><subparagraph id="H5928DB6E93F6427484C95C610AD46F8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any net benefit or cost to the air carrier from the change or cancellation, taking into consideration—</text><clause id="HB6F0C0AAF3DC4766954752092E210F9D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the ability of the air carrier to anticipate the expected average number of cancellations and changes and make reservations accordingly;</text></clause><clause id="H1F8FF90AC57A47EA84117AD4026583B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the ability of the air carrier to fill a seat made available by a change or cancellation;</text></clause><clause id="H69B7EF790ED0427499F7E00A1ADF1914"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any difference in the fare likely to be paid for a ticket sold to another passenger for a seat made available by the change or cancellation, as compared to the fare that was paid for the seat for which the reservation was changed or canceled; and</text></clause><clause id="HC2C72C57255C4F55AC9C6A15B729DD08"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the likelihood that the passenger changing or canceling the reservation will, as a result, fill a seat on another flight by the same air carrier; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H517EA67FFE3945A7AFD98C73F151FBDE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the costs of processing the change or cancellation electronically; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8DFFB1AB32D4293B20E443E9DCF4560"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any related labor costs;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H888CE0BCE03444BF96D03DA0A11C240E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to a fee described in subsection (b)(2) imposed by an air carrier relating to checked baggage—</text><subparagraph id="H76476F0FB9004F4BA0B32A0DA78FDC7F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the costs of processing checked baggage electronically; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95725D31CADA487BA96F034A3C53AC42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any related labor costs;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6739205FE934BE497CEDB320962B986"><enum>(3)</enum><text>with respect to a fee described in subsection (b)(3) imposed by an air carrier relating to the choice or assignment of seats on a flight in passenger air transportation, ensuring that passengers traveling with children age 13 or younger are able to be seated with those children at no additional charge to the passengers traveling with such children or to any other passenger traveling on the flight involved; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAB76726AA4E42D2BE80C7061B8E3868"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other considerations the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H13C09C91E46940B690615CD4387B01A9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Updated regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall update the standards required by subsection (a)(2) not less frequently than every 3 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD31D2E8A9B42466BBB1B020BB6876A88"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB80F7F200C0A4E20AB17398ADC10F4B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Air carrier</header><text>The term <term>air carrier</term> means any air carrier that holds an air carrier certificate under section 41101 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19840C3C59BB4A68999408EE6536482B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Passenger air transportation</header><text>The term <term>passenger air transportation</term> means, with respect to the transportation of passengers by aircraft as a common carrier for compensation, foreign air transportation, interstate air transportation, and intrastate air transportation, as such terms are defined in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

