<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE2EFEB16AD17444A96BAAD6DD5A345A9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3015 IH: Safeguarding Our Forces Abroad Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3015</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reduce the number of members of the Armed Forces stationed in certain foreign countries with which the United States does not have a proper and enforceable Status of Forces Agreement, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9E079CE2E3AD4BB2815AA18E500AC96C" style="OLC"><section id="H7335FABA84234B74A1ACE8183AB4F855" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safeguarding Our Forces Abroad Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SOFA Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H9A7C322DB8E1487BA27633B713489EB7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reduction of personnel stationed in foreign countries</header><subsection id="HE72DCF99622D4E2396298E73D25CF59A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall reduce, at a rate of 1 percent each month, the number of members of the Armed Forces stationed in each covered foreign country with which a binding and enforceable Status of Forces Agreement is not in place that—</text><paragraph id="HC749A3FA18A1466B98EAA50417367833"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prohibits the government of such country, including any jurisdiction within such country, from undertaking pretrial detention of any member of the Armed Forces subject to an accusation of committing a non-violent crime;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9795B93471164639B04D2181F97637D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">guarantees to any member of the Armed Forces who is accused of a crime and whose liberty is at risk the right to immediately have access to and the presence of counsel of choice during all stages of the legal process, including investigations and interrogations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59F22932E6EA496C9382D453D62FBC11"><enum>(3)</enum><text>guarantees to any member of the Armed Forces who is accused of a crime and whose liberty is at risk the right to immediately have access to appropriate language translation services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31A702DD6D774039903F9246D2140DFF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">guarantees that any such accused member of the Armed Forces may not be compelled to be a witness against themselves and will be protected from confessions obtained through torture, coercion, threats, violence, or any means of improper influence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDDE77861F0E4D7C82B9D962437802B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered foreign country</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered foreign country</quote> means a foreign country in which at least 1,000 members of the Armed Forces were stationed in the previous fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8CA33E12DE2548A09F00DBD33A02B478"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The requirement to draw down the number of members of the Armed Forces stationed in a covered foreign country under subsection (a) may be waived if the Secretary of Defense certifies to the Chair and Ranking Member of the Committees on Armed Services of the House of Representatives and of the Senate that it is in the national security interests of the United States to avoid such a reduction in forces.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

