<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB29BD2128C89469EA4BFA7E98158B5FF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1064 IH: Ensuring Military Readiness Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1064</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide requirements related to the eligibility of transgender individuals from serving in the Armed Forces.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8ACB90CB10A54742B0308DF346CD74A8" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H2D1B55F175E5488190BB6FDD7143AD3C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Military Readiness Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H26853107D1B145C0AC4EE990D31E36D4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitations on military service by transgender individuals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall prescribe regulations regarding transgender service as follows:</text><paragraph id="H825BF08510964F1F9CCE9E80E5175346"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transgender persons with a history of diagnosis of gender dysphoria are disqualified from military service except under the following limited circumstances:</text><subparagraph id="H60EF76A395EE4240B2A1EB13EDDF32A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Individuals may serve in the Armed Forces if they have been stable for 36 consecutive months in their biological sex prior to accession.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2440E10014D14C2D8874FB27179B7947"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Members of the Armed Forces diagnosed with gender dysphoria after entering into service may be retained if they do not require a change of gender and remain deployable within applicable retention standards. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7F3FDB0E6734C758AF746F0A645C997"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Members of the Armed Forces serving as of the date of the enactment of this Act who have been diagnosed with gender dysphoria may continue to serve in their current gender marker in the Defense Enrollment Eligibility Reporting System (DEERS) and receive medically necessary treatment for gender dysphoria. Such treatment may not include gender reassignment surgery or the commencement of hormone therapy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0D9FBDFC70B429DA0A8A96D0A751156"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Transgender persons who require or have undergone gender transition are disqualified from military service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF577C420D1C54D5D8F0FD7E1D40D0168"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Transgender persons without a history or diagnosis of gender dysphoria, who are otherwise qualified for service and meet all physical and mental requirements, may serve in the Armed Forces in their biological sex. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

