<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB9614FD58230450896DA9165CCB644B6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 984 IH: Commitment to Veteran Support and Outreach Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 984</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230210">February 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to authorize the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to award grants to States to improve outreach to veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2E79D29C237B439DB24B48248E85BBBD" style="OLC"><section id="H594E15AF0BCB48138574EE977E0A2DDD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Commitment to Veteran Support and Outreach Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HBA8B433585D54BD1A361702D5B477F21"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority for Secretary of Veterans Affairs to award grants to States and Indian Tribes to improve outreach to veterans</header><subsection id="H474A1E6E540E42E3A522AE361863C083"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/63">Chapter 63</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF927AB9731F54A049504B02CCC990135"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 6307 and 6308 and sections 6308 and 6309, respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A2224E0CD044715A733D684ADD98DAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 6306 the following new section 6307:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H914D0F7B01C34106BE4F38CA85AD46C5"><section id="H8D5A390043A646A6A36F05CB8A2982A7"><enum>6307.</enum><header>Grants to States and Indian Tribes to improve outreach to veterans</header><subsection id="H9C7B4323515747DFBC26912F328E794B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the purpose of this section to provide for assistance by the Secretary to States and Indian Tribes to carry out programs that—</text><paragraph id="H3CB4E21B1B0B40939491E8F75CD2C9CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improve outreach and assistance to veterans and the spouses, children, and parents of veterans, to ensure that such individuals are fully informed about any veterans and veterans-related benefits and programs (including veterans programs of a State or Indian Tribe) for which they may be eligible; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H290A5119AFF0409A84B73BE2213E1390"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate opportunities for such individuals to receive competent, qualified services in the preparation, presentation, and prosecution of veterans benefits claims.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1BE18FAABF1145C19095EEF8612CEA5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award grants under this section to States and Indian Tribes—</text><paragraph id="HDE1C6BBD19FC41908EA88BD35DFBD5FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to carry out, coordinate, improve, or otherwise enhance outreach activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EEFCF97B4A3440CB1B69744F559D689"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to increase the number of county or Tribal veterans service officers serving in the State or Indian Tribe by hiring new, additional such officers; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A1DA4EB7E584A0BBB17A25E3EA35022"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to expand, carry out, coordinate, improve, or otherwise enhance existing programs, activities, and services of the existing organization of the State or Indian Tribe that has been recognized by the Department of Veterans Affairs pursuant to section 5902, in the preparation, presentation, and prosecution of claims for veterans benefits through representatives who hold positions as county or Tribal veterans service officers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA971FFCA60BB44EA95A0B8F5E63A320C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA6B169EAFBAF4F6587DAF8AEC571065E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under this section, a State or Indian Tribe shall submit to the Secretary an application therefor at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A6CB276DDD9468C9F81BF798DE0D13D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each application submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H23372771369F4905ABEE40D3C2A1852E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed plan for the use of the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66BD209CEF9247ED97D54A9E963CBE2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the programs through which the State or Indian Tribe will meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (i).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1F87DE4D80442868A46F017777CD34D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of how the State or Indian Tribe will distribute grant amounts equitably among counties (or Tribal lands, as the case may be) with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H960DC46DE1F944018AC5E5D2B72330DE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A plan for how the grant will be used to meet the unique needs of American Indian or Alaska Native veterans, elderly veterans, women veterans, and veterans from other underserved communities. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D3CA2FBA0F649ADAC4AD91F4AE0054D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to ensure that grants awarded under this section are equitably distributed among States and Indian Tribes with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6FD6694693664C22998AB2B3414E33CA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary shall prioritize awarding grants under this section that will serve the following areas: </text><paragraph id="HF77A4B31F8D84572A2515F288048FA0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Areas with a critical shortage of county or Tribal veterans service officers. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AD5F29E318F4F57B7408A140F2BF6E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Areas with high rates of—</text><subparagraph id="H323A6A56A48B452D8365603F071F3145"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suicide among veterans; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H293B902597A6473BA1C00A86763CF9E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>referrals to the Veterans Crisis Line. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H49C09A3313A9444081E6C5E77D6DF7EF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of county or Tribal veterans service officers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or Indian Tribe that receives a grant under this section to carry out an activity described in subsection (b)(1) may only carry out the activity through—</text><paragraph id="H1ACB6BD6246F4E7586C5A66A2472C63C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a county or Tribal veterans service officer of the State or Indian Tribe; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA78E6BA3FBCC45D9B40160FE5527BEA9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the State or Indian Tribe does not have a county or Tribal veterans service officer, or if the county or Tribal veterans service officers of the State or Indian Tribe cover only a portion of that State or Indian Tribe, an appropriate entity of a State, local, or Tribal government, as determined by the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69A9234471BB4447A2429583CB49D9D9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Required activities</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used—</text><paragraph id="H4B781D08AF8E4952A83EE940CD2F5331"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to expand existing programs, activities, and services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8E0E47EEC8B4528BED6D019335265FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to hire and maintain new, additional county or Tribal veterans service officers; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B439E53DBA4D26ACE5ADDFBDA6E7C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for travel and transportation to facilitate carrying out paragraph (1) or (2). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA684DB57FEF94177B9B9108B94FA1F4A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Other permissible activities</header><text>A grant under this section may be used to provide education and training, including on-the-job training, for State, county, local, and Tribal government employees who provide (or when trained will provide) veterans outreach services in order for those employees to obtain and maintain accreditation in accordance with procedures approved by the Secretary. </text></subsection><subsection id="H66E67BDE66AA48BEA48E60597F643536"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Outcome measures</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7F8DE4463FBA43CF8D20C12C17276054"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall develop and provide to each State or Indian Tribe that receives a grant under this section written guidance on the following: </text><subparagraph id="H6779A9D5B9494811ADDC25C43604E65D" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Outcome measures. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H02A3B42DF1814845B10036555D504D7A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Policies of the Department. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="HC250F2D9A1DA418FA9E9F3C5CD111EA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In developing outcome measures under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider the following goals: </text><subparagraph id="H0B19A0DD4DFC44D594CC9B5D230CA360"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Increasing the use of veterans and veterans-related benefits, particularly among vulnerable populations. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC42B055BAA347979FA594AA5A008EB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Increasing the number of county and Tribal veterans service officers recognized by the Secretary for the representation of veterans under chapter 59 of this title. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A70001E1AB547B28872357E9F129854"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Tracking requirements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H69E1032D8E9248BD8B609967A4DE3967"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each grant awarded under this section, the Secretary shall track the use of veterans benefits among the population served by the grant, including the average period of time between the date on which a veteran or other eligible claimant applies for such a benefit and the date on which the veteran or other eligible claimant receives the benefit, disaggregated by type of benefit. </text></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H06244CF18B33475993B6BC4425F47B5F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than annually during the life of the grant program established under this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on—</text><subparagraph id="H4C5B2130AE3145A8B4A01AA36E0C24E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the information tracked under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H331FB6B2BC5C49BDA1C0935657C82C20"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how the grants awarded under this section serve the unique needs of American Indian or Alaska Native veterans, elderly veterans, women veterans, and veterans from other underserved communities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3C69C475CD745A5A55161485948E9EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>other information provided by States and Indian Tribes pursuant to the grant reporting requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD64BABC1FD346FCA28F23E94D76675E"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Performance review</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC764541AAB3848B383FD58FAF8885BCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall— </text><subparagraph id="H518ABC6F42FA4EDAB3F8333DBC5FD12D" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the performance of each State or Indian Tribe that receives a grant under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HB939FFA30B3042E990C2E98E9B702BBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make information regarding such performance publicly available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44796EE43008457A8FB4951AB7B13C60"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Remediation plan</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H510A32ED93B847AE8AA241F3C2C75B70"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a State or Indian Tribe that receives a grant under this section and does not meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (i), the Secretary shall require the State or Indian Tribe to submit a remediation plan under which the State or Indian Tribe shall describe how and when it plans to meet such outcome measures. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H174610BB74AE425BB3E36BC319C35AC6" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary may not award a subsequent grant under this section to a State or Indian Tribe described in paragraph (1) unless the Secretary approves the remediation plan submitted by the State of Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82FAC65C837A413C959ED90BBAFB1F45"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded under this section may not exceed 10 percent of amounts made available for grants under this section for the fiscal year in which the grant is awarded. </text></subsection><subsection id="H278ADB06EDCF420F866722DB4F1BD67F"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant State and local funding that is otherwise available. </text></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H541869F976E04F33942856497AF888BC"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section: </text><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H973C61F50243466783CF5B7DB15B287C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>county or Tribal veterans service officer</term> includes a local equivalent veterans service officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H905F7ECC8BC34158ABD634356CB08D57"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10E2A1869A89403D864E99FCC087CBB4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> includes the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEED9F67C3A2A49A2A04DDE036B67136C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4371D52B1B845C5869B793E8F1FE188"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 63 of such title is amended by striking the items relating to sections 6307 and 6308 and inserting the following new items:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57B3B453F5F546DE8A61BA77AFD0300F"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">6307. Grants to States and Indian Tribes to improve outreach to veterans.</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">6308. Outreach for eligible dependents.</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">6309. Biennial report to Congress.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H852763299D3C46A7BAFF9E4B28FD4794"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, $50,000,000 to carry out section 6307 of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H3FEFB1BB4EE748BA852E3FADEBF2DEA5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of additional full-Time equivalent employee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During fiscal years 2024 through 2028, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may hire two or more additional full-time equivalent employees in the Office of the General Counsel of the Department of Veterans Affairs, as compared to the number of full-time equivalent employees that would otherwise be authorized for such office, to carry out duties under the accreditation, discipline, and fees program.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

