<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1D9077C6372B48A6B4907AD794A0E9C2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6642 IH: Grant Recipient Accountability for Necessary Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6642</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the disclosure of foreign support provided to a recipient after the award of a research and development award, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9A195C828BE4445D878C323B22693912" style="OLC"><section id="H0DCBD62C951848F4AB7F05DC7DC30454" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grant Recipient Accountability for Necessary Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GRANT Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2AD023359104498EA668E6413C0DFF8C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H3E945BBBA2D84B7297E93A231DA8EFDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Department of Education identified several universities receiving Federal research and development funding that did not report foreign gifts as required by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A8E2DC982134EC39F6B9A2FCE2AEA66"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Department of Education found 6 universities of the 12 they investigated received gifts that amounted to more than $1,300,000,000 from foreign sources, including the People’s Republic of China, Qatar, and the Russian Federation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B641C8462DB413EBC748F9F6BE430BA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On April 13, 2023, the United States Environmental Protection Agency’s Office of Inspector General issued a memorandum concerning <quote>Disclosure of Foreign Support for EPA Research.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H539AD954ED0A43AB885D06497BFE6C9A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The EPA’s OIG <quote>identified a concern regarding the lack of a requirement for EPA research grant recipients to report foreign support after receiving a grant award.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DFA3A6A9CE9407982661944ABB8E802"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the memorandum, <quote>[a]s of March 22, 2023, the EPA only required grant applicants to disclose all active and pending research support before receiving a grant award.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H270EC8FD6940409FBAA069B725A66B80"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Security Presidential Memorandum—33 requires Federal research and development recipients to disclose any involvement in programs sponsored by foreign governments, instrumentalities, entities, including foreign government sponsored talent recruitment programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H931050166DE54B55986A4E6BEF2A8840"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The memorandum also provides guidance to require both pre-award and post-award disclosures.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H23DC5511ACC946388F35A95BCBEC617C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Disclosure of support for research and development award recipients required</header><subsection id="HC9EB876DDF3F458AA32581B622389825" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Recipient requirement To disclose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of a covered agency shall require in the terms and conditions of any research and development award issued by the covered agency that—</text><paragraph id="HBF71E4CF03C34A46A89545C9E2E0DE4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the recipient of the award disclose within 30 days after the date on which the recipient receives any support from a country of concern or an entity of concern a description of such support; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7C83169DE424CF0878B152E4CB79A08" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any covered individual report to the recipient within 30 days after a commitment of any support or the receipt of any support from a country of concern or entity of concern, which shall be disclosed to the covered agency within 14 days after any such report.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C30DF74533F4FB7955CC097D99E5B18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cooperation with inspectors general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of any covered agency shall cooperate with the inspectors general in order to ensure compliance with the requirements of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78B053E517974EC086B590CF8FF6FC7F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of the collected disclosure information</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Science Foundation shall—</text><paragraph id="H52A10BE29F544EE5AAFFD50F91137803"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish and maintain a searchable database on a website for any disclosure made to a covered agency pursuant to subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0D4F5671039474A802715DD2BA6F3D9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require covered agencies to transmit by electronic means an unredacted copy of the report required pursuant to subsection (a) to the Director;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA23DE027E4C94FB7B282F0228E9F1F56"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make the website publicly available (in electronic and downloadable format);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABE8E38E9BC84E2C856D849381D33C2D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure website and content is searchable and sortable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE3FE8442CEA4D8E852B2BAF8B7E022A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>make each such report available on the website not later than 30 days after receipt of the report.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1F89BC15CE1485DA96619B382B0E957"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Study on research security concerns</header><paragraph id="H8638681F697D4F199B571BC6CC27CEED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Transmission of reports to National Counterintelligence and Security Center</header><text>Not later than 7 days after the date on which a report is submitted pursuant to subsection (c)(2), the Director of the National Science Foundation shall transmit by electronic means an unredacted copy of such report to the Director of the National Counterintelligence and Security Center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCD388A3181F4AE9A26CA3BF8E6C0EFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Analysis</header><text>The Director of the National Counterintelligence and Security Center shall—</text><subparagraph id="H3DE8506DDBC24A52AEF5C47DCE912C36"><enum>(A)</enum><text>perform an analysis of each report submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) to identify broader research security concerns or patterns of misconduct by each country of concern or entity of concern; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2E8DE86A2D94E848108B0CE1461A975"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">share the analysis with Congress and the intelligence and Federal law enforcement agencies, including the inspector general office of each covered agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF58EC2D92A5A4C91843DD215BC704D58"><enum>(3)</enum><header>NSF analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Science Foundation, through the Research Security and Integrity Information Sharing Analysis Organization, shall submit to Congress and provide to the Director of the National Counterintelligence and Security Center an analysis and other information related to the information disclosed pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF5027EA964F14D51910EE9F2DCF0CEDA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than January 15 of each year, the head of each covered agency shall submit to Congress a report on compliance with the requirements of this section for the previous fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8B67A5A72B414CB4A96E69F06CD98204" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section applies to any research and development award issued on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H779C56551D694E44B1ACE4C60C2FFFE4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph id="H3727085BAD6C4E1682A046E322214101"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Actions for noncompliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of a covered agency shall take one or more of the following enforcement actions with respect to a recipient of a research and development award made by that agency that is not in compliance with subsection (a):</text><subparagraph id="HA5B5C11905C844FCB9B8D3A978A9A78A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Temporarily withhold cash payments pending correction of the deficiency by the non-Federal entity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23D594B2E8234E66BA83014B4C9BA44A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Disallow (that is, deny both use of funds and any applicable matching credit for) all or part of the cost of the activity or action not in compliance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87A524E96A9E4479ABC69B8DF218AFAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Wholly or partly suspend or terminate the Federal award.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8517684E45B74ECF9C858BBA66540DFC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Initiate suspension or debarment proceedings as authorized under part 180 of title 2, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act) and Federal awarding agency regulations (or in the case of a pass-through entity, recommend such a proceeding be initiated by a Federal awarding agency).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE6BFB1C636E4CDAB3268BCE57A87FD3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Withhold further Federal awards for the project or program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H105EFC710F15407E86A2BF0DDCB70101"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Place the covered individual into the integrity and performance system designated by the Office of Management and Budget accessible through the System of Award Management (<quote>SAM.gov</quote>) (currently the Federal Awardee Performance and Integrity Information System (FAPIIS)). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E9793C174BC466E8740C5158935F2DD"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Refer the failure to disclose under subsection (a) to the Inspector General of the agency concerned for further investigation or to Federal law enforcement authorities to determine whether criminal or civil laws were violated. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFE3C6771BBB48CCAFCDC168A10D8EC0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Take such other actions against the recipient as are authorized under applicable law or regulations. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20348CCE43FD404AAC7B8028043DD3C2"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recoup all funding up to and including the full amount of the award.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H43AA1B7F809740508ADA2A2F75E6E105"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evidentiary standards</header><text>A covered agency seeking suspension or debarment under paragraph (1) shall abide by the procedures and evidentiary standards set forth in part 180 of title 2, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC487B692B8D409C90E97604FFBB92AF"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3C11ED0966FF439B99027D993D0E6F24" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H883D108AC0C040EDB425484AE833157C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>country of concern</term> means the People’s Republic of China (including the Special Administrative Regions of China, including Hong Kong and Macau), the Russian Federation, Iran, North Korea, Cuba, and Venezuela, including any agency or instrumentality. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D06E96A36274E3686BF5CFFC8240C00"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered agency</header><text>The term <term>covered agency</term> means an agency that awards a research and development award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H274EC6DE0E4A40618296C8E28B1FA0CB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HA82584B8491548C5B4ED21A38C17BCF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>contributes in a substantive, meaningful way to the scientific development or execution of a research and development project proposed to be carried out with a research and development award from a Federal research agency (as such term is defined in section 10001 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18901">42 U.S.C. 18901</external-xref>)); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF1331B3A474455092BA7C5E23264CD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is designated as a covered individual by the Federal research agency concerned.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H583D9E8DBF8441E5A870990D64674C43"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Entity of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>entity of concern</term> means an entity organized under the laws of any country of concern, including any United States subsidiary of such entity or any entity that acts on behalf of any such entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7419C668D9434FED94C9A9BCFC85906E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Research and development award</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>research and development award</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HF4AAD678C1CB4488AFA9D667BE2F7740"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means support provided to an individual or entity by a covered agency to carry out research and development activities, which may include support in the form of a grant, contract, other transaction, or cooperative agreement; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B833BFDEDA745ECB8FF58902296F2BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include a transaction for the procurement of goods or services to meet the administrative needs of a covered agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H38F7B482E17542A6B6582955EDBA96E8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Support</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>support</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H0C7ECEE186D44785879C1691F1D941BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a grant or other financial support made by an individual or entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03A89B35DD2F4672A07CA50157B8723F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any in-kind contribution requiring a commitment of time and directly supporting the research and development efforts, such as the provision of office or laboratory space, equipment, supplies, employees, or students; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05771DF302414B0883FFD27617A0E2D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any other award or benefit, including any honorarium, prize, or paid travel for a speaking engagement or meeting, provided to any covered individual on a research and development award or to an institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101">20 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref>)) on behalf of covered individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

