<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD7DDB0D53DD0445983037B6436177237" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6871 IH: Hydrogen for Trucks Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6871</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Transportation, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, to establish a grant program to demonstrate the performance and reliability of heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles that use hydrogen as a fuel source, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5DB8F0C83B34415BAA5D5A867AD44A98" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF8AF1F368C06462DB4463420FECCAA25"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hydrogen for Trucks Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H3272371F9219476CB51A2E9DCF01AAFC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle demonstration program</header> <subsection id="HC0DB075FFA304438B5C61A16E5859E73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H1F19E7A894D942738C933063407CBCBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commercial motor vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>commercial motor vehicle</quote> means a self-propelled vehicle used on highways in commerce principally to transport passengers or cargo, if the vehicle has a gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight of at least 26,001 pounds, whichever is greater, or is designed to transport more than 10 passengers, including the driver.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F10A61E75F3441AAFC69BA751B56188"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity described in subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA80665BBB554C2F9AD2B31DAF3B0959"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fleet</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>fleet</quote> means the number of commercial motor vehicles owned and operated by an entity. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CDC4AD10BF046E9B25C68FD8B48E97E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle</header> <subparagraph id="HF6AF5564498540FCAC2F8917C432CB45"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle</term> means a vehicle that—</text> 
<clause id="H99143E6E28C945B0B8F04A3960D581D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has a manufacturer gross vehicle weight rating of more than 26,000 pounds, as determined by the Federal Highway Administration;</text></clause> <clause id="H83FDD0B96D2543D1B2F405D62A858BD5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not powered or charged by an internal combustion engine; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H3A1AE26FEC0343A5A3612112B5803D1A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is propelled solely by an electric motor that draws electricity from—</text> <subclause id="H9CF0F815A516451CAAADF94590825AE0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a fuel cell; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6F60C3FD57B443519CDC9BC62003BEDF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a combination of a fuel cell and a battery.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFEB89DC3C94B47D9874F68F72E21C308"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle</term> includes any off-road vehicle, such as a yard truck, that meets the requirements of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C1C388FBE5B42C8B25BA43ED1A05749"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>program</term> means the program established under subsection (b)(1). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3753BE8B683C41DA83CAC6D56DF08EC1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF9B6358DCF1D49C8A1022EFD305CCAC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header> 
<paragraph id="HB94C5349EE5D4EEEBEF486C061D808FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall establish a program under which the Secretary shall provide grants to eligible entities to assist the eligible entities in funding capital projects to purchase heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles and related equipment, including hydrogen fueling stations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H775E3A3300374F6E996BF82F4BB09E4F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under the program, an entity shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDC14F98E7F0F4FD9A9271CEACC019EE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a private heavy-duty truck fleet owner with high duty cycle or long-haul operations;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3CB586C3C2E64CD297903C83DD94A963"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an operator with a <quote>return to base</quote> mode that requires refueling primarily at a single station, including an airport, a delivery warehouse, and a shipping port;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6218E7EA1A534A229012303B052EFC54"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a leasing firm;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0330AD2A11DE4E509C90C1A1EEE50FF7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an independent owner-operator; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H88ED6535393E4670AA7CF24CDB68E393"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a public hydrogen fueling station developer or operator;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H500ED0E7C44A4424A40B8D029F33648B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Federal, State, or local agency that owns, operates, leases, or otherwise controls a fleet of public vehicles; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H56B152CA881940FC80C6C2C1E6783D81"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a partnership of 1 or more entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (E).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E960C9AA3744D82BE64ACF8AEF6717C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applications</header> <subparagraph id="H11E5CCABC53244EAA25DFCE14DE1CBC2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), an eligible entity desiring a grant under the program shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, may require. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H77B636F4F7704C7C98F505F21CAC6AB1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>If an eligible entity desiring a grant under the program intends to use the grant for only 1 of the uses described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (d)(1), the eligible entity shall include in the application under subparagraph (A) a description of—</text> <clause id="H76C93524CAF9436B825B777595A230A7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if the grant is to be used only for the use described in subparagraph (A) of subsection (d)(1), the availability of not fewer than 1 hydrogen fueling station that can be used by heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HF4AA7DB32E344323A7F9192F304C372F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the grant is to be used only for the use described in subparagraph (B) of subsection (d)(1), the availability of not fewer than 7 heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles that—</text> <subclause id="H4C76B536B1AF42DA97E8431EBF6CF1B5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>use hydrogen as a fuel source; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H49F423C6F54D417A849C6DAB90E4A2E8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>will use 1 or more hydrogen fueling stations demonstrated using the grant; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA651DBB7CD2449B8A605D4A2F17081E1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the means by which the project of the eligible entity will expand the demand for and use of any existing infrastructure. </text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H639D9AEAC6E142FC84F9BFB2CEE97AE9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to receive grants under the program, the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H4B78678562544BEBBFC9A9B75658E372"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take into account whether the eligible entity has the potential to expand the use of hydrogen demonstrated by the eligible entity using the grant to other applications within the region in which the eligible entity operates; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDFD537B01074450B9D974A6C7A17EAB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable—</text> <clause id="HAE3076BFCCA34962855479924ADC8212"><enum>(i)</enum><text>select eligible entities operating in different regions of the United States—</text> 
<subclause id="HE5CEA1FBCDC64FEA87B22A9BA4419D99"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to demonstrate different types of fleet operations, such as fleet operations with differing local hydrogen supplies, climate conditions, route lengths and geographies, and sizes of vehicles; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD075219F14A749939F21DC0B08FE6C79"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to identify any differences in performance demonstrated by the heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles used by the eligible entity that are due to regional characteristics;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HBC58AAEDC52D4CCB9B900448F607A9D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>select eligible entities that intend to use the grant for both of the uses described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (d)(1); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H4688339F9A9A408596FB2AAD95FD116E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>select projects that will generate the greatest benefit to low-income or disadvantaged communities (including cities, towns, counties, and reasonably isolated and divisible segments of a larger municipality) with an annual median household income that is less than 100 percent of the statewide annual median household income for the State in which the community is located, according to the most recent decennial census.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HA935A4BB549D4CD89F5AA5E2E84B6435"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In applying the criteria described in paragraph (4), the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall prioritize selecting—</text> <subparagraph id="H89DD0C53FC644713B4DAC1B9F2450D44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>projects that will provide greater net impact in avoiding or reducing emissions of greenhouse gases;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBDF06FAEBAD740CA878807F0F5C9DC6A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projects for which each applicable hydrogen fueling station is open to the public; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1FF9C4DDAB894B1B9C3B4BBB3F6D03BE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible entities that provide greater than 20 percent cost share.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H87B40AD3C9134593B4EFC5ACB542EC05"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the program shall be—</text> <paragraph id="H513FC361C9624D4FB754413E95A07B0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to demonstrate the performance and reliability of heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles in different regions of the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34B364423174478487C603BF760967B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to provide a basis for relevant cost evaluations and cost reductions; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H93657C0E5EBB4344B4F9580D440785BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to accelerate the market deployment of heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDC2E0BE464C7476B83F646753459E5B1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header> 
<paragraph id="H457A95555B7041F1BAEBAE19100AF1CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under the program shall use the grant to demonstrate the performance of—</text> <subparagraph id="H5EA6AD1B1F924B59A6351687C73DF4DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not fewer than 7 heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles that use hydrogen as fuel source; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA0AA0E83F76B41FDB7445EBE0CCEDEA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>1 or more hydrogen fueling stations for use by heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BB4F9E9FD9C4035A66C8D0D18597C51"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible costs</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under the program may use the grant for the following costs:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6E0073D48D864B97B82A2C755FB5A4FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The capital costs of—</text> <clause id="H4E9808D83CBD4609819664F8F49D3ED4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles described in paragraph (1)(A), subject to paragraph (4); or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H02F01F17872045ABA7CEF0D8668E7FE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>constructing a station described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2659361A1164B1D8C3667E59EDDC74A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The costs, such as costs associated with the cost of labor, complying with maintenance requirements, and administration of the program, of operating—</text> 
<clause id="H99846FA408DD4690ABF0116B391F189B"><enum>(i)</enum><text> the heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles described in paragraph (1)(A); or</text></clause> <clause id="H0E2457E989854D61A47402E7A8A2ECB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a station described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H55D7AB56A519470BAE4B9B86606BF3A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Overhead expenses.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFB2BFC4E354846A980848059674C3D2D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The costs of training personnel to ensure safety and best practices during construction, fueling and refueling, maintenance, and upkeep, as applicable, of—</text> 
<clause id="H02A0E9B3B90A4C21B822172D4C06733D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles described in paragraph (1)(A); or</text></clause> <clause id="HF13F9947C0DC4FDEBA229E53D562268D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a station described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3579A6B4110494F905EF1B85BD90172"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The costs of complying with—</text> <clause id="H82C55EB5930941E6AAD6F5A5F109B5C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the requirements of subsection (g); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0F75F1501DDD49F9AA6C627D4ACF9C67"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any reporting requirements under subsection (h).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEDD12CB3283458B9E6A8617679C606C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Project locations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project carried out with a grant provided under the program may be carried out on any public road or in other publicly accessible locations, such as parking facilities at public buildings, public schools, and public parks, or in publicly accessible parking facilities owned or managed by a private entity. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB58C252E293F4B18B26922B32AD98457"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Operation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9643DA60C62A4EB1B8D6BABF01378BCA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), an eligible entity that receives a grant under the program for a use described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1) may determine whether each applicable hydrogen fueling station shall—</text> <clause id="H8E03155A25C14276887953A53466353E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>allow only private access; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H053BAA28E2AD43EC80641314062E9584"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be open to the public.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H94A5F1E5F1F94B8692C28F138693C9DB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public hydrogen fueling station developers and operators</header><text>An eligible entity described in subsection (b)(2)(E) that receives a grant under the program to be used only for the use described in paragraph (1)(B) shall make each applicable hydrogen fueling station described in that paragraph open to the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD85C8925D3E64F49846B4447E430D154"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Capital costs of vehicles</header><text>With respect to the capital costs described in paragraph (2)(A)(i), the amount of grant funds used for those capital costs shall not exceed, with respect to each heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle purchased by the eligible entity and used for the applicable project, the lesser of—</text> <subparagraph id="H6F539B2EE8F341C79F37DA00679319D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an amount equal to the difference between—</text> 
<clause id="H8FE48D7C088648F59320B8340C9EDC57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the cost of the heavy-duty fuel cell vehicle; and</text></clause> <clause id="H70F1280DEE8E482986F0C8A90213F621"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the product obtained by multiplying—</text> 
<subclause id="H4FAB3984191843448E65979690804509"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the cost of a comparable gasoline- or diesel-fueled vehicle; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE9CD5ED7616044DA8977E73751097882"><enum>(II)</enum><text>0.5; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCC80A58F7F934C9099030FBEB5D2A4FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$500,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD46A155FF74D4BD1ACA390A9C6C6FECA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Amount of grant</header><text>The amount of a grant provided by the Secretary under the program shall be not more than $20,000,000. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5BAC95E0E67E4AEE873EF7B5328537A9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Cost sharing</header><text>The non-Federal share of the cost of a project carried out using a grant under the program shall be not less than 20 percent. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H39B0271B793B4939AACAEF2AF8CFB5A1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Leak detection</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under the program shall conduct—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBA87221A51A84B26A8EB75CB9701D0E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a hydrogen leakage monitoring, reporting, and verification (also known as <quote>MRV</quote>) program; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B3E93583DD0421A91D544ED03D996F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a hydrogen leak detection and repair (also known as <quote>LDAR</quote>) program.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3CC87EE47E5E45D59DC4E782A13BB912"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reporting</header> 
<paragraph id="HDD1146739D9445A59D12F878BC70CAC7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under the program shall submit to the Secretary such operational data relating to eligible costs described in subsection (d)(2) as the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, may require to accelerate market deployment of heavy-duty fuel cell vehicles that use hydrogen as a fuel source. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDDFEB1B2FAAB4947B1D67BA0846A6CF2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The operational data required by the Secretary under paragraph (1) shall include, at a minimum, data relating to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9356D75276FF47B4ADE7F8CED1A13714"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operational expenses;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0278D8540F9F4404A8DB3FBC49CC349E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fuel use; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9835BCDADF4C47CBA8244328597FDCAC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reliability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9DE8AA273A6456FBEF7D0576FBA9E49"><enum>(3)</enum><header>System</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall develop a system for data reporting and data sharing that allows similar fleet and fueling station operators to evaluate the performance of the program.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H72466D35CD274ECE8C790AD36285B119"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out the program $200,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection> </section> </legis-body></bill>

