<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3AF693ED6996402EA7C3B5FD816C8496" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5887 IH: Government Service Delivery Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5887</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, to improve Government service delivery, and build related capacity for the Federal Government, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD3C0033EA7AB4B6299BBC174E756AD56" style="OLC"><section id="HD5388A701C854724A8F938C1E9441599" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Government Service Delivery Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H99FEE0B569384BCEAF1BA84E27B971BC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal Government service delivery</header><subsection id="H0CD679CB43C64FE79401051D28A185EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">Chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HC7051400DF7A4F06917A89FE0A096863" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subchapter id="H85B63066C98E4002A29FD313B2D1B6BB"><enum>III</enum><header>Federal Government Service Delivery</header><section id="H970BBF699443422599E79895873E69B1"><enum>321.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subchapter:</text><paragraph id="H1E5A8465076F4E3C86A7972A3850BA49"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <quote>agency</quote> means the agencies listed in section 901(b) of title 31.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01E0167E996A4B25AFF596C9A810BD42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H776D5984C12144BF9AB7A29819A47C60"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Government service delivery</header><text>The term <quote>Government service delivery</quote> means any action by the Federal Government related to providing a benefit or service to an individual, business, or organization (such as a grantee or State, local, or Tribal entity) that interacts with an agency or program (including an interaction with a Federal employee, agency contractor acting on behalf of a Federal agency, or through a Federal information system or internet based interface) including any point of the Government service delivery process (such as the application for or receipt of a Government service or benefit, the request or filing of an agency document or record, or the use of a Federal facility or property).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF10562A54ABD4DB3A1AAEDE134918259" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Government service delivery channel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Government service delivery channel</quote> means a significant interaction with the Federal Government that is in-person, by mail, through a digital service, by telephone, through a contact center, through outreach and communication, and through collaboration with a third party and other ways in which an individual or entity significantly interacts with the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FC9D2C2B2B94BAB8B898488A5DC6291"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High impact service provider</header><text>The term <quote>high impact service provider</quote> means an agency program identified by the Director due to the scale and impact of the public-facing services of the agency.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H1F00BF8ABCE64B67981780A3D158B459"><enum>322.</enum><header>Federal Government service delivery</header><subsection id="H07998566E9354DEB9106CA264875962E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal Government Service Delivery Lead</header><text>The Director shall designate or appoint a senior official as the Federal Government Service Delivery Lead within the Office of Management and Budget whose primary responsibility is to coordinate governmentwide efforts to improve Government service delivery and related experiences. The individual shall have the following duties and authorities:</text><paragraph id="HA558F299ECC947E19E7BEB07A80A70C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Facilitate and coordinate governmentwide efforts to improve Government service delivery provided by agencies, particularly with respect to high impact service providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8481F67635B1409A8F264AE441B30942"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Carry out the duties and powers prescribed by the Director.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85BE2D27E59147819A8146A052B0CB09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Serve as the lead official responsible for Government service delivery by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB71D1843CB96430B8438CBAB60C6CAE0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Advise the Director concerning the continuous improvement of Government service delivery provided by agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90F91DF051DA42EF9C44289A5F68F782"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop and oversee implementation of governmentwide Government service delivery standards, policies, and guidelines for services and programs provided by agencies, including standards, policies, and guidelines to—</text><subparagraph id="H333A3961C10E44D0B631860FD39B1900"><enum>(A)</enum><text>understand needs from the perspective of an individual or entity interacting with a Government service or program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51ED937670D244E388CBA887F170B041"><enum>(B)</enum><text>solicit and consider voluntary feedback;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CD71FAFA5B544C7A1DC78BC5A001C62"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assess key aspects of the experience of individuals and entities with agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H867634613DB4467EB271F050BE48296F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consider the factors of ease, efficiency, transparency, accessibility, fairness, burden (as defined in section 3502 of title 44), and duration, including wait and processing times, with respect to the interaction of an individual or entity with a Government service or program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0553B59D90A4875B396011A953F2D3A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Evaluate the quality of Government service delivery provided by agencies using the standards, policies, and guidelines developed in paragraph (5) to improve and enhance Government service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H359845F2AACF44379F029584B8FFF1E9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Establish metrics, to be collected and reported through existing Office of Management and Budget reporting mechanisms, to evaluate the quality of Government service delivery provided by agencies, including metrics to assess the quality of Government service delivery provided by agencies and the process of high impact service providers in improving services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA550707CFE7B499DB8EC129C8ADA15BA"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Engage with stakeholders to identify best practices in service design and Government service delivery that would improve Government service delivery across agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA979F86DC64D478B0D7BAF7EC47D17"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Encourage the adoption of commercial products and services in accordance with section 3307 of title 41.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9A5AF110D5D4B7B93757BEB06E9345B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Ensure agency service delivery initiatives, including those related to the 21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3501">15 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/336">Public Law 115–336</external-xref>), are prioritized in congressional budget justifications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E45E5F7E51A464F98FFC5A006D99B80"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Coordinate with Office of Management and Budget stakeholders, including the Administrator of the United States Digital Service and the Administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs, and other agency stakeholders, including the Administrator of General Services and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, on Government service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9881CA5B43DC4F88B7EE80146B3E9A87"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In coordination with stakeholders, ensure that websites of agencies, including those designated as high impact service providers, are consistent with the objectives of this subchapter, the 21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act, and any other applicable law.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4ECA4FB529244B15A4714C3A4FCFAC29"><enum>323.</enum><header>Lead agency officials for Government service delivery</header><subsection id="H3F3409E3EA56431CA4D45402CFF4868E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Responsibility for Government service delivery</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each agency shall be responsible for the Government service delivery of the agency which shall, at a minimum, include continuously improving and enhancing Government services to better achieve the mission of the agency and build and maintain trust, transparency, and accountability.</text></subsection><subsection id="H69542F05F1634D178D7AE49F6E5AA530"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Lead agency service delivery officials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this subchapter, the head of each agency shall designate or appoint a senior official of the agency (who may be the deputy head of the agency) to implement this subchapter who shall have the following duties and authorities:</text><paragraph id="H488FF9F64C4D4F4C8F12BE31D3CF9DFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Report directly to the head or deputy head of the agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF7BD454D3424DCB8D8D484A8DB56825"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Possess sufficient operational authority to effectuate implementation of Government service delivery improvements within the agency, particularly high impact government service providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD03757778CB34D9889F70FC675A79E2D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate and execute, as appropriate, under the direction of the head of the agency, efforts to improve and enhance the Government service delivery provided by their agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4DE316DC624430B921B12BE07D057D5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Submit to the Federal Government Service Delivery Lead an implementation plan for improving agency Government service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66DF05F5C4A44D5C89749D9355CC25FF"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate the development and use of qualitative and quantitative metrics on Government service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CF059158410468CB43AD621F9FF6A2C"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facilitate collaboration among and between offices, components, and within the agency to improve and enhance Government service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1D150B4E91D43C695ADFF23AB9AA115"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Assist with the implementation by the agency of the 21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3501">15 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/336">Public Law 115–336</external-xref>) and provide improved digital services and service delivery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FF0F17E73DA464C8ED9B1EED118E77B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assist in the incorporation of the Government service delivery requirements by the agency established under this subchapter in agency plans and learning agendas.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H75400724B8A94BCB8A5F433F37A040FE" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H2585669966374734B0241E130E2105E0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HC7051400DF7A4F06917A89FE0A096863" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H85B63066C98E4002A29FD313B2D1B6BB" level="subchapter">Subchapter III—Federal Government Service Delivery</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H970BBF699443422599E79895873E69B1" level="section">321. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1F00BF8ABCE64B67981780A3D158B459" level="section">322. Federal Government service delivery.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4ECA4FB529244B15A4714C3A4FCFAC29" level="section">323. Lead agency officials for government service delivery.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA8D50E5EF60B4E6698EC8078F53B74DC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HC219FBFF40E24EACAF6FF975BADF5F24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the implementation and effectiveness of subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC117928BDC174888A280E830E86551A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Specific recommendations to further the implementation and effectiveness of such subchapter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44AE3B40CFA04E78AE9BB93AC7B715FA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No new funds authorized</header><text>No new funds are authorized to be appropriated by this Act or any amendment made by this Act and the head of each agency shall comply with this Act and any amendment made by this Act using existing funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF0726C4B66ED4A55A6CE45B8CA76C92D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Agency defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>agency</term> means each agency listed in section 901(b) of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

