<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H38A8AF82DA3548B298FB145F60D0DD7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1354 IH: Information and Communication Technology Strategy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1354</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information, to report on and develop a whole-of-Government strategy with respect to the economic competitiveness of the information and communication technology supply chain, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDDE12B45173E4FE5AD2EA532302402CC" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2676DE3EFC524D0EA9713D15E271BE4D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Information and Communication Technology Strategy Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5BE328FED3DF42ECB445B7434625D336"><enum>2.</enum><header>Economic competitiveness of information and communication technology supply chain</header> <subsection id="H3D29FA759E0C4B8CB93E9C7DC85BBA8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the information and communication technology supply chain that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF0B151128FE74C35A9D0986624EF0C3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies—</text> <subparagraph id="H32F5D36C7CA24062B99D2AD4C07EB5F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>information and communication technology critical to the economic competitiveness of the United States; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8D18B724538844618E88AB1B7A76BED4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the industrial capacity of—</text> <clause id="H0B16B9880B5A40798F41FBC933968726" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">United States vendors that produce information and communication technology identified under subparagraph (A); and </text></clause> 
<clause id="HFAB104D3CF5E4249BB984520C4FE9745"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>trusted information and communication technology vendors that produce information and communication technology identified under subparagraph (A);</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H87F6A1B62B6B452DB45B6101D3F82D4D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assesses the economic competitiveness of vendors described under paragraph (1)(B); </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H095861F20FDD468AB30722EEEC49A894"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assesses whether, and to what extent, there is a dependence by providers of advanced telecommunications capability in the United States on information and communication technology identified under paragraph (1)(A) that is not trusted;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8A7AAAA83CAC41D1B02B389FD4A734B2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identifies—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H639C22C97DB8483381F09EE45F9C8849"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what actions by the Federal Government are needed to support, and bolster the economic competitiveness of, trusted information and communication technology vendors; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB34EB925796D4BA0B5257B91A9974506"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what Federal resources are needed to reduce dependence by providers of advanced telecommunications capability in the United States on companies that—</text> 
<clause id="H71FFE261317E4E85BA250D1179AEC321"><enum>(i)</enum><text>produce information and communication technology; and</text></clause> <clause id="H331695FB8FB14049A840903C76E3D021"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are not trusted; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD49B30D26E349E682F88BB3C93DBB75" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>defines lines of effort and assigns responsibilities for a whole-of-Government response to ensuring the competitiveness of the information and communication technology supply chain in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H98ED5107A12E47CAB5EE257561DBAC45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Whole-of-Government strategy</header> <paragraph id="HD6CCA777B24A41B8A52A10B95EE18D1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall develop, on the basis of the report required by subsection (a), a whole-of-Government strategy to ensure the economic competitiveness of trusted information and communication technology vendors that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF0895DC977A340378214B178F883522B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recommendations on how—</text> <clause id="H9EC817960CE246129EA2F7882E883A45"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to strengthen the structure, resources, and authorities of the Federal Government to support the economic competitiveness of trusted information and communication technology vendors, including United States vendors that are trusted information and communication technology vendors; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H44C583D80B1346E79854793B7883A76F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal Government can address any barriers to a market-based solution for increasing the economic competitiveness of such information and communication technology vendors; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H622637AA41D144A083E0EAB327F83473"><enum>(B)</enum><text>defined lines of effort and responsibilities for Federal agencies to implement the strategy; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F6633FB24444E2E9F30DD7A30FA473B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of—</text> <clause id="H8187E58512BE4D1C9EC16C6C28AEB193"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any change to a Federal program, Federal law, or structure of the Federal Government necessary to implement any recommendation under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H01C9EB94FD9D4468903E342AB9D9C7B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any additional Federal resource necessary to implement any recommendation under subparagraph (A). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BBD4F2813674137911059AE2E995E56"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the submission of the report required by subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report containing the strategy developed under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6D62F347181F4C49BBA858820789C934"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation required</header><text>In carrying out subsections (a) and (b), the Secretary shall consult with—</text> <paragraph id="HC4AD9721960A4DD38982B3884C178AB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a cross-section of trusted information and communication technology vendors; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4B20B598A06427CB961D1E05AED52E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Attorney General, the Director of National Intelligence, the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, and any other head of an agency the Secretary determines necessary. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA3D7FE4C39394A06A36070537E40DDA4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H091C58E40A90427296FC79BB70B4A2B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced telecommunications capability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>advanced telecommunications capability</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 706 of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1302">47 U.S.C. 1302</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H504C9E180FF742BAA513DC1C956E08BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information and communication technology</header><text>The term <term>information and communication technology</term> means a technology (including software), component, or material that enables communications by radio or wire.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A4D1036AC644789AB68C6F758EBFECE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information and communication technology supply chain</header><text>The term <term>information and communication technology supply chain</term> means all of the companies that produce information and communication technology. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF45DBC05587474A87258E0A0C3C3667"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Not trusted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>not trusted</term> means, with respect to a company or information and communication technology, that the company or information and communication technology is <italic></italic>determined by the Secretary to pose an unacceptable risk to the national security of the United States or the security and safety of United States persons based solely on one or more determinations described under paragraphs (1) through (4) of section 2(c) of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1601">47 U.S.C. 1601(c)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBAC52BACD5094638B2BE40758A74E25B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA804C87AA714414EAF58054459FB4732" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Trusted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>trusted</term> means, with respect to a company, that the Secretary has not determined that the company is not trusted.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4820C700E022436486066C6F2E8B8881"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Trusted information and communication technology vendor</header><text>The term <term>trusted information and communication technology vendor</term> means a company—</text> <subparagraph id="H7775D7C7D6E84CD6965ED2624243DAF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that produces information and communication technology; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC47EF2840AC545E586FB82C1023B4B7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is trusted. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

