<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H17A8ABE6FAA842DA9080253432DE4D32" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 457 IH: Combating Global Corruption Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 457</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To identify and combat corruption in countries, to establish a tiered list of countries with respect to levels of corruption by their governments and their efforts to combat such corruption, and to evaluate whether foreign persons engaged in significant corruption should be specially designated nationals under the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H7431D344A9464A91BD2453B47DF9D5F4" style="OLC">
<section id="HE5C69AE9652C4DB5B0421D8519AF8785" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combating Global Corruption Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2FB81FF8D88F46AE91FB5EB01CDB21FA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H2795D6BAAAD844AE981D5FEEECB12A59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Corrupt actor</header><text>The term <term>corrupt actor</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HA57A204DAFCE4D1E9751FF721207CCB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any foreign person or entity that is a government official or government entity responsible for, or complicit in, an act of corruption; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5F17B4B4EF614A7185B6A00706C82229"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any company, in which a person or entity described in subparagraph (A) has a significant stake, which is responsible for, or complicit in, an act of corruption.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC34B161A7B154227B4541A985719E978"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Corruption</header><text>The term <term>corruption</term> means the unlawful exercise of entrusted public power for private gain, including by bribery, nepotism, fraud, or embezzlement.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H592582AE93B04FD6A77F79200E45B2C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Significant corruption</header><text>The term <term>significant corruption</term> means corruption committed at a high level of government that—</text> <subparagraph id="HF1F7E7DEEB984202A1D81774B7222726"><enum>(A)</enum><text>illegitimately distorts major decision making, such as policy or resource determinations, or other fundamental functions of governance; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF8B12BC5EE384BED8EFA9FF4F90E6382"><enum>(B)</enum><text>involves economically or socially large-scale government activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H52C9BE6B923F4F7C92BEE8D77941E111"><enum>3.</enum><header>Publication of tiered ranking list</header> <subsection id="H2696A7E5BCC9496384B1A593DBD591D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State shall annually publish, on a publicly accessible website, a tiered ranking of all foreign countries.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HC52832E1BBCB4044A7BE6FC878B17013"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Tier 1 countries</header><text>A country shall be ranked as a tier 1 country in the ranking published under subsection (a) if the government of such country is complying with the minimum standards set forth in section 4.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA44174AF203C4253AF8B594A09606712"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tier 2 countries</header><text>A country shall be ranked as a tier 2 country in the ranking published under subsection (a) if the government of such country is making efforts to comply with the minimum standards set forth in section 4, but is not achieving the requisite level of compliance to be ranked as a tier 1 country.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H620F3DE7EDB14D41ADEC8CFE9FBA6838"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Tier 3 countries</header><text>A country shall be ranked as a tier 3 country in the ranking published under subsection (a) if the government of such country is making de minimis or no efforts to comply with the minimum standards set forth in section 4.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HFEC7133C983E41B6876541A6DD83EE7F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Minimum standards for the elimination of corruption and assessment of efforts to combat corruption</header> <subsection id="HABE1F0C7AA49430498465369138000AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The government of a country is complying with the minimum standards for the elimination of corruption if the government—</text>
<paragraph id="HFB476F4113AA45A1AA7CD897118D7512"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has enacted and implemented laws and established government structures, policies, and practices that prohibit and generally deter corruption, including significant corruption;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9606AA4EE6B40D3BD354F0ED87FBA61"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enforces the laws described in paragraph (1) by punishing any person who is found, through a fair judicial process, to have violated such laws;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5C0187834A5947DC8DAC871AA7977520"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prescribes punishment for significant corruption that is commensurate with the punishment prescribed for serious crimes; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA7CA376DEA6442CA88B887FDF7FE1796"><enum>(4)</enum><text>is making serious and sustained efforts to address corruption, including through prevention.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H02D4DE438BEC43FA95DCEFF850B660D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Factors for assessing government efforts To combat corruption</header><text>In determining whether a government is making serious and sustained efforts to address corruption, the Secretary of State shall consider, to the extent relevant or appropriate, factors such as—</text> <paragraph id="H768CD2501F274E4BB972E28FC60FC12E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>whether the government of the country has criminalized corruption, investigates and prosecutes acts of corruption, and convicts and sentences persons responsible for such acts over which it has jurisdiction, including, as appropriate, incarcerating individuals convicted of such acts;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2A3D69AFD3DB4DBE9742D6B25DF16477"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether the government of the country vigorously investigates, prosecutes, convicts, and sentences public officials who participate in or facilitate corruption, including nationals of the country who are deployed in foreign military assignments, trade delegations abroad, or other similar missions, who engage in or facilitate significant corruption;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H55917103810B480EA8A5695BE0C74273"><enum>(3)</enum><text>whether the government of the country has adopted measures to prevent corruption, such as measures to inform and educate the public, including potential victims, about the causes and consequences of corruption;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDCD965C2B1304B34AD5F68A513ED3C20"><enum>(4)</enum><text>whether the government of the country has taken steps to prohibit government officials from participating in, facilitating, or condoning corruption, including the investigation, prosecution, and conviction of such officials;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF15CF755F744995815AD9B90AD1AF81"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the extent to which the country provides access, or, as appropriate, makes adequate resources available, to civil society organizations and other institutions to combat corruption, including reporting, investigating, and monitoring;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H81CD7D87BEA748828C7A3376A9B484AC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>whether an independent judiciary or judicial body in the country is responsible for, and effectively capable of, deciding corruption cases impartially, on the basis of facts and in accordance with the law, without any improper restrictions, influences, inducements, pressures, threats, or interferences (direct or indirect);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59977D6C180440B5A00D58EBFEF1EBF3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>whether the government of the country is assisting in international investigations of transnational corruption networks and in other cooperative efforts to combat significant corruption, including, as appropriate, cooperating with the governments of other countries to extradite corrupt actors;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H063D7E2E9E6743E2B38FBAAACCFE18CE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>whether the government of the country recognizes the rights of victims of corruption, ensures their access to justice, and takes steps to prevent victims from being further victimized or persecuted by corrupt actors, government officials, or others;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA375C89EBEC04736BCF9485DCC2C1C14"><enum>(9)</enum><text>whether the government of the country protects victims of corruption or whistleblowers from reprisal due to such persons having assisted in exposing corruption, and refrains from other discriminatory treatment of such persons;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE660E24479AA413F9044A5CB9AA297E8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>whether the government of the country is willing and able to recover and, as appropriate, return the proceeds of corruption;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB23D17FC1984197B8D74FF003FDEB5C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>whether the government of the country is taking steps to implement financial transparency measures in line with the Financial Action Task Force recommendations, including due diligence and beneficial ownership transparency requirements;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEE91600D4D6A4BDE97B6FB0BCA90F94B"><enum>(12)</enum><text>whether the government of the country is facilitating corruption in other countries in connection with state-directed investment, loans or grants for major infrastructure, or other initiatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9B0ED42CDE64EEA8D26ABB11DF1A597"><enum>(13)</enum><text>such other information relating to corruption as the Secretary of State considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD49CA87B7D0C461A9419F8A678742696"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessing government efforts To combat corruption in relation to relevant international commitments</header><text>In determining whether a government is making serious and sustained efforts to address corruption, the Secretary of State shall consider the government of a country’s compliance with the following, as relevant:</text> <paragraph id="H26EF6745D5EF43148EAA8AE965E43212"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Inter-American Convention against Corruption of the Organization of American States, done at Caracas March 29, 1996.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8781CB75C23143F5804C317D557C29D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Convention on Combating Bribery of Foreign Public Officials in International Business Transactions of the Organisation of Economic Co-operation and Development, done at Paris December 21, 1997 (commonly referred to as the <quote>Anti-Bribery Convention</quote>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFAD37E7A1614B5EBD1420C83D4160DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United Nations Convention against Transnational Organized Crime, done at New York November 15, 2000.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB9D6EED7A5F646A0B53B620913B15BA7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United Nations Convention against Corruption, done at New York October 31, 2003.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE1E6A414443468FB773DCABF7FAD6DB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Such other treaties, agreements, and international standards as the Secretary of State considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H766298ED3A464037B662A3A4AF9BDE08"><enum>5.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions under Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act</header>
<subsection id="H1B5CA257A2374C3CB658141CE8C73C1C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury, should evaluate whether there are foreign persons engaged in significant corruption for the purposes of potential imposition of sanctions under the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (subtitle F of title XII of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note) in all countries identified as tier 3 countries under section 3.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5ACF6C2D14F24F83B0FE5479BDBD9BF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after publishing the list required by section 3(a) and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State shall submit to the committees specified in subsection (e) a report that includes—</text>
<paragraph id="H67757158DF9E41CF9832A20C4A397BBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a list of foreign persons with respect to which the President imposed sanctions pursuant to the evaluation under subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFCB08F9CB8504F7FB01A9505A0DCFEB3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the dates on which such sanctions were imposed; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F6807B9596A47E0911603F532C3CBC7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the reasons for imposing such sanctions.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD03150EFFB6C4040A15CC43C81D83129"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text>Each report required by subsection (b) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HB735556DF8124AA98E242EBE38CEAA4B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Briefing in lieu of report</header><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury, may provide a briefing to the committees specified in subsection (e) instead of submitting a written report required under subsection (b), if doing so would better serve existing United States anti-corruption efforts or the national interests of the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HABD7A46406904054A0BE205AAA5343B1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Committees specified</header><text>The committees specified in this subsection are—</text>
<paragraph id="HF9B1D95ED8314B92B74FE87FF04A79B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD13236EE71B47A8932B56314675F5E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Financial Services, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H7811DE49ECE74D7BA1E0FEF3C9AFB287"><enum>6.</enum><header>Designation of embassy anti-corruption points of contact</header>
<subsection id="H2B8C2100DFF14654BB2BAB3EC3D404A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State shall annually designate an anti-corruption point of contact at the United States diplomatic post to each country identified as tier 2 or tier 3 under section 3, or which the Secretary otherwise determines is in need of such a point of contact. The point of contact shall be the chief of mission or the chief of mission's designee.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H769D8204A77A46848C6F690E3F5380D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>Each anti-corruption point of contact designated under subsection (a) shall be responsible for enhancing coordination and promoting the implementation of a whole-of-government approach among the relevant Federal departments and agencies undertaking efforts to—</text>
<paragraph id="HF26D7E7C004B4A2F8A7A0E3DB356CBE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote good governance in foreign countries; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6CF08A4A57784C3A9AEDDE80D2CFCBFA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enhance the ability of such countries—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF5C3C386645F4DFCA2E74522DDA4B839"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to combat public corruption; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F038E0726B64D92B5A22EFD07FB898E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to develop and implement corruption risk assessment tools and mitigation strategies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H18B7705F00494186B815BB0E7CEA2961"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Training</header><text>The Secretary of State shall implement appropriate training for anti-corruption points of contact designated under subsection (a). </text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

