<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H91C2A8AEF2DF408EB7DC401A75A356FC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1153 RH: Deterring America’s Technological Adversaries Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 43</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1153</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–63]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide a clarification of non-applicability for regulation and prohibition relating to sensitive personal data under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="HA4150EBCE79445C0A94FA315536D2732" style="OLC"><section id="H6EE8B942168042909557686859A6E17C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and table of contents</header><subsection id="HF6F3F761B2024AF190F424CA6718624E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Deterring America’s Technological Adversaries Act</short-title></quote> or <quote><short-title>DATA Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87EF8BC2FCB742BAA2E9FFED44D59A47"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows: </text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H6EE8B942168042909557686859A6E17C" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title and table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD5A1BD27F689476ABFEDE40B565B4794" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H984FF2A3B167460E9B25AE4D35D3FEB6" level="section">Sec. 3. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H667E64364F854CAAAA0C3C056AC51FE0" level="section">Sec. 4. Severability.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H38FD082AC4594653B42B431480AE1C9B" level="section">Sec. 5. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H910ABE3803164F7EA91AD0E0EFC48524" level="title">Title I—Clarification of non-applicability for regulation and prohibition relating to sensitive personal data under International Emergency Economic Powers Act</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE56370D52DEA42A2A2FC243DF040E1F1" level="section">Sec. 101. Clarification.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H008A96FCFC574EE1BB7734FE0D8454E3" level="section">Sec. 102. Directive.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H44AFBCBEF53E4C7E9D91A7DFBBE3ADA6" level="title">Title II—Imposition of sanctions on certain transactions relating to connected software applications</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5A8880F5C0374CBFB6E83C0CD03175CE" level="section">Sec. 201. Imposition of sanctions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE9EFED75CE234B188483FDC11BFA2538" level="section">Sec. 202. Sanction described.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H18E90A6E3C44459AAAC6EBAE03723A8F" level="section">Sec. 203. Sunset.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8062605565DB457989D4ED79A9109664" level="title">Title III—Specific determinations with respect to the imposition of sanctions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H18AADD031D3742289AA01EDFD33C0892" level="section">Sec. 301. Determination relating to Bytedance, Ltd., TikTok, and related entities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9601BD818C9E4B79B1D4664ED8CA3BE8" level="section">Sec. 302. Requests by appropriate congressional committees.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HD5A1BD27F689476ABFEDE40B565B4794"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HE11016C0C2F4481C9978BA530CA7F62B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On December 2, 2022, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, Christopher Wray, stated, <quote>We … do have national security concerns about the app [TikTok]. Its parent company is controlled by the Chinese government. And it gives them the potential to leverage the app in ways that I think should concern us … One, it gives them the ability to control the recommendation algorithm which allows them to manipulate content and if they want to, to use it for influence operations which are a lot more worrisome in the hands of the Chinese Communist Party than whether or not you're steering somebody as an influencer to one product or another. They also have the ability to collect data through it on users which can be used for traditional espionage operations, for example. They also have the ability on it to get access, they have essentially access to the software to devices. So you're talking about millions of devices and that gives them the ability to engage in different kinds of malicious cyber activity through that. And so all of these things are in the hands of a government that doesn't share our values and that has a mission that's very much at odds with what's in the best interest of the United States that that should concern us.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H812D5606411A46D387B9AC62C0F15114"><enum>(2)</enum><text>On December 3, 2022, the Director of National Intelligence, Avril Haines, <quote>It is extraordinary the degree to which China, in particular, but they're not the only ones, obviously, are developing just frameworks for collecting foreign data and pulling it in and their capacity to then turn that around and use it to target audiences for information campaigns or for other things, but also to have it for the future so that they can use it for a variety of means that they’re interested in.</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F791F81FFE14469939329EC596FA4B1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On December 16, 2022, the Director of Central Intelligence, Bill Burns, stated, <quote>I think it's a genuine concern … for the U.S. government, in the sense that, because the parent company of TikTok is a Chinese company, the Chinese government is able to insist upon extracting the private data of a lot of TikTok users in this country, and also to shape the content of what goes on to TikTok as well to suit the interests of the Chinese leadership … What I would underscore, though, is that it's genuinely troubling to see what the Chinese government could do to manipulate TikTok.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D84431F473043A9A58B67CA545B0609"><enum>(4)</enum><text>On December 23, 2022, both chambers of Congress passed a bipartisan spending bill that included a ban on using TikTok from government devices.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H984FF2A3B167460E9B25AE4D35D3FEB6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional amounts are authorized to be made available to carry out this Act.</text></section><section id="H667E64364F854CAAAA0C3C056AC51FE0" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act or its application to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity does not affect other provisions or applications of this section that can be given effect without the invalid provision or application, and to this end the provisions of this Act are severable.</text></section><section id="H38FD082AC4594653B42B431480AE1C9B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HF03C07E671B34EB8BCD691BA3E3D57FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency or instrumentality of a foreign state</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>agency or instrumentality of a foreign state</quote> has the meaning given such term under section 1603(b) of title 28, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF28152EA44474AD3975640C29D757075"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA2FB83B1EF0B4AF8BB90B788B33A428F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs, Committee on Ways and Means, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D62C610A02548D1AFE94ECD31C15F8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6489D59912244EBCA7CE0CF5C76DEB71"><enum>(3)</enum><header>China</header><text>The term <quote>China</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H7C9F42448C854161890CE9C222B77DE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>when used in the geographic sense, the country of the People’s Republic of China; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C211C93125549129E584C57D83AE881"><enum>(B)</enum><text>otherwise, the Government of the country of the People’s Republic of China, including any entity acting on behalf of, or the benefit of—</text><clause id="HABE41FAFE66E42C68B2D89DE48CA149C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the country of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></clause><clause id="H2D24B14B38F14D61BBCE32B644374CA7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Government of the country of the People’s Republic of China.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC429D64F8C3464AA2A6D0D1FF053D9B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Connected software application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>connected software application</quote> has the meaning given such term in Executive Order 14034 (86 Fed. Reg. 31423; relating to protecting Americans' sensitive data from foreign adversaries).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DB91C12356347D682F258C2B21E0FCC" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Election interference in or against a foreign country that is a treaty ally of the united states or a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States</header><text>The term <quote>election interference in or against a foreign country that is a treaty ally of the United States or a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States</quote> means actions to engage in, directly or indirectly, activities originating from, or directed by, persons located, in whole or in substantial part, outside the territory of a treaty ally of the United States or a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States that have the purpose or effect of tampering with, altering, unlawfully accessing, or causing a misappropriation of information with the purpose or effect of interfering with or undermining election processes or institutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6ED48E5CEE5248A08EA228B1A07C25AA" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Election interference in or against the United States</header><text>The term <quote>election interference in or against the United States</quote> includes actions to engage in, directly or indirectly, activities originating from, or directed by persons located, in whole or in substantial part, outside the United States that—</text><subparagraph id="H4E7B5D0272D540999B3E7C42C31B9E8C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have the purpose or effect of tampering with, altering, unlawfully accessing, or causing a misappropriation of information with the purpose or effect of undermining election processes or institutions; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H600C13E379A44F73A0E7816471011DE6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>deny access, block, degrade, or alter election and campaign infrastructure, or related systems or data related to political parties, candidates in elections for public office, the administration of elections for public office, or any public election activity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D9F12501A3542038E725A8048818835" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>consist of the making of contributions or donations, or any other activity prohibited under section 319 of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30121">52 U.S.C. 30121</external-xref>), with the purpose or effect of undermining election processes or institutions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C01C29C7F7243788777AD1E8E764BFD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign person</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H0BCEB3D81F434C99A69FC40BB21366C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a person that is not a United States person; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78C5304DAB644073B8536C8CCFF20E09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a nonresident alien individual, foreign corporation, foreign partnership, foreign trust, foreign estate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB01CC45FFEC148AA8AFA146423CD1303"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>knowingly</quote>, with respect to conduct, a circumstance, or a result, means that a person has actual knowledge, or should have known, of the conduct, the circumstance, or the result.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2F4C441DA034007932DBD9994C51B70"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Sensitive personal data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>sensitive personal data</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 7.2 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC1367C071514356BDFDE463A7648ED1" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Treaty ally of the United States</header><text>The term <quote>treaty ally of the United States</quote> means a foreign country that is a party to any of the following: </text><subparagraph id="HF17E8B974FFF4EBFAA7F2F4B2B1A45E0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The North Atlantic Treaty, signed at Washington, April 4, 1949.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30BA2CFBBE84471AA376AAE7A0336729" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Security Treaty Between Australia, New Zealand, and the United States of America, signed at San Francisco, September 1, 1951.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DDC61814CA74431907324D5C3A0E70C" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Mutual Defense Treaty Between the United States of America and the Republic of the Philippines, signed at Washington, August 30, 1951.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43247E5DCE0C4A5EBEBB33290D281199" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty, signed at Manilla, September 8, 1954.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A99DD1BB23E467DAC46FC7971B2DA3C" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security Between the United States of America and Japan, signed at Washington, January 19, 1960.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15DE07EA4F134BD380BA88E533155B0D" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Mutual Defense Treaty Between the United States of America and the Republic of Korea, signed at Washington, October 1, 1953.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E75466F64F54E7AA88B634A11DB789E"><enum>(11)</enum><header>United States person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H4AC2B7AFEFA54590BDFA589341F1AB44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H147A6DC017B34D80940BAEC2BB442BA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a permanent resident alien;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE08B71E2B6E04FD1B0DD3C4148E56924"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States (including foreign branches); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EF652816DDF4E299C19BEF1330F1555"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><title id="H910ABE3803164F7EA91AD0E0EFC48524"><enum>I</enum><header>Clarification of non-applicability for regulation and prohibition relating to sensitive personal data under International Emergency Economic Powers Act</header><section id="HE56370D52DEA42A2A2FC243DF040E1F1"><enum>101.</enum><header>Clarification</header><subsection id="HAF8F135C62B64253B8F52D933E4A358C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The importation to a country, or the exportation from a country, of sensitive personal data shall not constitute the importation from a country, or the exportation to a country, of information or informational materials for purposes of paragraph (1) or (3) of section 203(b) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702(b)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HBDB99E9AF5DA4F5C8881BE4D5B94F798"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a), and nothing in the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, may be construed to provide for the application of paragraph (1) or (3) of section 203(b) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702(b)</external-xref>) to the importation to China, or the exportation from China, directly or indirectly, of sensitive personal data. </text></subsection></section><section id="H008A96FCFC574EE1BB7734FE0D8454E3"><enum>102.</enum><header>Directive</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall issue a directive prohibiting United States persons from engaging in any transaction with a person that the Secretary of the Treasury determines knowingly provides or may transfer sensitive personal data of persons subject to United States jurisdiction to any foreign person that—</text><paragraph id="HE25121A7DD154565845323F4E9287860"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is subject to the jurisdiction or direction of, or directly or indirectly operating on behalf of, China; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H437641673EF84542A3AF840405CABEF8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is owned by, directly or indirectly controlled by, or is otherwise subject to the influence of China.</text></paragraph></section></title><title id="H44AFBCBEF53E4C7E9D91A7DFBBE3ADA6"><enum>II</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions on certain transactions relating to connected software applications</header><section id="H5A8880F5C0374CBFB6E83C0CD03175CE"><enum>201.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><subsection id="HBADD551997144FB5AD7920C2D0984D1B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall impose the sanction described in section 202 with respect to any foreign person that, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, knowingly—</text><paragraph id="HDD1B90E26B8D463C8C6176D2FD2D2990"><enum>(1)</enum><text>operates, directs, or otherwise deals in a connected software application that—</text><subparagraph id="HAC6FDF201AA74A83B87E00065B85B8F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is subject to the jurisdiction or direction of, or directly or indirectly operating on behalf of China, or is owned by, directly or indirectly controlled by, or otherwise subject to the influence of China; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34883BFC7C62410B85F4E8DA95EE8FB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is reasonable believed to have facilitated or may be facilitating or contributing to China’s—</text><clause id="H99B77D7961394CFFBF5A0431DB0736C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>military, intelligence, espionage, or weapons proliferation activities;</text></clause><clause id="HDE6484C5B18744CBB578DA5145969ECF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>censorship activities;</text></clause><clause id="H69F2D9CA155D4CC99A84315051B69EB9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>surveillance activities;</text></clause><clause id="H5070A7E5FB564CA5B85F3EC06DF54F7D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">control or use of recommendation algorithms that are capable of manipulating content;</text></clause><clause id="HDB5C5D061D4D480F9AAB7ED403227B7C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>malicious cyber activities; or</text></clause><clause id="H18BBCCCFCF474017A53C1189D1C93E1A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>use of data to target audiences for information campaigns;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD932C896EF4A461398541D197DCBC30B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">directly or indirectly orders, controls, directs, engages in, or otherwise facilitates an act of election interference against the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E4D852B01814E3093A954ED77B8E0B5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">directly or indirectly orders, controls, directs, engages in, or otherwise facilitates an act of election interference in or against a foreign country that is—</text><subparagraph id="H198504C7BDDD4F3094CE5DFCF15F9BCD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a treaty ally of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C2C1787B37A4575A4B7D32EEF919ACE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE803F460443440BB61401280665C0C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>directly or indirectly orders, controls, directs, engages in, or otherwise facilitates an act of steering United States policy and regulatory decisions in favor of China’s strategic objectives, to the detriment of the economic or national security of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20AF4D4031E340BE95D180C40B5E9C38" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly facilitates a transaction or transactions for or on behalf of a person described, or a person that has engaged in the activity described, as the case may be, in paragraph (1), (2), (3), or (4);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54AB26755604467F87209F6AC2F13F1A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><text>knowingly assists, sponsors, or provides financial, material, or technological support for a person described, or a person that has engaged in the activity described, as the case may be, in paragraph (1), (2), (3), or (4); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92755EB73EB949FFB66B1A70627D0F27"><enum>(7)</enum><text>is owned or controlled by, or has acted for or on behalf of, directly or indirectly, a person described, or a person that has engaged in the activity described, as the case may be, in paragraph (1), (2), (3), or (4).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B2294EE0D3644DDB5851D483F52FA67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>List of foreign countries that are democratic or emerging democratic partners of the United States</header><paragraph id="HC4817DE044384C48B91AF4FF772B8CE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees—</text><subparagraph id="HA33DE0D6D84642198278A71B36A49242"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a definition of the term <quote>democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D010042830542DE8A2790D3CE78A96B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a list of foreign countries that are designated as a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States for purposes of subsection (a)(3) that includes the countries listed in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H544332E7587F4DE095D338BB848D4DE1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial designations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sweden, Switzerland, Israel, India, and Taiwan shall be deemed to have been so designated as a democratic or emerging democratic partner of the United States for purposes of subsection (a)(3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H657EFFE663A04135AEBE0579D2562617"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an updated list under subparagraph (A) on a periodic basis. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE9EFED75CE234B188483FDC11BFA2538"><enum>202.</enum><header>Sanction described</header><subsection id="H22DBE596B4E54F37AE0C9953A1BE751D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanction described in this section is the exercise of all powers granted to the President by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) (except that the requirements of section 202 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any foreign person or an agency or instrumentality of a foreign state, as the case may be, if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subsection><subsection id="H53F0A5BE460E48B7A9D4EB3ACB25EBDD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H62ABD5F715614D1A9EF967851E963F75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><paragraph id="H36491F35FAB34A809DE42D4B9E8910E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary for the implementation of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E9E758373034EE9A95F14A370C4E073"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prior briefing required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 10 days before the prescription of regulations under paragraph (1), the President shall brief the appropriate congressional committees regarding the proposed regulations and the provisions of this title that such regulations are implementing.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H92CC27FA4936438C97959C934D5837C0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, or causes a violation of any sanction authorized by this title, or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out such sanctions, shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H71E88CCB6F474AB98A9E962D3D9EE7F9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following activities shall not be subject to the imposition of sanctions under this title:</text><paragraph id="H752A9E4EA6794BE9A73F28F080B85225"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any authorized intelligence, law enforcement, or national security activities of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AA7CE62FC884D929B735F8D015215CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any transaction necessary to comply with United States obligations under the Agreement between the United Nations and the United States of America regarding the Headquarters of the United States, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, or the Convention on Consular Relations, done at Vienna April 24, 1963, and entered into force March 19, 1967, or any other United States international agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6F15AF99A05C4F08B7536B7C82B4909C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may, on a case-by-case basis and for periods not to exceed 180 days each, waive the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this title if the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees, not later than 15 days before such waiver is to take effect, that the waiver is vital to the national security interests of the United States.</text></subsection></section><section id="H18E90A6E3C44459AAAC6EBAE03723A8F"><enum>203.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title, and the authorities provided by this title, shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></title><title id="H8062605565DB457989D4ED79A9109664"><enum>III</enum><header>Specific determinations with respect to the imposition of sanctions</header><section id="H18AADD031D3742289AA01EDFD33C0892"><enum>301.</enum><header>Determination relating to Bytedance, Ltd., TikTok, and related entities</header><subsection id="HB6D6B4B66A064DD0A8C9E45A194AAF19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter for 3 years, the President shall transmit to the appropriate congressional committees a determination of whether reasonable grounds exist for concluding that any of the entities described in subsection (b)—</text><paragraph id="H593CD2E5A7B04DFCB0797473F5E849A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>meets the criteria described in paragraph (1) or (2) of section 102 for purposes of applying a directive described in such section with respect to the entity; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA9DB1FCF56F4CB7A59D34A580062E42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>have engaged in any conduct described in section 201.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8264EAC86F34D7DA5CCCD026913C380"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>The entities described in this subsection are—</text><paragraph id="HC0535185311649F6B718C26CBFC80D73"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Bytedance, Ltd.; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF747E52ABB844BBA154A159DB557AAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>TikTok;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35BF81091BEC489CA8ADE302509DCEF1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any subsidiary of or a successor to an entity described in paragraph (1) or (2); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC6E5C4D3BB24DDB8573841431699BAB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any entity owned or controlled directly or indirectly by an entity described in paragraph (1), (2), or (3). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF8A88D2449464A2E9EEAE507C6661951"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The determination described in subsection (a) shall be transmitted in unclassified form, and any supporting documentation may be transmitted in a classified annex. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB4AA783BAF284CB098F5684C040A2785"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application of sanctions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President makes an affirmative decision under subsection (a) with respect to any entity described in subsection (b), the President shall impose the sanction described in section 202 with respect to the entity, as appropriate. </text></subsection></section><section id="H9601BD818C9E4B79B1D4664ED8CA3BE8"><enum>302.</enum><header>Requests by appropriate congressional committees</header><subsection id="H5FCC345C977C4B80B03A986D268ADB42"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after receiving a request from the chairperson or ranking member of one or more of the appropriate congressional committees with respect to whether a foreign person meets the criteria described in paragraph (1) or (2) of section 102 for purposes of applying a directive described in such section with respect to the person, or have engaged in any conduct described in section 201 for the imposition of the sanction described in section 202, the President shall—</text><paragraph id="HDB95433CE1AC4CBABB592E379F26B7B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine if that person meets the requirements described in the applicable section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22FFD9F2A2744BEFA10E519D50FE6305"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the chairperson and ranking member of the committee or committees a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H183714B915C946139C281B5FBA23D9E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a statement of whether or not the President imposed or intends to impose such sanction with respect to the person; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2B4B0A9F0104654A507669B35E5D0E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if applicable, a description of the sanction so imposed or intended to be imposed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE08F2B0F32524C1F97A81A26C86E208C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability of information</header><paragraph id="HF128ED119A8044CFADCCACB3CD5A0555"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any information obtained at any time with respect to the President making a determination with respect to a foreign person under subsection (a), or under any review of the foreign person through other United States Government national security review processes, shall be made available to a committee or subcommittee of Congress of appropriate jurisdiction, upon the request of the chairman or ranking minority member of such committee or subcommittee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA73A9598F6D496B95EC742D9219058D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on disclosure</header><text>No such committee or subcommittee, or member thereof, may disclose any information made available under clause (i), that is submitted on a confidential basis unless the full committee determines that the withholding of that information is contrary to the national interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H68DB01DB0B574E68BC1973DFA3358E4B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each determination described in subsection (a)(1), and each report under subsection (a)(2), may be submitted in classified or unclassified form, and any supporting documentation to such determination or report may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection></section></title></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

