<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H93CDF0DA8E434ABCAAC24DFED8325212" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1535 IH: Eliminating Backlogs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1535</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To preserve expiring employment-based visas, and make them available for issuance during fiscal year 2024.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H57C4089A1E2B422B8E825E2F6EA2B263" style="OLC"><section id="H20149DB1584F40B09909CBA6274D0194" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eliminating Backlogs Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H715245D8A141423E9C30BE7A13C048D6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Preservation of expiring employment-based visas</header><subsection id="H1CD58FB4D8404420A007C37B39B7E6EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for fiscal year 2024, the worldwide level of employment-based immigrants authorized under section 201(d) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151(d)</external-xref>) shall be increased by the number computed under subsection (b) with respect to such worldwide levels.</text></subsection><subsection id="H07A63F2D7C854E36ADA898695FAAD676"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Computation</header><text>The number computed under this subsection is the difference (if any) between—</text><paragraph id="H28C7910CFE61401AAFF1174DE0A8EA43"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of visas that were originally made available to family sponsored immigrants under section 201(c)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151(c)(1)</external-xref>) for fiscal years 1992 through 2021, reduced by any unused visas made available to such immigrants in such fiscal years under section 201(c)(3) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151(c)(3)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA1FE73229C141D3893FDE2369818722"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the sum of the number of aliens who were issued employment-based immigrant visas or who otherwise acquired the status of aliens lawfully admitted to the United States for permanent residence under section 203(b) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1153">8 U.S.C. 1153(b)</external-xref>) during the fiscal years referred to in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B3AA4E75BB3424A9FF456DDE128B72A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text>The Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall allocate the visas made available as a result of the increase authorized under subsection (a) on a proportional basis, in accordance with subsections (b) and (e)(1) of section 203 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1153">8 U.S.C. 1153</external-xref>), and with subsection (e) of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1E5996BF15324CA9A035B2A6E5DA6633"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each visa made available under this section shall remain available for use in fiscal year 2024 or in any subsequent fiscal year, until the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, determines that such visa has been issued and used as the basis for an application for admission into the United States. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA0A3176A90CA4CF5AC18B30D7A3FE52C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inapplicability of per-Country limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each visa made available under this section shall be awarded in the order in which employment-based visa applications were filed and shall not be subject to the numerical limitations under section 202 of the Immigration and Nationality Act to particular foreign states.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

