<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6934797BBE42417F8AB95BEFD9363CB3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6848 IH: To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to prohibit institutions of higher education from requiring ideological oaths or similar statements, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6848</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to prohibit institutions of higher education from requiring ideological oaths or similar statements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H43FA381642E54D19A4CFAF20F0A04A81" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H24375924B9AB48F09C253D3821891D9B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition relating to ideological oaths and similar statements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 487(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44DC967552E247C7A3E3611C01B516C0"> <paragraph id="H22CA724F39CC49CB99BF4E58E789BE48" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(30)</enum> <subparagraph id="HDFEE1A714D0D451BB0BAA267BEAA8D6C" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The institution will not—</text> 
<clause id="HC01F94A376134DE0A8BC6B1623EF432C" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>compel, require, induce, or solicit a student enrolled at the institution, an employee or contractor of the institution, or an applicant for admission to or employment or contracting at the institution to—</text> <subclause id="H29CCED210C504FACA580681C48DB2DA2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>endorse an ideology that promotes the differential treatment of an individual or group of individuals based on race, color, or ethnicity; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H131ABCAFAED44403AC85F2F76C4F0C86"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide a statement indicating the person’s—</text> <item id="HD29199C3DD604813A88989A7C3C42C21"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>race, color, ethnicity, or national origin, except to the minimum extent needed record any necessary demographic information;</text></item> 
<item id="H98485CE9E9E5404B906954109D561768"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>views on, experience with, or past or planned contributions to efforts involving diversity, equity, and inclusion, marginalized groups, antiracism, social justice, intersectionality, or related concepts; or</text></item> <item id="HC529E50232F04CFBA6A5D157215F093F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>views on or experience with race, color, ethnicity, national origin, or other immutable characteristics; or</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H7A10EA7DE13F4D4A82A1C8A79807D89B" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide preferential consideration to a student enrolled at the institution, an employee or contractor of the institution, or an applicant for admission to or employment or contracting at the institution on the basis of the person’s unsolicited statement in support of an ideology described in clause (i)(I).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC4146B6133D1419B8BBD87E166043E09" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Nothing in this paragraph may be construed—</text> 
<clause id="H46AD4D89CBD4465CA23C752AB98DFB10" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to restrict academic research or coursework;</text></clause> <clause id="H38F9ADC7CE284817944470A73197DC36" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to prevent a person from providing to an institution of higher education the information described in subparagraph (A) on the person’s own initiative separate from any specific requirement or request from the institution; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H87F8475702894E38B039AD274FB36B08" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to prevent an institution from requiring an applicant for admission to or employment or contracting at the institution to—</text> <subclause id="HED27C17FF81D439EBB8B03E8BC5D0FAE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>disclose or discuss the content of the applicant’s research or artistic creations;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8DC7E7BEC9FC46EC81FB22E72AC3786E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>certify compliance with State and Federal antidiscrimination law; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H37D4B54538794FF0A65FD72F8C619DCA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>discuss pedagogical approaches or experience with students with learning disabilities.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

