<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H484BBFBB0A2B45D59E5F8BB6C2C7E4CC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4296 IH: Weatherization Resilience and Adaptation Program Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4296</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior to establish a grant program to assist primarily low-income individuals in making their homes and property more resilient to the impacts of climate change, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE1C0FC264B594FE49A7D18FEAEBDD584" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCE780A77DA4C4704A151942C87ED277C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Weatherization Resilience and Adaptation Program Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9117686658644038AA316FDD3604F274" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFDB7C1E8B4294D1087103D322BC45836"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Human accelerated climate change is causing significant shifts in global surface and atmospheric temperatures, accelerating the frequency of extreme weather events around the globe.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HECF0F37CEACC4C7B87C8D5513B810658"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Extreme weather events create environmental hazards such as excessive flooding, fire, heat, wind, and drought that have catastrophic impacts on frontline communities, who experience the worst and most immediate impacts of our climate crisis and often bear the brunt of such events seasonally, creating a cyclical pattern of disruption and destruction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE596C49FD1054B4EAB3DA783DCDE950D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Individuals can take steps to prevent and mitigate the worst impacts of extreme weather events on their home and property by implementing resilience and adaptation best practices, but the cost of these solutions puts them out of reach for many households.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H656095DEEB224175AFD213D385C7AE17"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Low-income homeowners and individuals who reside in affordable housing disproportionately live in areas that face the greatest threat from extreme weather events, yet can least afford the changes to their property to make them more resilient to disasters and adapted to the changing climate.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HCC66FFC2BCEB4F78B708CB5052B7FA9D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="H483C71041B104102918C1C6F8BC2B4D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Climate change</header><text>The term <term>climate change</term> means long-term shifts in temperatures and weather patterns.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE130C9A318D8499185372B445DB14540"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Climate-driven hazards</header><text>The term <term>climate-driven hazards</term> means hazards, such as floods, wildfires, landslides, extreme heat, extreme wind, and atmospheric rivers that have a human, economic, and ecological impact with increased frequency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H053043F4917A4C9B981350986BFA474D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C6A1B91D4804183B0B366D16ABEFFA4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible program participant</header><text>The term <term>eligible program participant</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H14D8FFDE618B4E56B03D556F66223778"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEDDE06242C77430F82CDF7F3088427D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a federally recognized Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H268501E5D3D147EF9300B5F41C941EDE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H215B88B26CAF42CEB79E000AA1441D1D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible property owners</header><text>The term <term>eligible property owner</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HFDF3A8C5DCF849CEAA4B9AFB561F9773"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a low-income property owner;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1E48242EB23843C8AC7C2ECE2DEF86DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an owner of a property of which the deed, ground lease, or a loan for the improvement thereof has a restriction or covenant related to housing affordability which will not expire for at least 5 years following the receipt of funds awarded under this Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEB7D0BDBEBB7468E928CD397CF6BBB01"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an owner of a multifamily dwelling building where more than 50 percent of dwelling units are occupied by residents whose rent is subsidized under a covered housing program listed in section 41411(a)(3) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12491">34 U.S.C. 12491(a)(3)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H677E522B93B34132B774FA670540ED35"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an owner of a property used as a community of manufactured homes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3858570A66234B4F97BA6ECA12054DF6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Low-income</header><text>The term <term>low-income</term> means income in relation to family size that is at or below 300 percent of the poverty level determined in accordance with criteria established by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, except that the Secretary may allow an eligible program participant to use a higher level if, after receiving a justification from such eligible program participant, the Secretary determines that such a higher level is necessary to carry out the purposes of this part and is consistent with the eligibility criteria established in this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77C5AA0C85DA4A999C88FDD087438BFC"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Manufactured home</header><text>The term <term>manufactured home</term> has the meaning given that term under section 603(6) of the Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5402">42 U.S.C. 5402(6)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49D90B91B9E24302BFD54D64AA7C193F"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Natural solutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>natural solutions</term> means ways of adapting or making property more resilient to climate-driven hazards by making changes that imitate naturally occurring ecological functions that mitigate such hazards.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE51B114D08D4CF391583073685FFDB0"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Resilience and adaptation standards</header><text>The term <term>resilience and adaptation standards</term> means a set of building, landscaping, and construction guidelines for how property owners may preemptively mitigate the impacts of extreme precipitation, flooding, wildfires, heat, and other hazards attributable to global climate change in their dwellings and surrounding non-dwelling property.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFBFA76AF528458A8776F6DF995128DD"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> refers to the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7003E7B7A76E4B0EB026EBFF3FF1C6FE"><enum>(11)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HA16D7CDB102D4D7F8B6726DF1E1016E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA223A83B0C2C48759ECBE1EED6874653"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4D939D265A542ACAEB590AB2BCDD052"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any territory or possession of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H156A5B9BA72545B2B8B1BCDFE840AD72"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grant program</header> 
<subsection id="H0B17A92D7CCB43DBA548B5F1738D8AEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a grant program to award grants to eligible program participants to assist eligible property owners with dwelling and property adaptations to increase their ability to withstand climate-driven hazards.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7F05798369164263A131E6454F911A50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Eligible program participants applying for a grant under this section shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDD76099730C7406E95E2066F0EA9C53F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary an application—</text> <subparagraph id="HCC8E400E4494494786989F2F218546B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at such time and in such manner as the Secretary determines appropriate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13469FA745074460A61FE34983601A64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>containing a description of—</text> <clause id="H2A5A52FF63CC4750857636573AA284E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the eligible activities to be undertaken with the grant funds;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD34FB48E2D574B6BA373C72EF351BAAC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>how eligible program participants will prioritize eligible property owners in awarding funding based on factors that take into account varying levels of disaster risk and means;</text></clause> <clause id="H4FAB81E4570D481FA79E72AED60F4585"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>how eligible property owners awarded funding will be required to report on their use of funds; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5BAB75672E3D4ED3AF428838AA878A43"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other information, as the Secretary determines appropriate; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5D9200BCA93D4CBB9ACC72E01A3C4524"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if awarded funding under this Act, accept and process applications for funding from eligible property owners using an online system accessible on a smartphone or personal electronic device in addition to accepting and processing applications through a paper format.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBBD1CBAC68ED4499945D8DE8798C58FB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="HCB9F0055599948B383C5814EC965C601"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible program participants</header><text>Eligible program participants—</text> <subparagraph id="HA0FED462A0064719AC7670EC29AE26CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall use funds awarded under this Act to award grants to eligible property owners for resilience and adaptation activities to mitigate the impacts of climate change, including related modifications needed to maintain the existing accessibility of a property to individuals with disabilities, as the Secretary may determine after the consultation prescribed under section 5(a);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H742167ABBC0440CA92799E1561B9D268"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall be required to conduct outreach to educate eligible property owners, regardless of whether such property owners have received funds awarded under this Act, about how they can make structural improvements to their homes and property;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H07B6C4FF165A49BA9AEAB15C6B73370D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may use up to 15 percent of funds awarded under this Act for expenses related to administering such funds and for the outreach required under subparagraph (B);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE2ED1BAE18484756803DECED774D45AE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall not add additional eligibility requirements that materially change who is eligible for funding under this Act or add procedural burdens that limit property owners from applying for, and receiving, funding according to rules promulgated under section 5 of this Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F237CB0D42E445FB4C1FF968C502980"><enum>(E)</enum><text>shall only award grants for activities related to buildings, assets, or land located in areas where climate-driven hazards are more likely to occur as a result of climate change; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0AD550E4A69E42D2AEACE8A4DAC2C24C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>when awarding grants to the owner of a multifamily building—</text> <clause id="HF689035A62C446279448620B7F9BCE94"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may require financial participation from such owner as a condition of awarding a grant for an activity with respect to that multifamily building;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF046162EEFEB4FF9A17C43819C0D5881"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of projects funded under this Act that involve the displacement of a resident from any occupied housing unit, shall only award a grant on the condition that such owner—</text> <subclause id="H6ACA96E411B94A7B9EA88ABE6D24B3AA"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides, at the option of the resident, a suitable and habitable housing unit that is, with respect to the housing unit from which the resident is displaced—</text> 
<item id="HDB9ADC80BB2248BF8026143F9EF87329"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">of a comparable size;</text></item> <item id="H43DDCC041E32407DA64A411993A143EA"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">located in the same local community or a community with reduced hazard risk; and</text></item> 
<item id="HAF2CACB5D38C48E1A8BA4D23D32D1940"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offered under similar costs, conditions, and terms; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H9262757EDE214BD081C1D64686D3BB47"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensures that resident displaced are provided with the ability to return to their former unit, or a comparable unit located in the same multifamily dwelling following the completion of the grant-funded project; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE17AD4DABB324DC6B44DD2FC19DD31A1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall only award a grant on the condition that such owner refrains from—</text> <subclause id="H79B0E8B37CCF4FE4B27C088E44B9C965"><enum>(I)</enum><text>raising rent on dwelling units in such multifamily building as a result of any improvements paid for by funding awarded under this Act; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H71D7E4269288442BBD63A436FC2FCE83"><enum>(II)</enum><text>increasing rent on such dwelling units for any reason for at least 2 years unless specific rent increases during those 2 years were stipulated in agreements made prior to the awarding of funding under this Act to which such owner is a party.</text> </subclause></clause> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63B274D98B234B49A56F2CA88974DC69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible property owners</header><text>Eligible property owners shall use funds awarded under this Act to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H10EAE15B02E545B1872448A271E69DA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>make changes to existing buildings or other assets as necessary to meet the purpose of the program established under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46C9F5EB59CF4AA0AC9F4C8641DCB73E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>implement natural solutions to adapt land to changing conditions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H801B6D35B687470185C17A319005837E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rulemaking</header> 
<subsection id="HF5B5FB587391442AA2F8A73ACFE35E0C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall promulgate rules to carry out this Act in consultation with—</text> <paragraph id="H35B002BAEE3C4607A0AAF7600FE4047F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61BCE0EB5FBF43C9A0E6FE1D80D5F30B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2CAFD7B967434F1A8AE6C12693F68243"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98B82DFD7BC64E5B92359E070FDA327C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H331CD6BF4A504189B5190C52726407FF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the heads of such other Federal departments and agencies as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA9164034A9C3439DB20383FD9C7249D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required provisions</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that regulations promulgated pursuant to this section include provisions that—</text> <paragraph id="H38E0D4D18F5041878475E5961176BF5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in coordination with the Director, prescribe resilience and adaptation standards; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H464BA7E836AB460699B6097AF41B177D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide guidance to eligible program participants in the implementation of this Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED3A7A5605044351829051200203B354"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">create audits and annual reporting requirements as may be necessary or appropriate to determine whether an eligible program participant has carried out activities using grant funds—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H81F543626F1F4339A10F71B9BBA740CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a timely and effective manner; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H576B7B952E924853B29971CCE104C0A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in accordance with the requirements of this Act and other applicable laws; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4A2DD1FB5F2422EAE2A73F7A7F8D40E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and make publicly available performance targets for public review, which shall include spending thresholds for each year from the date on which funds are obligated by the Secretary to the grantee until such time all funds have been expended.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> <section id="H992028BD7FB54598B8ED7FF9D4C0340D"><enum>6.</enum><header>Standards</header> <subsection id="H1D7EDC338501480FA579F8ADE485423D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall develop and publish on the National Institute of Standards and Technology website resilience and adaptation standards, after consultation with—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4293506E479E49CD8209476FD8284903"><enum>(1)</enum><text>relevant Federal departments and agencies as the Director determines appropriate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41F9142B5696447E9B7DD03481A1CC0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>private sector organizations as the Director determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H071FE22816574B8DA8BE225D9DD28DA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The resilience and adaptation standards published under this section shall take into consideration—</text> <paragraph id="H6A5A2B54434C442DB8D65AC150308124"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the cost of building materials;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B65115206924311AC0397E2C0487D47"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fair labor standards;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA287DD87E425426FBA43A78EB0F01C3B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>variation in impacts of climate change, geographical and topographical location, and pre-existing weatherization projects; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B0F7A79B2AA49C6822230551303C177"><enum>(4)</enum><text>natural solutions.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE8AD9CAB71E44ECABBAE192457C678AE"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act—</text> 
<paragraph id="H381B5527BF084D2CB0C10BDF84C463D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the Secretary, $250,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF01BBCAAE80F4C20A45EFA450AA12D39"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the Director, $2,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

