<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H095BC1598B9D4F308EC2C939751B732A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1566 IH: Safe Storage Lockers for House Office Buildings Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1566</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To permit employees of the House of Representatives who are authorized to possess certain weapons in the District of Columbia to bring such weapons into House Office Buildings for secure storage, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H44FF5D479A6C45E59B1271DDA48FA745" style="OLC"><section id="HCD32759D3B68419AB6271315EF83C30E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header><subsection id="HFE8402132986462F9D37468A2F68EB31"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Storage Lockers for House Office Buildings Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB0BAA8D06BCC4F9DA3CF6EE399DB9A57"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H0E33B99DDFAC442191CCECE94B61383B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 2021, there were 2,654 violent crime incidents in the District of Columbia, and 2,900 offenses reported in the District of Columbia by 2 law enforcement agencies that submitted National Incident-Based Reporting System (NIBRS) data which covered the entire population of the District.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1FB607548FD48089B3FA751AD67BB95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many employees of the House of Representatives who work in House Office Buildings in the District of Columbia commute to and from their offices by walking, and many have themselves been victims of these crimes in the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0F0BEED16B546A7A44DAD077259E898"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Individuals in the District of Columbia are authorized under District of Columbia law to carry and use certain weapons for self-defense, including self-defense sprays, stun guns, and concealed firearms. However, District of Columbia and Federal law prohibit individuals from carrying these weapons inside a Federal building.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D01BA0666A42849A97523B1F60D22F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>As a result, employees of the House of Representatives who work in House Office Buildings in the District of Columbia are prohibited from carrying weapons inside the buildings in which they work, even if these employees are authorized under District of Columbia law to carry and use these weapons for self-defense outside these buildings.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA6C3CE7D96CC4B58BB57ED969355FE54"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorizing House employees to bring certain self-defense weapons into House office buildings</header><subsection id="H4FD98940A3A94774BC0B3F6448516E6C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual who is an employee of the House of Representatives may bring a weapon described in subsection (b) into a House office building if—</text><paragraph id="H6B0DEF5F973048BDA3FAC5FD47FA3A66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the individual is authorized under the laws of the District of Columbia to carry the weapon outside of the building;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0966464A49A4AC496079D9D3BB4B4ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>immediately prior to entering the building, the individual is carrying the weapon in compliance with such laws;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA72FCFF026D94D2B8011DCAAA65CCC77"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the individual enters the building through an external pedestrian entrance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H638B98968BC04D3BBE525A84A803E584"><enum>(4)</enum><text>upon entering the building with the weapon, the individual leaves the weapon in a storage locker operated by the United States Capitol Police under section 3 while the individual remains in the building; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F95FC44F795416CA59B38D5FF587684"><enum>(5)</enum><text>after retrieving the weapon from the locker, the individual leaves the building immediately.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H25DA62EAED5E45CE9EE27F39CB7E4527"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Weapons described</header><text>The weapons described in this subsection are as follows:</text><paragraph id="H0547A4C939D2403CB1E8B686840F8B76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A self-defense spray described in section 212 of the Firearms Control Regulations Act of 1975 (sec. 7–2502.12, D.C. Official Code).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D604AE9A63049358E54460A29696261"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A stun gun described in section 101(17A) of the Firearms Control Regulations Act of 1975 (sec. 7–2501.01(17A), D.C. Official Code).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD6E5B1588E942D6B2665C947683BBBD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A firearm described in section 101(9) of the Firearms Control Regulations Act of 1975 (sec. 7–2501.01(9), D.C. Official Code).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H67E9870D628249A092EB479020C8C754"><enum>3.</enum><header>Provision of safe storage lockers at building entrances</header><subsection id="HF8DA83EB0F1E494D92961FDBF7354132"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Responsibilities of Capitol Police Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Capitol Police Board shall design, install, and operate storage lockers at external pedestrian entrances to each House office building, which may be used while an employee of the House is in the building to safely store a weapon which the employee brings into the building under section 2, and from which the employee may retrieve the weapon when the employee leaves the building.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2068419F25C24099B4795A099CF15355"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Capitol Police Board shall promulgate such regulations as may be required to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H84F1A8B7063A43A58D19DB0A7641C322"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 5104(e)(1)(A) of title 40, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>except as authorized</quote> and inserting <quote>except as provided under the Safe Storage Lockers for House Office Buildings Act or as authorized</quote>. </text></subsection></section><section id="HBB894F0EB2E646588421DCD579A0ACA9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><subsection id="H156C2B0C03D24DABB01DC820C9232D4D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Employee of the House of Representatives</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act, an <quote>employee of the House of Representatives</quote> includes an intern (whether paid or unpaid) and a fellow assigned to an office of the House of Representatives.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC9E157D6DEDF4A0485E17146E019BF05"><enum>(b)</enum><header>House office building</header><paragraph id="HC889E1023AC04647814F5B663A776CD5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>House office building</term> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H93B3D8265F5245BC96AE7C10F4BEA3F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Cannon House Office Building.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43314AF4A7244A4599C81B50578D6B34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Longworth House Office Building.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H323F228CC75A422A84880B0F524EB398"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Rayburn House Office Building.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H514C56A5DEAD4C80A56E020A86E96177"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Ford House Office Building.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF671979EFAA04C7C93564F02E257D4AF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The O’Neill House Office Building.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F69690CC1EF46EBBD20D489DA20BADB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The House wing of the United States Capitol.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD86F43A5EBB24CB9BCCDB2FC9EEFA3D0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion of garages</header><text>The term <term>House office building</term> does not include a garage of a building described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

