<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8F62252431B9464DB615B38CACD5F47E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5189 IH: Voter Integrity and Defense Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5189</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230811">August 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to condition the eligibility of a State or jurisdiction in a State to receive Federal funds to support the administration of elections for Federal office in the State on having laws in effect that require voters to present a valid photo identification in order to receive or cast a ballot in such elections, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE982D7E4C4504A619F457D6432A64712" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC3648A59EAED4FBCBDCED7228E8711F0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Voter Integrity and Defense Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBDA23109FB3149B2A73DB96C1CDB0F47"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring photo identification law as condition of eligibility for Federal funds to support election administration</header> <subsection id="H0A8B71368E0A47FB8F9ED6F6469468E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle D of title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21001">52 U.S.C. 21001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new part:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3E3F080721F74C1CA7AC7A48A0ACF462" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<part id="H06593C47CE8A470D958EC75A2AAE7F48"><enum>7</enum><header>Conditioning Eligibility for Funds on Laws Requiring Photo Identification for Voting</header> 
<section id="H82BDD6962E0849948771BB4B3CCBED48"><enum>297.</enum><header>Condition on eligibility for funds</header> 
<subsection id="H8D59A56E81024D2CA9EF43D43CFA1D80"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requiring provision of photo identification for voting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or a jurisdiction in a State is not eligible to receive a payment from the Commission under this Act or any other Act unless the State or jurisdiction certifies to the Commission that the State has in effect a law that—</text> <paragraph id="HB8B23828BE544F799B4E61AEE75BCC16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prevents the appropriate State or local election official from providing a ballot for an election for Federal office to an individual who desires to vote in person unless the individual presents to the official a valid photo identification described in section 297A; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H171C17EC13E2498396C9FF54D3F70E13"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prevents the appropriate State or local election official from accepting any ballot for an election for Federal office provided by an individual who votes other than in person unless the individual submits with the ballot a copy of a valid photo identification described in section 297A.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H02FF4C84717A4285BF6BDB6613255AE3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception for absent military voters</header><text>A State or jurisdiction is eligible to receive a payment if the State provides an exemption under the law described in subsection (a) for absent uniformed services voters under section 107(1) of the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20310">52 U.S.C. 20310(1)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5C0ABF95B5A147CB9CE4B35ED8383F6D"><enum>297A.</enum><header>Valid photo identification described</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A valid photo identification described in this section with respect to an individual is any of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0AEC67C88E004E14AB6809077AD529F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A valid State-issued motor vehicle driver’s license that includes a photo of the individual and an expiration date.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCCAE1FB0919C4B7EA77FACD919251627"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A valid State-issued identification card that includes a photo of the individual and an expiration date.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F8939388F5B4E598491AE01CC7420ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A valid United States passport for the individual.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40DF1551B0694A11B4F7A4D1DE58E00D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A valid military identification for the individual.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C93668FB9064E99BA738D7D90C5956E"><enum>(5)</enum><text> Any other form of government-issued identification that the State may specify as a valid photo identification for purposes of voting in an election for Federal office.</text></paragraph></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC0503F2B0F274140A723186E22D0C848"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the items relating to subtitle D of title II the following:</text> <toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="yes-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> <toc-quoted-entry style="OLC"> <toc-entry idref="H06593C47CE8A470D958EC75A2AAE7F48" level="part">Part 7—Conditioning Payment of Funds on Laws Requiring Photo Identification for Voting</toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="H82BDD6962E0849948771BB4B3CCBED48" level="section">Sec. 297. Condition on payments.</toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="H5C0ABF95B5A147CB9CE4B35ED8383F6D" level="section">Sec. 297A. Valid photo identification described.</toc-entry> </toc-quoted-entry></toc> </subsection> <subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C1E3974E3044453A18E584F62AAD5AE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this Act shall apply with respect to payments made on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

