<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB67CBF07644F4AD490FD69B82C0CB43F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4457 IH: Protect American Voters Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4457</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230703">July 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to direct the Election Assistance Commission to adopt voluntary guidelines for election officials on the use of nonvoting election technology in elections for Federal office, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC9126AED701C41E3BF0CF4681667C514" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC3B57FDB36194B94B96EED6BC3B3313E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect American Voters Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HC8B0802EF0D442A6B89850DD1ECAD60E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Voluntary guidelines with respect to nonvoting election technology</header> <subsection id="H0A039F38B1A54670A01BFD8FAE10BFDF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Election Assistance Commission</header> <paragraph id="HE923C6F9E5E34ABD94804C68DF4F9AF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adoption of guidelines</header><text>Title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20921">52 U.S.C. 20921 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subtitle:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEF26D1CBBCC2451D809F4299183471B3" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subtitle id="H6DF919CDF70F4108A7BAC59B6C3B11B4"><enum>E</enum><header>Voluntary Guidelines for Use of Nonvoting Election Technology</header>
<section id="HCF434CEB90764038B9A5F10B092F1135"><enum>298.</enum><header>Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Commission</header>
<subsection id="HB5A4667023C3405EBFF64327D239E3D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Adoption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall adopt voluntary guidelines for election officials on the use of nonvoting election technology, taking into account the recommendations of the Standards Board under section 298A.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB11C94C6FF1941B1BBCECE29BE76DF4A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Commission shall review the guidelines adopted under this subtitle not less frequently than once every 4 years, and may adopt revisions to the guidelines as it considers appropriate.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H66B8BCEB52DE4D81A477B49B97846BA0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Process for adoption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The adoption of the voluntary guidelines under this subtitle shall be carried out by the Commission in a manner that provides for each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H3176A60B2F6342739EBD92814C9B35D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Publication of notice of the proposed guidelines in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1110B102EC4E4F978B5D5F1C54E4D714"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An opportunity for public comment on the proposed guidelines.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02E53F29C8B447D7BEB362770A5F9CA4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An opportunity for a public hearing on the record.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB6556CA161904ED79AC9562B8F96BD8E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Publication of the final recommendations in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H643453E241224089B6CCD49FEE41BBC2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadline for initial set of guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall adopt the initial set of voluntary guidelines under this section not later than December 31, 2026.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H953DF6A8161B4F79851EC1D0183EDF6E"><enum>298A.</enum><header>Role of Standards Board</header>
<subsection id="HE84A8F12BD864DFF8F9B1A6FF63D855A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Standards Board shall assist the Commission in the adoption of voluntary guidelines under section 298, including by providing the Commission with recommendations on appropriate standards for the use of nonvoting election technology, including standards to ensure the security and accuracy, and promote the usability, of such technology, and by conducting a review of existing State programs with respect to the testing of nonvoting election technology.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H588ECB8C9B9048239FE49E67516B4EB8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sources of assistance</header> <paragraph id="H57C184FC6C28472DAAA7B17BA5F991FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Certain members of Technical Guidelines Development Committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following members of the Technical Guidelines Development Committee under section 221 shall assist the Standards Board in carrying out its duties under this section:</text>
<subparagraph id="H9DA12EB103CF45ADB083699FFACF5883"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H858335E056F24F2CBA12B074D7F6C3D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The representative of the American National Standards Institute.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H554E4A27260B472DAF7404E304D43D72"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The representative of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HECE66EC3A87B4CB2BD27D6BE6906D08E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 4 members of the Technical Guidelines Development Committee appointed under subsection (c)(1)(E) of such section as the other individuals with technical and scientific expertise relating to voting systems and voting equipment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H86C3B115D7124E10940D2079D6C42E87"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Detailee from CISA</header><text>The Executive Board of the Standards Board may request the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security to provide a detailee to assist the Standards Board in carrying out its duties under this section, so long as such detailee has no involvement in the drafting of any of the voluntary guidelines.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H683E39A40BA24BA196555DFCAEF9B4A2" commented="no"><enum>298B.</enum><header>Use of payments to obtain or upgrade technology</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State may use funds provided under any law for activities to improve the administration of elections for Federal office, including to enhance election technology and make election security improvements, to obtain nonvoting election technology which is in compliance with the voluntary guidelines adopted under section 298 or to upgrade nonvoting election technology so that the technology is in compliance with such guidelines, and may, notwithstanding any other provision of law, use any unobligated grant funding provided to the State by the Election Assistance Commission from amounts appropriated under the heading <quote>Independent Agencies—Election Assistance Commission—Election Security Grants</quote> in title V of division C of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/93">Public Law 116–93</external-xref>) for the purposes of enhancing election technology and making election security improvements until December 31, 2024.</text></section>
<section id="H69364B79AEDC48B68925F23990C9D1CC"><enum>298C.</enum><header>Nonvoting election technology defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subtitle, the term <term>nonvoting election technology</term> means technology used in the administration of elections for Federal office which is not used directly in the casting, counting, tabulating, or collecting of ballots or votes, including each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H6064E960968743FE96B823E238EEA024"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Electronic pollbooks or other systems used to check in voters at a polling place or verify a voter’s identification.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0AB04FC97D904B84BC7819A17325C48A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Election result reporting systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FDFA7D52E4F4D2FB877CEAA140D0AC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Electronic ballot delivery systems.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3B0025827E88485FA367820C62FA6DDC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Online voter registration systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H38DF457FB8DC4207B2C53C88DC84EE3B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Polling place location search systems.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6288D8651C6447F785D94649D297C93B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Sample ballot portals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA68E75E6BC38497382A26273F8E2C76C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Signature systems.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8E74BCE3E5CB49FBAE440BCB7ADB15CA"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Such other technology as may be recommended for treatment as nonvoting election technology as the Standards Board may recommend.</text></paragraph></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EBEC16D829D40FEB660DA5F377527DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the items relating to title II the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6B77941F4A2B466BB030D0B108840B23" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="subtitle">Subtitle E—Voluntary Guidelines for Use of Nonvoting Election Technology </toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298. Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Commission. </toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298A. Role of Standards Board. </toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298B. Use of payments to obtain or upgrade technology.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298C. Nonvoting election technology defined.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H316363ABABFA47B8A0AF4D24F25C3536"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of technology used in most recent election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any nonvoting election technology, as defined in section 298C of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (as added by subsection (a)(1)), which a State used in the most recent election for Federal office held in the State prior to the date of the enactment of this Act shall be deemed to be in compliance with the voluntary guidelines on the use of such technology which are adopted by the Election Assistance Commission under section 298 of such Act (as added by subsection (a)(1)).</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

