<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F025B8F87D24ECFA4DCF19A35B4BC39" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5085 IH: Protect America's Children from Toxic Pesticides Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5085</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230728">July 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act to fully protect the safety of children and the environment, to remove dangerous pesticides from use, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4AACC34A25754200BEC29DA6B24BBBD2" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HDE298DC73D9D4B1B86F301D3CBE8CF9A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect America's Children from Toxic Pesticides Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD654E0CAD5634B8C9661B4A656BE5CCF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF1997865E2E54445A7C6A357F0B95DEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Environmental Protection Agency (referred to in this section as the <term>EPA</term>) regularly fails to incorporate updated scientific understanding to protect human health and the environment from the harmful effects of pesticide products, as envisioned by the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>), resulting in the use of billions of pounds of pesticides every year that were approved based on outdated science;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F32754C5A684F2883C7777F25AE6181"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States lags behind the European Union and other developed nations in protecting its people and its environment from toxic chemicals, allowing the use of 72 pesticides that have been banned or are being phased out in the European Union alone;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H007741CE716B41DB98ADA9374C3F9837"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the EPA registers nearly 65 percent of pesticides through conditional registrations and frequently waives requirements to extend the use of conditional registrations prior to completion of comprehensive registration;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H10FDC20381354E919281D03E0ACBBD69"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the EPA permits the continued sale of potentially dangerous stocks of pesticides after registration has been canceled, suspended, or otherwise voided;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDF5764BC8E2748CB9D1182789069AD32"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the EPA uses emergency exemptions to keep pesticides on the market for years without undergoing a comprehensive registration process that would ensure the safe use of the pesticides;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE6687F0D2AB74CD293982885856DB1B6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the EPA is prohibited from requiring the disclosure of inert ingredients, even though inert ingredients can account for 99 percent of a pesticide product and include carcinogenic and toxic chemicals;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H56BB1272B08545078E076948C5A6F998"><enum>(7)</enum><text>scientists have repeatedly linked exposure to organophosphate pesticides to neurodevelopmental damage in children;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4605D6B5CAEF40A08B987ABA1739F783"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the United States Fish and Wildlife Service and the National Marine Fisheries Service have determined that organophosphate pesticides jeopardize the survival of 97 percent of endangered species;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D5158144EDB4CAB84052E47FDCDC13A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>neonicotinoid pesticides are contributing to the rapid decline of pollinators and the deterioration of pollinator health, including impaired foraging behavior and increased susceptibility to viruses, diseases, and parasites;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H316404339C6C405F99B42864425D28B3"><enum>(10)</enum><text>exposure to paraquat—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDDB1CC913B824AD995D9773E09200F47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>causes heart failure, kidney failure, liver failure, lung scarring, and damage to brain cells; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC50F1C2B3E384B02A24AAB691F6C353A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>greatly increases the risk of developing Parkinson’s disease;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71BF5FAC96244BAB856BAB6D218BE6C8"><enum>(11)</enum><text>local communities have been blocked by States from enacting pesticide restrictions to protect people and environment from toxic chemicals; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7437F7507BB84FEFA433A847E1B87436"><enum>(12)</enum><text>farmworkers are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H223100D3D70842E0A1686BA84E18BCF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disproportionately exposed to and harmed by pesticide use; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE0504A0A3A08444EABD95C2D2C7E8356"><enum>(B)</enum><text>afforded inadequate safeguards and far less protection than industrial workers. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H8B263C9794114608949560663C66199A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ending indefinite delays on review of dangerous pesticides</header> 
<subsection id="HFB732FB0DD3540F79AAE36B76C33D62A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header> 
<paragraph id="H65BE65BFC14D47F390E472506FB354BD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H4BBB5CA9F1D1428B9231EC201A6D7373"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subsection (z) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF38A600496D4488080A6AFE9334C2036"> 
<subsection id="HC9B9CB5980994A6799937866F70383B1"><enum>(z)</enum><header>Registration</header><text>The term <term>registration</term> means the approval of an active ingredient or pesticide product under this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H90AFD498383B4C358FBC10DF844BD4D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that has not previously been registered under this Act; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84A8BF91A7EC48D7B1740DE2E1A4B08D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for a crop or use for which the active ingredient or pesticide has not previously been registered under this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H305CA279345C4A19A7E0CECEFDFA6E75"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (aa) through (oo) as subsections (bb) through (pp), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H76FD46ED8CA94F9C9EADB8ED9C22A208"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (z) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35509D30C5DE446FA06F8457857BA5A4"> <subsection id="H836A37D914E94F4597B6F1ABB5ED3BFB"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Registration review determination</header> <paragraph id="HEFC656836E1C4E79A1FC5A49269C95EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>registration review determination</term> means the final decision to renew the registration of a pesticide product or active ingredient to authorize the use of the pesticide product or active ingredient—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H727E123982384FBAA474E28AE83F04C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for an additional 15-year period from the date of the previous registration, reregistration, or registration review determination, as applicable; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD5112E92AEA94CCF8C588BB663B8474C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in compliance with all applicable laws and regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB3444A26E165449B9E5CE29EEEFB0747"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>registration review determination</term> does not include any interim determination regarding the continued use of a pesticide product or active ingredient by the Administrator.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF56BD17D85F49358A97D9B69D406F8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> <subparagraph id="H2C7F2E516016476CA2E555CBB0B40898"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 2(e)(1) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>subsection (ee)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (ff)</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H242276DBF8F943DE98847BB048282F51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 3(h)(3)(E) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a">7 U.S.C. 136a(h)(3)(E)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 2(mm)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 2(nn)</quote>.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D70A42921F145679CF369E16EBCA276"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 33(b)(3) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136w-8">7 U.S.C. 136w–8(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="HAF0494EF74934604B8C204C210D69B22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>§2(mm)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>section 2(nn)</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6870298C2F2B4FF49873EC06DEC1AC17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Section 2(ll)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 2(mm)(2)</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD1A5EA28F85942F38A4636716B7D8027"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Suspension of dangerous pesticides on failure To complete registration review on time</header><text>Section 4 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a-1">7 U.S.C. 136a–1</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB29D047F3D1542F78A78777BA7413144"> <subsection id="HD7D4AC638BA0488EB302199DE362BC0A"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Suspension of dangerous pesticides on failure To complete registration review on time</header> <paragraph id="HBCE52DD18DA24F2C921BB11AF97DDC4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of dangerous pesticide</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>dangerous pesticide</term> means an active ingredient or pesticide product that may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF8EDE51B34354A03B2CC2AD04D66820C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be carcinogenic;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5581AE7C7EEC494CAE30622FE65D47E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be acutely toxic;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8757353068544A5E9E7DF86943A8518D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be an endocrine disruptor;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A795E4DBE384D199A6335CD6D68F965"><enum>(D)</enum><text>cause harm to a pregnant woman or a fetus; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DA60CD459EC483E9A039AF7D79B6CD4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>cause neurological or developmental harm.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H42A3A175862F45E195A0C219365318B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Petitions to designate dangerous pesticides</header> <subparagraph id="H03E9289C14014A8C87A9459EAD5EBBC9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An interested person may submit a petition under section 553(e) of title 5, United States Code, to designate an active ingredient or pesticide product as a dangerous pesticide under this subsection.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H96E3250B78B041319A647070448C69DB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Review</header><text> On receipt of a petition under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall review the petitions submitted by interested persons under that subparagraph relating to that active ingredient or pesticide product to determine if the active ingredient or pesticide product may warrant designation as a dangerous pesticide.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1140B223C68248DDBD9969ACC3CAA7CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Initial findings</header> <subparagraph id="HFF5930053DC044509E305F82BCABB016"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the receipt of a petition described in paragraph (2)(A), the Administrator shall make a finding as to whether the petition presents substantial scientific information indicating that the designation of the petitioned active ingredient or pesticide product as a dangerous pesticide may be warranted.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7CE01AECAAEC4F3CA706FE5240370D43"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Failure to review petition</header><text>If the Administrator fails make a finding on a petition by the date required under subparagraph (A), the active ingredient or pesticide product that is the subject of the petition shall be deemed to be a dangerous pesticide.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD64D40217FB24B1CB99D487D1BA5DA6F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Full consideration of all science</header> <clause id="HF74ECDFE71FC4617B09890E7366DEED7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In making a finding as to whether a petition provides substantial scientific information that an active ingredient or pesticide product may warrant designation as a dangerous pesticide under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall fully consider all relevant evidence, including—</text> 
<subclause id="H5254FE7346DD44489AF1146595677C62"><enum>(I)</enum><text>epidemiological studies or data;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H8292F167F67345658BC80A3E71A3BDA1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>peer-reviewed literature; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7B303720CEE24FB2AF75A1FF9A31BCCA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>data generated by—</text> <item id="H3C668937620845F1BEA89958C5E34A92"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a Federal or State agency; or</text></item> 
<item id="H52C04D3B7CF94209AC01B3E8725950D4"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an agency of a foreign government.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H592F9B6CCB89476B9DFB3D75B92A626D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Administrator shall not discount or ignore information provided in a petition described in paragraph (2)(A) based on any criteria under part 152 or 160 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1097C9E523054BDEAC3566051B76598E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Suspensions of pesticide</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6C94ABEB16764E6EB401DCACDA882E2A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, on a finding under paragraph (3)(A) that an active ingredient or pesticide product may warrant designation as a dangerous pesticide, or on operation of paragraph (3)(B), the Administrator shall immediately suspend the registration of the active ingredient or pesticide product if a valid reregistration eligibility decision or registration review determination has not been made regarding the active ingredient or pesticide product during the 15-year period ending on the date of that finding or operation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2090E09DCD704512B7B3C6D31F014E41"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The registration of an active ingredient or pesticide product suspended under subparagraph (A) shall remain suspended until such time as the Administrator makes a registration review determination in accordance with this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC57598418A4347B3B5DB89FFEC81E909"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Existing stocks</header><text>In accordance with section 6(a)(1), the Administrator shall not permit the continued sale and use of existing stocks of an active ingredient or pesticide product the registration of which has been suspended under paragraph (4).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B82F7DA5C0E41299E558FC35630E145"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Cancellation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), if the Administrator fails to suspend the registration of an active ingredient or pesticide product that may warrant designation as a dangerous pesticide as required by this subsection by not later than 60 days after any deadline described in this subsection—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFB79248C4AB04DAC8544B7ED7F2B6AE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the registration of the active ingredient or pesticide product shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without any further proceedings; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H685E0DC439604F828C311583CDD9CDEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in accordance with section 6(a)(1), the sale of existing stocks of the active ingredient or pesticide product shall be prohibited.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF0FC6781A6914D6EB1DBD90C696DBED7"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Inapplicability of IREDS</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an interim registration review decision or any other interim determination with respect to an active ingredient or pesticide product shall have no force or effect regarding any requirement of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H03241009B8D145DB9F818A7BE1516EDC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Emergency review of pesticides banned in other nations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC06AE90EDFB0477BA182DDD0219EA349"> 
<subsection id="HAB427524A63947EEAF25CBEE8CBAD5B9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Suspension and expedited review of banned pesticides</header> 
<paragraph id="H5D04D0C63CF74699A0E8A3BF20DD9A2C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Suspension of banned pesticides</header><text>The Administrator shall immediately suspend the registration of any active ingredient or pesticide product that is—</text> <subparagraph id="H59B2C3FB41C54FBAA84C3249AAD708CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>banned or otherwise prohibited from entering the market by the European Union, 1 or more countries in the European Union, or Canada; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H691DCDE2DE754DD29F9686BC3B7FC9EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>registered for use within the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D4E01523519440687FA0750F3C59602"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expedited review</header><text>The Administrator shall complete an expedited review of the justification and rationale for the ban of a pesticide by the European Union or a country described in paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC282C0D7195C48B88BF9309406443E34"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cancellation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9D6AF5296D77463EA865F87165553CCE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), unless the Administrator determines after a review under paragraph (2) that the decision to ban a pesticide by the European Union or a country described in paragraph (1)(A) was clearly erroneous, the registration that is suspended shall be canceled not later than 2 years after the date of completion of the review.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1B464B1DAA8641A3BE6552F44955D5F8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Full consideration of all science</header> <clause id="H43A9BF99B0134855847B390CAE194343"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In determining whether the ban of a pesticide by the European Union or a country described in paragraph (1)(A) was clearly erroneous under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall fully consider all relevant evidence, including—</text> 
<subclause id="H0A7006B38FFB4F6AA26AE49AE0C13D5F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>epidemiological studies or data;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HCA204766B28A4F9CB2022FE111993929"><enum>(II)</enum><text>peer-reviewed literature; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE1B1CA1D1EED44C094903D3E072A562E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>data generated by—</text> <item id="H534E6BE365E142D5B8AD053C464AA5E4"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a State or Federal agency; or </text></item> 
<item id="HF358FF7D61404ED08242788A51FB201F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an agency of a foreign government.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC588FBF0474846AB8FBFD9A3501B5A91"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Treatment of information</header><text>Notwithstanding any requirements or criteria under parts 152 and 160 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), the Administrator shall not discount, otherwise ignore, or give disproportionately more or less weight to evidence described in clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6E1233F3BBCE4E1DB6C63684B9A2566F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consideration of economic cost prohibited</header><text>In determining whether the ban of a pesticide by the European Union or a country described in paragraph (1)(A) was clearly erroneous under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall not consider any economic analysis of the benefits or costs of continuing to register the pesticide.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB502300FF316470E9962449C36AF9F38"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>Prior to making a final determination under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall provide a draft determination for not less than 90 days of public comment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HD3EAFC9DD724457097D42A3548ACA4AC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Ensuring accountability in conditional registrations</header> 
<subsection id="HE710C85683E14E078596F8A254CBE385"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 3(c)(7) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a">7 U.S.C. 136a(c)(7)</external-xref>) is amended by striking subparagraph (C) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H27E6965B33154AF78F8C8E4C0837095F"> <subparagraph id="H95B36CC79D514866B9ADA58993B2DD07"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Time limits on conditional registrations</header> <clause id="H75BE1DE53E78445BB8FD1B7B44776906"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this subsection or section 6(e), the Administrator shall provide not longer than 2 years for the terms and requirements of any conditional registration under this paragraph to be met by the registrant.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H37208BA75BB04852A021226100520FE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Cancellation</header><text>The Administrator shall cancel a conditional registration under this paragraph unless the registrant fully complies with all conditions by the earlier of—</text> <subclause id="HB211B54F04C34E53AFB00E9071F0E1E6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>all deadlines established by the Administrator; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3E32BD08BC5F4032889A5E646396265C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>2 years after the effective date of the conditional registration.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA6971B9B9910443EB887BC7497A04AA8"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Existing conditional registrations</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, as of the date of enactment of this clause, each outstanding conditional registration under this paragraph for which the registrant has not fulfilled all conditions of the conditional registration shall be canceled.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB588C5D0BEF44908B200F3A3FB346331"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<subclause id="H50A1BFF91ED947129B11FA36381D0E76"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than December 31 of each calendar year, the Administrator shall submit to Congress an annual report describing the total number of conditional registrations under this paragraph that were registered during the immediately preceding fiscal year.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDCB4AE2210DE481CAF600243938BBE65"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>A report under subclause (I) shall include a description of—</text> 
<item id="HCC95FDADFDDD4C839C99F19562E21610"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>each conditionally registered pesticide and the conditions imposed, including any modification of those conditions; and </text></item> <item id="H18B520DB61404F84BF75B89D7B81F354"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the quantity produced of each pesticide described in item (aa).</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H48AB2899DA504981BDE6495E00209CD7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 6(e) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d(e)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H87A62DDC46A14856B183BC3A8BAE83D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking the last sentence and inserting <quote>The Administrator shall not permit the continued sale and use of existing stocks of a pesticide the conditional registration of which has been canceled.</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD5E6AD03F05947538F37877ECB42F49B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), in the third sentence, by striking <quote>, and whether the Administrator's determination with respect to the disposition of existing stocks is consistent with this Act</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H6743F879C727499289E93C7F95730443"><enum>6.</enum><header>Prohibition on the sale or use of existing stocks of suspended or canceled pesticides</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(a) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through the period at the end of paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35547A9B450F44C4856B225EB18115B3"> 
<subsection id="HAD4C55B653B34837807CBCE3FEC79B2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on the sale or use of existing stocks; information</header> 
<paragraph id="HB6D106B67E6B4397A3659A4109055419"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Existing stocks</header><text>The Administrator shall not permit the continued sale or use of existing stocks of a pesticide the registration of which is—</text> <subparagraph id="H9B671ED692854481BCBE445D48519C63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suspended or canceled under this section or section 3 or 4; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68FA27DB7D624865A486856626219083"><enum>(B)</enum><text>vacated or set aside by judicial decree.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HF1D40372517D4A9DAB35E49A4FA2722E"><enum>7.</enum><header>Ending abuse of emergency exemptions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 18 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136p">7 U.S.C. 136p</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2F9104AEE5234A61ACC880D0396919FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the first sentence, by striking <quote>The Administrator</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF472D75A5199495692F79E772A35DB61"> <subsection id="H2FADE92F6D534FDD89D1DB05AB486254"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFBB252538B4546C2BB01C3FBC408C47C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a) (as so designated), in the second sentence, by striking <quote>The Administrator</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H61A80AE63A88475B9BB6152B7A3E3CD6"> <subsection id="HDF8B7BB2ED174EF58C9E8F82AE8B33DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Administrator</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFBD07FC4B8414917ACDF5C73B397CE54"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H90C50A394FC340488F9F22AA7253613E"> <subsection id="H22439B8F37FD486094470054B50ADC00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitations on emergency exemptions</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Administrator shall not grant an emergency exemption under subsection (a) for the same active ingredient or pesticide product in the same location for more than 2 years in any 10-year period.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD9586636543B4F6D945B1F01A01C2342"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Restrictions on unregistered pesticides</header><text>The Administrator shall not grant an emergency exemption under subsection (a) to use an active ingredient or pesticide product that is not registered under section 3 for any use.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBD493455C8E24352AFB7FA565F9F0335"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Restrictions on conditional pesticides</header><text>The Administrator shall not grant an emergency exemption under subsection (a) for any active ingredient or pesticide product that is registered conditionally under section 3(c)(7)(A).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H64F264382F8543C78C875B29CF1284C7"><enum>8.</enum><header>Adding transparency for inert ingredients</header> 
<subsection id="HD1ED6FB705984047B5B2E237F2586541"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of ingredient statement</header><text>Section 2(n) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136(n)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HD43891043CE24494BE5F1BE19734D3CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (4); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC68169C37E9E4516957E11C58A85B379"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC9E0DEBA17DF4D39B644B77ECC0404E6"> <paragraph id="H1F5B6B800A6444308179B58776069F39"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name and percentage of each active ingredient in the pesticide product;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2007CEEAE8F4CFEA2D513B91CCF3A58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the name and percentage of each inert ingredient in the pesticide product;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95235C0C808F40439F4BE4B540BCB34F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>if applicable, a statement that the pesticide product contains an inert ingredient determined by a State or Federal agency, or the Administrator based on epidemiological data or peer-reviewed literature, to be likely—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H490F9AD3FF564D05AD2E1E051FD037FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be carcinogenic;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE8591D7B0AF84272B8770061FD5206D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to be an endocrine disruptor;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5019663D965C467ABCA157E6CBC08316"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to be acutely toxic;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDCDD2724F00D4ACFA54C0345A75FD125"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to cause harm to pregnant women or fetuses; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H88C16605AEAD429EA0A1685417A1CE9F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to cause neurological or developmental harm; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAEB8810113B341F98C81F037C4766289"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Complete list of inert ingredients</header><text>Section 3(c)(9) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a">7 U.S.C. 136a(c)(9)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H025BE71217A34246B73534CD5A31AA03"> 
<subparagraph id="H3866C95861584B93A85142D70AC087C1"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Complete list of inert ingredients</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the label or labeling required under this Act shall provide a complete list of inert ingredients.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H2CEF8DF52B2C45B38497273BCD65B0A1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 10(d) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136h">7 U.S.C. 136h(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC4E5990E37DD4943B0FC44221648461E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H2DEF3AD5DAC4498B9BBF72DCF81B4BBB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H309678B6546F45A0B9D4B22FC8EFD7FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F7D4EBF5BFD48D1A5CAEC475123B067"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (C); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9F604972F904546ACF025E6593B3D61"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>clause (A), (B), or (C)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subparagraph (A) or (B)</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H81F656FE916A42F6A3B766F6256B20A3"><enum>9.</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of organophosphates</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d</external-xref>) (as amended by section 4) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9363C63890044B248BA3592AA31DC163"> 
<subsection id="H75789D82964B4D1DBDCE77854873AA9F"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of organophosphate pesticides</header> 
<paragraph id="H1FA047ACEEF540209C1BE1CC4D08DA76"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<subparagraph id="HEC0D9B545F654D7D9E36B977E3DF6561"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cancellation</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection—</text> <clause id="HA7575E293BAF4EFE92E7D8AA6A0EE735"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all pesticides of the class organophosphate shall be deemed to generally cause unreasonable adverse effects to humans; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H86477150666142CB81436BD02C4A6325"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), the registration of all uses of pesticides of the class organophosphate shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without further proceedings.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF9C1E8418F64C9F83EDECFD91CD76F2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revocation of tolerances and exemptions</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall, in accordance with section 408(b)(1)(B) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/346a">21 U.S.C. 346a(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>), revoke any tolerance or exemption that allows the presence of an organophosphate, or any pesticide chemical residue that results from organophosphate use, in or on food.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7CC137B19BE54B4AA1A1346BD737EA84"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sale of existing stocks prohibited</header><text>In accordance with subsection (a)(1), effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the continued sale or use of existing stocks of pesticides of the class organophosphate shall be prohibited.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDDEAAB86FAC74B8FBFC13BC832F64137"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No future organophosphate registrations</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator may not register any pesticide of the class organophosphate under section 4.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71A3AB9EE09B4DA391971377578337FE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ineligibility for emergency use</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a pesticide canceled under this subsection shall not be eligible for use under section 18.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H7A50B2D8FA9E4922BEA47E3C16E7AB3C"><enum>10.</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of neonicotinoids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d</external-xref>) (as amended by section 9) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2426E32A1C76418D8D71D24DFEF03113"> 
<subsection id="HFAED9862A2B84A7694FC77846219ECAB"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of neonicotinoid pesticides</header> 
<paragraph id="H1628BBA2B9424965BF7C453547702531"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB6C37366577E4DAC820BDC9DEE334545"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cancellation</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection—</text> <clause id="H2ACF1DB31D9C45109A8F8CA565C8417C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all active ingredients and pesticide products containing 1 or more of the active ingredients imidacloprid, clothianidin, thiamethoxam, dinotefuran, acetamiprid, sulfoxaflor, and flupyradifurone (referred to in this subsection as <term>neonicotinoid pesticides</term>) shall be deemed to generally cause unreasonable adverse effects to the environment; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFE5B3C3A8B4F4F75B5BCAE54EDA6E678"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), the registration of all uses of neonicotinoid pesticides shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without further proceedings. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB74E59BBF4D4D71A3B75F26C04D7E7B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revocation of tolerances and exemptions</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall, in accordance with section 408(b)(1)(B) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/346a">21 U.S.C. 346a(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>), revoke any tolerance or exemption that allows the presence of a neonicotinoid pesticide, or any pesticide chemical residue that results from neonicotinoid pesticide use, in or on food.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F9EF0C5E3344CF6923ED34DE123F66D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sale of existing stocks prohibited</header><text>In accordance with subsection (a)(1), effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the continued sale or use of existing stocks of neonicotinoid pesticides shall be prohibited.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H19F64A69219E4054BF0E17862B954D0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No future neonicotinoid registrations</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator may not register any neonicotinoid pesticide under section 4.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8A4C54E730E4397B8075CF04D564DF1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ineligibility for emergency use</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a pesticide canceled under this section shall not be eligible for use under section 18.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H073B0581A3C54396B1310EE3EA8842BD"><enum>11.</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of paraquat</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136d">7 U.S.C. 136d</external-xref>) (as amended by section 10) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H91D531AC5CB54209849A1BC3601A85D1"> 
<subsection id="H72B2F54DF66645CF8C64D7F17F1B335C"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Cancellation of registration of paraquat</header> 
<paragraph id="H300124681D9240E6A2FBB6BDB43BC091"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<subparagraph id="H81F6194201BA45A882B371942BF58A43"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cancellation</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection—</text> <clause id="H787CBBE60DB649428458A84BA2D2E0D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>paraquat shall be deemed to generally cause unreasonable adverse effects to humans; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4187F285BE954310B7BDD439EC0E321A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), the registration of all uses of paraquat shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without further proceedings. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF63A127E79EE4CBBBD37F2E09E714259"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revocation of tolerances and exemptions</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall, in accordance with section 408(b)(1)(B) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/346a">21 U.S.C. 346a(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>), revoke any tolerance or exemption that allows the presence of paraquat, or any pesticide chemical residue that results from paraquat use, in or on food.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18254BC8D2F94810A42D90B2A16A66DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sale of existing stocks prohibited</header><text>In accordance with subsection (a)(1), effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the continued sale or use of existing stocks of paraquat shall be prohibited.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8E94B58FD87468F96406924AC304BBA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No future paraquat registrations</header><text>Effective on the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator may not register any paraquat pesticide under section 4.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA86E148F0C84265BFAA0CC6B1A5559F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ineligibility for emergency use</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a pesticide canceled under this section shall not be eligible for use under section 18.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H85B9FC3385ED4AA798BBFFCBF9D23D55"><enum>12.</enum><header>Empowering communities to protect themselves from pesticides</header> <subsection id="H503367748B6943F7B483D70EF17B9530"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 24 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136v">7 U.S.C. 136v</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H84BC3A968BC0467B8929FC89CD2F31DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H84B9B0DCEBFE4894B0D9033E15634232"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or any political subdivision of a State,</quote> after <quote>A State</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3386765F82B743A0A4051043D149119C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or political subdivision</quote> after <quote>the State</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6551B4C881EF48DC91EEE747BF3B7BF1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D154DD46B9F4F358DB1D406702DCC05"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9D8FEFDF97B946FD87C6FF4774329566"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 3(c)(5) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a">7 U.S.C. 136a(c)(5)</external-xref>) is amended, in the fourth sentence of the undesignated matter following subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>24(c) of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>24(b)</quote>.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8CE469013574488EB2B346644EF2A442"><enum>13.</enum><header>Protecting farmworkers from dangerous pesticides</header> 
<subsection id="H411B8DA938A64237957CCB599E2E07C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Language requirements for pesticide products</header><text>Section 3(c)(9) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136a">7 U.S.C. 136a(c)(9)</external-xref>) (as amended by section 8(b)) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H028A2EF3F5364B419CFC4C1F863F734C"> <subparagraph id="H715ECC0561054FC0B2106D751D8A94DD"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Language requirements for pesticide products</header> <clause id="HE28BE07049404746AA305A77EC00D483"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The label for any pesticide product shall be printed in both English and Spanish.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2F3DBDEB26FB42DFBFB4DA6B913A4BAA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other languages</header><text>In a case in which information exists that a pesticide product is used in agriculture by more than 500 individual persons or applicators who speak the same language other than English or Spanish, the Administrator shall provide a translation of that label in the language used by those individuals on the website of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></clause> <clause id="H4B36ED88FE534F22A7DC1AA298204073"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Educational information</header><text>The Administrator shall provide educational information to ensure that all users of a pesticide product are aware that information is available in alternate languages.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1CE52D8127F0427BAB0D0ECF52DDA744"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Farmworker safety</header><text>The Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4570E5A67B954C4F8E4F2235D89EC050"> <section id="H4D7368D25AD241B4A822DEC4708D8A07"><enum>36.</enum><header>Farmworker safety</header> <subsection id="H9A89ACC1C3B84629A75E1F4B3FDC1A38"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD0D0F7983F404C52B2DAA30FDBB063EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Farmworker</header><text>The term <term>farmworker</term> means an individual of any age that is employed in agriculture, including as a pesticide user or applicator, for any length of time, including migrant and seasonal employees, regardless of classification as a full-time, part-time, or contract employee.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H007BD05CF98D4DE49DDC65405CDB40F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Farmworker incident</header><text>The term <term>farmworker incident</term> means exposure of a farmworker to an active ingredient, a pesticide product, a tank mixture of multiple pesticides, a metabolite, or a degradate that results in—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H83A9C52B27D345B3A2DAE8658781EC2D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an illness or injury—</text> <clause id="H897D2C70A1A64E7DBDF06636DADCF6C4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>requiring medical attention or hospitalization of the farmworker; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H73484CC1E6F441BDAD9CEB542F702BFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that requires the farmworker to stop working temporarily or permanently;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H02766E28709E4F0F95347CE2FF9EAC6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a permanent disability or loss in function of the farmworker; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H76C72282A17245B68DF3B03B73850655"><enum>(C)</enum><text>death of the farmworker.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF614E7AE57164B68BBE92EC95F343CE9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mandatory duty To report</header> <paragraph id="H77DC34ABEF1F4A03A3C04F6861342FB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whenever a farmworker incident occurs, the employer of each affected farmworker shall report the incident to the Administrator.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H81964308056C489EB95E0CE3807933C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Online system</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD5B2189A57834A5F8F8DCDD3778FBA4D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall implement and deploy an online system to facilitate the reporting of farmworker incidents.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52D985330EB743CB9A40DDDDF4755F68"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The online system under subparagraph (A) shall include, at a minimum, a description of, with respect to each farmworker incident—</text> 
<clause id="HCE775AF03D1B491BAC808DD78E7ED1A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the time and location; </text></clause> <clause id="H7185A4F3C21D4463A4370ABA574920DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the name of each active ingredient and pesticide product involved;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4DC0D937B8D5482A951E193DE21CE450"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether such a pesticide was applied in accordance with the label instructions;</text></clause> <clause id="H062868C5975842AC83650EB62A126A5F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the harm that resulted to any affected farmworker; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HF39E607F4EC741CBAEF5EE32E69FBF63"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the nature of any medical care that was sought by any affected farmworker; and </text></clause> <clause id="HC51638363A46401FACB691872F65E831"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any other pertinent information.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0FAC89C59E614DF284892F2D2C7990CA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Anonymous reporting</header><text>The Administrator shall ensure that the online system under subparagraph (A) allows for anonymous reporting to protect farmworkers from retaliation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC45E3953D59F44478E692352106B211C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties for failure To report</header> <paragraph id="HBA845FD16EF54AB0B9A40C3B788B3596"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil penalties</header><text>An employer described in subsection (b)(1) that fails to report a farmworker incident shall be fined $1,000 per day beginning on the 8th day after the farmworker incident occurs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H25F0E30DFADE49D69D617EBC8DA91FBD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criminal penalties</header><text>An employer described in subsection (b)(1) that knowingly fails to report a farmworker incident, or that otherwise pressures or coerces a farmworker to not report a farmworker incident, shall be liable for a criminal penalty of up to $100,000, 6 months in prison, or both.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D0B22919F1C449D9C21EC5CE2D975BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rewards</header><text>The Administrator shall implement a reward system that a provides monetary award of not less than $25,000 per person per farmworker incident that leads to the identification of 1 or more employers that have failed to report a farmworker incident.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H974FB32F2FDC4980991AC7206F5735DA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Retaliation</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF6431B0D00564667A4EEEB830270CC7D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person that takes punitive action against a farmworker or a person that reports a farmworker incident shall be liable for a criminal penalty of not more than $100,000, 6 months in prison, or both.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H02892569362548D9B4D9E95DED516E5B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Immigration status</header><text>No Federal agency shall take any action regarding the immigration legal status within the United States of a farmworker, including initiating removal proceedings or any other prosecution of the farmworker, based solely on any information derived from the reporting or investigation of a farmworker incident.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HECFD03C29BAD442DA6DDC7DA45F8B624"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Preventing future harm to farmworkers</header> 
<paragraph id="H059F7BDB614446B8AE28E743DCE00D53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 15 days after the receipt of a report of a farmworker incident, the Administrator shall transmit a report prepared by the Administrator of the farmworker incident to—</text> <subparagraph id="HF56DA65AE520482ABB0267A19AD6D145"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the manufacturer of each involved pesticide product; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDA46CD2892314888BFCE967A6E6466AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the manufacturer of each involved active ingredient or ingredients.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC713822939D48E48827FBE452F09AD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Suspension</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if a farmworker incident results in the death of a farmworker, the pesticide product or active ingredient that caused the death shall be immediately suspended, pending the review required by this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4C83BA71F8AC42398CDEF0256B1F9896"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assessments</header> 
<subparagraph id="H00AEB21474BD46DE9198250FA1073042"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Pesticide product manufacturer</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the receipt of a report of a farmworker incident, the manufacturer of the pesticide product shall provide to the Administrator an assessment of the farmworker incident, including whether any changes to the label of the pesticide product or active ingredient are warranted at the time of the assessment to avoid future farmworker incidents.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20E9DE47BE0444B9BE628127D36D9D50"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Assessment by active ingredient manufacturer</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the receipt of a report of a farmworker incident, the manufacturer of each involved pesticide active ingredient shall provide to the Administrator an assessment of the farmworker incident, including whether any changes to the pesticide product or active ingredient are warranted at the time of the assessment to avoid future farmworker incidents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD518134866C045EEA4426B14232667B6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determinations by Administrator</header> 
<subparagraph id="H821B7C6AA7264C71AFC6E806DE9B4413"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Draft determination</header> 
<clause id="H301B8ED1EE9345C884A89019AD160769"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the earlier of 90 days after the receipt of an assessment required by paragraph (3) and 180 days after the occurrence of the farmworker incident, the Administrator shall make a draft determination as to whether a change in the label of an involved pesticide product or active ingredient is warranted. </text></clause> <clause id="HE7AB70F16C83430C9B7F18412DD483EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Administrator shall publish a determination under clause (i) in the Federal Register for a period of 30 days for public notice and comment.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBAB5DE6CC7384F7EAECF3AF198027B87"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final determination</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the close of the public comment described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the Administrator shall—</text> <clause id="HCEAC339031D94DA0AA00E17BAF2755F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>make a final determination as to whether the label of the pesticide product should be changed; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H251D0DC6C6644198ACE832D5E941ED3C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publish that final determination in the Federal Register.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA29FC44D6293484FB9D7D8B33109AC0A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Cancellations</header> <subparagraph id="H4A5D34A377674AEE98F7D5B6248EB65E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>failure to change label</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), if the manufacturer of a pesticide product or active ingredient does not change the label of the applicable product in accordance with a final determination of the Administrator under paragraph (4)(B), the pesticide product or active ingredient shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without further proceedings.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF3A75D95526E4DDFAA0B00AD1C5E439D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Cancellation for failure to comply</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 6(b), if the manufacturer of the pesticide product or active ingredient fails to comply with any applicable provision of this section, the active ingredient and all pesticide products containing the active ingredient shall be immediately and permanently canceled by operation of law and without further proceedings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF9099D5B91A6415BAF0D06A0BB17986B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Accounting for farmworker incidents during registration review</header> <paragraph id="H10B40409D06043968BA015775A47B73B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if a pesticide product or active ingredient is responsible for not fewer than 10 farmworker incidents of any type, or not fewer than 3 farmworker incidents resulting in death, and the pesticide product or active ingredient has not received a final determination regarding a registration review during the preceding 15-year period, the Administrator shall immediately suspend the pesticide product or active ingredient until a final determination is made regarding the registration review of the pesticide.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05B09321F5084062B7FCC93D0A82D1DB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Administrator shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H9A11579AB8004D8FBDA81A30D3635B2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include in a final determination regarding the registration review of a pesticide the registration of which is suspended under paragraph (1) a full and complete report describing each farmworker incident that has occurred during the period covered by the report; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE9E9DE1628241DE84B875A967E35E60"><enum>(B)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4AD390528A164A06B8B38FB6D9163AEE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require label changes to prevent farmworker incidents from occurring in the future; or</text></clause> <clause id="H437DB6C6104D44F288118684FE81E90A" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>explain why no label changes under clause (i) are warranted.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2901B5411539441BBF01130B27B3E84C"><enum>14.</enum><header>Authority To bring civil action</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 16 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136n">7 U.S.C. 136n</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDF0B0928EEC44919AAF5872C02AC2F4"> <subsection id="HB07C116EA6464838B65D16596D5C1AC8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authority To bring civil action</header> <paragraph id="H2E681314245A4B0AB1BD953CC2B3A572"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person may bring a civil action against the Administrator where there is an alleged failure of the Administrator to comply with any provision of this Act. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HACE5F3175BBB40A5ABAAA32BC3AC434B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The district courts of the United States shall have exclusive jurisdiction over a civil action brought pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HB96D8D120620400695D553B83AA56ED8"><enum>15.</enum><header>Employee protection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>) (as amended by section 13(b)) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2FC21FB66FB4113B95DBB94886D2192"> 
<section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H643FED15F5A94BD3B202FDC76FF5B1B7"><enum>37.</enum><header>Employee protection</header> 
<subsection id="H87E8C296A0424E12BE26FB1CC7AA53DA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>No employer may discharge any employee or otherwise discriminate against any employee with respect to the employee’s compensation, terms, conditions, or privileges of employment because the employee (or any person acting pursuant to a request of the employee)—</text> <paragraph id="H2C1E3C4CE0564176934C28FEC1601C3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has commenced, has caused to be commenced, or is about to commence or cause to be commenced a proceeding under this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA094AAC4DF9944A4BF8BE1DB10890B40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has testified or is about to testify in any proceeding described in paragraph (1); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H354CB3FB0D7446ADBE849E5EDAA6E41E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>has assisted or participated or is about to assist or participate in any manner in—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H285A90065BC149FFBE265CC6C31FC2D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any proceeding described in paragraph (1); or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA2E968FA57554CC5B11CE98D8D757995"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other action to carry out the purposes of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC80A608034CA40209582E09AF5099472"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Remedy</header> 
<paragraph id="H8A7A7EAC5C13437C92285F735863FE21"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Filing of complaint</header><text>Any employee who believes that the employee has been discharged or otherwise discriminated against by any person in violation of subsection (a) may, not later than 30 days after the date on which the alleged violation occurs, file (or have any person file on behalf of the employee) a complaint with the Secretary of Labor (referred to in this section as the <term>Secretary</term>) alleging that discharge or discrimination. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA62FCF74A0044BB4A80F8FF6C7A42D51"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>On receipt of a complaint filed under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall notify the person named in the complaint of the filing of the complaint.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4C3F49AB73594955A84C8EC76C806CAA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Investigations</header> 
<subparagraph id="H167D803A86C4403AA8C1418531605789"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receipt of a complaint filed under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall conduct an investigation of the violation alleged in the complaint. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF31811A016B4B6D925A1B0DDBB59DCF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Results</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Secretary receives a complaint filed under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<clause id="HC0D9899AF0284FB6B512E28F4B3E07A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>complete the investigation under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> <clause id="HB9FA0534B6774B80A19E1C61B59227E6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notify in writing the complainant (and any person acting on behalf of the complainant) and the person alleged to have committed the applicable violation of the results of that investigation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC26FC571280411997E4AA971E922270"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Orders</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3241D944F9F44A6086E211AA1465148A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the Secretary receives a complaint filed under paragraph (1), unless the proceeding on the complaint is terminated by the Secretary on the basis of a settlement entered into by the Secretary and the person alleged to have committed the applicable violation, the Secretary shall issue an order—</text> <clause id="HB42B723DFD0D4D89B02DDFB98BED198F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing the relief described in paragraph (5); or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H67668CB671D14C79A04466618D55FB41"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>denying the complaint. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H812FD95852034B3EA04CA9988E0AF850"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity for hearing</header><text>An order of the Secretary under subparagraph (A) shall be made on the record after notice and opportunity for agency hearing. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H40DF0E122A004BB2B277DAC2E792F503"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Settlements</header><text>The Secretary may not enter into a settlement terminating a proceeding on a complaint filed under paragraph (1) without the participation and consent of the complainant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF36FB6247BC2470E98B2329FD7434EC7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Relief</header><text>If, in response to a complaint filed under paragraph (1), the Secretary determines that a violation of subsection (a) has occurred, the Secretary shall issue an order—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4CD09DCC132A441D93EAF517CF418787"><enum>(A)</enum><text>requiring the person who committed the violation—</text> <clause id="HF6E35385938747D0AD5DF71F861AB4ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to take affirmative action to abate the violation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB529B09AA5E845A7B29DEE9EFF0FEAD4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the complainant was discharged by the person committing the violation, to reinstate the complainant to the complainant’s former position, with the compensation (including back pay), terms, conditions, and privileges of the complainant’s employment; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6C6A71AE8C4D449FA472B0094E3F3D7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assessing against the person who committed the violation—</text> 
<clause id="H771B6495B99344F0AD0012065EB4FCD6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>compensatory damages; </text></clause> <clause id="HF70E537A2EFB4B6FA15AFA67C5887D53"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if appropriate, exemplary damages; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF4C6AF18546C4923BFB6D861536435F5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at the request of the complainant, a sum equal to the aggregate amount of all costs and expenses (including attorney’s fees) reasonably incurred, as determined by the Secretary, by the complainant for, or in connection with, the bringing of the complaint.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8697826757B54BB7A296584C5712B770"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial review</header> <paragraph id="H129D3A4E72CF450EA02EEC7C1DA0642A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any employee or employer adversely affected or aggrieved by an order issued under subsection (b) may obtain review of the order in the court of appeals of the United States for the judicial circuit in which the violation with respect to which the order is issued allegedly occurred. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9BD82B68FB2D4F95B99AD2A9C58264FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Petition</header><text>A petition for review under paragraph (1) shall be filed not later than 60 days after the date on which the applicable order is issued under subsection (b). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A76D6BFEC334289A16A1064A706D911"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text>Judicial review under paragraph (1) shall be in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/7">chapter 7</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5FA330F9470F4547BE6F5F735A59CC17"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exclusive review</header><text>An order of the Secretary with respect to which judicial review may be or may have been obtained under paragraph (1) shall not be subject to judicial review in—</text> <subparagraph id="H87E62A739DC140E78A02401BE8B03B05"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a criminal proceeding; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H87541EA77B6E451F8A6955106B89D185"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a civil proceeding under any other provision of law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC44ECCE2F83E43C4A5924F9372E3F634"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <paragraph id="H83991E30CFD14B518A8178E5BAAD6113"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a person fails to comply with an order issued under subsection (b), the Secretary shall bring a civil action in the district court of the United States for the judicial district in which the violation is determined to occur to enforce that order. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7132818065A24C72841A81F7F86F351B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>In a civil action brought under paragraph (1), a district court of the United States shall have jurisdiction to grant all appropriate relief, including injunctive relief, compensatory damages, and exemplary damages.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H77D4FCB5739F496BBE4F75860E7E6131"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to any employee who, acting without direction from the employee’s employer (or any agent of the employer), deliberately causes a violation of any requirement of this Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

