<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC5DBB66ED3A54CF9BDB67921EE0547E3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4584 IH: National Wildland Fire Risk Reduction Program Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4584</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230712">July 12, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To improve the Federal effort to reduce wildland fire risks, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HEE039D269C574B0BBBE1A2757F3E0854" style="OLC">
<section id="HF27FC204C65B4002BBC53C607D5D33B1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Wildland Fire Risk Reduction Program Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H066DEBAC36C44E068B9E85D6ABD5EC31"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President shall establish a National Wildland Fire Risk Reduction Program with the purpose of achieving major measurable reductions in the losses of life and property from wildland fires through a coordinated Federal effort to—</text>
<paragraph id="HD493619B1FAB419A9323E8B3AD04DA1A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve the assessment of fire environments and the understanding and prediction of wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H7A35528AE0CA4027BEA582B60AFAE2AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at the wildland-urban interface;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H21722520D5864C6CAB5AF494A6AAF4CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on communities, buildings and other infrastructure;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H483D736C39344FF3B5A220BA25850A11"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on ecosystem services; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0450008CB6FD4F45B8478598644C2C01"><enum>(D)</enum><text>social and economic impacts;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8004ABED6F341D29DC9038C75D87E98"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and encourage the adoption of science-based and cost-effective measures to enhance resilience to wildland fires and prevent and mitigate negative impacts of wildland fires and associated smoke; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6C3F0C41DC934069A0446C5DFFF95A94"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improve the understanding and mitigation of the impacts of climate change and variability on wildland fire risk, frequency, and severity, and to inform paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HBE4A2A3B20324DB1B76A339373944A08"><enum>3.</enum><header>Program activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Program shall consist of the activities described under section 7, which shall be designed—</text>
<paragraph id="HC82EE0D846F5477F89265CD3B3D78264"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support research and development, including interdisciplinary research, related to fire environments, wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts, in furtherance of a coordinated interagency effort to address wildland fire risk reduction;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4F2F23D0CC224FE8A45460FD51BF4CB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to support data management and stewardship, the development and coordination of data systems and computational tools, and the creation of a centralized, integrated data collaboration environment for Program agency data, to accelerate the understanding of fire environments, wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts, and the benefits of wildland fire risk mitigation measures;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7722616636A34630807F89D9F99A6570"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to support the development of tools and technologies, including decision support tools and risk and hazard maps, to improve understanding, monitoring, prediction, and mitigation of wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12172882077740188707938A804A3D44"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to support education and training to expand the number of students and researchers in areas of study and research related to wildland fires;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC3495A8DA41D44899368ADF1C57B9071"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to accelerate the translation of research related to wildland fires and associated smoke into operations to reduce risk to communities, buildings, other infrastructure, and ecosystem services;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H231EFCA189D0428B92B4BBEF550AD08B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to conduct communication and outreach regarding wildland fire science and wildland fire risk mitigation, to communities, energy utilities and operators of other critical infrastructure, and other relevant stakeholders;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC1CB0FC670FE4D85AF94C926249B9D60"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to support research and development projects funded under joint solicitations or through memoranda of understanding between no fewer than two agencies participating in the Program; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1EF94BBE39A54D10B9CA9CBABBC55F2F"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to disseminate, to the extent practicable, scientific data and related products and services in formats meeting shared standards to enhance the interoperability, usability, and accessibility of Program Agency data, including data as part of paragraph (2) in order to better meet the needs of Program agencies, other Federal agencies, and relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H83AE5F10DB994D65AC64C70A2E71F1EF"><enum>4.</enum><header>Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildland Fire Risk Reduction</header>
<subsection id="HE573DB210F294884A7A1BDB14D2743BC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall establish an Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildland Fire Risk Reduction (in this Act referred to as <quote>the Committee</quote>), to be co-chaired by the Director and the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8F07E40C69B74200983645B281DF4C41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>In addition to the co-chairs, the Committee shall be composed of—</text>
<paragraph id="HEFF777E6A0BA49869AD9FEA5A94D2522"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Director of the National Science Foundation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H652BE2468D254B26823951D63C0B4B66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCD6DA1FF08754A578CE254F04D81E00B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE68A499052A34DBA833EA9C98C041FE4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the United States Fire Administrator;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDFF0651F5ED1404D86C3DF28E32F0D70"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Chief of the Forest Service;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EC6A35D48FC4A99930CAB21DB8977CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF421363159984E6689E29778D01E9009"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H686515EC8F8E49DDB2FE6B1F8341FFC0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA574F30B67904EF9A9A11B3EDF40404A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H747BF363828B4D18BB3AE9E3BA5AF615"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Management and Budget;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC93C6F0FE62D44048283CE182EEDB737"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0A6700EAA84F4C8FBC438916ED8798F7"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of United States Geological Survey;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8768831BA66B4E808B22504963EF1704"><enum>(13)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF30364A768FF44A487CF87E53499C71A"><enum>(14)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB29BBCA410E947E1B85A10AE90A15D6C"><enum>(15)</enum><text>the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA37E87554CFD42A2945F28EA29E75CF4"><enum>(16)</enum><text>the head of any other Federal agency that the Director considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H62E1FB6E648D44738226A992B428CE8E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Committee shall meet not less than twice a year for the first two years and then not less than once a year at the call of the Director.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCCBBE7062B9C48AD99CF4D412030EFFF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>General purpose and duties</header><text>The Committee shall oversee the planning, management, and coordination of the Program, and solicit stakeholder input on Program goals.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7A532917E4CA4385BEE643CFF758DDF9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall develop and submit to Congress, not later than 1 year after enactment, and update every 4 years thereafter, a Strategic Plan for the Program that includes—</text> <paragraph id="H9974B0FE87B546768EB0D8D6AA09BC2D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prioritized goals for the Program, consistent with the purposes of the Program as described in section 2;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF8232641141B42D7B1187615874664E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>short-term, mid-term, and long-term research and development objectives to achieve those goals;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H175284EB1E1240BD83CF00A56B46D83E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the role of each Program agency in achieving the prioritized goals;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H88A00B2FCC8743B2B273B9297DE303F8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the Committee will foster collaboration between and among the Program agencies and other Federal agencies to help meet the goals of the Program;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2BECEDF256744AA4A611A446E4C0BD8E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the methods by which progress toward the goals will be assessed;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H339884DA3D69412098D0862DBDBC2A9F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an explanation of how the Program will foster the translation of research into measurable reductions in the losses of life, property, and ecosystem services from wildland fires, including recommended outcomes and metrics for each program goal and how operational Program agencies will transition demonstrated technologies and research findings into decision support tools and operations;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA04E33ED68BA49E29CEE2FB0E156044A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the research infrastructure, including databases and computational tools, needed to accomplish the research and development objectives outlined in paragraph (2), a description of how research infrastructure in existence at the time of the development of the plan will be used to meet the objectives, an explanation of how new research infrastructure will be developed to meet the objectives, and a description of how the program will implement the integrated data collaboration environment per section 3(2);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7B0E805E76A24403BC266F4D0D18403B"><enum>(8) </enum><text>a description of how Program agencies will collaborate with stakeholders and take into account stakeholder needs and recommendations in developing research and development objectives;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DC85C87A44A4FFC948CF310E24513B1"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations on the most effective means to integrate the research results into wildland fire preparedness and response actions across Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial levels; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A133D09B1B842E6AF716BF92996E0FE"><enum>(10)</enum><text>guidance on how the Committee’s recommendations are best used in climate adaptation planning for Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial entities; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA58311202DA248988CB6068B951FB8B7"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nationally recognized, consensus-based definition of wildland-urban interface and other key terms and definitions relating to wildland fire, developed in consideration of the meaning given such term in section 4(11) of the Federal Fire Prevention and Control Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2203">15 U.S.C. 2203(11)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE8A3A3C9EB13485CAB2DD7980DC4AB52"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of opportunities to support new areas of research and development and new types of collaborations that seek to optimize building and landscape design across multiple resilience goals, including resilience to wildland fires and other natural hazards, energy efficiency, and environmental sustainability.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H858C090E2E0A465FB055A735C40A3DC4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination with other Federal efforts</header><text>The Director shall ensure that the activities of the Program are coordinated with other relevant Federal initiatives as appropriate.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H737090A8D29241BAA8821954E918DF54"><enum>(g)</enum><header>National Academies Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall assess the need for a study, or a series of studies, to be conducted by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, and how such a study, or series of studies, could help identify research areas for further study and inform research objectives, including further research into the interactions between climate change and wildland fires. The Committee shall brief the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate on its assessment under this subsection not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H01183C45C5854E30B5E43728EFD95CEB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Progress report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the transmission of the first Strategic Plan under subsection (e) to Congress and not less frequently than once every two years thereafter, the Committee shall submit to Congress a report on the progress of the Program that includes—</text>
<paragraph id="H433DCE95764F49A9A262B30A22D5F56D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the activities funded under the Program, a description of how those activities align with the prioritized goals and research objectives established in the Strategic Plan, and the budgets, per agency, for these activities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1FA87DD83294602B76454501FC40626"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the outcomes achieved by the Program for each of the goals identified in the Strategic Plan.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H22F3150EDEFA4CAE8AC4394A21B7A9BC"><enum>5.</enum><header>National Advisory Committee on Wildland Fire Risk Reduction</header>
<subsection id="H676E33390CAA40ABA0A9646B529F33B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall establish a National Advisory Committee on Wildland Fire Risk Reduction, consisting of not fewer than seven and not more than 15 members who are qualified to provide advice on wildland fire risk reduction and represent related scientific, architectural, and engineering disciplines, none of whom may be employees of the Federal Government, including—</text> <paragraph id="HA2C5279B0ADB49F2A3213B69A1831FAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>representatives of research and academic institutions;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1D3F937DEF0C4910A940FF8D28877CCF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>standards development organizations;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H727EE949F1B34A6C93BA12B78E942F12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>emergency management agencies;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA572278A8A7D45B2A36F6890D63853B6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>State, local, and Tribal governments;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81D957354E5B40ACAE4A82BF0F8B89E6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>business communities, including the insurance industry; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3675658C941149D7AF625384F95F03FC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other representatives as designated by the Director.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2AD97FA399F74234A92032792DF5E277"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall offer assessments and recommendations on—</text>
<paragraph id="H56485FC18A8E48E1BD94B8236293B245"><enum>(1)</enum><text>trends and developments in the natural, engineering, and social sciences and practices of wildland fire risk mitigation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H855C433BE7624E13A6A6F818862B82D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the priorities of the Program’s Strategic Plan;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H664AFE036FB4417DB2DC2114B03F5333"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the management, coordination, implementation, and activities of the Program;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H643B504BB12342E4A3164A78080CE321"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the Program in meeting its purposes; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H35FDA2E994FF4861963AA9D1D3C44E81"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the need to revise the Program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1EE6294EB1DC462BA863C4D5E1927B01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>The members of the Advisory Committee established under this section shall serve without compensation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE81F3DC857B34B6384A894A0A1D08BF6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>At least every 2 years, the Advisory Committee shall report to the Director on the assessments carried out under subsection (b) and its recommendations for ways to improve the Program.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEA26DCEB28D84C7A82A23626F2F89066"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Charter</header><text>Notwithstanding <external-xref legal-doc="usc-act" parsable-cite="usc-act/Federal Advisory Committee Act /14">section 14(b)(2)</external-xref> of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.), the Advisory Committee shall not be required to file a charter subsequent to its initial charter, filed under section 9(c) of such Act, before the termination date specified in subsection (f) of this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H5451AFD585E849ED901E461BC78DEAE5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall terminate on September 30, 2026.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB933B8E6E5A243CE8530EF0737C491E7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Conflict of interest</header><text>An Advisory Committee member shall recuse himself from any Advisory Committee activity in which he has an actual pecuniary interest.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H77886BD9214149168011C5C0DBA530F6"><enum>6.</enum><header>Government Accountability Office review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report that—</text> <paragraph id="H197D6324F8B040D499A62EF938B2D89F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluates the progress and performance of the Program in establishing and making progress toward the goals of the Program as set forth in this Act; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCCDE14BA50BF4399B650AEF87C1F8AD1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes such recommendations as the Comptroller General determines are appropriate to improve the Program.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H6D9D9596A9E3453B827DB046D718A5E1"><enum>7.</enum><header>Responsibilities of Program agencies</header> <subsection id="H336CAB04C79E43BDA0AE606870170BC5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National institute of standards and technology</header><text>The responsibilities of the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology with respect to the Program are as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="HBB6C5ACC25CF41A68C4C22FF011DA748"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research and development activities</header><text>The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HD14E29A6E2B64792A5F78E9C94837B49"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carry out research on the impact of wildland fires on communities, buildings, and other infrastructure, including structure-to-structure transmission of fire and spread within communities;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE202A28893AC4C1888BC31681BFA609D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>carry out research on the generation of firebrands from wildland fires and on methods and materials to prevent or reduce firebrand ignition of communities, buildings, and other infrastructure;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5177DAC166A4D78BB6550833C6F983E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>carry out research on novel materials, systems, structures, and construction designs to harden structures, parcels, and communities to the impact of wildland fires;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2B60B1C5F6D34AE58D70995D72EBE1DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>carry out research on the impact of environmental factors on wildland fire behavior, including wind, terrain, and moisture; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6686268AF73B4A458FEEE5E8A824C958"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the development of performance-based tools to mitigate the impact of wildland fires, and work with appropriate groups to promote and assist in the use of such tools, including through model building codes and fire codes, standard test methods, voluntary consensus standards, and construction and retrofit best practices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2500A46A1A0E42F681FDEAB85C94855E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Wildland-urban interface fire post-investigations</header><text>The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HA1F173A9E5544A55BEB40EE9F2BEA93B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate Federal post-wildland fire investigations of fires at the wildland-urban interface; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H181D1AC58BB8419D9B68B392DBD2B742"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop methodologies, in collaboration with the Administrator of FEMA and in consultation with relevant stakeholders, to characterize the impact of wildland fires on communities and the impact of changes in building and fire codes, including methodologies—</text> <clause id="HED953C8E0EB74B0C9D6FF494EC615340"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for collecting, inventorying, and analyzing information on the performance of communities, buildings, and other infrastructure in wildland fires; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB861A23231D64A57A470D8C15FC39381"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for improved collection of pertinent information from different sources, including first responders, the design and construction industry, insurance companies, and building officials.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFE68371564D84382A5CDFD1ADB9F4A79"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Science Foundation</header><text>As a part of the Program, the Director of the National Science Foundation shall support—</text>
<paragraph id="H4909EE830DA9409289A0C4844429ECFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">research, including large-scale convergent research, to improve the understanding and prediction of wildland fire risks, including the conditions that increase the likelihood of a wildland fire, the behavior of wildland fires, and their impacts on buildings, communities, infrastructure, ecosystems and living systems;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED8B9DE491C6495E928371608F4BBD07"><enum>(2)</enum><text>development and improvement of tools and technologies, including databases and computational models, to enable and accelerate the understanding and prediction of wildland fires and their impacts;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF7FE888F416942BFB3BDA82D708C0E84"><enum>(3)</enum><text>development of research infrastructure, as appropriate, to enable and accelerate the understanding and prediction of wildland fires and their impacts, including upgrades or additions to the National Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD02486C527DD4FBBA4CC932AF5FE05E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>research to improve the understanding of—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB66A01EC74CB49F1BD4E2496B4DA3679"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the response to wildland fire risk and response messages by individuals, communities, and policymakers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4E851DC709341DBB1D6A1B6FE42F9E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">social and economic factors influencing the implementation and adoption of wildland fire risk reduction and response measures by individuals, communities, and policymakers; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H60D0124D9A52444DBC535D3809EC4A6C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>decision making and emergency response to wildland fires; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A978B845500431995344105F9699EA8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>undergraduate and graduate research opportunities and graduate and postdoctoral fellowships and traineeships in fields of study relevant to wildland fires and their impacts; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H486597FB83DA4A1F8D344C5718997B7C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>research to improve the understanding of the impacts of climate change and climate variability on wildland fires, including wildland fire risk, frequency, and severity, and wildland fire prediction, mitigation, and resilience strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFD089C6023524E7795CAF0A953D8AEBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National oceanic and atmospheric administration</header> <paragraph id="H5ACE677D506947CFA899FBB0F35C65D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) shall conduct research, observations, modeling, forecasting, prediction, and historical analysis of wildland fires to improve understanding of wildland fires, and associated fire weather and smoke, for the protection of life and property and for the enhancement of the national economy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H19D1F559F6F548FD8EC08BF92D24DF17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Weather forecasting and decision support for wildland fires</header><text>The Administrator shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H915DCE4475D645D98015C2DEACEEF078"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and provide in consultation with the relevant Federal Agencies, as the Administrator determines appropriate, accurate, timely, and effective warnings and forecasts of wildland fires and fire weather events that endanger life and property, which may include red flag warnings, operational fire weather alerts, and any other warnings or alerts the Administrator deems appropriate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H93DEF6D30C56469C9221B4562709D8B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide stakeholders and the public with impact-based decision support services, seasonal climate predictions, air quality products, and smoke forecasts; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4ECA6AB1328B4305B91B3FBC3EE31D62"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide on-site weather forecasts, seasonal climate predictions, and other decision support to wildland fire incident command posts, including by deploying incident meteorologists for the duration of an extreme event.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4FF6AF6D888F4B45B0D25AE24A9997CD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Wildland fire data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall contribute to and support the centralized, integrated data collaboration environment per section 3(2) and any other relevant Federal data systems by ensuring—</text> <subparagraph id="H3513B1BB00884441B2899283C7ED32ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">interoperability, usability, and accessibility of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration data and tools related to wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H154CB17AB50C47E68AB8B5246375AFA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">inclusion of historical wildland fire incident and fire weather data, and identifying potential gaps in such data; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9447E8E047F1417194003B96FADF4600"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the acquisition or collection of additional data that is needed to advance wildland fire science.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7F859431140B46C5A4234F9C0C850A16"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Wildland fire and fire weather surveillance and observations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in coordination with Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and in consultation with relevant stakeholders—</text> <subparagraph id="HDA5354C190C44DB782B1EEF88E38ACCE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall leverage existing observations, technologies and assets and develop or acquire new technologies and data to sustain and enhance environmental observations used for wildland fire prediction and detection, fire weather and smoke forecasting and monitoring, and post-wildland fire recovery, with a focus on—</text>
<clause id="HAC11A60648DB4F2EAE2756D6E8C8D009"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collecting data for pre-ignition analysis, such as drought, fuel and vegetation conditions, and soil moisture, that will help predict severe wildland fire conditions on subseasonal to decadal timescales;</text></clause> <clause id="H8AAD5337142E46BB89CDF0B549EFA9A7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting identification and classification of fire environments at the smallest practical scale to determine vulnerability to wildland fires and rapid wildland fire growth;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6A35794762134C3DA71B47DF81A51529"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>detecting, observing, and monitoring wildland fires and smoke;</text></clause> <clause id="HB5A18F637F3243D6B93F07A6D378C408"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>supporting research on the interaction of weather and wildland fire behavior; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H5CB7268FB3B443888FFD643E4CF0D6B8"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting post-fire assessments conducted by Program agencies and relevant stakeholders;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95482DDDF16B47369AB12B91EA4D1699"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall prioritize the ability to detect, observe, and monitor wildland fire and smoke in its requirements for its current and future observing systems and commercial data purchases; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0F31CD772B794BDB86F01C8598810B25"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act—</text> <clause id="H50FAA6C7FDEF44FDAA55107894521689"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may offer to enter into contracts with one or more entities to obtain additional airborne and space-based data and observations that may enhance or supplement the understanding, monitoring, prediction, and mitigation of wildland fire risks, and the relevant Program activities under section 3; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H0FF2C41B6D0A49F4B0F0B288E1AD7D0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in carrying out clause (i), shall consult with private sector entities through an advisory committee to identify needed tools and data that can be best provided by NOAA satellites and are most beneficial to wildfire and smoke detection and monitoring.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H201077C568414215A4246858D1535A27"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fire weather testbed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In collaboration with Program agencies and other relevant stakeholders, the Administrator shall establish a Fire Weather Testbed to evaluate physical and social science, technology, and other research to develop fire weather products and services for implementation by relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H56E0C194FB0B490FBBEDB4C3E5F5B077"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Wildland fire and fire weather research and development</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall support a wildland fire and smoke research and development program that includes both physical and social science with the goals of—</text> <subparagraph id="H3C7D43B554C544D6913DC1015378A46F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improving the understanding, prediction, detection, forecasting, monitoring, and assessments of wildland fires and associated fire weather and smoke;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6EDDA0B916A24626A0B36EDEDA0A45A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing products and services to meet stakeholder needs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58AEC4669780460D8E40E13791766202"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transitioning physical and social science research into operations;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3EEC1AE1956442F2B753701B0DF6C5FA"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improving modeling and technology, including coupled fire-atmosphere fire behavior modeling, in consultation with relevant Federal agencies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E8D89728BB049EF805F7333CBF9DE85"><enum>(E)</enum><text>better understanding of links between fire weather events and subseasonal-to-climate impacts; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1DC432318D1849E5A9DBF2C61E946FE0"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pursuing high-priority fire science research needs applicable to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration as identified by any other relevant Federal program. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3CE5974B0B3C4CE8B67E8D82B036EA84"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Extramural research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall collaborate with and support the non-Federal wildland fire research community, which includes institutions of higher education, private entities, nongovernmental organizations, and other relevant stakeholders, by making funds available through competitive grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements. In carrying out the program under this paragraph, the Administrator, in collaboration with other relevant Federal agencies, may establish one or more national centers for prescribed fire and wildfire sciences that leverage Federal research and development with university and nongovernmental partnerships.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2D39C2D3D610420D999D1E04EDD888DD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>High performance computing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall acquire high performance computing technologies and supercomputing technologies, leveraging existing resources, as practicable, to conduct research and development activities, support research to operations under this subsection, and host operational fire and smoke forecast models.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H20B9576C1414428BAF8E4296935103ED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Federal Emergency Management Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, acting through the United States Fire Administration, shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H14FBAFFA80714391848155B102EA0C4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support—</text> <subparagraph id="HAA18AF3FFA464EF9B43C426D853BB7CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the development of community risk assessment tools and effective mitigation techniques for preventing and responding to wildland fires, including at the wildland-urban interface;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC7616558BA4F439BB389A3BAE0E61F47"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">wildland and wildland-urban interface fire and operational response-related data collection and analysis;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H589E9B9FCA52486BB872C11E175629D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">public outreach, education, and information dissemination related to wildland fires and wildland fire risk; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE50122E3F8274055A939660B1852E2E5"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promotion of wildland and wildland-urban interface fire preparedness and community risk reduction, to include hardening the wildland-urban interface through proper construction materials, land use practices, sprinklers, assessment of State and local emergency response capacity and capabilities, and other tools and approaches as appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE6881865EEA4A71AAA836CE9BE7403C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in collaboration with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and other program agencies, as appropriate, promote and assist in the implementation of research results and promote fire-resistant buildings, retrofit, and land use practices within the design and construction industry, including architects, engineers, contractors, builders, planners, code officials, and inspectors;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H63A0A619F2A444579CF43FBFC967901D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and operate a wildland fire preparedness and mitigation technical assistance program to assist State, local, Tribal and territorial governments in using wildland fire mitigation strategies, including through the adoption and implementation of wildland and wildland-urban interface fire resistant codes, standards, and land use;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9DB20E39420D43B0AC2DBF854E7ECD3C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incorporate wildland and wildland-urban interface fire risk mitigation and loss avoidance data into the Agency’s existing risk, mitigation, and loss avoidance analyses;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBD7655E9A6C14DA38D22DDA5BDDD7D35"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incorporate data on the adoption and implementation of wildland and wildland-urban interface fire resistant codes and standards into the Agency’s hazard resistant code tracking resources; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5CD0BB0CDA6E4454AB419357E5B43F90"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">translate new information and research findings into best practices to improve firefighter, fire service, and allied professions training and education in wildland fire response, crew deployment, prevention, mitigation, resilience, and firefighting; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5BC7FF1400214CF7B62D3068969CC7D7"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct outreach and information dissemination to fire departments regarding best practices for wildland and wildland-urban interface firefighting, training, and fireground deployment; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2F06DBD75CC491DB07C6DBA7901521F"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in collaboration with other relevant Program agencies and stakeholders, develop a national level, interactive and publicly accessible wildland fire hazard severity map that includes community and parcel level data and that can readily integrate with risk gradations within wildland and wildland-urban interface fire resistant codes and standards; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAE3590C8E4244728A53AD1F3D0EAD330"><enum>(9)</enum><text>develop resources regarding best practices for establishing or enhancing peer-support programs within wildland fire firefighting units.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H72597A6DE69446F1B1CD99F703B7C5E7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</header><text>The responsibilities of the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) with respect to the Program are as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="HE536AC71DE99429398B05829AB825F76"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall, with respect to the Program—</text> <subparagraph id="H2D1375E817E64FDBAF4B7D5AAA0CFB66"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support relevant basic and applied scientific research and modeling;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7E177779BDA14412BD9765DFD9AB3A52"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure the use in the Program of all relevant National Aeronautics and Space Administration Earth observations data for maximum utility;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H09F2C6727C8547069DDDE860D7A4504B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>explore and apply novel tools and technologies in the activities of the Program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H16CE6D15C9094E74BF3E73418B0C363A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support the translation of research to operations, including to Program agencies and relevant stakeholders;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D601B7ACE1842DBA973B48939C8B85E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>facilitate the communication of wildland fire research, knowledge, and tools to relevant stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3188591545A94FF8AEFB0699BCA96E7F"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use commercial data where such data is available and accessible through existing Federal Government commercial contracts, agreements, or other means, and purchase data that is deemed necessary based on consultation with other Program agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCC573DFF965641D3A2BC82CDE84421C4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Wildland fire research and applications</header><text>The Administrator shall support basic and applied wildland fire research and modeling activities, including competitively selected research, to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H68338D120A9549E6BE1F0FC44ABC99F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve the understanding and prediction of fire environments, wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H058410FFA4664F6CB6BE7F327B32A27E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improve the understanding of the impacts of climate change and variability on wildland fire risk, frequency, and severity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6B4531415E58418E8BAE140E6CFAF130"><enum>(C)</enum><text>characterize the pre-fire phase and fire-inducing conditions, such as soil moisture and vegetative fuel availability;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4B607B15E5E54F1A995C3E8EA5030938"><enum>(D)</enum><text>characterize the active fire phase, such as fire and smoke plume mapping, fire behavior and spread modeling, and domestic and global fire activity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7B52DA3FCFD4437989E5DCF701AAE9D3"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">characterize the post-fire phase, such as landscape changes, air quality, erosion, landslides, and impacts on carbon distributions in forest biomass;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42A9DB80DAAE442AA32D04510DB2F974"><enum>(F)</enum><text>contribute to advancing predictive wildland fire models;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H10F64631ED524B3BA0A6BEA1FFCCF20C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>address other relevant investigations and measurements prioritized by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Decadal Survey on Earth Science and Applications from Space;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6AE21E125C4464794BB77A063D55C52"><enum>(H)</enum><text>improve the translation of research knowledge into actionable information;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H400172837C3641EE986D8176D14ED1DD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>develop research and data products, including maps, decision-support information, and tools, and support related training as appropriate and practicable;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCBA567F93E014E40928A918930BC1993"><enum>(J)</enum><text>collaborate with other Program agencies and relevant stakeholders, as appropriate, on joint research and development projects, including research grant solicitations and field campaigns; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H34DBE64574C84E79A5C2CAEC99456E1B"><enum>(K)</enum><text>transition research advances to operations, including to Program agencies and relevant stakeholders, as practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2B332A87C8E4EBABA9694AC72B28A06"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Wildland fire data systems and computational tools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6AC8B3B9AC8D4220A91DA161CB07B36F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify, from the National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s Earth science data systems, data, including combined data products and relevant commercial data sets, that can contribute to improving the understanding, monitoring, prediction, and mitigation of wildland fires and their impacts, including data related to fire weather, plume dynamics, smoke and fire behavior, impacts of climate change and variability, land and property burned, wildlife and ecosystem destruction, among other areas;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H330BCE920179456896BF39F1D5BCC82E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritize the dissemination of data identified or obtained under this subparagraph to the widest extent practicable to support relevant research and operational stakeholders;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDB8B46D1B2894C9583C2946455C2542D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>consider opportunities to support the Program under section 2 and the Program activities under section 3 when planning and developing Earth observation satellites, instruments, and airborne measurement platforms;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H957FE268A836458890EF0058E216D66A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify opportunities, in collaboration with Program agencies and relevant stakeholders, to obtain additional airborne and space-based data and observations that may enhance or supplement the understanding, monitoring, prediction, and mitigation of wildland fire risks, and the relevant Program activities under section 3, and consider such options as commercial solutions, including commercial data purchases, prize authority, academic partnerships, and ground-based or space-based instruments, as practicable and appropriate; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H529051C55B4748A5ADFD1E10E0A0B56C"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contribute to and support, to the maximum extent practicable, the centralized, integrated data collaboration environment per section 3(2) and any other relevant interagency data systems, by collecting, organizing, and integrating the National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s scientific data, data systems, and computational tools related to wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts, and by enhancing the interoperability, useability, and accessibility of National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s scientific data, data systems, and computational tools, including—</text> <clause id="H1D0FF54A84A5467DB234AEB04DE48AD1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>observations and available real-time and near-real-time measurements;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6F4AD0B221034D14B5E3E0A107B76E17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">derived science and data products, such as fuel conditions, risk and spread maps, and data products to represent the wildland-urban interface;</text></clause> <clause id="HB71633CC9B0243F3943793B5723C5EA8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant historical and archival observations, measurements, and derived science and data products; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HA4E90024740144B6BF9E01D9326EECA5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other relevant decision support and information tools.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC71833F359C1463989D1FA488AB7C1DC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Novel tools for active wildland fire monitoring and risk mitigation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in collaboration with other Program agencies and relevant stakeholders shall apply novel tools and technologies to support active wildland fire research, monitoring, mitigation, and risk reduction, as practicable and appropriate. In particular, the Administrator shall:</text>
<subparagraph id="HEC593432051F472CABB9FBCB27EA37BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish, in collaboration with the heads of other relevant Federal agencies, a program to develop and demonstrate a unified concept of operations for the safe and effective deployment of diverse air capabilities in active wildland fire monitoring, mitigation, and risk reduction. The objectives of the Program shall be to— </text> <clause id="H620198731D7B416D8FA7426D7AFC49EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and demonstrate a wildland fire airspace operations system accounting for piloted aircraft, uncrewed aerial systems, and other new and emerging capabilities such as autonomous and high-altitude assets;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD11082A9705E41CFB4BF368A35C06328"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop an interoperable communications strategy;</text></clause> <clause id="HDEFEFB4596444018BFB2DCC6258048DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>develop a roadmap for the on-ramping of new technologies, capabilities, or entities;</text></clause>
<clause id="H023FC19F047241F88204056A6A11624B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identify additional development, testing, and demonstration that would be required to expand the scale of operations;</text></clause> <clause id="H5F1F3067BC284A3BB50CE5435A73AA11"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify actions that would be required to transition the unified concept of operations in subparagraph (A) into ongoing, operational use; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H69480568371D45B586D6F1786A6AADDE"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>other objectives, as deemed appropriate by the Administrator.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AB9F36EB68C45E6A2C31AADE597F0F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Develop and demonstrate affordable and deployable sensing technologies, in consultation with other Program agencies and relevant stakeholders, to improve the monitoring of fire fuel and active wildland fires, wildland fire behavior models and forecast, mapping efforts, and the prediction and mitigation of wildland fires and their impacts. The Administrator shall—</text>
<clause id="H208BDA4A1D67439C8C3AF1AFAF628985"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">test and demonstrate technologies such as infrared, microwave, and active sensors suitable for deployment on spacecraft, aircraft, uncrewed aerial systems, and ground-based and in situ platforms, as appropriate and practicable;</text></clause> <clause id="HB81268A793D541E0863BF1F9A9326023"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop and demonstrate affordable and deployable sensing technologies that can be transitioned to operations for collection of near-real-time localized measurements;</text></clause>
<clause id="H48F73D328E5149B5A79DB974E8BA454F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and demonstrate near-real-time data processing, availability, interoperability, and visualization, as practicable; </text></clause> <clause id="H3131C924C0464FBBA86F9DA16CC44B22"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify opportunities and actions required, in collaboration with Program agencies and relevant stakeholders, to transition relevant technologies, techniques, and data to science operations, upon successful demonstration of the feasibility and scientific utility of the sensors and data;</text></clause>
<clause id="H38B93671833648B8A816978071B0748D"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">transition demonstrated technologies, techniques, and data into ongoing, operational use, including to Program agencies and relevant stakeholders;</text></clause> <clause id="H723729B351DC411991CB50925752B4B8"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>prioritize and facilitate, to the greatest extent practicable, the dissemination of these science data to operations, including to Program agencies and relevant stakeholders; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HD729329484DF4645B687D5588F9673C2"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider opportunities for potential partnerships, including commercial data purchases, among industry, government, academic institutions, and non-profit organizations and other relevant stakeholders in carrying out clauses (i) through (vi), as appropriate and practicable.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H29C922993C614DE9A81164A88F85201B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Environmental Protection Agency</header><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall support environmental research and development activities to—</text>
<paragraph id="HF895860C717E4DCA86B56B618AFA4105"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improve the understanding of—</text> <subparagraph id="H299C4A70102C45A082CA8F1CDF022BEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">wildland fire smoke plume characteristics, chemical transformation, chemical composition, and transport;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1511E77B597147A0A342FF862D0AC2C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>wildland fire and smoke impacts to contaminant containment and remediation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF5BACF7B8FF4D41B309F731BE1DFB43"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the contribution of wildland fire emissions to climate forcing emissions;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8A7CBDF73E274D5681C09B689435400A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>differences between the impacts of prescribed fires compared to other wildland fires on communities and air and water quality; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5723901810B44F16A8AB1DCB4D8E7CF5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>climate change and variability on wildland fires and smoke plumes, including on smoke exposure;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H53C6524BFE904EC0A3D150A22D9CE5ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and improve tools, sensors, and technologies including databases and computational models, to accelerate the understanding, monitoring, and prediction of wildland fires and smoke exposure;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA642E1A5BEE848808615819445AB0CCD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>better integrate observational data into wildland fire and smoke characterization models to improve modeling at finer temporal and spatial resolution; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE0DC3A18F5BE4ACABC73E4F308B6C712"><enum>(4)</enum><text>improve communication of wildland fire and smoke risk reduction strategies to the public in coordination with relevant stakeholders and other Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6A3B54F1EFD14B35A10167852A5E35A2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Department of Energy</header><text>The Secretary of Energy shall carry out research and development activities to—</text>
<paragraph id="H3BF839B3CE854C28A2529259AA9DFB7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create tools, techniques, and technologies for—</text> <subparagraph id="H02B31EDF85F54E21A930BB3A4C336577"><enum>(A)</enum><text>withstanding and addressing the current and projected impact of wildland fires on energy sector infrastructure;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA74652D14081494A8C6EB77AD98F1545"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing real-time or near-time awareness of the risks posed by wildland fires to the operation of energy infrastructure in affected and potentially affected areas, including by leveraging the Department’s high-performance computing capabilities and climate and ecosystem models;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC3C734A057A449ADAFDCECAE34B9D97B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enabling early detection of, and assessment of competing technologies and strategies for addressing, malfunctioning electrical equipment on the transmission and distribution grid, including spark ignition causing wildland fires;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5EDBC3E9C1C44E26BF0CE52EACE3BF36"><enum>(D)</enum><text>assisting with the planning, safe execution of, and safe and timely restoration of power after emergency power shut offs following wildland fires started by grid infrastructure;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H32D25D58152E48BDAE65E793E93D5B49"><enum>(E)</enum><text>improving electric grid and energy sector safety and resilience in the event of multiple simultaneous or co-located weather or climate events leading to extreme conditions, such as extreme wind, wildland fires, extreme cold, and extreme heat; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE0904A6329E54670BBDCE48192881D98"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improving coordination between utilities and relevant Federal agencies to enable communication, information-sharing, and situational awareness in the event of wildland fires that impact the electric grid; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4E84720E098F4D3DB2287162A69E2D83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate data and computational resources across relevant entities to improve our understanding of wildland fires and to promote resilience and wildland fire prevention in the planning, design, construction, operation, and maintenance of transmission infrastructure; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5BAD685F5F7D4362BB726AA03DC642D8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>consider optimal building energy efficiency and weatherization practices, as practicable, in wildland fire research;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CF17AE50FBA4A7A920A90CE0EA3F085"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilize the Department of Energy’s National Laboratory capabilities, including user facilities, earth and environmental systems modeling resources, and high-performance computing and data analytics capabilities, to improve the accuracy of efforts to understand and predict wildland fire behavior and occurrence and mitigate wildland fire impacts; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF041CB26CC114782B2379A7F1D6A57B4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">foster engagement between the National Laboratories and practitioners, researchers, policy organizations, utilities, and other entities the Secretary determines to be appropriate to understand the economic and social implications of power disruptions caused by wildland fires, particularly within disadvantaged communities and regions vulnerable to wildland fires, including rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H6ED4375D87CE44ECB13787CEE83225F4"><enum>8.</enum><header>Budget activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Director of the National Science Foundation, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Secretary of Energy shall each include in the annual budget request to Congress of each respective agency a description of the projected activities of such agency under the Program for the fiscal year covered by the budget request and an estimate of the amount such agency plans to spend on such activities for the relevant fiscal year.</text></section>
<section id="H1ED59E36E83444039409CA62BB0B5C17"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HAA8EAED6CDEF4C6D93A8A4D2E1813D8C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF5E9DDBD72142D0ACF3BE5CAB6226BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <quote>Program</quote> means the Program established under section 2.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BCD99245D4D42A79995721D77098043"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Program agencies</header><text>The term <quote>Program agencies</quote> means any Federal agency with responsibilities under the Program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEB9BF72F9F4748C18E7A8182DBBD309A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Stakeholders</header><text>The term <quote>stakeholders</quote> means any public or private organization engaged in addressing wildland fires, associated smoke, and their impacts, and shall include relevant Federal agencies, States, territories, Tribes, State and local governments, businesses, not-for-profit organizations, including national standards and building code organizations, firefighting departments and organizations, academia, and other users of wildland fire data products.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC4AB3276F4CE4751817A9C8C8E935F3F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Wildland fire</header><text>The term <quote>wildland fire</quote> means any non-structure fire that occurs in vegetation or natural fuels and includes wildfires and prescribed fires.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5793412DAA6B4863AA2C36AD1B6BC93F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Fire environment</header><text>The term <quote>fire environment</quote> means surrounding conditions, influences, and modifying forces of topography, fuel, and weather that determine fire behavior.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HB82BC16926CC4BBABFDF80564AE59450"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> <subsection id="H68F32A9D09B543039933DF810E902D1C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Institute of Standards and Technology for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H1E44C4AB6C5043FFA023345796B28AE3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$35,800,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39A09217702B44FA9F9679F23B31938D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$36,100,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2F85657BA354882973F010D15904A91" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$36,400,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFAF41EF198344221AAB276037968F6D6" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$36,700,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H90FED6796CEF471E8122E629CD3950D9" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$37,100,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAF6EBB837129470B97C9DAF9C80630A0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Science Foundation</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Science Foundation for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H84A94DF8AFA54CDBBB0DF592D36317AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB57512DB2472477D8A2070E2576206E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$53,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA23C2DCC965A4C13899A5C85C269BDF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$56,200,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H338526C30D244B40808C82B6230DE684"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$59,600,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B0652C811C1492AB51DBF01DF74158D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$63,100,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB5712D17399E4DF795F5024314B20D03"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="HE3EC6D9A9D85450FB820BA0F77789337"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$200,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5EBBE69C1047491889774BC0321620CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$215,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H45047ADDB3E24AB5BB09EC27627B15F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$220,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74998D0DCD9340FAA7E34B924B212651"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$230,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9048B44C19BE497B95F1C9C68D46B0BB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$250,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6FE0FCE782C2449998E454488ADF8150"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Aeronautics and Space Administration for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H549F55F7912B4E398EA990836283395E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$95,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14E51B4FDF57491A94FF3D2101EFDB2F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$100,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCBCA9B5151234A06A076C55EDDDBD819"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$110,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8D8E67BCD7C4CF1923314738F3A1FB5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$110,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5B0ACEEC54E3436C8973EB8830D4EFEC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$110,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H70DFF7873B214B8690D899DC7DF3ADCE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Environmental Protection Agency</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Environmental Protection Agency for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="HB01317330DCD42898BF0F213199A1D09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$11,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBEAAEEFF6CCF4116B2C91ECBBF437EE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$11,700,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE5F4F8686884466BC37806558775F64"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$12,400,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H263B87514EE14C9480E21444CBC695A9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$13,100,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H18D115765E7E43C080A1181E7A0EECEA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$13,900,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCAC424350DAE4B449CE339DBECD32EB3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Federal Emergency Management Agency</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Federal Emergency Management Agency for carrying out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H8EA8DDFC5D1844B68590E150683CCCB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$6,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07231D0D777043F9B4DB1F23D5DDE52A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$6,400,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCAFA4770F9D04DDEA3D3253F8D9248FB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$6,700,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56C562A1E63043799E72A63B7616D30A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$7,100,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF7D00951D8B3429E8A82B36FB036FFBC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$7,600,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

