<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFB7C175A3C294A8595E24C87D6557CA8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4133 IH: Private Prison Information Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4133</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require non-Federal prison, correctional, and detention facilities holding Federal prisoners or detainees under a contract with the Federal Government to make the same information available to the public that Federal prisons and correctional facilities are required to make available.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1934F891BB454035A55BCE31F50CADD9" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H3C8CB86C7C93478486C50A4AF8105DEE"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Private Prison Information Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H593BF6B1222D4118A526B4A405DC0ADE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3F2248260EE24035A29B97BB1695476A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CF2A856DA2D4F869482288C6FE02BB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>applicable entity</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0DCF3DE7D30D4699A8E26C4909F93629"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nongovernmental entity contracting with, or receiving funds directly or indirectly from, a covered agency to incarcerate or detain Federal prisoners or detainees in a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E1F7D4D723A499CBF1C10023092FC35"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State or local governmental entity with an intergovernmental agreement with a covered agency to incarcerate or detain Federal prisoners or detainees in a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B595A71335C4412875EE8B09FDCD538"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>covered agency</term> means an agency that contracts with, or provides funds to, an applicable entity to incarcerate or detain Federal prisoners or detainees in a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C25D4ECB9E54176A9D1736B51CF1FDC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7C11A09A5A2E4811A6E23F586638CCB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a privately owned or privately operated prison, correctional, or detention facility; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC3620AD47A64AB29CCEB52C0C494E97"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State or local prison, jail, or other correctional or detention facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H93B598A9176A423C9B2A3D395C32F5FB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Freedom of Information Act applicable for contract prisons</header> 
<subsection id="H771995D278AA41E6A619DD7E4A7CB2E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A record relating to a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility shall be—</text> <paragraph id="HACAADFCEEA8146C9B00986675BD33CDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>considered an agency record for purposes of section 552(f)(2) of title 5, United States Code, whether in the possession of an applicable entity or a covered agency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDB8EB320308413BB2CDD2A6352E1844"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subject to section 552 of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>), to the same extent as if the record was maintained by an agency operating a Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H53FE8ED8AA944EFCA9906021E6DA4213"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Withholding of information</header><text>A covered agency may not withhold information that would otherwise be required to be disclosed under subsection (a) unless—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDF40848428AE4C36A53BF32A31243338"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the covered agency, based on the independent assessment of the covered agency, reasonably foresees that disclosure of the information would cause specific identifiable harm to an interest protected by an exemption from disclosure under section 552(b) of title 5, United States Code; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABE0A632605E4CD682F26E3C7508D9D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>disclosure of the information is prohibited by law.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H63DEFE11FE3E42D595075E7E09FE65A7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Format of records</header><text>An applicable entity shall maintain records relating to a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility in formats that are readily reproducible and reasonably searchable by the covered agency that contracts with or provides funds to the applicable entity to incarcerate or detain Federal prisoners or detainees in the non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC3CB9E310F424C6C86B9C2EB81050E7D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header> <paragraph id="H4770E2BE25EB44F68CAF1D13A872C7F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, a covered agency shall promulgate regulations or guidance to ensure compliance with this section by the covered agency and an applicable entity that the covered agency contracts with or provides funds to incarcerate or detain Federal prisoners or detainees in a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD6BED59F47244978BBB58C6008E269C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance by applicable entities</header> 
<subparagraph id="H82B343194E7147EF87B74DB9F2D8632C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Compliance with this section by an applicable entity shall be included as a material term in any contract, agreement, or renewal of a contract or agreement with the applicable entity regarding the incarceration or detention of Federal prisoners or detainees in a non-Federal prison, correctional, or detention facility.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8C02A551EF04EBCA8AF64711AE15BFF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Modification of contract or agreement</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, a covered agency shall secure a modification to include compliance with this section by an applicable entity as a material term in any contract or agreement described under subparagraph (A) that will not otherwise be renegotiated, renewed, or modified before the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7A999ED907574B4C831205DDA703C65D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to limit or reduce the scope of State or local open records laws.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

