<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF7F1A436878144C0ABEB0057A7757291" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2510 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to make the credit for the adoption of special needs children refundable.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2510</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to make the credit for the adoption of special needs children refundable.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1D7EC4E0AAE044B4B672379D408430F1" style="OLC"><section id="HE5F00EF26D6A4139AC253B0FC257115B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Adoption credit for special needs children made refundable</header><subsection id="HAA4831FB7A934DB9A3DD9051CEA4F1B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/23">Section 23</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (i) as subsection (j) and by inserting after subsection (h) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9C2BAF3971914B1A80503B8136F0F457" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HB174B0679CDE4AB4A09D1A013F247FB3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Portion of credit related to special needs children made refundable</header><paragraph id="H87395A26B9564809999553B1C7CAA636"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>So much of the credit allowed under this section for any taxable year (determined without regard to this subsection and subsection (c)) as does not exceed the special needs adoption expenses for such taxable year shall be treated as a credit allowed under subpart C (and not allowed under this section).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4512586A774740D1A3E46D6760842A20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special needs adoption expenses</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>special needs adoption expenses</quote> means, with respect to any taxpayer for any taxable year, the aggregate amount of qualified adoption expenses with respect to adoptions of children with special needs which is taken into account in determining the credit allowed under this section to such taxpayer for such taxable year (determined without regard to this subsection, subsection (b)(2), and subsection (c)).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBEC813C417C14AC5BBEF704E5AB9FBF2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with carryforward of non-Refundable portion</header><text>Section 23(c)(1) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>under subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>under this section (determined after application of subsection (i))</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0CA449FF21A84C5082D0DB166965DECC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the later of the date of the enactment of this Act or December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

