<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2049941C5412479C9C3197DFD47CBF39" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2367 IH: Truck Parking Safety Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2367</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, to establish a competitive grant program for projects for commercial motor vehicle parking, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD2B0DCEE8E43491DB8CFD621A9C1792F" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H77B4400FB51B44508BB26590D817C57E"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Truck Parking Safety Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H89789FF1826D41F0897CA813EBE7FD6C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that it should be a national priority to address the shortage of parking for commercial motor vehicles on the Federal-aid highway system to improve highway safety.</text></section><section id="H6B6403437D494499AB428A6DB07C5977"><enum>3.</enum><header>Parking for commercial motor vehicles</header><subsection id="HAE26BB1620FF44E185FC70551D21C7B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">Chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HB27A4C95DF394605AFA8C82142A94499"><section id="HC158C636BB3B4BD381A496641B7A9F71"><enum>180.</enum><header>Parking for commercial motor vehicles</header><subsection id="HA344E32B23A041C49B54969982DAC5F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H5DC6A8B250D749EEB943D7F3A2D0EA4C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commercial motor vehicle</header><text>The term <term>commercial motor vehicle</term> has the meaning given the term in section 31132 of title 49.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E594B8D552F4D3DAD300C4569F3571C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Safety rest area</header><text>The term <term>safety rest area</term> has the meaning given the term in section 120(c)(1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H871F5D1ED89D44EF9F13C21A9AB14B01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text>Subject to the availability of funds, the Secretary shall make grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities for projects to provide public parking for commercial motor vehicles and improve the safety of commercial motor vehicle drivers. </text></subsection><subsection id="H90D642A590834C358A14E5DBCEC2AF12"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><paragraph id="H10CF25E5244F40BCAF8B8C6EFD279A6D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity eligible to receive a grant under this section is any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE9855D08EA794FDA83026934B0542676"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D5B35FFDB4D46878FAF0D360067B4C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A metropolitan planning organization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9F861771912437083A7C35FCEB1BC61"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A unit of local government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B0B010AC06A433E858E66DBCC3F47EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A political subdivision of a State or local government carrying out responsibilities relating to commercial motor vehicle parking.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD57F7D87739F49D0885653700593E54D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A Tribal government or a consortium of Tribal governments. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F7C0E024C344B528607D72251739CCC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A multistate or multijurisdictional group of entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (E). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6FFC7EB568E420A80560869360F2113"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Private sector participation</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may partner with a private entity to carry out an eligible project under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H241D468C5CB44AC28B952E587E3F7C73"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><paragraph id="H88F7892CE6D54483806ED60847A07DD4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity may use a grant provided under this section for a project described in paragraph (2) that is on—</text><subparagraph id="HD76DEB4B9D7640CB9C09ABDC1C8A692F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Federal-aid highway; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEABB75E67EF146519128F369BB0DCAA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a facility with reasonable access (as described in section 658.19 of title 23, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation)) to—</text><clause id="H9C180116D2F446C9A5F835D2804D86C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a Federal-aid highway; or</text></clause><clause id="HB2EB01D489D7482AA4B92042D3A13827"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a freight facility.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE34911BA1AE413A8A4E75C08DCEEE5E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Projects described</header><text>A project referred to in paragraph (1) is a project—</text><subparagraph id="H083AD077B2A54021B018079451B94697"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to construct a safety rest area that includes parking for commercial motor vehicles;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2D7E445BDDD4F10B0F5E89BD6DF0045"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to construct additional commercial motor vehicle parking capacity—</text><clause id="HDE091D3CE9F94FC6B4272BE3E92F1F6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>adjacent to a private commercial truck stop or travel plaza;</text></clause><clause id="HBF47AA83B1444AD6B03974302984DAE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>within the boundaries of, or adjacent to, a publicly owned freight facility, including a port terminal operated by a public authority; </text></clause><clause id="H7DA5ED2619F34865A8A27DF9C4528614"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at an existing facility, including an inspection or weigh station and a park-and-ride location; or</text></clause><clause id="H1DD66A8C744D49F398263C2591F454CE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>at another suitable facility, as determined by the eligible entity, in concurrence with the Secretary;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C9B68BEEE774E4FB18E7177ADBBAB0C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to reopen an existing weigh station, safety rest area, park-and-ride facility, or other government-owned facility, that is not in use, for commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78BD95ED87764C1FBA47156D4FFAD7DC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to construct or make capital improvements to an existing public commercial motor vehicle parking facility to expand parking use and availability, including at a seasonal facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H259E27F989DD47819B1A98B0A6D02018"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to identify, promote, and manage the availability of publicly and privately provided commercial motor vehicle parking, such as through the use of intelligent transportation systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA727B5B0E8F405AB02E5E3EDB9D6BF4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to improve the personal safety of commercial motor vehicle drivers at a parking facility as part of a project described in subparagraphs (A) through (D); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4BB39D08ABEC461090F3338BEEB16FE5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to improve a parking facility, including through truck stop electrification systems, as part of a project described in subparagraphs (A) through (D).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECD13DA8CBA34FF8B0E7394CF8887782"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text><paragraph id="HC519B7B8AEE24CDDA251FF88FD41C2BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the proposed project; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7BEFDBDA0404BA99D189A61D2EDB415"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary determines to be necessary. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F26D1B504A048F4B8E99977C6DF780A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>The Secretary may select a project to receive a grant under this section only if the Secretary determines that—</text><paragraph id="HF5232A7EB54C4A279C4FB57490603A36"><enum>(1)</enum><text>there is a shortage of commercial motor vehicle parking capacity in the corridor in which the project is located;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9422D801062B4D56B56BC62B2ED70498"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the eligible entity has consulted with motor carriers, commercial motor vehicle drivers, public safety officials, and private providers of commercial motor vehicle parking regarding the project;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03519BB1F3D947C582EDB42448519CFB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the project will likely—</text><subparagraph id="H6679D11DCD9F4758836E93C6A9A65B9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increase the availability or utilization of commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEA3A77F439B4F51A6567E313F86F438"><enum>(B)</enum><text>facilitate the efficient movement of freight; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50805A294D804999BDA0EB2CD120D24F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improve highway safety, traffic congestion, and air quality; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7FE9EA614ED460184F4CEB62CCC4D84"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the eligible entity demonstrates the ability to provide for the maintenance and operation of the facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0506355CD4944C33B929E4D62E887B63"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional consideration</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, the Secretary shall select projects to receive grants under the program in a manner that maximizes the geographic dispersion of new commercial motor vehicle parking capacity across the United States. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE17E3E8388BF4CDFB25DD0765DE85E3F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><paragraph id="HECA1A5768E7B4CDB824B22832B46117D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity may use a grant under this section for—</text><subparagraph id="H35B03D877FB949D69F30B68EE6304AB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>development phase activities, including planning, feasibility analysis, benefit-cost analysis, environmental review, preliminary engineering and design work, and other preconstruction activities necessary to advance a project under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C62A8A5D3DF49B99796084097C4EFCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>construction and operational improvements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H320245A924B34DD8A315FF7C82EF8D65"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header><subparagraph id="HD116F336AB374A699697D5C6B5A29207"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity may use not more than 25 percent of the amount of a grant under this section for activities described in paragraph (1)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC82FDE90447C4D0B8E1922A43B07A108"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Existing facilities</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC0BD9D5860524C72AE01854200AB8305"><enum>(i)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), not more than 10 percent of the amounts made available for each fiscal year for grants under this section may be used for projects described in subsection (d)(2)(E) that solely identify, promote, and manage the availability of existing commercial motor vehicle parking.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53B76CB90BBB4823A4A8AC76DFA3E003"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply to a project described in subsection (d)(2)(E) that is part of a project to expand commercial motor vehicle parking capacity. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4F46CA534914372A7BFBD0AC5BD317A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0957AFB0C4874682A5BDE2552C8D229E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts made available to carry out this section shall not be used for the construction, or development phase activities that would enable the construction, of charging or fueling infrastructure for the propulsion of a vehicle, including a commercial motor vehicle. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF16067C6EEF7475B8220718A224CAE42"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph limits the use of funds other than funds made available to carry out this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D6DD09E114D444B980CF78E7CF1EC67"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Requirements</header><paragraph id="HB4916F02FAA549838A8658E6F486BCC9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publicly accessible parking</header><text>Commercial motor vehicle parking constructed, opened, or improved with funds from a grant under this section shall be open and accessible to all commercial motor vehicle drivers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8A17057A36248D7A8E2D0211AC1AE38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on charging fees</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B75FF03B41942CFBE6B032054F414C2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No fee may be charged by an eligible entity to a commercial motor vehicle driver to gain access to parking constructed, opened, maintained, or improved with a grant under this section. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E395C3CB1BC47D189B302B686B97D01"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Treatment of projects</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a project carried out under this section shall be treated as a project on a Federal-aid highway under this chapter.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3702B236E1314997991045D1293591EB"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Period of availability of funds</header><text>Amounts made available for projects under this section shall remain available for a period of 3 years after the last day of the fiscal year in which the amounts are made available.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H42A8279B972F4D6E99A964174959BCF9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HDBB88B14B3664B36B8226920D99C1115"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">180. Parking for commercial motor vehicles.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HC7ADE15A447A417B8FA9364708786F07"><enum>4.</enum><header>Survey and comparative assessment</header><subsection id="HF4AD96C1809645B18C4F44404F615196"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary of Transportation, in consultation with appropriate State motor carrier safety personnel, motor carriers, State departments of transportation, and private providers of commercial motor vehicle parking, shall submit to the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report that—</text><paragraph id="HC1C2EA6BF214478F9E4F57A66460615E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluates the availability of adequate parking and rest facilities, taking into account both private and public facilities, for commercial motor vehicles engaged in interstate transportation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A843158F73F4F9688E1330FED16FB80"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluates the effectiveness of the projects funded under section 180 of title 23, United States Code, in improving access to commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H013E2E4045424A35AE7718901227B042"><enum>(3)</enum><text>evaluates the ability of eligible entities that received a grant under section 180 of title 23, United States Code, to sustain the operation of parking facilities constructed with funds provided under that section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AE44E204FEC46B6BA1A5204C830A773"><enum>(4)</enum><text>reports on the progress being made to provide adequate commercial motor vehicle parking facilities. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB1F90813255F4546BBC2DC89106310EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Results</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation shall make the reports under subsection (a) available to the public on the website of the Department of Transportation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9513C103BAE3407A8A0EBB74431678F4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Alignment of reports</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary of Transportation shall—</text><paragraph id="H7B9F2457AE7748EC90A0E376DAE140F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider the results of the commercial motor vehicle parking facilities assessments of States under subsection (f) of section 70202 of title 49, United States Code; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H891B316E23CB4E2489FB0E7D37A59634"><enum>(2)</enum><text>seek to align the contents of the reports under subsection (a) and the submission and publication of those reports with the State freight plans developed and updated under that section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="HF8372AD9BFEC4133BBB099B1344DF6AA"><enum>5.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Transportation for projects for commercial motor vehicle parking under section 180 of title 23, United States Code—</text><paragraph id="H1B4403A92DDD41F88B85DCE441727644"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$175,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B3DAE20B56F4F95ADF77303DB5D6F2C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$260,000,000 for fiscal year 2025; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7049FCF11B504FC79AF1627108A40CDE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$320,000,000 for fiscal year 2026.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

