<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEBAA28AC517640A7B68252B062322AFD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5949 IH: Protecting Gun Owners’ Privacy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5949</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231012">October 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to enhance the privacy of legal gun owners, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5C0C604596814216BC2C7A63BAA864A6" style="OLC"><section id="HCC1F5F2D343547D1A018AE827DC20671" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Gun Owners’ Privacy Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H31078B493FBD4C5E80824E2AE8238179"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhancement of privacy of legal gun owners</header><subsection id="H93B3DC818F234B8DB6866D28ECF5F457"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Disposition of records</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 923(g) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD2B328BFA7A549C5A2EBEAB911F736D7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H2D73D3D05765400AA1775C93ADD5F9F4" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H94CF84311DFF48E79C11B77BE7475ADA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall be interpreted to expand or restrict the authority of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives to carry out any provision of this chapter.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E37550C17CF41F9A057B6C82CD1B604" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8F4334D31F1649D48082EA471F54F926"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A department, agency, or instrumentality of the Federal Government may not store any record or bound volume required under this chapter that is received by the department, agency, or instrumentality on or after the date of the enactment of this clause, unless the record or bound volume is needed in an ongoing bona fide criminal investigation or prosecution.</text></clause><clause id="H4CFDEC2489F64EA48CB94ABFCCFDF0CE" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In the case of such a record or bound volume received by such a department, agency, or instrumentality before such date of enactment, the department, agency, or instrumentality shall destroy the record and any information from the record or bound volume that the department, agency, or instrumentality has stored, unless the record or bound volume is needed in an ongoing bona fide criminal investigation or prosecution.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H430903C27E93495C95262985E6CE6403" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A department or agency of the Federal Government may not acquire directly from a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer a record required to be maintained by the licensee under this chapter. On request of such a department or agency, the Attorney General may provide the department or agency, as the case may be, with such a record obtained by the Attorney General pursuant to this chapter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC3FD816F53B24C6B8856C110EF0A88C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on content of required reports and records</header><paragraph id="HAF8637927D4E42FD8517EDC12B3506EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Multiple firearm sales reports</header><text>Section 923(g)(3)(A) of such title is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Attorney General may not require or authorize any personal identifying information to be included on the form.</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61F7FA45BBAF4241B3F525572EBDB19D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Firearm transaction records</header><text>Section 926 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5FEAAF1DA4E241428BF43C20BE371608" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HA8083E376EB34A998097372F2CD9806D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General may not require or authorize any personal identifying information of an individual seeking to acquire a firearm to be included in any record required to be kept pursuant to this chapter.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDE3C5FB0E3F4B32B3A11C5F83A8430B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of personal identifying information</header><text>Section 921(a) of such title is amended by inserting after paragraph (30) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB81BFF2279264D93B0BC5D72D68AB4C3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H62290F57245D421DBD6BF25C907BE36E" indent="up1"><enum>(31)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>personal identifying information</term> means any representation of information that permits the identity of an individual to whom the information applies to be reasonably inferred by either direct or indirect means, including information enabling the contacting of the individual.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

