<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB3D7EA571BD4415A818633B5D8F1D97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1741 IH: More Teaching Less Testing Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1741</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to decrease the frequency of standardized tests administered to students in grades 3 through 12, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HF55E08FA8C624EF1BE65109ECC925DAB" style="OLC">
<section id="H6FA37EE25ABA42649C2C2610D61E8D97" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>More Teaching Less Testing Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H60AC3382C5D343E9850D0CF69920CDF6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HBB61D5340CB94E5783EBC5178E1C9EF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An overwhelming body of research evidence demonstrates that—</text> <subparagraph id="H1EFBC907F81640D390DAD43B49EDF67D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>standardized testing scores are highly correlated with the socioeconomic status of a student; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9A0AC34610F64BB68CB396E7A8ACA413"><enum>(B)</enum><text>test-based accountability has not improved equity in public schools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79723A0CF3934DF0957F99299062CC4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the National Education Association, there is a nationwide shortage of 300,000 teachers and school staff.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF8A2D00DC69E48C88D5762831771352A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the 2022 report of the American Federation of Teachers Teacher and School Staff Shortage Task Force titled <quote>Here Today, Gone Tomorrow?</quote>, reducing the frequency of standardized testing and empowering teachers to use authentic assessments that measure what students know and can do is a critical component to addressing the nationwide teacher shortage.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD42B6324EC174A33BED688267291FE0A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Research published by the National Academies Press shows that summative assessments are appropriate for curriculum and in-school accountability but are not appropriate when used as a dominant factor in making high-stakes decisions and can undermine the quality of education and equality of opportunity.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCA01CE0BA99A460D9D500D8BE8559D1D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The peer-reviewed Research in Middle Level Education Journal published a study in 2017 showing that State standardized test results are strongly influenced by non-school factors and that standardized test results cannot capture the complexities of the influence of middle level administrators may have on the lives of students. Nevertheless, the use of State standardized test results drove school administrator evaluations in more than 40 States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A470EC598EA49C4826942A3235E5C39"><enum>(6)</enum><text>More than 1,185 accredited, four-year colleges and universities removed ACT and SAT test score requirements for prospective applicants for the Fall 2022 semester.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6E8E6A315FDE4E928D833F13A9A4D8EC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>According to a sum of mean science, reading, and mathematics scores from the OECD Programme for International Student Assessment (in this Act referred to as <quote>PISA</quote>) results for 2018, the United States ranked 22nd out of participating countries. In mathematics, the United States ranked 36th out of the 79 participating countries and regions, which was below the international average. Throughout the high-stakes accountability era, standardized test scores in the United States have remained flat. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H692419F0ABC6489ABE97F5DE6E4F0984"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Even before the COVID–19 pandemic began, progress had stalled on the main measure of academic well-being in the United States, the National Assessment of Educational Progress (in this Act referred to as <quote>NAEP</quote>). According to the 2019 NAEP, the average performance of American fourth-and eighth-graders in math and reading has declined since the 2017 NAEP. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H56A8FD4826B44753BFF9F03443CA5DF9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>According to the National Center for Education Statistics, students demonstrating the lowest performance in reading have made no progress since the first NAEP was conducted almost 30 years ago.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5B96CCC36874CFC985D22D7251B32FF"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to the 2015 survey from the Council of the Great City Schools titled <quote>Student Testing in America’s Great City Schools: An Inventory and Preliminary Analysis</quote>, there is no correlation between the amount of mandated testing time and the reading and mathematics scores in grades four and eight on the NAEP. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H748329EEB23A4C4EBC95176714FACF85"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In the same survey from the Council of the Great City Schools, 39 percent of school districts reported having to wait between two and four months before final State test results were available at the school level, minimizing the utility of these tests for instructional purposes.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8180BEA5612D4C678A2AAC28786C3D66"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In 2015, a typical American student took 112 mandated standardized tests across the length of their elementary and secondary education years, including both federally mandated summative assessments and non-federally mandated summative assessments. Countries that outperform the United States on the PISA only test their students three times throughout the kindergarten through twelfth-grade years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA4A381EF692941DF8F00D538D3A0FCBC"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Research has shown that current testing volumes narrow curriculum to the tested topics, particularly when exams are high stakes. Other important subjects, such as art, music, finance, foreign languages, social studies, civics, and physical education are downplayed or ignored.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADC3EA9586994789A202F7CD25D897AF"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Studies show that standardized testing leads to the narrowing of instruction and classroom curriculum even within assessed subjects.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9AD075EF25834432B8FB451AE9D26DE9"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The negative impact of standardized testing extends to students, their families, and the economic well-being of their communities. The mass availability of school ratings based on standardized test scores has accelerated divergence in housing values, income distributions, and education levels as well as the racial and ethnic composition across communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29373D1C426A48CE9C0A0A4464843779"><enum>(16)</enum><text>African Americans, especially boys, are disproportionately placed or misplaced in special education, frequently based on standardized test results.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57F3A10F0164498CB29B228B265DB694"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A reduction in the administration of and preparation for mandated summative assessments would afford more time and resources for other learning opportunities that—</text> <subparagraph id="HA377AB73C48C4925BD9B8ABC6099E7C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>incorporate a diverse array of high-quality assessment methods, including formative assessments embedded within instruction, performance-based assessment, and methods to assess understanding and skill development through project-based learning; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H36AAAD00059846A68C048108A0ECEAD4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promote deeper learning, positive cognitive development, and the skills needed for the 21st century workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HD12A11E82F774FA488EA492FE82234B9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress relating to appropriate uses of summative assessments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
<paragraph id="HC69F1CE6481F40A0BF6D0C9C5535D6E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support a love of learning that fosters joy, curiosity, creativity, rigor, collaborative problem solving, and the development of 21st century skills, public elementary and secondary schools need more capacity and resources for meaningful educational experiences;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59A05E89F18649059DA27AE5F414CC5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the requirement for States to administer annual standardized tests to receive Federal funds under title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 limits classroom instruction, promotes memorization over critical thinking, and prioritizes multiple choice tests over balanced assessment systems using multiple measures that promote high-quality teaching and learning;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8091D73E721844219215B263AA6EE937"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a robust body of research demonstrates that the overuse of standardized testing takes a negative toll on students, teachers, and the classroom environment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1C162CDFE3E14236A64F9205457C7B46"><enum>(4)</enum><text>States should be supported in developing and implementing innovative, evidence-based, and standards-based assessment systems that support high-quality teaching and learning and the ability to meaningfully measure performance rather than using commercial assessment products that are limited to demonstrating proficiency to a standardized test; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1C1AC1BA51B045F2958F220A0203B9EC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>State assessment and accountability systems should—</text> <subparagraph id="H6A536CBEBBC24E8F8C4E1B6C056A286F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>focus on, not hinder, critical thinking; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H827D7AECB47B440CB13A700B0C984682"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reflect principles of reciprocity, such that identified needs and areas for growth result in the allocation of both resources and capacity building opportunities to support improvement; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9EEEE9B2EE1E4ABEA3DB7F5E8EE365DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promote equitable opportunities for high-quality teaching and deep learning on a range of academic, socioemotional, and 21st century skills.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="H20209DFFFE11405EB498F4F49131E96B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Decreasing standardized testing frequency for students in grades 3 through 12</header>
<subsection id="HDDC2BC3AF34C427F92821570ED8B3080"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expansion of State educational assessment options</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4B470E29065A4E878CE1CB1BD705437D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H27BAC8166009456BAB25EFD23551224F"><enum>(53)</enum><header>Combination testing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>combination testing</term> means an educational assessment system in which a State administers grade-span testing using—</text>
<subparagraph id="H49DE1702A75D42C5B4469168479E5472"><enum>(A)</enum><text>representative sampling; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4FE27BD3AFE47318F4304331590214C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>matrix sampling.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H831F7D0BFAB449A9BD409FAE209ECC1E" commented="no"><enum>(54)</enum><header>Grade-span testing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>grade-span testing</term> means an educational assessment system in which a State administers each of the assessments described in section 1111(b)(2)(A) once during—</text> <subparagraph id="HD2A2F5000D964110AE9B0027490F31CB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>grades 3 through 5;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD255A7CD7DD14D5790337422244E3D40" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grades 6 through 9; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2127C2260F2E457391F18AD335485BB2" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>grades 10 through 12.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5077905FCD2345F895632B96BBFCBF2C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(55)</enum><header>Matrix sampling</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>matrix sampling</term> means an educational assessment administration method in which a State—</text> <subparagraph id="H6029A73D57D94B8CAFD15FC38E4AEAE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>divides the total number of questions on an educational assessment into groups that are comprised of an equal number of questions;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF145AAD1FC5C4CD2AB91C1CDBEAFDA7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>divides the students enrolled at an elementary or secondary school who will receive such educational assessment into groups that are comprised of—</text> <clause id="H440DD32DF17F4C9797EFCCB4B7262FC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an equal number of students; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H19A039BE291A47F4B57E0F1C90D061A3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to each subgroup of students (described in section 1111(b)(2)(B)(xi)), a number of students belonging to such subgroup that is equal to the proportion of—</text> <subclause id="HCA2F597019C5445E8BC4446CE4DFAFF4" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the total number of students enrolled at such school belonging to such subgroup; to</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB78E40DEB3E94E27A5699A21EEC16FB5" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total number of students enrolled at such school; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC34B242D4F94A94923BD37ED9DB7F6D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>administers such groups of questions to such groups of students in a manner determined by the Secretary to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9467EF724C494E7AA42A7993FAA3C8CC" commented="no"><enum>(56)</enum><header>Representative sampling</header>
<subparagraph id="HC02C6F7D79434639BB5D512CFDE98010"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>representative sampling</term> means an educational assessment administration method in which a State—</text> <clause id="H1620AC31023B4930AAF08ECB0F805E44" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administers, in accordance with subparagraph (B), math, reading or language arts, and science assessments to a representative sample of students from a sample of public elementary and secondary schools in the State; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HE2C679DCC6614E0A9A5F28F2AF0BB7EE" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is able to draw from such sampling valid and reliable inferences about the performance of students—</text> <subclause id="H7031B504B5924BD3AA52606721F5FF0C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the State and in local educational agencies served by the State; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HF913766AF11A49DEBB864B53419CDBD9" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the elementary and secondary schools selected for such sampling.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H455059D28A5A48068F881B935C0339DC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sample requirements</header><text>A State shall ensure that—</text>
<clause id="HD2A6D42C984641BE97931FBEF8044049"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each assessment described in subparagraph (A)(i) is administered to a different representative sample of students; and </text></clause> <clause id="HC9CC2A438C1E4DBCBD4E5837B8FF2EFB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the composition of each such representative sample of students enables results to be disaggregated in accordance with section 1111(b)(2)(B)(xi).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HC253836525FB4FA087EA7FE97B0A3548"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State discretion concerning the frequency of standardized testing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1111(b)(2)(B) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HD26310E0248C4E2AB5662E2402C26A19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)(II)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H01FAA20A6C9142B3AEAEF9DAD1366C11"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, in accordance with clause (v), </quote> after <quote>administered</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3DB99F8C57714C89B902DCF2873E31BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>all</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A35D95631CB44E090BF4E8FB54BA86A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (v)—</text> <subparagraph id="H27B8DF5E684D41BE9C18073A9EB2B962"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending subclause (I) to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF767C170F33A4F8197B5E8445D7D00F3" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subclause id="H84A0E012B09E4141B40CA0234180C8BC" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of mathematics, reading or language arts, and science, be administered using—</text> <item id="H697B4A8E62E145EE8A6CAF59E140ADBA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>combination testing;</text></item>
<item id="HDF6DA6787F184A42ABF77ED01D3930FB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>grade-span testing; or</text></item> <item id="HDFE6D059C465440CA12A9D887E2C9360" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>representative sampling—</text>
<subitem id="H6FB927363C4042678EB93C70F91E01F0" commented="no"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>not more than once in each of grades 3 through 8; and</text></subitem> <subitem id="H9DF43A124ECA401A976E8A70D03EE570" commented="no"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>at least once in grades 9 through 12; and</text></subitem></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H971D30C787244C07BCB721D43F3C21DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subclause (II); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H94DA11214BF14B72BE72C2C0FDA783B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subclause (III) as subclause (II); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD0AA89A014F04BE096C9B81B63CA51BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in clause (vii)(I), by inserting <quote>, as applicable</quote> after <quote>students</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3C09999ACB0D4CE29BBE82B6DC858B40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Statewide accountability system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1111(c)(4) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HE54302919CB644F29767FBED24005C45"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A)(i)(I)(aa), by striking <quote>annual</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA3C7D777EF249FD85C5BA58BBC92EF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subclauses (I) and (II) of subparagraph (B)(i), by striking <quote>annual</quote> in each place it appears.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HB7AA2860812649BBB29C28520DA673DF"><enum>5.</enum><header>Public comment period regarding the administration of assessments for each grade</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1111(b)(2)(L) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(2)(L)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H93BC862E5CAF47018DF0039D9FB3C23F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>at the sole discretion of such State</quote> and inserting <quote>following a 90-day public comment period inviting input from a broad community of local stakeholders, including educators, principals, other school leaders, parents, and primary caregivers</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1EB6B0209769432D89F26CB64FDDD945"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, and preparation for,</quote> after <quote>administration of</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H40C91EA670AC4CE6AED8160C57C8B0CE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Establishing a taskforce to evaluate testing practices and to promote quality teaching</header> <subsection id="H802D287CE42A4A26B4616D2B5E297F8C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a taskforce within the National Center for Education Research to be known as the <quote>Taskforce to Evaluate Testing Practices and Promote Quality Teaching</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Taskforce</quote>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HC49041394BC24CEF857F90FD52EF35B5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> The duties of the Taskforce shall be to—</text> <paragraph id="HB666B2327D9D4C82AD5366F86C014518"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD6F2A153A4A54A18B047843A7133123D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the effect standardized test practices have on student wellness, learning, and postsecondary education success;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H07390C17FB984419986AC71F60915031"><enum>(B)</enum><text>opportunities to promote in elementary and secondary schools performance-based assessment systems that are developmentally appropriate, promote experiential and project-based learning, and build technological literacy skills;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC18088577598413D9EC6D0E23C795DE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>potential metrics of educational quality and equity that do not rely on standardized assessments, including opportunity-to-learn data; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB44211512CD45F0A5E38204B75A72A6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>barriers that prevent elementary and secondary schools from establishing innovative assessment systems; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC7AFBBBA303F459A8E43EE97D8093DE2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make recommendations to address such barriers.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3F4B0CA25FD744A49B06D8A0A81C5AD2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header> <paragraph id="HBE7EFDEBE1D8413280B780C081C16C27"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner for Education Research shall appoint to the Taskforce not fewer than 5, and not more than 10, members.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD129E8D6F92423A838DFA9DDAFF5AD0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of educational assessment experts</header><text>At least 1 member shall be an individual with expertise in education assessment systems, including performance-based assessments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32B613D248E349069116D2561F208395"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>Each member shall be appointed for a term of 2 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEA72ECAE0AC140BEB9D014B430BF6D50"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Basic Pay</header><text>Members shall each be paid at a rate equal to the rate of basic pay for level IV of the Executive Schedule.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H435B180319EE4CE88D3FDE4B03748E26"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy in the Taskforce shall be filled by an appointment of a new member by the Director (as described in subsection (d)) in consultation with—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7EA528FBC4BB40C78938D6CBAA3400A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>public elementary school teachers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H927A38A5E77944B99D868B2F7A425959"><enum>(B)</enum><text>public secondary school teachers;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H553E8175C67F46EA9DE51BBD09B0CCBB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>public school leaders; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7208AEC68544439CA82A3195A488CAD3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>individuals representing organizations with expertise in education policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3F1FF63ED5B045B288A7EF9E7A10BC51"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Director of Taskforce</header><text>The Taskforce shall have a Director who shall be appointed by the Commissioner, in consultation with—</text> <paragraph id="H4242E3DB13DB4AF488A5C0C7462B28F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text> public elementary school teachers;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDE673417A3124ACCAC873F6328E5311D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>public secondary school teachers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0E0412DDED0E4B5FB7E9ED2BD378AED2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>public school leaders;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA02D35421336423C9D3AB1806C2F59CC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>school-based mental health services providers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB6490D1AF6C84ACF9F862DEB2DA99AEE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>individuals representing organizations with expertise in education policy.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H974FD5E266F04F57B792BAEA1F0E25C5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report Required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Commissioner completes all appointments to the Taskforce required under subsection (c)(1), the Taskforce shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text> <paragraph id="HB1B5DEFE0A014B058099DAF1AC4B4E13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a review, disaggregated by each State, of assessments administered to students in kindergarten through grade 12 that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD1EC348053AC49A2A313A7F2E5306245"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of each summative assessment the State used, including assessments developed pursuant to the innovative assessment demonstration authority under section 1204 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6364">20 U.S.C. 6364</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA3472916E21544248662B324CE22AA86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an estimation of the cost of administering each such assessment;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H811E010670B748CB91872CD641D7C6EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an estimation, for each grade, of the test administration time allocated each academic year for such assessments; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B193C93E36041A79D26E6D28317E93E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an estimation, for each grade, of the classroom instructional time lost each academic year while preparing students for each such assessment; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H334C7A2957EC425D8A6B41D83253A653"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how each State is using data from such assessments, including whether such data is used for punitive purposes;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9873E9E0710940368DCF7A4F6A454B96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an accounting of Federal, State, and local funds paid to for-profit entities for the purpose of designing, developing, administering, and scoring summative assessments;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE2EF16D3FA0A46C3AF5CA1FCD6BD61D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a study of the interaction between statewide summative assessment and accountability systems, as implemented as of the date of the beginning of the report required under this subsection, and the quality of teaching and learning, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H47DF256B15CF478CB70A99C057539C4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which statewide summative assessments are aligned to 21st century skill development;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1839E46F40A44984A5140E508475A1D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the extent to which such assessment and accountability systems lead to a narrowing of curriculum; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H19CBE3EB1AF445679C67F9AF1BB148B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of such assessment and accountability systems on the quality of instruction and opportunities for deeper learning across a variety of subjects and skills;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF0A634961374401AAED6953C27BE3774"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of barriers that prevent schools from establishing and implementing innovative assessment systems that promote performance-based assessment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H047E178698D44D458049A69728531A43"><enum>(5)</enum><text>recommendations to overcome such barriers; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5CCCCA3C33E740A79DE1A06A18176594"><enum>(6)</enum><text>recommendations for innovative assessment systems that—</text> <subparagraph id="H645C7177733946B483B27CD40F09F234"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are created in partnership with teachers and other educators;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5FD9D76730C64F18A3034E8182A9C501"><enum>(B)</enum><text>empower teachers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1B364D0FDDF4FF280E9FFF1185685F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reduce elementary and secondary school reliance upon summative assessment tools from for-profit third-party vendors; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H083DDD98286D4F39964FE3ED620A6532"><enum>(D)</enum><text>create a framework for designing a balanced assessment system that supports equitable opportunities for learning and centers students’ needs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1F823AA2048542288855CD43233DF93A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Expiration of Taskforce</header><text>The Taskforce shall expire on the date that is 30 days after the date of the submission of the report required under subsection (d).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4D815BD6CEFD45A5B727C29B25ED5EC0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HD9B1E51ACD604372AFE73DDAA6A4F385"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6793514A88A0436D829FAA915353166B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committees on Appropriations of the Senate and House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8B95299F2C045F2BFDA6E0EE07E78F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H20A9A5970056499FB43A4064445A3711"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4342142EBADE4CAB9F4FC74F86C24AB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header> <subparagraph id="H1981173E516F494DB6BE90A2ED820FA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>school leader</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD28FC1CCE3584F7DA48277736DED0BFF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>innovative assessment system</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1204(a) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6364">20 U.S.C. 6364(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1805437B990E42CB88832C305502901B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>school-based mental health services provider</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4102 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7112">20 U.S.C. 7112</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H739938170BFD40DFBEC57380B5E7BA9C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Expansion of innovative assessment demonstration authority</header>
<subsection id="HAF60AE450E0241FFB205A8B32E282B4E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expansion of authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1204 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC8AA67E1F626488F8EE3FE6268E741EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking <quote>an annual</quote> and inserting <quote>a</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5986A63BC65E4E8D9F2EF5F9E55A62F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H6419C50061D544AD9BF1BF15C6EEAE50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>5 years</quote> and inserting <quote>7 years</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB21D5B4685814C1D90DA46DDB1C41126"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <clause id="HF962F93E0A46406B9733BD8C138F312C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>3 years</quote> and inserting <quote>5 years</quote>; and </text></clause>
<clause id="H044A4DDA02DD4ACB957FEEA1EEC0504E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>a total number of not more than 7 participating State educational agencies</quote> and inserting <quote>a total number of not fewer than 20 participating State educational agencies</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61144EDCF45144758DA7E9491886090B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2)(A)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCDF0ED2585FF4EDC88872481871CB667"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (x)—</text> <clause id="H56FD4176C58947CDBD4E19E6535F0155"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an annual, </quote> and inserting <quote>a</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="H776B660C24764BEEAF5D1A6677F19E6E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>assessed in a given subject in a given year</quote> after <quote>each individual student</quote>; and </text></clause> <clause id="H0E7913AFAC6845D184F8B4F6A42839C4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC2E6ECF4FEB64D419F30D77C36679154"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (xi)(II), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4EE3F2D2A736404DB5474EE46EE305CC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3B839791EA30402FA317AA27F0D0D7F9" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<clause id="H42CBC138070E4A9D8F8FD1900EFA57E9"><enum>(xii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be of equal or greater rigor to the State assessments under section 1111(b)(2).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA4F1B21FEB64D1B91C99031C2086C62"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(1)(B)(i), by striking <quote>comparable to the State assessments</quote> and inserting <quote>determined by the Secretary to be of equal or greater rigor to the State assessments</quote>; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H600ED44A59EF49FFB3A03923AD53A36E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (i)(3), by striking <quote>comparable to measures of academic achievement</quote> and inserting <quote>determined by the Secretary to be of equal or greater rigor to measures of academic achievement</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CE8FFAF2DD84343A2FAD6612A0433F2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (m)(1)(A)(ii), by striking <quote>comparable with statewide assessments</quote> and inserting <quote>determined by the Secretary to be of equal or greater rigor to statewide assessments</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE318809B313A43D883804AF99117F8E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Education $100,000,000 for the fiscal year in which the date of the enactment of this Act occurs, and for each of the 4 succeeding fiscal years, to carry out section 1204 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6364">20 U.S.C. 6364</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H1D9A020296BB4DF88A62966CEA26B817"><enum>8.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for local educational agency grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1002(a) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6302">20 U.S.C. 6302(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD46FFE69D2A645798E7EBAE572B8F9C2" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HDF66763344444A7E9140C6108EF6581C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Local educational agency grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated $66,000,000,000 for the fiscal year in which the date of the enactment of the <short-title>More Teaching Less Testing Act of 2023</short-title> occurs, and for each of the 9 succeeding fiscal years, to carry out the activities described in part A.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HEC1B5277415A4786BE90E66FFF17D3DD"><enum>9.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of ESEA funds for certain purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State receiving funds under the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6301">20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq.</external-xref>) may not—</text>
<paragraph id="HB79B09CFA0D04FCA93EEDD1A1B729536"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider the summative assessments required under section 1111(b)(2) of such Act as a sole or dominant factor when—</text> <subparagraph id="H823E0AD6D9AC4C6EA52BF764C914A28D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>implementing grade-retention policies;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC1D131D6C7A546DEBC85B677F6F2EFCD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>awarding a student a high school diploma; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H577D9ED9841D4021AEB4098DD1A747CD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evaluating the performance of teachers or administrators;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF20811DADEC24FA1BB879B686FFF05CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a rating system for elementary schools or local educational agencies that serve such elementary schools based exclusively on the summative assessment scores of students who attend such elementary schools; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BCF4078634B43A1AF9A9EB342EA19D5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establish a rating system for secondary schools or local educational agencies that serve such secondary schools based exclusively on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H41DD8FED82B9463D91B1B9877ECB3202"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the summative assessment scores of students that attend such secondary schools; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB6CB6BE924774419BC9AE1F544F88D46"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the graduation rates of students that attend such secondary schools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


