<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79CCCA9365E5422CA50F42A17CDD56BC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5132 IH: United Against Transnational Criminal Organizations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5132</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To bolster Department of Homeland Security efforts to combat cross-border threats posed by transnational criminal organizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H75FCD306D52F4DB8BDA9942AA46BC585" style="OLC"><section id="H1B0AD54E20DC46DA8BDA3848C870B0DA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United Against Transnational Criminal Organizations Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD0C7D3020ECC4F7DAE5118FE72AFA3A9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Bolstering DHS efforts to combat cross-border threats posed by transnational criminal organizations</header><subsection id="HDD3995025DC04B5B9684C19BEA1441B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>DHS Joint Task Force</header><paragraph id="H71BF474101BF49539E2C4900E04F5329"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b)(11) of section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/348">6 U.S.C. 348</external-xref>), not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall, pursuant to such section, establish a Department of Homeland Security Joint Task Force to conduct operations using personnel and capabilities of the Department to combat cross-border threats posed by transnational criminal organizations operating along the land borders of the United States for the purpose specified in clause (i) of subsection (b)(2)(A) of such section. Such task force shall—</text><subparagraph id="H44CC91DD781246D18F5B7B5A2ACA1B9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pay particular attention to transnational criminal organizations that target foreign nationals, particularly children and families, for smuggling or trafficking across the land border of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8783DBF727CA45F095741989F0B91170"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when appropriate, refer to the Attorney General for prosecution border-related criminal activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H522044DC7D074C04A7652369C5D40708"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The task force established in accordance with paragraph (1) may, when appropriate, refer to the Attorney General for prosecution border-related criminal activity, and shall pay particular attention to transnational criminal organizations that—</text><subparagraph id="H148F1B5A0E1849BE87866B0E51EFB15A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">target people, particularly children and families, for smuggling or trafficking across the land borders of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC789496181B4D39A235E7F338C5E386" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are engaged in the smuggling or trafficking of fentanyl, fentanyl chemical precursors, or related equipment and material across the land borders of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD87345799EE42B1BD72C9C5F7FD817C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Performance metrics</header><text>Consistent with subsection (b)(9) of section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish and submit to the appropriate congressional committees performance metrics to evaluate the effectiveness of the Joint Task Force established pursuant to paragraph (1). Such performance metrics shall include outcome-based metrics associated with efforts to achieve the priorities described in paragraph (2), including information on effectiveness at identifying transnational criminal organizations engaged in such activity, the sharing of information regarding such organizations, efforts to dismantle or disrupt such activity by such organizations, and investigative contributions to the prosecution of such organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C89EC8384E44251AE413BB0FF9256E6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Quarterly reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than four months after the establishment of the Joint Task Force pursuant to paragraph (1) and every four months thereafter until such Joint Task Force is disbanded by the Secretary in accordance with paragraph (4), the Director of such Joint Task Force shall report to the appropriate congressional committees on the activities of such Joint Task Force during the preceding four-month period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H551BB007914F46EBA73324BD553E992E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Disbanding of Joint Task Force</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text><subparagraph id="H1B66FA4A140C4B31A0649D8903DEE4C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>upon establishment of the Joint Task Force pursuant to paragraph (1), report to the appropriate congressional committees the criteria to be applied by the Secretary before making a determination to disband such Joint Task Force; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF46AB2F46A0B4098B241AD588B035392"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 15 days prior to disbanding such Joint Task Force, submit to such committees a justification relating thereto.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7D6B535BA9449ABBBB2F1AEA4CD3E00"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the committees specified in subparagraph (F) of section 708(b)(6) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3249497225FB422E82AC600287224E0C" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transnational criminal organization border screening strategy</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall issue a strategy to improve the effectiveness of the screening of vehicles, persons, and cargo at land ports of entry that may be at higher risk of being related to transnational criminal organization activity. Upon issuance of such strategy, the Secretary shall brief the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate regarding such strategy.</text></subsection><subsection id="H524AB85AC39B4423AD0D0F3618210858" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Integrated border intelligence analytical cell</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish within the National Targeting Center of U.S. Customs and Border Protection an integrated border intelligence analytical cell focused on sharing information regarding potential concentrated surges of migrants arriving at the land borders of the United States, and smuggling or trafficking that may pose a border security, homeland security, or other threat to the land borders of the United States. Such cell shall integrate intelligence capabilities from across the Department of Homeland Security to carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="HE0FBA55C06794C35BFD5FFE9BF282608" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Develop intelligence products to improve the Department’s ability to track, prepare for, and manage in a humane and effective manner concentrated surges of migrants arriving along the land border of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58B046D775A14D698F3CC86267C829D7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report on transnational criminal organizations exploiting migrating populations and migration routes to smuggle or traffic fentanyl or other illicit goods across the land border of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H525D967E95924682AC3A5FD9FEE43926" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Support Federal efforts to dismantle or disrupt smuggling and trafficking routes along the land border of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F23B2BB03784032B85D06ACDA6899B6" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Report on information circulated by transnational criminal organizations and other malicious actors to encourage illicit migrant travel to the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1B86BD6C8A443FB7B092385656492C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Develop other related intelligence products that support the Department’s border security operations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H49EBCC49011049B898F04FFA998CCA0E" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Strengthening cross-Border partnerships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Secretary of State, shall expand partnership efforts with law enforcement entities in Canada, Mexico, countries in Central America and South America, and other appropriate countries to combat smuggling and trafficking of people, fentanyl, fentanyl chemical precursors, or related equipment and material within such countries, including through the following:</text><paragraph id="H24A91D024213437799D9475295F8D526" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Expansion of transnational criminal investigative units to identify, disrupt, dismantle, and prosecute transnational criminal organization activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF50976445B274F789F83BD71F6669025" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Participation in the Bilateral Human Trafficking Enforcement Initiative by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the Department of Justice with their Mexican law enforcement counterparts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86AB7AE5E1FD4A3F9C319AF27524EF1F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Expansion of advanced training programs for investigators and prosecutors from Canada, Mexico, countries in Central America and South America, and other appropriate countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B7A330A943D40FB92A31BFA4AD9B39C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Increase of capacity-building efforts to support international partners in improving the ability of such partners to detect and interdict fentanyl, fentanyl chemical precursors, and related equipment and material originating from or transiting through their territories.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE008051C156E42AB89199909922C3414"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Fentanyl interdiction and supply chain disruption</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall seek to strengthen intelligence sharing operations with Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial agencies involved in prevention, detection, and interdiction of fentanyl, fentanyl chemical precursors, and other related equipment and material to enhance efforts to disrupt and dismantle supply chains for such illicit drugs and equipment and material.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

