<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Enrolled-Bill" dms-id="HF32E2340A315499CA8D40C4C02CDAE2F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title> HR 366 ENR: Korean American Vietnam Allies Long Overdue for Relief Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">One Hundred Eighteenth Congress of the United States of America</congress><session display="yes">At the First Session</session><enrolled-dateline>Begun and held at the City of Washington on Tuesday, the third day of January, two thousand and twenty-three</enrolled-dateline> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 366</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no"></current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to treat certain individuals who served in Vietnam as a member of the armed forces of the Republic of Korea as a veteran of the Armed Forces of the United States for purposes of the provision of health care by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H55BB0308297B4DB6B502246106B90AFE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H994BE955468E4DCC8AE6B08245D6147A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Korean American Vietnam Allies Long Overdue for Relief Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Korean American VALOR Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1581393D709745FB96C3BD2315F1D95D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Provision of certain benefits to individuals who served in the armed forces of the Republic of Korea</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 109 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC86A329C488F4CB9A6E6BF37AB06C9BC" style="USC"> 
<subsection id="H8133AC1968034301B1AFF01DDDA56473"><enum>(d)</enum> 
<paragraph id="H2D41CC98FBA644B084E6854841910D60" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any person described in paragraph (2) is eligible for the benefits specified in subsection (a) to the same extent and under the same conditions (including with respect to applicable reciprocity requirements) as a discharged member of the armed forces of a government specified in such subsection who is eligible for such benefits under such subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1DBA3A2A234F4264A1602BE32CC885AC" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person described in this paragraph is a person whom the Secretary determines served in Vietnam as a member of the armed forces of the Republic of Korea at any time during the period beginning on January 9, 1962, and ending on May 7, 1975, or such other period as determined appropriate by the Secretary for purposes of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><role>Speaker of the House of Representatives.</role></attestation-group><attestation-group><role>Vice President of the United States and President of the Senate.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
</bill> 


