<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H49B082DF56D24133AEA24D5614A5ADD2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3560 IH: National Drone and Advanced Air Mobility Research and Development Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3560</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000491">Mr. Lucas</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for coordinated Federal efforts to accelerate civilian unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility research and development for economic and national security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8DB53747C8244825A97F8E33FCF234B6" style="OLC"><section id="HB3ACFCF62016471DAB3D3E326C8A5126" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H7527873E1F264F6C86F015FA08CD0DC4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Drone and Advanced Air Mobility Research and Development Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAF77618ACE5E4358B6D2974DF957F7B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HB3ACFCF62016471DAB3D3E326C8A5126" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9836659620194AE5B76107D178C68ED7" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB8B974CF89C74698B6D372862C5ED2D7" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H44D54D737E294CC1AADF52E6A3398622" level="section">Sec. 4. Purposes.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD8CAF6A2D764482396B1A18121ACD773" level="title">Title I —Interagency Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2C626893065C4716B575F0C4B5B10AF6" level="section">Sec. 101. Interagency working group.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9A63EC1DB72B43219CF353A0023A71B5" level="section">Sec. 102. Strategic research plan.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2968F99292A04F5CB4F4203D30A1379A" level="section">Sec. 103. Counter-UAS research plan.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2E09B58C340A4E7BB4C0D6AC447262E0" level="section">Sec. 104. National drone technology center.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4889C59AD3314AE3BD88934D07A1189E" level="section">Sec. 105. GAO study on foreign drones.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9D50EFFFE8964D6E895F7DEC40353886" level="title">Title II—National Drone and Advanced Air Mobility Research Institutes</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA6899A6DE8984E9EBF43334A95A0E898" level="section">Sec. 201. National drone and advanced air mobility research institutes.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9D9E0ABFA57E4F7697F46D12CD3718F2" level="title">Title III—National Institute of Standards and Technology Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5F62F8F3B50D473C8E6B4DA113E68BB3" level="section">Sec. 301. National Institute of Standards and Technology activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE4C2B74EE283418B971BFEAD8938A0E6" level="section">Sec. 302. National Institute of Standards and Technology manufacturing activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF74F8ADB004048E7ACDFEE4403D8404E" level="title">Title IV—National Science Foundation Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2F08696FC9E84B3FB7182C2F6BB6A5D5" level="section">Sec. 401. National Science Foundation activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2BB2176C9B444EB88D9DC1EA51F541D6" level="title">Title V—National Aeronautics and Space Administration Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1B06384B09FA49D786E703CB62BDCD11" level="section">Sec. 501. National Aeronautics and Space Administration activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4B0D84839818426ABA807E1384ACB048" level="section">Sec. 502. National student unmanned aircraft systems competition program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H51D5A81EF6BB480888DCFE883F2DC3DE" level="title">Title VI—Department of Energy Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2CEA5522756F45EF8D7B9B682AD230B4" level="section">Sec. 601. Department of Energy research program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD025DA6A26584378B6AF7675CCDB14D8" level="title">Title VII—Department of Homeland Security Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H08F37563A2FB42DF93F1B0C1755B71EC" level="section">Sec. 701. Department of Homeland Security activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H977642080B7945C5A9DC225750C40916" level="title">Title VIII—National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H570B364FF731412CAD548D741A43C9EC" level="section">Sec. 801. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0431FBC4A92E4E918C58A7F9E9557B24" level="title">Title IX—Federal Aviation Administration Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H377282197F8E4F138B5C9FBE55F4B785" level="section">Sec. 901. Federal Aviation Administration research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9B363C5AEC4049C8AF5155B7C8586AAC" level="section">Sec. 902. University unmanned aircraft systems and advance air mobility centers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDDB4B27B32EF46D8B7CDE12E7DA7F875" level="section">Sec. 903. Allowance for the purposes of research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H904AD334D709440D954DC70F8B642BC3" level="section">Sec. 904. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDBFEFACBB8DC4C55B54B22A8C94E3673" level="title">Title X—Limitation</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H941EF5AAD95E4A4CB136FCC620702E01" level="section">Sec. 1001. Limitation.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H9836659620194AE5B76107D178C68ED7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H1A863E14EA2347BEA3519BE5BA77EC23"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Unmanned aircraft systems have the potential to change and transform sectors of the United States economy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD82A87C6957445AA2160F31C85151A7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Advanced air mobility aims to transform the way people and goods are transported through new capabilities and applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8E6877C4B714CE7BD0712AD05F37174"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Current uses and applications of unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility include agriculture, transportation, law enforcement, public safety, disaster evaluation and response, fire detection, border security, weather forecasting, construction, utility monitoring, and many other uses and applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA95A97A451F4401DBD07DCBB34ADA975"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Research, development, demonstration, testing, and evaluation of counter-UAS systems and detection systems activities are critical to fully understand the capabilities of and threats posed by unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE9F5659284B48C5B7045B78600827CC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility systems are subject to safety, privacy, cybersecurity, and supply chain risks, particularly as most unmanned aircraft systems in the United States are manufactured or assembled from parts manufactured in foreign countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87A0908E03234F668962F758A2CAE8D9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>National and homeland security threats posed by unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility systems include criminal and terrorist use for espionage, surveillance, and intelligence gathering, smuggling drugs and contraband, and platforms to deliver explosives or chemicals, biological, radiological or nuclear weapons, and other firearms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1456C86E91CE48D997BE2E67367D9C3F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Federal Government has an important role in advancing research, development, voluntary consensus technical standards, and education activities in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technologies through coordination and collaboration between State, local, Federal, and Tribal governments, academia, and the private sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9D76FFA9A3C440CAF55EB36A3AF0AF3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>There is a lack of voluntary consensus technical standards for unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility for academia and the public and private sectors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEF16C9977FF44AEAA4C735FD78B1305"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States needs to invest in domestic manufacturing and secure supply chains of unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility systems to meet the demand by the Government and the commercial sectors, to reduce reliance on foreign-made systems.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB8B974CF89C74698B6D372862C5ED2D7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H1C2615BD2FC64BA7B2DDBAC1A8827E94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced air mobility</header><text>The term <quote>advanced air mobility</quote> means a transportation system that transports people and property by air between two points in the United States using aircraft with advanced technologies, including electric aircraft or electric vertical take-off and landing aircraft, in both controlled and uncontrolled airspace.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9917C5CA8F8F462F9A275EA152ADF03B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Counter-UAS system</header><text>The term <quote>counter-UAS system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 44801(5) of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41334E41E2EF493EAA364C752845E8DA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institute</header><text>The term <quote>Institute</quote> means a Drone and Advanced Air Mobility Research Institute described in section 201(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3401C2A2B764B26BA5FEF6E275A347B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Interagency working group</header><text>The term <quote>Interagency Working Group</quote> means the Advanced Air Mobility and Unmanned Aircraft Systems Interagency Working Group of the National Science and Technology Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D83A976F5524977BDE48BC5F1E75782"><enum>(5)</enum><header>National laboratory</header><text>The term <quote>National Laboratory</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC623C5A3253B4BAFAEED00FF15383864"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Tribal government</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>tribal government</quote> in section 421 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 ( <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/658">2 U.S.C. 658</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AE390AD2B8D4F23A85C10A1DAFDA620"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The term <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 44801(12) of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H44D54D737E294CC1AADF52E6A3398622"><enum>4.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to ensure United States leadership in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, and maximize benefits and mitigate risks of such systems by—</text><paragraph id="H842CE3E8098443AC84DEF6D369487573"><enum>(1)</enum><text>supporting research, development, demonstration, testing, and transition to operations of secure advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems, including research and development to accelerate integration of such systems into the National Airspace System;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A728A36684646709A2AD8003BDE12CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improving the interagency planning and coordination of Federal research and development of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and maximizing the effectiveness of the Federal Government’s advanced air mobility and next generation unmanned aircraft systems research and development programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84571DFA0EEF48D9B254581F286BC341"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promoting research and development collaboration among the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, National Laboratories, industry, and academic institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9459C31C6BCE42D380E94639BB91573E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>promoting domestic manufacturing of unmanned aircraft systems and mitigating supply chain risks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB829F6316E89421697D4C5BC0AADD0A9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>supporting activities to mitigate risks to public safety and national security and homeland security, including through response to disasters;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3DA5EFDAB0F4A34A6B1EC7BC9C2C248"><enum>(6)</enum><text>preparing the present and future United States workforce for the integration of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems across sectors of the economy, including through support for curriculum development and research opportunities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6ECBDF75BAF45059906118882E027B7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>supporting research, development, demonstration, and testing of civilian applications of unmanned aerial systems, including improved safety and sustainability of ground transportation, environmental monitoring, and disaster response;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H573CE1CCEFBA4DCDA04DFF7064D12340"><enum>(8)</enum><text>promoting research and development collaboration among the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, National Laboratories, industry, and academic institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59579BF324A34AC0989EDC93641D3264"><enum>(9)</enum><text>promoting the development of voluntary consensus technical standards and best practices for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H101FC0DE38E14209BB217520A09CC027"><enum>(5)</enum><text>applying lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HD8CAF6A2D764482396B1A18121ACD773"><enum>I </enum><header>Interagency Activities</header><section id="H2C626893065C4716B575F0C4B5B10AF6"><enum>101.</enum><header>Interagency working group</header><subsection id="H8970AEBEBC984B84A573DA4096C61328"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><paragraph id="H25C595C14B3A46EAA0FF525727A7646F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The National Science and Technology Council shall establish an interagency working group on advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems to coordinate Federal research, development, deployment, testing, and education activities to enable the advancement of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H913F14BC0DC44DDD9D121219BAA303B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The interagency working group shall be comprised of senior representatives from the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the Department of Transportation, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the National Science Foundation, the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and such other Federal agencies as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDFDB6A76ED746EE9AC234B3D76BBA84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The interagency working group shall—</text><paragraph id="H4D98A7610FAA4DF8BB24804A5BE82140" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop a strategic research plan to guide Federal research to enable advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and oversee implementation of the plan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8038753072774EAFB455E4E05816371C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>oversee the ongoing development of—</text><subparagraph id="H0D1BF6D398EE450B95BA179264A11D48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the current state of United States competitiveness and leadership in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, including the scope and scale of United States investments in relevant research and development; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69895A5F70794C5695548F5AB46F64EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strategies to strengthen and secure the domestic supply chain for advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H126173C6428049A19DDBFA10510DBC44"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitate communication and outreach opportunities with academia, industry, professional societies, the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, and other stakeholders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H811BA19AA3D74D46B125E20D5D0FB0E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>facilitate partnerships to leverage knowledge and resources from industry, the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, National Laboratories, Unmanned Aircraft Systems Test Sites, academic institutions, and others;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ADC99C3A8E34CB18C32D96115D1A3AB" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>coordinate with the Advanced Air Mobility Working Group and heads of other Federal departments and agencies to avoid duplication of research and other activities to ensure the activities carried out by the interagency working group are complementary to those being undertaken by other interagency efforts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H009CC3EE44074C1E9F8D45AAD2E04786"><enum>(6)</enum><text>coordinate with the National Security Council and other authorized agency coordinating bodies on the assessment of risks posed by the existing Federal unmanned aircraft systems fleet and outlining potential steps to mitigate such risks.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB0AC17FCB8F14B85BFF862348D29F0F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><paragraph id="HCD65D99C2216410F8202D29965A1C42B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the interagency working group shall transmit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HAE0C6958234D47FEAEAEE990579679BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes a summary of federally funded advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development, deployment, and testing activities, including the budget for each of these activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18395F0C7EAF438EA6FED5999EB545ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describes the progress in developing the plan required under section 102 of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7610546B1A34470B04443059ACC5F3F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Biennial report</header><text>Not later than two years after the delivery of the initial report under paragraph (1) and biennially thereafter until December 31, 2033, the interagency working group shall transmit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H5873BB2EACCF4A7F858F45B5B94996AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of federally funded advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development, deployment, and testing activities, including the budget for each of such activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18B98AE818954F84A43A52C419736F98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an analysis of the progress made towards achieving the goals and priorities for the interagency research plan developed by the interagency working group under sections 102 and 103.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E23F7895F1411ABA98E133F9EC4DA3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Strategic research plan</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the interagency working group shall transmit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate the strategic research plan developed under section 102.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9A63EC1DB72B43219CF353A0023A71B5"><enum>102.</enum><header>Strategic research plan</header><subsection id="H7BEB3D1EC6F54EE388E7FBFCCB441CB8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the interagency working group shall develop and periodically update, as appropriate, a strategic plan for Federal research, development, deployment, and testing of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems. In developing the plan, the interagency working group shall consider and use information, reports, and studies on advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems that have identified research, development, deployment, and testing needed, and recommendations made by the National Academy of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine in the review of the plan under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H89BAADD1A7964679B2EAFB8FAC9654B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of the plan</header><text>The plan shall—</text><paragraph id="H886C420F88644B5AAA7440E8B56CC3D1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine and prioritize areas of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing requiring Federal Government leadership and investment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H987416E00F8B46EDB204E1D975F046B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish, for the 10-year period beginning in the year the plan is submitted, the goals and priorities for Federal research, development, deployment, and testing which will—</text><subparagraph id="H9D8C4127E4C94EE598E69FCA2B0CA1EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support the development of advanced air mobility technologies and the development of an advanced air mobility research, innovation, and manufacturing ecosystem;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H866C51F795C647079904E471E61A629A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide sustained, consistent, and coordinated support for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development, and demonstration, including through grants, cooperative agreements, testbeds, and testing facilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C173DB4732B4D4A817052C55DA28F67"><enum>(C)</enum><text>apply lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD948EC8B8A147FAB3610A340F6F8A5A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support the development of voluntary consensus technical standards and best practices for the development and use of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB34E045266304B5D934ABB312F7CE835"><enum>(E)</enum><text>support education and training activities at all levels to prepare the United States workforce to use and interact with advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3AE0832CEF0497A9C50B5D14D9A62C5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>support partnerships to leverage knowledge and resources from industry, the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, National Laboratories, Unmanned Aircraft Systems Test Ranges, academic institutions, and others to advance research activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1000D699CD7742A3ABE8427A6F7BE894"><enum>(G)</enum><text>leverage existing Federal investments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6B0AC6CEE2C437A9FA85A6AE4966DE7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>promote hardware inoperability, open-source systems, and standards-driven hardware;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07B40F6018664AC5BF4AC119ADD4995B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support research and other activities on the impacts of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems on national security, safety, economic, legal, workforce, and other appropriate societal issues;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD467B6482888405585E47B3DE241FAB8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>reduce barriers to transferring research findings, capabilities, and new technologies related to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems from the laboratory into operation for the benefit of society and United States competitiveness;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEF456AA278B44E6A90E2060FD73E5D3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in consultation with the Council of Economic Advisers, measure and track the contributions of unmanned aircraft systems to United States economic growth and other societal indicators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCE032E0A3734D538588531D1C347C84"><enum>(6)</enum><text>identify relevant programs and make recommendations for the coordination of relevant activities of the Federal agencies and set forth the role of each Federal agency in implementing the plan; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49BC5700705345078C92589A8EAF41D3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>consider and utilize, as appropriate, reports and studies conducted by Federal agencies, the National Research Council, or other entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H602B40970F2F4D1A802F50490F7C96A7" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine review</header><text>The interagency working group under section 101 shall enter into an agreement with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to review the plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="H301EB05C9E074187BB211F146F6DCA1C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the plan, the interagency working group shall consult with representatives of academic, State, industry, local, Tribal, and other stakeholder groups. Not later than 90 days before the plan, or any revision thereof, is submitted to Congress, the plan shall be published in the Federal Register for a public comment period of not fewer than 60 days.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2968F99292A04F5CB4F4203D30A1379A"><enum>103.</enum><header>Counter-UAS research plan</header><subsection id="H9D715C9DEE5242E582768A16BF8667F7" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the interagency working group shall develop and periodically update, as appropriate, a strategic plan for Federal research, development, evaluation, and testing of counter-UAS systems, as consistent with current counter-UAS systems legal authorities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3930B04A312448F096C380CF2649FFD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of the plan</header><text>The plan shall—</text><paragraph id="H29970D303BDB48DE9227ECC1ACE1ABFC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine and prioritize areas of counter-UAS systems research, development, evaluation, and testing requiring Federal Government leadership and investment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9DC26BFAC0E474784196A7A9F85CE02"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish, for the 10-year period beginning in the year the plan is submitted, the goals and priorities for Federal research, development, evaluation, and testing which will—</text><subparagraph id="HC5874B2E2A0340F6B2B618FFB9A9DFD1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support the development of counter-UAS technologies and the development of a counter-UAS systems research, innovation, and manufacturing ecosystem;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1F4300D20704E5E821B043F5FDC2FFB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide sustained, consistent, and coordinated support for counter-UAS systems research, development, and evaluation, including through grants, cooperative agreements, testbeds, and testing facilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6BE7C14281B4DB68A2F07D9B47779DB" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support education and training activities to prepare the United States workforce to use and interact with counter-UAS systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E54E507391C42549767EFB8FA54660A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support partnerships to leverage knowledge and resources from industry, the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, National Laboratories, Counter-UAS Test Ranges, academic institutions, and others to advance research activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DED02BE6AB04567828CE833728C1625"><enum>(E)</enum><text>leverage existing Federal investments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A880F29F39742B4BD1BB8E6E40C8D26"><enum>(F)</enum><text>promote hardware inoperability, open-source systems, and standards-driven hardware;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE26F10E415A4A578B2D32A83DF6E8E1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support research and other activities on the impacts of counter-UAS systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71B5336A9EEA45FA80C80DEDE4C04911" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in consultation with the Council of Economic Advisers, measure and track the contributions of counter-UAS systems to United States economic growth and other societal indicators; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA6200BDAAD44AAA844CD549A78794AE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify relevant programs and make recommendations for the coordination of relevant activities of the Federal agencies and set forth the role of each Federal agency in implementing the plan.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2E09B58C340A4E7BB4C0D6AC447262E0"><enum>104.</enum><header>National drone technology center</header><subsection id="HE5E1B22A38AF41FDA70996C74955844B" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary of Commerce, in collaboration with the Secretary of Defense, may establish a national drone technology center to conduct research and development of unmanned aircraft systems to strengthen the economic competitiveness and security of the domestic supply chain. Such center shall be operated as a public-private sector consortium with participation from the private sector and the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></subsection><subsection id="H539D99E040A54884BFB7C58EDCBF1D1F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The functions of the center established under subsection (a) shall be to conduct research and development related to unmanned aircraft systems manufacturing, design and components, and prototyping that strengthens the entire domestic ecosystem and places emphasis on the following:</text><paragraph id="H4E4F041D7E6E44CB8B9C2AACADC1747A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Unmanned aircraft systems advanced testing and assembly capability in the domestic ecosystem.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA94A1DCBD2B24846B7FD7F70239AA70D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Materials characterization, instrumentation and testing for unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1D0E8A5EC6A4572A23C1B9FBEBF93AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Virtualization and automation of maintenance of unmanned aircraft systems machinery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC359C8C8888244E5B820B3CC00E104B0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Metrology for security and supply chain verification.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4889C59AD3314AE3BD88934D07A1189E"><enum>105.</enum><header>GAO study on foreign drones</header><subsection id="H17DBD70589264C05A35AD9EB1C622885"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on the use of foreign-made unmanned aircraft systems in the Federal Government unmanned aircraft fleet.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2C746E2D8BD04824BC001AB16D632A14"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study under subsection (a) shall include an assessment of the following:</text><paragraph id="H9FCCE92DA48B476C821E19F2CF16DA24"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The size of the Federal unmanned aircraft fleet and the extent to which any unmanned aircraft systems and components have been procured from a covered foreign entity on the list maintained in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A053A9B60934ED684A60221E3A252D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The operation of such systems across the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF8573AB7C4B44DA96338C5DD83C35D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Policies and practices governing the procurement of unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08B0EC31C3384A40B6BE7CAF14D7DBDA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The availability of unmanned aircraft systems from any domestic sources for government use.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H425D32D165E9499C944439CF0238A54C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The risks associated with use of such systems by the Federal Government, including relating to physical safety, privacy, and cybersecurity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE12830C6F3714159B5B3748F7382F21C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall report to Congress all findings and determinations made in carrying out the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H9D50EFFFE8964D6E895F7DEC40353886"><enum>II</enum><header>National Drone and Advanced Air Mobility Research Institutes</header><section id="HA6899A6DE8984E9EBF43334A95A0E898"><enum>201.</enum><header>National drone and advanced air mobility research institutes</header><subsection id="H0A0F3BDBE01948D6925FB17D2A0C4359"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall establish a program to award financial assistance for the planning, establishment, and support of a network of Institutes (as described in subsection (b)(2)) in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAE8D37B36198441B8BFEE4314604DD70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Financial assistance To establish and support national drone and advanced air mobility research institutes</header><paragraph id="HBF02013863B14880B30C77989606BE78"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Director of the National Science Foundation, the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, and any other agency head may award financial assistance to an eligible entity, or consortia thereof, as determined by an agency head, to establish and support an Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H496E71E43BD340FA9EEF887367FB3013"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Drone and advanced air mobility institutes</header><text>An Institute described in this subsection is an unmanned aircraft systems research institute that—</text><subparagraph id="H03CB58E8852A4DA0A22128658B1B0083"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may focus on—</text><clause id="H8F2F1DB249DF49FA835CAAB7C027B68C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a particular economic or social sector, including education, manufacturing, transportation, agriculture, security, energy, environment, and public safety, and includes a component that addresses the ethical, societal, safety, and security implications relevant to the application of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems in that sector; or</text></clause><clause id="H81B3915F9DAB481A917A9DE6CEB5B394"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a cross-cutting challenge for research, development, testing, or use of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CE88814746344068007D677D1AFBE87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>requires partnership among public and private organizations, including, as appropriate, Federal agencies, academic institutions, nonprofit research organizations, Federal laboratories, State, local, and Tribal governments, industry, and others (or consortia thereof);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88142846D093415780AAD2D7E20E2CFE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has the potential to create an innovation ecosystem, or enhance existing ecosystems, to translate Institute research into applications and products, as appropriate to the topic of each Institute;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC25169C3D3C64980B7B9C6FD0D7660F0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>supports and coordinates interdisciplinary research and development across multiple institutions and organizations involved in unmanned aircraft systems research and related disciplines, which may include physics, engineering, mathematical sciences, computer and information science, robotics, material science, cybersecurity, and technology ethics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A2B234D2DA43A4A370647E22A4A3F5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>supports interdisciplinary education activities at all levels, including curriculum development, research experiences, and faculty professional development across two-year, undergraduates, masters, and doctoral level programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9BC781515FE414A84B7578E1CF081F0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establishes a robust data management strategy that ensures digital access and machine-readability; that promotes findability, interoperability, analysis- and decision-readiness and reusability; and ensures applicable scientific data are managed for wide use by the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, academia, and the public;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BC571D5E3304CA184586D7D4232C50D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>applies lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE916ADD84C8A41F58EF8776F8FA9E0A5"><enum>(H)</enum><text>supports workforce development in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems related disciplines in the United States, including broadening participation of underrepresented communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAB55D3086894BF882305BE4C72C507F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Financial assistance awarded under paragraph (1) may be used by an Institute for—</text><subparagraph id="H75A81F24B4A34CA98A904B939DF51B97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>managing and making available to researchers accessible, curated, standardized, secure, and privacy protected data sets from the public and private sectors for the purposes of training and testing advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems, and for research and development using advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5880AEF1F07C414BB390637AA2536D28"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing and managing testbeds, Unmanned Aircraft Systems Test Ranges, for advanced air mobility or unmanned aircraft systems, including sector-specific test beds, designed to enable users to evaluate advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems prior to deployment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64EFDAB1FB63499A962CC6BA61D647E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conducting research and education activities involving advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems to solve challenges with economic, scientific, and national security implications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7943198EDD24429DBB28E5F313CD31B5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>conducting research and development on advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems platform development and innovation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7BDD8C48D094217A619251F7540EFB0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>providing or brokering access to computing resources, networking, and data facilities for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research and development relevant to the Institute’s research goals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H329E650D8DB347939746B2950B489C16"><enum>(F)</enum><text>providing technical assistance to users, including software engineering support, for advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems research and development relevant to the Institute’s research goals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H067BFE4A3D6E4340942AB1109E280C37"><enum>(G)</enum><text>supporting the purchase of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems software;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BF661690F0A4619967CA570326966C3"><enum>(H)</enum><text>engaging in outreach and engagement to broaden participation in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development and workforce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D58EC1F40294FC78C3BC27C2FEABEA8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>supporting artificial intelligence and machine learning research related to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10A37AB31B134E6CB8DBBB748C3CAB83"><enum>(J)</enum><text>such other activities that an agency head whose agency’s missions contribute to or are affected by advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems determines is appropriate to fulfill the agency’s missions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02212EE9194C41248AE55734007EE2E7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duration</header><subparagraph id="H8CF48BADC3BD410681F36ECAB7E9FDEE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial periods</header><text>An award of financial assistance under paragraph (1) shall be for an initial period of up to five years, subject to Office of Management and Budget uniform guidance for Federal assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA2265F11AB145FABBA582D2C3075EE4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>An established Institute may apply for, and the agency head may grant, extended funding for periods of up to five years on a merit-reviewed basis using the merit review criteria of the sponsoring agency, subject to Office of Management and Budget uniform guidance for Federal assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66A64D08BE1C4A48B2534B4BA52E982D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Application for financial assistance</header><subparagraph id="H0C7EBDF3FEFE4AECB13B761CA680B330"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity seeking financial assistance under paragraph (1) shall submit to an agency head an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the agency head may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AAE7646C22A4C7881BA7AD679445B80"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) for an Institute shall, at a minimum, include the following:</text><clause id="HAABF4446C54846ABAB3DD602F76F0BC2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A plan for the Institute, including—</text><subclause id="HF8200BB5B4624D8B8291D18965967DA0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the proposed goals and activities of the Institute;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4AD3494BC4DE4B448C590344CB6CA9D4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description of how the Institute will form partnerships with other research institutions, industry, nonprofits, academic institutions, and others to leverage expertise in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and access to data;</text></subclause><subclause id="H54B383E864144EF29F75E9D5BF8C5A56"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a description of how the institute will support long-term and short-term education and workforce development in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, including broadening participation of underrepresented communities; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE53729390EF94D9CA4003B3465BEE6D5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a description of how the Institute will transition from planning into operations.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H825851B38FDC4B7CA6573F2ABE86285D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A description of the anticipated sources and nature of any non-Federal contributions or other Federal agency funding.</text></clause><clause id="H08353C53C1AB48DAB1056EE7E5118848"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A data management plan that addresses the collection, use, retention, protection, dissemination, and management of data collected, consistent with the purposes of this Act.</text></clause><clause id="H19DA62D57510447D98F0DEDBBC1AF7A1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A description of the anticipated long-term impact of such Institute.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEE5FABBE0CF43C983391E723EC50545"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Competitive merit review</header><text>In awarding financial assistance under paragraph (1), the agency shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4019BFE816CF4C04B0EC5F9D1EE72174"><enum>(A)</enum><text>use a competitive merit review process that includes peer review by a diverse group of individuals with relevant expertise from both the private and public sectors; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6FE8F7FC7EA4FFC9AF5978B7FAD55AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure the focus areas of the Institute do not substantially duplicate the efforts of any other Institute.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF99BA404FE045C58D1CA5E2FA86C64A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><subparagraph id="H437878F8C6B74A4E979A0CCE5B3A70CA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In awarding financial assistance under paragraph (1), an agency head may collaborate with Federal departments and agencies the missions of which contribute to or are affected by advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0426481295384007B95A5365725BA3E8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Nonduplication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under this section, the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall coordinate with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies to avoid duplication of research and other activities to ensure that the activities carried out by Institutes are complementary to those being undertaken by other agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC23B61C61D274CEE93586A4FFF31484D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Coordinating network</header><text>The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall establish a network of Institutes receiving financial assistance under this subsection, to be known as the <quote>Drone Leadership Network</quote>, to coordinate cross-cutting research and other activities carried out by the Institutes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC238ABFD9E4942ECAA6CA4CFF4469372"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>The head of an agency may request, accept, and provide funds from other Federal departments and agencies, State, United States territory, local, or Tribal government agencies, private sector for-profit entities, and nonprofit entities, to be available to the extent provided by appropriations Acts, to support an Institute’s activities. The head of an agency may not give any special consideration to any agency or entity in return for a donation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB60655716CE84F41912E43DF566D651E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the National Aeronautics and Space Administration $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out the activities authorized in section 201(a).</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H9D9E0ABFA57E4F7697F46D12CD3718F2"><enum>III</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology Activities</header><section id="H5F62F8F3B50D473C8E6B4DA113E68BB3"><enum>301.</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology activities</header><subsection id="H210CD14AD58A4A30A0969671032A2C92"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall—</text><paragraph id="H4CA2156FAE354095B43BE45D284F80F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support measurement research and development of best practices and voluntary consensus technical standards for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, including for—</text><subparagraph id="H01C399E287E24E5B9D0E16A0F1F6FC14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>privacy, security, and cybersecurity of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E00DB8159C1485F836CF6609FBB03C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>safety and operational performance of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BDADC9D254F4DC99476EFCC211885DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hardware and components designed for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H593353DAE2FF41398617D76F09593368"><enum>(D)</enum><text>data management and techniques to increase the usability of data for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB11737B632D4AF382380337C17E78F9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>supply chain risks for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F2DF7B5434746A0A38626FAA2F03B36"><enum>(F)</enum><text>all other areas deemed by the Director to be critical to the development and deployment of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05EB288C662549DABCE35A3D4A61AEF2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support one or more Institutes as described in section 201(a) of this Act for the purpose of advancing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B6B605E19814559959F00AEAD8833A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>produce curated, standardized, representative, secure, and privacy-protected data sets for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research, development, and use, prioritizing data for high-value, high-risk research;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D8C3F69AF4B43CB94B2ABE3509478F2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support and strategically engage in the development of voluntary consensus technical standards, including international standards, through open, transparent, and consensus-based processes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75694EEA321A44B8988EF3EA2EC30E07"><enum>(5)</enum><text>enter into and perform such contracts, including cooperative research and development arrangements and grants and cooperative agreements or other transactions, as may be necessary in the conduct of the work of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and on such terms as the Director considers appropriate, in furtherance of the purposes of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC61BDAD8BC9E46E89391824A2562542A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>applies lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69FE62DD0C7846529C5C87D0047BC5EF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>coordinate the development of voluntary and consensus technical standards and best practices with other Federal agencies as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF7C477BE30024D1BB1FADDEFB52FE896"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Solicitation of input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall—</text><paragraph id="H3816F037E5634E77AE0CEDA0704AEE01"><enum>(1)</enum><text>solicit input from university researchers, private sector experts, relevant Federal agencies, Federal laboratories, State, local, and Tribal governments, civil society groups, and other relevant stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H780CC6B24BDE4E48BDAC53ABE31F5DF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide opportunity for public comment on guidelines and best practices, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A4AEEF0BCF148E0B17AFBD904B3671E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Drone research challenges</header><paragraph id="HEB78DC0A2C4D4DF2A8724C9C9336AA8A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prize competition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursuant to section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall carry out a program to award prizes competitively to stimulate research and development of innovative advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technologies to expand upon and improve emergency response operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F4D3200B7624795995A18A377A7B0F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Plan for emergency response operations</header><text>Each prize competition entry submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) shall include a plan for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems implementation in emergency response operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DE0572E2AAD416AB40F94734E37E49B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prize amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under paragraph (1), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology may award not more than a total of $2,250,000 to one or more winners of the prize competition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A8B9B56EC634D418AB43BC154E3EB2F" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date on which a prize is awarded under the prize competition, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that describes the winning entry of the prize competition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02A62D0E734440CA97D44B3B025A3248"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under paragraph (1), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology may consult with the heads of relevant departments and agencies of the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4BB255D379AA4188BB9BE25704ABE7F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Institute of Standards and Technology to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="HD1756710811840E6A8BEDCF6887CBB51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$20,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA224F9A7784C54BD85A5EBB5CFB0D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$21,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD826634814C4712AAA33B852D1287F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$22,050,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H737DA65E555048ABB404B86DB78D4D63"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$23,152,500 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B894B676DBA42EFA2C999DA3AC29A82"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$24,310,125 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE4C2B74EE283418B971BFEAD8938A0E6"><enum>302.</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology manufacturing activities</header><subsection id="H8827181D86BA4BF4BCEAD0404F079AA9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems pilot program as a part of the manufacturing extension partnership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Institute of Standards and Technology Act is amended by inserting after section 25B (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278k-2">15 U.S.C. 278k–2</external-xref>) the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="HD4737F99E20142E6B6EB5FCAA7B20591" style="OLC"><section id="H1C075A68E6A24333A96B2405CCDAE90C"><enum>25C.</enum><header>Expansion awards for unmanned aircraft systems pilot program</header><subsection id="H1DC003BEFC994A94B4320034CF02309F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>The terms used in this section have the meanings given the terms in section 25.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA0229B5FFAD54ECBAB3BDD052D2B84B8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Director shall establish as a part of the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership a pilot program of expansion awards among participants referred to in subsection (c) for the purposes described in subsection (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1EE0E4E740F04300B30C556CBAECDE22"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Participants</header><text>Participants receiving awards under this section shall be Centers, or a consortium of Centers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4291D94191334E108F1BE545EEDF5B43"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Award amounts</header><text>An award for a recipient under this section shall be in an amount equal to the sum of the following:</text><paragraph id="H66A2FC8602674D109EA3CFE8C05DD3CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Such amount as the Director considers appropriate as a minimum base funding level for each award under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB59F4F9D47504318B21FADDF231D547F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such additional amount as the Director considers in proportion to the manufacturing density of the region of the recipient.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A8081377E344B738CF50BED01AD4B00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such supplemental amounts as the Director considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9C45BCAF1B04777856F83A4729B3CED"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Purpose of awards</header><text>An award under this section shall be made for one or more of the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H413D77C9C668472ABEACBDC77EFD65A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To provide coordinating services on—</text><subparagraph id="H09B3B3420E7B457FB18772EF393369F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development of working concepts for new advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems products, including review and design analysis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6AFD7B174A8444480836AE3AF1068F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the review and optimization of current advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems designs and components, including industrial engineering and manufacturing design upgrades;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE628C1C313E6439CB51071984C23F9D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>rapid advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems prototyping services, including three-dimensional modeling;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA185E3691FFD4BD88C6DF7CAFD22AB03"><enum>(D)</enum><text>software development for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems application;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H026C618539A0498FB35AECB56B8AA6C8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>commercialization of new products and technology to improve performance of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB45761F9DEBC4EC698304DD9B50F1728"><enum>(F)</enum><text>supporting existing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and components manufacturing operations and the development of unmanned aircraft systems and components manufacturing operations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BE37A6B048B4CD0BFCD3DFD4AD7A866"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To provide services to improve the resiliency of domestic advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AA70379B1F44392B59A4B976B11CD5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To expand advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technology services to small and medium-sized manufacturers and software developers, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H3F192572C1084631B58BEF636F2C5C1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>facilitating the adoption of technologies, including smart manufacturing technologies and practices; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFD01B6932014D44B2B94C59029493A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing partnerships, for the development, demonstration, and deployment of unmanned aircraft systems technologies, with—</text><clause id="H8206301EBE1A4EDCBA5DD7E34382D295"><enum>(i)</enum><text>National Laboratories (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="H5E09774F2A1E4DA381F22482AB3B6184"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Federal laboratories;</text></clause><clause id="HC7FDAB6E01D549559EF22125B6391CFD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Manufacturing USA institutes;</text></clause><clause id="H2B0B571188E341FC86F81C03F661B239"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Unmanned Aircraft Systems Industry; and</text></clause><clause id="H74A7437B8A9F4E0B8C9E79E2109E1FEC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>institutions of higher education.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85AC0BBA0ABC41A5BC7FCF415F5AC409"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>Applications for awards under this section shall be submitted in such manner, at such time, and containing such information as the Director shall require in consultation with the Manufacturing Extension Partnership Advisory Board.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0CA0411F2A3F477CAE1354D0EE5CC53A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Selection</header><paragraph id="H07FAA36E91EE42D8BDFD0FE7582779AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reviewed and merit-based</header><text>The Director shall ensure that awards under this section are reviewed and merit-based.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2440505AFF1C4CEA9DAB372FD6CAD720"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>The Director shall endeavor to have broad geographic diversity among selected proposals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF384588FA29A4D9481D61C7DFFA903CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Director shall select applications consistent with the purposes identified pursuant to subsection (e) to receive awards the Director determines will achieve one or more of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H6A10F8EE1FEC4177A728096B16781186"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Improvement of the competitiveness of domestic advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems industries in the region in which the Center or Centers are located.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BAD3AAD04414454A1ABE0798BDCB550"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Creation of jobs or training of newly hired employees.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0753B123C9724B5195437109A87A6FB4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Promotion of the transfer and commercialization of research and technology from institutions of higher education, national laboratories, or other federally funded research programs, and nonprofit research institutes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10C3A63D79744F6AA11CC88A5C5258AD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any other result the Director determines will advance the objective set forth in section 25(c) or 26.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65AB99ABB49A465985E21ADB94D18E69"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Global marketplace projects</header><text>In making an award under this section, the Director, in consultation with the Manufacturing Extension Partnership Advisory Board and the Secretary, may take into consideration whether an application has significant potential for enhancing the competitiveness of small and medium-sized United States manufacturers in the global marketplace for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technologies.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7D6A5F15B39A4E30A47ABBF7E16E2586"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The Director shall ensure that the duration of an award under this section is aligned and consistent with a Center’s cooperative agreement established in section 25(e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6330F3E279F444ED8691B6FE07CECC3B"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the completion of the pilot program under subsection (b) and not later than October 1, 2025, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="H355C5F750081443E87AC43C6E5231D7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary description of what activities were funded and the measurable outcomes of such activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84CB4180D5804B6E8DEF2ADF3AD6129A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of which types of activities under paragraph (1) could be integrated into, and supported under, the program under section 25;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C1ABA707E394EE09F024C9A2F939AF1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of which types of activities under paragraph (1) could be integrated into, and supported under, the competitive awards program under section 25A; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2914442401D246F1A4A6158C47CF013E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a recommendation, supported by a clear explanation, as to whether the pilot program should be continued.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H56644BA635CD46889E2771A3D789C4D4"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the pilot program under this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4E9FE4ECF2244463B196B9823BD664E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Manufacturing extension partnership survey</header><paragraph id="H5D96C9B21D6045D682DBBE455C732C02"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Survey</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall carry out a survey of the Manufacturing Extension Partnership Centers (referred to in this section as the <quote>Centers</quote>) to understand the manufacturing capabilities of the United States manufacturers to support robust advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems industries in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FE3F4CB237241658324539908384B6E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the survey required under subsection (a), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall solicit feedback regarding the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF9C58A345AF04BE2A736D2BE6BC5707A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Familiarity and current manufacturing work by small and mid-sized manufacturers on advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, including components, software, sensors, or other technology associated with advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5046D7E5A9684AEB83A87DB40DF1CA62"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A list of the basic manufacturing procedures that can be easily converted to conduct the manufacturing of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems projects.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96B14C0B89B143559AF14A838C06B59F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Potential for small-and mid-sized manufacturing to work with industry and academia to support the manufacturers of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems prototypes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38E04F02BC62453990C2AEBD1798DE91"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Potential for commercialization of ongoing manufacturing development research related to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems projects.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB725B6C0A98E4ABCBD890047B3AA381A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of supply chain and technological challenges that small and mid-sized manufacturers face in building up advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems capacity, and the prevalence of such challenges.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6EC5321DA9342AEA5C98E7F5AECBCC8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Regulatory and legal barriers faced by small and mid-sized manufacturers and developers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E29ACA1462C4D4C8E1BFD82334AFAB9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Any challenges that small and mid-sized manufacturers experience in recruiting skilled workers familiar with advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems manufacturing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H468276A1620543D99B1CFA07753990E6"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other information that the Director or the Manufacturing Extension Partnership Advisory Board determine is appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2119BEEA62A94D8A8E854F25FA955644"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after completing the survey required under paragraph (1), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, in consultation with the Manufacturing Extension Partnership Advisory Board, shall provide to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report summarizing the results of the survey.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0135910F190B4BB683E17E192EDCED83"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Manufacturing uSA program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, acting through the Manufacturing USA Program, shall prioritize research, development, and demonstration activities to enhance and grow the domestic manufacturing capacity of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems and components. Such activities may include—</text><paragraph id="H033112F1D8184270AA92EF2277FFDDF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>rapid-prototyping and reproduction of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems structures;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AC6916859D34E41836D412C03388493"><enum>(2)</enum><text>additive manufacturing to improve capabilities to produce large tools, dies, and molds for advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems and components;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2AED4EFA4A240F7B50033BEB8486D0B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>testing innovative manufacturing processes and manufactured components to improve safety, endurance, and quality of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFED81036BBD94EDB997187CF17EBD788"><enum>(4)</enum><text>development of software to streamline fabrication and integration of manufacturing components, such as sensors for use in advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EA4AE5033144BF282D69092EC3169E3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other activities that the Director considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HF74F8ADB004048E7ACDFEE4403D8404E"><enum>IV</enum><header>National Science Foundation Activities</header><section id="H2F08696FC9E84B3FB7182C2F6BB6A5D5"><enum>401.</enum><header>National Science Foundation activities</header><subsection id="H906EF10760E845BBBB512F451D22E453"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Science Foundation shall support research and STEM education and related activities in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, components, and related technologies, including competitive awards or grants to institutions of higher education or eligible nonprofit organizations (or consortia thereof).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE2AFD19334E4485A822B2EDEBD21E09A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Director of the National Science Foundation shall—</text><paragraph id="H305B7C3A2C3641DAA90F95AB43FCFC71"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support fundamental research on the underlying technologies for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, components, and related technologies, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H7F91018219764CB098ADEBFAE1C2490D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improving the safety and reliability of operation systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6760DAC911E49189BE247983AB2FE58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing and improving autonomous control systems, including real-time control and autonomous decisionmaking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35A4C975B09241BE857BFD35AEDC5148"><enum>(C)</enum><text>incorporating the use of artificial intelligence into systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF375D1197704CEC82A2408B2748F2E1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>improving or developing materials for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEFA14812BF84ABEB2254CFDFB1F7108"><enum>(E)</enum><text>understanding safety and sustainability of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems as a part of a transportation system, including the impacts of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems on ground transportation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DB90003B5114307B140152E85730CDF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>developing and improving communications systems, including multivehicle coordination and task and path planning; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB281DC6D37174E15A4516DBB74893EFE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>understanding the human-drone interface;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C72849536704BBB9941B56978FF1969"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support research and development of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system enabled uses, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H250F73C0DFE345ABA1A3469075A1A9EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>creating new sensing tools to improve understanding, prediction, and detection of severe weather and natural hazards, including wildfires;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D9747F908794749A3F9BC3B47EC36A2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enabling advanced air mobility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF19BA2C74C9E436B9EC3AFCA24C6456C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>monitoring and surveying infrastructure;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77139892D1BC4D2D80EFE805921FCB1F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>disaster reconnaissance, including the collection of data to model and simulate disasters and assist responders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4F4824C9035486BA077DD149FD9E95E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>improving the reliable use of advanced sensing systems in rural and agricultural settings;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07D0A404057A4C40B60088FA7A326A46"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support research on data modeling and validation of the use of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C1D89F171014DDAA71DFBF49215CB69"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support research and development on security, including the cybersecurity, of advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aerial aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC96C08EF825E4DD2A937C8F101890F75"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support research on the ethical use of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, including protection of individual privacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE127814AC10B4E1CAB2D03C006F8B7BD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>support middle school and high school level STEM education research and related activities related to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and related technologies, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H587CD0278CDC41FFAB996068BF7660D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supporting curriculum development relating to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system applications, including developing place-based learning curriculum, particularly for students in poor, rural, or Tribal communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E5FE1ACC5A7411685346C3202EDC65C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>utilizing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technologies to advance the engagement of students, including students in poor, rural, or Tribal communities, in STEM through providing before school, after-school, out-of-school, or summer activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12AC06D49BAF4715AB3C9263D96D16F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developing professional development resources for STEM educators in utilizing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems technologies and applications in their curriculum and classrooms, including through distance-delivered courses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45EFF757FCD44719A56D188185EFF0C5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>connecting relevant STEM curriculum to the design, construction and demonstration of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C36A9E883AD4D0A86A6F4DFC46B3475"><enum>(E)</enum><text>designing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system related activities designed to help students make real-world connections to STEM content and educate students on the relevance and significance of STEM careers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H46C0270BD8234B18A91C7E171CB561E1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>support undergraduate and graduate education and workforce development research and related activities related to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and related technologies, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="HFCE21E0791F74DFC84C74C97AD60E059"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supporting curriculum development relating to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems applications and technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1971CF0249C546D29FEAC2D264BA6707"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supporting hands-on research opportunities at institutions of higher education, research institutions, including National Labs, and industry for undergraduate and graduate students relating to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems applications and technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A7E06900DF447A38925EB49085DA095"><enum>(C)</enum><text>facilitating participation in collegiate level advanced air mobility and unmanned systems robotic competitions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H788515843D3949C3B7D612C8D38D8BBC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensuring that students pursuing master’s degrees and doctoral degrees in fields relating to advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems are considered as applicants for scholarships and graduate fellowships under the Graduate Research Fellowship Program under section 10 of the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1869">42 U.S.C. 1869</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H41A223D7FC254A9F83079FF7886F69FC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>support activities to develop a skilled technical workforce for supporting and operating advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems, which may include establishing national centers focused on educating and training the skilled technical workforce in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system applications and technologies through the Advanced Scientific and Technical Education Program as authorized by the Scientific and Advanced-Technology Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1862i">42 U.S.C. 1862i</external-xref>), including by—</text><subparagraph id="HA9508C389E1440C191B5D284774B3FE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expanding educational resources to address current workforce demands in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system applications and technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3082AE24EE7843C6AF10CD42495F0AB4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing curriculum for community and technical colleges to train and upskill the skilled technical workforce in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system applications and technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD93390DF248B47D588D5F60CCBFD3F08"><enum>(C)</enum><text>engaging the skilled technical workforce community in STEM, advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system applications and technologies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79EC5B7F68FB4D81BF1B016B05C2CEAE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in partnership with industry, employing activities to increase the visibility and utility of careers in advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft applications and technologies;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD63093ECAF794AA19F748D12B0DBFC85"><enum>(9)</enum><text>engage veterans and departing members of the Armed Forces in activities specified in paragraphs (7) and (8);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDFB7CFC1F9C4266A5AC2599B9266904"><enum>(10)</enum><text>support one or more Institutes as described in section 201(a) for the purpose of advancing the field of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H366806F423804C11A91F1E6A22215739"><enum>(11)</enum><text>support prize competitions pursuant to section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7A5F88603B04453BE06A4936B731FAC"><enum>(12)</enum><text>establish a robust data management strategy that ensures digital access and machine-readability; that promotes findability, interoperability, analysis- and decision-readiness and reusability; and ensures applicable scientific data are managed for wide use by the Federal Government, State, local and Tribal governments, academia, and the public;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8BC520CDA724225B71E5FC927188AA2"><enum>(13)</enum><text>applies lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87CD1B4E86A7414BB8060F7D323A1DCA"><enum>(14)</enum><text>any other activities the Director determines necessary to meet the goals specified in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFAF1123BFD44774AD87CA1BC289F89B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public-Private partnerships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the activities under subsection (a), the Director of the National Science Foundation shall support public-private partnerships to support domestic development of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems in the United States and address pre-competitive industry challenges.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8CA72183B03449BA878E0215EF0ED709"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under this section, the Director of the National Science Foundation shall coordinate with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies to avoid duplication of research and other activities to ensure that the activities carried out under this section are complementary to those being undertaken by such other agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDE553E3D5AF74BD4B6FD2D852E06C449"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Science Foundation to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="H269DEB3172DA484382CA1985D8B6CE19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A50223DE85641EF9F61E379B5213ABD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$52,500,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8ECDA64D67D14356A66F93D9AB55A295"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$55,125,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CA615952524A56A0E4D0C40B3040CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$57,881,775 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC173AC655C4420A436411060D186C5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$60,775,863 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H2BB2176C9B444EB88D9DC1EA51F541D6"><enum>V</enum><header>National Aeronautics and Space Administration Activities</header><section id="H1B06384B09FA49D786E703CB62BDCD11"><enum>501.</enum><header>National Aeronautics and Space Administration activities</header><subsection id="HA75C6B6E5D604711BBAA273DCB6B0A72"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration and other relevant Federal agencies, shall direct research and technological development to facilitate the safe integration of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems into the National Airspace System, including—</text><paragraph id="HC4805283EBCE478ABDA19A29AE2B0FAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>positioning and navigation systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38B43C09042C40159CBDF85F62558C7F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>sense and avoid capabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9C12979FE1246E19242414900133432"><enum>(3)</enum><text>secure data and communication links;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26BE0DF717C04AECAC5B28E5770893D4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>flight recovery systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DDE52AB893A47D5925417E4B9FDABF7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>human systems integration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C19760718684E709234A5144AF703F4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>hazardous weather condition avoidance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75061889CF9149E28C360389AEBD0A58"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cooperative unmanned aircraft system activities</header><text>Section 31504 of title 51, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>Operational flight data derived from these cooperative agreements shall be made available, in appropriate and usable formats, to the Administration and the Federal Aviation Administration for the development of regulatory standards.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC7D6A72286DF47AA916982B496C40C8D" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall work with industry, the Federal Aviation Administration, the Department of Defense, the Department of Homeland Security, and academia to mature and help operationalize advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system traffic management related concepts, architecture, services, and strategic as well as tactical deconfliction to ensure safe integration of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems in airspace in presence of other aircraft. As part of such activities, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall consider commercial and public good use cases, such as wildfire and disaster monitoring and mitigation, with a primary focus on enabling many simultaneous drone operations beyond visual line of sight.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA855E276374C439AAB07EFCDC371E4A0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Lessons learned</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall apply lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8781A5F406724A43BF8A30D10FDF8FE2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall coordinate with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Director of the National Institutes of Standards and Technology, State, local and Tribal governments, and industry to inform the development of voluntary consensus-based technical standards to facilitate the incorporation of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems into the National Airspace System and decrease the need for regulations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDE8F0F22E462445C9DC95FAF6F58CF33"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall coordinate with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to conduct an assessment to identify metrics and performance measures necessary to safely integrate unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility systems into the National Airspace System.</text></subsection><subsection id="H15C9151A02AC4D039EA62EF9BB83FA54"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the completion of the assessment under subsection (f), the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the progress toward meeting metric and performance measures referred to in such subsection.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4B0D84839818426ABA807E1384ACB048"><enum>502.</enum><header>National student unmanned aircraft systems competition program</header><subsection id="H577032833FBD458F8EA6EF14DB71040E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall establish a national program to carry out unmanned aircraft systems technology competitions for students at the high school and undergraduate level (in this section referred to as <quote>competitions</quote>) in which students shall compete to design, create, and demonstrate an unmanned aircraft system.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA7E91AC0D76A4973B63C3B3CC448F43E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Competition administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall select, on a merit-reviewed, competitive basis, an institution of higher education to administer the competitions (in this section referred to as the <quote>competition administrator</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H97C20C2D30624C1CAA873F8DC8DEDD40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations for selecting competition administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting an institution of higher education to administer the competition, the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall consider the institution of higher education’s prior experience in—</text><paragraph id="H2698C3AD516F426FA835733DC3541587"><enum>(1)</enum><text>administering such competitions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1859C18798EC43C09250BC0B0322D013"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administering national STEM engagement programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AFE5031892C4C00B42B85BAF7F42F8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>engaging eligible institutions from diverse geographic areas, including poor, rural, and Tribal communities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H867CEE8F7A3041CFB3022B4CFD5E9DAC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>connecting STEM activities to Administration missions and centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63CB987B41F7437F90E04EFC1AD02E7D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Competition administrator responsibilities</header><text>The competition administrator shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="H7FF187B571734E7484B543BA14EAD3C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>awarding grants to institutions of higher education or nonprofit organizations (or a consortium of such institutions or organizations) on a merit-reviewed, competitive basis to host individual competitions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4237D5377D2F4FA99481D354855CCFC8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>developing STEM curriculum to be utilized by the competition awardees to help students make the connection to the design, construction, and demonstration of the unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C10C9AE3484D43B14EED0987F1DAB1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>developing curriculum to assist students in making real-world connections to STEM content and educate students on the relevance and significance of STEM careers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21B8F8E91F7F40AFB4D40A9426774076"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensuring awardees are supporting the activities laid out in subsection (f);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE289589A09614B459AFD42E822DBA2C9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conducting performance evaluations of competitions, including data collection on—</text><subparagraph id="H082FF780CDC6466C9FFADD17BE925502"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of students engaged;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A5E89B5CC9445BEB6DF2D8CF1D17355"><enum>(B)</enum><text>geographic and institutional diversity of participating schools and institutions of higher education; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEEC14F1350C4F2596BA05EA19E2B574"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other activities the Administrator finds necessary to ensure the competitions are successful.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB2E83D9A2A34C1AB262995C073D2152"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Additional considerations</header><text>In awarding grants authorized in subsection (d), the competition administrator shall give priority to applications that include a partnership with that State’s space grant program under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/51/403">chapter 403</external-xref> of title 51, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE772F55D2F9342DA96095D468D06F65F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Permitted activities</header><text>In carrying out the competitions authorized in subsection (a), the competition administrator shall ensure competitions occurring at both the high school and undergraduate levels—</text><paragraph id="H2CC6F542C3AE46DC9553A926F41E5FF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>allow students to design, construct, and demonstrate an unmanned aircraft system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52516E2DE4F34F50A7DBE369FC2717D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allow students to compete with other teams in the performance of the constructed unmanned aircraft system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB1E1578E8774F35AF0378624DB8359E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>connect to relevant missions and Center activities of the Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEBBB276816744309983715751CF545F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>connect relevant STEM curriculum to the design, construction, and demonstration of unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6A261E01CF3484FB33915E0BFCF4F2E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support activities designed to help students make real-world connections to STEM content and educate students on the relevance and significance of STEM careers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35C042C0AD3E4BADB40933AD81D286D5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>are geographically dispersed in order to serve a broad student population, including those in rural and underserved communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB4A0E6CC7D954C03AA5A301929829EBF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration $6,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section. Of the funds authorized for each such fiscal year—</text><paragraph id="H1D5F31BA25B94EA4B350A2C2E5B34276"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$1,000,000 shall be for the competition administrator as authorized in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF11E61E5BFC5423E8CC03BD3881926C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$5,000,000 shall be awarded for grants to carry out competitions as authorized by subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H51D5A81EF6BB480888DCFE883F2DC3DE"><enum>VI</enum><header>Department of Energy Activities</header><section id="H2CEA5522756F45EF8D7B9B682AD230B4"><enum>601.</enum><header>Department of Energy research program</header><subsection id="HB030116D9A27446A839ABCAEA1B8594A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy shall carry out a cross-cutting research, development, and demonstration program to advance unmanned aircraft system technologies, capabilities, and workforce needs and to improve the reliability of unmanned aircraft systems implementation methods relevant to the mission of the Department of Energy. In carrying out such program, the Secretary shall coordinate across all relevant offices and activities at the Department, including the Office of Science, the Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, the Office of Nuclear Energy, the Office of Fossil Energy, the Office of Electricity, the Office of Cybersecurity, Energy Security, and Emergency Response, the Advanced Research Projects Agency–Energy, the Office of Environmental Management, the Office of Environment, Health, Safety and Security, the National Nuclear Security Administration, the Artificial Intelligence Technology Office, the UAS Research and Engineering Center, and any other relevant office or activity as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H67A490D450674957B6F87287484C5B59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall—</text><paragraph id="H96FE8A72097E4590991BCED3B4FD275C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">formulate goals for unmanned aircraft systems research activities to be supported by the Department of Energy, including in the research areas under subsection (c);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC40C4D018AB54A95A9F3EC6A3073E253"><enum>(2)</enum><text>leverage the collective body of knowledge from existing unmanned aircraft systems research and development activities, including the work underway by the Unmanned Aircraft Systems Research and Engineering Center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C3942ECEE814D459B79E6C82061B04F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide research experiences and training for undergraduate and graduate students in unmanned aircraft systems research and development, including in the fields of—</text><subparagraph id="HD13FCA8703BE4E23BC8F9728D0FBBCCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>artificial intelligence and machine learning;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86D099A6F3774EE8830644AA7D5E2154"><enum>(B)</enum><text>applied mathematics and algorithm development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C1E61B72B134ECF93AAC6EC1550B313"><enum>(C)</enum><text>advanced imaging, sensing, and detection technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B9E4F699EC246C598835BC88E2E615E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>materials science and engineering; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDD6D5A3577A4E53B06D0ABB00C6D5A1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>advanced energy technologies and propulsion approaches;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C1383302162403E8DE46FB108231B39"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establish a robust data management strategy that—</text><subparagraph id="H9E76929E81104208A249F4FD1A5589A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures digital access and machine-readability;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0620F18B92DA49918A2D258FC2D11BA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promotes findability, interoperability, analysis- and decision-readiness and reusability; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF49668E490114655811BFAF9119857A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensures applicable scientific data are managed for wide use by the Federal Government, State, local, and Tribal governments, academia, and the public; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB831B6295DBB49F6919435E8B1F445E3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support one or more Institutes as described in section 201(a) for the purpose of advancing the fields of unmanned aircraft systems and the mission of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99033E5434934C06BEE4513221C39219"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Research areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall award financial assistance to eligible entities to carry out research, development, and demonstration projects over a range of subject areas including—</text><paragraph id="H5A55F1FBB93847FC9678317E79E486B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>fundamental science and technology areas, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="HD397192E903546C2876212FBEB5FEE97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advanced sensor technologies and processes, including—</text><clause id="H0DBE3BE45F674F0F962912FB81364F11"><enum>(i)</enum><text>optical capabilities, including Light Detection and Ranging, hyperspectral, thermographic, and visible imaging capabilities;</text></clause><clause id="HDA5ACF13AB4B4033A427AD5FA593D974"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nonoptical electromagnetic capabilities, including radar and radiofrequency capabilities;</text></clause><clause id="HC99E082AF4F54C82900B4D9F0EA7E30B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>acoustic capabilities, including ultrasonic capabilities; and</text></clause><clause id="H479DB1CDA9EB42428A1E6B9CB94D710C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>radiation detection, gravimetric, hyperspectral or other measurement modalities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECB177705A804486A186645DFD5C857F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>advanced technologies and methods for remote handling, precision positioning, and navigation control;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B39A25737DA40CA94C11A0FBAAA0CB7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>advanced technologies for secure autonomous operation, including edge computing and artificial intelligence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A3DC01C28224F74AAB2B2CFCA2C83A4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>power electronics and wireless charging systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31D9B267426A4747BDEEEC505AC93326"><enum>(E)</enum><text>novel materials, including lightweight and radiation-resistant materials;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DA6145A61714967BC21345616A24D66"><enum>(F)</enum><text>scalability of unmanned aircraft systems for increased payload capacity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB058D4D05A8435C8F650757121B5B56"><enum>(G)</enum><text>technologies and processes to improve secure interoperability practices, including with existing satellites, constellation networks, and surface-based facilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C9E49F3765C47528F321B52ED4D2968"><enum>(H)</enum><text>strategies and technologies for integrated cybersecurity considerations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86DEA5B112484325B1FC3F932B588FD0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>strategies and technologies for improved endurance, including lightweight long duration fuels, batteries, and fuel cells;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0EBA0A9654C46A095098C237EABA992"><enum>(J)</enum><text>open architectures and advanced algorithms to enable multi-sensor fusion and tracking of unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14A205F013814B2CB163629F88968BB9"><enum>(K)</enum><text>swarm and cooperative drone data collection and operation, and integration of drone control systems with dynamic sampling and real-time digital twin simulations; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD05AF2B72B74A53933D2BCA4D3D3613"><enum>(2)</enum><text>approaches for leveraging unmanned aircraft systems for diverse applications, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H79B39FFF593742778BCD9B2009EBDCB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advanced assessment, characterization, mapping, and recovery of energy resources, such as geothermal energy, biofuels, and critical minerals resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C1B2637F26B478886833265DDEF7F3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>field testing and monitoring of energy systems, such as onshore and offshore wind energy, fossil energy, solar energy, marine energy, nuclear energy, and hydropower systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7F7525CF4514650AC18185B4FA34C36"><enum>(C)</enum><text>damage assessment of the electric grid and energy infrastructure following physical events such as wildland fires, including prescribed burns containment and emissions measurements, potential health and safety effects from contaminant releases and dispersals, and real-time analysis of impacted assets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D38FBCD8F7B4ED9AECBA6ECF2999C59"><enum>(D)</enum><text>leak detection of greenhouse gases related to energy production, including methane leak detection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C48258829C048DCA68E7169C41AC3BA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>agriculture and aquaculture applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4781284A82FA44E6A9DDAF6BDCDB16C8"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">integrated data collection to inform and enhance Department of Energy modeling capabilities, including the development of climate and earth systems models;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H364D9CB5E203437D98459F573B76AD1A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>assistance in environmental management and cleanup activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDE32F5FBCD34FA39846BDE979F06572"><enum>(H)</enum><text>assistance in Department infrastructure management at National Laboratories and other relevant Department sites;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64308B739CA94CEEBA7C6360A763E417"><enum>(I)</enum><text>intrusion detection and facility monitoring for physical security applications; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB2B8EC263DC4BE7BD7C09AD97A73284"><enum>(J)</enum><text>asset extraction of building envelope features and characteristics for rapid energy modeling purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE5AD8183A0194B6D9BA0B34B091328BC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technology transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), and in coordination with the Office of Technology Transitions, the Secretary of Energy shall support technology transfer of unmanned aircraft systems research by partnering with industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEF43114F08F0436D9A095B853B445AE6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Facility use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall make available high-performance computing infrastructure and other relevant research facilities and test beds at the National Laboratories.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA41585F92B1E4AD4AECAE9DEDDED9249"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Interagency coordination and nonduplication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall coordinate with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies to avoid duplication of research and other activities and to ensure that the activities carried out under such program are complementary to those currently being undertaken by such other departments and agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA1397616991B43978535B76CCB3711D8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Department of Energy to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="H5DC7ADA08F9C42F798D48E0FAEAD1E40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDEB5C560E6A4ACAA9DF6273AAE80B1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$52,500,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB01759CD8A0D4A80A90EAE22C3514663"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$55,125,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70A8849485714E83A4587F6AEAC7490E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$57,881,775 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD074229763374361ABF9CDC5F13034F5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$60,775,863 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA08955CA0508449D87911FAF32B1586B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Eligible entities defined</header><text>In this title, the term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H94DA6E6C697D4C3F839281E9B8B5CA9F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BABE75C2D884058A139D777E7E27B7E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a National Laboratory;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6778DE0100384CF098F19A66BC5FD4F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a State, local, territorial, or Tribal government research agency;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B3FB5683A584EA699CD8CD2056D6579"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a nonprofit research organization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF68865D18E64546ADA8DBCC8839784C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a private sector entity; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EA12E3E4F474956B8C3C4376A0EC4D6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a consortium of two or more entities described in any of paragraphs (1) through (5).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HD025DA6A26584378B6AF7675CCDB14D8"><enum>VII</enum><header>Department of Homeland Security Activities</header><section id="H08F37563A2FB42DF93F1B0C1755B71EC"><enum>701.</enum><header>Department of Homeland Security activities</header><subsection id="H50FA663B961F440A994CE363167F4FF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Under Secretary for Science and Technology of the Department of Homeland Security, shall—</text><paragraph id="H3C80102BE1E447A69378956CD73E0E11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support research, development, evaluation and testing for advanced air mobility, unmanned aircraft systems, counter-UAS systems, and detection systems capabilities, including for—</text><subparagraph id="HF1FAA590C48D4716845672020D128B4B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>air domain awareness and advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems traffic monitoring;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4919ECFB29BB4363A556399090F2BFB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>privacy, security, and cybersecurity of advanced air mobility systems, unmanned aircraft systems, and counter-UAS systems capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD64600ACBE942838141C6F7D62CDD23"><enum>(C)</enum><text>safety of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01AE1BC45FB94714B09E47FC7210662D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>safety of operations in the National Airspace System; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H726FADC7EE3041C2917D365817586980"><enum>(E)</enum><text>testing and evaluation of unmanned aircraft systems and counter-UAS systems capabilities, performance systems engineering, and operational analysis;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H781D0BDB29F14FAC866E8F5E0555B4E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate with all relevant offices and programs of the Department of Homeland Security, including the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, U.S. Customs and Border Protection, the Federal Emergency Management Agency, the Federal Protective Service, the Transportation Security Administration, the United States Coast Guard, and the United States Secret Service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H129392771EEF4FF4B861AE1A5B0B8206"><enum>(3)</enum><text>produce curated, standardized, representative, secure, and privacy protected data sets for advanced air mobility systems, unmanned aircraft systems, and counter-UAS systems, including detection systems, development, archiving, and use, prioritizing data for high-value, high-risk research;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFE3D594852E45A991BAC1C4D76A1F72" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support one or more Institutes as described in section 201(a) for the purpose of advancing the field of advanced air mobility, unmanned aircraft systems, and counter-UAS systems, including detection systems capabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB26E022BA9F4B619BDF2A634EDC4EBF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>apply lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, evaluation, and testing to advanced air mobility systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H215F26CD5A2D4ADE911279F5B0CA97BB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>enter into and perform such contracts, including cooperative research and development arrangements and grants and cooperative agreements or other transactions, as may be necessary in the conduct of the work of the Department and on such terms as the Secretary considers appropriate, in furtherance of the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D693655685B4437AA624049C4E01D4D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Counter–UAS center of excellence</header><paragraph id="H5896FA276A0D4B8687879483E3082EF9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish in the Department of Homeland Security a center of excellence to carry out research and development that advances counter-UAS systems capabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C0BEBA2CA114DA7B4EAA5755D64B06F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of host institution</header><subparagraph id="HE40C9292155E4D9EB7AC085FCDBA3F3D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall make a grant to one institution of higher education, or a consortium of institutions of higher education, to host and maintain the center of excellence established under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCE778BA69004BF78AC03D2E89E0A700"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting such an institution or consortium, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text><clause id="HEECBD450D2144934BABFC9FE08D5B1E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>give preference to applicants with strong past performance related to counter-UAS systems research, education, and workforce development activities;</text></clause><clause id="HFB7C216808B64A1BA68C95CB6A689734"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>give preference to applicants geographically collocated within 100 miles of Federal departments or agencies that currently possess or operate extant counter-UAS system facilities;</text></clause><clause id="H2E8636AF27A742B0B2C846118DEB1332"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>give preference to applicants having proven abilities and strong research enterprises in systems engineering, radio frequency (RF) directed energy, radar and antenna research and development, atmospheric monitoring that can support chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear detection to include trace gases and particular matter (PM), target tracking, remote sensing, and the ability to leverage artificial intelligence and machine learning to support the required data analytics;</text></clause><clause id="H8ED2C246AAA44167A160D05ED6183DB4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>consider the extent to which the applicant would involve the public and private sectors; and</text></clause><clause id="HC320AC33B1ED4C4A8B6EE0244907899A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>consider the regional and national impacts of the applicant’s proposed research and development activities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA00EB1236F1491190F94553082F334E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>The institution of higher education or consortium may use funds provided under this subsection to carry out fundamental research, evaluation, education, workforce development, and training efforts related to counter-UAS systems subject areas, including safety, privacy, security, cybersecurity, detecting, identifying, monitoring, tracking, disrupting and seizing control, confiscating, disabling, damaging, destruction, remote sensing, forensics, testing and evaluation of systems capabilities, performance, systems engineering, operational analysis, and advanced technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C9805931D044D859E4F0E415B2C34B8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Homeland Security share of a grant under this subsection shall not exceed 75 percent of the costs of establishing and operating the center of excellence and related research activities carried out by the grant recipient.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A39880D3CF24B198DE5FF67ECE44128"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subparagraph id="H322D82EC1D324C6C9F86D069B36FAA7B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Fiscal year 2024</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security $10,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 for making grants under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC96CDEDF0564B46A119CEDF61C9CEC9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fiscal years 2025 through 2028</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security $5,000,000 in each of fiscal years 2025 through 2028 for making grants under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBB76ECE4AEF4BC991F173D1839C23B0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7093C01AD02B49FDA6E0E087F7B1F8B7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall coordinate with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies to avoid duplication of research and other activities and to ensure such activities are complimentary to those currently being undertaken by such other departments and agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="H003731DE52A44C62B0D6217E19ECB0ED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="H20BF589756184A5D9E8E244B608DB152"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$30,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0444D599E7C42CAB01071FBF490EB02"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$31,500,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C18F10D52FB4F1D970209BB5AEFA842"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$33,075,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8405DF632DC44FE78F5A584661A929F2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$34,728,750 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A7E3FD75270499E807061DE5CEED6EC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$36,465,187 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H977642080B7945C5A9DC225750C40916"><enum>VIII</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Activities</header><section id="H570B364FF731412CAD548D741A43C9EC"><enum>801.</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration research and development</header><subsection id="H0CCC098962F34FE98A7DEE60C9DB40C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall carry out and support research, development, and demonstration activities to advance unmanned aircraft systems technologies, and capabilities, and to enhance the deployment of, and data collected by, unmanned aircraft systems relevant to the mission of the Administration, incorporate such data into operations, and ensure data are managed, stewarded, and archived appropriately. In carrying out such activities, the Administrator shall coordinate across all relevant offices and programs of the Administration, including the Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research, National Environmental Satellite, Data, and Information Service, National Marine Fisheries Service, National Ocean Service, National Weather Service, and the Office of Marine and Aviation Operations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H842E6E99A5604654A23BDBAA3958F181"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall—</text><paragraph id="H4992ECC8426041A48F7873C0CEF4F32B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>test, evaluate, and demonstrate the utility of unmanned aircraft systems technologies for the Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H056174EF457E41568F6DD41CF6E7432A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support Administration activities and Cooperative Institute referred to in subsection (i)(3) projects, and support and encourage Federal and State agencies, academic institutions, nongovernmental organizations, industry representatives, and others to—</text><subparagraph id="H1FFC540BBBEC458F92639AA7C06FB1B9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>accelerate the transition of unmanned aircraft systems capabilities from research to operations and other uses and facilitate new unmanned aircraft systems applications within the Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DEBEE54A4334A4C8DB2D9BF2CB488CB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evaluate current observation strategies and identify critical data gaps best suited for advanced unmanned aircraft systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4D66082DB484319910EC6B4E3F78BE3" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prioritize activities that collect or acquire routine observations which feed forecasts and models;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FBDCD4471C546DBA112D825198D7B58" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>test, develop, and evaluate safe systems capable of safely operating beyond visual line of sight;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D1097A5CE164CF29F7D2DAE74BCDC53" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>collect or acquire measurements of atmospheric and oceanic parameters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9F28E49AFFC4224893E7623C8D6DC5D" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>ensure the archiving, stewardship, utility, and preservation of and public accessibility to the observations collected are shared with the Administration;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6F9790D0FFD4453A7AD52DAC3762A34" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide and support research experiences and training for undergraduate and graduate students in unmanned aircraft systems research, development, and operations relevant to the mission of the Administration, and other education and training opportunities consistent with the purpose of this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC329629777E6400F8A3BBBAA9D095625"><enum>(4)</enum><text>contribute to and supplement field campaigns at the Department of Energy’s Atmospheric Radiation Measurement user facility in order to incorporate unmanned aircraft systems and resulting data into the development of combined observational and modeling elements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FC35C1E3C5E4EE58F5C9476B1D2C7D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support and conduct leading-edge research and development of innovative unmanned aircraft systems technologies and concepts to advance research areas in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CD3DB3C410A4C90BB453FB145317BE3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Research areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall award financial assistance to eligible entities to carry out projects on the use of unmanned aircraft systems to collect environmental data and monitor climate impacts, including—</text><paragraph id="HC5FA64D22C9345639C053B2751D33044"><enum>(1)</enum><text>severe weather forecasts and damage assessments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D444E3D65674675B124FD3605D702DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>rapid flood mapping;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H466E055A4B4E4A32AE37F7353E016D98"><enum>(3)</enum><text>real-time hurricane data, including close-to-surface and low altitude meteorological measurements;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B3310F89D6249F68A0E5A4162C98A50"><enum>(4)</enum><text>enhanced atmospheric monitoring and sampling, including physical and chemical measurements in the atmospheric boundary layer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03067D09EF16410BAE229E99B34A0F0E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>marine mammal detection and monitoring;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46D19B733913470FB581BFAB262AEC55"><enum>(6)</enum><text>near-real time harmful algal bloom measurements for rapid response efforts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34ABE6C7C5694B0AAF24CAC765E327FD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>coastal restoration and habitation monitoring, including detection and monitoring of marine debris, oil spill, and hazardous materials;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H867DE9FBE63E494CB4C8EA40073179E9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>mapping, charting, and geodesy applications to support safety of navigation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90DB518E9E1A4F53840A48072AC36020"><enum>(9)</enum><text>wildfire observations and data to improve fire weather modeling;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E63BD14BA5A4DFB9C20DC53E0500132"><enum>(10)</enum><text>other areas related to science and stewardship of the climate, weather, oceans, coasts, and Great Lakes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AB52E83F83D46FC94D7B9D79DCB5F93"><enum>(11)</enum><text>any other areas the Administrator determines necessary and appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3075A66391564C05B854B3E0BA82B887"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the research areas in subsection (c), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall, to the maximum extent practicable, prioritize activities that increase the Administration’s operational use of unmanned aircraft systems by extending the range of times, location, and conditions in which observations can be made at lower cost. As part of such activities, the Administrator may—</text><paragraph id="H08C14CE5CAFE4C40940765E984D791DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enter into contracts with one or more entities in the commercial data sector to acquire data collected by unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H346D7BC2873D47F5AFBCBDC6A8DB0CE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>leverage existing facilities, instruments, and tools, including the Administration’s satellites, fleet of ships, and crewed aircraft.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEA6D105508364C29AADF9889F4978EFE" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technology transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), and in coordination with the Small Business Innovation Research program of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Administrator of the Administration shall support technology transfer of unmanned aircraft systems research by partnering with Federal agencies and industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE3DC70A0D6094EAE898ED717E9EE432C" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall coordinate the activities authorized under this section with the activities authorized in section 3 of the Commercial Engagement Through Ocean Technology Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/4102">33 U.S.C. 4102</external-xref>) and engage with other Federal departments and agencies, research communities, nongovernmental organizations, and industry stakeholders through the interagency working group under section 101.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC8B0B249F1EE46D1A36F48296F4189B1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Support of institutes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of subsection (a), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may support relevant activities at one or more Institutes under section 201(a) for the purpose of advancing the field of unmanned aircraft systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0A0D09D8CFDC43BDB2BAA33A74EE639D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="H9B709633ADB841BC88562D7F2A5C3646"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0A523F2D85343A291F0E060F98610B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$15,750,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H705D001F076743EFA3391C960F4419D4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$16,537,500 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22B30773A97244FEB8CB7ABDE64807A0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$17,364,375 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5C96A021216428A8AC5622AB5E50269"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$18,232,593 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H381C9DAF1F684D90B2E6CA79B505636B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>In this title, the term <quote>eligible entities</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HC9E677279A354215BCC3A6C5C631C3B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A4DB1CD97774ACAACD6F57BBB6685F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a National Laboratory;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64EEED47C9ED4DF2A2C9442B443CA9F8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a NOAA Cooperative Institute;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FC1EE52C49B40BAB4AA7CDEFDB6C87E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a State, local, territorial, or Tribal government agency;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10FF5674ABD340CBB5830D752D4BE92E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7921F530FD744332B2699CE2E32C4A23"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a private sector entity; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC91A54FEF9F4043AACDE44B4D650947"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a consortium of 2 or more entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (F).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H0431FBC4A92E4E918C58A7F9E9557B24"><enum>IX</enum><header>Federal Aviation Administration Activities</header><section id="H377282197F8E4F138B5C9FBE55F4B785"><enum>901.</enum><header>Federal Aviation Administration research and development</header><subsection id="HF70103CB044F43529F781684E0995A82"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in coordination with the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and the heads of other Federal agencies, shall carry out and support research, development, testing, and demonstration activities to—</text><paragraph id="HA587FDB7B39B4D88ADF768CD51025ACE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advance advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4F452293C34417FA10C42927A55E6CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate the safe integration of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems into the national airspace system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H19E1DBAC664B42F58D485387BF4E4CE1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Lessons learned</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall apply lessons learned from unmanned aircraft systems research, development, demonstration, and testing to advanced air mobility systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7C605D7C78C94FA3AA080860DA1EF7AC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unmanned and manned aircraft safety research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the activities under subsection (a), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall conduct comprehensive research and testing for advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems safety, including—</text><paragraph id="H63A200B71F9A462CB7587C3B41CFF457"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collisions between advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems of various sizes, traveling at various speeds, and commercial jet airliners of various sizes, traveling at various speeds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C54927644BA4C3BBF3B20646F702427"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collisions between advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems of various sizes, traveling at various speeds, and propeller planes of various sizes, traveling at various speeds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1983BE426CC48A28AF8376EB3121CAF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>collisions between advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems of various sizes, traveling at various speeds, and blimps of various sizes, traveling at various speeds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE3A3A502DEB4EE4AF811459FC801FF9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>collisions between advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems of various sizes, traveling at various speeds, and rotorcraft of various sizes, traveling at various speeds; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2A297E82E4344B39FE3B1785F6DEAD1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>collisions between advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems and various parts of the aircraft specified in paragraph (1) through (4), including—</text><subparagraph id="H9AB74CF471D24FBC87EA9B0C11642DAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>windshields;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63502688159E4FFCADD54CDE124CB277"><enum>(B)</enum><text>noses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H388E8B98BD1D4F63BAF5BA6175478801"><enum>(C)</enum><text>engines;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3127406D357A4D45B6E735B630678080"><enum>(D)</enum><text>radomes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38159F3E61B345078008B8B899355A68"><enum>(E)</enum><text>propellers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FE179F0719440D7BAB9FCFE034A4804"><enum>(F)</enum><text>wings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31558B6CB1B64097BB79E5F0D93E3640"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report summarizing the costs and results of research under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2A8BF0C59AA4449E9B508C07DDE611D5" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall commission an independent study to—</text><paragraph id="H04926E7D1F5D44C9836F88E992650E6A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop parameters to conduct research and development for probabilistic metrics to enable the identification of hazards and the assessment of risks as necessary to make determinations under section 44807 of title 49, United States Code, that certain advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems may operate safely in the national airspace system; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB3985FECF4640DB8C608351534D547C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify additional research needed to more effectively develop and use such metrics and make such determinations.</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection" commented="no">In developing parameters for probabilistic metrics, the study conducted pursuant to this subsection shall take into account the utility of performance standards to make determinations under section 44809 of title 49, United States Code. The Administrator shall consider the results of the study when making a determination under such section 44809.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="HEDD8222FEAEB4F5A8104F7D3204EFAFF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Study submission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than nine months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate the results of the study conducted under subsection (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCA5092E0BDBE48AEA4378BC9887B3732"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Probabilistic assessment of risks</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall conduct research and development to enable a probabilistic assessment of risks to inform requirements for standards for operational certification of public advanced air mobility systems and unmanned aircraft systems in the national airspace.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB598DAEDEBF94671818C32CF5DAD5D2D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Support for institutes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration may support one or more institutes described in section 201(a) for the purpose of advancing the field of unmanned aircraft systems and supporting the mission of the Administration.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9B363C5AEC4049C8AF5155B7C8586AAC"><enum>902.</enum><header>University unmanned aircraft systems and advance air mobility centers</header><subsection id="H727C21D6F15C4336A1C8FAF82FB2F096"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants for establishment and operation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall make grants to one or more institutions of higher education to establish and operate one regional university advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft system center in each of the ten Federal regions which compromise the Standards Federal Regions established by the Office of Management and Budget in the document entitled <quote>Standard Federal Regions</quote> and dated April 1974 (circular A–105).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0AF2FB62EFC54DA0AF23496E449B212D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The responsibilities of the unmanned aircraft systems and advanced air mobility center established under this section shall include the conduct of advanced air mobility research and research concerning safely integrating unmanned aircraft systems into the national airspace system and the interpretation, publication, and dissemination of the results of such research. The responsibility of one such center may include research on detection and avoidance capabilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H251D04D1EC344A3D80B64B24AD5020B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An institution of higher education interested in receiving a grant under this section shall submit to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration an application in such form and containing such information as the Administrator may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD6A4BC5954834994B418EE633393288B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall select recipients of grants under this section on the basis of the following criteria:</text><paragraph id="HD32FC12013BA467D9113CA44B51659CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The grant recipient shall have demonstrated research and extension resources available for carrying out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45F7A5BFD953448F8033AF7C677E57DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The grant recipient shall have demonstrated its capability to provide leadership in making national and regional contributions for addressing long-range and immediate advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems issues.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4301849E5EF4E398B81C28641D03370" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The grant recipient shall have an established advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems or related research program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F2F069956C24FE4899C2B9C047D1729"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The grant recipient shall have a demonstrated commitment to supporting ongoing advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11A81AA6BEC34C08B242C8E7551CECC2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The grant recipient shall have demonstrated ability to disseminate results of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems research and educational programs through a statewide or regionwide continuing education program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E159716133C444BBDEBB718310655E5" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>In making a selection of a grant recipient, the Administrator shall consider the projects which the grant recipient proposes to carry out under the grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEDE0551DFC8243CC8ABAA59696A11AD6" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Location</header><text>The unmanned aircraft system and advanced air mobility center shall be located in a State which is representative of the needs of the Federal region for improved advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems test facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3394D7AFAB8A42928AB0D02E9953F19B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of a grant under this section shall be 75 percent of the costs of establishing and operating the regional center and related research activities carried out by the grant recipient.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC26A7108AC9A483F8BDDAD9CF3B0947E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>National advisory council</header><paragraph id="HE6D680C089C448CFBF2780F343743ED9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment; functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall establish in the Administration a national advisory council to—</text><subparagraph id="HC943D4830D4B403E99128C00D42924BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate the research and training to be carried out by grant recipients;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AA6F623E2AE4D5796980CF99F9F487A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disseminate the results of such research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B2CADE2BF3B448CA33FF0C1154DB97E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>act as a clearing house between such centers and the advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems industry; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C18E9A22A884D2A96DB57FC869AA49D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>review and evaluate programs carried out by such centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D775965F57A4031A1A0974E5CDF7F2F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The national advisory council established under this subsection shall be composed of the directors of the advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems centers and 19 other members appointed by the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H0146522B3990417A86300462CD1E831A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Six officers of the Federal Aviation Administration, of whom—</text><clause id="H787F5A58D0D441D39B1B86B795AB3F12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>one represents the Office of the Administrator;</text></clause><clause id="HE3451B93E4B945F3BBC762FE5BFD819D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>one represents the Unmanned Aircraft Systems Integration Office;</text></clause><clause id="HFC3FA23DCC884212A06ABFDF9F48CF13"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>one represents the Office of NextGen;</text></clause><clause id="HB13DEF3B483C423784C49C8B32C9B50E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>one represents the Office of Aviation Safety;</text></clause><clause id="HBE4D055236E148DB9A1BD9AB30932B81"><enum>(v)</enum><text>one represents the Office of Air Traffic Organization; and</text></clause><clause id="H8F7D49237DA140BD85EF62DE90543D36"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>one represents the Mike Monroney Aeronautical Center.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30257D9FF82E4C9D9B75E3ACB3814B01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Five representatives of State, local, Tribal, or territorial governments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6E84E46F09E42E09537FB6A8CE3D63E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Eight representatives of the unmanned aircraft systems industry, including private industry.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FAEC2E200A542DA868B308269D6395B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Term of office; pay; chairman</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each of the members appointed by the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall serve without pay. The chairman of the national advisory council shall be designated by the Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C4D81DD68D148BF8DAAC66FACEAE3BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The national advisory council shall meet at least annually and at such other times as the chairman may designate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75E2170BD7F4B9D8FAF44E5112CEE7B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Agency information</header><text>Subject to subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, the national advisory council may secure directly from any department or agency of the United States information necessary to enable it to carry out this subsection. Upon request from the chairman of the council, the head of such department or agency shall furnish such information to the council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D6ABE5315B14605BA872F984FC1484C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Termination date inapplicable</header><text>Section 14 of the Federal Advisory Committee Act shall not apply to the council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A692D0999EF489F8E846C1FC52B092E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Allocation of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall allocate funds made available to carry out this section equitably among Federal regions.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE65E33431FBD44D89BD8A2DB300D077B"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Technology transfer set-Aside</header><text>Not less than five percent of the funds made available to carry out this section for any fiscal year shall be available to carry out technology transfer activities.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDDB4B27B32EF46D8B7CDE12E7DA7F875"><enum>903.</enum><header>Allowance for the purposes of research and development</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as necessary to support enforcement action under applicable provisions of law against persons operating an advanced air mobility system or unmanned aircraft in a manner that endangers the safety of the National Airspace System, and notwithstanding any other provision of law relating to the incorporation of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems into Federal Aviation Administration plans and policies, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration may not promulgate any rule or regulation regarding the operation of an unmanned aircraft system—</text><paragraph id="HBA65C34BAECF4B09A92BD2C7585E6CF7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that is flown strictly for research and development use;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01E12EE346074F5285EA489E0969480B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is operated less than 400 feet above the ground and in Class G airspace;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4410ACDC05B44F8B6A058DE10305CE4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that is operated in a manner that does not interfere with and gives way to any manned aircraft; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8758E141927456B9034445395E1B502"><enum>(4)</enum><text>with respect to which, in any case in which the unmanned aircraft system is flown within five miles of an airport, the operator of the aircraft provides the airport operator and the airport air traffic control tower (when an air traffic facility is located at the airport) with prior notice of such operation, including by establishing a mutually agreed upon operating procedure in cases with respect to which such unmanned aircraft system is flown from a permanent location within five miles of an airport.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H904AD334D709440D954DC70F8B642BC3"><enum>904.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="H45B27C1964EB4D819A1F2C0ED0CC81A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal Aviation Administration research and development funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to carry out section 901—</text><paragraph id="H6F2DA87258444AB080AFB5648C767352"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$20,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7088C7F5C40F47EAA1721B0A1BD217CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$21,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D91B9560F7146648BC6D65F46E3AB6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$22,050,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H447FC9E3DC3D4646B7268FCFE40770ED"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$23,152,500 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H897AA692F0BB41D1B8E65B91DD8DF69F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$24,310,125 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD82C510D3B5D4774BD1C90311BF09E8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>University unmanned aircraft systems center funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to carry out section 902—</text><paragraph id="H53F6DC4894DF411186CE1EF6C3D75435"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$100,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5690C23B82034FA49830E0E2F5FF89EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$105,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFA2860C144D46BB9B8E8EBCEE399ACA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$110,250,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D3E881BB9604FB19301454EF1E83EEA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$115,762,500 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7586CBA75D0B4F0CA67F4B7B1C877892"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$121,550,625 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HDBFEFACBB8DC4C55B54B22A8C94E3673"><enum>X</enum><header>Limitation</header><section id="H941EF5AAD95E4A4CB136FCC620702E01"><enum>1001.</enum><header>Limitation</header><subsection id="HBB73712E2334424C89F0EB8FCB51FE7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, none of the funds authorized to be appropriated by this Act may be used for the purchase, acquisition, or operation of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems—</text><paragraph id="HDAA4D7F2225F4345B5730EC1F7EED585"><enum>(1)</enum><text>produced or assembled in, or containing components produced or assembled in, a foreign country of concern; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF16A342E328477B89099F8AF5C22D5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>produced or assembled by entities owned, controlled by, or subject to the jurisdiction or direction of the government of, a foreign country of concern.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H597C568B9D3D436DACDB69D0C3347755"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The limitation in subsection (a) shall not apply to the acquisition of advanced air mobility and unmanned aircraft systems for the purposes of research and development for improving the United States counter-unmanned aircraft systems capabilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H44175BCB504842A494C5FD9DD9573008"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce may waive the limitation in subsection (a) if the Secretary determines, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence, that such waiver is in the national security interest of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H51235B9DCE3A4A63B99E402553DB160C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall report the issuance of such a waiver to the relevant committees of jurisdiction of Congress not later than 30 days after issuing such waiver.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7781D5E4BFAB42CDA323581CB145237D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>foreign country of concern</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HD03F419932A7417AB3D4F8413E22D15C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a country that is a covered nation (as defined in section 4872(d) of title 10 United States Code); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA119AAD5E0C9410099BDCE0E47B1DF61"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any country that the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Director of National Intelligence, determines to be engaged in conduct that is detrimental to the national security or foreign policy of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

