<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD2139C8A6704AE5A936B52DAA6F7B7F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5341 IH: Family Farmer and Rancher Tax Fairness Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5341</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230905">September 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To exclude from gross income certain assistance provided to farmers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF349998A02084889A427E37B8056CB8B" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H0C7A716F421C4E7EA239211F2D614F25"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Family Farmer and Rancher Tax Fairness Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3D32E076250B44BF984E8A8D5190727B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tax treatment of certain assistance to farmers, etc</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, in the case of any payment described in section 1006(e) of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (as amended by section 22007 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>) or section 22006 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>—</text>
<paragraph id="HF20C83D910154B8DA5DA365F2834507E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such payment shall not be included in the gross income of the person on whose behalf, or to whom, such payment is made,</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC98F1C3D26A434C9AF1CC7020B92324"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no deduction shall be denied, no tax attribute shall be reduced, and no basis increase shall be denied, by reason of the exclusion from gross income provided by paragraph (1), and </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H70677D36E1064A8ABE577918B5FB4484"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the case of a partnership or S corporation on whose behalf, or to whom, such a payment is made—</text> <subparagraph id="HADF5159001184767A448F43DB41E50F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any amount excluded from income by reason of paragraph (1) shall be treated as tax exempt income for purposes of sections 705 and 1366 of such Code, and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H22564FB07B5047A9B91B7E2F75ECE63F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>except as provided by the Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary’s delegate), any increase in the adjusted basis of a partner’s interest in a partnership under section 705 of such Code with respect to any amount described in subparagraph (A) shall equal the partner’s distributive share of deductions resulting from interest that is part of such payment and the partner’s share, as determined under section 752 of such Code, of principal that is part of such payment. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

