<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6057B3E33BFF4884B2B7B9AA764EAC52" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2637 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to waive the early withdrawal penalty on certain distributions from qualified retirement plans.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2637</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230417">April 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to waive the early withdrawal penalty on certain distributions from qualified retirement plans.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H82110251D8094994B9BE1AB3DB270CE7" style="OLC"><section id="H7C265B096E744813B64330FADEC849F6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Waiver of early withdrawal penalty on certain distributions from qualified retirement plans</header><subsection id="H93AB0C2A9D7547789C4A5DE5CF1B5C17"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/72">Section 72(t)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended to add at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H18CCB18A2ED74EE9BDED7C294EF2ACA1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H981FAE540BE34487998DD37882D0E394"><enum>(O)</enum><header>General exemption amount</header><clause id="HB1E39AD1E48049EC90F18E0B40EEB2C2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any distribution (other than a distribution to which paragraph (1) does not apply without regard to this subparagraph) from an applicable eligible retirement plan (as defined in subparagraph (H)(vi)(I)) of any individual to the extent that such distribution does not exceed the excess of $10,000 over the aggregate amount of such distributions made from all such plans of such individual during the 5-year period ending on the date of such distribution.</text></clause><clause id="H84F38778DA2A4046B74463FD36096517"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Treatment of plan distributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An applicable eligible retirement plan (as defined in subparagraph (H)(vi)(I)) shall not be treated as failing to meet any requirement of this title merely because the plan allows a distribution to an individual, unless the aggregate amount of such distributions (other than distributions allowed without regard to this clause) from all plans maintained by the employer (and any member of any controlled group which includes the employer, determined as provided in subparagraph (H)(iv)(II)) to such individual during the 5-year period ending on the date of such distribution exceeds $10,000.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HE81B0F34BA69412499455C5460431637"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to distributions made after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

