<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H75BA053B7AA0411789922B2C5C9861B9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2463 IH: Junk Fee Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2463</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230403">April 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To limit and eliminate excessive, hidden, and unnecessary fees imposed on consumers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAAA8A4596B314310ABEBE62AA6A3FC86" style="OLC"><section id="H0543C45F9B314F56ABB092921900C9B9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Junk Fee Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9C6792C56D0F48F99BE930C4C85ECEE0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protecting consumers from excessive and hidden fees</header><subsection id="HBCD53B0179B2412E8B4266A09CCAE692"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Protecting consumers from hidden fees</header><text>A covered entity shall clearly and conspicuously display, in each advertisement and when a price is first shown to a consumer, the total price of the good or service provided by the covered entity, including any mandatory fees a consumer would incur during the transaction, which shall not change during the purchase process.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95BB78F89530451F8C0BC9ACE921B6DB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Excessive fees</header><text>A covered entity shall not impose on a consumer or advertise any mandatory fees that are excessive or deceptive for any good or service offered by the covered entity.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E2D3CB13D44442C9678C50EC6B3A256"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Ticket holdbacks</header><text>If a good or service provided by a covered entity is a ticket to a sporting event, theater, musical performance, or an event at a place of public amusement of any kind, the covered entity shall, not less than 72 hours prior to the first public sale or presale of such ticket, clearly and conspicuously disclose to the public, including at the point of sale, the total number of tickets offered for sale by the covered entity or available for the given event.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07520267D2414543ABC12183FF9C03F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Protecting refunds</header><text>A covered entity shall clearly and conspicuously disclose any guarantee or refund policy prior to the completion of a transaction by the consumer and, in the event of a refund, provide a refund in the amount of the total cost of the ticket including any mandatory fees.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF6EB5577EBA44D3DBCA1C1F8F93B9086"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Speculative ticketing</header><text>If a covered entity does not possess a ticket at the time of the sale, it shall provide to the consumer—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8A7309C2BB4484C8385A5B9D12648EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a clear and conspicuous notice that the covered entity does not possess the ticket; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F7772B1305847C8841038E4323289E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full refund if the covered entity cannot provide the ticket advertised to the consumer in a timely manner prior to the event.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59E61DDBB77C472E873B94DCA598D211"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rulemaking on excessive and hidden fees</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission may promulgate rules in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, regarding the disclosure and imposition of mandatory or deceptive fees, including any such fee not described in subsections (a) through (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H07915A2E775744248AA16FF23058E13E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Excessive fees</header><text>In considering whether a mandatory fee is excessive, the Federal Trade Commission or court shall take into consideration—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE112B8E3811D4B07ABD6B74A6DDA7CA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the fee is reasonable and proportional to the cost of the good or service provided by the covered entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8E8CB5A0C44469897EC009021300755"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reason for which the covered entity charges such fee; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FC2735CA27B4DC894C96C93B617C579"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other factors determined appropriate by the Federal Trade Commission or the court. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H39DE888EB5AE491892BC91A261921277"><enum>(h)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Enforcement</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H72B9BE573D7A4ECEA45DA068BA580B91"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Enforcement by the Commission</header><subparagraph id="HB6E5AE1AA19F4E2D85267A152B7738C6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder shall be treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7511C984E7A94F6E9BC0456799082350"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Powers of the Commission</header><clause id="H227D2F299AA04A2887C11A19D4336A96"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section.</text></clause><clause id="H0B15D0AD2E534290856A6D6FE71B8814"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Privileges and immunities</header><text>Any person who violates this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause><clause id="H5C29B4727B274AC9AB415B0DDC04BEDB"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Authority preserved</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the authority of the Federal Trade Commission under any other provision of law.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33B98D7B578B4AE5AE537209C0B32580"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement by States</header><subparagraph id="H578DB977DE8B46B1B6F54EE4786F2673"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the attorney general of a State has reason to believe that a covered entity has violated or is violating this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder that affects the residents of that State, the State, as parens patriae, may bring a civil action in any appropriate district court of the United States, to— </text><clause id="H08B3C74F2CF44765AE605D1D24E6DE61"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enjoin any further violation by the covered entity;</text></clause><clause id="HB120480E227149A78005994E1070F54E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enforce compliance with this section or such regulation;</text></clause><clause id="H49E0721CD89C44A68F00D824180D0E46"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>obtain other remedies permitted under State law; and</text></clause><clause id="H14F1892526404CCBB2F24710A10D959F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E85D9008D4F47BBB7DFB60DA6378581"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The attorney general of a State shall provide prior written notice of any action under subparagraph (A) to the Commission and provide the Commission with a copy of the complaint in the action, except in any case in which such prior notice is not feasible, in which case the attorney general shall serve such notice immediately upon instituting such action.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F38BAE89E7C4C94981CDE252EFB1494"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Intervention by the Commission</header><text>Upon receiving notice under subparagraph (B), the Commission shall have the right—</text><clause id="H9341D6E0654C47C0BCF959C4055A8233"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to intervene in the action;</text></clause><clause id="H1B231F579B4E4AD6A6AA8B3BB614B0DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>upon so intervening, to be heard on all matters arising therein; and</text></clause><clause id="HEADF0FC2A93A44C5958B877033AF0340"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to file petitions for appeal.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AE0709100BD4C75B7B1BBDA4BE884E7"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation on State action while Federal action is pending</header><text>If the Commission has instituted a civil action for violation of this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder, no State attorney general, or official or agency of a State, may bring a separate action under subparagraph (A) during the pendency of that action against any defendant named in the complaint of the Commission for any violation of this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder that is alleged in the complaint. A State attorney general, or official or agency of a State, may join a civil action for a violation of this section or a regulation promulgated thereunder filed by the Commission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE07930C5CBF476CA0F881AAE55F9018"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>For purposes of bringing a civil action under subparagraph (A), nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent the chief law enforcement officer or official or agency of a State, from exercising the powers conferred on such chief law enforcement officer or official or agency of a State, by the laws of the State to conduct investigations, administer oaths or affirmations, or compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and other evidence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B990D751429498FAF8DDBA6273A5E63"><enum>(i)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H345802D52A374A318894740B455D9313"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA61EEBA0BAA4E609C5D89176A358B5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered entity</term> means—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H319BE9F8F37941FC99F80623A678A7C5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a provider of short-term lodging or an entity that advertises rates or the purchase of short-term lodging;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B9F398741BD4BAC8A40E86A575F738A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a provider of a ticketing service that sells tickets for an event or retains the authority to otherwise distribute tickets for such event, whether as a primary seller of tickets or in the secondary marketplace for ticket sales; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H85606805DD4C4A0293176D502B6D9396"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other entity determined appropriate by the Commission through a rulemaking in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H79C0A38FDA4841B99CB6ACF9D11987C7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Short-term lodging</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>short-term lodging</term> means any lodging that is offered for an occupancy of less than 6 months.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EA3EA3E551D47F78680C61721D54729"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mandatory fee</header><text>The term <term>mandatory fee</term> includes—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5711AE129D734DDA8AA2EF4FF4E5571A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any fee or surcharge that a consumer is required to pay to purchase a good or service being advertised;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23E1C9254AFA4D41AC90E10BF5948EFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a fee or surcharge that is not reasonably avoidable;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H14544E1FF7C84645BBE9323E00C0013E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a fee or surcharge for a good or service that a reasonable consumer would not expect to be included with the purchase of the good or service being advertised; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF01E07ED82C84D75A50B7C88B25FEDF8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other fee or surcharge determined appropriate by the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="HBC18916AD7DC4EEABE4DAFD716617C6E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Communications service fees</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6A9EFCA06D94653AB5B6A12A9BD7061"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ending early termination fees</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2463E7A4AB094BF6BF14799799E8D20F"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>A provider of a covered service may not charge a fee to, or impose a requirement that is excessive or unreasonable on, a consumer for the early termination of a covered service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AE02475E9DB4F8E938286AF7D535448"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Device purchase and return</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not prevent a provider of a covered service from charging a consumer for—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04FB7C939DF147739A90A8AE3102D4A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cost of rental or loan equipment that is not returned to the provider within a reasonable period of time; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0234EF3057948E696E7D60BFDA10FC1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the outstanding cost of a purchased device.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF4E8179784F4C6E971B23E45A3FED25"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Communications Commission may promulgate regulations to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF71683FDAE1C4EDBA6393F6FA304B97D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking on mandatory fees</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall commence a rulemaking proceeding—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7DC74583394445068928E9F2E1A5878D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to consider whether and how the Federal Communications Commission should—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC4F159D8981442DB4532127AE657F18"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require the disclosure of mandatory fees with respect to a covered service; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H373F957DD13F47D99413B2105E28F55D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prohibit the imposition of mandatory fees with respect to a covered service, in particular any such fee that a consumer would reasonably assume to be included in the advertised price of such service; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C5B8F66B56E42779FB4CA39C89A3575"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in which the Federal Communications Commission may promulgate regulations to implement the requirements or prohibitions described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75F84949C2E1429583CBA56F676DE3A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph id="HD41B8D72C90E4631BE0B325C5755F395"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be treated as a violation of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) or a regulation promulgated under that Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9011127E26AA4F74A00A0B43BD3D8F84" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Manner of enforcement</header><text>The Federal Communications Commission shall enforce this section and the regulations promulgated under this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H85650127713641C88B2E1FFE398529A6"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76EF6E2C9E2B46F7BCD5A24629B1DC1A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered service</term>—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F9F83B804D443ED8C04EC3F641AA315"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H870C3B1FE389433D94FB8728C3B7719A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">internet service;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02A7A62C7B8B44B6B092CDFD4053DE1E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>voice service (as defined in section 227(e)(8) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/227">47 U.S.C. 227(e)(8)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10D506089D794504B79E0BF462A4B35B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">commercial mobile service (as defined in section 332(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/332">47 U.S.C. 332(d)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7DABCFD13BF44F95B62253AEE46CB43D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>commercial mobile data service (as defined in section 6001 of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1401">47 U.S.C. 1401</external-xref>)); or</text></clause><clause id="HFC72A03BB6374AEF857897CD2DC87157"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a service provided by a multichannel video programming distributor (as defined in section 602 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/522">47 U.S.C. 522</external-xref>)), to the extent that such distributor is acting as a multichannel video programming distributor; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A29DAB3A31E4492A620409CB3BEC6C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any other service offered or provided as part of a bundle or package with any service described in clauses (i) through (v) of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE65B3B43BAA84DD6B2B6FCFD5E83C801"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mandatory fee</header><text>The term <term>mandatory fee</term> includes—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H393B0465261A4E90992BFACC4B8AADBB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any fee or surcharge that a consumer is required to pay to purchase a good or service being advertised;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD955B7B8E796485BB4B7BC61A1455E6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a fee or surcharge that is not reasonably avoidable;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4061E76F55874FAABB9CF1AD4EC67CC7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a fee or surcharge for a good or service that a reasonable consumer would not expect to be included with the purchase of the good or service being advertised; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB57E940F9F914F1187153712FCD78B4D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other fee or surcharge determined appropriate by the Federal Communications Commission. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7730FE5577CD45429A97FD4C9BDE2CFA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Seating young children adjacent to an accompanying adult passenger</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF848F1D7656D4361A241CEFE3A9084E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/417">chapter 417</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCF78A85A8FCB4554A15F2DA397430940"><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67E97B22B4974F55A4F63C27BED04C69"><enum>41727.</enum><header> Seating young children adjacent to an accompanying adult on aircraft.</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H63E3D5930FCD473D938112FAC1AE3EA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of this section apply for the purposes of each scheduled flight segment to or from any airport in the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3B09924CF7C149BA9CA4FA5C0ADE9F93"><enum>(b)</enum><header>General requirement</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C86B952A1B54D9199C8E7A79790C6C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assigned seats</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (f), an air carrier or foreign air carrier that assigns seats, or allows individuals to select seats, in advance of the date of departure of a flight shall seat each young child adjacent to an accompanying adult, provided that adjacent seat assignments are available at any time after the ticket is issued for the young child and before the first passenger boards the flight.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3188707197CB4046B62A616EB2488BFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Unassigned seats</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (f), an air carrier or foreign air carrier that does not assign seats or allow individuals to select seats in advance of the date of departure shall board customers in a manner that ensures each young child is seated adjacent to an accompanying adult.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H039389B5B9C84CF582D376E0F20F6F8F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H058D93F689D044FF85CDF0AACF745BEA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An air carrier or foreign air carrier may not charge a fee or impose an additional cost to seat a young child adjacent to an accompanying adult within the same class of service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2B6B3BAA3CA478FBE8A4B0466326B01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Class of service requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every class of service an air carrier or foreign air carrier offers must allow for seating of a young child adjacent to an accompanying adult. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2D397B9662E41C0B8D3DB99FBC200BF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prohibition on availability limits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An air carrier or foreign air carrier may not limit the availability of adjacent seats in a manner that results in an undue burden on the ability of a young child to receive an advance seat assignment adjacent to an accompanying adult.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2BD03BDBA9B244828FD6CD624FD79B6E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional requirements for advance seating</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA32A3F10E0A476F97769ACFBCC11A70"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Subject to subsection (f), an air carrier or foreign air carrier that allows individuals to select seats or that assigns seats at the time of booking a flight shall provide, not later than 48 hours after the issuance of the ticket for each young child—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB74F4CFD4BA144E3BF4C5E20D680F34E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a seat assignment for the young child adjacent to the seat assignment of an accompanying adult for each flight segment of the ticket at no additional cost, provided that adjacent seat assignments are available; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC1ACA545BC9141DC9B2246CC6F2CC340"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the event that adjacent seat assignments are not available as described in subparagraph (A), an accompanying adult the choice of—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF0F6441774F5494EA24C9979C2259B32"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full refund of the cost of the tickets for the young child and the accompanying adult, as well as any other individual on the same reservation; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5D3D06C0C4E445D885410FC73EA329B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">waiting for adjacent seat assignments to be provided by the carrier.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H795BD6E67A7C4C7EAB605EA05BA7DB09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required option period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The air carrier or foreign air carrier shall provide the accompanying adult a period of not less than 7 days from the date of notification of the choice described in paragraph (1)(B) to make a selection between the options described in clauses (i) and (ii) of such paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55731EC48BE34665BD5CCBA419B157AF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No available adjacent seat assignment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the event that an accompanying adult chooses the option described in paragraph (1)(B)(ii) and adjacent seat assignments for the young child and the accompanying adult on a ticketed flight segment do not become available before the first passenger boards the flight, the air carrier or foreign air carrier shall, at the choice of an accompanying adult—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE45A8416FA4E4278AE3BC96F000101E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rebook the young child and the accompanying adult, as well as any other individual on the same reservation, on the next available flight at no additional cost; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B8C73D6476B4AEC9979749D5237F098"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">transport the young child and the accompanying adult on their original ticketed flight segment in seats that are not adjacent, when seats on the aircraft are available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28DD4AE9AA9E441DB8EE0688F9ADD0F6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional requirements To mitigate passenger harm in event of violation</header><text>An air carrier or foreign air carrier that violates subsection (b) or (c) shall, at the choice of an accompanying adult—</text><paragraph id="H667AA06B4F194C908388B42D745AAA8C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>rebook the young child and the accompanying adult, as well as any other individual on the same reservation, on the next available flight at no additional cost; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24A49301EFC44C43984A9A710F0A06C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H87C49867B075406EA4C43AC938459E98"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full refund of the cost of the tickets for the young child and the accompanying adult, as well as any other individual on the same reservation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9EDDB8A1AB444066BC8184056696F263"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such individuals are at a connecting airport, return air transportation for such individuals to their origination airport at no additional cost; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FBC4406AADE4979B0BD1882F4671D91"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">transport the young child and the accompanying adult on their original ticketed flight segment in seats that are not adjacent, when seats on the aircraft are available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95F5EDB52C1E4830B8ED7F0C14DF81A5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2EBA5BB09EEF41B1B178D6220F6A36D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An air carrier or foreign air carrier that violates a requirement of this section is subject to civil penalties as set forth in section 46301 and other applicable remedies under this part.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9638E7641F64EE58E2BC2425D122E0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Investigations of complaints</header><subparagraph id="H4A622258BE024B338EB9D69273BAE3CD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall promptly investigate each complaint alleging a violation of this section that is received by the Department of Transportation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C0F7C17E2284315A7E1885B642914EF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Publication of data</header><text>The Secretary shall publish data on complaints alleging violations of this section in a manner comparable to other consumer complaint data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C90BEECD5994F7A80A379800A57AF87"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (b) and (c) shall not apply to the extent that—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B4DAD0DE3FF45EA8E03BD58656370F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the young child does not have an accompanying adult traveling with such child;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55E042416AEC44C4BD76BBA91E759FDA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an accompanying adult selects a seat apart from the young child or declines to accept a seat assignment or a seat that is adjacent to the seat assignment or seat of the young child offered without additional cost by the air carrier or foreign air carrier;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H233F2FC925314EA4B92CF86C2E5AC58D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of young children traveling in the same party make it impossible for the air carrier or foreign air carrier to seat all the young children adjacent to an accompanying adult based on the seat layout of the aircraft; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4F6E7DF62A6489AA15FF04BCE591DEE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an exception to subsection (b) or (c) deemed appropriate by final rule of the Secretary applies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59C264718711498B9D885E868FAA70F9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H54C9877E72D04BC79093765CB965B36A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Accompanying adult</header><text>The term <term>accompanying adult</term> means, with respect to a young child, an individual who is—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H682BE4057F834194ABA9E958CE1E11F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">14 years of age or older on the date of the scheduled departure of the flight; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H81A6D2CE37574E73A0EF51E78AF45917"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the same reservation record as the young child. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCC1B1B395C5245CCB428F131DB4D1BF0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Adjacent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>adjacent</term> means, with respect to the seat of a young child, a seat that is—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H40F06EBB37464F28B2D97B8C0A14D9D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">next to and in the same row of the aircraft as the seat of the young child; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C45ABC8B6A846679EDA8C5AE7AEABE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not separated by an aisle. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC06CAB73BD4418FBE07E3E7FC664E1F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Available</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>available</term>, when used in connection with seats or seat assignments, means capable of assignment by the air carrier or foreign air carrier without—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H968E8B10B1B04585A2902804A8D5F88B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an upgrade of a young child or an accompanying adult to a different class of service than ticketed; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0CBD5278D974EFD9D2AF5068F38510A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">displacing an individual with an assigned seat.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4678010C7BA84CEF9A8215D33C08AF7F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Class of service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>class of service</term> means first class, business class, general economy (including basic economy), or premium economy.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H684D24F4652547FD92BC9836818FF107"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No additional cost</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>no additional cost</term> means no added charge for the seat beyond the fare.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFE1BE9065A243A3B39176D8CA3F1E0F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0DD1651E82643038B2DFA93B4C57DDF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Young child</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>young child</term> means an individual who is 13 years of age or younger on the date of the scheduled departure of the flight. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AEE52592EBF4EC28C73D921B74CED4E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may issue regulations to implement this section, including regulations that amend the definitions in subsection (g).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H748743D126E14252AAC3F56F8494040B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H5D68154AE0A840828F586F101D45BEC7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/417">chapter 417</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/41726">section 41726</external-xref> the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H84C909461D3B4A6BB6D84345F80A8A5B"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H67E97B22B4974F55A4F63C27BED04C69">41727. Seating young children adjacent to an accompanying adult on aircraft.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H580FA89CA4B04526B830519F3358E394"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Repeal of FAA Extension, Safety, and Security Act of 2016 family seating provision</header><text>Section 2309 of the FAA Extension, Safety, and Security Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/42301">49 U.S.C. 42301</external-xref> note prec.) is repealed.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

