<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCD7A9D51EE3C4256ADE00558557F99FC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 282 IH: Infant Protection and Baby Switching Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 282</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require hospitals reimbursed under the Medicare system to establish and implement security procedures to reduce the likelihood of infant patient abduction and baby switching, including procedures for identifying all infant patients in the hospital in a manner that ensures that it will be evident if infants are missing from the hospital.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HAC33F772A5F84294879319E3640A1DD8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3DAA55F97EC940798AB7F3B7B3F4C007" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Infant Protection and Baby Switching Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDAF0183D16C3426D9EA7B8C0B3051079"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medicare payments to hospitals contingent on implementation of security procedures regarding infant patient protection and baby switching</header> <subsection id="H71C8AE78A75945209B9FC1E1DEA76EC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agreements With Hospitals</header><text>Section 1866(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H705673F3FC4D45C5B38239A9C4583D02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (W) and (X), by moving the margin of each subparagraph 2 ems to the left;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26C8DF8E757046478BC60C083347C08F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (X), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD90924B67BF54953AFBDC1C013EC5CF8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (Y), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11BEF25E5A464A78B835F7EFA9A23F07"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (Y) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H7462C9FAE0CA4547AE9085709808C42F" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H37B137D870514287880DBA6F8F57824B" indent="up1"><enum>(Z)</enum><text>in the case of hospitals and critical access hospitals that provide neonatal or infant care, to have in effect security procedures that meet standards established by the Secretary (in consultation with appropriate organizations) to reduce the likelihood of infant patient abduction and baby switching, including standards for identifying all infant patients in the hospital in a manner that ensures that it will be evident if infants are missing from the hospital.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB8844C80FB8B41AA80E5DF534EC93ECB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header> <paragraph id="HA89AABE7C5A84F6793B5B5EB4E990142"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In promulgating regulations under subparagraph (Z) of section 1866(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc(a)(1)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H75C5378337854DEF9DD67AFF6F277784"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consult with various organizations representing consumers, appropriate State and local regulatory agencies, hospitals, and critical access hospitals;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H002FF79FAA434830993B81EF23320AFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>take into account variations in size and location of hospitals and critical access hospitals, and the percentage of overall services furnished by such hospitals and critical access hospitals that neonatal care and infant care represent; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13AFF060EABC4B8FA20AC0340D9CEE36"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promulgate specific regulations that address each size and type of hospital covered.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E7C06022BB54D1BAC4CA9D2FDF8130D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for publication</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall publish the regulations required under paragraph (1). In order to carry out this requirement in a timely manner, the Secretary may promulgate regulations that take effect on an interim basis, after notice and pending opportunity for public comment.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H21F0B39EBB86448F83D9C0A75DCEE7E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header> 
<paragraph id="HBA62B59C89044286B60998DB016A24EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount of penalty</header><text>A hospital that participates in the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act under an agreement pursuant to section 1866 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc</external-xref>) that commits a violation described in paragraph (2) is subject to a civil money penalty of not more than $50,000 (or not more than $25,000 in the case of a hospital with fewer than 100 beds) for each such violation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14D7EEF916854E3481B63BFC73CB93BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Violation described</header><text>A hospital described in paragraph (1) commits a violation for purposes of this subsection if the hospital fails to have in effect security procedures that meet standards established by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 1866(a)(1)(Z) of such Act, as added by subsection (a), to reduce the likelihood of infant patient abduction and baby switching, including standards for identifying all infant patients in the hospital in a manner that ensures that it will be evident if infants are missing from the hospital.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD73D9B74889448C59A14BB96AF8D1C5F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header><text>The provisions of section 1128A of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320a-7a">42 U.S.C. 1320a–7a</external-xref>), other than subsections (a) and (b), shall apply to a civil money penalty under this subsection in the same manner as such provisions apply with respect to a penalty or proceeding under section 1128A(a) of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE540AC3E002E414992195C0780A737DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section, and the amendments made by this section, shall take effect on the date that is 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, and shall apply to contracts entered into or renewed under section 1866 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc</external-xref>) on or after such date.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H36371D148A994AEFA89C7D28A7938A44"><enum>3.</enum><header>Baby switching prohibited</header> 
<subsection id="HDD1BDFA0D53E42789B8CF3212555E1F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/55">Chapter 55</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HD23EF44E6A64428CA19FFF620FE85B8F" style="OLC"> <section id="HB7E2C429FB914779B9BFF3CB02C166FD"><enum>1205.</enum><header>Baby switching</header> <subsection id="H117EAC5AC6244EC9BBF793D26137613B"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Whoever being in interstate commerce knowingly alters or destroys an identification record of a newborn patient with the intention that the newborn patient be misidentified by any person shall be fined not more than $250,000 in the case of an individual and not more than $500,000 in the case of an organization, or imprisoned not more than ten years, or both.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HED738AF82A234485828502ADB59CBFF3"><enum>(b)</enum><text>As used in this section, the term <term>identification record</term> means a record maintained by a hospital to aid in the identification of newborn patients of the hospital, including any of the following:</text> <paragraph id="HC8AA5D55D6C14719B40D5DE5175F5456"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The footprint, fingerprint, or photograph of the newborn patient.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H828B6AD6E3FD4979A533CA8EFEA58491"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A written description of the infant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC03575EC44FA46CCB39F4BB3B43EA713"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An identification bracelet or anklet put on the newborn patient, or the mother of the newborn patient, by a staff member of the hospital.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8057615B81584B02ACA71835CFFFE4B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical Amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> <quoted-block id="HACEA1AC907614F34AC6BE16F4AC2CC2A" style="OLC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">1205. Baby switching.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

