<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEDFE819407D44F8EAE699C1263D4051E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1338 IH: Satellite And Telecommunications Streamlining Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1338</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to provide authority for certain licenses, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE805567D17DA4060A6DB276F72434AB1" style="OLC"><section id="HDBFFF21C4A5A4A33B2339536255D4F1A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Satellite And Telecommunications Streamlining Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAT Streamlining Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC012627832E435F94955A14BE9EBA3D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority regarding certain licenses</header><subsection id="H54937EC295F846FCBCFF108F8FB9C233"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text>Part I of title III of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/301">47 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H22EAE648AD504189A7FDFFB8B67689A4" style="OLC"><section id="HDEE69FD1C2BA472F83B5B789DDE6ACB5"><enum>346.</enum><header>Radiofrequency licensing authority regarding certain operations</header><subsection id="H2139BAC0C3174B06A0974314ABD02227"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rules</header><paragraph id="HD91B3CAD6C7B44CE924C09A6161A8160" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Commission shall issue rules to amend part 25 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations, to establish—</text><subparagraph id="H896B386F602B42A6B04C5C44E46BBEC1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any license granted under subsection (b) or grant of market access granted under subsection (c), specific, measurable, and technology-neutral performance objectives for space safety and orbital debris, in accordance with paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H984CDE4E2CA44C87A40A334494C77374" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for any license granted under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (b), specific modifications (or classes of modifications) to such a license that warrant expedited treatment under subparagraph (A) or (B) (as the case may be) of subsection (g)(2); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD39CE4C7A334C3B9EAF72AF24A1CCFC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any license granted under subsection (b), grant of market access granted under subsection (c), authorization granted under subsection (d), or covered authorization, the manner in which the licensee, grantee, or entity shall notify the Commission of a request to submit a modification under subsection (g)(5);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H099A9DE16E114037A342A6F242B2FC37"><enum>(D)</enum><text>for any request to modify a covered authorization, the manner in which the entity with the covered authorization shall indicate in the request whether the entity is seeking a modification described in subsection (h)(2)(B)(i)(I) or a modification described in subsection (h)(2)(B)(i)(II);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H195A7DFFCAAD44A7BF88BE3565D3C92A" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any license granted under subsection (b)(1), grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1), or covered authorization, in a spectrum band with service rules that require a licensee of such a license, a grantee of such a grant, or an entity with a covered authorization to share spectrum, specific actions taken by such a licensee, grantee, or entity with a covered authorization, or by any other entity that is authorized to use such shared spectrum, that constitute a failure to coordinate in good faith, including whether withholding from another such licensee, grantee, entity with a covered authorization, or other entity information necessary to coordinate in good faith that it is technically feasible to make available to such licensee, grantee, entity with a covered authorization, or other entity is such an action;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBACA9602284043E98A2F685945C22B7B" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any license granted under subsection (b)(1) or grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1), in a spectrum band with service rules that require a licensee of such a license or a grantee of such a grant to share spectrum (except with respect to the use of a gateway station), a quantifiable level of protection required under subsection (h)(4);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF64CA1B212704E5881A33CB8C026BCD3"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rules that—</text><clause id="H6CC1AF527DA244D28384710254B86C5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>clarify, for purposes of subsection (h)(1)(B), the protection from harmful interference that, during the covered period, an entity with a covered authorization that was approved in a processing round is required to provide to any other entity with a covered authorization that was approved in an earlier processing round; and</text></clause><clause id="H0BA5557C65D5480ABD8D28ADEB5D8C27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seek to promote competition, innovation, and efficient use of spectrum by entities with covered authorizations, including by accounting for advancements in technology capable of managing interference concerns to the greatest extent possible consistent with clause (i); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4659A64BFAA044CBB32DD10C20CD68AB"><enum>(H)</enum><text>for any application or request for modification described in subsection (n), what constitutes reportable foreign ownership for purposes of paragraph (1) of such subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9390EAFF389F4C148528A4C0475C8395" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conflict with interagency standard practices</header><text>In the rules issued pursuant to paragraph (1)(A), or any successor rule, the Commission may not establish performance objectives that conflict with any standard practice adopted by the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BEAA3EF4131465D823884C1B4DDB695"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application for license</header><paragraph id="HAE8C64CAA39C49D9B9E0A093EA093339"><enum>(1)</enum><header>NGSO determination required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (5) and subsection (m), not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for a license for radiocommunication services using—</text><subparagraph id="H84440BFCEBBF49E2BD098FF37C1AC140"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6A73426C12A40139731C14A323581B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a blanket-licensed earth station or earth stations that will operate with a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE28060F59946401483740F08E2F8FA6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations and the blanket-licensed earth station or earth stations that will operate with the nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDECE5BD1E854920AAD554EE38A1D90D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GSO determination required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (5) and subsection (m), not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for a license for radiocommunication services using—</text><subparagraph id="HD0D42AAB68B942BB93BEA2BCF2C1096F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a geostationary orbit space station or space stations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1158FBE1BEEA4377A50BBCB715C005C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a blanket-licensed earth station or earth stations that will operate with a geostationary orbit space station or space stations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H825854092AF849C6840C4FA86C1BA70A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a geostationary orbit space station or space stations and the blanket-licensed earth station or earth stations that will operate with the geostationary orbit space station or space stations. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1CD150E101C4B9493A386FE33E66F59"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents of application</header><text>In addition to the application requirements described in section 308(b), an application submitted under paragraph (1) or (2) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA5B92E2C56F2465BA6D84C1A9616C381"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Performance metrics with respect to the frequencies and transmission power to be used.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB06CE956884E40419071BF6742744DC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A demonstration of compliance by the applicant with the performance objectives established under subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36CE89F98B5F4D059FFE45364F1D1791"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an application submitted under paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H756A799D2BE544CFB1D439B62F5AE25D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of compliance by the applicant with the actions established under subsection (a)(1)(E); and</text></clause><clause id="H207C0E292838455EB8CD93ED69C48CF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a demonstration of compliance by the applicant with the quantifiable level of protection established under subsection (a)(1)(F).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H56F47F7DD1264A6F880DDB926CD6A87E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Term of initial license</header><text>The Commission shall grant a license for a term not to exceed 15 years for any application granted under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H284EA083ABE348B9A24E97395CE978C6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The deadline for the determination required in paragraphs (1), (2), and (6) may be extended by the Commission for an application subject to review under subsection (n).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7693BB7E3ECC4F49854EF58787F230EC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Timely grant of certain applications</header><subparagraph id="H57D5AB1E62EA4C4490312372ADA832AA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (5) and subsection (m), not later than 60 days after the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission for a license described in paragraph (1) with respect to which the applicant indicates in the application that the application meets the additional criteria described in subparagraph (B), the Commission shall—</text><clause id="H757F3372ECE24D6D98E454A773C1258F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine whether such application meets the additional criteria described in subparagraph (B); and</text></clause><clause id="H19FC194F81DA41AAA9E138785759A276"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the determination under clause (i) is affirmative, grant such application.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB76927C118154E078EE209DDC70D60FC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Criteria described</header><text>The additional criteria described in this subparagraph are as follows:</text><clause id="H890EC9AD2725472CA406BBA8272701F2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A limit on the number of space stations authorized by the license, as determined by the Commission.</text></clause><clause id="H7DC7EA5543C14895A739DD719137D9D2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A limit on the total in-orbit lifetime for any individual space station, as determined by the Commission.</text></clause><clause id="H181774D738FC4D7ABD51372099B9C663"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>For each space station, the following:</text><subclause id="H0F0648A9DEBB47B5986C561AE7972B90"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A limit on the orbital altitude at which the space station may operate, as determined by the Commission.</text></subclause><subclause id="HA6764003AD2F44DC882A7705C1CC6C6B"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that the space station has a maneuverability capability and the ability to make collision avoidance and deorbit maneuvers, as determined by the Commission.</text></subclause><subclause id="HA6AACBDE5DAC47F9A8E4AEF67307AF24"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that the space station is identifiable by a unique signal-based telemetry marker that meets requirements issued by the Commission.</text></subclause><subclause id="H73CD103F526F45DD95BE8EB07460F658"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>A requirement that the space station releases no operational debris.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC7856AA2033749EDA536F915F39B377D"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that the space station can be commanded by command originating from the ground to immediately cease transmissions and the applicant has the capability to eliminate harmful interference when required by the Commission.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H035FCB15BF9743DCB344EFF390B3351B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A requirement that the operator has assessed and limited the probability of an accidental explosion, including an explosion that results from the conversion of energy sources on board any space station into energy that fragments the space station.</text></clause><clause id="HA3B87B90DD6E491DA6510588E90DB280"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A limit on the probability of a collision between each space station and any other large object, as determined by the Commission.</text></clause><clause id="HC531E29ED6A74D64BC324FE6CDDF5558"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that each space station is disposed of post-mission and the probability of human casualty from disposal meets requirements issued by the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B0586F07A834BA8B9A30263B78B3027" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Criteria not met</header><text>If the determination under subparagraph (A)(i) with respect to an application is negative, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application under paragraph (1) by the deadline specified in such paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7C40C7C45414441AFC1256A302B07F1" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Evasion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An application does not meet the additional criteria described in subparagraph (B) if the Commission determines that, taken together with any other application or applications submitted by the applicant under subparagraph (A) (including an application that has been approved), such applications are submitted with the purpose of evading a negative determination with respect to such additional criteria.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC041A2CC9E484156B946FEB4053EF161"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section (other than this paragraph), any reference to an application submitted or granted or a license granted under paragraph (1) shall be construed to include an application submitted or granted or a license granted (as the case may be) under subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94A525B911354A9E81BEFA5B01F5EBBB"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Implementation</header><clause id="H006260C964FB472D978A775DA8C91393"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Commission shall—</text><subclause id="HBC55E3C11E4640DDAE51EB7EC92CC572"><enum>(I)</enum><text>issue rules to implement this paragraph; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H8130FE79D55C4E41BC1620C85FD06765"><enum>(II)</enum><text>make the finding described in clause (ii).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2D29867961B545C9814A666F0BAA0095"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Finding described</header><text>If the Commission finds that the rules of the Commission, as of the date of the enactment of this section, satisfy the requirements in this paragraph, the Commission shall issue a public notice stating such finding.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H560EE37942754EC5A22978E5493D97DF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application for grant of market access</header><paragraph id="H40C3F2A6633D4183A0D722905F13A4FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>NGSO determination required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for market access within the United States for radiocommunication services using—</text><subparagraph id="HE637B6452F0A4288B9F7F3AB8EFAF8DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD961218FE3974380B4C8F196CE0DEF65"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations and the blanket-licensed earth station or earth stations that will operate with the nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1ADB1B449A7409CA73077CAC5866080"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GSO determination required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for market access within the United States for radiocommunication services using a geostationary orbit space station or space stations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AB95506BE6E4B77A8D6B7057CE83254"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents of application</header><text>In addition to the application requirements described in section 308(b), an application submitted under paragraph (1) or (2) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7978E917D3464B42BFA6079F0E681908"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Performance metrics with respect to the frequencies and transmission power to be used.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BDFAAFA25B34DE3A89D6C1224D05FA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A demonstration of compliance by the applicant with the performance objectives established under subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E56951028CB4FC8B112DA37465DDFE9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an application submitted under paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H2E7817A7847D4194ADE1BFEF83C66EF0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of compliance by the applicant with the actions established under subsection (a)(1)(E); and</text></clause><clause id="H9A08A932D142465BB99BBC97D634F4D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a demonstration of compliance by the applicant with the quantifiable level of protection established under subsection (a)(1)(F).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6BF23375E744406B4DF24F16AE4A80E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Term of initial grant of market access</header><text>The Commission shall grant a grant of market access for a term not to exceed 15 years for any application granted under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAEF14958EF0E480C9DBB507FC4334851"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Earth station authorization</header><paragraph id="H2DD3C5480CAD4CBE812C4D3CDE15AD18"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination required for individually licensed earth stations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (4) and subsection (m), not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for authorization to use an individually licensed earth station.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9DE52CD1A2048CF9DECA727521B2834"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination required for receive-only earth stations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (4) and subsection (m), not later than 30 days after the date on which the Commission issues a public notice of the acceptance for filing of a written application submitted to the Commission, the Commission shall make a determination whether to grant such application for authorization to use an earth station or earth stations to receive a signal from—</text><subparagraph id="H4E33C4F8B87D4335964725EF81BA4CAF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations operated under a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB49A2442280B4E228B7C756168815E77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a geostationary orbit space station or space stations operated under a license granted under subsection (b)(2) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FD476251F0942C5A7F7665C7C4746D1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deemed granted</header><text>If the Commission fails to grant or deny a written application submitted under paragraph (1) or (2) by the deadline for the determination required by such paragraph (including any extension of such deadline under paragraph (4) or subsection (m)), the application shall be deemed granted on the date on which the Commission receives a written notice by the applicant of the failure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5472F726635E4B9F8F97245BBEAEFD71"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The deadline for the determination required by paragraph (1) or (2) may be extended by the Commission for an application subject to review under subsection (n).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35D91CD5F4B34B75B9B452D4F9C5312E" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Inapplicability to blanket-licensed earth stations</header><text>This subsection does not apply with respect to an earth station or earth stations to the extent that the earth station or earth stations will be blanket-licensed with a space station or space stations as described in subsection (b)(1)(B), (b)(1)(C), (b)(2)(B), (b)(2)(C), or (c)(1)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB5574E07FE84C199BBE00A98862D39B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Determination of public interest, convenience, and necessity</header><text>The Commission may not make a determination to grant an application, renewal, or modification under subsection (b), (c), (d), (f), or (g) (as the case may be) unless—</text><paragraph id="H361C65473AC849FE92D07CE4C2601815"><enum>(1)</enum><text>except in the case of a modification under subsection (g)(2), the Commission determines that the license, grant, or authorization (as the case may be) serves the public interest, convenience, and necessity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD07A0E14FB30444CB9584B80CDE7AFB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Commission determines that—</text><subparagraph id="H15DE36EAA9034B90909AE43FC0FD6791" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a licensee or grantee to which subsection (h)(4) applies—</text><clause id="H32161190277349B4B3B48E8B977D27C4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an application, except in accordance with a coordination agreement, the licensee or grantee will not, during the term of the license or grant, exceed the quantifiable level of protection established in subsection (h)(4) in operating under the license or grant;</text></clause><clause id="HB0D420EE63844E53B2FA7E47FC8086A9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a renewal, except in accordance with a coordination agreement, the licensee or grantee has not exceeded, during the preceding term of the license or grant, and will not exceed, during the term of the renewal of the license or grant, the quantifiable level of protection established in subsection (h)(4) in operating under the license or grant; and</text></clause><clause id="H3C265E75F86B4892B94C7B8B47287459"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a modification, except in accordance with a coordination agreement, the licensee or grantee has not exceeded, during the portion of the term of the license or grant preceding the determination, and will not exceed, during the remainder of such term, the quantifiable level of protection established in subsection (h)(4) in operating under the license or grant; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8514A0D4934542A1819C9CFF9162C416"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a licensee or grantee that is required to protect radio astronomy observatories by the International Telecommunication Union, the application, request for renewal, or request for modification demonstrates that the licensee or grantee will provide such protection in operating under the license or grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD82D34DBDCF847BDB5EB4266444D1288"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Renewal of license, grant of market access, or authorization</header><paragraph id="HFCA243FA32F341099E6541C06276B1C8" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in section 309(k)(2), the Commission shall grant a renewal for a license granted under subsection (b), a grant of market access granted under subsection (c), or an authorization granted under subsection (d), upon request by the licensee, grantee, or entity with such authorization (as the case may be), for a term not to exceed the length of the initial term beginning the day after the date on which the preceding term of the license, grant of market access, or authorization expires, if the Commission determines the requirements under subsection (e) and section 309(k) have been met.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA7BBCB953C743C78B897C84A0042049"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (m), not later than 180 days after the date on which the Commission receives a request for renewal of a license granted under subsection (b), a grant of market access granted under subsection (c), or an authorization granted under subsection (d), the Commission shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE023CC389AC64EEC9AEA13DC029E8F95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>grant such renewal; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCB812DED9E34D40A0DAAB7BDFAA0218"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make the determination described in section 309(k)(3) and deny such renewal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0629517D2C9F4D588AA72EFF96F1EB66"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Modification of license; grant of market access</header><paragraph id="H90FD1D593EC546B6BFF5320368BC4017" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Major modifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraphs (2), (3), (5), and (6) and subsection (m), and not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission receives a request to modify a license granted under subsection (b)(1), the Commission shall grant the request if the Commission determines the modification meets the requirements under subsection (e). Except as provided in paragraphs (2), (3), and (5), the Commission may grant a request to modify a license granted under subsection (b)(2) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c) if the Commission determines the modification meets the requirements under subsection (e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6AFA4B146AD469BA0EEC8830C9464F5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expedited treatment for minor modifications</header><subparagraph id="H37C27094C7274BF780CA2E7E6EE5483C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>NGSO license modifications</header><text>Except as provided in paragraphs (3), (5), and (6) and subsection (m), the Commission shall grant a request made by a licensee to modify a license granted under subsection (b)(1) not later than 90 days after the date on which the Commission receives the request to modify if—</text><clause id="H0728919B1C9B4484B2BAE416F5003649" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Commission determines that the modification or modifications meet the requirements (if applicable) under subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (e)(2); and</text></clause><clause id="H1872A100799B4578BF65C7619F4EF67C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the request is limited only to modifications, or a class of modifications, that—</text><subclause id="HA155192AD0224B44B4EE95643B26569A" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>increase transmission capacity;</text></subclause><subclause id="H79808F116B454621817469B42D6CC20B" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve spectral efficiency, such as by improving compression technologies;</text></subclause><subclause id="H12E9FCAF4AA04FDE9CD773D8F7F7D8DE" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve the orbital variance efficiency of the space station (or space stations, considered collectively, if there is more than one such space station) authorized by the license; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC7193C4FD2BD456E8AC5C8EC80EF5110" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise do not substantially modify the space station (or space stations, considered collectively, if there is more than one such space station) authorized by the license.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H036640C85CF64AA2BA61E3507AAE0D17"><enum>(B)</enum><header>GSO license modifications</header><text>Except as provided in paragraphs (3), (5), and (6) and subsection (m), the Commission shall grant a request made by a licensee to modify a license granted under subsection (b)(2) not later than 90 days after the date on which the Commission receives the request to modify if—</text><clause id="H470D959156CE48ECB270000C5CBFF73C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Commission determines that the modification or modifications meet the requirements (if applicable) under subsection (e)(2)(B); and</text></clause><clause id="H009DB8A701BA4558B189380D0613EAD9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the request is limited only to modifications, or a class of modifications, that—</text><subclause id="HEF813A152665444D8C4B8814D2060FF4" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>increase transmission capacity;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9C0C0B17BFF24DF3AAF6697884BBC0B9" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve spectral efficiency, such as by improving compression technologies; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H78CE5A97A23840EA8B3034E7975B5CBB" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise do not substantially modify the space station (or space stations, considered collectively, if there is more than one such space station) authorized by the license.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F8CA565A82548DDACE85BD851BCF537"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deemed granted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Commission fails to grant a request made by a licensee under subparagraph (A) or (B) by the deadline specified in such subparagraph (including any extension of such deadline under paragraph (6) or subsection (m)), the request shall be deemed granted on the date on which the Commission receives a written notice by the licensee of the failure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC1D78A66AF04784AE61E652DB762CD5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Emergency grant, renewal, or modification</header><text>If the Commission finds that there are extraordinary circumstances requiring temporary operations in the public interest and that delay in the institution of such temporary operations would seriously prejudice the public interest, the Commission—</text><subparagraph id="H29359B26AECA4D28B8D15C8747E96C71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may grant a license described in subsection (b), a grant of market access described in subsection (c), or an authorization described in subsection (d), a modification of such a license, grant of market access, or authorization, or renewal of such a license, grant of market access, or authorization for a period not to exceed 180 days in a manner and upon the terms the Commission shall by rule prescribe in the case of an emergency found by the Commission involving—</text><clause id="H5B65B075DFB649AC91806F6DB2B114AD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>danger to life or property; or</text></clause><clause id="H60F69774728248E59BE720063FD52A27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an action that is necessary for the national defense or security of the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2B202E947F6468A815DF318F1E12EC1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall include with a grant made under this paragraph a statement of the reasons of the Commission for making such grant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B0B0297C32C463890FB022BA7794F89"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may extend a grant made under this paragraph for periods not to exceed 180 days; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3617FA619D3142078A2919DF68ED8128"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall give expeditious treatment to any timely filed petition to deny such application and to any petition for rehearing of such grant filed under section 405.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EA19323CE3348EDBE49B52094D0820D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>Paragraph (2) shall not apply to a request to modify a license for—</text><subparagraph id="HC8A624EB0771464ABC3D6F50F7212258"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the addition of an ancillary terrestrial component; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1772BC4C6CF142CD91249A22743575F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>modifying the service offered under the initial license granted under subsection (b) between fixed satellite service and mobile satellite service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D0AB51BDEA94E1EA0E4739B95B54B9B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Automatic grant of certain modifications</header><text>Upon notification to the Commission, the Commission may automatically grant a request to modify a license granted under subsection (b), a grant of market access granted under subsection (c), an authorization granted under subsection (d), or a covered authorization, to replace—</text><subparagraph id="H16C11EACE91C4829956B01E13C64A38E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one space station (or component of such space station) with a technically similar space station (or component of such space station) previously approved by the Commission; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FA86DFF5CED44848035DF6A1789729D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one earth station (or component of such earth station) with a technically similar earth station (or component of such earth station) previously approved by the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E485872B77E405A902EB5935041E37C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The deadlines under paragraphs (1) and (2) may be extended by the Commission for a request subject to review under subsection (n).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF902629262043AE9A75D93D59372A5D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Shared spectrum; protection from harmful interference</header><paragraph id="HC1FDF66D8E34486895893D9B122F0E1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grandfathered treatment and sunset of certain authorizations</header><text>For the duration of the covered period—</text><subparagraph id="H76DD34A9DC3A4267B23B548A88FD8E7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a covered authorization shall not be treated as being granted under subsection (b)(1) or subsection (c)(1) (as the case may be); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F366EEE2AAF4B46BCC749DD57AFBF9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity with a covered authorization shall be afforded, and shall afford to any other entity with a covered authorization, protection from harmful interference that is consistent with the terms of such protection afforded before the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC6EAE3FBE264E48AF8E280A9DA86D91" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transitional rules</header><subparagraph id="H6D260C036DFE4D3C86A7E470E4371A1E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Renewal under this section</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity with a covered authorization may, at any time before the end of the covered period, seek renewal of the covered authorization under subsection (f) as if the covered authorization were a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1) (as the case may be). If the Commission grants the renewal, the renewal shall be treated as a renewal of a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1) (as the case may be).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FC4718FD41842DB80F880A5E57E4719" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Modification</header><clause id="H933D4EA24764413984ED6A2E3237C2FC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Indication of type of modification sought</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an entity with a covered authorization submits to the Commission a request to modify the covered authorization, the entity shall indicate in the request whether the entity is seeking—</text><subclause id="H12F9D8B51A6C4996B1529688DA173943"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a modification of the covered authorization under the law and regulations applicable to the covered authorization; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H21CA6962A40746BDA5B682BF6A454655"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a modification of the covered authorization under subsection (g) as if the covered authorization were a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1) (as the case may be).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF5A67A8FE3944C3297C6C1E9D5DF56B7" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Treatment</header><text>If the Commission grants a request to modify a covered authorization—</text><subclause id="H64372A0CCA2E42B192F3B0709FDC76FA" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a request for a modification described in clause (i)(I), the covered authorization as modified shall continue to be treated as described in paragraph (1)(A) and the entity with the covered authorization shall, with respect to the covered authorization, continue to be afforded, and to afford to any other entity with a covered authorization, the protection described in paragraph (1)(B); and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF9BEA10DFAA34E1EABA91AEBEC1B294A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a request for a modification described in clause (i)(II), the covered authorization as modified shall be treated as a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1) (as the case may be) with respect to which a request to modify has been granted under subsection (g).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0435D89C03B4FA4BB8B0C63F5AD21DB" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Good faith coordination of shared spectrum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date on which the rules issued pursuant to subsection (a) take effect—</text><subparagraph id="H872D3B97A8EC4A7D83E2F2354694F482" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a licensee of a license granted under subsection (b)(1), a grantee of a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1), or an entity with a covered authorization, in a spectrum band with service rules that require such a licensee, grantee, or entity to share spectrum, shall make a good faith effort to coordinate the use of such shared spectrum (including the use of such shared spectrum by an individually licensed earth station) with any other such licensee, grantee, or entity with a covered authorization and any other entity that is authorized to use such shared spectrum; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE60560119A9472E8E71680969AAFB47" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other entity that is authorized to use such shared spectrum shall make a good faith effort to coordinate the use of such shared spectrum with any such licensee, grantee, or entity with a covered authorization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H650A136A0AD54539BCC3D41AD4AE126F" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Protection from harmful interference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date on which the rules issued pursuant to subsection (a) take effect, for any spectrum band in which the Commission grants a license under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access under subsection (c)(1) and for which the service rules require such a licensee or grantee to share spectrum (except with respect to the use of a gateway station), the Commission shall establish a quantifiable level of protection that (except with respect to the use of a gateway station) such a licensee or grantee shall afford to any other entity (including an entity with a covered authorization but not including a licensee of a license granted under subsection (b)(2) or a grantee of a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(2)) that is authorized to use such shared spectrum.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21694C95B4C44CB3B4AAFAA160F65154"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consideration required</header><text>When establishing the quantifiable level of protection described in paragraph (4), the Commission shall, with respect to the entities to which the quantifiable level of protection is required under such paragraph to be afforded—</text><subparagraph id="H2F33D40AFECE4EA1AC81307FB1AFC481"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider protection of such entities based on a degraded throughput methodology, requiring that, except in accordance with a coordination agreement, a licensee of a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grantee of a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1) may cause no more than a certain percentage increase in the link unavailability of such an entity and may reduce the throughput of such an entity by no more than a certain percentage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1364D3855AA4C6FA43C4717A93525AF" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider protection of such entities from interference beyond a permissible interference-to-noise ratio, or whether interference-to-noise alone provides a sufficient level of protection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B04E9E79D7546E99020B058349BBEB3" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider protection of such entities from harmful interference by awarding a greater share of spectrum during in-line events to earlier-filed systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EC2358B334B45CCA17954E7C4B749B9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Relation to ITU radio regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require the Commission to adopt rules regarding the use of spectrum that contravene a requirement of the radio regulations of the International Telecommunication Union.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H217A773D20BF4691905C1FF6B0E70312" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity with a covered authorization shall not be required to submit additional information in order to retain such authorization, nor shall paragraph (1) affect any obligation of such entity under applicable law or regulation until the end of the covered period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA605AEBCB6A04D6FAA6FF8A15614A5A2" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>State preemption of market entry; rates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no State or local government shall have any authority to regulate the entry of or the rates charged by an applicant or licensee related to a license granted under subsection (b), an applicant or grantee related to a grant of market access granted under subsection (c), or an applicant or entity related to an authorization granted under subsection (d), except that this subsection shall not prohibit a State from regulating the other terms and conditions of such a licensee, grantee, or entity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H67B2A76870174DA4A0483785AA644ABF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Regulatory restraint</header><paragraph id="HFA6256A7AF4648FC90C5853ADD056E9C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation on information required to be provided</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In performing any act, making any rule or regulation, or issuing any order necessary to carry out this section, the Commission—</text><subparagraph id="H44166B1450A9454A85234765C24925E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall limit the information required to be furnished to the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD405D609CF0E43F49E1A3F89008633BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall demonstrate the Commission has taken every reasonable step to limit the information required to be furnished to the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E48FCC137054C07986D4DB8A4EB3DFD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not require, with respect to an application under subsection (b), (c), or (d), a request for renewal under subsection (f), or a request for modification under subsection (g), the filing of any information which previously has been furnished to the Commission or which is not directly material to the considerations that affect the granting or denial of such application or request (but the Commission may require any new or additional facts the Commission deems necessary to make its findings); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4219BE4C7D264685B73DB1BE909916DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>may not request additional information regarding the performance objectives established under subsection (a)(1)(A) for any case in which an applicant has demonstrated compliance with such performance objectives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5449C18709B5496496C24F1825FCCFB6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for petition determination</header><text>If an applicant for a license or a licensee under subsection (b) files a petition under part 1 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation) relating to information required to be furnished to the Commission under this section, the Commission shall grant or deny the petition within 90 days after the date on which the petition is filed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFF2FD31815DC4FB793E6C73D3CB8E31C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Relation to experimental and amateur uses</header><text>This section shall not apply to any Commission authorization in—</text><paragraph id="HF252AA67E70645B8B51CE410E26AAD10"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the experimental radio service; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5365B2BDF12B4316ADEABAA6EDA59F64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amateur radio service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6BFBC269D780469A80762025C9CB4C78"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Completeness</header><paragraph id="HAD3A2B4EB0904255832FF79AC2D8FE5C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 20 business days after receiving a written application submitted under subsection (b), (c), or (d), the Commission shall—</text><subparagraph id="H15039B8F95D34B1798A932B925353523"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine whether—</text><clause id="HA50CB80A97D4452FB6156665799BCBB0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such application contains—</text><subclause id="H4C83CE06D4BF49069E4C154AC79D50E9"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an application submitted under subsection (b), all of the information required to be submitted with the application under subsection (b)(3) and the first sentence of section 308(b);</text></subclause><subclause id="HE14FECF69C1B48F390C0C4D4FDC4D159"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an application submitted under subsection (c), all of the information required to be submitted with the application under subsection (c)(3) and the first sentence of section 308(b); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H6871E8E220E54D1487D7A8367ADA21F4"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an application submitted under subsection (d), all of the information required to be submitted with the application under the first sentence of section 308(b); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H7730BBCFEB45467C842A30DF825C5E07" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the applicant has paid the fee (if any) required under section 8 in connection with the application; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCB9B23CA6234DE79B9CB30E96D8D060"><enum>(B)</enum><text>either—</text><clause id="HA26B550F3F534155A5E696D03EF35F42"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if both determinations under subparagraph (A) are in the affirmative, issue a public notice of the acceptance for filing of such application; or</text></clause><clause id="H805376C5088E48AA914C86125DCB0EAC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if either determination under subparagraph (A) is in the negative, provide notice to the applicant of the negative determination, including what information that was required to be submitted was not submitted or the amount of the application fee due, or both (as the case may be).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F780311C6AE43CAA1F07A396E1B6CD4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inaction by Commission</header><text>If the Commission does not comply with paragraph (1) with respect to an application by the deadline specified in such paragraph, the Commission shall be deemed for purposes of subsection (b), (c), or (d) (as the case may be) to have issued a public notice of the acceptance for filing of such application on the date that is 21 business days after the date on which such application was received.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFF01A621EFB44B4ADAE362362EFE5C3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>In making a determination under paragraph (1)(A)(i), the Commission may only consider whether the application contains the information described in subclause (I), (II), or (III) (as the case may be) of such paragraph and may not consider whether the information is sufficient to allow the Commission to grant or deny the application.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H480C4FCBBC1F4803AE7B744E71BD373D" commented="no"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Tolling</header><paragraph id="HD3EEE72FBDFA46D9ADA834C55E63CA3A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsections (b)(5), (d)(4), and (g)(6), with respect to an application for a license under subsection (b) or an authorization under subsection (d), or a request for renewal under subsection (f) or modification under subsection (g) of a license granted under subsection (b), a grant of market access granted under subsection (c), or an authorization granted under subsection (d), the Commission may extend the deadline under subsection (b), (d), (f), or (g) (as the case may be) for consideration of the application or request only if the Commission—</text><subparagraph id="H040CF2CB38C54EEAB4075A4E8214C63F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>finds that there are extraordinary circumstances requiring additional time for consideration of the application or request such that, if the deadline were not extended, the public interest would be seriously prejudiced; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAA8E5EA39C44AF38B9DEA5BED3A09D8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>issues a public notice of the finding described in subparagraph (A) that states—</text><clause id="HA0B57ED6454A443C81F6D305D0AD5B40"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reasons of the Commission for the extension; and</text></clause><clause id="HA85BDABCF1824D4DBC8D118BDA923A19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the length of the period of the extension.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D8366AB31FF4E3085FFB46C19981474"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Length</header><text>The Commission may not grant an extension of a deadline under paragraph (1) for a period that exceeds 90 days but may grant 1 or more additional extensions of such deadline under such paragraph, if the Commission makes the finding and issues the public notice required by such paragraph with respect to any such additional extension.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3217E8F491534C7591AF8BA0D7FCA3E7"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Review for national security and law enforcement concerns</header><paragraph id="HAC6F0C54680A4F26A45024B727B6D9FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review required for entities with reportable foreign ownership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an application under subsection (b), (c), or (d), a request for modification under subsection (g), or a request for modification of a covered authorization that is submitted by an entity that the Commission determines to have reportable foreign ownership, the Commission shall refer such application or request to the Committee for the Assessment of Foreign Participation in the United States Telecommunications Services Sector established by Executive Order No. 13913 (85 Fed. Reg. 19643) (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Committee</quote>) for review of national security and law enforcement concerns that may be raised by such application or request.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA77399E23B8343EBB04B7848E0C839CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Review at discretion of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the applications and requests that the Commission is required to refer to the Committee under paragraph (1), the Commission may, in the discretion of the Commission, refer any other application under subsection (b), (c), or (d), request for modification under subsection (g), or request for modification of a covered authorization to the Committee for review of national security and law enforcement concerns that may be raised by such application or request.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H870B1628536A49B4B66819CFEE62BEB0"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Clarification relating to shared spectrum</header><paragraph id="HBFB40F0E1A3B40DC8B604159C9C451FE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><subparagraph id="H6D81A66F501041EB99C81EF8A0C5AA6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>spectrum shall only be treated as being shared if more than 1 entity described in paragraph (2) is authorized to use the same frequencies of such spectrum; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02A6DC21C9B54D9FB87AD18F69F4628B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the spectrum between the frequencies of 1617.775 megahertz and 1618.725 megahertz, inclusive, shall not be treated as being shared.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8891BD7A7E8743AD80ED2ACADA99F9EC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Entity described</header><text>The entities described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="HEC07C6D7FB22422FBE2A3111B29843E7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A licensee of a license granted under subsection (b)(1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAD1887F8E324886BF4B1D914AD0A9BE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A grantee of a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0434647171540FC84F8D11F4D7DE692" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An entity with a covered authorization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55A15E07EE754DD3845DA0D3CA1D7917" commented="no"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H883E15090604405BA42D0B5AC64178B7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered application</header><text> The term <term>covered application</term> means an application for a license or grant of market access to operate a system described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) or subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (c)(1) in a processing round established before December 31, 2022, that is pending on the date of the enactment of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87E2EC26EC594E13881A44EE3106AED4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered authorization</header><text>The term <term>covered authorization</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H94C0A0D4C3644699A6404235E6317E0D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a license or grant of market access granted by the Commission to operate a system described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) or subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (c)(1) in a processing round established before December 31, 2022; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE37A234723E24472A86A866443445A9A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a license or grant of market access granted by Commission approval of a covered application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC475764E7D984042A5D7E398D5F209CC" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered period</header><text>The term <term>covered period</term> means, with respect to a covered authorization, the period of time that begins on the date of the enactment of this section and ends on the earliest of—</text><subparagraph id="H9DBED0C588274978B911EEF120C9FCE5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the covered authorization expires;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FF56A9197A04237B66FE39E445B437B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date that is 15 years after such date of enactment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC91D8DD503D4828BAC042DB3986AE03"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the date on which the Commission determines that the licensee or grantee (as the case may be) has not either—</text><clause id="H4597B7DC4BBD4D9888CFEBA50F62F65E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">deployed a level of service commensurate with the terms of the license or grant of market access; or</text></clause><clause id="H4BF0589AAB7F4DA0BE6B4AAC28972E92"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise demonstrated progress and investment consistent with the deployment obligations under the license or grant of market access;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33B5709333FC4D7C90D6157D59C37CB3" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the Commission grants a request to renew the covered authorization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7F2FA76C0D246C39F281DF3BFB8281C" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the Commission grants a request for a modification of the covered authorization described in subsection (h)(2)(B)(i)(II).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8D67DBB643E4FFE82DDF50F9126F5FD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Gateway station</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>gateway station</quote> means an earth station or a group of earth stations that—</text><subparagraph id="HABB325E10664430F9B9BA3AE1AA3343E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supports the routing and switching functions of a system operated under a license granted under subsection (b) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22F0F779ABB8447BB41D02370D0FD1EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may also be used for telemetry, tracking, and command transmissions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D722F73D5C6455EB9EEC36355472994"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not originate or terminate communication traffic; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H515F1A5C8C78477787E538246B8704F8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is not for the exclusive use of any customer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC91D0F69BA4C4CAA96867CA3688E64ED"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Individually licensed earth station</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>individually licensed earth station</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6CAD704F4932465FAD23843EB4F7FF9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an earth station that sends a signal to, and receives a signal from—</text><clause id="HCC6977092559407389F979684E2CA27F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nongeostationary orbit space station or space stations operated under a license granted under subsection (b)(1) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(1); or</text></clause><clause id="H95651BB7C67540C1B232DDA7C672A847"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a geostationary orbit space station or space stations operated under a license granted under subsection (b)(2) or a grant of market access granted under subsection (c)(2); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H263C7D6253094B79B7A19D6E861BABEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a gateway station.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2459EF10166342CDBA6786F5373B1911" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Orbital variance efficiency</header><text>The term <term>orbital variance efficiency</term> means the mean of the distance between the actual altitude of each space station and the authorized altitude for each space station authorized under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H127F49F04A5E4740A900D0633138768C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Radiocommunication service</header><text>The term <quote>radiocommunication service</quote> has the meaning given such term in the radio regulations of the International Telecommunication Union that are in force as of the date of the enactment of this section (or any successor to such regulations).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H28C3566F4292417BA4DA69F2069ECA43"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Relation to other law amendments</header><text>The Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H489A7A1B1B36433AA1B08B3462DB2C49"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 309(j)(2)—</text><subparagraph id="H18CF68DA98D44AA3AB27213581281C57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63AACD7D21C747ACA5DF246E51D48120"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (D); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H936CD5CC5DB54CA6B93214CE077D1B66"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="H59313FA07DD54DFFA7FD32B682BBFD00" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H2E49C0CA56C8423A9F443037C3822F8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for licenses, grants of market access, or authorizations granted under section 346; or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BBBDF7D2C374EC18F46E544BC2AAC51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 309(k)—</text><subparagraph id="H7501FED56DE241359ED77DEE356AAC14"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Broadcast station renewal procedures</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Renewal procedures for certain authorizations</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EE6F9A6DF4642A986ED88E214CC670F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H1B8C563FD77B4B6CB299D9F4E5EE8EB2" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H1632DC1A4EB24D3F947761638040718A" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, the licensee of a license granted under section 346(b), the grantee of a grant of market access granted under section 346(c), or an entity with authorization granted under section 346(d),</quote> after <quote>broadcast station</quote>; </text></subclause><subclause id="H1510B13BCCA246F9A2CDBEB466AA27C5" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, grant, or authorization</quote> after <quote>such license</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3DEA4B1ECD2C4A05B11316C8A3E3F8F3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that station</quote> and inserting <quote>that licensee, grantee, or entity</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF6B9BEF52AB34196AE962F137138E7D7" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, grant of market access, or authorization</quote> after <quote>its license</quote>; </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD09AD61B1830498B8FFD640DC92E26DC" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>the station</quote> and inserting <quote>in the case of a broadcast station, the station</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HAD30A7066B6F497AA856236422110E28" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) as subparagraphs (C) and (D), respectively;</text></clause><clause id="HDF74D8F639C642FF9BC9587EC35D21F3" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following:</text><quoted-block id="H6420C49034DB406C9962534607CDBF04" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H50DF5BF52221499FA22CCF2CDFD32413" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a licensee of a license granted under section 346(b), a grantee of a grant of market access granted under section 346(c), or an entity with authorization granted under section 346(d), the licensee, grantee, or entity has met the requirements of section 346(e);</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H0A0C2EFD9DF34C5C8BBA707A489FF611" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (C), as so redesignated, by inserting <quote>, grantee, or entity</quote> after <quote>licensee</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HE641D6E682F74494AAEC7952B9ADA029" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (D), as so redesignated, by inserting <quote>, grantee, or entity</quote> after <quote>licensee</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12C7EB19910046D69ABB907B5DFAB46A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>, or the licensee of a license granted under section 346(b), the grantee of a grant of market access granted under section 346(c), or an entity with authorization granted under section 346(d),</quote> after <quote>broadcast station</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B9FE0C9C79247729E1B467156666542"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><clause id="H66C0911C4D3E4266A57FC0D864833F8F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>of a broadcast station, a licensee of a license granted under section 346(b), a grantee of a grant of market access granted under section 346(c), or an entity with authorization granted under section 346(d)</quote> after <quote>that a licensee</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H3653836B307F4D31883E935E0377D1E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HBD9F208ADE5C4F8C943C296AD953A92B" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, grantee, or entity</quote> after <quote>licensee</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6BF03403F0F24C528721EDF2541C0D74"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or 346</quote> after <quote>section 308</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H5B41BDA0917D45248C3D73412B9CEEA1" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>former licensee</quote> and inserting <quote>former licensee of a broadcast station or such applications for a license, grant of market access, or authorization as may be filed under section 346(b), 346(c), or 346(d) specifying the information of the former licensee, grantee, or entity</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C59E6AA7809454D964AA65B62471E11"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting <quote>, grant of market access, or authorization</quote> after <quote>license</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8EE7DAE443C4098B1879BF6A01BCA2B" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements in the amendments made by this section apply with respect to any application submitted under subsection (b), (c), or (d) of section 346 of the Communications Act of 1934 and any request for renewal or modification submitted under such section, as added by subsection (a), on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

