<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H001E8EF72A8345A6B925383B57911646" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6327 IH: Youth Financial Learning Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6327</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the financial literacy of secondary school students.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE6CC687D2B7D4C7EBC212A4E92E2BFC0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCE851B0273204B99A81F149C48BD0C16" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Youth Financial Learning Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0E6ED0B6B40A4AD1AC612065514E2D8F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statewide incentive grants for financial literacy education</header> <subsection id="H3C97D8C0977F4898A8EE93323A5B4269"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act, the terms <term>community-based organization</term>, <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>professional development</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, <term>Secretary</term>, <term>State educational agency</term>, and <term>well-rounded education</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HB3F45528FB824B2F86FF096DCF702783"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants Authorized</header>
<paragraph id="HA790D3E9FFD249CDA2DA8C69C582BFD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>From amounts appropriated under subsection (f), the Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to State educational agencies to enable those State educational agencies to integrate financial literacy education into public elementary schools or secondary schools by carrying out the activities described in paragraph (4).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF853CA43527C48C3A57F79C9FC49579B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A grant awarded under this section shall be for a period of not more than 4 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8BDC043A3CE849538EABD04ED341BCE4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each State educational agency desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HC67DCECDBB7C48DA956BEBFF0856AD15"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the State educational agency will award subgrants to local educational agencies;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H05EBAB0CFAB740189856578DE103BAF4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of how the State educational agency will ensure sustainability of the grant activities after the grant program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HDAC9EE29DBEE4856BB60314890E0644E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assertion that teachers, principals, parents, and students have been consulted in the process of developing the application; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H09765C9C0FC941A082359D30760A1CC6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of how the State educational agency will ensure geographic diversity so that grant activities benefit students in urban, rural, and suburban locations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FB690034CC64DE996CFDB7280159DDB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Uses of State funds</header> <subparagraph id="H7EB633281D424436B645BEDFE34E1855"><enum>(A)</enum><header>State activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State educational agency receiving grant funds under this section may use not more than 10 percent of such grant funds—</text>
<clause id="H1B3810748C81471F9ED4AC4DBB79C4BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for technical assistance;</text></clause> <clause id="HB33A8622DD5A4D65B51482EEDDD618E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for curriculum development;</text></clause>
<clause id="HC6FB1A0F113647B08577A8EDFA560B59"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to provide guidance to local educational agencies; or</text></clause> <clause id="H2299B4767F294EB4BB57D129C557BE2D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to conduct an evaluation of the impact of financial literacy or personal finance education on students’ understanding of financial literacy concepts.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5D448D463672481284B2D225B7D5AF59"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subgrants</header>
<clause id="HF722621D316E4887BF4EEE2C1A15A4DA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Each State educational agency receiving grant funds under this section shall use the remainder of such grant funds to award subgrants to local educational agencies in the State.</text></clause> <clause id="H540FC44433A044D1B66DF4069A80FBEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding such subgrants, a State educational agency shall give priority to local educational agencies that—</text>
<subclause id="H565CC505524C483AB826BD94EE871CFB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>serve high numbers, or a high percentage of, elementary schools and secondary schools implementing plans under paragraphs (1) and (2) of section 1111(d) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(d)</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB26113346ED54F04BBB7B51429B20029"><enum>(II)</enum><text>demonstrate the greatest need for such funds, as determined by the State educational agency; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB235E6F61C164940AB2CA0E309F77CDC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>demonstrate the strongest commitment to using funds under this section to enable the lowest-performing schools to improve students' financial literacy and student outcomes.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1E522080BC624D76BBD658C9044732A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of subgrant funds</header><text>Each local educational agency receiving a subgrant under this section shall use the subgrant funds—</text>
<paragraph id="H80A756BBE6CC449CBDB1FD8CDD6865B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to implement, expand, or sustain, in one or more elementary schools or one or more secondary schools, school-based financial literacy activities and curriculum that is a substantial portion of any class, in order to enhance student understanding of and experimental learning with consumer, economic, entrepreneurship, and personal finance concepts, including personal credit, student loans, and financial aid;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA281E3114BF74628AAED8389C4168842"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to promote partnerships between the local educational agency and community-based organizations that provide innovative, evidence-based financial literacy activities to elementary school or secondary school students, which may include after school activities; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1882DD935E29433B8C6BD18E8BAE9DFF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to promote professional development programs to embed financial literacy or personal finance or entrepreneurship education into a well-rounded education in elementary schools or secondary schools.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9291549644D848D48CB37C6872C1E9DC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Matching funds</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this section shall provide matching funds, from non-Federal sources, in an amount equal to 25 percent of the amount of grant funds provided to the State educational agency to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H72336859C675482BA57E96C69008C42D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Grant funds provided under this section shall be used to supplement, not supplant, other Federal or State funds available to carry out activities described in this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H41DB464215F04A4288F0D9ED3391D3E3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 4 succeeding fiscal years.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

