<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H87CC48970E9245CD866BEF3F615DA3BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3352 IH: Improving Diaper Affordability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3352</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to treat diapers as qualified medical expenses; and to prohibit States and local governments to impose a tax on the retail sale of diapers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H00929D4E737B4551AEE2F1AAF4698816" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBDC0CCDA44D1492DA510C436B9431881" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Diaper Affordability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H0533501286404E0DB844577F3CA0E555"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H199C7DDDCDCF4DE4AD0783C08BE3EB68"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One in 3 families with infants and toddlers struggles to provide the diapers their children need.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H75BEF5D91F1C48DEB1FFB7E0EECBD7B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Low-income families with infants spend 14 percent of their income on diapers alone, which is roughly $936 per child, per year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE72B539B6D304CC9B27621EFF65B69CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Low-income families spend twice as much on diapers for their children, compared to families who have the means to buy diapers in bulk at a lower price.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDB1F99A9D82644E88B8F1F25E21CFC83"><enum>(4)</enum><text>More than 5 million children under the typical potty training age of 3-years-old live in low-income families.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H740DB10D7A79466BB4647E72090E8A2B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Diaper need affects not only the health and well-being of the child but it can affect the economic security of the entire family.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAD6E56BAA354C1DAA79545AAB981B19"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Over half of families in diaper need who rely on child care in order to go to work or school, missed work or school in the preceding month because they did not have the diapers they needed to put their child in child care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE3B48568784348B4AF0F8E5A7F144339"><enum>(7)</enum><text>No State or Federal child safety-net program allocates dollars specifically for the purchase of diapers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C736A3334F54714B7FE93CE078D6484"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since the start of the COVID–19 pandemic, diaper banks around the country have experienced double, triple, or greater increase in demand for diapers due to the pandemic and economic shutdown.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HA6FF9FEF7AC34F04902CE8A410558135"><enum>3.</enum><header>Inclusion of diapers as qualified medical expenses</header> 
<subsection id="HA367B5B455104CCD92E7921339CCE9CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Health savings accounts</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">Section 223(d)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end of subparagraph (A) the following: <quote>Notwithstanding the first sentence, amounts paid for diapers shall be treated as paid for medical care.</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE97263AC6691483C8122448614FD182C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Archer <enum-in-header>MSA</enum-in-header>s</header><text>Section 220(d)(2)(A) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Notwithstanding the first sentence, amounts paid for diapers shall be treated as paid for medical care.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDD62BC0E29474DCD88F51ECE1B0F9568" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Health flexible spending arrangements and health reimbursement arrangements</header><text>Section 106 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block id="H2399E405A89A45C3B1659D24AFEFCFCB" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H8C3DA42AFD074737B930AF24E291B8D4" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reimbursements for diapers</header><text>For purposes of this section and section 105, expenses incurred for diapers shall be treated as incurred for medical care.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFB4A0140BF564A9187E6AB52A2816F59"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dependent care assistance and dependent care flexible spending arrangements</header><text>Section 129(e)(1) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Such term shall include expenses incurred for diapers.</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8640FA9853064EDF8CCA6C7309061C5B" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limited purpose flexible spending arrangements and health reimbursement arrangements</header><text>Section 223(c)(1)(B) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (ii), by striking the period at the end of clause (iii) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H351EB09CF9804F9BAAFA9F633F5FB707" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H7CD706BDDB0441858305BAA2D07C58B8" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coverage under a flexible spending arrangement, or health reimbursement arrangement, that pays or reimburses for coverage described in clause (ii) (other than long-term care services and, in the case of a flexible spending arrangement, other than through insurance). Coverage shall not fail to be treated as coverage described in the preceding sentence solely by reason of paying or reimbursing expenses incurred for diapers.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H32F2AD084D75432DB53DEF006D3C6B24" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective dates</header> <paragraph id="H922395768D5E495193893C44B6CCA067" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Distributions from health savings accounts</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall apply to amounts paid after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD8D6E58BC15A4F48A1C8E38F0D4C5852" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reimbursements</header><text>The amendment made by subsections (c) and (d) shall apply to expenses incurred after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFB544ECC173454396B2BF78DD5EBF66" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limited purpose HSA and HRA</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (e) shall apply to months beginning after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE7329BD71AF84A568B775CED51572607"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition of retail sales taxes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State, or unit of local government of a State, may not impose a sales and use tax on the retail purchase of diapers.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

