<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAFCBFD46300B4ECE8EC2C76D14F1D801" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4108 IH: Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4108</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 to require export controls with respect to certain personal data of United States nationals and individuals in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8429B269D53B4DE89C959EB90DE41EFE" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H11CD22D4391E4CBE87A7C7B427E0509D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H563FE376977D4BF28B787EE33A76181F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HE3205D20A99F4E0AA46C95D23D3DDA17"><enum>(1)</enum><text>accelerating technological trends have made sensitive personal data an especially valuable input to activities that foreign adversaries of the United States undertake to threaten both the national security of the United States and the privacy that the people of the United States cherish;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77066A912E32464AA39B9D5FF0DE4B38"><enum>(2)</enum><text>it is therefore essential to the safety of the United States and the people of the United States to ensure that the United States Government makes every effort to prevent sensitive personal data from falling into the hands of malign foreign actors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2ECDC82D55764899ACB9BAEA4786C566"><enum>(3)</enum><text>because allies of the United States face similar challenges, in implementing this Act, the United States Government should explore the establishment of a shared zone of mutual trust with respect to sensitive personal data.</text></paragraph></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HD2C54FCF17AD4F008891B6DD52C3D4C3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement to control the export of certain personal data of United States nationals and individuals in the United States</header><subsection id="HFBCCEC2403F94F14BAE04B58D1534C23"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part I of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4811">50 U.S.C. 4811 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 1758 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB13A98BC90C147D09CB08B098E03B731"><section id="HA226177E4D5543B894810316D9F4DDDC"><enum>1758A.</enum><header>Requirement to control the export of certain personal data of United States nationals and individuals in the United States</header><subsection id="HBC254C4374264B15902F32E562F5169E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Identification of categories of personal data</header><paragraph id="HE16FCCD6B52F4927AF73F754B303BBB7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, identify categories of personal data of covered individuals that could—</text><subparagraph id="HCDFEFC1928CB48CFA7BE923FB963720F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be exploited by foreign governments or foreign adversaries; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DD156BC62D642E59FC28DE04F4570E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if exported, reexported, or in-country transferred in a quantity that exceeds the threshold established under paragraph (3), harm the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7165166DA044C2A91166ABBF7826C1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>List required</header><text>In identifying categories of personal data of covered individuals under paragraph (1), the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall—</text><subparagraph id="H133CAFD4A30E42FD98743D7AB6CFC9F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify an initial list of such categories not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA2DEB24C3324E81901D300B3AAE0FDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>as appropriate thereafter and not less frequently than every 5 years, add categories to, remove categories from, or modify categories on, that list.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59CF65E8422F4A61B59BAF374197CD17"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Establishment of threshold</header><subparagraph id="H172CF0AE27094348A5862EA1735DEB55"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall establish a threshold for determining when the export, reexport, or in-country transfer (in the aggregate) of the personal data of covered individuals by one person to or in a restricted country could harm the national security of the United States. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H053B2CA36E314640B10941CCEA46E27D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Number of covered individuals affected</header><clause id="HAB07429DCD2745B19F5CCCE663253AEC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided by clause (ii), the Secretary shall establish the threshold under subparagraph (A) so that the threshold is—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA5B3CD8B0484484993BAAFE82838F7CE"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not lower than the export, reexport, or in-country transfer (in the aggregate) by one person to or in a restricted country during a calendar year of the personal data of 10,000 covered individuals; and </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFEEF8B158F694E4892D6285686C961A7"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not higher than the export, reexport, or in-country transfer (in the aggregate) by one person to or in a restricted country during a calendar year of the personal data of 1,000,000 covered individuals. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H956E3619EAB941BFB79E0C8ADD024C84"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exports by certain foreign persons</header><text>In the case of a person that possesses the data of more than 1,000,000 covered individuals, the threshold established under subparagraph (A) shall be one export, reexport, or in-country transfer of personal data to or in a restricted country by that person during a calendar year if the export, reexport, or in-country transfer is to—</text><subclause id="H76B25CFC225145E19748A7A6037BF06D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the government of a restricted country;</text></subclause><subclause id="H69536C46E8474F88995FCCD0A76B01A8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a foreign person that owns or controls the person conducting the export, reexport, or in-country transfer and that person knows, or should know, that the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of the personal data was requested by the foreign person to comply with a request from the government of a restricted country; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HCA87507C6D464FF9AA15A312A2D1DFDA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an entity on the Entity List maintained by the Bureau of Industry and Security of the Department of Commerce and set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H343D9DB4B1B64BB5BCDA2732A54B1CFE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Category thresholds</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, may establish a threshold under subparagraph (A) for each category (or combination of categories) of personal data identified under paragraph (1). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FAB94D631614D42A8858872048A0E83"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies—</text><clause id="HBE5B6547D35C45218A5AF90BCDEE7AF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may update a threshold established under subparagraph (A) as appropriate; and </text></clause><clause id="HF00F9F303CD54F98A5C8F1A58572945C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall reevaluate the threshold not less frequently than every 5 years.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H342F127AD45E45E18E1B9E1F1A5F19C4"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Treatment of persons under common ownership as one person</header><text>For purposes of determining whether a threshold established under subparagraph (A) has been met—</text><clause id="H2064500E87614BB2A817CAB5FF9C015B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all exports, reexports, or in-country transfers involving personal data conducted by persons under the ownership or control of the same person shall be aggregated to that person; and</text></clause><clause id="HE8408690AF81424481B3277EE146D064"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that person shall be liable for any export, reexport, or in-country transfer in violation of this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8646C50EE7143B98861E1EB34D04FB1"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In establishing a threshold under subparagraph (A), the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall seek to balance the need to protect personal data from exploitation by foreign governments and foreign adversaries against the likelihood of—</text><clause id="H535B0D84E6A54B66A9868720807DF3BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>impacting legitimate business activities, research activities, and other activities that do not harm the national security of the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="HE24978FE91FF44419AC81BAA8FBBBB90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>chilling speech protected by the First Amendment to the Constitution of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA48F6E297EA0470B835E811E115CB840"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determination of period for protection</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall determine, for each category (or combination of categories) of personal data identified under paragraph (1), the period of time for which encryption technology described in subsection (b)(4)(A)(iii) is required to be able to protect that category (or combination of categories) of data from decryption to prevent the exploitation of the data by a foreign government or foreign adversary from harming the national security of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6493A907713B4A59AF8CB10EBACADBDD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of information; considerations</header><text>In carrying out this subsection (including with respect to the list required under paragraph (2)), the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall—</text><subparagraph id="H17E50D56D31241D6B3DFA764FE67590D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>use multiple sources of information, including—</text><clause id="HF99F5ECE551B452CBC8E645CCBFB77E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>publicly available information;</text></clause><clause id="H7C5D7600953A422AA19623B16C3ADE9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>classified information, including relevant information provided by the Director of National Intelligence;</text></clause><clause id="HF15E35F5DBE14F7C801B9E54639B374C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>information relating to reviews and investigations of transactions by the Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States under section 721 of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4565">50 U.S.C. 4565</external-xref>); </text></clause><clause id="H427F497946254B949273C1D9E2F753BC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the categories of sensitive personal data described in paragraphs (1)(ii) and (2) of section 800.241(a) of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, and any categories of sensitive personal data added to such section after such date of enactment; </text></clause><clause id="H043D3442B31A4E8293E0C4D126A097A6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>information provided by the advisory committee established pursuant to paragraph (7); and</text></clause><clause id="HDEBFDB172FCB408297E368174078398B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the recommendations (which the Secretary shall request) of—</text><subclause id="H5C482620CB084E54972C111121893003"><enum>(I)</enum><text>experts in privacy, civil rights, and civil liberties, identified by the National Academy of Sciences; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3EEB483A2B5A456E8DEC27C4BD8C608A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>experts on the First Amendment to the Constitution of the United States identified by the American Bar Association; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7282B15FD37B4A07A7B954DBC3BB2C4A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>take into account—</text><clause id="HA2B26C0B82604BED91E246C6099201B8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the significant quantity of personal data of covered individuals that is publicly available by law or has already been stolen or acquired by foreign governments or foreign adversaries;</text></clause><clause id="H7EF8AF7E991C4D2986EA4CD8DAD216D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the harm to United States national security caused by the theft or acquisition of that personal data;</text></clause><clause id="H813BE4395F744C589C4AADBCCD541221"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the potential for further harm to United States national security if that personal data were combined with additional sources of personal data;</text></clause><clause id="HF0A714A925234E85B10EE83EBF35C051"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the fact that non-sensitive personal data, when analyzed in the aggregate, can reveal sensitive personal data; </text></clause><clause id="H7B0542AF9BC346FE9AE7A1B15D9DECF8"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the commercial availability of inferred and derived data; and</text></clause><clause id="H6713C4C1D44A4096B1CA6B3F92F50A5F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the potential for especially significant harm from data and inferences related to sensitive domains, such as health, work, education, criminal justice, and finance. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1C8E1A3C56C4C3CAADAE97D6EE2F5C3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Notice and comment period</header><text>The Secretary shall provide for a public notice and comment period after the publication in the Federal Register of a proposed rule, and before the publication of a final rule—</text><subparagraph id="H17CB0E1066E942E0B7EC505FCF2AA6AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying the initial list of categories of personal data under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (2); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78F9CF88739E4F1C9243FA09EE2D86CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>adding categories to, removing categories from, or modifying categories on, that list under subparagraph (B) of that paragraph; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5808E53A4D144C1DBD40A2E6F7FCF43D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establishing or updating the threshold under paragraph (3); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EC1B522B5F34F0588275B3FD922EBAA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>setting forth the period of time for which encryption technology described in subsection (b)(4)(A)(iii) is required under paragraph (4) to be able to protect such a category of data from decryption.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H85EC1952FF9649F4A58D84F43851DF7E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Advisory committee</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4D209FF7849D4C2A8800294DA38B23A0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an advisory committee to advise the Secretary with respect to privacy and sensitive personal data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC82F6E994E944C999EF3351B78937926"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The committee established pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall include the following members selected by the Secretary:</text><clause commented="no" id="H57EBE358051042EF8E336C5A3C684451"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Experts on privacy and cybersecurity.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HAD62F6B3F5194E3B8A77BFB9B095A8E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Representatives of United States private sector companies, industry associations, and scholarly societies.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H7307918AE3BE4DEB86DEFDEDB34D7A54"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Representatives of civil society groups, including such groups focused on protecting civil rights and civil liberties. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26ABCF7CD42647ADB0E2A53DF88FFB71"><enum>(C)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Applicability of Federal advisory committee Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (a)(1), (a)(3), and (b) of section 10 and sections 11, 13, and 14 of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the advisory committee established pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20F360C495FC4003AE911C25A0DED621"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Treatment of anonymized personal data</header><subparagraph id="H77809390414741548B8DB532B7FC8F74"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary may not treat anonymized personal data differently than identifiable personal data unless the Secretary is confident, based on the method of anonymization used and the period of time determined under paragraph (4) for protection of the category of personal data involved, it will not be possible for well-resourced adversaries, including foreign governments, to re-identify the individuals to which the anonymized personal data relates, such as by using other sources of data, including non-public data obtained through hacking and espionage, and reasonably anticipated advances in technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2FCC2042840489094F668B4FA3C60D8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology shall issue guidance to the public with respect to methods for anonymizing data and how to determine if individuals to which the anonymized personal data relates can be, or are likely in the future to be, reasonably identified, such as by using other sources of data. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E1F74C0647446D38A58A1F5EB2CC731"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Sense of Congress on identification of categories of personal data</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that, in identifying categories of personal data of covered individuals under paragraph (1), the Secretary should, to the extent reasonably possible and in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury and the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, harmonize those categories with the categories of sensitive personal data described in paragraph (5)(A)(iv). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4433E981C6C24E3BB8B7F90BB4BE772C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Commerce controls</header><paragraph id="H9CC23C2BE8D64320BAC5942F64FA633E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Controls required</header><text>Beginning 18 months after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall impose appropriate controls under the Export Administration Regulations on the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, all countries (other than countries on the list required by paragraph (2)(D)) of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3), including through interim controls (such as by informing a person that a license is required for export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data), as appropriate, or by publishing additional regulations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B497FBEEB7D42888B98E9F89A4FC517"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Levels of control</header><subparagraph id="HB75D1B123F744390A50EB8229CAA0988"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C) or (D), the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H468DEEB7E75B4109B4093AD771DFF3EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require a license or other authorization for the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3);</text></clause><clause id="HC668E689B6114D9CAAFFDDD7C5C88B98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>determine whether that export, reexport, or in-country transfer is likely to harm the national security of the United States—</text><subclause id="HBEC0F897E0A9452CB064D4092D990B2E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>after consideration of the matters described in subparagraph (B); and </text></subclause><subclause id="HD635573AE69248AEB5C97F82B0073AF6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8BD8914FEC044542AC4F7100E5E32822"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines under clause (ii) that the export, reexport, or in-country transfer is likely to harm the national security of the United States, deny the application for the license or other authorization for the export, reexport, or in-country transfer.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H499066CB6E2445D585D22323568C5398"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In determining under clause (ii) of subparagraph (A) whether an export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data described in clause (i) of that subparagraph is likely to harm the national security of the United States, the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall take into account—</text><clause id="H0D24D71F873549FEBFF65B73B38470F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the adequacy and enforcement of data protection, surveillance, and export control laws in the foreign country to which the covered personal data would be exported or reexported, or in which the covered personal data would be transferred, in order to determine whether such laws, and the enforcement of such laws, are sufficient to—</text><subclause id="H6397C08C01194B5E896B1A9C44BA80AA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>protect the covered personal data from accidental loss, theft, and unauthorized or unlawful processing;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBE2B7A7002674B5A93B98E2427ECC32F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensure that the covered personal data is not exploited for intelligence purposes by foreign governments to the detriment of the national security of the United States; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H14911B50636543A094626F7592B58E6F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>prevent the reexport of the covered personal data to a third country for which a license would be required for such data to be exported directly from the United States; </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9476314EC86D4ACFAE388A943E37A4BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text> the circumstances under which the government of the foreign country can compel, coerce, or pay a person in or national of that country to disclose the covered personal data; and </text></clause><clause id="H84D79A711B764B3EB1788A7F0355B7EE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether that government has conducted hostile foreign intelligence operations, including information operations, against the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7527BF0936864E1E84695AA923CEFDB8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>License requirement and presumption of denial for certain countries</header><clause id="HD519F5D075B248E19E34A620D6DA9892"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subclause id="H099ADB6C4A8B4870A94A937A661ECEE4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>require a license or other authorization for the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, a country on the list required by clause (ii) of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the threshold established under subsection (a)(3); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0548C5D67CE640C5BB6D52C6DB647A44"><enum>(II)</enum><text>deny an application for such a license or other authorization unless the person seeking the license or authorization demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Secretary that the export, reexport, or in-country transfer will not harm the national security of the United States. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H85E651FF6FA4436F9CEE72FDD451DF9B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>List required</header><subclause id="HC9EB2DCA4506465AA0DC45F236A95E2A"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall (subject to subclause (III)) establish a list of each country with respect to which the Secretary determines that the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, the country of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3) will be likely to harm the national security of the United States.</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HBD319019A27E4254AE36661767AF3408"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Modifications to list</header><text>The Secretary (subject to subclause (III))—</text><item commented="no" id="H7F474BB88E584DED9D4417A87B4E5A61"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may add a country to or remove a country from the list required by subclause (I) at any time; and</text></item><item commented="no" id="H2512A447242E4B59A7C1731E1F4BA03D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>shall review that list not less frequently than every 5 years. </text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D6BCFB8EF5945A192AFDD69E180309C"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Concurrence; consultations; considerations</header><text>The Secretary shall establish the list required by subclause (I) and add a country to or remove a country from that list under subclause (II)—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8A7648CD5A04638A8B6909951D309E0"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the concurrence of the Secretary of State; </text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC05AF3C38604764A13FA9FE9B75C4C7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in consultation with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies; and </text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H141C34CB597047E199AEC36CC18CC933"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the considerations described in subparagraph (B). </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1890C5FBFEF48BCAB80A4922795E351"><enum>(D)</enum><header>No license requirement for certain countries</header><clause id="H4117162ECB454B27ADCFD797C7707293"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may not require a license or other authorization for the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, a country on the list required by clause (ii) of covered personal data, without regard to the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3).</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF4CF8EB9B17A4B56A9A17F74F2299264"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>List required</header><subclause commented="no" id="HC935661B46A64200A52EE0799A7D14C3"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall (subject to clause (iii) and subclause (III)), establish a list of each country with respect to which the Secretary determines that the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, the country of covered personal data (without regard to any threshold established under subsection (a)(3)) will not harm the national security of the United States. </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HCC7A7683E603454C8C1232CC505C2A5F"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Modifications to list</header><text>The Secretary (subject to clause (iii) and subclause (III))—</text><item commented="no" id="H65B93EFDB63F48449F5F26E99D70658E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may add a country to or remove a country from the list required by subclause (I) at any time; and</text></item><item commented="no" id="H5D73B3B043544BD3864976D45B3EE328"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>shall review that list not less frequently than every 5 years.</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE106FD94DF774442BBF31A0D09B52739"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Concurrence; consultations; considerations</header><text>The Secretary shall establish the list required by subclause (I) and add a country to or remove a country from that list under subclause (II)—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92824045BC9142159275E302F5492B07"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the concurrence of the Secretary of State; </text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8EE3804619A14F0F8AB94C7A7D84815D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in consultation with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies; and </text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1AAC316C8D14A50A4CD78C7C692D6D8"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the considerations described in subparagraph (B). </text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0B51563E76FB4EFA8CCA944AA5EE52B8"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Congressional review</header><subclause commented="no" id="HFB8C28BE65A847DEB316952CD53AF1FF"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The list required by clause (ii) and any updates to that list adding or removing countries shall take effect, for purposes of clause (i), on the date that is 180 days after the Secretary submits to the appropriate congressional committees a proposal for the list or update unless there is enacted into law, before that date, a joint resolution of disapproval pursuant to subclause (II).</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HD6E74E7AE3964AD3B0BFEA1D45F13F2E"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval</header><item commented="no" id="H0161F705A82240DAAA48B139C1BB56DC"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval defined</header><text>In this clause, the term <term>joint resolution of disapproval</term> means a joint resolution the matter after the resolving clause of which is as follows: <quote>That Congress does not approve of the proposal of the Secretary with respect to the list required by section 1758A(b)(2)(D)(ii) submitted to Congress on ___.</quote>, with the blank space being filled with the appropriate date.</text></item><item commented="no" id="H1401AF46AADB4DAB94B08C9428728C37"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>The procedures set forth in paragraphs (4)(C), (5), (6), and (7) of section 2523(d) of title 18, United States Code, apply with respect to a joint resolution of disapproval under this clause to the same extent and in the same manner as such procedures apply to a joint resolution of disapproval under such section 2523(d), except that paragraph (6) of such section shall be applied and administered by substituting <quote>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs</quote> for <quote>the Committee on the Judiciary</quote> each place it appears.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H7E3769DE32FB4A7BA9D23D41BCA70D3D"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Rules of house of representatives and senate</header><text>This clause is enacted by Congress—</text><item id="H1F5FE6797A7E49429CA6A193A76724F0"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and the House of Representatives, respectively, and as such is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, and supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></item><item id="H29C2D196604E41C6BFB0CBD24E6E015C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House. </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6C363941BE24DEFAC5FA5121C6D2B63"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Review of license applications</header><subparagraph id="H5CD1D4C3FC124F659FD05D17DCE7BE2E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, consistent with the provisions of section 1756 and in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies—</text><clause id="HB7FD532481C24B44BBBDA48C02829B91"><enum>(i)</enum><text>review applications for a license or other authorization for the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, a restricted country of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3); and</text></clause><clause id="H7B0D0BCA4EB44267B2593D43ACE9A06D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish procedures for conducting the review of such applications.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1B942A4B0D9481697FDBF10EE5CBFE0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disclosures relating to collaborative arrangements</header><text>In the case of an application for a license or other authorization for an export, reexport, or in-country transfer described in subparagraph (A)(i) submitted by or on behalf of a joint venture, joint development agreement, or similar collaborative arrangement, the Secretary may require the applicant to identify, in addition to any foreign person participating in the arrangement, any foreign person with significant ownership interest in a foreign person participating in the arrangement. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F943D308D4745F7AEC9D3A1D8D0BEF0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="H633FC8FF25A6483C9B239E997A1A59EC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall not impose under paragraph (1) a requirement for a license or other authorization with respect to the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data pursuant to any of the following transactions:</text><clause commented="no" id="H49F67D67EEC14B1D82F801EE07304AA1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The export, reexport, or in-country transfer by an individual of covered personal data that specifically pertains to that individual.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H24020349097B40798720663680C27389"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The export, reexport, or in-country transfer of the personal data of one or more individuals by a person performing a service for those individuals if the service could not possibly be performed (as defined by the Secretary in regulations) without the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of that personal data.</text></clause><clause id="HDC5EF5F042AC45B3A5F2CC6EEB8BB957"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The export, reexport, or in-country transfer of personal data that is encrypted if—</text><subclause id="HA4A902B6D7E04AE7B4C3D63E5F1FBE78"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the encryption key or other information necessary to decrypt the data is not, at the time of the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of the personal data or any other time, exported, reexported, or transferred to a restricted country or (except as provided in subparagraph (B)) a national of a restricted country; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H88E796BAE5EA4B51BDA35BA92CBB9E69"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the encryption technology used to protect the data against decryption is certified by the National Institute of Standards and Technology as capable of protecting data for the period of time determined under subsection (a)(4) to be sufficient to prevent the exploitation of the data by a foreign government or foreign adversary from harming the national security of the United States. </text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HD4A8EF4DA25E4DAA941CE8F1F8328FB2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The export, reexport, or in-country transfer of personal data that is ordered by an appropriate court of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03983C07BEF3417F8B5484E2E8A23CEC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception for certain nationals of restricted countries</header><text>Subparagraph (A)(iii)(I) does not apply with respect to an individual who is a national of a restricted country if the individual is also a citizen of the United States or a noncitizen described in subsection (l)(5)(C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7404E4188D2744D8B5BAB2B2343D17CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements for identification of categories and determination of appropriate controls</header><text>In identifying categories of personal data under subsection (a)(1) and imposing appropriate controls under subsection (b), the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, as appropriate—</text><paragraph id="HCFE2F1EA1C7E43E2A812CE864DA63D1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may not regulate or restrict the publication or sharing of—</text><subparagraph id="HB913A52160C94307A227A4F737302CD4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>personal data that is a matter of public record, such as a court record or other government record that is generally available to the public, including information about an individual made public by that individual or by the news media;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB28A532C3ED848B080020FDE337C5E3D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information about a matter of public interest; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF06B5A3D951144368A4FC31C9375A77E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other information the publication or sharing of which is protected by the First Amendment to the Constitution of the United States; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2564B63E2DE84E689F9F796BB7243E24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall consult with the appropriate congressional committees. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H74D8B549AD3D4EAC8D174DFD5F53A858"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H1E3CD0F614CC439E8F29BFFCA3B943CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Liable persons</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDD31AF5C69904B40981A95D3F88A44B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to any person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of section 1760, an officer or employee of an organization has committed an unlawful act subject to penalties under that section if the officer or employee knew or should have known that another employee of the organization who reports, directly or indirectly, to the officer or employee was directed to export, reexport, or in-country transfer covered personal data in violation of this section and subsequently did export, reexport, or in-country transfer such data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2700FF85935A4E678C542E297190AFE9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions and clarifications</header><clause id="H2C2ADF083F3D4266B8DBE0BCBC8395E1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Intermediaries not liable</header><text>An intermediate consignee (as defined in section 772.1 of the Export Administration Regulations (or any successor regulation)) or other intermediary is not liable for the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data in violation of this section when acting as an intermediate consignee or other intermediary for another person. </text></clause><clause id="HB956E68FD088412CAAFBCFE1C7567295"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Special rule for certain applications</header><text>In a case in which an application installed on an electronic device transmits or causes the transmission of covered personal data without being directed to do so by the owner or user of the device who installed the application, the developer of the application, and not the owner or user of the device, is liable for any violation of this section. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF25AA099723A453094611F31C97923E2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criminal penalties</header><text>In determining an appropriate term of imprisonment under section 1760(b)(2) with respect to a person for a violation of this section, the court shall consider—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H049E8109461447FC958C28CAAFCC0595"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how many covered individuals had their covered personal data exported, reexported, or in-country transferred in violation of this section; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE3430E87CF824227A8D3D7FA2BD0FF70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any harm that resulted from the violation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE89203025ECE4CBD82F6A31BA9856EF4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the intent of the person in committing the violation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3834920A49B46CFAD00217D36A971E3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><paragraph id="H225629B215A64B56962A985162BDC57A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than annually, the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of the appropriate Federal agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the results of actions taken pursuant to this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC499B1F06C814F648EACB2D24335B320"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall include a description of the determinations made under subsection (b)(2)(A)(ii) during the preceding year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68F8C0B614804DA0B3477B520694645A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD84084B78B924A788812DB23E9787F4A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Disclosure of certain license information</header><paragraph id="HFEBB426A0B2F4DD2821C2574A45DD7D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than every 90 days, the Secretary shall publish on a publicly accessible website of the Department of Commerce, including in a machine-readable format, the information specified in paragraph (2), with respect to each application—</text><subparagraph id="H027F9F8939C644859D57400BAD26A224"><enum>(A)</enum><text> for a license for the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, a restricted country of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA384422E17444C25AE4A4B2EF9F27D5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to which the Secretary made a decision in the preceding 90-day period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD20CB028569F47769D5DB346E26BE998"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information specified</header><text>The information specified in this paragraph with respect to an application described in paragraph (1) is the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCF57B27307114E499575228A9383B367"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The name of the applicant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BBF9BE4186149F8A2564E00CE7B8694"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The date of the application.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5987B50D0EC04AC0AADDE3F3568F8349"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The name of the foreign party to which the applicant sought to export, reexport, or transfer the data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA311DBD3DDD544B8AA000B6F0A0C467E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The categories of covered personal data the applicant sought to export, reexport, or transfer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA168DDA83CE64581B413664BA011AB45"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The number of covered individuals whose information the applicant sought to export, reexport, or transfer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EAF7E7A77054C569E4EE293DAA9562E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Whether the application was approved or denied.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD166D371F2344E4698E3353BFE6931D2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>News media protections</header><text>A person that is engaged in journalism is not subject to restrictions imposed under this section to the extent that those restrictions directly infringe on the journalism practices of that person. </text></subsection><subsection id="H299187BFF17549069A3622277E40D676"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Citizenship determinations by persons providing services to end-Users not required</header><text>This section does not require a person that provides products or services to an individual to determine the citizenship or immigration status of the individual, but once the person becomes aware that the individual is a covered individual, the person shall treat covered personal data of that individual as is required by this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H643C75ECB8C644E9B3AEF0F02F39727C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Fees</header><paragraph id="HD4777F5830874F1CA9B8B9A141FD2E68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1756(c), the Secretary may, to the extent provided in advance in appropriations Acts, assess and collect a fee, in an amount determined by the Secretary in regulations, with respect to each application for a license submitted under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD18B10790AD44A4EB5586D2E4BCB6C35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deposit and availability of fees</header><text>Notwithstanding section 3302 of title 31, United States Code, fees collected under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H0CAD801D6E4C41C0906C4B7A6B81C7E3" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be credited as offsetting collections to the account providing appropriations for activities carried out under this section; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1728AA9C16E14CD39605824E7966EC17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be available, to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts, to the Secretary solely for use in carrying out activities under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB5D9655E41041C39596284722653462"><enum>(C)</enum><text>remain available until expended.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15FF801A20D148B88EFA680125FD1286"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary may prescribe such regulations as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H24AEE2DDB2034C4785A31B2C4636C559"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary and to the head of each of the appropriate Federal agencies participating in carrying out this section such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section, including to hire additional employees with expertise in privacy. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC8371E2F6F6A449FBF6C6EB223B8BB1F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section: </text><paragraph id="H14E9AC40B05045BA8F11DFFD81789900"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6DC0BFAB66474BD391BD0AD2B63596DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Finance, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2C8B254F1CC44DCA00CA58C0E40664E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Ways and Means, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3E77906BDD84A4E8D973EE5E6B3C905"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate Federal agencies</header><text>The term <term>appropriate Federal agencies</term> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="H21FB1891CA224129826943529211C9F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Department of Defense. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H929F31B3B2F24D5183A5281239E94691"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of State. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CF94ED7CA2B4DAC8D6CD4174EC3CCFF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5632D9FF28AC4CB0A5F07F546C7108FC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H744E71B6575149E9ABDA487FD954CB5E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Office of the Director of National Intelligence. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9742C751C26D487FAEEF2FA525AE7981"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Office of Science and Technology Policy. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2557BCF706C640EDB6A2B580114B7658"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED9717FC21684848961FC3EA8A32A443"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Consumer Financial Protection Bureau.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CA42703AD7A4DA3ABAB69F07B89DE63"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Federal Trade Commission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6332C6CEACA84AB2AA3D5B914130807E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Federal Communications Commission. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0519D1FE48F14EEBBD29C30FAEB1DC3D"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Department of Health and Human Services. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3D84F5B000F4E068F62063F2DCE5D26"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Such other Federal agencies as the Secretary considers appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70D4D792147646D1A64B34BD59FB5C70"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text>The term <term>covered individual</term>, with respect to personal data, means an individual who, at the time the data is acquired—</text><subparagraph id="H84DC94EB7EE24FC49FA064188D7ECD09"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is located in the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88F1F1CCAF1248AB8D17D46A881E78D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="H923817550CC744B6ACB452C5A52BD5FB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>located outside the United States or whose location cannot be determined; and</text></clause><clause id="H21CE01673F1A41C19E6206647FDCB2F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a citizen of the United States or a noncitizen lawfully admitted for permanent residence.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H08A4E5F9FDB5434C9D3422CC91485B27"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered personal data</header><text>The term <term>covered personal data</term> means the categories of personal data of covered individuals identified pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBE2E1D942A84C6D9463811694F61504"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Export</header><subparagraph id="H9C61CE7453EC4D619E0D33179B7F3D75"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>export</term>, with respect to covered personal data, includes—</text><clause id="HA568E190866E416E89DB500102A83426"><enum>(i)</enum><text>subject to subparagraph (D), the shipment or transmission of the data out of the United States, including the sending or taking of the data out of the United States, in any manner, if the shipment or transmission is intentional, without regard to whether the shipment or transmission was intended to go out of the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H852A18C48E1A423C952548922C3076E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the release or transfer of the data to any noncitizen (other than a noncitizen described in subparagraph (C)), if the release or transfer is intentional, without regard to whether the release or transfer was intended to be to a noncitizen.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6D56F9B3CF04CA7A107610B18D36546"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The term <term>export</term> does not include—</text><clause id="H50D984668C5141AE8C2BC8417D1E0659"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the publication of covered personal data on the internet in a manner that makes the data discoverable by and accessible to any member of the general public; or </text></clause><clause id="HC87807E2845443838E32642DAD27E010"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any activity protected by the speech or debate clause of the Constitution of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H058F93026CED43089FB399D833C215CD"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Noncitizens described</header><text>A noncitizen described in this subparagraph is a noncitizen who is authorized to be employed in the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D0E89BE8E45444A8DCE53FD2CF86779"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Transmissions through restricted countries</header><clause id="H7188D67869284A6C8EF97EE59C44F49C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On and after the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Protecting Americans' Data From Foreign Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title>, and except as provided in clause (iii), the term <term>export</term> includes the transmission of data through a restricted country, without regard to whether the person originating the transmission had knowledge of or control over the path of the transmission.</text></clause><clause id="H1DD183E0ECF9459F81E2241B969FED7C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Clause (i) does not apply with respect to a transmission of data through a restricted country if—</text><subclause id="H1F837B4CDAC94BE88F31B5CAE36B86D9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the data is encrypted as described in subsection (b)(4)(A)(iii); or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA182B6621F3F4D829FE255FCD26DA3E4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the person that originated the transmission received a representation from the party delivering the data for the person stating that the data will not transit through a restricted country.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8D8E80BECB91464286342CEFAA5C0FD4"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>False representations</header><text>If a party delivering covered personal data as described in clause (ii)(II) transmits the data directly or indirectly through a restricted country despite making the representation described in clause (ii)(II), that party shall be liable for violating this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H76F271B2C049424BA2E30F80AA3696EE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Foreign adversary</header><text>The term <term>foreign adversary</term> has the meaning given that term in section 8(c)(2) of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1607">47 U.S.C. 1607(c)(2)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H859AC53B0091438FA26560360A485C6E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>In-country transfer; reexport</header><text>The terms <term>in-country transfer</term> and <term>reexport</term>, with respect to personal data, shall have the meanings given those terms in regulations prescribed by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3B74DE742154296B3127CBD81EAEC27"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Lawfully admitted for permanent residence; national</header><text>The terms <term>lawfully admitted for permanent residence</term> and <term>national</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECE1E58ECEFB4010A46BAE3C3F3326BD"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Noncitizen</header><text>The term <term>noncitizen</term> means an individual who is not a citizen or national of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA46B2A2D43884496AF24067CFBE06E82"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Restricted country</header><text>The term <term>restricted country</term> means a country for which a license or other authorization is required under subsection (b) for the export or reexport to, or in-country transfer in, that country of covered personal data in a manner that exceeds the applicable threshold established under subsection (a)(3).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDD20380B847642FCAE140200CB4DEC9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>Section 1752 of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4811">50 U.S.C. 4811</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H83E351E3992E4950A444A5A0EF2910EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="HB281A2A53E164579A6854E4075002E61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86710FE4DF934461BA5B497597B209B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65CF207893D44279B9ECCFB37F37175C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9C683FECE1D143598C423B74E8C4C7B5"><subparagraph id="H790137A1B66542EFBA054CEAE35CFC90"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to restrict, notwithstanding section 203(b) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702(b)</external-xref>), the export of personal data of United States citizens and other covered individuals (as defined in section 1758A(l)) in a quantity and a manner that could harm the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF96ABA174886427EBF620C7138B34951"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF88FB7BC37F849CEA4BDAA9A1F854200"><subparagraph id="HC58C0EEBD62B4746B23CF0F6B95D0706"><enum>(H)</enum><text>To prevent the exploitation of personal data of United States citizens and other covered individuals (as defined in section 1758A(l)) in a quantity and a manner that could harm the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDC7013EB627484CA29BB1673D5648EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation on authority To make exceptions to licensing requirements</header><text>Section 1754 of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4813">50 U.S.C. 4813</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HFB271F48651943B5AAA32EA7F9A867A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(14), by inserting <quote>and subject to subsection (g)</quote> after <quote>as warranted</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7E76D29A0DB41B1BD9FB489605CE155"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2F847B88431348E7943E5483C60D8AA0"><subsection id="HD1F805B229B4471096BCE714C4D2D024"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation on authority To make exceptions to licensing requirements</header><text>The Secretary may create under subsection (a)(14) exceptions to licensing requirements under section 1758A only for the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of covered personal data (as defined in subsection (l) of that section) by or for a Federal department or agency.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8AF8CF8E72384187BE0E9858D5DF16A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Relationship to International Emergency Economic Powers Act</header><text>Section 1754(b) of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4813">50 U.S.C. 4813(b)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(other than section 1758A)</quote> after <quote>this part</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF55A56AC4C74447E92508FEE465724A5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of or any amendment made by this Act, or the application of any such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of the provisions of and amendments made by this Act, and the application of such provisions and amendments to any other person or circumstance, shall not be affected.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

