<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCE1DF9E133064D1C866A6F813D0D0ABA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>92 HR 3245 IH: Nonprofit Stakeholders Engaging and Advancing Together Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3245</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To strengthen the partnership between the nonprofit organizations and the Federal Government, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19326AA7ADDD4558B30585708EBFFD15" style="OLC"><section id="HD5328B44638E4679BBC0830D5DA740CC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nonprofit Stakeholders Engaging and Advancing Together Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA069D0BE08A54B9B86A893F17881EEAC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds that:</text><paragraph id="H6F19A2B5D6EE454682555726FC2D05C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The nonprofit sector is a trusted partner in working with American communities, strengthening civil society, and ensuring that all people living in the United States have the opportunity to thrive.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB24317051518443FBC3B0975EA26142E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Nation relies on the nonprofit sector for its ability to harness and direct the generosity, service, and volunteerism of the American people.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96441C7FB596448AA4CE1B0F49F51569"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nonprofit organizations are a significant and highly diverse sector of the United States economy that includes 1,800,000 organizations as of 2020, according to the Internal Revenue Service. United States nonprofit organizations contributed $1.5 trillion to the economy in 2022 and accounted for 5.6 percent of the Gross Domestic Product of the United States, according to Bureau of Economic Analysis data interpreted by Independent Sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1B3C3C5EA334D80B01329832D5DB253"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collectively, the nonprofit sector engages through and is supported by more than 12.5 million workers, 20 million board members, 60 million volunteers, and millions more donors. In 2017, United States nonprofit organizations paid over $670 billion in wages.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7B36725E1A444D9B79B4185FD88C40B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>92 percent of the 501(c)(3) public charities in the United States have an annual budget of less than $1,000,000 according to data provided by the Internal Revenue Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B987166A2C1406790182EAE40FE3F75"><enum>(6)</enum><text>While no Federal agency regularly collects systematic employment data on the nonprofit sector, at the local level, nonprofits are a time-tested mechanism for delivering critical community services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C51BA94FFB54B3ABF93C2F4BCAB2AEF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In order to maximize the nonprofit sector’s ability to utilize Federal investments to respond to community needs, the Federal Government should take steps to encourage, support, and promote volunteerism and charitable giving.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D7CA79751FE4547868EAC7DC6B96BDE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>National service programs provide an essential vehicle for Americans of all ages eager to serve their communities and transform their own lives in the process. Service programs also provide a critical pipeline of emerging leaders into the workforce, including the nonprofit workforce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC25B4F3D2294618AC81A0DE25988B2C"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Like for-profit entities, the nonprofit sector is challenged during times of economic downturns. As employers and providers of services to countless people, the sustainability of this sector is of great national importance, yet the Federal Government provides significant support to for-profit businesses through the Small Business Administration and other agencies and programs that nonprofit organizations are not able to access.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3390B924DB504E3B8DB6B657EDC985CA"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Despite the importance of the nonprofit sector to the United States economy and to the success of many Federal, State, and local policy initiatives, no Federal agency or office has responsibility for evaluating, building, or maintaining the capacity of the nonprofit sector.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H8FC29E7B63C04BF883FDB0850711CDFB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are the following:</text><paragraph id="H8E0E67BC0E984CA4B21D0631EABCBD94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To enhance the ability of the nonprofit sector to address public challenges and maximize opportunities to improve quality of life in the communities where nonprofit organizations work.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDAB8DC7C395495EB463489E93A9B233"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To strengthen communities across the United States by making the Federal Government a more productive partner with nonprofit organizations through the establishment of better Federal coordination with respect to, enhanced transparency with respect to, and greater support for the work of nonprofit organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF7EFC264C5C4900B351DFEC5EF89898"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collect, assemble, and make available Federal data and research on the nonprofit sector and to generate new data and research where necessary to support the development of effective Federal policy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE26C4A4C410B47F4AD8350E3905F9BF8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Raise awareness of the nonprofit sector and the vital civic, social, and economic contributions nonprofit organizations make to the United States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H3FDD28A618AD4F5DB7C193D5A83120BA"><enum>4.</enum><header>White House Office on Nonprofit Sector Partnership</header><subsection id="H55F0DD15CBCC43F08BDD6F694827B868"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Executive Office of the President an Office on Nonprofit Sector Partnership (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>). The Office will be led by a Nonprofit Advisor.</text></subsection><subsection id="H76F50635EAB34FFAB095925444435F0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The Office shall—</text><paragraph id="H10258D7C16234C79844B0C8083C22D5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strengthen and develop policies and actions which enhance the sector’s ability to address national and community priorities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CCADD20A3C04307BD9538ADAA638E08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and promote policies that increase and sustain charitable giving, volunteerism, and national service to support the capacity of the nonprofit sector;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF45581FAAA8A493C9B32A770940FF302"><enum>(3)</enum><text>publish, based upon regular consultation with the nonprofit sector, policy options and recommendations for leveraging the unique partnership between the Federal Government and the nonprofit sector to accelerate repair and rebuilding across America, particularly with respect to underserved and marginalized communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9939C9104A84D7FBA7E267C744C7085"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify barriers and policies that hinder, increase, or sustain opportunities for nonprofits to operate internationally both on their own or in partnership with the Federal Government;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DD646F18C384FBE8AE03C517E189025"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate, across relevant Federal agencies, the task of compiling, producing and making publicly available key existing Federal data sources of relevance to the nonprofit sector. This will include data on the economic health and impact of the nonprofit sector (including employment and wage data), data on Federal funding of the nonprofit sector (including grants and contracts), Census data, and data on aggregated types of revenue, volunteering and civic engagement and be published publicly annually; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA9064EB90D4116BADB78AB4307F6DD"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">direct a Federal agency, to be determined by the Nonprofit Advisor within 180 days, to initiate, in consultation with States, a competitive grant process to build a single online portal, such that charities can fulfill State registration and reporting requirements for States that choose to participate through a single filing. An eligible grant recipient must be a nonprofit organization with governing board members possessing experience working to align charitable registration requirements across States. In evaluating applications for this portal, the Federal agency shall consider whether the application will—</text><subparagraph id="HF7BFF1C836A14110B75366A7213F8EEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enable smaller charities to respond to disasters in their communities by raising funds from multiple States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B9E8E4A4E2F46E197AA8208F3ECF45F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>empower the public to make responsible donations, especially to help those in need during natural disasters or other crises of national significance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF903131F7CF84F8B80F0D8EBFD98CC58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>eliminate costly inefficiencies for charities operating or fundraising in multiple States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53A6BCA1B93E4EE69C96705DD77937B7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>help nonprofits meet existing registration and filing requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H548F8DEBDD8C4D94B29E47C74061DFD0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>ensure appropriate cybersecurity standards are being met or exceeded;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32D75C0DFAA549FDA638AF84CAFA9715"><enum>(F)</enum><text>preserve the public’s trust in nonprofits; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H303E7D238CA74C5F84049A26EE450F57"><enum>(G)</enum><text>establish a sustainable funding mechanism that is not reliant on Federal funding for ongoing costs; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H47AA0E4CCF824858BDF9FA0EA50C8DA5" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>convene a commission on Federal grant reform composed of individuals representing Federal grantmaking agencies, pass-through entities, and nonprofit grantees and subgrantees to offer recommendations to streamline and improve the operational relationship between all levels of government and the nonprofit sector. In addition, the sector’s access to, participation in and performance in Federal, State, and local government contracting and funding shall be assessed—</text><subparagraph id="H8AECF5B11C8141B8B7A40CE9C5DE1EEB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the commission members shall be appointed by the President and be drawn from the nonprofit sector to include designees with substantial and diverse experience in Federal, State, and local governmental grantmaking processes, and shall include proportional representation from small, medium, and large nonprofit organizations as determined by annual expenses, and include meaningful racial, gender, ethnic and geographic diversity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D52D19140304000906A1778D502C3D6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the report of the commission shall include recommendations on—</text><clause id="HB412CC1682BF4E5893E21410B70F306A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improving provisions of the Uniform Administrative Requirements, Cost Principles, and Audit Requirements for Federal Awards (OMB Uniform Guidance), (2 C.F.R. 200), related to racial, gender, ethnic inclusion in grantmaking processes, and to negotiation of indirect costs, including a de minimis indirect cost rate;</text></clause><clause id="HD79EC7E236394AF1A18FCD03E2617D38" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promoting Federal agency compliance with the OMB Uniform Guidance to preserve the integrity of Federal programs while allowing nonprofit organizations streamlined access to Federal funding opportunities, expressly in the areas of payment by pass-through entities and others of indirect cost rates and establishment of a clearinghouse of agency decisions or other means for maintaining consistent interpretation of the OMB Uniform Guidance;</text></clause><clause id="H11CEA8ADFEE54938A0DB14B9C9379555" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>reviewing Federal statutes and regulations to identify inconsistent requirements and restrictions on payment of <quote>administrative costs</quote> and other terms and definitions, and consider the impact of inconsistent or conflicting rules on organizations seeking Federal and State pass-through grants on their operations and sustainability;</text></clause><clause id="H772B6F2FBA9B4EAAA319832EA5B4C146" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>assessing how grant agreements and reimbursements can be modified to enable and incentivize nonprofits to utilize government grant funds to provide relevant professional development to employees working on those grants, and to ensure that interns and those in apprenticeships working on government grants or contracts are paid rather than unpaid; and</text></clause><clause id="H52915AA7394C4FA5A9B50851D7B05A24" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>reporting its recommendations on the foregoing to the President and Congress, no later than 18 months after enactment, and addressing how grant and contract agreements and reimbursements should be modified to enable nonprofit grant recipients to respond to issues of national significance; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E47E17D115F4AD28607950692399618" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at the direction of the President, but no later than 5 years after the release of the report described in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph, the commission shall reconvene to further review the operational relationship between all levels of government and the nonprofit sector and evaluate it for improvement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H14C18679BB4248D29C076469ED1C0350"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The President shall appoint a Nonprofit Advisor within 90 days of enactment of this legislation. The Nonprofit Advisor shall, in addition to being Director of the Office, serve as the head of the Interagency Council, co-chair of the Advisory Council, and responsible to carry out the provisions of this section and coordinate with executive departments as appropriate with respect to the mission of the Office and related governmental entities.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9351D20CD8DF45B1BE1991536A7A099D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interagency Council on Nonprofit Sector Partnership</header><subsection id="HA6885769FE6148CC9448FA3FAFB02742"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the executive branch an independent entity to be known as the Interagency Council on Nonprofit Sector Partnership.</text></subsection><subsection id="H219DC7E5AC3543ED84BA72E1DA0A1481"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Council shall be composed of the head of each cabinet agency, or their designee in addition to the—</text><paragraph id="H1ABBC224E37C48508C06C16F5DF11F1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Corporation for National and Community Service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EF6DFACA4D149BDA6B40FD1CCBDB558"><enum>(2)</enum><text>National Endowment for the Humanities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59ED6EB1103F4E0BA5F9668BD5A7EAB2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>National Endowment for the Arts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41B2837C991A49ED985DC64DD9EFECDA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>National Science Foundation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8547F25AF7A449FA861B3859488CD2ED"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Institute of Museum and Library Services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7AE05E08AEE4791A5B756F864BB9069"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other agencies as determined by the President.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD8DBF515B7474D06A8EBC6278A66235E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Interagency Council, shall issue biennial reports providing specific recommendations on how the nonprofit sector can best leverage and accelerate Federal investments to repair and rebuild American communities and to offer specific recommendations for strengthening, promoting, and improving the overall ability of the nonprofit sector to address issues of national significance. These recommendations shall include consideration of—</text><paragraph id="HD7C66A4D53EC46F6B52219D1DE7D8FCE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improving Federal research and data access and transparency, including by collecting and disseminating disaggregated data and research relevant to the ability of the nonprofit sector to respond to societal need;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBF04A9766704971AFA637C94E8CF3D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consulting and partnering with nonprofits as an engine of employment, preparing Americans for their first jobs or new jobs, deploying national service members to rebuild communities while acquiring valuable professional and civic skills and career guidance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEABB31383D3453A99461DC0CDF4C9EF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>legislation, regulation, and other action toward these goals, including changes to the structure of the Interagency Council;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H783E403E4EFE4836A874BBEC5134929E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Federal efforts that could have an impact on charitable giving, volunteerism, and national service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D10435134314CF782068468B7CC8482"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Federal investments that could bolster the civic infrastructure of the United States, which includes its workforce, volunteer force, capacity of nonprofit institutions, and the norms and practices that help communities solve problems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D53CD1E97E540D7AEBED339BCE78854"><enum>(6)</enum><text>how Federal technology policies and funding could be more effectively aligned with the nonprofit sector and the communities it serves.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE07DDCD738EE4CAE8544ABF062888D86"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Interagency Council shall be chaired by the Nonprofit Advisor and may accept staff detailed from Federal agencies to support coordination and implementation efforts. The Interagency Council shall meet no fewer than four times per year.</text></subsection></section><section id="H04643BD2A4CF4324BB14848DE3BA3C84"><enum>6.</enum><header>Advisory board on the nonprofit sector</header><subsection id="HEBB2634F6D6449D69408A5F642FC0141"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is hereby established under the Federal Advisory Committee Act, (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/92/463">Public Law 92–463</external-xref>), an Advisory Board on the Nonprofit Sector, co-chaired by the Nonprofit Advisor and a designee from the nonprofit sector, as appointed by the President and Congress as described below, except for subsection (b)(2)(B) of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3E917D12E3C1433FBB3E5C88441B0537"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="HDE338CE309224223A5096CC940E91B01"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number and appointment</header><text>The Advisory Board shall be composed of 16 members as follows:</text><subparagraph id="HF104F2BAB6B5433A8FCAB6BCAE1E3363"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Nonprofit Advisor and seven additional members shall be appointed by the President.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14E04C0B047E4AA185D800BF09F4C98C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A547599745C4E5BA2F0E89B51E7A5E8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02BEA18520F34433A7DC652DB7C6640F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the majority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H423AA32F038A4C728D2A858CA062E699"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCCDA70AF5F44B51BE79DBCDD6014CCD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With the exception of the Nonprofit Advisor, membership of the Advisory Board shall be drawn from the nonprofit sector to include designees with substantial and diverse experience and points of view in the issues facing the nonprofit sector. This shall include leading national organizations that represent the interests of the broad sector, as well as proportional representation to the extent possible from representatives of large, medium and small nonprofit and philanthropic organizations as determined by annual expenses and include meaningful racial, gender, ethnic and geographic diversity. The terms of members to the Advisory Board shall be staggered between three and four years and renewable for one term.</text><subparagraph id="H17BDB7980E81486ABE58D1B433F9923F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy on the Board shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAA011C62B9540BD8CBF4F5BF29B8661"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Basic pay and travel expenses</header><text>With the exception of the Nonprofit Advisor, all Voting Board members shall, and nonvoting members may, be appointed as special Government employees and receive a consultant fee and be reimbursed for travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in the same manner as provided under the Federal Advisory Committee Act, unless such compensation and reimbursement are waived.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3530AEEE5AAF47DC83146CF1D667E0B5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Co-chairs</header><text>The President shall designate the Nonprofit Advisor as a co-chair of the Advisory Board and select an additional co-chair from among the members of the Board, who may not be members of the same political party.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9CF0B1633EDE4045872660DE46543AAF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The Advisory Board shall issue biennial reports to Congress, as well as advise the President and the Interagency Council on matters involving policy affecting the nonprofit sector, volunteerism, service, and other related topics. The Advisory Board shall meet regularly, upon the call of the co-chairs, and shall—</text><paragraph id="HC56F76C1DEE84D309BBCB6DD3A745B6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>respond to requests from the President or the President’s designee for information, analysis, evaluation, or advice;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40E62B43900A409FBBB61BE29F7202B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>solicit information and ideas from a broad range of stakeholders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H413B4A3F702E4FAFB8064DE7F5A10604"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in its biennial report, provide information on the state of the nonprofit sector, charitable giving, volunteerism and national service, as well as feedback on the effect of Federal policies on each;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10B5422549E741E6B82CF78E080CA5B9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in its biennial report, provide recommendations on legislative, regulatory, and executive actions to improve and support the nonprofit sector and its partnerships with the Federal Government;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7396A63DD534A4E953AA8D2ED7EC5A6"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in its biennial report, provide recommendations on long-term opportunities to strengthen the nonprofit sector, charitable giving, volunteerism and national service through Federal actions and policy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2E20B5A27A442D880B6A13CA2B9A615"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in its biennial report, include a statement analyzing how any recommendations would impact the disparities between members of different racial and ethnic groups.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7521542D272A42E88B3CAE60A43AA819"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The heads of executive departments and agencies shall provide the Advisory Board with information concerning appropriate matters when requested by the Advisory Board Co-Chairs and as required for the purpose of carrying out the Advisory Board’s functions, unless otherwise prohibited by law.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDE5FF30886A747109F46C828A74549BD"><enum>7.</enum><header>Volunteerism and charitable giving</header><subsection id="H0220A20AF83247009C84CE75544B2ED6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Treasury department</header><text>The Secretary of the Department of the Treasury shall—</text><paragraph id="HBC47668F5602425E9F17081949D903F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>analyze and publicly release the impact of relevant statutes, regulations, and other actions on charitable giving specifically and the nonprofit sector generally, including analysis disaggregated by demographic factors whenever possible; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9CD6462070E46B6A7B9DB4C5B4C88C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>examine the reconstitution of the Advisory Committee on Tax Exempt and Government Entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E466B2B4CA44760960EE63C6A011E2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Department of labor, bureau of labor statistics</header><text>The Bureau of Labor Statistics shall within two years of enactment, issue a biennial report on trends in the non-stipended volunteer force.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9A55659E01AA42F3BBF90F6B24A7A66D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Corporation for national and community service</header><text>The Corporation for National and Community Service shall—</text><paragraph id="H9B89BCADA3034F36B4878A67CDECB8CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issue a comprehensive report assessing how CNCS can best be structured and resourced to support the unique needs and potential of both the non-stipended volunteer force and the national service community. This assessment shall also consider how underserved and marginalized communities can access service programs. CNCS shall share that report with Congress within six months of enactment and issue updates every two years, thereafter;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H141CE4B0C9904685AD086FF4FF2F6890"><enum>(2)</enum><text>review existing programs such as the Volunteer Generation Fund and the Nonprofit Capacity Building Program to determine how these programs could be strengthened and/or expanded to ensure, among other critical functions, they will support a wide diversity of nonprofits to build capacity to engage, sustain, and support the volunteer force, and to share such recommendations with Congress within six months of enactment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69042EF343DC4A879DE00AA6316C1A61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>within 90 days of enactment, solicit input from the nonprofit sector and the public about enhancing and revising the Current Population Survey with supplements on—</text><subparagraph id="H3602D9F485724F7DA8DA2004C3E814DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>volunteerism;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0BA2FFBEAF043CA9DAC67DFB05EDC01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>charitable giving; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDE6D64DBD1546ADBBB95E8CF415FB10"><enum>(C)</enum><text>civic engagement; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B511F0DDD0B489E9401EDD4DEF9DCB4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>within six months of enactment, present the findings of the input described in paragraph (3) to Congress and the Office on the Nonprofit Sector.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H09882D961B9F4A998973BEF39A4EF200"><enum>8.</enum><header>National service</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Corporation for National and Community Service shall—</text><paragraph id="HA8B31A8319BA4B0AAF603237F944BB31"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by no later than one year from the date of enactment, make recommendations to Congress on updating Service Year Fellowships to broaden access to national service for underserved and marginalized communities and provide increased capacity for all section 501(c)(3) nonprofits in moments of increased need; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D35D23DAB8E4A0B830D1157F0AE8747"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by no later than two years from the date of enactment, redesign and relaunch the eGrants system, including user testing that engages organizations who are not current grantees and that represent or reach underserved and marginalized communities to test barriers to submitting for a grant.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA58391E4B5074631B41510F156296EAC"><enum>9.</enum><header>Government research and data</header><subsection id="H8A3617A0249B4551BB2176AD46564E7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Treasury department</header><text>The Secretary of the Department of the Treasury shall—</text><paragraph id="H60ED053BB54B4EE081F0F5ADEE6330AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in consultation with the Advisory Committee, make recommendations to Congress on how to formulate the way data are recorded concerning government grants, contracts, and reimbursements to nonprofit organizations on Form 990, Return of Organization Exempt from Income Tax, to increase the utility and clarity of Form 990 information. The IRS shall also take steps to improve public access to 990 e-filed data, providing the schema and metadata necessary to facilitate public use;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2D48C485A584067A43D947EDE415F30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>revoke the use of form 1023–EZ for nonprofit filing status and initiate a process to replace it, based upon recommendations from the Advisory Board, the nonprofit sector, representatives of the National Association of State Charities Officials and government examinations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD764C180276E4C7CB2761E0925CF47BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in consultation with stakeholders in the nonprofit sector, including the Advisory Board, consider and publicly release recommendations, funding needs, and activities to improve the nonprofit sector and to preserve integrity within the sector and on behalf of the general public.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9757A4908BB54ED1B5EE5F16BF364937"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Department of labor, bureau of labor statistics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau of Labor Statistics shall include nonprofit organizations as a distinct category of employer in quarterly reports from its Quarterly Census of Employment and Wages. Within 90 days of enactment, the Bureau of Labor Statistics shall transmit a plan to Congress that will accomplish this goal.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEB8CBD25A875492C817E7225EA87BC25"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of commerce, bureau of economic analysis</header><text>The Bureau of Economic Analysis shall in consultation with the Advisory Committee, create a Satellite Account on Nonprofit and Related Institutions and Volunteer Work within its national accounts program. This account shall be published no less frequently than on a biennial basis.</text></subsection><subsection id="H68C2FDF399F54048BD58EEE7E5616DDC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>White House, Office of Management and Budget</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Management and Budget shall—</text><paragraph id="H3CF7B827489D4FD6A04B3834BC04BB48"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">solicit information from all relevant Federal agencies that collect existing data on the nonprofit sector in all published reports and publicly available tables and datasets and direct these agencies to include existing data disaggregated by the following factors— </text><subparagraph id="H2C37231F4D0045FF8D12DD5659305DD1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of clients served by nonprofit organizations, including existing data on the race, gender, age, income level, languages spoken, and geographic location of such clients;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1189F0B038504366891F443342CECF26"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">existing data on types of revenues, expenses, and operating reserves by nonprofit organizations of various sizes and missions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H067CEA71E9934F77A556055355FEB813"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the volunteer hours contributed to nonprofit organizations by individuals in the United States; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H831CA5BB812F49FF88A97C4E4AD365C0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other factors in existing data as determined in consultation with the Advisory Board; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB63AFA89E15B47C783A65FC7102171D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct an impact assessment of how government data collection, algorithm use, and accuracy may have a discriminatory or disparate impact on nonprofit issues or communities they serve, particularly underserved and marginalized communities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDEB87AE797624EBB9482C9273F9A6D3E"><enum>10.</enum><header>Nonpartisan civic engagement and advocacy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Government Accountability Office shall, within 1 year of enactment and after gathering input from the Advisory Board and the broader nonprofit sector, issue a report to Congress on—</text><paragraph id="H10B570848C604EDA8847D26BBE29F933"><enum>(1)</enum><text>opportunities to clarify the difference between nonpartisan civic engagement and the current prohibition on political campaign intervention for organizations organized under section 501(c)(3) of title 26, United States Code; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2168F809B2D04544A84C853A2C254A77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the role of the current <quote>facts and circumstances</quote> standard for tax-exempt entities organized under provisions of the Internal Revenue Code other than section 501(c)(3) of title 26, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE855A64E625E4108BEFAE0BDDB29C17F"><enum>11.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HC9E9460B25704836908BAD85322B48C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nonprofit</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit</term> or <term>nonprofit organization</term> shall include the definition included in section 501(c)(3) of title 26, United States Code, and in addition shall mean a group organized for purposes other than generating profit and in which no part of the organization’s income is distributed to its members, directors, or officers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57BCA252CB9A4A4685BCE04283C2B2CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pass-through entity</header><text>The term <term>pass-through entity</term> shall include the definition included in section 200.1 of title 2, Code of Federal Regulations, a non-Federal entity that provides a subaward to a subrecipient to carry out part of a Federal program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC44BAEE6FDA419BB9796667D1558F1F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nonprofit advisor</header><text>The term <term>Nonprofit Advisor</term> means an individual who is—</text><subparagraph id="H1B577190216F4465877698846C44F40D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>designated as an Assistant to the President;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H760A537750B84A1E85B0E563DDC8654A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has experience working in the nonprofit sector and government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C8420B01D5B4072956CBF6E012DCDBF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has demonstrated a commitment to strengthening the partnership between the Federal Government and the nonprofit sector.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H632462155D7541DD8961CDED878C3235"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Current Population Survey</header><text>The term <term>Current Population Survey</term> means the jointly sponsored survey administered by the Census Bureau and the Bureau of Labor Statistics and approved by the Office of Management and Budget (OMB Number 0607–0049).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE26B32365CD3448DB2436E58DCB149A6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Underserved and marginalized communities</header><text>The term <term>underserved and marginalized communities</term> means individuals who are—</text><subparagraph id="HE4365F1DF78C499680B5BF2A698A3918"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, Black or African American, Hispanic or Latino, or Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, and other demographics included in and according to Office of Management and Budget Statistical Policy Directive No. 15, Race and Ethnic Standards for Federal Statistics and Administrative Reporting as amended;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H475AC7B393024C41A5A006FD0061A93E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rural populations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H203CF87AB2B6437FBEE28375793E9B3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>individuals with disabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EC6BE39BC9A40CEB896C2F11A2B520F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>low-income or homeless individuals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H450D117D508C4815AFD3368551363370"><enum>(E)</enum><text>individuals with mental health or substance related disorders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDB2867149144E3B9D1B92124178F90A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>victims of abuse or trauma;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07F0E2D1EC294403BB1F616E0E0FCAC0"><enum>(G)</enum><text>lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA669BE41FB5546D08DA9161C2CE84DEA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>refugees or migrants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H46B1EBB216CD4C0E9E7FB3ECE12CE2CE"><enum>12.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the provisions of this Act $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

