<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1B8B9507B57847519DF2FC843B0CF4A6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5440 IH: Protecting Americans from Foreign Commercial Spyware Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5440</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230913">September 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 to prohibit assistance to foreign governments that engage in the use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC77078299C90461F9C161DF3146A4E3A" style="OLC"><section id="HEBDD4431805C4795B2EB40B9CC0C0FFD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Americans from Foreign Commercial Spyware Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1DACC0642138458D9486DF531AA133AA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on assistance to foreign governments that engage in the use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Chapter 1 of part III (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2351">22 U.S.C. 2351 et seq.</external-xref>) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA02DEA5FCD2E4C48A9E9385D6B55DD18" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HDF1F6611C41D43DD9265BF2FF05FE9BD"><enum>620N.</enum><header>Prohibition on assistance to foreign governments that engage in the use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons</header><subsection id="HA8A96E0B6C6A42BD80A03C54999EA112"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided in this section, no assistance may be provided under this Act to the central government of a country with respect to which the President makes a determination based on credible information and in accordance with subsection (c) that the government engages in the use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD3B7373BCA0D401C8B0B241BCF9A0F86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President certifies in writing to the appropriate congressional committees that extraordinary circumstances or national security priorities exist warranting provision to a central government of a country of assistance otherwise prohibited pursuant to subsection (a), the United States may provide to such government such assistance.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9BB1C44E11E14DEAA3C6FB529BFE794C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making a determination under subsection (a) with respect to the central government of a country, the President shall give particular consideration to whether the government—</text><paragraph id="H520518FDABF74588B3303BE4A60AF469"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has a record of acquiring commercial foreign commercial spyware;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9014A25858DD417993A01F97631F67D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has used foreign commercial spyware against its own citizens, particularly journalists, political opponents, or activists; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06601EFF7DFC492792B114E8349C6182"><enum>(3)</enum><text>has failed to undertake serious and sustained efforts to combat the use of foreign commercial spyware in undemocratic ways.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52F1E6585E624206B7E00040B611E124"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The prohibition under subsection (a) does not apply to military assistance.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEDDD95C10E4B46C7BEE5BBEEF1F19A55"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibition under subsection (a) with respect to the central government of a country shall terminate 1 year after the President makes a determination that the government no longer engages in the use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons.</text></subsection><subsection id="H57F89AC96E644621B1A6E9EC73E86FBC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall annually submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate as part of the presentation materials for assistance programs proposed for each fiscal year, a full and complete classified report, prepared in consultation with the intelligence community’s classified annex, required under section 1102A of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3232a">50 U.S.C. 3232a</external-xref>), with respect to governmental use of foreign commercial spyware to target United States persons in each country proposed as a recipient of assistance under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD2F21FC48B6747B79F5CEF40243B1CFB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB0D8D115D96F48D4A889F8554403E476"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Foreign commercial spyware</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘foreign commercial spyware’ means a tool (or set of tools) sold, leased, marketed, or otherwise provided as an end-to-end system originally developed or owned by a foreign spyware company that provides a purchaser remote access to information stored on or transiting through an electronic device connected to the internet, including end-to-end systems that—</text><subparagraph id="HD5EC195D112244128C982548084DAB20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allow malign actors to infect mobile and internet-connected devices with malware over both wireless internet and cellular data connections, including without any action required by the user of the device;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H697BF7C072D14DF5B023CE1F8CF25D7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>can record telephone calls and other audio;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3A56D7147224BE8976A961A11F327D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>track the location of the device; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EB79CCC19DD4434A560852203ED7455"><enum>(D)</enum><text>access and retrieve information on the device, including text messages, files, e-mails, transcripts of chats, contacts, photos, and browsing history.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H104B1589547C462AA48D52DA32B30DBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D64E294A1BD4F4FB068732100B61FA0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>United States person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>United States person</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 560.314 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

