<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAC53612D55EE4D749904426E851EEEA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1288 IH: Holding Countries Accountable for Negligent Chemical and Biological Programs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1288</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991 to impose sanctions against governments of foreign states that engage in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to state owned, operated, or directed chemical or biological programs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB77732D736D64E19A5DDC694330BE916" style="OLC"><section id="HDD8F0B9A941643098EDCEC13367B7ADC" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Holding Countries Accountable for Negligent Chemical and Biological Programs Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H3F1A2FB3A0224074890C4E62795A25D9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It shall be the policy of the United States to impose sanctions against governments of foreign states, and take other measures if the governments of such foreign states that engage in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to State-owned, operated, or directed chemical or biological programs. </text></section><section id="H5DA9F9DDF95C4864A374B4E16CF82079"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendments to the Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991</header><subsection id="H41F66894ED354C4FA78C19642E9EF82B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purposes and definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 502 of the Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5601">22 U.S.C. 5601</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H07F545326CC540238F147BCE0C3943FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by adding at the end before the period the following: <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">and definitions</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3FF4859E09A46F285B7A1A814AFE845"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The purposes</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Purposes</header-in-text>.—The purposes</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5634FA7BF249A08003D9C3ECC1ED56"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H4FC8A336115E4FF7B731D92F420CF6D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or use</quote> and insert <quote>use</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97AB32100BBD47C3B76B9B904CA27601"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or engage in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state</quote> after <quote>nationals</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4321FCA3EA24D3599EF21DC55617503"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5A72F20813CD40138A27F70D810C936B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H5AAF557FBABC417D82FD59934CBD84D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD1D2DCED50E74AC79A52CD8C2E5ACB64"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gross negligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>gross negligence</quote>, with respect to an act or acts of a government of a foreign state, includes the government knew, or should have known, the act or acts would result in injury or damages to another foreign state or other such foreign states.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1028074C96B74AE4A0F2DDFFC2ABF9CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign state</header><text>The term <quote>foreign state</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H8CBBDD3D78E84BEE9E3F3CEB5C87325C"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1EFE1D2A0E724F168FE2631CF97FB4CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the meaning given that term in subsection (a) of section 1603 of title 28, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H479D0C95F61340ABB505B3F4AB011408" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes an <quote>agency or instrumentality of a foreign state</quote> as that term is defined in subsection (b) of such section; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE97F8AF76E64A149ED555E478804930"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes an entity that is—</text><clause id="HA97C61919DA849DCAC56982EB50D5DB7"><enum>(i)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1A30378A421040039F5058D00A9B3EF6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly or indirectly owned, controlled, or beneficially owned by, or in an official or unofficial capacity acting as an agent of or on behalf of, the government of a foreign state; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H76823B18593A4985A4B56DB81BD6DB5D" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>received significant material support from the government of a foreign state; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF06AD61849C94405B0C3338841222FFE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>engaged in providing commercial services, shipping, manufacturing, producing, or exporting.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H56687BCD6D5E412EBF0572D37256CD09"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determinations regarding use of chemical or biological weapons</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 506 of the Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5604">22 U.S.C. 5604</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H772C7B4630964A02922C03A355775A88"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H200334D91F2A494CB857791B485633D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC20199106C4D939824F3168FB6B05B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H610037BFDE7441718E1DBBFB606331EE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HE65ABEB1109F4AF7946CA58CA7D956D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional determination by the President</header><subparagraph id="HD5AC0F4CC712428C89867D406ABECD99"><enum>(A)</enum><header>When determination required; nature of determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever credible information becomes available to the executive branch indicating a substantial possibility that, on or after January 1, 2020, the government of a foreign country has engaged in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state, the President shall, within 60 days after the receipt of such information by the executive branch, determine whether that government, on or after such date, has engaged in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state. Section 507 applies if the President determines that that government has so engaged in such act or acts of gross negligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA513ABBCDFEF46358D3292ECE8C6767E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Matters to be considered</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making the determination under subparagraph (A), the President shall consider the following: </text><clause id="HB9D1254FA9DC4D189B76E461B5C73FBD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>All physical and circumstantial evidence available bearing on the possibility that the government in question engaged in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state. </text></clause><clause id="H4D2FE029CF674E0DBD5B210958D6D749"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Whether evidence exists that such program or programs have civilian and military purposes or applications. </text></clause><clause id="HC494A29F534D40F895CA211A0A3EECFC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Whether the government in question attempted to conceal or otherwise withhold information from other governments or international organizations regarding an act or acts of gross negligence. </text></clause><clause id="H5B2B3690BF414E7E90041EAC054C81A1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Whether, and to what extent, the government in question is compliant with its obligations under the Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention or Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, Production, Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons and on their Destruction, as applicable.</text></clause><clause id="H45B71C652655465E890CB6DA73009B41"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Whether, and to what extent, the government in question is providing or otherwise voluntarily disclosing substantive information to relevant international organizations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0663FD704E7A4669844FC8D95371BAF8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (4) (as redesignated)—</text><clause id="H89BC4B2781D64CBC871B4F0AB5125D01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>or (3)</quote> after <quote>paragraph (1)</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H7D64037E906A40B48CC6D2F00F2E9FC1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the second sentence, by inserting <quote>under paragraph (1)</quote> after <quote>determination</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H4FD4268A5D4B44DA9A71DA17641A8431"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>If the determination under paragraph (3) is that a foreign government had engaged in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state, the report shall specify the sanctions to be imposed pursuant to section 507A.</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04DD9632BB7F48218254FB603368EB34"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H7553E09826D9462DBC6087ED10CE0A07"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="HC3F6E1351D1B411B9C0255D91A7D6DCB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>whether a particular foreign government</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC7AF2B85E29242BAB3927C48D3D62651" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>whether—</text><subparagraph id="HBD61DF5A1F6E4ECFA9DF99023C4E0136"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a particular foreign government</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H814170CCCE5C4243A1BAC774CF6BF5FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC9F3C047CC374A8993DF2DFE24A4DB0E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBD4544E40A694C3D8DFC250C6A36A220" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H64D8C81D07BF4BA189915CB07FE4B837"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a particular foreign government, on or after January 1, 2020, has engaged in an act of acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA7C7E79132E4B658037A781826B7E8D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="HABFDCC80B78045F19589EF1CE15C26D8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the first sentence—</text><subclause id="H2D1E29BC8373495198144049BBEAEF02"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>whether the specified government</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H94DD0F1E8A80479EB8E9D32465F52E96"><text>whether—</text><subparagraph id="HC20DC9732ACF401D9FEF03ED92368B1A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the specified government</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="H8E2E8D5434124ABCAE3B5E740FDBD7D2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0C924CEC0E844A92A232D896B1B27938"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1C77DFE717434BB2AD170ADA3AC73C2B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="HF611DF7C56D5415EB8F131FCF09EFC48"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the specified government, on or after January 1, 2020, has engaged in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H8CAFE0066AE24D7291825F071748C2B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the second sentence—</text><subclause id="H661CCC7A838E43CCB9BBEAC7E2CA5E5D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or (3)(B), as applicable</quote> after <quote>subsection (a)(2)</quote>; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HE58203888D764B9DA08455A4D4C38FB1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by moving the margin of the second sentence so it has the same level of indentation as margin of the matter preceding subparagraph (A) of the first sentence.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE18A8CD62E264A77A4F45FFD50CA6AD0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions against foreign states with respect to chemical or biological programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5601">22 U.S.C. 5601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 507 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7FC48D852C214C1686C2826640565646" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HD4A738E2F5584810BD497D4703CEC4B0"><enum>507A.</enum><header>Sanctions against foreign states with respect to chemical or biological programs</header><subsection id="HF242A0CCA10E452684DF4414B45517AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial sanctions</header><paragraph id="HE55BF4054E5142939E31179C8EAD8AB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the President makes a determination pursuant to section 506(a)(3) with respect to the government of a foreign state, the President shall, within 30 days of making such determination, impose the sanctions described in paragraph (2) with respect to the foreign state.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H812369E67CB049F2AE08E485672A73C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this paragraph are the following: </text><subparagraph id="HB7093B24660B4472A7A91D1EC4CAE4AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The United States Government shall suspend all scientific cooperative programs and efforts with the government of the foreign state.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3BC6F904607443E925884EB9C343647"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The President shall prohibit the export to the foreign state of any goods, services or technology under Category 1 and Category 2 of the Commerce Control List. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC007E50D82BB4753ABAE075CEC7822AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The United States Government may not procure, or enter into any contract for the procurement of, any goods or services from any person operating in the chemical or biological sectors of the foreign state. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4B59C596EADC4214A4CCEE52C93AD95E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intermediate application of sanctions</header><paragraph id="HEA84D927C1BA44F986B9F2006FACA7AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>Not later than 120 days after making a determination pursuant to section 506(a)(3) with respect to a government of a foreign state, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a determination as to whether—</text><subparagraph id="H34079934EFD147EC86E2C34869558D89"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such government has adequately addressed an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82E2CCD78C564F91BB017791A74F42C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such government has developed or is developing necessary measures to prevent any future act or acts of gross negligence; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00943ED1C5434BC09E7254F6855CDFEA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such government is providing or otherwise voluntarily disclosing substantive information to the United States and relevant international organizations; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72014DF5926D43BFB412C641CF527D34"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such government is compliant with its obligations under the Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention or the Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, Production, Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons and on their Destruction, as applicable. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H125A29D2CFB94C6394A0F167448EEEB6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of determination</header><text>If the President is unable to certify that a government of a foreign state has taken the actions described in subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of paragraph (1), the President shall impose 2 or more of the sanctions described in paragraph (3) with respect to the government of the foreign state. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4747D1CDF012418DAA6234DC213A5A74"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H63D953BC9D2D49DAA08403F3E9274358"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The United States Government shall terminate assistance to the government of the foreign state under the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151">22 U.S.C. 2151 et seq.</external-xref>), except for urgent humanitarian assistance and food or other agricultural commodities or products.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H276EF5D2A8FB40A096B943EDD340A5CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>No sales of any defense articles, defense services, or design and construction services under the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2751">22 U.S.C. 2751 et seq.</external-xref>) may be made to the government of the foreign state.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C7925A242F947C1AA2DFE167A60F4D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>No licenses for export of any item on the United States Munitions List that include the government of the foreign state as a party to the license may be granted.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2CFE8492BC3414DA111E9CAD8900DDA"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No exports of any goods or technologies controlled for national security reasons under the Export Administration Regulations may be made to the government of the foreign state, except that such prohibition shall not apply to any transaction subject to the reporting requirements of title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/413">50 U.S.C. 413 et seq.</external-xref>; relating to congressional oversight of intelligence activities).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B6E243A3B984908BBDED06DC7C691CF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The President may order the United States Government not to issue any specific license and not to grant any other specific permission or authority to export any goods or technology to the government of the foreign state under—</text><clause id="HF9C282DF341F4E6E9C7DFCCCC375D5EC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4801">50 U.S.C. 4801 et seq.</external-xref>); </text></clause><clause id="HFFB88DF997844BE68DFD31478178CF97"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2751">22 U.S.C. 2751 et seq.</external-xref>); </text></clause><clause id="H723BD6901F2F42908ED890ABDD1E01DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2011">42 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>); or </text></clause><clause id="H363B00B2455B473CB6823B96CBA6E1FF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other statute that requires the prior review and approval of the United States Government as a condition for the export or reexport of goods or services.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEEEAF6B530C2413B8B905FEF398A1737"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Final application of sanctions</header><paragraph id="H5E05111D2C504586A04FA7B94364636E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 210 days after making a determination pursuant to section 506(a)(3) with respect to a government of a foreign state, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a determination as to whether the government of the foreign state has taken the actions described in subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8E651AB6E26403595AA57BD96E3375B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President is unable to certify that a government of a foreign state has taken the actions described in subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of subsection (b)(1), the President shall impose the sanctions described in paragraph (3) with respect to the government of the foreign state. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1036DCD87CBF405086282DC15EC917D7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sanctions</header><text>The sanctions described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H6536293CD4084879857CA20E550C1659"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The President shall, pursuant to such regulations as the President may prescribe, prohibit any transactions in foreign exchange that are subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and in which the government of the foreign state has any interest.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB74AE966B3794E82BE75E31FC97C02AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The President shall, pursuant to such regulations as the President may prescribe, prohibit any transfers of credit or payments between one or more financial institutions or by, through, or to any financial institution, to the extent that such transfers or payments are subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and involve any interest of the government of the foreign state.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A7F6B0AC84241FA88E3FBBBC3F78075"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Removal of sanctions</header><text>The President shall remove the sanctions imposed with respect to the government of a foreign state pursuant to this section if the President determines and so certifies to the Congress, after the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date on which sanctions were initially imposed on that government of a foreign state pursuant to subsection (a), that—</text><paragraph id="H1A9647878133466887F880239697B160"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such government has adequately addressed an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CF322D8204C439EA4790F756F1392B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such government has developed or is developing necessary measures to prevent any future act or acts of gross negligence; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95993214E3C04D069CDA81515F6F247E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such government is providing or otherwise voluntarily disclosing substantive information to the United States and relevant international organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44AB4A5B3974414FB4CDA3D6AAC76758"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such government is compliant with its obligations under the Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention or Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, Production, Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons and on their Destruction, as applicable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D64D9DFCAFA47508E53F589ACFB600D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such government is making restitution to those affected by an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of the government of a foreign state, including United States persons.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A8523DCE8BD4417A89DCC563E0AFF68"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver</header><paragraph id="H1DD381DD976F4A56851C37F0E6C7CC26"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President may, for periods not to exceed 180 days, waive the imposition of sanctions under this section if the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that such waiver is vital to the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H229DD69647574CF9966BD54B4A828BBC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The President may not exercise the authority described in paragraph (1) beginning on the date that is 4 years after the date of enactment of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75A7AB9075E44CE99306A80E6F2B9BA8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HCF99090D66B34A9F9CD8819F9AD055D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9985D1F0556422A88628D61314BA9E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HF552C59FC25C42D8A03AA9E2BBCE4A16"><enum>4.</enum><header>Determination regarding the People’s Republic of China</header><subsection id="H830B3EBD4F3E4BDEA269E73D6E5A528E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall determine whether reasonable grounds exist for concluding that the Government of the People’s Republic of China meets the criteria for engaging in an act or acts of gross negligence with respect to a chemical or biological program owned, controlled, or directed by, or subject to the jurisdiction of that government under section 506(a)(3) of the Chemical and Biological Weapons Control and Warfare Elimination Act of 1991, as amended by section 3 of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H06DFCD57DA4747029B04C0E80E51323C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report required</header><paragraph id="H7EEB1058516F41EE893D86DA90AD8E7B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after making a determination under subsection (a), the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes the reasons for the determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF864F1388F3243EFB806F5C7F3D25153"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>A report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H67A13DE00D624DAA900E129729D8883E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Regulatory authority</header><subsection id="HEA81DC21F973464598198BBC52E2B349"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, prescribe regulations as necessary for the implementation of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC34269D3165F458281D80F5B64D50EAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification to Congress</header><text>Not later than 10 days before the prescription of regulations under subsection (a), the President shall notify the appropriate congressional committees regarding the proposed regulations and the provisions of this Act and the amendments made by this Act that the regulations are implementing.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE6027BD6D351411E8CA18076AB2B9310"><enum>6.</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H3F62582491524EC0B0A03DD55DD6477F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D57FAB08DDB4C14ACAC6A4E3286C245"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

