<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H50C41404E19C456EBA35900E7DA65F79" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 99 IH: Less Imprecision in Species Treatment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 99</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Endangered Species Act of 1973 to provide for improved precision in the listing, delisting, and downlisting of endangered species and potentially endangered species.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8C74055D2CED466F8BA1F04BCA449706" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H035B7C610C7E4481A5AAECBADB611E90" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Less Imprecision in Species Treatment Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>LIST Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD24B1129E9B14B0A890E64952C05ADF6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement to initiate delisting</header> <subsection id="HB74A7B61CDE04FB8BA8662083D2574EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement in case of recovery</header><text>Section 4(b) of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H1C55130CF0D7467786D5B4EE5A314CEF" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="HD633181F2C0D44C1B40B774E4B44964A"><enum>(9)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1EA735FC4EE745EB86CE755EC9329BC4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary shall initiate the procedures in accordance with subsection (a)(1) to remove a species from a list published under subsection (c) if—</text> <clause id="HE055303A225040C69B90ACBE6AE6327D" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the goals of a recovery plan for the species developed under subsection (f) have been met; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H7CA3E2AAE6EA419086464300051672AC" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the goals for recovery of the species have not been developed under subsection (f), and the Secretary determines that the species has recovered sufficiently to no longer require the protection of the Act.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85F17DD7541646C29B36FF8EF1F6E8EB" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Notwithstanding the requirement of subsection (c)(2) that each determination under subparagraph (B) of that subsection shall be made in accordance with the provisions of subsections (a) and (b), the Secretary shall remove a species from any list published under subsection (c) if the Department of the Interior has produced or received substantial scientific or commercial information demonstrating that the species is recovered or that recovery goals set for the species under subsection (f) have been met.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6DB5C4AAAB9242EBA043DA95E7817B30" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>In the case of a species removed under subparagraph (A) from a list published under subsection (c), the publication and notice under subsection (b)(5) shall consist solely of a notice of such removal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H48A1CAF0E85C474D823572BCC070C86D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement in case erroneously or wrongfully listed</header><text>Section 4(b)(3) of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533(a)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H31CC4BD003754D2987133459BE5173C4" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="HA9C1C65B8C3844A58C9E6564842E57E9"><enum>(H)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H35AC94D6A15A4C00B0572C93F42701FC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Not later than 90 days after the date the Department of the Interior receives or produces under this subsection information described in clause (ii) regarding a species included in a list under subsection (c), the Secretary shall to the maximum extent practicable find whether the inclusion of such species in such list was less than likely to have occurred in the absence of the scientific or commercial information referred to in clause (ii).</text></clause> <clause id="H4BFE76D3BAF4407D879BDAEDCCE751D8" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Information referred to in clause (i) is any information demonstrating that the listing was determined on the basis of scientific or commercial information available to, or received or produced by, the Department under paragraphs (1) and (3) of subsection (b) that at the time the scientific or commercial information was available to or received or produced by the Department it was—</text>
<subclause id="HBB9DE802C4484FA5BB1418DD94467D7A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>inaccurate beyond scientifically reasonable margins of error;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9976AC77E03E439DB8F837C0BCC4EACB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>fraudulent; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HD92F6F3A81424FEC88E68AE6EF0B9A12"><enum>(III)</enum><text>misrepresentative.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H46F8386C196740E4926C2AD6B833C2A2" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Notwithstanding the requirement under subsection (c)(2)(B) that each determination under subparagraph (B) shall be made in accordance with the provisions of subsections (a) and (b), the Secretary shall—</text>
<subclause id="HD7977B423220428D928D7D448862F307"><enum>(I)</enum><text>remove from any list published under subsection (c) any species for which a positive finding is made under clause (i); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAF0E6E2B5AEE43E9A62E9399E2847F70"><enum>(II)</enum><text>promptly publish in the Federal Register notice of such finding that includes such information as was received or produced by the Department under such clause.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H852E4E3C2EF141FF9090A273D7CB03B8" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Any positive finding by the Secretary under clause (i) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></clause> <clause id="H53FE611FCBA04100BBC1DB61EB7BC204" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Any negative finding by the Secretary under clause (i) shall be subject to judicial review.</text></clause>
<clause id="H49779E567D034A70A41D924766C5FD8D" indent="up1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>In the case of a species removed under clause (iii) from a list, the publication and notice under subsection (b)(5) shall consist solely of a notice of such removal.</text></clause> <clause id="H6B666F6979F54C96B970B6557EA093EA" indent="up1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>If the Secretary finds that a person submitted a petition that is the subject of a positive finding under clause (i) knowing that it contained scientific or commercial information described in clause (ii), then during the 10-year period beginning on the date of the finding under this clause the person shall not be considered an interested person for purposes of subparagraph (A) with respect to any petition submitted by the person after the date the person submitted such scientific or commercial information.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="H0124E5815606491DA91582DA7831DC1A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Expanded consideration during five-year review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4(c) of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H72AC91B650404C1480D38E2421A3C9F9" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H8B5C56CC56C64B62848D2F3A8BCCB181"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Each determination under paragraph (2)(B) shall consider one of the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H77DEABBE57254B1CA40AF8C2A00A5005"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph, the criteria required under subsection (f)(1)(B) in the recovery plan for the species.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0BF3E6E6F47346EEABFC67EAF3826E9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If the objective, measurable criteria under subsection (f)(1)(B)(ii) are not established, the factors for the determination that a species is an endangered species or a threatened species set forth in subsections (a)(1) and (b)(1).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H62BE7E0B59244B6C8A6296D26F902613"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A finding of error in the determination that the species is an endangered species, a threatened species, or extinct.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEA111455E5E49CBA77B15B6C0641B06"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A determination that the species is no longer an endangered species or threatened species or in danger of extinction, based on an analysis of the factors that are the basis for listing in subsections (a)(1) and (b)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

