<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAF4F4B12976C4DD5A8156FB618A866B1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 5154 IH: Connecting Hard-to-reach Areas with Renewably Generated Energy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5154</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission to promulgate regulations with respect to regional and interregional transmission planning, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1921B944054F43488F0428B0A8A53098" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC1F13CDB44174EFC91833C080FD0FE18"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecting Hard-to-reach Areas with Renewably Generated Energy Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CHARGE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H64AA51CE15314A6F9CBF919E75CFAEDE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="H5B5EAC0FFC6C422DBAA47A730CE18D16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>current transmission planning is fractured across many jurisdictions, prioritizes incumbent entities and highly localized transmission, and fails to identify cost-effective solutions for 21st century needs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E14E359244B4F19B34ACAA81A4328E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the historical structure, regulations, and incentives of the electric power system lead to under-planning and under-investment in the regional and interregional transmission lines that are needed for a reliable and resilient grid;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEAAB96E31EF410B89476A2DA2D68029"><enum>(3)</enum><text>much of the existing transmission infrastructure of the United States is in need of significant upgrade or replacement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0BCF62CC7CC4C65830CBC259440B1A5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the energy sector of the United States is at a critical juncture, with a rapidly changing power generation mix and new public policy mandates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E37D167EDE74AD9886B5FAF820FA2FD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>it is imperative to proactively plan for electricity transmission in the future, including by taking into account long-term changes to demand and load growth;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35CF1170555C4F38AD133F23041931C4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>renewable energy resources must be incorporated into the grid efficiently in order to meet State and Federal decarbonization goals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB77AA58905B40D9B6537D5173F7202C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the public desires, and has a right to, electricity data that are transparent, organized, and accessible;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B118042D9284E6AA9A4825F0498BE91"><enum>(8)</enum><text>having reliable and diverse sources of electricity generation is a foundational need for the entire economy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F061590D52542369B4974C18C4AA7A0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>climate change has increased the frequency and intensity of severe weather events that affect the grid;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAA73F7AA08E4D09BB11CEB45A33CC7C"><enum>(10)</enum><text>it is in the national interest to implement policies that provide effective electric infrastructure to save consumers money, avoid preventable damage, ensure energy reliability, and save lives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE3CED9A80244FAC8B5D1328B594DE1F"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the Federal Government has a responsibility to combat rising transmission costs and ensure customers receive just and reasonable rates for electricity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H173C603CA9C248E1A084B2C2DA8EACBB"><enum>(12)</enum><text>industry experience, scientific studies, and modern examples of reformed electricity transmission provide confidence that new public policies and regulatory guidance will achieve more efficient and beneficial planning than the status quo; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5CBC8757BF2A407BB2674B5D65FFE1BC"><enum>(13)</enum><text>there is increasing opportunity for public, Tribal, or rural cooperative development of transmission due to the recently established direct-pay incentives under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6417">section 6417</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, enacted by section 13801 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> (commonly known as the <quote>Inflation Reduction Act of 2022</quote>) (136 Stat. 2003).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H26267E2B591F4F6B87E35D3D74A9CF1D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H42F3A5FF1BEF4C6E814345ABAA719881"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD176DA95F8614DFDBFE0540BAA7ED429"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Independent System Operator</header><text>The term <term>Independent System Operator</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/796">16 U.S.C. 796</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AA6725BEB1B4EDC96CCF27E1C10B17E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interconnection customer</header><text>The term <term>interconnection customer</term> means an individual or entity that has submitted to the owner or operator of a transmission facility or transmission system a request to interconnect a generation project or energy storage project that is subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D6AF1403EE14969AFCCFE1E8FEC4624"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Interregional transmission planning process</header><text>The term <term>interregional transmission planning process</term> means a joint process by transmission providers in 2 or more adjacent transmission planning regions to evaluate electric energy transmission needs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9A4CEF0F10140258BC9A065AFE31B90"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Load-serving entity</header><text>The term <term>load-serving entity</term> has the meaning given the term in section 217(a) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824q">16 U.S.C. 824q(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA58BCA0FCD74FAE91B778E9A7F8519E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Regional Transmission Organization</header><text>The term <term>Regional Transmission Organization</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/796">16 U.S.C. 796</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A5946235043417FAA86D55BFCAED12D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Transmission facility</header><text>The term <term>transmission facility</term> means a facility that is used for the transmission of electric energy in interstate commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D7F1E952CE5410A96BC6110FDE3490E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Transmission planning region</header><text>The term <term>transmission planning region</term> means a region for which electric energy transmission planning is appropriate, as determined by the Commission, such as a region established pursuant to the guidance contained in the final rule of the Commission entitled <quote>Transmission Planning and Cost Allocation by Transmission Owning and Operating Public Utilities</quote> (76 Fed. Reg. 49842 (August 11, 2011)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84F8DD84A0DA44499701037F17700440"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Transmission provider</header><text>The term <term>transmission provider</term> means a public utility (as defined in section 201(e) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824">16 U.S.C. 824(e)</external-xref>)) that owns, operates, or controls 1 or more transmission facilities.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H899723A131C7426D86881AD4B22F87CC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Transmission planning and cost allocation</header><subsection id="H3FC2FC9FE9DF4D47B9369A9459A1DFCD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate a final rule that—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H812F632BF22A4DD0AE0A13F51080D877"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes transmission planning processes and cost-allocation processes that—</text><subparagraph id="H35B986B9F25348718B43ED6E4CAB93D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that transmission providers—</text><clause id="HE914CF65388541A0880A0D04B7650A5C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>engage in interregional transmission planning processes and interconnection-wide transmission planning processes, in conjunction with transmission planning processes within transmission planning regions;</text></clause><clause id="HD30FC43B871A4C10853DA4F7565A3413"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>harmonize interregional transmission planning processes and interconnection-wide transmission planning processes with other regional transmission planning processes, such as by using a joint model on a consistent timeline with a unified set of minimum requirements regarding needs, input assumptions, and benefit metrics;</text></clause><clause id="H74D8653113A64A57A9E5A60B3B1A2EEA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include as part of planning and cost-allocation processes the use of grid-enhancing transmission technologies and alternative transmission technologies that increase delivery of power over transmission networks, including, at a minimum—</text><subclause id="H24EA3FFBF4784E61843492DBB678E677"><enum>(I)</enum><text>dynamic line ratings;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBB7ECF9DDA284AE99323F6239E3F204A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>topology optimization;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6D04DD8CCFC8473EBDA6D5EEB3C8CCB2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>power flow control;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE15DE09ABEE843F3AE015548889F5142"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>advanced conductors and superconductors; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE58D5228257D40CEB3F0392BE9CB3A64"><enum>(V)</enum><text>storage-as-transmission;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8FE9E7501026424DA0EFC43CA1BCBE7E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>conduct interregional and interconnection-wide planning regularly and not less frequently than once every 5 years;</text></clause><clause id="H1320E30F41984673A3C6027B84C1DFBC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>conduct interregional and interconnection-wide planning based on a range of possible future load and generation scenarios; and</text></clause><clause id="H87BDE4AC9FD14FF1B133B342EAC74FED"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>are required to incorporate in a transmission planning process the full scope of benefits of transmission investment, including, at a minimum—</text><subclause id="H8ADE5392D84B4BEC993639B869F82BBF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>reduced costs of electric energy to customers, including reduced costs associated with lower quantities of necessary capacity, ancillary services, and reserve margins;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD030E297A36A41E185BDC3507053A364"><enum>(II)</enum><text>access to resources in neighboring transmission planning regions;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD5A0A3FE6DAE429F83731C64DC4092AD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the transmission of renewable energy or the ability of renewable energy to connect to the grid;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6E13E916E76D426E9F9D2D557978D0D4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>improvements in reliability, resilience, and flexibility of the grid, including, at a minimum—</text><item id="H3193E221387A411788E0061951FBDD45"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>reduced loss of load probability; </text></item><item id="H49F78AB6CE0E4C6E8BF0A3D345A6A501"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>increased resource diversity; </text></item><item id="H6C58BAE6A1BD4C4C82740A80C86FDF41"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>increased climate hardening; and </text></item><item id="H5D68E06C64B34AB699E442E9DD6CA007"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>increased ability to maintain functionality during regionally appropriate weather conditions and severe weather scenarios;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H2D4E3846643646C59EFD074C17726E9F"><enum>(V)</enum><text>leveraging resources across climatological patterns or time zones to account for resource availability and weather patterns;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1116A76B56C74B6097A7351A2D2131B5"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>avoidance, to the maximum extent practicable, of sensitive environmental areas and cultural heritage sites;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA0C1881F26724913A59207A6739EDFB9"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>reasonable and economical use of existing rights-of-way;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9FC5FD5B6F4941F5BBF8AE9B94A271CD"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>market facilitation benefits, including, at a minimum, increased competitiveness, liquidity, and integrity of broader geographic markets;</text></subclause><subclause id="H320A12A7BE8B496A96629665AC0EE3FD"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>avoided costs and deferred cost savings, including reduced generation costs and reduced future transmission investment costs;</text></subclause><subclause id="H45F37456654A4452A329853DDB0AD1A0"><enum>(X)</enum><text>the integration of grid-enhancing technologies;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA104474322644D6CBA345417F94B20E4"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>meeting local, State, and Federal policy goals, including goals established in decarbonization, climate, and clean energy laws (including regulations);</text></subclause><subclause id="H3F056C93887E4D5C9C90934CBC1072C6"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>protections to maintain just and reasonable rates for customers; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H5B37140064EE4D48A671D3AF3C09D9B8"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>any other production costs savings or other economic benefits from proposed transmission projects;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6FC333CEB8914733875E5C861A510B53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require that regional and interregional cost-allocation methodologies allocate costs on the basis of the multiple benefits described in subclauses (I) through (XIII) of subparagraph (A)(vi); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H49860147F3714742A3A94B566750A8A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>incorporate a 10- to 20-year future resource mix for each load-serving entity and State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF79EF9A029A84199A5B9A958CD3B6A35"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensure that local or regional transmission planning processes do not impair interregional and interconnection-wide transmission planning processes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5F86F9CFACEB40A695E562C66EF7EADE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>require transmission providers to maximize the use of portfolio-based cost allocations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H171F8AC99582495FBE1BD91E7FAC7058"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in cases in which costs and benefits are difficult to quantify, may allocate transmission investment costs among transmission system customers in proportion to—</text><clause commented="no" id="H0A271C0A64084E2BB19693D0FFE26C0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of regional projects, the share of electricity of each customer in the region; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC598C83AF05F4918ACBE57E535AADD84"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of interregional projects, the share of electricity of each customer in each applicable region; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H950AA42B4B464A3197252B81AC1465FB"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, prevent transmission providers from using cost-allocation methodologies that—</text><clause commented="no" id="H04990129726840FEAC1EB341B1EEC447"><enum>(i)</enum><text>discourage distributed generation, energy efficiency, demand response, or storage if more economic than transmission;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0D78F8E60A6047BAB3F6AAFCA1B02095"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are constrained by consideration only of benefits that are easy to allocate; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H69FCCC3CCD994967B7A93B790CF728B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>undermine previous cost-allocation agreements for projects already in operation; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F7B1B98ACF84E4B87709DCF52DD03B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allows a transmission developer of an interregional transmission project to submit to the Commission a request to recover all or a portion of the costs of the project under section 205 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824d">16 U.S.C. 824d</external-xref>) if—</text><subparagraph id="HB74AECD3A61C45149E612C5F30085881"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the project is selected through a transmission planning process that meets the criteria described in paragraph (1), in accordance with the transmission planning processes and cost-allocation processes established under that paragraph; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15E77DFF2A0346E1A4AF990432E25D79"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the transmission developer demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Commission that—</text><clause id="H6D5791A660D14CCF9786E8358D908D6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the project connects more than 1 transmission planning region; and</text></clause><clause id="H9E8948A012B241149551C39074B94DE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the benefits of the project substantially outweigh the costs of the project after accounting for any transmission projects developed pursuant to a transmission planning process that meets the criteria described in paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6B5C702743D447ABEC0CA6BB7404E70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cost recovery and allocation requirements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C151EC917EF4CF3B78ED15CC962FD2F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cost-benefit analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making a determination under subsection (a)(2)(B)(ii) of whether a transmission developer has demonstrated to the satisfaction of the Commission that the benefits of a project substantially outweigh the costs of the project, the Commission shall consider the benefits described in subsection (a)(1)(A)(vi).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96ADB29888D14A1DB25550A6E7D172ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text>For transmission projects that meet the criteria of subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (a)(2), the Commission shall allocate the costs of those transmission projects to customers in the applicable regions that benefit from those projects—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H90AE2452B57F4FF28C2577A3E0CFC5D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using the benefits described in subsection (a)(1)(A)(vi); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FFED272FB124F0E8F3D010160C713A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in cases in which those benefits are difficult to quantify, using the cost allocation methodology described in subsection (a)(1)(F).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0733A7DF4D2E4435A2326741F68E3EBB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>Nothing in this section limits, or may be construed to limit, any rights of transmission developers to submit and have rates approved by the Commission pursuant to section 205 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824d">16 U.S.C. 824d</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0186383611C2435DBE1FC5FA8D0BC61B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of resource plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may require a load-serving entity to make publicly available any applicable resource plans, including any plans relating to the requirement described in subsection (a)(1)(C), if, in the determination of the Commission, the plans are not adequately described in publicly stated plans in Securities and Exchange Commission filings, State agency filings, and power purchase contracts.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1642DC01CB3849DBB0B7B5E163EAA3B7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical conferences</header><paragraph id="HAF688DC3BB954489B51CAABB9EE7FB8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the rulemaking process under subsection (a), the Commission may convene a technical conference to consider implementation details, as the Commission determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4FFFC15B06D4EABB9D85882FA76554C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Participation</header><subparagraph id="H432A9C0CC4C84894A502A8B0DF6353BB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Leadership</header><text>A technical conference convened under paragraph (1) may be led by the members of the Commission, subject to subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H735E7AE54A7D47E2A060C680362AA402"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required invitations</header><text>On election under subparagraph (A) by members of the Commission to lead a technical conference, the Commission shall invite to participate in the technical conference representatives of residential ratepayers, transmission providers, environmental justice and equity groups, Tribal communities, Independent System Operators, Regional Transmission Organizations, consumer protection groups, renewable energy advocates, State utility commission and energy offices, and such other entities as the Commission determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70715DB390CF4CA6A53A5695838C8897"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Timeline</header><text>The Commission may establish and enforce a timeline for a technical conference convened under paragraph (1) that discourages actions by participants that may unnecessarily delay the conference.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H96A20143DD0B496ABDAA5D5AEC80B8EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>The Commission may provide an opportunity for public comment on the topics considered by a technical conference convened under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H067556665A1D4E059A4DDA2D5F971F89"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Office of Public Participation</header><text>The Commission shall consult the Office of Public Participation during the rulemaking process under subsection (a), including with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H14A5858AC1BB44F39912C2930E35EF19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>guidance on public participation requirements;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BE7A4AE1EB547A4ABBC404A01B3016D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>communications with the public concerning transmission planning that may impact local communities and landowners, including Tribal, indigenous, and environmental justice communities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2566350130604AFE9E8CD3D38EEA232D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>minimum data transparency and access requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H550D61BCC67B456EB6C2A5193D86A2FC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Joint Federal-State Task Force on Electric Transmission</header><text>The Commission may consult the Joint Federal-State Task Force on Electric Transmission in any actions that—</text><paragraph id="H7162BF5D3F29430F8690FCB82C5ACDE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>involve shared Federal and State regulatory authority and processes; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H715FDC121FD14B6483ABAEA32B024B95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>would benefit from a combined Federal and State perspective. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCA813E57BF844F80B8E1953E1C86C314"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interregional minimum transfer requirements</header><subsection id="H13C84CFEAFE640AB9253AE6BE338A72C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Electric reliability</header><text>Section 215(i)(2) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824o">16 U.S.C. 824o(i)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>or transmission</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6850173B40794AED8A9785AE7D7E7168"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF3F59F72EEC422C9E7DCAF6AD5B589C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate a final rule that establishes a minimum transfer capability that—</text><subparagraph id="H1DD6E74AD6E24D5DBFCD925378129AD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall govern minimum transfer requirements between transmission planning regions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H987D105343BD4899A1EE02851846FF5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>achieves reliability and resilience standards during plausible extreme weather scenarios;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3E79D8E824B4BCEBC35BA49C84F3520"><enum>(C)</enum><text>optimizes efficiency of delivering renewable energy to demand centers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC852739703124087BA92A644302FCF04"><enum>(D)</enum><text>incorporates the best available science relating to energy transmission, climatological patterns, climate change causes and impacts, grid reliability, and grid resiliency, including study results from the Department of Energy or National Laboratories (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23FFD7B46C194991BA6AE615D3BAB2FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All rates associated with transmission facilities developed pursuant to the rule promulgated under paragraph (1) shall be subject to the requirements of sections 205 and 206 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824d">16 U.S.C. 824d</external-xref>, 824e) that all rates, charges, terms, and conditions—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44D197F10B6E4216850E6D02B61FBCF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be just and reasonable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0241FE526C364AE98C3663ACA03ADC12"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be unduly discriminatory or preferential.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC9B690C500544C4499548A2EA71E7762"><enum>6.</enum><header>Data transparency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part II of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824">16 U.S.C. 824 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9649EA9473574F9593369F6A11D701B3"><section id="H6670A043E6CE4671B5E01AE1AA70E20C"><enum>224.</enum><header>Data transparency</header><subsection id="H277E8E22708C42CD8642A7F6B763F889"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Data</header><text>The Commission shall require all public utilities and other entities subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission to make, through coordination with the Environmental Protection Agency and an online database operated by the Administrator of the Energy Information Administration, hourly operating data transparent and accessible to the public, including original source data that—</text><paragraph id="H6339659E29614DF2A48396BCE5784FA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are organized and easy to understand;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9E8BAE7BC6A4978A3F07B4C6F2B4241"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are centralized and provided in usable formats, including an application programming interface;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC185E35F4AC4832AB04CE7BA02354BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>are available free of charge;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H469D4D8FAA7341D69A49FF4A31A26C77"><enum>(4)</enum><text>are published as close to real-time as is practicable; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FE4238C61A54570880EDEA512A4D388"><enum>(5)</enum><text>include generation by fuel type;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72F91D8BA2054A378D04094701E21668"><enum>(6)</enum><text>include hourly marginal greenhouse gas emissions per megawatt-hour of electricity generated within the metered boundaries of each entity and for each specific electrical bus location on the grid where an injection or withdrawal of power is modeled (commonly known as a <term>pricing node</term>), subject to the condition that the marginal greenhouse gas emissions data made available pursuant to this paragraph shall be measured in the same time interval by which locational marginal price is measured at the same location, but in no case shall the interval by which marginal greenhouse gas emissions are measured for purposes of this paragraph be greater than hourly;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9AA1288BE9FF44AAB85A7FCCF103C3F9"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include congestion cost and the limiting elements that cause the congestion; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71FB076E373B439A92E9BE37F279D1EE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>include hourly locational data on generation curtailment and the reasons for that curtailment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCA2D345477D24FCBBA5BE81FEDBDFB28"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Commercial products</header><text>The Commission may identify and reduce regulatory barriers to the development of commercial products that use the data made publicly available under subsection (a) in order to provide verifiable emissions reductions, including short- and long-term nodal congestion products.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H698C204AB1B54F93BBFE0C2988DD02AA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>In addition to amounts otherwise made available to the Administrator of the Energy Information Administration, there is appropriated to the Administrator of the Energy Information Administration for fiscal year 2024, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $10,000,000 to develop and operate the database described in subsection (a), to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H5F29C697B1BD408F89016AD5EDCA907D"><enum>7.</enum><header>Study on methods of electricity procurement and development</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H34CBB00A8C2D45C08611665FBFDC1464"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, in coordination with the Commission and the Department of Energy, shall conduct, and submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and make available on a public website a report describing the results of, a study that identifies the potential benefits and other effects to consumers from—</text><paragraph id="HE3CBFC6B788E4DC3950D04F8F207CCA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>procuring generation from independent entities that are not utilities through a competitive process administered by—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF3354D7C39F404E8F4A7611A161CF04"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an Independent System Operator or a Regional Transmission Organization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15C7262C917A4AF0A8AC8B0AE03FC2EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">another independent entity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H074B754A6DA84F78BA111F2E23532A92"><enum>(2)</enum><text>generation and transmission that is financed, developed, or owned by—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2EB246D750E94EB2B65AD7FA92A7E497"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity described in subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H727F4E7BBD084860816564C5ABDC2898"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any corporation that is wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by 1 or more entities described in that subsection; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H783CB45E9D0B41858AE2C77F41EA4CEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cooperatives that furnish electricity to rural areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDFDF9360F51E46C2B87930E59F1268C6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entity described</header><text>An entity referred to in subsection (a)(2)(A) is—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20C41250C36A4CFC99D9BA6E168A42DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H01D60E4BC0714FD39DEAC519889F7325"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CAD1F9560174C2F8AC6807FF118AF1E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the District of Columbia;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76A1640DB13C4DAA80EDE50886727020"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F61C489858D460ABE3349DF7CC04422"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other territory or possession of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3362FD62B9EF48EBAFFBFB83950DEF0C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any political subdivision of an entity described in any of paragraphs (2) through (5);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C3C75A12FA845EF8C2406EEC577B437"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a Tribal government; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H939906169E2D4294B95F8047B28B7FEB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>any agency, authority, or instrumentality of any 1 or more entities described in paragraphs (1) through (7).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4A337FE3FA434AD3A1D077EDC3A779C7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study conducted under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H01924965A26B4CF783385FD1AC387E7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take into consideration, at a minimum, potential benefits with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="HE19FD2A7945D45DBBC41510288BA9EA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cost savings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C349222CCEF450288C029DB9F12262A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improved grid reliability and resilience; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62AF12BD649344D3BD2C6502545CE951" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>greenhouse gas reductions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8DAA235910B47359723295B89214D8D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compare the potential benefits identified under paragraph (1) to the circumstances of consumers whose generation is not procured through a competitive process; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FB43740357D484699422747822E8B4A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>compare the potential benefits and effects identified under subsection (a)(2) to the circumstances of consumers whose generation and transmission is not financed and developed, directly or indirectly, by a public entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6781A23649424F6ABAA55748F698953A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC48DA75AF25140348EB804C3D2BECAA2"><enum>8.</enum><header>State subsidies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part II of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824">16 U.S.C. 824 et seq.</external-xref>) (as amended by section 6) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF63C9EC0D8940AC80BC6F5481EC52BB"><section id="H4A9835EE1B9543FB95E3C23ED9E3D2C5"><enum>225.</enum><header>State subsidies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In order to promote competition in wholesale markets, reliability, and affordability, the Commission shall not use offer-price mitigation methods to counteract the effects of State subsidies for renewable energy resources.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HF1B3338E609F454C9E45367076B7B2C5"><enum>9.</enum><header>Office of Transmission</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part III of the Federal Power Act is amended by inserting after section 317 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/825p">16 U.S.C. 825p</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AD25EA83C984312B1F9D9D37101A881"><section id="H3BE183B58CC1463880EF3095BDEF768C"><enum>318.</enum><header>Office of Transmission</header><subsection id="H42D43A8173BB4E45A9E60B7CDD4B5BD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There shall be established in the Commission an office, to be known as the <quote>Office of Transmission</quote> (referred to in this section as the <term>Office</term>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H94480E89512A4EF3BD32C103E01486A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Office shall be administered by a Director, who shall be appointed by the Chairman of the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87DBADF0C22746A1AC8CA58F4572D881"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Director of the Office shall—</text><paragraph id="H71AA82256F1043CCAAC90D8C1DA5D63D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review transmission plans submitted by public utilities in accordance with the regional and interregional transmission planning processes, including the processes established pursuant to section 206;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE33D55C3B762450186B890EE2D1A4E38"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate transmission-related matters of the Commission, as the Commission determines to be appropriate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C3119F62A5E4FFB82E7BABC63B4ED74"><enum>(3)</enum><text>carry out the responsibilities of the Commission under section 216, in coordination with the Office of Energy Projects of the Commission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6F20199928B4A24A3150A05A8576851"><enum>(4)</enum><text>review opportunities for innovation in transmission planning and operation, including deployment of grid-enhancing technologies, advanced conductors, and other approaches; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF51A8E1766F492C8E869351168B17AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide oversight of transmission planning activities subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3E1F5410F67449C494273A9FBF496514"><enum>10.</enum><header>Interconnection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations, or revise existing regulations—</text><paragraph id="H6C7D718059394BB5892B831CF3B8713D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to prohibit a public utility from requiring an interconnection customer to exclusively or disproportionately fund, without reimbursement, the costs of any network upgrade identified as necessary for the interconnect request of the interconnection customer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFD0FC075C5C40CFAF11E5BDF33B9724"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to encourage cost-sharing models that reflect the broad set of benefits and beneficiaries for any network upgrades identified as needed in an interconnection or affected system study, subject to the requirement that the model adheres to any requirements established under paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H030F4E410B384A038D7746559F5B5040"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to alleviate interconnection backlogs and reduce informational and procedural barriers in interconnection, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H4DC2F6E13DD64BBA8C30E21EB92D1BC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the establishment of an interconnection analysis center within the Office of Transmission established under section 318 of the Federal Power Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA28399A319384E7198A750569A9371AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consultation with staff and the use of other resources of the Department of Energy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HBBF138E1BFD64C13B7138DBA26693F58"><enum>11.</enum><header>Independent transmission monitor</header><subsection id="H80F647B562D049B8B8FD6A7006D0BF4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, for the purpose of monitoring the planning and operation of transmission facilities in transmission planning regions, the Commission shall—</text><paragraph id="HB37CBEBB4720476AA46403B6140368F2"><enum>(1)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H39513201CB1E4D088DAFA77399280FC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require each transmission planning region to establish an independent entity to monitor the planning and operation of transmission facilities in the transmission planning region; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CF3B6D6C729408995E750B015B0242C" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish a council, to be known as the <quote>Council of Transmission Monitors</quote>—</text><clause id="HEA8188DB79D14BB5B71E0B5AD205160F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to provide oversight of each independent entity established pursuant to subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H9B82B7FD04FE42A68806795E1A9E452B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to ensure interregional collaboration and consistency; or</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2785F90ED6714FFBACE32A10ACE4B20B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish an independent entity to monitor the planning and operation of transmission facilities in all transmission planning regions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9AB1215CD807411DA5220F2E1C1F9A30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Role of transmission monitor</header><text>An independent entity described in paragraph (1)(A) or (2) of subsection (a) shall, as applicable—</text><paragraph id="HA11785DAE2CE4DD2A86C33041D17AEEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review the operation of applicable transmission planning regions for inefficiency and practices that may lead to unjust and unreasonable rates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE25B48DE59AD4E84B87E26A848140DB1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>review costs of transmission facilities, including identifying inefficiencies among local, regional, and interregional planning;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB654B28DD396401FB70AFEC192807B65"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide examples and advice to transmission providers on appropriate regional transmission operations, planning, and cost-allocation processes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A61CA60F9C54AA6951CCEE447936059"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify situations in which—</text><subparagraph id="H0C2BB175335B4BDDA9C6B30C5D1BA315"><enum>(A)</enum><text>nonwire alternatives may be more cost-effective than transmission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H575256E948F740E39876754DB4E242E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grid-enhancing technologies may be appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B53CBDBF16B4623A72E164D0DD86690"><enum>(C)</enum><text>high-capacity, interregional lines may be—</text><clause id="H5965D66935EB46E9BAC58599E7E0E82B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>more cost-effective; or </text></clause><clause id="HC4740E74AF9C4A858EB1260C09646EF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a more appropriate reliability and resilience alternative; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD286A33DF88E4D40A89933FC057D0B46"><enum>(D)</enum><text>high-capacity regional lines may be more cost-effective than local upgrades.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD8002F4FF5864A41A7D113465A8D2EEE"><enum>12.</enum><header>Advisory committee</header><subsection id="H9234AC2707BF4297B9B164B1BDBB60A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall establish an advisory committee (referred to in this section as the <term>committee</term>) to make recommendations regarding—</text><paragraph id="H7379EFB4A9FA4468BFF706F7DA0DB454"><enum>(1)</enum><text>oversight and governance of Independent System Operators or Regional Transmission Organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D78BFB6700541BE896F33026047E736"><enum>(2)</enum><text>stakeholder participation best practices—</text><subparagraph id="H237AD5F80C5442F1B41EA58232EFEE1E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that ensure transparency, accountability, independence, oversight, and fair representation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4254887F98064578B1F4318CD2C24343"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the purposes of which are to promote competition, reliability, and affordability in all transmission planning regions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44DBEB43F264438C9228C6ADBFA7C966"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that include best practices relating to stakeholder disclosure of the impact of a proposed tariff reform on the company or client of the stakeholder prior to voting on the proposed tariff reform;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC8AD3DDAF7843DCBACF6FDCDC96BA08"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enhancing transparency and open decisionmaking in regions not classified as Independent System Operators or Regional Transmission Organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A2D1C624848427EADFBEABDCCDA85E5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the requirements of governing boards within Independent System Operators or Regional Transmission Organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E5A8A3647834CCB8BFB351659A94D7B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>The committee shall be composed of not more than 30 members, including—</text><paragraph id="H8EE03E80AEFA4CE0977ED8D46410E28D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at least 2 representatives of end-use customers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB5A3A0C17A04B18800E0D1AFCA29F8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of transmission providers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H265D30ABCD8C445DBD52B503D32D8D78"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at least 2 representatives of environmental justice and equity groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF353C3C2FF4E4B17B818E3DAACB41B0B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of Tribal communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED2FF0A96EE543E0A3AEFD9941483EDC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of Independent System Operators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04B5421BF39C4B87861951F7F7975C3A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of Regional Transmission Organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0AACF7AF2F04B4793E9A3CA51C4B5A3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of consumer protection groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C625065839B4C648DFC7C4A2AABF8A9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>at least 2 representatives of renewable energy advocates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A9F83D9929442EE95E43AC9DF12C2B8"><enum>(9)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of State commissions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H536EDF7FD50240E9AA1088A1ACE24A34"><enum>(10)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of public power entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA24A9451C99D4CA490451436D8B57AFE"><enum>(11)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of marketers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB57981B6F96940CB89E7C00388CADC32"><enum>(12)</enum><text>at least 1 representative of generators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1756D44453B347848C88F090229B69B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>FACA applicability</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote><act-name parsable-cite="FACA">Federal Advisory Committee Act</act-name></quote>), shall apply to the committee.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCC9E9645089F4258919036E210CFB89C"><enum>13.</enum><header>RTO and ISO Governance</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D144DC74672442B81B5882E44CA957C"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Stakeholder processes</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3597537FECD2477B82BDF3F99CFF365A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public voting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each vote cast by any party during a stakeholder process of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator shall be made public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99E19EA9BA654F66B683AA4035D2DC0A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public participation funding</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations requiring Regional Transmission Organizations and Independent System Operators to develop a process to provide intervenor compensation or other funding to assist with public interest participation in the stakeholder processes of the Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0AB83C3029943FC98D1D76C9D0CE249"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consumer organizations; membership fee waivers</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations requiring each Regional Transmission Organization and Independent System Operator—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC224B75A85842B58694008E431AD34C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to grant full voting and participation rights for consumer organizations within stakeholder processes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BD63F1B48374EDDB12D1501DD794109"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to consider membership fee waivers for stakeholder processes. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32CCFAC881E44E928F181F0227EC8397"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Stakeholder meetings</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F15C8E38EF3403DA0DA309396242E23"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recording and transcription</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each stakeholder meeting of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator shall be recorded and transcribed, and the recording and transcription shall be made freely available to the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8EC213898A694740856FA1BEAC6897EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure requirement</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3821E1538D7E4175B0C7F7BC8BD57660"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual described in subparagraph (B) shall publicly disclose, at any stakeholder meeting of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator that the individual attends or in which the individual otherwise participates—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H30BBDA777545422A8FA7566A056508A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that the individual is attending or participating on behalf of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE57729FECBEE429A8E8B24407C84112D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the identity of that Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2DA899AAA0A45D686861B21015C91CB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Individual described</header><text>An individual referred to in subparagraph (A) is any representative of a law firm or consulting firm, or any other agent, that is compensated to represent or advocate for the interests of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA43BDECC64F412ABB14208F313B3E13"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of FOIA</header><text>Section 552 of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>), including any exceptions under that section, shall apply to the activities, records, and proceedings of each Regional Transmission Organization and Independent System Operator, including with respect to the operations of the Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7ECF162ED78F4C3C80645D7CF1AA9BE7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitations on sponsorships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCB1105E573D42E1A85A303C1870FFB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to prohibit entities with interests in matters before a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator from serving as financial sponsors of special events or activities at Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator meetings; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5090372590D4FC3940B44ED3B27B570"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the Commission determines appropriate, to establish disclosure requirements for entities with interests in matters before a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator that serve as financial sponsors of special events or activities at Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator meetings.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5F92F2DECCE46CBAF7F91D3E8A435B5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Boards of directors</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2EEAD586A154537AD6093D90B6EFAC5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Independent board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations requiring, subject to exceptions defined by the Commission, that the board of directors of a Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator be independent from, and not affiliated with, the members of the Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21D7B753F92E4F58A4FB3A6605A979F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF742D77D1A07495C98D001E6475FE5E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requiring the board of directors of each Regional Transmission Organization and Independent System Operator to have members who have expertise and experience in representing consumers, including at least 1 member with expertise in the interests of retail residential consumers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7FFB2A1930A14A368DF2ADC3D26FBC0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing the number of members described in subparagraph (A) that shall be required on a board of directors described in that subparagraph in order to avoid marginalization of the perspectives and contributions of those members; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DA7B8FD0069415B8B70BA87828F400D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>requiring each Regional Transmission Organization and Independent System Operator to designate at least 1 member of the board of directors of that Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator who shall represent and be directly accountable, in such manner as the Commission determines to be appropriate, to the public interest within the geographic footprint of the Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9BB53EF6C15D47DDA595C7BF78C88FE4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Employment and compensation</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7C6CD8D4509D493DAECAB8E20FCCB1EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Revolving door prohibitions</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCCFA51C66A904E8F879C213C60F6A649"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate regulations requiring Regional Transmission Organizations and Independent System Operators to establish rules prohibiting the Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator from employing, during the periods described in subparagraph (B), an individual who is or was an executive of a utility (commonly known as a <quote>revolving door prohibition</quote>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H049D36DFD6254A31A8A9BE1708146E39"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Periods described</header><text>The periods referred to in subparagraph (A) are—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95CB84E26B794759AEB69B147470EFA5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any period during which the individual is an executive of a utility; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H871B26FC5C404376B058464EA8BFBEF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 1-year period beginning on the date on which the employment of the individual as an executive of a utility ends.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB208380F54148A893988FCC40D30E7B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall establish guidelines for executive compensation at Regional Transmission Organizations and Independent System Operators in order to limit excessive compensation of those executives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA74934B3959D413A8D2D41A0CF5295A4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>The Commission shall enforce the requirements of this section using the authority of the Commission under sections 205 and 206 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824d">16 U.S.C. 824d</external-xref>, 824e).</text></subsection></section><section id="HC61A6B55BF6840879BD11BDA3E7CBBA1"><enum>14.</enum><header>Intervenor funding at Office of Public Participation</header><subsection id="HD5F499AB18CB4543AB72D0727914D321"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 319(b)(2) of the Federal Power Act (16 U.S.C. 825q–l(b)(2)) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCC4BC7CE0704C1D9A39C4010332D946"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A), by striking the comma and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB618118F2F64D4AA45D6A0A1779A3B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively, and indenting the clauses appropriately;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2FDF22508154CE9AD2FF2721EF42C90"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i) (as so redesignated), in the second sentence, by striking <quote>Such compensation</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB539B3AD4FE43459201BF8A67604A6A"><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H79917C47FFAC47C8A68A74AE6C08A3E6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determinations required</header><text>Compensation under this paragraph</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB3406EBE4A9467EA7DA35A8E0A0DE7A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking the paragraph designation and all that follows through <quote>by it,</quote> in the matter preceding subparagraph (B) (as so designated) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5DEBAB6B1ECF4E3A9DB65C8FD4FE23B2"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02C59A72E80544DA9E701D27805F2E2F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensation</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HED1224AC4B024F01A26D2D6108950CBF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On making the determinations described in subparagraph (B) and in accordance with rules promulgated by the Commission, the Commission shall</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8AD0649B2EC6405D86C52D947F133FC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall promulgate a final rule to provide compensation under paragraph (2) of section 319(b) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/825q-1">16 U.S.C. 825q–1(b)</external-xref>) in accordance with the amendment made by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2D63EE852A64149A1BF7DA66AD94C31"><enum>15.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In addition to amounts otherwise available, there is appropriated to the Commission for fiscal year 2024, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $200,000,000, to remain available until expended, to carry out—</text><paragraph id="H32BA021522CF4D2898BD4188C357FBC9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sections 4, 5, and 10; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B226761A1D649D0B0FE4717F19D2F55"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amendment made by section 9.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

