<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H06C53BAC78F94B6F895514614BB2CF2B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3555 IH: Banking Regulator Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3555</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance the reporting and testimony requirements for Federal banking agencies.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H673CFA0A8E4B44519100F5AD68FB2A57" style="OLC"><section id="HF66D77EEC68B48988CBE52A10ED3F83F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Banking Regulator Accountability Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H84B4BAE660154FFEA61003AB70809176"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reports and testimony to Congress on supervision</header><subsection id="H22DCF17F92EC4DBAB11AA7C80251A70F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Testimony and reports to Congress on Federal Reserve System supervision</header><text>Section 2B of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/225b">12 U.S.C. 225b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9865C926724B45EE9931FB488BDED175" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H6A28CCAC497143A0AC1EC00A2350A3B0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Semi-Annual testimony and report to Congress on supervision</header><paragraph id="H12B2D92569C440C594DB70454E838258"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Vice Chairman for Supervision shall submit a semi-annual report to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Board with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of depository institution holding companies and other financial firms supervised by the Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC0B890DFB9C41F8BA4E452C382DFE94"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum contents</header><text>At a minimum, each report under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HDABAAD7D0E644342BED0828FF0C083D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conditions of financial firms, including examination or inspection ratings, on an aggregate basis by firm asset size;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6434CBFD1C2416F84AE2F7EDD4EF93B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>granular data on outstanding material supervisory determinations by type of determination, including the types of risks covered, on an aggregate basis by firm asset size;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4903C0172D57411681D0B3F458C4D9D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">changes in the number and types of outstanding material supervisory determinations over the previous 5 years;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6D7034C0E5A43E38FFDB0A60A501CF1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>aggregate data on the ratings of financial firms over the previous 3 years;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05ABB85DDC6A4C60AAA34DA9A8F9234F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the number of informal and formal enforcement actions, by type of enforcement order and showing changes in the last 3 years, against supervised financial firms on an aggregate basis by firm asset size; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94FC68D6E5D148B6A4944E5B8DFAD6D2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a description of the organization of the supervisory functions of the Board with respect to financial firms, including information on roles, responsibilities, accountability, and talent management.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H841B4186BE8740E1AAEC68704969E3F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Confidential report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concurrent with each report under paragraph (1), the Vice Chairman for Supervision shall submit a confidential report to the chair and ranking member of each committee described under paragraph (1) identifying—</text><subparagraph id="HD706FF24E57F4E0EA30229E3D4279C21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each supervised financial firm with less than satisfactory examination or inspection ratings; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5ED1D95897334A618A0B5117837D403C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each supervised financial firm with an active formal or informal enforcement action, and the status of each provision of each enforcement action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2982824A2F5D421E91BB4BAF2B549440"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Testimony and reports to Congress on Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation supervision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 17 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1827">12 U.S.C. 1827</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3E9D9405542443D8AC0C2747BF204C14" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H41CA124685594A708602C456A34D87F9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Semi-Annual testimony and report to Congress on supervision</header><paragraph id="H079EE3EC70E44FD38AFC7B3CB966B844"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appearances before Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chairman of the Corporation shall appear before the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives at semi-annual hearings regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Corporation with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of depository institutions supervised by the Corporation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC40192B3714F4D7FB0B47337DA227EE0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><subparagraph id="H2D3BCC5C6DFA4179BD849B78CBD36C64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chairman of the Corporation shall transmit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives semi-annual reports regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Corporation with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of depository institutions supervised by the Corporation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B5E2F8C7D7140FB86B442C024DA50DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum contents</header><text>At a minimum, each report under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="H5ECBBEBD8B234639963903BEDAA09EA2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conditions of depository institutions, including examination or inspection ratings, on an aggregate basis by institution asset size;</text></clause><clause id="H21DA31ACFA5F491B94E4C824C84E8E2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">granular data on outstanding material supervisory determinations by type of determination, including the types of risks covered, on an aggregate basis by institution asset size;</text></clause><clause id="HDCCB19B930A3472EAFDBE46B64F809B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">changes in the number and types of outstanding material supervisory determinations over the previous 5 years;</text></clause><clause id="H5EA8D8629A9044F594E3017878191A84"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aggregate data on the ratings of depository institutions over the previous 3 years; </text></clause><clause id="HF9644831A4364A799F166E3DE103CFD5"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of informal and formal enforcement actions, by type of enforcement order and showing changes in the last 3 years, against supervised depository institutions on an aggregate basis by institution asset size; and</text></clause><clause id="H39AEAF9EE11942CEBBC0B4D71964CA0C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the organization of the supervisory functions of the Corporation with respect to depository institutions, including information on roles, responsibilities, accountability, and talent management.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30D18D6BDF9544DE97CC9E3CC4B94F86"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Confidential report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concurrent with each report under subparagraph (A), the Chairman of the Corporation shall submit a confidential report to the chair and ranking member of each committee described under subparagraph (A) identifying—</text><clause id="H72FD2DF5B10D4903B4BE607B6ABF3F99"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised depository institution with less than satisfactory examination or inspection ratings; and</text></clause><clause id="H3469E958F8D041298A81083BA22D0589"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised depository institution with an active formal or informal enforcement action, and the status of each provision of each enforcement action.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HE23DB2BDF871411ABC5CD935307E3F21"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Testimony and reports to Congress on Comptroller of the Currency supervision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The second section 333 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/14">12 U.S.C. 14</external-xref>; relating to the annual report) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H96BEF028EC26481C871AE60C6838795C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Comptroller</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFD06181D7E304C0885CCD16EC3A74CA0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HCD84175FD42648E2A69B51751010E9B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HA22D1D51818F4B32AC19258A0AAEC916"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5015673E01244153B2131742D0757874" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H89739185A181498A85A043A856397515"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Semi-Annual testimony and report to Congress on supervision</header><paragraph id="H228E963E8C394FFFADCA1ECD71AB5478"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appearances before Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller of the Currency shall appear before the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives at semi-annual hearings regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of national banks and other financial firms supervised by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5454A72D1AA47E4B8E7E71412994FAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><subparagraph id="HE631F3FEFB8A4234AFA77B156DA9BB5A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller of the Currency shall transmit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives semi-annual reports regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of national banks and other financial firms supervised by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD96D3D9CC8D94191B5C33018622D6BAF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum contents</header><text>At a minimum, each report under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="H46CD20DD976042F3AA81EC95ECE465CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conditions of national banks and other financial firms, including examination or inspection ratings, on an aggregate basis by asset size;</text></clause><clause id="HC660850948E0400FABBBE9EE973A7AD4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">granular data on outstanding material supervisory determinations by type of determination, including the types of risks covered, on an aggregate basis by asset size;</text></clause><clause id="H7491432D945145DEB6575EABC445D7C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">changes in the number and types of outstanding material supervisory determinations over the previous 5 years;</text></clause><clause id="H0775B77A127743F98C87232ED4A05FD3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aggregate data on the ratings of national banks and other financial firms over the previous 3 years; </text></clause><clause id="HACE9B7B08FB34F5A821E1DA75633E5C0"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of informal and formal enforcement actions, by type of enforcement order and showing changes in the last 3 years, against supervised national banks and other financial firms on an aggregate basis by firm asset size; and</text></clause><clause id="HB90E2A72E8DF422285CD54B2CE76EF39"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the organization of the supervisory functions of the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency with respect to national banks and other financial firms, including information on roles, responsibilities, accountability, and talent management.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3CB090587B84E3FA3AFA6212CAB90FB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Confidential report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concurrent with each report under subparagraph (A), the Comptroller of the Currency shall submit a confidential report to the chair and ranking member of each committee described under subparagraph (A) identifying—</text><clause id="H0AE25164C35D4DA7AA9F80992EB33F36"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised national bank or other financial firms with less than satisfactory examination or inspection ratings; and</text></clause><clause id="H1828443730DF44C1A18980ADBB147E79"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised national bank or other financial firms with an active formal or informal enforcement action, and the status of each provision of each enforcement action.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5BA569FAD9B5450A8504675D80EB8650"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Testimony and reports to Congress on National Credit Union Administration supervision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102 of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1752a">12 U.S.C. 1752a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H89537667109E436F833B224901371046" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H82EEEBBD8FBE4DE687C950FA03CF9FF7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Semi-Annual testimony and report to Congress on supervision</header><paragraph id="HE6A29AE0D8054DAE8847EAEF0D04AD24"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appearances before Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chairman of the Board shall appear before the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives at semi-annual hearings regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Administration with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of credit unions supervised by the Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5FFF694A1B4AA689A25E9B6E6B94B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><subparagraph id="HF66282C4BE31473CB0F4929F776A3F84"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chairman of the Board shall transmit to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives semi-annual reports regarding the efforts, activities, objectives, and plans of the Administration with respect to the conduct of supervision and regulation of credit unions supervised by the Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00125BADE0FF4679AAB81C1064E77F01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum contents</header><text>At a minimum, each report under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="HD1E7C6CDF8F84108B1F6E8E43B260021"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conditions of credit unions, including examination or inspection ratings, on an aggregate basis by credit union asset size;</text></clause><clause id="HF11FFF77F01B4A5F88D75FF9EA006F23" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">granular data on outstanding material supervisory determinations by type of determination, including the types of risks covered, on an aggregate basis by credit union asset size;</text></clause><clause id="H6F268F18679B4DDC9A65A945ABAB5424"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">changes in the number and types of outstanding material supervisory determinations over the previous 5 years;</text></clause><clause id="HF15BE599502948ABA63CFE166ECC09F6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aggregate data on the ratings of credit unions over the previous 3 years; </text></clause><clause id="H64E2A997A4F34BF285AC5161F087C9BD"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of informal and formal enforcement actions, by type of enforcement order and showing changes in the last 3 years, against supervised credit unions on an aggregate basis by credit union asset size; and</text></clause><clause id="H694D17CF489943BA86D1FE4077358A8C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the organization of the supervisory functions of the Board with respect to credit unions, including information on roles, responsibilities, accountability, and talent management.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6ACAE7B12AEE4892AFD8EF156DC20B7F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Confidential report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concurrent with each report under subparagraph (A), the Chairman of the Board shall submit a confidential report to the chair and ranking member of each committee described under subparagraph (A) identifying—</text><clause id="HD2D5C6BC3A494EAE8E8851E8F50B5E37"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised credit union with less than satisfactory examination or inspection ratings; and</text></clause><clause id="HB239206E1B50498DA82F1078FEA42D4B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each supervised credit union with an active formal or informal enforcement action, and the status of each provision of each enforcement action.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

