<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB6EA121A71DD47DA9C7626D3B45F5751" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 645 IH: Healthy Foundations for Homeless Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 645</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to permanently authorize the use of certain funds to improve flexibility in the provision of assistance to homeless veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0175C37957A3447FAF0B93C5D1C413B0" style="OLC"><section id="H8D7702CFBAD444028859A861A8591531" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Foundations for Homeless Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4A93E07EC9084E3BAD380C4F7E76A093" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of use of certain funds for improved flexibility in assistance to homeless veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle VII of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/20">chapter 20</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section (and conforming the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter accordingly):</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H5054FBD328264CE489A028373BA7BC5B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HF78B5F97FD364C5180FFBD386D9EE189"><enum>2068.</enum><header>Flexibility in provision of assistance to homeless veterans</header><subsection id="H91A95BF12CDF4B03AFA8E1EE20FBC711"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may use amounts appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs to carry out section 2011, 2012, 2031, or 2061 of this chapter to provide to homeless veterans and veterans participating in the program carried out under section 8(o)(19) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(19)</external-xref>), as the Secretary determines necessary, the following:</text><paragraph id="H5D26A0C38E9E435A92E672CE8DCB04E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Assistance required for the safety and survival of the veteran (such as food, shelter, clothing, blankets, and hygiene items).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H515409AFD6E444E5AC4D6E5C9DBD143E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Transportation required to support the stability and health of the veteran (such as transportation for appointments with service providers, the conduct of housing searches, and the obtainment of food and supplies).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85272B04B5434028BF36BACD9399AAC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Communications equipment and services (such as tablets, smartphones, disposable phones, and related service plans) required to support the stability and health of the veteran (such as through the maintenance of contact with service providers, prospective landlords, and family members).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13FAA09D6E884C25ADA9FA3DD7C7D225"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Such other assistance as the Secretary determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA29FCBD722B74E9C898816DB7DD69BDB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Homeless veterans on Department land</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8F6FBB6BC3604E7688DF092FCC832248"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may collaborate, to the extent practicable, with one or more organizations to manage the use of land of the Department for homeless veterans for living and sleeping.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1250F1083105484C8AF37E4DDAE152BE" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collaboration under paragraph (1) may include the provision by either the Secretary or the head of the organization concerned of food services and security for property, buildings, and other facilities owned or controlled by the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

