<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE0593442E37C43798796127D2212FBF2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2941 IH: Recognizing the Role of Direct Support Professionals Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2941</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Office of Management and Budget to revise the Standard Occupational Classification system to establish a separate code for direct support professionals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCC6230D44DA646BEBA4CDD3CF31A909F" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H417DBF6DE7F54F83A5DE5C3D9BECEF6B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Recognizing the Role of Direct Support Professionals Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCC8060384E934C4FAC106D01EC6879C3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H36A538746CA44DD1A65620C43108A915"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Direct support professionals play a critical role in the care provided to individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18AB05694EB64823BCBAC00B83C7D4AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Providers of home- and community-based services are experiencing difficulty hiring and retaining direct support professionals, with a national turnover rate of 43 percent, as identified in a 2021 study by the National Core Indicators, and full-time vacancy rates increasing by 94 percent between 2019 and 2021.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFE7044F37D94996B323CDA726B6A6DF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>High turnover rates can lead to instability for individuals receiving services, and this may result in individuals not receiving enough personalized care to help them reach their goals for independent living.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE709FEDBB4534E12802300A9AA35E3FF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A discrete occupational category for direct support professionals will help States and the Federal Government—</text><subparagraph id="HC3EA1CCBD4644F3B82BB1397CCD676C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>better interpret the shortage in the labor market of direct support professionals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00535CCCC5B6460DB9C9D722D946E8E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>collect data on the high turnover rate of direct support professionals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6839E772A8E34FB99E23577506C43F9B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Standard Occupational Classification system is designed and maintained solely for statistical purposes, and is used by Federal statistical agencies to classify workers and jobs into occupational categories for the purpose of collecting, calculating, analyzing, or disseminating data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD5BAA564DA54609BD630930B42032B3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Occupations in the Standard Occupational Classification system are classified based on work performed and, in some cases, on the skills, education, or training needed to perform the work.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4F199C13196476A82B2578DD90EA41F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Establishing a discrete occupational category for direct support professionals will—</text><subparagraph id="HCCDD47BB867D400A85A094B329715C6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>correct an inaccurate representation in the Standard Occupational Classification system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34D0E6C9E6C0445396795F43A684D589"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognize these professionals for the critical and often overlooked work that they perform for the disabled community, which work is different than the work of a home health aide or a personal care aide; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1CAE74B6A8144F3847EFA838337C75D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>better align the Standard Occupational Classification system with related classification systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H3CF1B34A86A74350B481AF76FFBBC59F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definition of direct support professional</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>direct support professional</term> means an individual who, in exchange for compensation, provides services to an individual with an intellectual disability or a developmental disability (as defined in section 102 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15002">42 U.S.C. 15002</external-xref>)) that promote such individual’s independence, including—</text><paragraph id="H8868ECA9845B4AF4BC56586EEC2E0707"><enum>(1)</enum><text>services that enhance independence and community inclusion for such individual, including traveling with such individual, attending and assisting such individual while visiting friends and family, shopping, or socializing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H625C4A4A20044B38B2C861F504AF5AF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>services such as coaching and supporting such individual in communicating needs, achieving self-expression, pursuing personal goals, living independently, and participating actively in employment or voluntary roles in the community;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18E0991614044F4691499B3F661663D5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>services such as providing assistance with activities of daily living (such as feeding, bathing, toileting, and ambulation) and with tasks such as meal preparation, shopping, light housekeeping, and laundry; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBEAEB110451F486C9F38E28908881717"><enum>(4)</enum><text>services that support such individual at home, work, school, or any other community setting. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HD25F937F9C244ABD9A0F8E08CAC19AF2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Revision of Standard Occupational Classification system</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall, not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, revise the Standard Occupational Classification system to establish a separate code (31–1123) for direct support professionals as a healthcare support occupation. Such code shall be a subset of 31–1120, which includes home health aides and personal care aides.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

