<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE43B492FB20C434293EF7D757DFC07A7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 952 IH: Kids’ Access to Primary Care Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 952</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to renew the application of the Medicare payment rate floor to primary care services furnished under the Medicaid program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4A12816BF7BA4F499A3FA15D9D94102D" style="OLC">
<section id="H0F2D8C169BAD4FFB80A16FEE6E74ADAA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Kids’ Access to Primary Care Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" id="H27A3CD76802844D6AB606CEA463ECF9C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Renewal of application of Medicare payment rate floor to primary care services furnished under Medicaid and inclusion of additional providers</header> <subsection commented="no" id="HB3F3DD2D835E40C5B4AA6BF07E048C8C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Renewal of payment floor; additional providers</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H9AFC77667A6241B58D96A05BC87FD778"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1902(a)(13) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>) is amended by striking subparagraph (C) and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC75911C3F215478DBE3B28A44C40064B" style="OLC">
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCFF11347371D4F42A1CAF03111ACD457"><enum>(C)</enum><text>payment for primary care services (as defined in subsection (jj)) at a rate that is not less than 100 percent of the payment rate that applies to such services and physician under part B of title XVIII (or, if greater, the payment rate that would be applicable under such part if the conversion factor under section 1848(d) for the year involved were the conversion factor under such section for 2009), and that is not less than the rate that would otherwise apply to such services under this title if the rate were determined without regard to this subparagraph, and that are—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F22731F22EB4F4D995D84B20BC977C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>furnished in 2013 and 2014, by a physician with a primary specialty designation of family medicine, general internal medicine, or pediatric medicine; or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2091ED318BDC45018362CFB7C5755F79"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">furnished during the period beginning on the first day of the first month beginning after the date of the enactment of the Kids’ Access to Primary Care Act of 2023—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H51D5E953E3FD487696FBE313657D8D66"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by a physician with a primary specialty designation of family medicine, general internal medicine, pediatric medicine, or obstetrics and gynecology, but only if the physician self-attests that the physician is board-certified in family medicine, general internal medicine, pediatric medicine, or obstetrics and gynecology, respectively;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H3C17EFC18E4246EC9C394B22E6ACDC62"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by a physician with a primary specialty designation of a family medicine subspecialty, an internal medicine subspecialty, a pediatric subspecialty, or a subspecialty of obstetrics and gynecology, without regard to the board that offers the designation for such a subspecialty, but only if the physician self-attests that the physician is board-certified in such a subspecialty;</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CB0D719DD2445A5AB60A79C77C7ACA6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by an advanced practice clinician, as defined by the Secretary, that works under the supervision of—</text>
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35EED57D4F1045C5BBC6390BF2CE9A19"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a physician described in subclause (I) or (II); or</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA10DC79D8F64D2F92553429DD8B9D27"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a nurse practitioner or a physician assistant (as such terms are defined in section 1861(aa)(5)(A)) who is working in accordance with State law, or a certified nurse-midwife (as defined in section 1861(gg)(2)) who is working in accordance with State law;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" id="H4805E1A9B014465CBAB13D03C565D63E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by a rural health clinic, Federally-qualified health center, or other health clinic that receives reimbursement on a fee schedule applicable to a physician described in subclause (I) or (II), an advanced practice clinician described in subclause (III), or a nurse practitioner, physician assistant, or certified nurse-midwife described in subclause (III)(bb), for services furnished by—</text> <item id="H5FD6493FBAAB42658A9AB6B81B8100E5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>such a physician, nurse practitioner, physician assistant, or certified nurse-midwife, respectively; or</text></item>
<item id="H8A8B80751C5F4540829377625C7E8252"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an advanced practice clinician supervised by such a physician, nurse practitioner, physician assistant, or certified nurse-midwife; or</text></item></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9DAD8ECA8123481CB8E6E8BD4373E98F"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by a nurse practitioner or a physician assistant (as such terms are defined in section 1861(aa)(5)(A)) who is working in accordance with State law, or a certified nurse-midwife described in subclause (III)(bb) who is working in accordance with State law, in accordance with procedures that ensure that the portion of the payment for such services that the nurse practitioner, physician assistant, or certified nurse-midwife is paid is not less than the amount that the nurse practitioner, physician assistant, or certified nurse-midwife would be paid if the services were provided under part B of title XVIII;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H07D923345D844D96AD27907064DD2CA1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 1905(dd) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(dd)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H53A6FC2B482E4518BA2DAF25600417B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Notwithstanding</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03261FB107AC41EE96D1A87B5CD047AE" style="OLC">
<paragraph commented="no" id="HABF6673492DF45359A6765CE96395464"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H318B0FBB9A1C436B90907EE8E0DA69FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or furnished during the additional period specified in paragraph (2),</quote> after <quote>2015,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HDA360AA4D091475980099A0BE91A3FAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCC86FED4A7B4D5E9517B922C03AB65A" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" id="H04440DF0B2284EB091BD506C4CB9712C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the additional period specified in this paragraph is the period beginning on the first day of the first month beginning after the date of the enactment of the Kids’ Access to Primary Care Act of 2023.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H39DB77ADA56846118882DB27BBD2BFCD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Improved targeting of primary care</header>
<paragraph id="H2316CF28DA2D4984816F8D5774964C03"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(jj) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(jj)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HB7897C76253B470EB2CEC385674F3578" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, and moving the margin of each such subparagraph, as so redesignated, 2 ems to the right;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H13A73256A4ED4C6BB81808EDEAF97F90" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>For purposes of</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19EE4AE0DD4B4D4F96022D7C8F17A41A" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" id="HBB28EDC229784775A637CA7D9851C0CC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6CDFE539D3BD4378BDA66F7823CA58EB" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA6636E4BF52C40F082FA4C28CB2506C3" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" id="HA77B345FA7DD42B6955EE312DD58674B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>Such term does not include any services described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1) if such services are provided in an emergency department of a hospital.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H85B7C2C617124FAE82C74ED84BC511A8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by paragraph (1) shall apply with respect to primary care services provided on or after the first day of the period described in subparagraph (C)(ii) of section 1902(a)(13) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H520D77431AED474EACDE668EF609825C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Ensuring payment by managed care entities</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HF477158A1ADA4E9880A62C6E6B338056"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1903(m)(2)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(m)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE8254DDEBFFB48E597320DDDFF6B266B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (xii), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0F7A754146764C35A8FF6706624C4A83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (xiii)—</text>
<clause id="HE1AA1F34109D471FB74D6FE497746ECC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by moving the margin of such clause 2 ems to the left; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7DA50236D1564CD887DBC399C0681C1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HF59F1E3092AF469ABD55D1B5CA121123"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (xiii) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H310CD244D3AE42BCA358DB1F4FDAAD72" style="OLC"> <clause commented="no" id="H7345C8C11ACF41D7A6591BA7E0CCE3C4" indent="up2"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>such contract provides that (I) payments to health care providers specified in section 1902(a)(13)(C) for furnishing primary care services defined in section 1902(jj) during a year or period specified in section 1902(a)(13)(C) are at least equal to the amounts set forth and required by the Secretary by regulation, (II) the entity shall, upon request, provide documentation to the State that is sufficient to enable the State and the Secretary to ensure compliance with subclause (I), and (III) the Secretary shall approve payments described in subclause (I) that are furnished through an agreed-upon capitation, partial capitation, or other value-based payment arrangement if the agreed-upon capitation, partial capitation, or other value-based payment arrangement is based on a reasonable methodology and the entity provides documentation to the State that is sufficient to enable the State and the Secretary to ensure compliance with subclause (I).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H47C302386E7E4427A81EEAC53011CB95"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1932(f) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396u-2">42 U.S.C. 1396u–2(f)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and clause (xiv) of section 1903(m)(2)(A)</quote> before the period.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDD0C2D6CB0A485AA026307C9C1A619E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply with respect to contracts entered into on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H207A821DB35148F18B90EC7D727FE216" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study</header>
<subsection id="H26D79047D030493F802C1A1A3BBEBC2B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date that is one year and one month after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall conduct a study—</text> <paragraph id="H80658DC43F424064A4A2CD7368169C79"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comparing the number of children enrolled in a State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) (or a waiver of such plan) during the 12-month period preceding the first day of the period described in subparagraph (C)(ii) of section 1902(a)(13) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, to the number of children so enrolled during the 12-month period beginning on such first day;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB0436C95908F45D1B1015766582B85D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comparing the number of health care providers receiving payments for primary care services under the Medicaid program under such title during the 12-month period preceding the first day of the period described in subparagraph (C)(ii) of section 1902(a)(13) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, to the number of health care providers receiving such payments during the 12-month period beginning on such first day; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE02566FF836F4A9596AD5BF76159B4D3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comparing health care provider payment rates for primary care services under the Medicaid program under such title during the 12-month period beginning on the first day of the period described in subparagraph (C)(ii) of section 1902(a)(13) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, across States, using the indexes described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFADBC20BD38A4F7CB6A33AA37B3E3D64"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Indexes described</header><text>The indexes described in this subsection are each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H4F46DE5821D84C58893AC9565AF24A5B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Medicaid fee index, comparing each State’s average fee for primary care services under the Medicaid program under such title to the national average for such services.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H10155B13BF5744799D64FA769F1424FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A Medicaid-to-Medicare fee index, comparing each State’s average fee for primary care services under the Medicaid program under such title to the fee for such services under the Medicare program under title XVIII of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H28F77A5776134A54B41E1E99AC9B6CD5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Medicaid fee change index, comparing fees for primary care services under the Medicaid program under such title during the 12-month period preceding the first day of the period described in subparagraph (C)(ii) of section 1902(a)(13) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, to the fees for such services during the 12-month period beginning on such first day.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0EA7647BBCA94C3EB15D703679F67352"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $200,000 for fiscal year 2024, to be available until expended.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H4C36E1405EA24529B379AA1FD66AADC7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding use of Bright Futures guidelines</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that health care providers should provide early and periodic screening, diagnostic, and treatment services (as defined in section 1905(r) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(r)</external-xref>)) in accordance with the guidelines of the American Academy of Pediatrics entitled, <quote>Bright Futures: Guidelines for Health Supervision of Infants, Children, and Adolescents</quote>.</text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


