<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H85FF99A5F4F547A289C19088D548ADAB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3614 IH: American Offshore Wind Opportunity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3614</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230523">May 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to submit to Congress a report on offshore wind development vessels, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6412F651109848ADB85F1BDFD9DEEF68" style="OLC"><section id="H4B931FEB0DFD45C48CD7143E4D6CF7C5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Offshore Wind Opportunity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA2170AD1A7F349839AFE38740D860DEF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>GAO study</header><subsection id="HFB73FDBC7C5C4990B11932F4A5112708"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall initiate a study described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="HAA8209F5685E467EAD0D0F3A7329712B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>The Comptroller General shall submit to appropriate congressional committees, including the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, the results of the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC1360D9440034AFD989DFF2BBDDDE7EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents of study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Comptroller General shall include—</text><paragraph id="H20F6F1FDE87D44A4847C679EEB17B902"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an outline of policy and regulatory options that could be adopted to increase the role of United States built vessels, flagged vessels, and mariners in offshore wind turbine installation to meet the goal of developing 30 gigawatts of offshore wind capacity by 2030;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A50B6345A3C44B6B7B7D51EE98E4EAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an outline of any potential ways to—</text><subparagraph id="H6C120F3E33E644CAA9367CA23FC7C077"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the role of United States crews on vessels that are subject to the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act and not subject to chapters 121 and 551 of title 46, United States Code, commonly referred to as the <quote>Jones Act</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H092B2559C8A44DCAB7ABA2A75A6B904D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>domestically manufacture vessels described in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49AB38EFAA4145C4B330B4D7E074C968"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the workforce needs that would be required to build an United States mariner workforce for offshore wind construction, operations, and maintenance to meet the 30 gigawatt goal in subsection (1), specifically—</text><subparagraph id="H84132C1F720C464B97E1ED6054409A58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of such workers needed to crew the offshore wind vessels necessary to meet the goal of developing 30 gigawatts of offshore wind capacity by 2030;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H543F8C6951D04268855DE6F9585C862B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of workers needed to manufacture, build, operate, maintain, and support offshore wind projects;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72EFD5442B73491C88FD9765D983200A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the types of skills and competencies, including those unique to offshore wind construction, operations, and maintenance, required for such employment opportunities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3A187541E97432BBE154BADB21F929C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the required industry or recognized postsecondary credentials required of such workers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CBED61166754D1C8DBF2132D803CE14"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the adjacent skills required for other similar occupations, such as oil drilling, that can be leveraged for reskilling of existing United States workers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFC5466D79FC4FB48223CFF59669AD1B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the gaps in the availability of registered apprenticeship programs and the ability of employers to recruit, hire, and train such workers, including—</text><clause id="H689828B06CDD4EA2A8A464266BF1284E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total cost of training for such programs to skill up such workers; and</text></clause><clause id="H735918DF58FF4C708C7437BDFD437FC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the policies the United States Government can take to eliminate such gaps and costs; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E0C33EAA571421DA79D57E6139A566F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the actions that foreign and domestic wind developers and vessel operators are taking or could be taking to ensure the availability of United States mariners;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA4A95A3F616490FA6112170C5C0B225"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assessment of the capacity of United States shipyards to build wind turbine installation vessels, heavy lift vessels, fall pipe vessels, cable laying vessels, and oceanographic research vessels in addition to larger Jones Act compliant feeder vessels; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9785BB393AC145EAB854082830E3FF4D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of public and private investments needed to spur use of a United States manufactured fleet of offshore wind vessels to support meeting the goal of developing 30 gigawatts of offshore wind capacity by 2030. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

