<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCD13450352DD4F2DA4D6F2B716FF66FC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5838 IH: Strengthening Authorities For Expedited Removal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5838</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve immigration adjudicatory capacity, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD81FBFC8365747349B4BC34EE91BC3C7" style="OLC"><section id="HC8457FF71BD34ED8B03469357A678FEA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening Authorities For Expedited Removal Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAFER Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD8283708F95B48B2842470F3F53E251B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Credible fear interviews</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 235(b)(1)(B)(v) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(B)(v)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>there is a significant possibility</quote> and all that follows, and inserting <quote>, taking into account the credibility of the statements made by the alien in support of the alien’s claim, as determined pursuant to section 208(b)(1)(B)(iii), and such other facts as are known to the officer, the alien more likely than not could establish eligibility for asylum under section 208, and it is more likely than not that the statements made by, and on behalf of, the alien in support of the alien’s claim are true.</quote>.</text></section><section id="H7C0E9C7BDF84416CB5EE9B35383CEEE4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Immigration court docketing priorities during irregular migration influx events</header><subsection id="H13B12E910986420886F220F16CDEFF56"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General shall, to the greatest extent practicable, prioritize docketing and processing of removal cases under section 240 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>) for aliens who are apprehended on entering the United States in connection with an irregular migration influx event.</text></subsection><subsection id="H05C3BD75F35F4ED0A839C94E3253E037"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Irregular migration influx events</header><text>The Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall establish criteria for determining when an irregular migration influx event commences and ends for purposes of carrying out the docketing priorities under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4C4DB2314854CD78C1BE0DB03E80C6E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Access to legal counsel</header><text>The Attorney General shall ensure that any master calendar or merits hearing in a removal case prioritized under subsection (a) is scheduled on a date and at a time that permits the alien a fair and reasonable opportunity to consult with and retain counsel prior to such hearing, consistent with section 292 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1362">8 U.S.C. 1362</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE59AF051B7A54ACC943EF3C9DC1D4215"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="H90BF367509DA4ECD9943DDD96E298149"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of aliens who were apprehended after entering the United States in connection with an irregular migration influx event identified in accordance with subsection (b) and placed in removal proceedings under section 240 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>), organized by the fiscal year in which the apprehension occurred and stating the number of single adults, unaccompanied alien children, and aliens that are apprehended as part of a family unit;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6BE78300D3346CFA6179E6245173760"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of aliens identified under paragraph (1) who appeared at master calendar hearings, including—</text><subparagraph id="HD3139CDDEAAB4D4BB38756F17FD308B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number and percentage represented by counsel at such hearings; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68E28D7E52B848FEB7B94947B759B1D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the average number of days between apprehension and such hearings;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEA7C58614CD4C6E9323110CE5547D46"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of in absentia orders of removal issued to aliens identified under paragraph (1) at master calendar hearings, including the number of such aliens represented by counsel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H373AEFE0DCBF4DD6899431C29599AD55"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the number of aliens identified under paragraph (1) who appeared at final merits hearings, including the number and percentage represented by counsel at such hearings, and the average number of days between apprehension and such hearings; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BE78724C3764EA683C3FBFFB1170011"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the number of in absentia orders of removal issued to aliens identified under paragraph (1) at final merits hearings, including the number of such aliens represented by counsel.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0BF9466EF1634336B84B919853118FEA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Negotiations by secretary of state to disincentivize unlawful immigration</header><subsection id="H59EFED10BAB448C386B5EA4C38AEE1C7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization To negotiate</header><text>The Secretary of State shall seek to negotiate agreements, accords, and memoranda of understanding between the United States, Mexico, Honduras, El Salvador, Guatemala, and other countries in the Western Hemisphere with respect to cooperation and burden sharing required for effective regional immigration enforcement, detention, and repatriation of foreign nationals seeking to enter the United States unlawfully.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC899E0CE73DA49F3A3449441058E118B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>DHS enforcement</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall prioritize the expeditious execution, within the legal jurisdiction of the Department of Homeland Security, of any agreements reached under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HA65B4B5F67AA44F3BD3AA2C4E1E4584D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out subsection (b).</text></subsection></section><section id="H8568B297A55C425495AA593FED22706F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Appropriations for Executive Office of Immigration Review adjudicatory capacity</header><subsection id="H97F0EA2F6B074067B439941A0A3F0907"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Attorney General shall expeditiously improve adjudicatory capacity at the Executive Office for Immigration Review and hire not less than 150 additional immigration judges and support staff to increase adjudications.</text></subsection><subsection id="H503C456F4EB04E54A14AB5477CFD4E4F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the status of hiring additional judges and support staff as required under subsection (a). </text></subsection><subsection id="H0146B4C220904006BEDE184A259F8293"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H276B870A5986448D83993F9176611584"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H3B82A0B7E405468EB939484FBBC6471C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4E02F9508B7449B9DD2FF2C7FFDA97E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C89DF71E63B423F97B44E922BBF9944"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

