<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H548C19805E10450386FB277F39108EDD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2819 IH: Good Samaritan Health Professionals Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2819</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to limit the liability of health care professionals who volunteer to provide health care services in response to a disaster.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1879A645F0E0454EAD06415684E0634D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6436FF1004F7485FBBAAAA575FC20FF1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Good Samaritan Health Professionals Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H457B2231D68D4F37A8584254A62152F4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on liability for volunteer health care professionals</header> <subsection id="HBE0AD2D1F7D84232AC4E36A7220F7892"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/202">42 U.S.C. 202 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 224 the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H4E597BE580F54D0EBA2B983A34DAF16E" style="OLC">
<section id="HC5F38FE1487D4C939C43BBD21276E942"><enum>224A.</enum><header>Limitation on liability for volunteer health care professionals</header>
<subsection id="H73E5D927DCF84302A667C426CD09484A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on liability</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), a health care professional shall not be liable under Federal or State law for any harm caused by an act or omission of the professional in the provision of health care services if—</text> <paragraph id="H90348B23F11847E5B24D6C5F4A7D09A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the professional is serving, for purposes of responding to a disaster, as a volunteer; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H64B9D2966981401E9FE14A2683AA1A5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the act or omission occurs—</text> <subparagraph id="HC1933319ED01477DB72219593E050A86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during the period of the disaster, as determined under the laws listed in subsection (d)(1);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0F3DAB3C79E744309A5FCCBF43BBCC84"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the State or States for which the disaster is declared;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5D5CA572C05A4A9FB29213D21DD49716"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the health care professional’s capacity as a volunteer;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H06085DE85BEE4574845095F0E396E6CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the course of providing services that are within the scope of the license, registration, or certification of the volunteer, as defined by the State of licensure, registration, or certification; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H92F3E2E06E1B4FA1B5A7BEC4A01902A9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in a good faith belief that the individual being treated is in need of health care services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE1F8169F76014A67B3B8BC04765256B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Subsection (a) does not apply if—</text> <paragraph id="HF5387F7348E14AA585F2659EDF3679B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the harm was caused by an act or omission constituting willful or criminal misconduct, gross negligence, reckless misconduct, or a conscious flagrant indifference to the rights or safety of the individual harmed by the health care professional; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H787151C1E6A742F2ADA2ECD9BB1A0B21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the health care professional rendered the health care services under the influence (as determined pursuant to applicable State law) of alcohol or an intoxicating drug.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEE7BC61D3ED54F0C8A77EF6DEC28D20E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preemption</header> <paragraph id="H030216A3F09E468591FD2374FFDA8721"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This section preempts the laws of a State or any political subdivision of a State to the extent that such laws are inconsistent with this section, unless such laws provide greater protection from liability.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC0CF38C7AA5745A39D3D9C6E4AF464DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Volunteer Protection Act</header><text>Protections afforded by this section are in addition to those provided by the Volunteer Protection Act of 1997.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA76918D0FA684E23A7DFD0CDFED165A0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H0B94C86C7D5E46E79EB5EB4EE519B9EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>disaster</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H36EA463DA1CA4E70A138BBCBDFD57770"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a national emergency declared by the President under the National Emergencies Act;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H096D23E2BBD84AAA8992A9A1642022DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an emergency or major disaster declared by the President under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC44A52783394F9B8CFCD546FC1E2F8A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a public health emergency that is determined by the Secretary under section 319 of this Act with respect to one or more States specified in such determination—</text>
<clause id="H1F4C1B1800854C359CCC188586D4D5B4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>during only the initial period covered by such determination; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6CE3D79DF9234351B30A8ED55FBC2185"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>excluding any period covered by a renewal of such determination.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H20012422E9D6439498C981F63A2A9FC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>harm</term> includes physical, nonphysical, economic, and noneconomic losses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45AC25101A8B4B91818D5F2C3039875A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>health care professional</term> means an individual who is licensed, registered, or certified under Federal or State law to provide health care services.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0C35FD99F1A34EC1997B27FAC3D5A3B0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>health care services</term> means any services provided by a health care professional, or by any individual working under the supervision of a health care professional, that relate to—</text> <subparagraph id="H07561DE886B1460BBEF45D8AFA30EEAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the diagnosis, prevention, or treatment of any human disease or impairment; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC739852E584A4E4FAA6C803D2B124745"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the assessment or care of the health of a human being.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8490B251D5254563BD262FFBC69B53F7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>State</term> includes each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, the Northern Mariana Islands, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H623D359149EC4C4A90007080706A374B"><enum>(6)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4BD644E0BE014C949EF3051E3DAB3A7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>volunteer</term> means a health care professional who, with respect to the health care services rendered, does not receive—</text> <clause id="HE8986F763DC042149F42A9DBBE937FC3" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>compensation; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HB124394DE7E44F75A19AE82D30599FF9" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other thing of value in lieu of compensation, in excess of $500 per year.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBDD5E6917AEA4E0D8A17E389272D8654" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>compensation</term>—</text>
<clause id="H168FD43C6888405FBFCF6605D3DE8CD9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>includes payment under any insurance policy or health plan, or under any Federal or State health benefits program; and</text></clause> <clause id="H622FA413BE5A4134A90143453C56E288"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>excludes—</text>
<subclause id="HA35A2D30177D45A98A04438317DA3FED"><enum>(I)</enum><text>reasonable reimbursement or allowance for expenses actually incurred;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HFE933641129F4EEC8EDE701EC25BEDC3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>receipt of paid leave; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HE0434FA1277C454299539B1331D11CC4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>receipt of items to be used exclusively for rendering the health services in the health care professional’s capacity as a volunteer described in subsection (a)(1).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H362609B39390446A9FDC7430CD3F4687"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header> <paragraph id="HAF03B2AA26DD4C96A58B57C6EF4E4366"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 224A of the Public Health Service Act, as added by subsection (a), shall take effect 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80C2D4694B104C24BC8F70653824FB08"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Section 224A of the Public Health Service Act, as added by subsection (a), applies to a claim for harm only if the act or omission that caused such harm occurred on or after the effective date described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HC058D5189C5A417DA20A1CFFA8A12CE3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
<paragraph id="H663B248AC4E24E999B509D558CA255CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>health care professionals should be encouraged to register with the Emergency System for Advance Registration of Volunteer Health Professionals (ESAR–VHP), and States should employ online registration with the promptest processing possible of such registrations to foster the rapid deployment and utilization of volunteer health care professionals following a disaster;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C4D8163D34E4C2784FFD52688C5275D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Federal and State agencies and licensing boards should cooperate to facilitate the timely movement of properly licensed volunteer health care professionals to areas affected by a disaster; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8BDAF5EA65EF4727A57E13BDE1F2AE28"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the appropriate licensing entities should verify the licenses of volunteer health care professionals serving disaster victims as soon as is reasonably practical following a disaster.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

