<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H664D8B743C644DA7A2777C5418DBDE27" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5355 IH: Save Our Airports Reporting Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5355</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to submit to Congress progress reports on the development and implementation of a national plan to transition to the use of a fluorine-free firefighting foam, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5CB36BD7DBDA4CC3B71B64165D360D63" style="OLC"><section id="H93181B3420B0400E8F7313508DBF4A05" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Save Our Airports Reporting Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDF40064AFF544D359626C6EF7AC9D23E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Progress reports on the national transition plan related to a fluorine-free firefighting foam</header><subsection id="HCA1FB8C12C3248B3B3AFE3BD26BD2332"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, and every 180 days thereafter until the progress report termination date described in subsection (c), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Secretary of Defense, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a progress report on the development and implementation of a national transition plan related to a fluorine-free firefighting foam that meets the performance standards referenced in chapter 6 of AC No: 150/5210–6D and is acceptable under section 139.319(l) of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, for use at part 139 airports.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4259B2A64E849D2B3BCB309718AB43A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each progress report required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H057FFB4952874A12865A8335530168EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the progress made by the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration with respect to providing part 139 airports with—</text><subparagraph id="HA80DF77BD51144299D37B11449DADB38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>guidance from the Environmental Protection Agency on acceptable environmental limits relating to such fluorine-free firefighting foam; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8A076F387F34360952BEF3CCEDB0B7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>guidance from the Department of Defense on the transition to a fluorine-free firefighting foam by the Department;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B74750FBA9B4291A70F1153FFB0403A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>best practices for the decontamination of existing aircraft rescue and firefighting vehicles, systems, and other equipment used to deploy firefighting foam at part 139 airports; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H531518A2F6924567A30E07F2CE165BC4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>timelines for the release of policy and guidance relating to part 139 airport implementation plans for obtaining approved military specification products and firefighting personnel training.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF5E7E7642F9401B890B05A721C11945"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of the progress made by the Administrator with respect to providing airports that are not part 139 airports and local authorities with responsibility for inspection and oversight with guidance described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1) as it relates to the use of fluorine-free firefighting foam at such airports.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71F21A8A984B49D4AADA2287BE96CD17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other information as the Administrator determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C6825EA6706403AA76417190119381C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Progress report termination date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the progress report termination date described in this subsection is the date on which the Administrator notifies the appropriate committees of Congress that development and implementation of the national transition plan described in subsection (a) is complete.</text></subsection><subsection id="H46101601E6134663B44962D1744E24FE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H1CF18C87E70E43F1A201699223F59D80"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H8A550A2B61AA43BEB7EE4E7987369099"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committees on Transportation and Infrastructure, Energy and Commerce, and Armed Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8DA68868E8440979AB9AAA5AC657DA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committees on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, Environment and Public Works, and Armed Services of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEC2B121F9D945B3927792755B0045E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Part 139 airport</header><text>The term <quote>part 139 airport</quote> means an airport certified under part 139 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

