<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H64AE30318AE941BD9949D86A97D6B597" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6252 IH: Modernize Nuclear Reactor Environmental Reviews Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6252</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to submit a report and conduct a rulemaking on facilitating efficient, timely environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF9FFE2C2EE2F4EE38DFEA53D41FFFF18" style="OLC"><section id="HE898A831D9B7411CBE5CB5EB8E482507" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Modernize Nuclear Reactor Environmental Reviews Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1C18E0219AD549458B18ADBC800BA7EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Facilitation of efficient environmental reviews</header><subsection id="HE342194AC4164AECBCAFA5F15A048C18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission (in this section referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>) shall submit to the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report on the efforts of the Commission to facilitate efficient, timely environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications, including through expanded use of categorical exclusions, environmental assessments, and generic environmental impact statements. </text></subsection><subsection id="H70DFC86BF99048B6A5BF2F5D8FFDA41C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>In completing the report under subsection (a), the Commission shall—</text><paragraph id="H7E17E1C399E343F8B3D874EA23C019F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe the actions the Commission will take to implement the amendments to the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) made by section 321 of the Fiscal Responsibility Act of 2023;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC72637E713BB497CA89DDA4B783BFF49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consider—</text><subparagraph id="HFE6438E606AB45259E5406B794EB25FF" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using through adoption, incorporation by reference, or other appropriate means, categorical exclusions, environmental assessments, and environmental impact statements prepared by other Federal agencies to streamline environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB007CE107724C398549170C53F6117A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using categorical exclusions, environmental assessments, and environmental impact statements prepared by the Commission to streamline environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FF8A04A21284DA38F4F61F27F8DA48F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using mitigated findings of no significant impact in environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission to reduce the impact of a proposed action to a level that is not significant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B2A6EC3D31D4F16A898DFBDB57894F3" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which the Commission may rely on prior studies or analyses prepared by Federal, State, and local governmental permitting agencies to streamline environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6939ABF5661F4510BD7D3FD1B38B5D92"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">opportunities to coordinate the development of environmental assessments and environmental impact statements with other Federal agencies to avoid duplicative environmental reviews and to streamline environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16CC67A6EE224F009D6C2C5EBF1102AC" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">opportunities to streamline formal and informal consultations and coordination with other Federal, State, and local governmental permitting agencies during environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F8BDF15020F4DF69C0DE0DC450559C7" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">opportunities to streamline the Commission’s analyses of alternatives, including the Commission’s analysis of alternative sites, in environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications by the Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDBC3B749BED4754A8739ED3CD235C01"><enum>(H)</enum><text>establishing new categorical exclusions that could be applied to actions relating to new nuclear reactors applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H509CE0EB95AF48D7A021E80B1C83C9D1" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">amending section 51.20(b) of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, to allow the Commission to determine on a case-specific basis whether an environmental assessment (rather than an environmental impact statement or supplemental environmental impact statement) is appropriate for a particular nuclear reactor application, including in proceedings in which the Commission relies upon a generic environmental impact statement for advanced nuclear reactors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4123C5194A484182866485E6AB06B142" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>authorizing the use of an applicant’s environmental impact statement as the Commission’s draft environmental impact statement, consistent with section 107(f) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4336a">42 U.S.C. 4336a(f)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34C33B67186D4C41AFF120611DEDFBD6" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">opportunities to adopt online and digital technologies, including technologies that would allow applicants and cooperating agencies to upload documents and coordinate with the Commission to edit documents in real time, that would streamline communications between—</text><clause id="H8E12A6B7D664413EB0977C57A1E2D01F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Commission and applicants; and</text></clause><clause id="H8E58C54B0C5242008938C66FF1036FC7" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Commission and other relevant cooperating agencies;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94BF5BEADD024AA5A408552C2A9AFF07" commented="no"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> in addition to implementing measures under subsection (c), potential revisions to part 51 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, and relevant Commission guidance documents, to—</text><clause id="HDBAFBFCC767044198A88DF50CBC27C33" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>facilitate efficient environmental reviews of nuclear reactor applications;</text></clause><clause id="HAF4D973FF82942B7905D3BC678B2F05F" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assist decision-making about relevant environmental issues;</text></clause><clause id="H8621AF9B63A0490A99FB457566A35DA5" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>maintain openness with the public;</text></clause><clause id="H2E42CEFAD94A492B9E2DAA619188F4CA" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meet obligations under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="HEF03A25680C943CA840422E38BAA0FD9" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>reduce burdens on licensees, applicants, and the Commission; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H90C3F3DF96E343C99DE8BEB0A789D8DF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include a schedule for promulgating the rule required under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9799A0EB58A3411B85863E7F067DFECB" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the submission of the report under subsection (a), the Commission shall promulgate a final rule implementing, to the maximum extent practicable, measures considered by the Commission under subsection (b)(2) that are necessary to streamline the Commission’s review of nuclear reactor applications.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

