<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H74645C4EF77146C1924F09D80C47D1A9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 170 IH: Domestic Security Using Production Partnerships and Lessons from Yesterday Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 170</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in collaboration with the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and in coordination with the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Homeland Security, to establish a program of entering into partnerships with eligible domestic manufacturers to ensure the availability of qualified personal protective equipment to prepare for and respond to national health or other emergencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCAC39E23ACAA42F0821FF4A9B897D5AF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA5468C76835A4CA19D63399652B09AD9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Domestic Security Using Production Partnerships and Lessons from Yesterday Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Domestic SUPPLY Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HB77C3D306A8B4238BCA9B3394DCA2961"><enum>2.</enum><header>National defense and health security domestic manufacturing partnership program</header> <subsection id="HFAA269B76A57461E922C3B0C890C3268"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in collaboration with the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and in coordination with the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall establish a program of entering into partnerships with eligible domestic manufacturers to ensure the availability of qualified personal protective equipment for preparing for and responding to public health emergencies.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H73F4EAAA4E85463C9D3D8BDCF39DA395"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contractual purchasing agreements</header>
<paragraph id="H624392F23DCD41EA82F7AE8D85B05214"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Process</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall finalize a process for entering into contractual purchasing agreements with eligible domestic manufacturers to implement the partnerships described in subsection (a). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H571D342F70E7440EA46E8EF20A657EC8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The contractual purchasing agreements entered into under this section, collectively, shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9732863B84804CB29AFD463645679A64"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">guarantee the availability of supplies and manufacturing lines to produce qualified personal protective equipment in amounts specified by the Secretary to prepare for and respond to public health emergencies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8690EB570F4B4F4DBC39C5B022EC67E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fulfill such other requirements as are—</text>
<clause id="H40981CA86062495B8B0142FBC6768D00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>deemed necessary by the Secretary to prepare for and respond to a public health emergency; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1A15019F31AC4C039F887F9C157FA84F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>covered under the contractual purchasing agreement.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H97D626CFCF504DC9B5A60F5D6008EFD8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible domestic manufacturers</header><text>To be eligible to participate in a partnership described in subsection (a), a manufacturer shall—</text> <paragraph id="H851CE9144E234E978ED9FBD760601302"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be headquartered in the continental United States;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1850EB6184E94B779999DCFEA039C990"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">manufacture in the continental United States 100 percent of the products to be supplied to the Federal Government pursuant to such partnership;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA47AA911971F4DE59DC409EE5B312933"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be majority owned and operated by United States citizens; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H11279CFD53E64C92ACAB69CA06929943"><enum>(4)</enum><text>have supply agreements in place to verify supply chain security and sourcing; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72EB368A24CC4FCC817AC26B3A9F62CB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">attest in writing to the fact that the manufacturer’s entire product lines meet or exceed all applicable quality guidelines of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the Occupational Safety and Health Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7D3F6F233C9D4A75BCF684739F0F4B31"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Qualified personal protective equipment</header>
<paragraph id="HCBC04BB55C77477DB0466591EBEC1F66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall maintain a list of products that are eligible for treatment as qualified personal protective equipment under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE8949A14B6E4085AB20AB847FE2024C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>To be included on the list under paragraph (1), a product shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7A3676569F1541D7BE683C72B255FFD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meet or exceed all applicable quality guidelines of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the Occupational Safety and Health Administration;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDDBF018FD29547A9AAE151509C8387B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have been cleared under section 510(k) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360">21 U.S.C. 360(k)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7C754781A45E4ED8B09CDD6E87EC4E72"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be priced using fair-market benchmarks established by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC81EBC33AC4541C1A6C36335D3E40952"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H2FB23086FDE8499288607E3D9D19EB78"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public health emergency</term> means a public health emergency for which a declaration is in effect under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDCBA058C1BA94DFC9896A50A10E4E311"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H23424FEBFA4F424695B9F3F031F21639"><enum>3.</enum><header>Domestic procurement of clothing or equipment used to prevent the transmission of infectious disease</header>
<subsection id="HBFD72C1602D142A5B49C09C00591DD94"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Procurement by Federal Government</header>
<paragraph id="H7640DDD96C164CDD8A729157440ECC5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No clothing or equipment used to prevent the transmission of infectious disease may be procured by the Federal Government unless such clothing or equipment is manufactured in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC89C9710BEA1428EA3A698EE71CFE6D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The exceptions in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (a)(2) of section 8302 of title 41, United States Code, shall apply with respect to the prohibition in paragraph (1) of this subsection to the same extent and in the same manner as such exceptions apply with respect to the prohibition in subsection (a)(1) of such section 8302.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAF308754394642979ACB2220E6A94B39"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception documentation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an exception described in paragraph (2), documentation, including a detailed justification for the use of the exception, shall be submitted by the official responsible for applying the exception.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1D5FD58A2217496E9239BC5F866281AE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procurement by State and local governments using Federal funds</header> <paragraph id="HB0BDD54400A94BDAB8BD03ED90FDA08A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No clothing or equipment described in subsection (a)(1) may be procured by a State or local government using Federal funds unless such clothing or equipment is manufactured in the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1B0710894BC3401880AEEC936957F33B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The exceptions in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (a)(2) of section 8302 of title 41, United States Code, shall apply with respect to the prohibition in paragraph (1) of this subsection to the same extent and in the same manner as such exceptions apply with respect to the prohibition in subsection (a)(1) of such section 8302.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DA311CD462947A8845CB0CB1A4C5124"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception documentation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an exception described in paragraph (2), documentation, including a detailed justification for the use of the exception, shall be submitted by the official responsible for applying the exception.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5F0318D63CE4F6F8FA806E4D1429A3D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>Paragraph (1) applies only with respect to the award of Federal funds on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H7D1137D38A0D46C3B64F8B94B4B68E82"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report on the impact of changes to PPE requirements on frontline worker safety</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health, shall submit a report to the Congress on—</text>
<paragraph id="H8A84CBA896774A6D8EA635DA53C8D645"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the changes to the Federal requirements applicable to personal protective equipment that have taken place since the beginning of the COVID–19 pandemic; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7ECCDDAB2D244E2EB88D2919297DB5CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of these changes on the safety of physicians and other medical professionals caring for patients face-to-face during the years 2020 and 2021.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

