<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H35110E264BB64B7D84BFC0F5F168A662" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5728 IH: Government Shutdown Impact Report Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5728</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Congressional Budget Office to submit daily reports during the period in which a Government shutdown is in effect on the effects of the shutdown on the economy and the costs of the shutdown to taxpayers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF71B904F8C4644C3B829BA36FD8B4B81" style="OLC"><section id="H7423CD8239CD42DB9751EB17275FC253" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Government Shutdown Impact Report Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7CFFAA56471B4E54B9F387DB3FA10527"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reports by Congressional Budget Office on economic costs and costs to taxpayers of government shutdown</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 24 hours after each day on which a Government shutdown is in effect, the Director of the Congressional Budget Office shall submit a report to Congress containing information on each of the following, based on the most recent information available to the Director:</text><paragraph id="HF8134B8EB04941E8A0ED9E45060C865A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An estimate of the economic output lost on that day as the result of the Government shutdown.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE841F09E9D6542D4B8A652B4E475C866"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An estimate of any decrease in gross domestic product for the quarter that will occur as the result of the Government shutdown.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CEAD798E8BD419FAA7E15D1290DAA82"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The value of any assistance, including loans, grants, and contracts, that the Small Business Administration was unable to provide as the result of the Government shutdown.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36CD859ED91D42BD8DDFE33E1BD9A0A3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The amount of any revenue for the National Park Service that was lost on that day as the result of the closure of National Park Service lands and historic sites.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75C2C0D4C5614284B9CF523CBEDB2F9B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An estimate of revenue lost on that day because of the effects of the Government shutdown on tourism and travel to and within the United States, including travel by foreign tourists.</text></paragraph></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H325B1AFB8861496D943A398165AE5D7C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determination of Government shutdown</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, a Government shutdown shall be considered to be in effect if there is a lapse in appropriations for any Federal agency or department as a result of a failure to enact a regular appropriations bill or continuing resolution.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

