<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB7344EB92D5B4154AF41E5E81E47705F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6352 IH: Tax Stamp Revenue Transfer for Wildlife and Recreation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6352</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To transfer a portion of the firearms transfer tax imposed under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to the Federal aid to wildlife restoration fund and the Conservation of America&#8217;s Wildlife Trust Fund, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H696AC3AA57694CA99CB2BE5AE6291CCD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCF5C06CFB12C4052805913C3F5861BCA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tax Stamp Revenue Transfer for Wildlife and Recreation Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HDC3FC280D51B400E925D8A1E756CE997"><enum>2.</enum><header>Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund</header> <subsection id="H048D17B2BB524E2FB3AFF3236E2C84EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/98">chapter 98</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDBF4951A98144102928CEA81522DD810" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HE7AD94C6EC7F493DBCDA4D0FB629172D"><enum>9512.</enum><header>Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund</header> 
<subsection id="H00BB0DAF7FD246D794529BE558D3BE73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury of the United States a trust fund to be known as the <quote>Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund</quote> consisting of such amounts as may be appropriated or credited to such Trust Fund as provided in this section or section 9602(b).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H05366F26EB424B11B7E83CC618BC79F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfers to trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are hereby appropriated to the Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund amounts equivalent to 15 percent of the net revenues received in the Treasury (after the date of the enactment of this Act) from the tax imposed under section 5811 on the transfer of silencers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAEB1DC97CBE4486B963C3748929FB918"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures from trust fund</header><text>Amounts in the Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund shall be available, as provided in appropriations Acts, to the National Firearms Act Division of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives only for the purpose of expediting the processing of applications for transfer and registration of silencers described in section 5812(c) and applications to make ans register silencers described in the third and fourth sentences of section 5822.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF76499E1C03547B1A25D2C61E5D8DB7A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Offset of budgetary impact</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall transfer from the Department of Justice Assets Forfeiture Fund (established under section 524(c) of title 28, United States Code) to the general fund of the Treasury amounts equivalent to the amounts appropriated to the Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund under subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC3231FECF1CC4956A98AC933A4346884"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Silencer</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>silencer</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 5845(a)(7).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H51973B84D76D4DA992FB5E32D55AB608"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Subsection (b) shall not apply with respect to the amount of any tax imposed with respect to any transfer after the date which is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAE9A51B06EF34504B4B961C3025433FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/98">chapter 98</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H763182E9FCB440CEAAD43764B36BF35D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HDBF4951A98144102928CEA81522DD810" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> <toc-entry idref="HE7AD94C6EC7F493DBCDA4D0FB629172D" level="section">Sec. 9512. Conservation of America’s Wildlife Trust Fund.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H752404EC48D54BE2BA8B367DF34BA247"><enum>3.</enum><header>Expediting of certain firearm silencer applications</header> <subsection id="H36A0F66E38424CA2810C215D086D7F48"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Processing of applications for transfer of firearms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5812">Section 5812</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6A6EB800098E464EA0EE2C67EC2E431C" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H48720E934039466F85AB84A7CCF3FB58"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Processing of applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an application for the transfer and registration of a silencer (as defined in section 5845(a)(7)) that meets the requirements of paragraphs (1) through (5) of subsection (a) and that is filed during the 7-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, such application shall be deemed to have been approved by the Secretary on the date which is 90 days after such requirements are met (and such transfer may thereafter be made) unless the Secretary (before such date) determines that the transfer, receipt, or possession of such silencer would place the transferee in violation of law. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0A705928E58345C7823370F36456B43D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Processing of applications for making of firearm silencers</header><text>Section 5822 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>In the case of an application to make and register a silencer (as defined in section 5845(a)(7)) that meets the requirements of subsections (a) through (d) and that is filed during the 7-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, such application shall be deemed to have been approved by the Secretary on the date which is 90 days after such requirements are met (and such silencer may thereafter be made) unless the Secretary (before such date) determines that the making or possession of such silencer would place the person making such silencer in violation of law.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB90544E827304479A4070FDD0FE4946C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to applications filed after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H783552BDCF2D47A0A571208364403E61"><enum>4.</enum><header>Federal Aid to Wildlife Restoration Fund</header> <subsection id="HA3147006C7BF4BC59F7AA805A40FBEED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(a) of the Pittman-Robertson Wildlife Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/669b">16 U.S.C. 669b(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBEC9355E053541A09AACB5BCF9B55F1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, and an amount equal to 85 percent of all revenues accruing each fiscal year, beginning with the fiscal year 2024 and ending with fiscal year 2030, from the tax imposed on the transfer of silencers (as such term is defined in section 5845(a)(7) of such Code) by section 5811 of such Code,</quote> after <quote>4181)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC4D14C369041488FA45443B25CECF102"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H63D4C9CEC261459694310D8215EC6D99" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H551A55351650484A98C8699B6DBFEF02"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall transfer from the Department of Justice Assets Forfeiture Fund (as established under section 524(c) of title 28, United States Code) to the general fund of the Treasury an amount equal to the amount covered into the fund from the tax imposed by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5811">section 5811</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4510E9729C2B450A8E1A235E9A1144CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Apportionment of revenues</header> <paragraph id="H6213B232BF854011BCD7C7CB60FCE5F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 4(c)(1) of the Pittman-Robertson Wildlife Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/669c">16 U.S.C. 669c(c)(1)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H52C29BE714EC4F7D83FA56861D248CFC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HB7CBBE54956B4BBEB03FC7EC8AE4E802"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the following shall be apportioned among the States in proportion to the ratio that the population of each State bears to the population of all the States:</text> <subparagraph id="H2245813DB5864522A1A65B7F09545F08"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><fraction>1/2</fraction> of the revenues accruing to the fund under this Act each fiscal year (beginning with the fiscal year 1975) from any tax imposed on pistols, revolvers, bows, and arrows.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBC141D22A91E4850B77FBF42F975D808"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">15 percent of the amount covered into the fund each fiscal year, beginning with the fiscal year 2024 and ending with fiscal year 2030, from the tax imposed by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5811">section 5811</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as described in section 3(a)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H582024F8F29C47C3BAA145E9EF54A5B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4(c)(4) of the Pittman-Robertson Wildlife Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/669c">16 U.S.C. 669c(c)(4)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC7FA04B67F304C86A41093B8F19D3304" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H2E0A9B8342A945D68340D5985E2AAB4B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<subparagraph id="H374B3D92D10C442AB83799A59F8CCC96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In addition to other uses authorized under this Act, amounts apportioned under paragraph (1)(A) may be used for hunter recruitment and recreational shooter recruitment.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8A41370839384CF7977612671A129AF4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with section 8(b), amounts apportioned under paragraph (1)(B) shall be used to construct, maintain, expand, or operate public target ranges.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA6588F2F688E41E88E41BF199AD391AF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures for management of wildlife areas and resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(b)(1) of the Pittman-Robertson Wildlife Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/669g">16 U.S.C. 669g(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 4(c)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 4(c)(1)(A), and shall use the funds apportioned to it under section 4(c)(1)(B),</quote>.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

