<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7FE1C94104F943C28A2A30C5E2440A17" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6208 IH: Trash Reduction And Suppressing Harm from Environmental Degradation at the Border Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6208</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture to submit to Congress a report on the amount of waste collected on certain Federal land along the southern border of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H844B10D4CD5C42A8B800E5B4D32E1A59" style="OLC">
<section id="H210361EB9D0D41879251C84CEB5CBF2E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Trash Reduction And Suppressing Harm from Environmental Degradation at the Border Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRASHED Border Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB78B07F7EFBD4B608F5B3A06DF72D9A2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Policies and procedures to reduce trash along the southern border</header> <subsection id="H97D4BB8FD0CA47EE89FB6E615A8BC18F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in coordination with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall establish and implement policies and protocols to prevent and mitigate environmental degradation on covered Federal lands caused by aliens without lawful immigration status—</text>
<paragraph id="HBE1B43ED054A48838202CB5F31AE28AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>crossing the southern border; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H42488C28AEC04EB985A22C0C19C41D66"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">being housed, or otherwise illegally encroaching or camping, on National Forest System lands or lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC179FE0E117433F98C468B6D5F548B8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Protocols</header><text>In developing the policies and protocols under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall consider policies and seek to implement best practices with respect to—</text> <paragraph id="HE908BD07E09B48D790678D697CFCF1E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reducing trash accumulation, particularly in ecologically sensitive areas—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1A91C93B8C9342E6901F6B19203E79D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on covered Federal lands; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H010B9DD651424E08B10FE99D867A4781"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">where aliens without lawful immigration status are being housed, or are otherwise illegally encroaching or camping, on National Forest System lands or lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H979EB8F069AF4D72B13E278395E66FF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>address the destruction of sensitive natural and archeological resources; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA340F5FDBA784971A1D0C5BCE835AC80"><enum>(3)</enum><text>address the destruction of wildlife habitat.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HED9D068E780F44D1B406818B0A3EFC4C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transparency and accountability in trash accumulation on the southern border</header>
<subsection id="HBBEAC1CC4AC34AC49A576286C6DA2671"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and for each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary concerned shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the amount of waste collected in the following areas:</text> <paragraph id="H23AED85060B94B68831C2333E49F2C5A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Covered Federal lands. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H92FD2BF3FF8F4509A3FEF1C6E481884D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Sites on National Forest System lands or lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior—</text> <subparagraph id="HAD42C081141F4BB6A3FEBB16177E0E9D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on which aliens without lawful immigration status are being housed, or are otherwise illegally encroaching or camping; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBB737BDAEB4C4ABC92FF286169860D13"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">used for the illegal cultivation of narcotics, including the cultivation of cannabis, by aliens without lawful immigration status.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2384700127E4457782539A82FCD37C4F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>Each report submitted under subsection (a) shall include the following with respect to areas covered by the report:</text>
<paragraph id="HA50CECC56E724127A8146283497F62E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total amount of waste collected (in pounds) by employees and contractors of Federal agencies and the cost of collecting such waste, including a breakdown by agency, region, or other unit the Secretary concerned determines appropriate in illustrating the distribution of waste.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3F160013D334EB5B8E17621BA473423"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Suggestions on how to reduce environmental degradation caused by waste.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1DAB66E0FF71405B8C99DDA9DEF098BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Data provided by Federal, State, and local agencies, nonprofit and volunteer organizations, and individuals with respect to—</text> <subparagraph id="H7F8DC237BD684F039B8727297E69E9E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of waste collected; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H94CC39417AE249CE85FF8670A9E763C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of waste collection events.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97BC115D1F26436DB5ABACC7BF83201B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The total number of acres of wildlife habitat impacted by waste.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD2242BE2B95040AAA75E7F3F57373954"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The discovery of any unauthorized trails or roads.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F44FE3FA1174794943E08FA89006A1B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The number of wildfires started as a result of unauthorized human activity, including fires started by aliens without lawful immigration status.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H69AD167E04BC4C5BA7EAB7E83577BFCE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary concerned determines appropriate to demonstrate the amount of waste found or collected.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H344111475FEF4BCEA452647B7860227F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Collection data</header> <paragraph id="HC8E572FB4EAE43B3BE67359AB551A9AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In developing the reports required under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H19982550430141C5B10BD6DA39039450"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collaborate in information gathering with State, local, nonprofit, and volunteer organizations and individuals assisting in waste collection efforts; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H50DD65CEF53E4FF0A254C39CF6369C02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, verify the information provided by such organizations and individuals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H92EDBF5B1FA04017972D3A9F4FF2B159"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protection of data</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall take precautions to ensure the privacy of organizations and individuals submitting data for the purposes of this Act and prevent the disclosure of personal identifiable information to the public.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H139023C4FB2A4002B3EEAF50DBC2B69A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dates for submission</header><text>Except for the first report submitted in accordance with subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees each fiscal year report not later than 90 days after the last day of the fiscal year covered by the report.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H0878A2EEF1CE4ACA92B3D9B802248964" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Penalties and fines</header>
<subsection id="H3E4FEA54AB73401A83E31D1F3073E439"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An alien without lawful immigration status who, while on covered Federal land, carries out an activity prohibited under applicable fire and sanitation regulations shall be subject to penalties and fines.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3BCCD650DEF94879B8DA29C318A62B18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties doubled</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall promulgate rules and regulations to double the penalties and fines for prohibited activities referred to in subsection (a) carried out on covered Federal lands.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H861EC505757343D29127AD55AFACCB36"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall enforce existing regulations regarding penalties and fines, specifically regarding applicable fire and sanitation regulations on covered Federal land.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD2B884BF37C14AC29F0338B07DDBB22D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and for each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary concerned shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report detailing the total amount collected in penalties and fines under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HB2E46155144C4B8CAB9BB9D4A2D91384"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H6B9F7AD398214CCEA1D9425807102F7E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable fire and sanitation regulations</header><text>The term <term>applicable fire and sanitation regulations</term> means the following provisions of the Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act:</text>
<subparagraph id="HEBC82F42B2524246B795D995CFF00402"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior—</text> <clause id="H02035A784893485FA8B547EB08382C50"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sections 2.13 and 2.14 of title 36;</text></clause>
<clause id="HE4516892F1864136999B16A50F207245"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sections 423.29, 423.31, 423.34, 8365.1–1, 8365.1–7, 8365.2–1, 8365.2–3, 9212.1, and 9212.2 of title 43; and </text></clause> <clause id="H98031FAE8A9E40D4AE1C67E79D8CA936"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>sections 26.34, 27.94, and 27.95 of title 50.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA82FC2C424E34A828A0467B931E9728D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>With respect to National Forest System lands, sections 261.5 and 261.11 of title 36. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABE25016E2FB45259BB31B80B4D48651"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBDD81C04F8C34F2FBB2E8DFDAE308A57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committees on Natural Resources, Agriculture, Homeland Security, and the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4ADDAADB4BBC46EC9E469C29002B3601"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committees on Energy and Natural Resources, Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry, Homeland Security &amp; Governmental Affairs, and the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD4272879A43C47A49E7F9E5D422EAC30"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered federal lands</header><text>The term <term>covered Federal lands</term> means land—</text> <subparagraph id="H4AB13ACF2D9847FAA9A4FC16FBDA120E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>owned by the United States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9CC60524475C4AA799A1AB4E8171F026"><enum>(B)</enum><text>located in a unit that shares an exterior boundary with the southern border; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H159FF2C74BC9445AAD322FD1AB44548B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>administered by—</text>
<clause id="H8410717368314A4189A214AA0C51D3C0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the National Park Service;</text></clause> <clause id="H9483E296406C4101AF9ECF6B5F49CC7A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Bureau of Land Management;</text></clause>
<clause id="HC43045720D8B47C589E18F9D6DC5F55E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the United States Fish and Wildlife Service;</text></clause> <clause id="HB39306016EBD4ED2AB239218DD1AA284"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Bureau of Reclamation; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HAB60F754645944A18774C6732410CBA2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Forest Service.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BA2A169F5744265A491F912B226C818"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE4DFD8818B3D4A72A037569621002DD4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEDEC15FA127B45D1932BD830D99021DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, with respect to National Forest System lands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1327EACD259941BF93A7F7FCC0B3F624"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Southern border</header><text>The term <term>southern border</term> means the international land border between the United States and Mexico. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H092554D545F44C1AA81F50A43862A4CF"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Waste</header><text>The term <term>waste</term> means any refuse, garbage, rubbish, trash, debris, or litter left or created by humans and disposed of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1171C10C897C4E549DA4923E15F32EBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>without authorization from the Federal agency administering the area where the waste is found; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5F76B2F3A494C62BFCD14CFAEE3EA05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outside of a waste collection receptacle.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


