<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H38668181EF724A8DAB3327C56D381FAF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6249 IH: Think Differently About Emergencies Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6249</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a review and report on the assistance and resources that the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency provides to individuals with disabilities and the families of such individuals that are impacted by major disasters, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8D57652153204B94A6E9DD92CBFA385B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H55F00198DD274350AF0CA852C64A3570" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Think Differently About Emergencies Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCE4C41E76DAD47E8AECCD66E32CF1A90" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header> <subsection id="H7FF2CD4DE6264B77A9F2DDAC2716FF3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report describing the assistance and resources that the Administrator provides for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities and the families of such individuals who are impacted by major disasters declared under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) to the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0C1E3B807A7446B2A9FEC2FFD928C974"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H24738E95F6584B13B8D991DD72EFE964"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Localities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H495027B088584926AE5E1E82BD8E9A4E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Nonprofit organizations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D7443804BDA47C093E9925F15D7212B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Directly to such individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8AACDA67E16F45AB8086B1C5D512F147"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall contain—</text> <paragraph id="HD334178BB02446828C7BDF687B7E3A0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the resources and best practices that the Administrator makes available to the entities listed in paragraphs (1) through (4) of subsection (a) that are impacted by major disasters declared under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40F62B472B844B96B1833755F60A9937"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">detail the process the Administrator undertakes to train personnel and deploy such personnel into areas to coordinate with States, localities, and nonprofit organizations to provide assistance and ensure that the needs of individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities and the families of such individuals are met following such a disaster;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2820EA27304E4919B061CC11F97FD1AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">list the number of programs the Administrator administers which support individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities to prepare for and recover from such disasters, including by provide accommodation to such individuals and the families of such individuals;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5436FDF177954FF89C34CDB89FDB376C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">description of outreach activities of the Administration to State, local, and nonprofit experts on addressing the needs of individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities and the families of such individuals impacted by such disasters; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H75D99CD829394580BD1134EAB610C19C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">report that identifies, with respect to individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities and the families of such individuals, areas for improvement in supporting such individuals and families to prepare for and recover from such disasters.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2BAA078A346F4CACBCBC31B9EE754591"><enum>3.</enum><header>Review of assistance and resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States and the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall each—</text> <paragraph id="H6ED6D08610A44ACCAFCECB48662F5ED0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a review of assistance and resources the Administrator provides to States, localities, nonprofit organizations, and individuals to assist—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H508F58979DB84661AC729B8552F4AA44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H949590416CF241D9806E8428165D7D8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals with physical disabilities; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H687BE9CFE1614AF1ADF28025E9D03F8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the families of the individuals described in subparagraphs (A) and (B);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BE8535516484344AC0A3DF20BCEE3AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify potential legal impediments to providing such assistance and resources;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B74AF36C5DF4E8395B04945A6DDA856"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide to Congress recommendations on how the Administration can—</text> <subparagraph id="H1E3438E008F24319B2315FE2807B4285"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve such assistance and resources; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00AE9B8B39DD426E84A2D33AF2926405"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enhance coordination with States, localities, nonprofit organizations in carrying out such assistance and providing such resources; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H740B34CBB60349F7A1A788F53633F06E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>streamline the application process and delivery of assistance and resources to individuals described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) of paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED71C8FC3077405D86CC55D095C2272B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide to Congress recommendations on any legislative reform necessary to improve such assistance and resources.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

