<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8288178387454537BA742213F3EEE1EE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3200 IH: Gateway Community and Recreation Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3200</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior to carry out certain activities to enhance recreational opportunities for gateway communities, to amend the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act to provide for the establishment of a digital National Parks and Federal Recreational Lands Pass, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H89E1883C4821480D8A88D6702D0394E9" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H6D3EAAFDA6CA42E6A5C05AD35399A47F" changed="not-changed"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Gateway Community and Recreation Enhancement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC88F39244EB34319AC68C34FC059025D" changed="not-changed"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD916EE9D2E544E3583E960483DCC2BFB" changed="not-changed" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal recreational lands and waters</header><text>The term <term>Federal recreational lands and waters</term> has the meaning given the term in section 802 of the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6801">16 U.S.C. 6801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7C8980C5CAE4D26AAC4603A3CA97C5D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Gateway community</header><text>The term <term>gateway community</term> means a community that serves as an entry point or is adjacent to a recreation destination on Federal recreational lands and waters or non-Federal land at which there is consistently high, in the determination of the Secretaries, seasonal or year-round visitation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A063E76120240BCAFC9B7C7842C612B" changed="not-changed" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FB15A6D24294118948088B67BED4F59" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <term>Secretaries</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HF3694A7353494471A01A03C71DE88AF6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01132535EC4C41C0AC50C04E33380A30" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph changed="not-changed" commented="no" id="HC0430A255ED54DA387229C4CB5634665"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H3CF7C5C889D24B6C934E71D173EAE005" changed="not-changed"><enum>3.</enum><header>Gateway communities</header><subsection id="H2209AB90F801453080284B6BCFBACC07" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessment of impacts and needs in gateway communities</header><text>Using existing funds available to the Secretaries, the Secretaries—</text><paragraph id="HAFC597B636174741B38DCBE694F414D1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall collaborate with State and local governments, Indian Tribes, housing authorities, applicable trade associations, nonprofit organizations, and other relevant stakeholders to identify needs and economic impacts in gateway communities, including—</text><subparagraph id="HE56F5F1341054F6F9F654BD2541EA151" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>housing shortages;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CB191238C314D2AAFB7875C44D93C6C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demands on existing municipal infrastructure;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA60CAACFA70347FD9B012BE2EB0F908D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>accommodation and management of sustainable visitation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D1235E31B034FDF9C14EA17832C8AAE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the expansion and diversification of visitor experiences by bolstering the visitation at—</text><clause id="H272D600212664A72840417DAB1C3DF75" changed="not-changed" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text> underutilized locations on nearby Federal recreational lands and waters that are suitable for developing, expanding, or enhancing recreation use, as identified by the Secretaries; or</text></clause><clause id="H67668BA55405494AAB688012CF7D1B26" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lesser-known recreation sites, as identified under section 5(b)(1)(B), on nearby land managed by a State agency or a local agency;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A83DECAB7184865B69E6437446DFEC3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may address a need identified under paragraph (1) by—</text><subparagraph id="H34B2A312CD3F43B4861E863712B38FE4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing financial or technical assistance to a gateway community under an existing program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2677784A28945C88D4447D9941554AD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>entering into a lease, right-of-way, or easement, in accordance with applicable laws; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A4D5CA219EC4889B225C0675BA481FD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>issuing an entity referred to in paragraph (1) a special use permit (other than a special recreation permit), in accordance with applicable laws. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2A1D7F9E74D479DBA32DE635EA5D6F7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and financial assistance to businesses</header><paragraph id="H2C3A373264014EF79FC71A55BDDDE98B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture (acting through the Administrator of the Rural Business-Cooperative Service), in coordination with the Secretary and the Secretary of Commerce, shall provide to businesses in gateway communities the assistance described in paragraph (2) to establish, operate, or expand infrastructure to accommodate and manage sustainable visitation, including hotels, campgrounds, and restaurants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AFBEC210C7E4653A2495610CC3C1528" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistance</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture may provide assistance under paragraph (1) through the use of existing, or the establishment of new, entrepreneur and vocational training programs, technical assistance programs, low-interest business loan programs, and loan guarantee programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB5A0E583A974E6793F90A371725EE2D" changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretaries may, in accordance with applicable laws, enter into a public-private partnership, cooperative agreement, memorandum of understanding, or similar agreement with a gateway community or a business in a gateway community. </text></subsection></section><section id="HC5A8E137DC6745D0A25D8D848164DF59"><enum>4.</enum><header>Public meetings before reduction of access to national Parks</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Before taking any action that will reduce access to a National Park (not including actions to reduce access due to incident specific events that present a risk to health and safety such as a weather event or vehicle accident), the Superintendent of the affected National Park shall—</text><paragraph id="H0E27BD658CD546F4AFEB2B982FF63447"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct public meetings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36B6FAB09A564CB7AA56F602566A04F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consult local stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAE194FC771745AC9151C792DBADEF10"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide an opportunity for submission of public comments for a period of not less than 60 days. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H8886DB4D3C20479B867D47016CD317EC" changed="not-changed"><enum>5.</enum><header>Improved recreation visitation data</header><subsection id="H6A074C1598F04B2584D8D607BC9807E3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consistent visitation data</header><paragraph id="HA39930E4E556473DA94FD80BDC29DB5E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual visitation data</header><text>The Secretaries shall establish a single visitation data reporting system to report accurate annual visitation data, in a consistent manner, for— </text><subparagraph id="HCC7EAF92D6BE4F3CB8223BEA88E0A7E9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each unit of Federal recreational lands and waters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE68CB7CACA1F4CAABFF6AC214FD8E153" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>land held in trust for an Indian Tribe, on request of the Indian Tribe.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88711247240048BE9658B78AF9E05059" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Categories of use</header><text>Within the visitation data reporting system established under paragraph (1), the Secretaries shall—</text><subparagraph id="HC283A326154740D7AC2BC4CD499368F2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish multiple categories of different recreation activities that are reported consistently across agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B0A11895FCA4E29BC4A06866602C827" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide an estimate of the number of visitors for each applicable category established under subparagraph (A) for each unit of Federal recreational lands and waters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD601B793DA4549C1AD1195AF7597A2F7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Real-Time Data Pilot program</header><paragraph id="HAD3285A9BDAB44DFA76BC133821F6AC0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, using existing funds available to the Secretaries, the Secretaries shall carry out a pilot program, to be known as the <quote>Real-time Data Pilot Program</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Pilot Program</quote>), to make available to the public, for each unit of Federal recreational lands and waters selected for participation in the Pilot Program under paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="H8B693A125AAE445C99D36B0CADBD4917" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>real-time or predictive data on visitation (including data and resources publicly available from existing nongovernmental platform) at—</text><clause id="H5837EF0111E9404686F97B05FC29C0B1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters;</text></clause><clause id="H9B6D127A412045D6A8C46EF32EEB3115" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, areas within the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters; and</text></clause><clause id="H68D6E4847FC5473CA06DC92A6AD8E074" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, recreation sites managed by any other Federal agency, a State agency, or a local agency that are located near the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE02A8B59BE06427CADD3FACEC7306978" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through multiple media platforms, information about lesser-known recreation sites located near the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters (including recreation sites managed by any other Federal agency, a State agency, or a local agency), in an effort to encourage visitation among recreational sites.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H657983DC4B3C498197EF9CEA12D4539C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Locations</header><subparagraph id="HF78537D7C5054287B407A269E9F28FD2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial number of units</header><text>On establishment of the Pilot Program, the Secretaries shall select for participation in the Pilot Program—</text><clause id="HE4E04958354C4147BD36299F623412E9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>15 units of Federal recreational lands and waters managed by the Secretary; and</text></clause><clause id="HA2EC9CEEE326409B94A742C4C86A2F9E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>5 units of Federal recreational lands and waters managed by the Secretary of Agriculture (acting through the Chief of the Forest Service).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0347824761C14C0F8AAF119C5BCB9048" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Expansion</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretaries shall expand the Pilot Program by selecting 80 additional units of Federal recreational lands and waters managed by the Secretaries for participation in the Pilot Program, not fewer than 50 of which shall be units managed by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06AD53F322AD4400A7310B21A4C6DC26" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Feedback; support of gateway communities</header><text>The Secretaries shall—</text><clause id="H87E1F1F9922648E2A2EBFE6D0D4691A0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>solicit feedback regarding participation in the Pilot Program from communities adjacent to units of Federal recreational lands and waters and the public; and</text></clause><clause id="H9D0D832D8C1F4E27BB15D9E78BEFE419" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in carrying out subparagraphs (A) and (B), select a unit of Federal recreation lands and waters to participate in the Pilot Program only if the community adjacent to the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters is supportive of the participation of the unit of Federal recreational lands and waters in the Pilot Program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE985D9E19ABE4B6085DB5A05F27E240E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Dissemination of information</header><text>The Secretaries may disseminate the information described in paragraph (1) directly or through an entity or organization referred to in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B8418C42B6B40AA8FE742BEEFE96828" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Community partners and third-Party providers</header><text>For purposes of carrying out this section, the Secretary concerned may—</text><paragraph id="HC3FCAEC99CE140F98EDD1C6921A16FA4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate and partner with—</text><subparagraph id="H9AF15888F52B49E49A381A93727C7EFD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>communities adjacent to units of Federal recreational lands and waters;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A80214DBD59419E8BE601C6D9F016AF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>State and local outdoor recreation and tourism offices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EE429EFF8634624B5951848AECCBB91" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>local governments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F203F20616F495098212F979BBCA330" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Indian Tribes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD085771D2093448385762052E49EAC9F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>trade associations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16E1542C890043A78B01AE365C738CF2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>local outdoor recreation marketing organizations; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7C53C6D3E184FA3B605D84EAA4F24A3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(G)</enum><text>permitted facilitated recreation providers; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3928723EB7984697AAF5D3096C0B8AF8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other relevant stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B080EF4DE0042899D1543D874577C9E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate or enter into agreements, as appropriate, with private sector and nonprofit partners, including—</text><subparagraph id="H2084517FC6E843C7B77253493AF4A661" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>technology companies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA12C15FABA8043C8B3A55B36A2D3B6A6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>geospatial data companies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6330627AABC14F36BDA217A51566445C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>experts in data science, analytics, and operations research; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F09B5FA962842559879599F75D702FB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>data companies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1182804942A46AC985B17B1158F7B3B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Existing programs</header><text>The Secretaries may use existing programs or products of the Secretaries to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7471814DAE664E988483E9CDCF3677A2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Privacy clauses</header><text>Nothing in this section provides authority to the Secretaries—</text><paragraph id="H7724C97D724F4CAA8878C5C296F2DC02" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to monitor or record the movements of a visitor to a unit of Federal recreational lands and waters;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43F5DCD7A62546EA8A111553F5178393" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to restrict, interfere with, or monitor a private communication of a visitor to a unit of Federal recreational lands and waters; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EDE018F3BE24C5E85FBC886D5079B47" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to collect—</text><subparagraph id="H5801B5658B344BFCB0DBCFD315580A0F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>information from owners of land adjacent to a unit of Federal recreational lands and waters; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3C289A1C4714E4B97D19FFBF3704FE9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information on non-Federal land. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0FE75E118F994A2ABAACC3366FB08397" changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2024, and annually thereafter, the Secretaries shall publish on a website of the Secretaries a report that describes the annual visitation of each unit of Federal recreational lands and waters, including, to the maximum extent practicable, visitation categorized by recreational activity.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2F4E852936794FF7B009617B9E7B9CB8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Establishment of a digital version of america the beautiful—the national parks and federal recreational lands passes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 805(a) of the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6804">16 U.S.C. 6804(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7446D8C0BB7409198072AB0DFC41F26"><paragraph id="HB7015FA3117241F58045DB893EA752FE"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Digital recreation passes</header><text>By not later than January 1, 2024, the Secretaries shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4FFD0BEB23244D6BA9D8C963246B0B71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish a digital version of the National Parks and Federal Recreational Lands Pass that is able to be stored on a mobile device; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H787B786FBD0B458EAC5371D30D8E4B86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on the completion of a sale of a National Parks and Federal Recreational Lands Pass carried out under paragraph (6)(A), make available to the passholder the digital version of the National Parks and Federal Recreational Lands Pass established under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

