<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H14A5BE4FB87C4AFB9FA93FAE58827564" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3855 IH: National Digital Reserve Corps Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3855</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to establish a National Digital Reserve Corps to help address the digital and cybersecurity needs of Executive agencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE4063839146E4BFEBC7B3F23D921062B" style="OLC"><section id="H612015FCCAD6470AAB043C51FDED45D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Digital Reserve Corps Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFD9A79E4A2C04EF2B8D9728D0B2FD05B"><enum>2.</enum><header>National digital reserve corps</header><subsection id="H995ED28A5CFA4168979DB1DCE7CD1593"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subpart I of part III of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H62A11B831333470EAC28C21DA7A61A3C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><chapter id="HCE4FBEB210DD450DB78052D08757752F"><enum>104</enum><header>National Digital Reserve Corps</header><toc container-level="chapter-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HCE4FBEB210DD450DB78052D08757752F" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HD000469C8CDF4511B496E796C31AFFF9" level="section">10401. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H761ACA15A6E74F93BA85C8C035857B59" level="section">10402. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7A599AB1605C4C629ED17007F6F8F6E6" level="section">10403. Organization.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H06A1B7FFE4E64F4EAC11025E6FA28469" level="section">10404. Assignments.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBB57F25FE2944696931EDC5EE6597379" level="section">10405. Reservist continuing education.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDD165D34B9C6470AB2293141A694C087" level="section">10406. Congressional reports.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H557E2B11DE4A4342923A6050337244DD" level="section">10407. Construction.</toc-entry></toc><section id="HD000469C8CDF4511B496E796C31AFFF9"><enum>10401.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this chapter:</text><paragraph id="H6D6D835A31EF45E9820595EAA5CE9D10"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Active reservist</header><text>The term <term>active reservist</term> means a reservist holding a position to which such reservist has been appointed under section 10403(c)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H728AA71FB36149308998BC606D449A48"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the General Services Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8231000724C542A1A86C88E203DD2EB2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered Executive agency</header><text>The term <term>covered Executive agency</term> means an Executive agency as defined in section 105, except that such term includes the United States Postal Service, the Postal Regulatory Commission, and the Executive Office of the President.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DA25840E7E1416CA8661026A78EF83E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the program established under section 10402(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7610D1C30E9644F2B560C731D49E94BB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reservist</header><text>The term <term>reservist</term> means an individual who is a member of the National Digital Reserve Corps.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H761ACA15A6E74F93BA85C8C035857B59"><enum>10402.</enum><header>Establishment</header><subsection id="HA0A083E400FC4A34A70BB6CA48683446"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the General Services Administration a program to establish, recruit, manage, and assign a reserve of individuals with relevant skills and credentials, to be known as the <quote>National Digital Reserve Corps</quote>, to help address the digital and cybersecurity needs of covered Executive agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE780B9B25A6043A896B612DD9BEC2BCB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><paragraph id="HA855CBA11025494BABAFD91B1646B714"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, shall issue guidance for the National Digital Reserve Corps, which shall include procedures for coordinating with covered Executive agencies to—</text><subparagraph id="HFD7EA6DBF1E44601AED2C0B8584DF8CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify digital and cybersecurity needs which may be addressed by the National Digital Reserve Corps; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H207B1D2ADCA1410C9978DB1DAEE98058"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assign active reservists to address such needs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0743333FCDA4233902E0576B2223535"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recruitment and initial assignments</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator shall begin recruiting reservists and assigning active reservists under the Program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7A599AB1605C4C629ED17007F6F8F6E6"><enum>10403.</enum><header>Organization</header><subsection id="H2326005E1B414FD1AB4E6581C9E713E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="HA2D52FE750EB421FB5976CEE414F30E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The National Digital Reserve Corps shall be administered by the Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H679AF24F9D4E49E8BFC66A0BB051EFAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>In carrying out the Program, the Administrator shall—</text><subparagraph id="H73E1C542E29F47DC936B9435BEB6A02E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish standards for serving as a reservist, including educational attainment, professional qualifications, and background checks in accordance with existing Federal guidance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D0D108ED80D40649B357886C38FEEC3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure the standards established under subparagraph (A) are met;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC760F9A425F5473C9A470878627ED943"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recruit individuals to the National Digital Reserve Corps;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB087578DE7F84AC688CBBD8143F1D7F6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>activate and deactivate reservists as necessary;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD94FC0DBA752445AAF9B8F599304CDCF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>coordinate with covered Executive agencies to—</text><clause id="HF57D021A5C5049268B0E470FB9AD62D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine the digital and cybersecurity needs which reservists shall be assigned to address;</text></clause><clause id="HE9A8CB5A91704445BBAFD55232988530"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure active reservists have access, resources, and equipment required to address digital and cybersecurity needs which such reservists are assigned to address; and</text></clause><clause id="H74E084676BFF4F00A22ED240EE4347DE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>analyze potential assignments for reservists to determine outcomes, develop anticipated assignment timelines, and identify covered Executive agency partners;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53F13FC8A08245828FA9BBC1992507C0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>ensure reservists acquire and maintain appropriate security clearances; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF1813D992D7458781F512656F1AE2E6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>determine what additional resources, if any, are required to successfully implement the Program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95B8052206964A61AC20A53BD4A697BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National digital reserve corps participation</header><paragraph id="HFF24999F476847EB891D422AFB319719"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Service obligation agreement</header><subparagraph id="H0DB6F7AF6BAF423C8F673B8DAE6ACF20"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An individual may become a reservist only if such individual enters into a written agreement with the Administrator to become a reservist.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC6A1AC2D805444B804D3A35FA28F116"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contests</header><text>The agreement under subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="H05411782ACA94113B88FBAAB8EA392D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require the individual seeking to become a reservist to serve as a reservist for a 3-year period, during which such individual shall serve not less than 30 days per year as an active reservist; and</text></clause><clause id="H5B21D58907E2446AA63CBE73C6BD79F4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>set forth all other the rights and obligations of the individual and the General Services Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDB9A154B63D4BE2BCD87880877814DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>The Administrator shall determine the appropriate compensation for service as a reservist, except that the annual pay for such service shall not exceed $10,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H198D60A6778543328F08E226B299A122"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Employment protections</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall prescribe such regulations as necessary to ensure the reemployment, continuation of benefits, and nondiscrimination in reemployment of active reservists, provided that such regulations shall include, at a minimum, those rights and obligations set forth under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2715230FA81746A49DD2E7AD02269F2F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Penalties</header><subparagraph id="H4601977B80CB4B3D995AFCC59900B134"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A reservist that fails to accept an appointment under subsection (c)(2) or fails to carry out the duties assigned to a reservist under such an appointment shall, after notice and an opportunity to be heard—</text><clause id="HA596734AB933492E842C3F9AB503B97A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>cease to be a reservist; and</text></clause><clause id="H5E8AE1FA4210490E9EA14C6C0DB298FD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be fined an amount equal to the sum of—</text><subclause id="H97552F474E504EB8A9EECEB015145981"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an amount equal to the amounts, if any, paid under section 10405 with respect to such reservist; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA79FAF8F8A4047C3A48A9A06F4B0EAC2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the difference between the amount of compensation such reservist would have received if the reservist completed the entire term of service as a reservist agreed to in the agreement described in paragraph (1) and the amount of compensation such reservist has received under such agreement.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA204840677304EA0ABB295DE3D50053D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><clause id="HBA9BFB32CA4D4C6F9296EE60DCDC25E5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to a failure of a reservist to accept an appointment under subsection (c)(2) or to carry out the duties assigned to the reservist under such an appointment if—</text><subclause id="H443F5835BE314CC6AA5A9A61CCF7BB3B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the failure was due to the death or disability of such reservist; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HBF8445D0A5A74F048D4468AEC107ECEA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Administrator, in consultation with the head of the relevant covered Executive agency, determines that subparagraph (A) should not apply with respect to the failure.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H7E73BAA21F794CBA8F36AE7778F6E998"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Relevant covered Executive agency defined</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <quote>relevant covered Executive agency</quote> means—</text><subclause id="H05C2681AA90B4AA9A806C45B2FD207AB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a reservist failing to accept an appointment under subsection (c)(2), the covered Executive agency to which such reservist would have been appointed; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HBE70565DBCF5474193D90E48605ED1C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a reservist failing to carry out the duties assigned to such reservist under such an appointment, the covered Executive agency to which such reservist was appointed.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A0F7D4A812E4686A2224959D365E6C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Hiring authority</header><paragraph id="H80E9CCC4AE0B42E5BE00B120F141AE0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Corps leadership</header><text>The Administrator may appoint qualified candidates to positions in the competitive service in the General Service Administration for which the primary duties are related to the management or administration of the National Digital Reserve Corps, as determined by the Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74E05684B4164BBAA9C6C6A89151E1CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Corps reservists</header><subparagraph id="H9FFFBD7F8CF845E18BD1F6EF55D0643F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may appoint qualified reservists to temporary positions in the competitive service for the purpose of assigning such reservists under section 10404 and to otherwise carry out the National Digital Reserve Corps.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BC958EC710A4A85A1D7E8AC2A6D758B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointment limits</header><clause id="H773ADE053E5D442F897289F2E3C43305"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may not appoint an individual under this paragraph if, during the 365-day period ending on the date of such appointment, such individual has been an officer or employee of the executive or legislative branch of the United States Government, of any independent agency of the United States, or of the District of Columbia for not less than 130 days.</text></clause><clause id="HEE416582FFEE465AABD847405DBBE240"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Automatic appointment termination</header><text>The appointment of an individual under this paragraph shall terminate upon such individual being employed as an officer or employee of the executive or legislative branch of the United States Government, of any independent agency of the United States, or of the District of Columbia for 130 days during the previous 365 days.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H463F32FE331844B6968F7460DEB97FBB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Employee status</header><text>An individual appointed under this paragraph shall be considered a special Government employee (as such term is defined in section 202(a) of title 18).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68613C5AA4B8457E864C3275059434A3"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Conflict of interest</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Individuals appointed under this section shall not, as an active reservist, have access to proprietary or confidential information that is of commercial value to any private entity or individual employing such appointee.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF27279AFA4BD4CA1B79C4F4E2180041D"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Additional employees</header><text>Individuals appointed under this paragraph shall be in addition to any employees of the General Services Administration whose duties relate to the digital or cybersecurity needs of the General Services Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H06A1B7FFE4E64F4EAC11025E6FA28469"><enum>10404.</enum><header>Assignments</header><subsection id="H17BBF4F349F6402A946F2B4461F8B630"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may assign active reservists to address the digital and cybersecurity needs of covered Executive agencies, including cybersecurity services, digital education and training, data triage, acquisition assistance, guidance on digital projects, development of technical solutions, and bridging public needs and private sector capabilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9A2DF275833D45B48D3DAE95F9E693F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assignment-Specific access, resources, supplies, or equipment</header><text>The head of a covered Executive agency shall, to the extent practicable, provide each active reservist assigned to address a digital or cybersecurity need of such covered Executive agency under subsection (a) with any specialized access, resources, supplies, or equipment required to address such digital or cybersecurity need.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB819ED9E359E42FD9F9DA891642E066E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>An assignment of an individual under subsection (a) shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H2C90A3FA953243EEBCB05F73C4987B77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date determined by the Administrator;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H841A85B203A041FFB37B8982F640D81E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the Administrator receives notification of the decision of the head of the covered Executive agency, the digital or cybersecurity needs of which such individual is assigned to address under subsection (a), that such assignment should terminate; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B2385CE7B84443A84A3C95D04DF6BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the date on which the assigned individual ceases to be an active reservist.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HBB57F25FE2944696931EDC5EE6597379"><enum>10405.</enum><header>Reservist continuing education</header><subsection id="H25347EDADAC7490BA78595601C5A738A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Administrator may pay for reservists to acquire training and receive continuing education related to the duties assigned to such reservists pursuant to appointments under section 10403(c)(2), including attending conferences and seminars and obtaining certifications, that will enable reservists to more effectively meet the digital and cybersecurity needs of covered Executive agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC5F230F40CF14877A7B12A46E5EB3DB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Administrator shall establish a process for reservists to apply for the payment of reasonable expenses related to the training or continuing education described in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H96BCA00EDC03422DA39348DA4F498FE2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report on the expenditures under this subsection.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDD165D34B9C6470AB2293141A694C087"><enum>10406.</enum><header>Congressional reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report on the Program, including—</text><paragraph id="H66AC969126C548BDA06DBBCE2CDBAA9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of reservists;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C7E33DE8C749BD89AD926CBC3372BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a list of covered Executive agencies that have submitted requests for support from the National Digital Reserve Corps;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78FBF0BC3BAC4B9188B78AA556939C8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the nature and status of such requests; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB667DB4AB3F2429CB7D49A1310301A58"><enum>(4)</enum><text>with respect to each such request to which active reservists have been assigned and for which work by the National Digital Reserve Corps has concluded, an evaluation of such work and the results of such work by—</text><subparagraph id="HDFF026C20F9E4CE4BBCECC8FDE633821"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the covered Executive agency that submitted the request; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DEDDC1C940F4E23975BF19A0E15DCF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the reservists assigned to such request.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H557E2B11DE4A4342923A6050337244DD"><enum>10407.</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to abrogate or otherwise affect the authorities or the responsibilities of the head of any other Executive agency.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6B4B8B7B884042B3B48D6EA86CFBD0FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of chapters for part III of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item related to chapter 103 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H44DA1883381F40769C8FA8D63EEA7FBD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><multi-column-toc-entry level="section"><toc-enum>104.</toc-enum><level-header level="section">National Digital Reserve Corps</level-header><target>10401</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H410BA98206134F7B81DAE9B227ACBC27"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $30,000,000, to remain available until fiscal year 2024 to carry out the program established under section 10402(a) of title 5, United States Code, as added by this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H44F2764FA5BB416B91476B70B03E76AE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1142(b)(3) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>and the National Digital Reserve Corps</quote> after <quote>Selected Reserve</quote>.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

