<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H772F08F7BB8A43D58C981113C1955172" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1066 IH: Collecting and Analyzing Resources Integral and Necessary for Guidance for Social Determinants Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1066</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to issue and disseminate guidance to States to clarify strategies to address social determinants of health under the Medicaid program and the Children’s Health Insurance Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7FB7247D375D4A86830380CC695EA34C" style="OLC"><section id="H3A5CA6F89DD84EBEBB01325DD4B99F80" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Collecting and Analyzing Resources Integral and Necessary for Guidance for Social Determinants Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CARING for Social Determinants Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3593DE447BD142DB999E555E485DBD17"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement to issue guidance to clarify strategies to address social determinants of health in the Medicaid program and the Children’s Health Insurance Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, and not less frequently than once every 3 years thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall update the State Health Office letter 21–001, issued on January 7, 2021, to clarify strategies to address social determinants of health under the Medicaid program and the Children’s Health Insurance Program. Such update shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H8969B9FB4051451CBF0856FF4CF1E4EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Guidance to State Medicaid agencies regarding the strategies that States can implement under authorities in existence as of such update under title XIX of the Social Security Act, title XXI of such Act, or section 1115 of such Act to address social determinants of health in the provision of health care, including strategies specifically targeting children receiving medical assistance under a State plan under title XIX of such Act (or a waiver of such plan) or child health assistance under a State child health plan under title XXI of such Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65C41E93655B47FA8FED964C7A6A4653"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Guidance on how States can encourage and incentivize managed care entities to address social determinants of health through contracts with such entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H211E288BB66B44D7B39CE7A143DF1768"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Updated examples from States with respect to how States are addressing social determinants of health in the provision of health care under the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act and the Children’s Health Insurance Program under title XXI of such Act, including through payment models.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

