<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H67236B8C307A4BE2875E3D4BE828B738"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1353 RH: ALERT Parity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 25</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1353</legis-num> 
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–39]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230424">April 24, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction> 
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 3, 2023</action-instruction> 
<action-desc><pagebreak/></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Federal Communications Commission to issue rules for the provision of emergency connectivity service, and for other purposes.<pagebreak/></official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HA82F67210B9A4DE6BB355433EA5ABA37"> 
<section id="HF61017CAA1E646C5A18C456ACFACDBD8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advanced, Local Emergency Response Telecommunications Parity Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>ALERT Parity Act</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H33C6C8DC579A4EE196F81C5999691D7A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Emergency connectivity service</header> <subsection id="H82AFB0D463C54326A9D094F0776C4993"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rulemaking required</header> <paragraph id="H3DC1873C3978464188800A6994990665"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall issue rules for the provision of emergency connectivity service under which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5823B8FD4BDF40349C91296D6E28EE61"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person may submit to the Commission an application for approval to provide such service to an area—</text> <clause id="H464FB037797945C19EF6C9D8F3C5ACB1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is an unserved area with respect to either or both services described in subsection (i)(5)(B); or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H40508AAD0D2C45EFBF6B7D52D785C799"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the event that such area becomes an unserved area with respect to either or both such services due to destruction of infrastructure, a power outage, or any other reason; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E86B59D28C94F51A71C11D2445AC4D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any period during which such approval is in effect and such area is an unserved area, such person will receive access to electromagnetic spectrum in accordance with subsection (d) to provide emergency connectivity service to such area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H850CBB808A9342C89ABBA5A35FDD1316"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Provider not licensee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall include in the rules issued under paragraph (1) language to ensure that approval of an application to provide emergency connectivity service under such rules does not render the provider of such service a licensee (as such term is defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4562B2E045445F8B19CA26B9FEC3E2D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline to initiate rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall initiate a rulemaking to issue the rules required by paragraph (1) not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB02A08D77EC0447FAED959F435E73E6D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Demonstrations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the rules issued under subsection (a), the Commission shall require a person who submits an application to provide emergency connectivity service under such rules, in order for such application to be approved, to demonstrate to the Commission the following:</text> <paragraph id="H4F38C51CD742422A9708D78EE4CE1313"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such person has a technical proposal describing how such person plans to provide such service and how the proposal complies with technical requirements included in such rules under subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F4590BAC05643A799A423216654CD2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such person will not use any electromagnetic spectrum to which access is made available under such rules to provide any service other than emergency connectivity service, unless the other service is provided under a separate authorization to use such spectrum held by such person.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCE4D4BA2D83548FFA8FD584754B6D56D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such service proposed can withstand the impact of major natural disasters, such as earthquakes, hurricanes, wildfires, floods, blizzards, and tornados.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38C61387016740A39BAB6D169924E824"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such person has the capability to begin providing such service in a rapid manner—</text> <subparagraph id="H88915C486E3949B596CE4207808C0987"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of an application to provide such service to an area that is an unserved area at the time at which the application is submitted, after the approval of the application; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H168A161281D2464A88EA1F275318DD55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an application to provide such service to an area in the event that such area becomes an unserved area due to destruction of infrastructure, a power outage, or any other reason, after such area becomes an unserved area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB5924364B5CA458AAA4CE615035A1073"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication of list of providers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall publish on the internet website of the Commission a list of all providers of emergency connectivity service for which an approval is in effect to provide such service under the rules issued under subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6F8464BCE34C461A9A161FAE0C66CE1B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Access to electromagnetic spectrum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall include in the rules issued under subsection (a) the following:</text> <paragraph id="H6C1AABDD150B43B8B20E8742390382AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a provider of emergency connectivity service that is approved to provide such service to an area under such rules and that seeks access to spectrum that another entity is authorized to use, access to such spectrum shall be made available to such provider only if such provider receives voluntary express written consent for such access from such entity. An entity that receives a request for consent under this paragraph shall reasonably engage with the provider submitting the request and make a determination with respect to such request in a timely manner.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AD85F017770430FAC926431D1E06463"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to providers of emergency connectivity service that are approved to provide such service to an area under such rules, technical requirements applicable to such providers that ensure that the use of electromagnetic spectrum under a relevant approval does not cause harmful interference to the use of spectrum by another entity authorized to provide a service to such area or an adjacent geographic area.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEC9FBC9D05284F85924D97645C7A9F65"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Areas unserved with respect to both services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an area that is an unserved area with respect to both services described in subsection (i)(5)(B), the rules issued under subsection (a) shall require that, if a provider approved to provide emergency connectivity service to such area under such rules chooses to provide emergency connectivity service to such area, such provider shall provide both services described in subsection (i)(5)(B) to such area.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFD4B7406703644979BFF4D030E0B3AE2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation of liability</header> 
<paragraph id="HD995DB60575A497BA2A65F93D2A77251"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Transmission of alert messages</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 602(e)(1) of the Warning, Alert, and Response Network Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1201">47 U.S.C. 1201(e)(1)</external-xref>) shall apply to a provider of emergency connectivity service (including its officers, directors, employees, vendors, and agents) with respect to the provision of such service (to the extent such service consists of the provision of the service described in subsection (i)(5)(B)(i) of this section) in accordance with the rules issued under subsection (a) of this section, as if such provider were a provider of commercial mobile service that transmits emergency alerts and meets its obligations under such Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1565A1929F29439FBF84E4B3A56E9379"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Provision of 9–1–1 service</header> <subparagraph id="HF5559143E88244E8B52FDE4060EF8D53"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4 of the Wireless Communications and Public Safety Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/615a">47 U.S.C. 615a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H76E6D3C4319245519DB90CC89FB70575"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subclause id="HA116F7136160454E949D126954C6729E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>emergency connectivity service provider,</quote> after <quote>IP-enabled voice service provider,</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7E6C635A78944F9796FF660D11363B1E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>emergency connectivity service,</quote> after <quote>emergency services,</quote>;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H7A0E18BBAB70498AB9E3328CE6D7E617"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subclause id="HABA3941AAE1A4E1492C3E3C1FF7FA963"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>IP-enabled voice service or</quote> and inserting <quote>IP-enabled voice service, emergency connectivity service, or</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE664AA8C67244924BFBB62F4CEC4909E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>emergency connectivity service,</quote> after <quote>IP-enabled voice service,</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H0D2DCD4AF259474AAF598B76F37DB49D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by inserting <quote>emergency connectivity service,</quote> after <quote>IP-enabled voice service,</quote> each place it appears.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H267CCB0A19634C77B99080B052211BE7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 7 of the Wireless Communications and Public Safety Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/615b">47 U.S.C. 615b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAFB9E8379C004347BEDDCED5269A6449" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HD321AF2489F047D1A3D420F0D875978A"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Emergency connectivity service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>emergency connectivity service</term> has the meaning given such term in paragraph (5) of section 2(i) of the Advanced, Local Emergency Response Telecommunications Parity Act, to the extent such service consists of the provision of the service described in subparagraph (B)(ii) of such paragraph.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H28123C4F03544C74BF3E6BBEE6DC6539"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Emergency connectivity service provider</header><text>The term <term>emergency connectivity service provider</term> means a person who provides emergency connectivity service in accordance with the rules issued under section 2(a) of the Advanced, Local Emergency Response Telecommunications Parity Act.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD9229081D336490EB57161EB800D341C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission issues rules under subsection (a), and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report regarding the provision of emergency connectivity service under such rules, which shall include a description of—</text> <paragraph id="H43FAE0CEFED9411D81351E2169668274"><enum>(1)</enum><text>each instance during the preceding year that emergency connectivity service was provided under such rules; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF353980A525B411C88B613F747A4C021"><enum>(2)</enum><text>each instance during the preceding year that an entity authorized to use spectrum declined to provide, to a provider of emergency connectivity service, the consent described in subsection (d)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H944358F95E754832904D342F0445791E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H12D0611FAD2D4217B87924EEE049E144"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide the Commission with new authority to regulate the terms, conditions, or rates applicable to an agreement between 2 or more parties to facilitate the provision of emergency connectivity service;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF237A8583614B429ABC4BF7BDDE0641"><enum>(2)</enum><text>preclude the Commission, before it issues rules under subsection (a), from permitting the use of electromagnetic spectrum by a person that otherwise meets the requirements of this section; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC85557760A864176A84433B2D164F0F3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>preclude the Commission from approving an application to provide emergency connectivity service under the rules issued under subsection (a) that proposes using spectrum in a manner that is inconsistent with the Table of Frequency Allocations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H06D5BF98376A49BE9ADF8B8707C8F7A1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H87634AA5237645C3917DA2C68FD81FAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alert message</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>alert message</term> has the meaning given such term in section 10.10 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23933AB51BCA45A2B649FA854DC5E7C8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commercial mobile service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>commercial mobile service</term> has the meaning given such term in section 332(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/332">47 U.S.C. 332(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H895BDFE802F74BD6B97BACD4C4D79029"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC685A04F872A4868A123725BEF225811"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered device</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered device</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC73C963FF048456D948CCCE78A8373F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a mobile device; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF358E428C52B4ACB907191BDC36D68AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other device that is capable of—</text> 
<clause id="H43CEBA193F6240BCA7CC5B16BC167FED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receiving alert messages; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCF3FE56D11B44AD994AF5F4E82FCCE3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing emergency information to a public safety answering point (which may include enhanced 9–1–1 service).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD6BFA845BC774192BD5591503646F23B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Emergency connectivity service</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF4B1ECFB438F4C98BB3B611629DDBBD8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>emergency connectivity service</term> means a service—</text> <clause id="H5D5AE4A3D45B48CD9E5764E69AD542F8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to which covered devices are capable of connecting—</text> 
<subclause id="H9B61EE49629643D19C11E2C80B39E503"><enum>(I)</enum><text>without any technical capability specific to such service; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H47419EF38E374288A5858C5273C4A1B7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>regardless of whether commercial mobile service or any other service is initialized on the device; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H0DDE0B14E5024ECC95E3228CD36E9D4A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that consists only of the provision of a service described in subparagraph (B) to an area that is an unserved area with respect to such service.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6C65255A5EBA43F592A86F336B4DBB28"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Services described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The services described in this subparagraph are the following:</text> 
<clause id="H7252173C66C4462098FCED6223514B7D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Transmitting alert messages to covered devices.</text></clause> <clause id="HDD592BEF2EEF4BCDB40567B32EC70F5C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Providing emergency information from a covered device to a public safety answering point (which may include enhanced 9–1–1 service).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5BE61DF370B4FB9AC9AEB69487F1290"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Enhanced 9–1–1 service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>enhanced 9–1–1 service</term> has the meaning given such term in section 7 of the Wireless Communications and Public Safety Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/615b">47 U.S.C. 615b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB6B23F05D524548BF064449A6A507B2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Mobile device</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>mobile device</term> has the meaning given such term in section 10.10 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0B50FEEFCDCC4A45B75F21171F0FD94D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Public safety answering point</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public safety answering point</term> has the meaning given such term in section 7 of the Wireless Communications and Public Safety Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/615b">47 U.S.C. 615b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7B4949D6F7A42FDB69D85B236362ECB"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Table of frequency allocations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>table of frequency allocations</term> means the United States table of frequency allocations contained in section 2.106 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44B0A44F160E481F8F9531E203370F89"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Unserved area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>unserved area</term> means, with respect to a service described in paragraph (5)(B), an area that, due to lack of infrastructure, destruction of infrastructure, a power outage, or any other reason, has no provider of commercial mobile service that is capable of providing such service.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> <endorsement display="yes"> <action-date>April 24, 2023</action-date> <action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> </endorsement> </bill> 

