<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5044838044E94E7A9CE4CA086F3B23E9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4881 IH: To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to limit cost sharing for drugs under the Medicare program.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4881</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to limit cost sharing for drugs under the Medicare program.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB19BE3F66365494D88C86353C0EC471C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB953F8A459E94664937D13AFCFDB1DAA" commented="no" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Limitation on cost sharing to net price amount under Medicare part D</header> 
<subsection id="HC5DA59B7480747E0A2C93FEABB98B129" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1860D–2 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-102">42 U.S.C. 1395w–102</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA606122C991E444DB68E8D219460D040" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2B53116ED0FE4971AB2777909D4FB030"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>(8) and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(8), (9), and (10)</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFF1082DB19D2424B8AE5653D82D8A9A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (9)(B)(ii), by striking <quote>For a plan year</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to paragraph (10), for a plan year</quote>; and </text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5A99285A4C4F4F58A2D279293EED1BAD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8F8EE74EF954B86A996E71FABD0DA91"> <paragraph id="HBEE1CF4AE433463DB9B7E71A2AB42D6A" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Limitation on cost sharing to net price amount</header> <subparagraph id="HCB8EE8910DAE4367B4F7F137396173A0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a plan year beginning on or after January 1, 2027, the coverage provides benefits for a supply of a covered part D drug dispensed by a pharmacy, for costs in excess of the deductible specified in paragraph (1) and prior to an individual reaching the out-of-pocket threshold under paragraph (4), with cost-sharing for a month’s supply that does not exceed the average net price for such a supply of such drug during such plan year (or, if lower, the applicable cash price for such a supply of such drug so dispensed by such pharmacy).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H48390269400D43189E7924486010903F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> <clause id="HE098D18CEB8A48BEA6C1438E8CB64F36"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Applicable cash price</header><text>The term <quote>applicable cash price</quote> means, with respect to a supply of a covered part D drug dispensed by a pharmacy, the price that such pharmacy would charge for such supply of such drug dispensed to an individual without benefits for such drug under any Federal health care program (as defined in section 1128B), a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage (as such terms are defined in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act), or the program established under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/89">chapter 89</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA3AE50769DFF4F228D7EE78C0D964377"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Average net price</header><text>The term <quote>average net price</quote> means, with respect to a supply of a covered part D drug, a prescription drug plan, and a plan year, the average amount paid under such plan (including any amounts paid by an individual enrolled under such plan as cost sharing for such drug) as payment for such a supply of such drug dispensed during such year, less any rebates or other forms of remuneration received under such plan with respect to such drug.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0117721D0ADD46788657A6A58BE6D8F9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E2040D6A654413E9FA3072F73DC5191"> 
<paragraph id="HAB0E01983D1B49EEBF134752838673AE" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Cost sharing limited to net price</header><text>The coverage is provided in accordance with subsection (b)(10).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H948D453B909F45FC9CE2144D943BC402" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment to cost-Sharing for low-Income individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1860D–14(a)(1)(D)(iii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-114">42 U.S.C. 1395w–114(a)(1)(D)(iii)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>For plan year 2027 and subsequent plan years, the copayment amount applicable under this clause to a supply of a covered part D drug dispensed to the individual may not exceed the amount provided under section 1860D–2(b)(10).</quote>.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H92E1FE94A9154F70A481556B3841D89B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2029, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report containing—</text> <paragraph id="HF61C8B68DF9E451D954E269487A62A42"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of compliance with the amendments made by this section;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD4A1CA39BD54E4D811A9EF263B9C8C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of enforcement of such amendments; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB38329E3AB048D0A36905FCC546FB29"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations with respect to improving such enforcement; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H29BF5971A4B9416AA9655C8BC64BE169"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations relating to improving public disclosure, and public awareness of, the requirements of such amendments.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> </legis-body> </bill> 

