<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5DA1793E192846ECB1A302497312E653" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6672 IH: Marshall ‘Major’ Taylor Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6672</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal posthumously to Marshall Walter <quote>Major</quote> Taylor in recognition of his significance to the nation as an athlete, trailblazer, role model, and equal rights advocate.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H54743B9EAC954166B7611765D692F709" style="OLC"><section id="HC378C1F865414045BC7E2D7DF910E02C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the as the <quote><short-title>Marshall ‘Major’ Taylor Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDAB41F7D4A40478BB3BEE1FC8726D1CB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H2BED0876D020438FBD39B7D2EA139679"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Marshall Walter <quote>Major</quote> Taylor was born in Indianapolis, Indiana, on November 26, 1878, to Black parents who likely had been enslaved in Kentucky, and died impoverished on June 21, 1932, in a hospital charity ward in Chicago, Illinois.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC556E4FB7E04892B1F4FD323950893B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As a child, Taylor spent considerable time at the home of a wealthy White family in Indianapolis who employed his father as a coachman, treated the Black youngster as an equal to their son, Daniel Southard, and gave Taylor his first bicycle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF117DAF9CF3442394826B22A8FE1337"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Taylor acquired the nickname <quote>Major</quote> in his youth when he performed bicycle tricks outside his workplace, the Hay &amp; Willits bike shop in Indianapolis, while wearing a military-style jacket, and he won his first bike race in 1890 at age 11.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA24D766E64F849018A28991B9AD02DC8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Taylor moved to Worcester, Massachusetts, with his employer, mentor, and racing manager, Louis D. <quote>Birdie</quote> Munger, in 1895, and became known in his sport not only for his lightning sprints but also for his good sportsmanship, disciplined physical training, and devotion to his religion.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1549F13234CD4EAFAA6469AFE0C471D5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Taylor received a professional racing license from the League of American Wheelmen at age 18 despite the League’s 1894 <quote>whites only</quote> rule for amateur membership and made his professional debut in December 1896 in a six-day race at Madison Square Garden in New York, New York, defeating national champion Eddie Bald in a half-mile exhibition race on the eve of the six-day endurance contest and placing eighth in the six-day track cycling competition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBB8AD02542244A38BF42B359177BB1E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 1897, Taylor earned a spot alongside 4 White men on one of the first racially integrated professional sports teams in the nation, a five-man squad that won a Boston vs. Philadelphia pursuit race held in Cambridge, Massachusetts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H676744776A9B4C309FDA8D65AB4E97A1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Taylor set numerous world speed records and held 7 world records at the end of 1898 for various distances, including the coveted 1 mile, and he further lowered the 1-mile world record to 1 minute, 19 seconds in 1899.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD939CD51940C498C925F3FEC8DBF0E3F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Taylor overcame racial prejudice throughout his career, showing remarkable dignity in the face of closed doors and open hostility, including race-based denial of meals and lodging; racist cartoons and caricatures; bureaucratic maneuvers that threatened his racing eligibility; race-based exclusion from certain tracks and competitions on the national circuit; White opponents’ plots and tactics to box him in on the track, cause him to crash, or prevent him from competing in the first place; a post-race choking by a competitor on a racetrack in Taunton, Massachusetts, that left Taylor unconscious; White neighbors’ objections to his purchase of a house in Worcester; and a death threat signed <quote>White Riders</quote> that was delivered in Savannah, Georgia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AB00FD1B85840E1B04B5292BFE0BD7B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Taylor was one of the first Black athletes to secure corporate sponsorship, representing bicycle brands such as Iver Johnson, Sager, Stearns, and Orient, and he became one of the wealthiest Black men in America and a substantial benefactor to his church in Worcester.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E8779FC88B74998AFEB7BD50DA06A45"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Taylor pioneered the use of an innovative adjustable handlebar stem, using the extension to improve his aerodynamic position, and to this day this type of outrigger is called a Major Taylor stem.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BD5D65C876941508FB859D849B3E6ED"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Taylor won the world 1-mile sprint championship in Montreal on August 10, 1899, becoming the second Black athlete to win a world title in any sport, and won the United States championship later that year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1C00C9DC98E4146837CA8E03F0A90A0"><enum>(12)</enum><text>As a devout Christian, Taylor refused for years to race on Sundays, and accordingly he turned down lucrative offers to race in Europe, until, by virtue of his international superstardom, he could negotiate a <quote>no Sundays</quote> provision in a European racing contract for 1901.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFB3C5AE247347CB8F1E45318065B190"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Finding refuge in France, where he was still often the only Black racer on the track, Taylor defeated every European champion during the course of six tours of Europe from 1901 to 1909 and also had numerous racing successes in Australia and New Zealand.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05191C5BD4A7462BA2073962EE41F89E"><enum>(14)</enum><text>After retiring from racing in 1910 and finding little success in the business world, Taylor wrote his 1928 autobiography, <quote>The Fastest Bicycle Rider in the World,</quote> with an appeal for <quote>simple justice, equal rights, and a square deal</quote> for African Americans in sports and <quote>every … human endeavor,</quote> as well as advice for youth on good sportsmanship and clean living.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A782EACB75745C7B07E071B5C87F3A8"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Drawing on exemplary determination and perseverance, Taylor demonstrated not only dominant athletic prowess but also tremendous strength of character as he broke racial barriers, reached the pinnacle of international sport, and served as a role model for generations to come.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5762015A592742F6B5B4DEDDC6783015"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="HEF292F3DF5F74977831DD60EB922843C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the posthumous presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design in commemoration of Marshall Walter <quote>Major</quote> Taylor, in recognition of his significance to the nation as an athlete, trailblazer, role model, and equal rights advocate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD3EF34AEBB54B189FD8E83868EFA623"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the presentation referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary. The design shall bear an image of, and inscription of the name of Marshall Walter <quote>Major</quote> Taylor.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA68A7AF1C52B49729075A052CB8AE1BE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disposition of medal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to the great-granddaughter of Marshall Walter <quote>Major</quote> Taylor, Karen Donovan.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1CBE52E859EC4C8DA2A0A88A0E259DEC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3 at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses. </text></section><section id="H14027A79C57C4C39B1157F33804E206F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><subsection id="H353AB766B51F4DCDB8F9DCD61FF0AB23"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAA132A5A45A147D795609902FEAD6BEE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of section 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA7E3592E0AE7427BB688048D03BD77AA" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="H7F1E403711F449D481095ED8A78CD456"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck pursuant to this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1F333B853DC349658A10FB2EB40C3641"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>The amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

