<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H132F2D83A9894B458D6E7FE286E13D2B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1102 IH: UNRWA Accountability and Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1102</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To withhold United States contributions to the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East (UNRWA), and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFC696957E01C46098D0F874FBB51F54E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H20582C137E9A47EEA059EC0C5EE29509" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>UNRWA Accountability and Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HEDDC8ADD251F4CC8AF81F5167E888DA7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header> <subsection id="H60FA31B498904F5184756AC609113DC3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Palestinian refugee defined</header><text>It shall be the policy of the United States, in matters concerning the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East (referred to in this Act as <quote>UNRWA</quote>), which operates in Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, the Gaza Strip, and the West Bank, to define a Palestinian refugee as a person who—</text>
<paragraph id="H8BF1BCED864745C8AC3692D1C0D97A1B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>resided, between June 1946 and May 1948, in the region controlled by Britain between 1922 and 1948 that was known as Mandatory Palestine;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C3A23851AC14524B973D8046C307821"><enum>(2)</enum><text>was personally displaced as a result of the 1948 Arab-Israeli conflict; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0C4B40FA649A45D6A3396F89F45AB58C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>has not accepted an offer of legal residency status, citizenship, or other permanent adjustment in status in another country or territory.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5AF3FE33940A4403800EF9B461F7EEB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations on refugee and derivative refugee status</header><text>In applying the definition under subsection (a) with respect to refugees receiving assistance from UNRWA, it shall be the policy of the United States, consistent with the definition of refugee in section 101(a)(42) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(42)</external-xref>) and the requirements for eligibility for refugee status under section 207 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>), that—</text>
<paragraph id="H5833675E99974586B6C0A2CD74AC8055"><enum>(1)</enum><text>derivative refugee status may only be extended to the spouse or a minor child of a Palestinian refugee; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6128436823A94ACEAF02BAED77F3C828"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an alien who is firmly resettled in any country is not eligible to retain refugee status.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HC3D6FFCE97FF40D0BFFE2FC5B1E3E860"><enum>3.</enum><header>United States contributions to UNRWA</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 301(c) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2221">22 U.S.C. 2221</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA27F0C2559644DD9670039C31552F87"> <subsection id="H78BE15C8FB144F6782181DBAEFA6677B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Withholding</header> <paragraph id="H0A60E2A6435C455BBFACB88DCED87647"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text>
<subparagraph id="H5BB66E67547B4508A40F12D7757DFF46"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Anti-semitic</header><text>The term <term>anti-Semitic</term>—</text> <clause id="HBC8F4284D76E42548479445D49B03D5E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the meaning adopted on May 26, 2016, by the International Holocaust Remembrance Alliance as the non-legally binding working definition of antisemitism; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H1E72B7C0FF114BFDA67AD3CEC4D82B02"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes the contemporary examples of antisemitism in public life, the media, schools, the workplace, and in the religious sphere identified on such date by the International Holocaust Remembrance Alliance.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6C5EDB788D034FA2BD060872DB55AA34"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<clause id="HC9F01B0AC0FB44E797C4F03572E0D86F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></clause> <clause id="H932D593568D340DABC8B63474BCC8A5B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></clause>
<clause id="HFBA7D2EA363341E2963F4A1F3E15353C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and </text></clause> <clause id="H9F334CAF1E0840528DF35B17E0203DA8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name>.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC843320F40324228BDCB70847E5CBBF3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Boycott of, divestment from, and sanctions against israel</header><text>The term <term>boycott of, divestment from, and sanctions against Israel</term> has the meaning given to such term in section 909(f)(1) of the Trade Facilitation and Trade Enforcement Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/4452">19 U.S.C. 4452(f)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8FB18B9FC559463BAC7CE9AE4BC78A45"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Foreign terrorist organization</header><text>The term <term>foreign terrorist organization</term> means an organization designated as a foreign terrorist organization by the Secretary of State in accordance with section 219(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB55ECFAF4CAC4F1582442644F6461F9E"><enum>(E)</enum><header>UNRWA</header><text>The term <term>UNRWA</term> means the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2E733F71EAD4C7882D2CAEC70ABD806"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the United States may not provide contributions to UNRWA, to any successor or related entity, or to the regular budget of the United Nations for the support of UNRWA or a successor entity (through staff positions provided by the United Nations Secretariat or otherwise) unless the Secretary of State submits a written certification to the appropriate congressional committees that— </text>
<subparagraph id="HF395202AF60D49B894A64B05E27D94C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>no official, employee, consultant, contractor, subcontractor, representative, affiliate of UNRWA, an UNRWA partner organization, or an UNRWA contracting entity pursuant to completion of a thorough vetting and background check process—</text> <clause id="H9C92C191F6F14FB1A845B1677455CEE2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a member of, is affiliated with, or has any ties to a foreign terrorist organization, including Hamas and Hezbollah;</text></clause>
<clause id="H22140D0B67994BE28F79D4A8A08655AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has advocated, planned, sponsored, or engaged in any terrorist activity;</text></clause> <clause id="H1D0BEE6B348C43D8B58A9102E7EFD442"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has propagated or disseminated anti-American, anti-Israel, or anti-Semitic rhetoric, incitement, or propaganda, including—</text>
<subclause id="H26743597397949C58E8D8B89763F39B3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>calling for or encouraging the destruction of Israel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H59A2F5B44FDF40009176B99DC05F2D55"><enum>(II)</enum><text>failing to recognize Israel’s right to exist;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H0D4E0042DF4B4AF8B71BBDFFDF7802EF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>showing maps without Israel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5725360E3C1C45E18B5DC381177B660B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>describing Israelis as <quote>occupiers</quote> or <quote>settlers</quote>;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB8D15275A56E4E0184055526975FEEAF"><enum>(V)</enum><text>advocating, endorsing, or expressing support for violence, hatred, jihad, martyrdom, or terrorism, glorifying, honoring, or otherwise memorializing any person or group that has advocated, sponsored, or committed acts of terrorism, or providing material support to terrorists or their families;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H569D6081A3E24E738CFEE4721FBA4239"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>expressing support for boycott of, divestment from, and sanctions against Israel (commonly referred to as <quote>BDS</quote>);</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB9F0605D7DED4397B03094E3CB766C06"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>claiming or advocating for a <quote>right of return</quote> of refugees into Israel;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6948535645CF4F9D842527A7A7C9C562"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>ignoring, denying, or not recognizing the historic connection of the Jewish people to the land of Israel; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC3D3E68DD7B142BAB3FE4436255AE98A"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>calling for violence against Americans; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8FBB44437AFA4D9485E6C0BE557134B4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has used any UNRWA resources, including publications, websites, or social media platforms, to propagate or disseminate anti-American, anti-Israel, or anti-Semitic rhetoric, incitement, or propaganda, including with respect to any of the matters described in subclauses (I) through (IX) of clause (iii);</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H30B620C78EB44B5CBFC39E6E8184FA7A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>no UNRWA school, hospital, clinic, facility, or other infrastructure or resource is being used by a foreign terrorist organization or any member thereof—</text> <clause id="H3108457C6C3B4CB2AF6C7118F54BA874"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for terrorist activities, such as operations, planning, training, recruitment, fundraising, indoctrination, communications, sanctuary, storage of weapons or other materials; or </text></clause>
<clause id="HA88941ECBF444F46A26ECC97B1A37A5E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>as an access point to any underground tunnel network, or any other terrorist-related purposes;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFB5ED24EA2147C88999020E7DDDC943"><enum>(C)</enum><text>UNRWA is subject to comprehensive financial audits by an internationally recognized third party independent auditing firm that—</text>
<clause id="HA368915F664E46188C77156E6220B17B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is agreed upon by the Government of Israel and the Palestinian Authority; and </text></clause> <clause id="HF6A33985E7D648C5A7465E3B0FCA386B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has implemented an effective system of vetting and oversight to prevent the use, receipt, or diversion of any UNRWA resources by any foreign terrorist organization or members thereof;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H64FB0FDA6D9E4012B39D2031037413FD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>no UNRWA controlled or funded facility, such as a school, an educational institution, or a summer camp, uses textbooks or other educational materials that propagate or disseminate anti-American, anti-Israel, or anti-Semitic rhetoric, incitement, or propaganda, including with respect to any of the matters described in subclauses (I) through (IX) of subparagraph (A)(iii);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H04D85536E10A4403AD96484F160B6EC3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>no recipient of UNRWA funds or loans is—</text>
<clause id="H4A1DA3DE52E24EE6AB92C56B28B1F8BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a member of, is affiliated with, or has any ties to a foreign terrorist organization; or </text></clause> <clause id="H6A7A1DEDD3FD469B89C59A6B7BA89792"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>otherwise engaged in terrorist activities; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF29055FD1751407EACD7C80F6BF97146"><enum>(F)</enum><text>UNRWA holds no accounts or other affiliations with financial institutions that the United States considers or believes to be complicit in money laundering and terror financing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA7A14B6D9A3F4794B369B657495C11AF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Period of effectiveness</header> <subparagraph id="H2B959EF46BAD44DEAEE177E3290FB666"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A certification described in paragraph (2) shall be effective until the earlier of—</text>
<clause id="HFB16BF79F66A469B83B9A4827B63F98E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the Secretary receives information rendering the certification described in paragraph (2) factually inaccurate; or</text></clause> <clause id="H6D6057B2983843EEB0596A433CEA2FD3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date that is 180 days after the date on which it is submitted to the appropriate congressional committees.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8DF60A4D5FBF441CB2D8B6C942554CEF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notification of renunciation</header><text>If a certification becomes ineffective pursuant to subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall promptly notify the appropriate congressional committees of the reasons for renouncing or failing to renew such certification.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H87F62149A9814090B48647DA8DFB3281"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>During any year in which a certification described in paragraph (1) is in effect, the United States may not contribute to UNRWA, or to any successor entity, an amount that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H2D3CE5B472464CF3BCCEAE51614B7895"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is greater than the highest contribution to UNRWA made by a member country of the League of Arab States for such year; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBE4E36DD7F5745229B1A8048BBF3B087"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is greater (as a proportion of the total UNRWA budget) than the proportion of the total budget for the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees paid by the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H1AD3450185A749DBBF5E5D468836F136"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header>
<subsection id="H205BFBBF37CB4117B39AA094BA202B29"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H0A729F3F5C164217801C9E13098D07F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68306378FD1A45B1B1426E51A91ABECC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01954A4B4373463FA683919717BF54E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3E33D754C8E040608B4E619588EE7D73"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name>. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7D6E3D6A191E48DCBCB45F619753D8F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees describing the actions being taken to implement a comprehensive plan for—</text>
<paragraph id="HFF08590C9E3141FCB7FDDB4F10021959"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encouraging other countries to adopt the policy regarding Palestinian refugees that is described in section 2;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H20ABC5B175EA4C02905CFB3C61B1A180"><enum>(2)</enum><text>urging other countries to withhold their contributions to UNRWA, to any successor or related entity, or to the regular budget of the United Nations for the support of UNRWA or a successor entity (through staff positions provided by the United Nations Secretariat or otherwise) until UNRWA has met the conditions listed in subparagraphs (A) through (F) of section 301(c)(2) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as added by section 3;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H14698311AB1B4D59B536144480EF2D4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>working with other countries to phase out UNRWA and assist Palestinians receiving UNRWA services by—</text> <subparagraph id="H3A38785D0314437BAEAE65733CD73C1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>integrating such Palestinians into their local communities in the countries in which they are residing; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23727A2A4B7141F399BD2DEEF8977D01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>resettling such Palestinians in countries other than Israel or territories controlled by Israel in the West Bank in accordance with international humanitarian principles; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49266D97662449ECBE125DA935705D47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensuring that the actions described in paragraph (3)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF8FB7DFE6E484075B7101E0B45046252"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are being implemented in complete coordination with, and with the support of, Israel; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF149958745D34B0DAFB75407362C8643"><enum>(B)</enum><text>do not endanger the security of Israel in any way.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

