<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB4F9349E1D4343A08D5D3E1EBDBF01F3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 826 IH: Supply Chain Security and Resilience Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 826</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a National Resilience Center of Excellence in the Department of Commerce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H572757B5F281422CAD2C9FA8D824A2EF" style="OLC"><section id="H5F2E4032FC8942EBA39B6583B77A4414" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supply Chain Security and Resilience Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3B1895876F4A4AC4AF353FEA2F6C09A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Resilience Center of Excellence</header><subsection id="H7282E0AB36BA4548AD1C8ED13FDAE1A3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Office of the Secretary of Commerce a Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office to carry out the activities described in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB09BAAE044DD4C4397647DED7E91DD77"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Office shall be the following:</text><paragraph id="HD920D35447254D70BD8AE4FCC48C692D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Help to promote the leadership of the United States with respect to critical industries and supply chains that—</text><subparagraph id="H1DB28929098B45F9989AC5B260B84E93"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strengthen the national security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5595FEF89D344B58B96D2FB40DB2FAE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a significant effect on the economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7E6818C7A2F4A0CA3B52CBBC7E4F2EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Encourage partnerships and collaboration with the Federal Government and the private sector, labor organizations, the governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States, State governments and political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments in order to—</text><subparagraph id="H96B5541A84D54CA0AA27C5167356B287"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote the resilience of supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25EE86811DAA40CA91A60F3722D62BE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>respond to supply chain shocks to—</text><clause id="HA52ED234BFAF4F1BA263BD0FB860D3C7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical industries; and</text></clause><clause id="HD38A27138BE44E53BD507E094B08DBBF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supply chains.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8B9339880FE4CD1BAA43FFC9D4C77DF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Monitor the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains and critical industries, including by—</text><subparagraph id="H4B7028EF2336443ABA4F96B18F173375"><enum>(A)</enum><text>monitoring the financial and operational conditions of domestic manufacturers and domestic enterprises;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79C5628C4A24478189BE5BA11343C5A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>performing stress tests for critical industries, supply chains, domestic enterprises, and domestic manufacturers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13CB185181F941738F35765C408939FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>monitoring the demand and supply of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFD95D552D994AF08344E4CBA13D3B84"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Support the development, maintenance, improvement, competitiveness, restoration, and expansion of the productive capacities, efficiency, and workforce of critical industries and domestic manufacturers of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81FC6AEF896A4874BCA009F8BD64B40C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Prepare for and take appropriate steps to minimize the effects of supply chain shocks on critical industries and supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB54DCAE4E28947C4A371DBC6892AD89D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Support the creation of jobs with competitive wages in the manufacturing sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB196AFAA95B9430BB5793F2A6309DDF9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Encourage manufacturing growth and opportunities in economically distressed areas and communities of color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30A645B19FB541738F933B8584FA2DF3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Promote the health of the economy of the United States and the competitiveness of manufacturing in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1E3208B23804B2EB2B6B41B6A80C1D7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Coordinate executive branch actions necessary to carry out the functions described in paragraphs (1) through (8).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB94B0F6196AD40F4819E78BCD67790CD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Under Secretary of the Office</header><paragraph id="HA4DD612198C64BC59444B29A81CC86B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment and term</header><text>The head of the Office shall be the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response, appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, for a term of not more than 5 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74F10096F9154438A06B990391ACAD3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pay</header><text>The Under Secretary shall be compensated at the rate in effect for level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20939E4C4FAC4D01BB26C65AA154F053"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative authorities</header><text>The Under Secretary may appoint officers and employees in accordance with chapter 51 and subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC6EF535A8F054BC39310B8934EDB070F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall, on an ongoing basis, facilitate and support the development of a voluntary set of standards, guidelines, best practices, management strategies, methodologies, procedures, and processes for domestic manufacturers and entities manufacturing, purchasing, or using a critical good or service to—</text><paragraph id="HCE9FF1B0732943F2ADB0224BC46C42AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>measure the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3054F0D1D2DC4DE3A4CE203E6CA1AC4B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the value of the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B111CE9C369400CB0096368571A3115"><enum>(3)</enum><text>design organizational processes and incentives to reduce the risks of disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a supply chain.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H182A7B50F2AE4B18A280FC73206BC23A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out subsection (d), the Under Secretary shall do the following:</text><paragraph id="HD8F01403551E48CAADF35C58FB6D4F57"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinate closely and regularly with relevant private sector personnel and entities, manufacturing extension centers established as part of the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership, Manufacturing USA institutes as described in section 34(d) of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278s">15 U.S.C. 278s(d)</external-xref>), and other relevant stakeholders and incorporate industry expertise.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H195ABA79ED9E487F89C5E3C9C44F721F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Consult with the head of any relevant Federal agency, including those with jurisdiction over supply chains, State and local governments, Tribal governments, the governments of other nations, and international organizations, as necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D6505EC73F145918B9765601E2D9C40"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Identify a prioritized, flexible, repeatable, performance-based, and cost-effective approach that may be voluntarily adopted by domestic manufacturers and entities purchasing or using a critical good or service to help them—</text><subparagraph id="HC00C8F9153F045AABE147A60449CAFE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify, assess, and manage risks to supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE612C376B7054CA497970EAAAF7CAA28"><enum>(B)</enum><text>value the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of their supply chain.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F7EECBC69B941C7BA104E718D259A70"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Design voluntary processes for selecting suppliers that support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0783625605BB4782B9A9CC1F271B1943"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Include methodologies to identify and mitigate the effects of a disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a supply chain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1540B0B5743F483BB6E4A2F954382895"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Disseminate research and information to assist domestic manufacturers redesign products, expand manufacturing capacity, and improve capabilities to meet domestic needs for critical goods and services and supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6A72898DD0D41E7A528DA2EDE51D5A1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Incorporate relevant voluntary standards and industry best practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72B6DF66724C4A01B6A15227E25B8CE6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Consider small business concerns.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8C82C32DA3A4D6A942656472B0EC4A1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Any other elements the Under Secretary determines to be necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD74EC2906C28454583E977BF7C2EF16E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Office $500,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, for the Under Secretary to carry out this section, of which not more than 2 percent per fiscal year may be used for administrative costs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE32821D459F34DAAAC348C531695E055"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD64F3CA7509A49778B6A4ABE88DEBA18"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical good or service</header><text>The term <quote>critical good or service</quote> means any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including any mineral, metal, or advanced processed material), article, commodity, supply, product, or item of supply the absence of which would have a significant effect on—</text><subparagraph id="H4D8A8CFC582E4954AAD9A25DE6945548"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the national security or economic security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FD16BA9C246416D93EB85DE2147FCF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB9472784219420DB8764EA56F1DB6F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Domestic enterprise</header><text>The term <quote>domestic enterprise</quote> means an enterprise that conducts business in the United States and procures a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF81B0E6225554E8B9086202B7E997302"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Domestic manufacturer</header><text>The term <quote>domestic manufacturer</quote> means a business that—</text><subparagraph id="HDAAAB61A56564E318D5FA288A50AEEE0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducts in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0C687740F2245BE9A94E79C4FEF2B75"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if provided financial assistance by the Federal Government, will conduct in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B987BE0F1FA4C5EA9CB4E591D96EC29"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <quote>Federal agency</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>agency</quote> in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BFAD48F9E5E4C898EAB55ED50B21C09"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <quote>Office</quote> means the Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office established under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CCF99B257134D6CA8C3281F3619EB29"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text>The term <quote>small business concern</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 3(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E0D7B38513F4C9BAA47B96177237AF1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain</quote> means a supply chain for a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD065C67B71D94F668456F55461F142BF"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Under Secretary</quote> means the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response appointed pursuant to subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

