<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H820F335321094CA2A55201F6BEC9BE5E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 464 IH: Separation of Powers Restoration Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 464</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001184">Mr. Massie</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To restore the separation of powers between the Congress and the President.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H1F235E0B6CD443258C5A4EE47859ABBF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H94E122ADF63C45C0B3E8A76E327E7267" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Separation of Powers Restoration Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H53B5AC5CC3A549C6B367A49AF769E565"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H23E462DEB2D84FE7A5920F33E3BACF5C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>As a limit on governmental power, constitutional framers vested Federal powers in three coequal branches of government, each with unique and limited powers and each with a coequal duty to uphold and sustain the Constitution of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF707D194F46A4F8DAE1D38A0796C3B32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A Supreme Court justice stated, <quote>The doctrine of the separation of powers was adopted by the convention of 1787 not to promote efficiency but to preclude the exercise of arbitrary power. The purpose was not to avoid friction, but, by means of the inevitable friction incident to the distribution of the governmental powers among three departments, to save the people from autocracy.</quote> Myers v. United States, 272 U.S. 52, 293 (1926) (Brandeis, J., dissenting).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB9DC75F39F1E4048B8339CEE30851FDB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>James Madison, quoting Montesquieu, stated in Federalist 47, <quote>There can be no liberty where the legislative and executive powers are united in the same person, or body of magistrates.</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FB624F4DD884D95A0CB07BB8F5796BC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Article I of the Constitution provides, <quote>All legislative powers herein granted shall be vested in a Congress of the United States.</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE22141AE82FE4BCD90680C327B2DC29B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A congressional committee print has noted that, <quote>[b]ecause the President has no power or authority over individual citizens and their rights except where he is granted such power and authority by a provision in the Constitution or by statute, the President’s proclamations are not legally binding and are at best hortatory unless based on such grants of authority.</quote> 85th Cong., 1st Sess., Executive Orders and Proclamations: A Study of a Use of Presidential Powers (Comm. Print 1957).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9726E7ADFD84BF59FE24EDF373E6518"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Supreme Court has stated that, even if Presidents have, without congressional authority, taken actions only the Congress may take, <quote>Congress has not thereby lost its exclusive constitutional authority to make laws necessary and proper to carry out the powers vested by the Constitution <quote>in the Government of the United States, or any Department or Officer thereof.</quote></quote>. (Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube Co. v. Sawyer, 343 U.S. 579 (1952)).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCBCF5F5A8CB46B5913AA605DE62700A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Treaties or executive agreements which purport to assign powers not amongst those specifically granted to the Federal Government by the Constitution are non-binding and cannot constitute law.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H719644ACB68D40B9AF0EA3A449F1EE90"><enum>3.</enum><header>Separation of powers restoring rescissions</header> <subsection id="H64A84E28501D4C4BAD353019EB7502E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repeal of war powers resolution</header><text>The War Powers Resolution (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1541">50 U.S.C. 1541 et seq.</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H33ECB2D2AD40468DADF4F418F3E56685"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination of states of emergency</header> 
<paragraph id="H91E17D322446429C866C335FD0D1DD5A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All powers and authorities possessed by the President, any other officer or employee of the Federal Government, or any executive agency (as defined in section 105 of title 5) as a result of the existence of any declaration of national emergency in effect on the date of enactment of this Act are terminated 90 days after such date. Such termination shall not affect—</text> <subparagraph id="H83BA12F31E3245B9A8669DAA5104400E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any action taken or proceeding pending not finally concluded or determined on such date;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2E270F5F2173467B9032414018108E77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any action or proceeding based on any act committed prior to such date; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9DF8A88B42F0412196CC1264EB1D53B0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any rights or duties that matured or penalties that were incurred prior to such date.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8851FF25A942466B9F4B1856853E7C6E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For the purpose of this subsection, the term <quote>national emergency</quote> means a general declaration of emergency made by the President or any other officer or employee of the executive branch.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0566AAE1BC834DF59D7AD8F07D5354E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination of authority To declare emergency</header><text>To the extent that any Act of Congress in effect on the date of enactment of this Act grants to the President or any other officer or employee of the executive branch the power to declare a national emergency, such power is hereby divested to the Congress alone.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8458FCC01FC041E183EC883358EBAD22"><enum>4.</enum><header>Requirement of statement of authority for presidential orders</header> 
<subsection id="H34849602E51745CDA7C3427092D91293"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of authority</header><text>The President shall include with each Presidential order a statement of the specific statutory or constitutional provision which in fact grants the President the authority claimed for such action.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8EFBAFFEF3284E81ADFFDA89DFB82DE2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Invalidity of nonconforming orders</header><text>A Presidential order which does not include the statement required by subsection (a) is invalid, to the extent such Presidential order is issued under authority granted by a congressional enactment.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H3689778107A044E2BDECDCA13B29E0FB"><enum>5.</enum><header>Effect of presidential orders</header> 
<subsection id="H4AFA363A42304BD2B9F0F107E0C02F64"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limited effect of presidential orders</header><text>A Presidential order neither constitutes nor has the force of law and is limited in its application and effect to the executive branch.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBFF9A4C783F445F39B8C06592852DA27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Subsection (a) does not apply to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCA8CF37194324CDDA4EE68BCB9A91D63"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a reprieve or pardon for an offense against the United States, except in cases of impeachment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D4F6FFF08FF42F7A8537D830730AB69"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an order given to military personnel pursuant to duties specifically related to actions taken as Commander in Chief of the Armed Forces; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64FAE38DD1434A0AAED85A5425600E89"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a Presidential order citing the specific congressional enactment relied upon for the authority exercised in such order and—</text> <subparagraph id="H03ACCC170B7748F693DBEA751BF1CD2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issued pursuant to such authority;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFDAA1DEC83B045A386A5C3CC30927CF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>commensurate with the limit imposed by the plain language of such authority; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H124ABD0ACD104643BFB0ECA6610443A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not issued pursuant to a ratified or unratified treaty or bilateral or multilateral agreement which—</text> 
<clause id="H2EE42EB56A8C4677B8AE8A9B63C7C565"><enum>(i)</enum><text>violates the ninth or tenth amendments to the Constitution; or</text></clause> <clause id="H4114CCBDD77A4FF6ACF330599C11C370"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>makes a delegation of power to a foreign government or international body when no such delegating authority exists under the Constitution.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCCF82C4E9D35492E953BE57B13425812"><enum>6.</enum><header>Standing to challenge presidential orders which impact separation of powers integrity</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The following persons may bring an action in an appropriate United States court to challenge the validity of any Presidential order which exceeds the power granted to the President by the relevant authorizing statute or the Constitution:</text> <paragraph id="H09C44A87AEC2444E97E4A6BE2BCFF2BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Congress and its members</header><text>The House of Representatives, the Senate, any Senator, and any Representative to the House of Representatives, if the challenged Presidential order—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB3E37D0ED8AF4111BB2383968E52681E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>infringes on any power of Congress;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35BD150A7797405AA898C504515646F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>exceeds any power granted by a congressional enactment; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA2F9E4F34BF14109A2E24AF7045C98C0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>violates section 4 because it does not state the statutory authority which in fact grants the President the power claimed for the action taken in such Presidential order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1CF2F4DF741145CF81C9B9C58FF04171"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State and local governments</header><text>The highest governmental official of any State, commonwealth, district, territory, or possession of the United States, or any political subdivision thereof, or the designee of such person, if the challenged Presidential order infringes on the powers afforded to the States under the Constitution.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H29E548B7CF5C4580AF481129A9EC81C8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Aggrieved persons</header><text>Any person aggrieved in a liberty or property interest adversely affected directly by the challenged Presidential order.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H573D3A20821843E890D7D400B7DD7A32"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definition of presidential order</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> In this Act, the term <quote>Presidential order</quote> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB17633DEE9D1461E83C5715BB8A242ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any Executive order, Presidential proclamation, or Presidential directive; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2E736B6B52248BC97C2280B648B94C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other Presidential or Executive action by whatever name described purporting to have normative effect outside the executive branch which is issued under the authority of the President or any other officer or employee of the executive branch.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


