<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE5874B77A6824037AB70831652ACD1B0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>103 HR 4392 IH: PrEP Access and Coverage Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4392</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230627">June 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase access to pre-exposure prophylaxis to reduce the transmission of HIV.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEC50184820084266A2B0D1F1805FB3BB" style="OLC"><section id="H9C974BEB4D9B4A17BD8523C26086F818" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>PrEP Access and Coverage Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H61C9E13F51CE47CCA7DC480BB4654691"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="HB34474C7BDA14C4295FBA6DDDE02178F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HAF4F1C7946254F239DDA8A08A7412290"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention estimates that approximately 1,200,000 individuals in the United States are living with HIV.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9C6F77ACF944FA9BE0159DD6983C869"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 2021, there were 36,136 new diagnoses of HIV in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F97CE0F41524EE1A68E9F742624EBD1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>HIV disproportionately impacts gay and bisexual men, transgender women, and, in particular, people of color. In 2021, approximately 71 percent of new HIV diagnoses were estimated to be among gay and bisexual men, 40 percent of new HIV diagnoses were among Black people, and 29 percent of new HIV diagnoses were among Latinx people. Recent studies suggest that transgender women are up to 49 times more likely to be diagnosed with HIV than the general population. Members of communities at the intersections of these groups are most heavily impacted.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA89BDAD131AC4D829E2ED378CDB56BEC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Pre-exposure prophylaxis (referred to in this section as <quote>PrEP</quote>) is a daily antiretroviral medication that helps prevent individuals from acquiring HIV. Daily PrEP use reduces the risk of getting HIV from sex by more than 99 percent. It reduces the risk of getting HIV from injection drug use by at least 74 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37B31E66E9B4419EA263A6C353815D7D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Many individuals at risk of exposure to HIV do not use PrEP. Of the approximately 1,200,000 individuals in the United States who could benefit from PrEP, only 31 percent, or 382,364 individuals, filled prescriptions for the drug in 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H944F5AADD87D4E28975CF1E04946445D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>PrEP usage is inconsistent across racial and gender lines. In 2022, only 11 percent of Black/African American and 21 percent of Hispanic/Latinx individuals who were eligible for PrEP were prescribed it, compared to 82 percent of eligible White individuals. PrEP usage is low among women, in particular among heterosexual women of color, slightly less than 12 percent of women eligible for PrEP received a prescription in 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA89B704D2574B619EBF3DC4A162AE84"><enum>(7)</enum><text>PrEP use helps strengthen families by allowing couples with partners of different HIV statuses to prevent the transmission of HIV. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6CB1C5620044CD48C9035E099BB73FE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>There are currently 2 brand name drugs and 1 generic drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the use of PrEP on a daily basis. A long-acting injectable PrEP drug has also been approved by the Food and Drug Administration. Other types of HIV prevention treatments, including other long-acting injectables, long-acting oral pills, implants, and vaginal rings are in the research pipeline. These innovations can increase widespread use of PrEP along with adherence, which can speed the Nation’s goal to end HIV and address inequities in health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B258E51337B4972A8EC5699F408DC52"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Section 2713 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-13">42 U.S.C. 300gg–13</external-xref>) requires non-grandfathered private health insurance plans to cover preventive services without cost-sharing, including such services with a rating of <quote>A</quote> or <quote>B</quote> under recommendations of the United States Preventive Services Task Force. On June 11, 2019, the United States Preventive Services Task Force issued a final recommendation giving an <quote>A</quote> grade for PrEP for individuals at high risk of HIV; non-grandfathered private health insurance plans have to cover PrEP for such individuals without cost-sharing effective January 2021. Updated United States Preventive Service Task Force guidance incorporating the new long-acting injectable PrEP drug is pending.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16268000FDAC4B3B904598131615A69D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Joint guidance issued by the Department of Labor, the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Department of the Treasury on July 19, 2021, clarifies that ancillary services necessary to maintain the PrEP regime, including subsequent provider visits, clinical testing, and other services, is required to be covered by health insurers without cost-sharing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1DC37FB2AC346BF98FE4FA9C7B9B3FC"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Permanently expanding access to cost-free PrEP and ancillary services for all individuals, including individuals who do not have health insurance, through legislation, is a critical step towards eliminating HIV transmission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AE9AB505F8C401D862450F7478D2C90"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Post-exposure prophylaxis (referred to in this section as <quote>PEP</quote>) is a daily antiretroviral treatment which, when initiated promptly after a sexual or other exposure to blood or body fluids that are associated with a high risk of HIV transmission, is highly effective at preventing HIV transmission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84A40C15B3E04599914160E6DDB56E04"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommends PEP for an individual who has experienced a high-risk exposure incident, provided that the individual tests HIV-negative, initiates such treatment not later than 72 hours after exposure, and continues the treatment for 28 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D0638807D4A4F0984BFF26C4D5F1546"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Despite PEP’s proven effectiveness in preventing HIV transmission after high-risk sexual exposures, including sexual assault, awareness of PEP is low among individuals who would benefit from the treatment. Studies suggest that awareness of PEP and of the importance of its prompt initiation is particularly low among young gay and bisexual men of color, transgender individuals, and women of all gender identities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF35E3F1AB8F04DCA8F17E837BBC0B975"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Adequate knowledge of guidelines issued by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for assessing indications for PEP and for initiating and sustaining PEP are low among health care providers and staff. Because PEP is an emergency intervention, insufficient knowledge among providers and staff in hospital emergency rooms, urgent care centers, community health centers, and primary care physicians is of particular concern.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5EE451EB89419EB3226F8F3D5635E8"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Private and public health insurance plans and programs frequently impose requirements for coverage of PEP, including pre-authorization requirements and requirements to obtain the medications through designated specialty pharmacies and mail-order programs that pose significant obstacles to timely initiation of treatment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F579336778740599B376F706A7809F5"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Insurance deductibles and co-payments for PEP medications create significant barriers to PEP utilization by many individuals who have experienced high-risk incidents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B523E77CF7E4CBEBB80B8C9F5BEF4DA"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The Federal Government has a compelling interest in preventing new cases of HIV. Lowering the prevalence of HIV protects public health and saves on the cost of HIV treatment. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFF1AB59CD1C4B8CB5DAAC80709F499F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Department of Labor, the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Department of the Treasury should ensure compliance with the requirements described in paragraphs (8) and (9) of subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H8F45B03523624267BCD8B1BB353D94DF"><enum>3.</enum><header>Coverage of HIV testing and prevention services</header><subsection id="HD20A61BF22C3427DACBD2BF9C449710E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Private insurance</header><paragraph id="HC86083E964C1494985BD525A5F0C45E6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2713(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-13">42 U.S.C. 300gg–13(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H98EE72D5AA05413CB086BD6F14D154EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDC91B98151445DCAF03D1BD93DEE48C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking the period and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19484CF7AFAE43A6A7226255541F7110"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB620690920CC40F8BC5E894BD8B368ED"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BC6A5AC838F4D9EAB9214FFEB1A6AB6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3CAC5AD22E6F461AAF9E924450FD40B1"><paragraph id="HDDB6ED6B5FDE4EB5A1F5C2F627E7C42A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV (other than a drug subject to preauthorization requirements consistent with section 2729A), administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CE581E4950246029F51B5261767EFA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on preauthorization requirements</header><text>Subpart II of part A of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-11">42 U.S.C. 300gg–11 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3197E7E528FE4731959B290C57A0611B"><section id="HFE4D479F18DF4847A4C2B07592758B30"><enum>2729A.</enum><header>Prohibition on preauthorization requirements with respect to certain services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A group health plan or a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall not impose any preauthorization requirements with respect to coverage of the services described in section 2713(a)(6), except that a plan or issuer may impose preauthorization requirements with respect to coverage of a particular drug approved under section 505(c) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act or section 351(a) of this Act if such plan or issuer provides coverage without any preauthorization requirements for a drug that is therapeutically equivalent.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE26F26655764C9CB52501A4AB344C68"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coverage under Federal Employees Health Benefits program</header><text>Section 8904 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA455FCE65E9641B39D017F7A5C845640"><subsection id="H94F3F7B6A9BE48C185A4C25CDEAE8938"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Any health benefits plan offered under this chapter shall include benefits for, and may not impose any cost-sharing requirements for, any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBEA1EDC3809D4A46BE0F8B748DB101DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><paragraph id="H0C5B843A43A549B989F68D650F742DA0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H1A84AEAB2CE04B3BBA5831526AAA3E40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(4)—</text><clause id="HF72D240B94BB48FE8B4C11345EA1744C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (D)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (D)</quote>; </text></clause><clause id="H04A075FA0CF94708A6E89DFA0CD1A0EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (E)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (E)</quote>; </text></clause><clause id="H72DF7B4A3D1349A5BB63730ADC35A569"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (F)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (F)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H5F95E71F8F174BA39B68EB2944FD4FC6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>; and (G) HIV prevention services;</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE13EEDA983FC402E873BC67185FC9DCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block act-name="" id="H19C745E9EF4D4A07BC40EF1C337AF0B9" style="traditional"><subsection id="H44A1B8A6653142FDA7FC8F5ECBD5B58B"><enum>(jj)</enum><header>HIV prevention services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a)(4)(G), the term <term>HIV prevention services</term> means prescription drugs for the prevention of HIV acquisition, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A656BD6CD8D4E73A84BDB82459FC280"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No cost-sharing</header><text>Title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H55861CC4A1B7498A938B31E8EAF02C7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 1916, by inserting <quote>HIV prevention services described in section 1905(a)(4)(G),</quote> after <quote>section 1905(a)(4)(C),</quote> each place it appears; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF52B0E581A342F89D0984D5F9FF4D62"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 1916A(b)(3)(B), by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block act-name="" id="HAC0052BFB5124A93851DBD3F9DF45D41" style="traditional"><clause id="H84DB0F17B1324B23930CAE34A4B95CE8"><enum>(xv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HIV prevention services described in section 1905(a)(4)(G).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AF77D32967D46829736B2BA7AF654AD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inclusion in benchmark coverage</header><text>Section 1937(b)(7) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396u-7">42 U.S.C. 1396u–7(b)(7)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HF1A227B9C2E94E3E9A6293C33FF083BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph header, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">and HIV prevention services</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">supplies</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30B09393BFE24FAEA5C79657F0FF166E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>includes for any individual described in section 1905(a)(4)(C), medical assistance for family planning services and supplies in accordance with such section</quote> and inserting <quote>includes medical assistance for HIV prevention services described in section 1905(a)(4)(G), and includes, for any individual described in section 1905(a)(4)(C), medical assistance for family planning services and supplies in accordance with such section</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H32FCD7DB97BB4423B7CB55CCED95677E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>CHIP</header><paragraph id="H8114B31FE60D46C58C67D65DF80F2B14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2103 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397cc">42 U.S.C. 1397cc</external-xref>), as amended by section 11405(b)(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended— </text><subparagraph id="HA01F3212023041C7811179A71501EA26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>and (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>(8), (10), (11), and (13)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06A46FBDB47145CAB7E23AC5FDC9C66D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block act-name="" id="HAA0DBACCB7BB4128B46EB5824C571DF9" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H95EB18FBE1D64832BB326411D8FC9E9D"><enum>(13)</enum><header>HIV prevention services</header><text>Regardless of the type of coverage elected by a State under subsection (a), the child health assistance provided for a targeted low-income child, and, in the case of a State that elects to provide pregnancy-related assistance pursuant to section 2112, the pregnancy-related assistance provided for a targeted low-income pregnant woman (as such terms are defined for purposes of such section), shall include coverage of HIV prevention services (as defined in section 1905(jj)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H75C64D1E271F4A10965B0DF793869777"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No cost-sharing</header><text>Section 2103(e)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397cc">42 U.S.C. 1397cc(e)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>HIV prevention services described in subsection (c)(13),</quote> before <quote>or for pregnancy-related assistance</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18572CE6555B4CD29652BBD0BBA3AEE1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><subparagraph id="HC2B744A12B5148F6A5E238D8146440A7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the amendments made by subsection (c) and this subsection shall take effect on January 1, 2025.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C36F2F15FC840C3885EDFB896BE443E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Delay permitted if State legislation required</header><text>In the case of a State plan approved under title XIX or XXI of the Social Security Act which the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines requires State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) in order for the plan to meet the additional requirements imposed by this section, the State plan shall not be regarded as failing to comply with the requirements of such title solely on the basis of the failure of the plan to meet such additional requirements before the 1st day of the 1st calendar quarter beginning after the close of the 1st regular session of the State legislature that ends after the 1-year period beginning with the date of the enactment of this section. For purposes of the preceding sentence, in the case of a State that has a 2-year legislative session, each year of the session is deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCCCE8B69D17C4302A1FD14DD97383E9D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coverage and elimination of cost-Sharing under Medicare</header><paragraph id="HED1C188B8BD74CE89AF4BFDC1D47CAC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coverage of HIV prevention services under Part B</header><subparagraph id="HD0CCDF73698F443696636FD4CC78EAC9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Coverage</header><clause id="H5C684DE6BE2048B9957FAC231361E0A6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1861(s)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(s)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subclause id="H2C6F0CC67FB4467F8AB31E3C77F10D50"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (II), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD267F37D465C443DB760435D7ACEB97D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (JJ), by inserting <quote>and</quote> at the end; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HFBB1DAAF3A504A5996425345F58D50A4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC536C618D5284EBB967C17BB35D01949"><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5972412D70564D2B939731560C411FCC"><enum>(KK)</enum><text>HIV prevention services (as defined in subsection (nnn));</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H8B49A10D62134769AD54EF1D91B4F6FD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9EDE1C72D42D47B58D4658150B40DD9D"><subsection id="HBF562A12F6EA40288F25164B7DB4FE3F"><enum>(nnn)</enum><header>HIV prevention services</header><text>The term <term>HIV prevention services</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H54654EE7BEA74A1982FCA2820CC2033F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>drugs or biologicals approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFE3C60CC2504EAC830647003D0A2C86"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administrative fees for such drugs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C87F3B974ED4FF6B10237C27DAA5194"><enum>(3)</enum><text>laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB232A3E46FA542AAAD3171A9827D5999"><enum>(4)</enum><text>clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C192A9D6A664C0682E66CE0E41336B9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elimination of coinsurance</header><text>Section 1833(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause id="H695F88E610F14290AEDE36B3A3C0858C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and (HH)</quote> and inserting <quote>(HH)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HA4C5587F5A5944FB98CD6BC69D79969B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, and (II) with respect to HIV prevention services (as defined in section 1861(nnn)), the amount paid shall be 100 percent of (i) except as provided in clause (ii), the lesser of the actual charge for the service or the amount determined under the fee schedule that applies to such services under this part, and (ii) in the case of such services that are covered OPD services (as defined in subsection (t)(1)(B)), the amount determined under subsection (t)</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19F6DC21127E4E2DA3E4C99AAA373843"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exemption from Part B deductible</header><text>The first sentence of section 1833(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause id="HC2222086B61A4D4C8139390A9CA27C23"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, and (13)</quote> and inserting <quote>(13)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H31A0F51C78BD4BFA8A32FA594D3B40C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>1861(n)..</quote> and inserting <quote>1861(n), and (14) such deductible shall not apply with respect to HIV prevention services (as defined in section 1861(nnn)(1)).</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H831DB161D9754E30BB7CC60CC860C1E6"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this paragraph shall apply to items and services furnished on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A6AABDCB1994096819DB216C438B94E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elimination of cost-sharing for drugs for the prevention of HIV under part D</header><subparagraph id="H73E57A61D5AD469DB8506D6789D87FEE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1860D–2 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-102">42 U.S.C. 1395w–102(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDA13F98B4B94F4984BD5C0747CF276D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subclause id="HF282CCC35C8E46B4BC99353ABA16080A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (9), and (10)</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA762612C63D54E99A037320F88FDCB44"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><item id="HF9DB10A400F949D09C3744413218C0B0"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (9), and (10)</quote>;</text></item><item id="H9E81071ECCD7466BA7A465D7BE77A316"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)(i), in the matter preceding subclause (I), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), and (10)</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HE94D9C55024D45F5A1680448E1F27188"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)(i), in the matter preceding subclause (I), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), and (10)</quote>;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H03D6E4A8D1554C1181C172083B67B9EF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(A), in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), and (10)</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5264288C6B194CB6872725D9338985EE"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(A)(i), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (9), and (10)</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HEA36B2A33ED841CC9A8381179C4883E3"><enum>(V)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H52E8566E7FD64B058D9A0DE93F3F073D"><paragraph id="H6EFCE6978A70444F9E8B67B2CF8D30EF"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Elimination of cost-sharing for drugs for the prevention of HIV</header><text>For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, with respect to a covered part D drug that is for the prevention of HIV—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0D9753BF3A4745779536A2E084EFF1A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the deductible under paragraph (1) shall not apply; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H050C2A71BB924F69B54EE9CF913130FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there shall be no coinsurance or other cost-sharing under this part with respect to such drug.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="HA217441D18AD409A821171FE36B0C988"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H840564E0E5CE4716AF4EDA89A8618994"><paragraph id="H8AED4461484745EFBCD39A1F4B0E7796"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Treatment of cost-sharing for drugs for the prevention of HIV</header><text>The coverage is provided in accordance with subsection (b)(10).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7345265606348F2B9A778BBB4ACA2B7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Conforming amendments to cost-sharing for low-income individuals</header><text>Section 1860D–14(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-114">42 U.S.C. 1395w–114(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause id="HA33D96F21E6F473BA03CD3D6A4C0885E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(D), in each of clauses (ii) and (iii), by striking <quote>paragraph (6)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (6) and (7)</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H81664517AA1F4ED7B08D493686088AB7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subclause id="H7EA27EDC88314FA0ABFC0250E0ECFF1E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (9), and (10)</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H2620E69ECACC417C84FEB2FF95ED184D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>paragraph (6)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (6) and (7)</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D96C644EF31437EAA2FDEB2B64ACE8D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>paragraph (6)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (6) and (7)</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9A92170CBD3E46CD9E2D287E72D14E78"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H931826030FA7457B8B51539B681B596C"><paragraph id="H487358BC40A34BE1B6BC80BDDB3BA15D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>No application of cost-sharing or deductible for drugs for the prevention of HIV</header><text>For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, with respect to a covered part D drug that is for the prevention of HIV—</text><subparagraph id="H886C675628B5478EBA489267B2893FE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the deductible under section 1860D–2(b)(1) shall not apply; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC1C95FBAB9946DB85F9EF6557CF2273"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there shall be no cost-sharing under this section with respect to such drug.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H857939B4A8464B83A16C51DE3B578DC7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coverage of HIV prevention treatment by Department of Veterans Affairs</header><paragraph id="H08DD2349D46445EE85F15F2FB900FA60"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Elimination of medication copayments</header><text>Section 1722A(a) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H58F7779D77E44511AA432C7AC69AC76C" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H190CBF2D7F2140C084FA2249A4FDC98D" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Paragraph (1) does not apply to a medication for the prevention of HIV.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H64F730F7C80B4029A3334FE31B767B1E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elimination of hospital care and medical services copayments</header><text>Section 1710 of such title is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HF275662C7466436AB0F5A44B7C7873CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text><clause id="H978C4362A8504FEABC9540CD6A0A5A9B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (5) as paragraph (6); and</text></clause><clause id="HABF1D58499374A78A6B3982988B5B9E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (4) the following new paragraph (5):</text><quoted-block id="HA024B38B7C4A44FDB9ADAC4713485E45" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HCE9AEA83825148CE91142E7D81537BEC" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A veteran shall not be liable to the United States under this subsection for any amounts for laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, or for laboratory or other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, or clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00C9E6F8369043608ED91B964CCEFBEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (g)(3), by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="HFEB82287B47749B4B6D2E5506F4E351D" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H800657B4D29D42ADA068BBAC74F20970" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E04090519354D3F88F967A2932ECEBE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inclusion as preventive health service</header><text>Section 1701(9) of such title is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H75A0A54729294A3FA38C6898C0EEC7C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (K), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A1055C5396E4B058344AD972CF2F6B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (L) as subparagraph (M); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4793183DE5F34EBA888466123B46EF87"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (K) the following new subparagraph (L):</text><quoted-block id="H71EED6F5DE2B41D496B65D1AC37F3B0C" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H63244462066A44F49E71A7D68EF48C7C"><enum>(L)</enum><text>any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA0F089FB61646A699F5280BEDD8A5D2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Coverage of HIV prevention treatment by Department of Defense</header><paragraph id="H5374E2B5004341B3A17D1BD0FA0A94B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/55">Chapter 55</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1074o">section 1074o</external-xref> the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H2D4B71DD5FB14805A8E24D6DFC2339CF" style="USC"><section id="H3B797A8373B646259C8032A0728F7F28"><enum>1074p.</enum><header>Coverage of HIV prevention treatment</header><subsection id="HAA58DC78ADBD476790311B3B58AAEC98"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure coverage under the TRICARE program of HIV prevention treatment described in subsection (b) for any beneficiary under section 1074(a) of this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0D3C5F93A07F4C61A01872DD819ADA28"><enum>(b)</enum><header>HIV prevention treatment described</header><text>HIV prevention treatment described in this subsection includes any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H831D09C7E4514193965A0D3B3A0113D2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No cost-Sharing</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1075, 1075a, or 1074g(a)(6) of this title or any other provision of law, there is no cost-sharing requirement for HIV prevention treatment covered under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H893744090C344D2F84490C6E82E07154"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1074o the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="H57CD20501324448DB5E4BDE9253EB605" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">1074p. Coverage of HIV prevention treatment.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08F5549BEE6240DE8CF17832453E5C8C"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Indian health service testing, monitoring, and prescription drugs for the prevention of HIV</header><text>Title II of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act is amended by inserting after section 223 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1621v">25 U.S.C. 1621v</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H34459AFACC6D445B82CFD9C6F3DFE7DE"><section id="H461101A01CA74C1CB9C9C74486DA20A8"><enum>224.</enum><header>Testing, monitoring, and prescription drugs for the prevention of HIV</header><subsection id="H9BD943EF976141F78DC557FB75AD7A9F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of HIV/AIDS Prevention and Treatment under section 832, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations, shall provide, without limitation, funding for any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of human immunodeficiency virus (commonly known as <quote>HIV</quote>), administrative fees for that drug, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of that drug, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines.</text></subsection><subsection id="H990C2ACC0FBD4B19B5BB86562FAFBE7A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H870C1243A1434F01A5BE2094E6EC039F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a), (b), (e), (f), (g), and (h) shall take effect with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB2648EF592BD4125B0A512C1CE0897DC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on denial of coverage or increase in premiums of life, disability, or long-term care insurance for individuals taking medication for the prevention of HIV acquisition</header><subsection id="H1652D811D42D4FE495803FE68F77D1ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, it shall be unlawful to—</text><paragraph id="H55B40A6420884C4BB291DDDD394A2CA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>decline or limit coverage of an individual under any life insurance policy, disability insurance policy, or long-term care insurance policy, on account of the individual taking medication for the purpose of preventing the acquisition of HIV;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6612146D64FD4F808CBD5B10CD825646"><enum>(2)</enum><text>preclude an individual from taking medication for the purpose of preventing the acquisition of HIV as a condition of receiving a life insurance policy, disability insurance policy, or long-term care insurance policy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E50666D07554B0AABFD848BD6433966"><enum>(3)</enum><text>consider whether an individual is taking medication for the purpose of preventing the acquisition of HIV in determining the premium rate for coverage of such individual under a life insurance policy, disability insurance policy, or long-term care insurance policy; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09502777EA104572BE1F7802202E385B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>otherwise discriminate in the offering, issuance, cancellation, amount of such coverage, price, or any other condition of a life insurance policy, disability insurance policy, or long-term care insurance policy for an individual, based solely and without any additional actuarial risks upon whether the individual is taking medication for the purpose of preventing the acquisition of HIV.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A0DCD7615A042E29219C5F75F395EC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>A State insurance regulator may take such actions to enforce subsection (a) as are specifically authorized under the laws of such State.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0DC2A93B75B7483F8EBE1C20767E5388"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HACF75D0F6D794599B965D50E890FB3AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disability insurance policy</header><text>The term <term>disability insurance policy</term> means a contract under which an entity promises to pay a person a sum of money in the event that an illness or injury resulting in a disability prevents such person from working.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAAC1597AF984C44B3C4F5601B8C2F9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Life insurance policy</header><text>The term <term>life insurance policy</term> means a contract under which an entity promises to pay a designated beneficiary a sum of money upon the death of the insured.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE93E47260F614579B76B557D5FCC003F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Long-term care insurance policy</header><text>The term <term>long-term care insurance policy</term> means a contract for which the only insurance protection provided under the contract is coverage of qualified long-term care services (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7702B">section 7702B(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB516D752E4F94085AA0C5DF35074DBAC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Public education campaign</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part P of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280g">42 U.S.C. 280g et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1821074317154154AC2D89A7E750A566"><section id="HCC7C3F9B152840F1BC6119E224F338B4"><enum>399V–8.</enum><header>Pre-exposure prophylaxis and post-exposure prophylaxis education campaigns</header><subsection id="H5C199490E2D34E9A9E444DA180DBED75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Public education campaign</header><paragraph id="HF136201F8B0B4464A00D32E1FAA7F6C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Infectious Disease and HIV/AIDS Policy, shall establish a public health campaign for the purpose of educating the public on medication for the prevention of HIV acquisition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H304B3F9F9FBC493EB295F7068E643054"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary shall ensure cultural competency and efficacy within high-need communities in which PrEP or PEP are underutilized by developing the campaign in collaboration with organizations that are indigenous to communities that are overrepresented in the domestic HIV epidemic, including communities of color and the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer community. The Secretary shall ensure that the campaign is designed to increase awareness of the safety and effectiveness of PrEP and PEP, the recommended clinical practices for providing PrEP-related and PEP-related clinical care, and the local availability of PrEP and PEP providers, and to counter stigma associated with the use of PrEP and PEP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FEFB92DAD104EFF96257FC2A86EB4F1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Evaluation of program</header><text>The Secretary shall develop measures to evaluate the effectiveness of activities conducted under this subsection that are aimed at reducing disparities in access to PrEP and PEP and supporting the local community. Such measures shall evaluate community outreach activities, language services, workforce cultural competence, and other areas as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0893731BD6B94EDF98F4725956731C34"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provider education campaign</header><paragraph id="H6043C3A6F2D24048B66F998F970A7A05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Administrator of the Health Resources Services Administration, and the Office of Infectious Disease and HIV/AIDS Policy, shall establish a provider campaign for the purpose of educating prescribers and other associated health professionals on medication for the prevention of HIV acquisition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEA3542942E0406AA743DF8242A1433F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary shall increase awareness and readiness among health care providers to offer PrEP or PEP, as appropriate, with a focus on areas of high-need communities in which PrEP or PEP is underutilized by developing an educational campaign with input from health care providers and organizations that are indigenous to communities that are overrepresented in the domestic HIV epidemic, including communities of color and the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer community. The Secretary shall ensure that the campaign is designed to increase awareness of the safety and effectiveness of PrEP and PEP, the recommended clinical practices for providing PrEP-related and PEP-related clinical care, cultural competency among PrEP and PEP prescribers, and to counter stigma associated with the use of PrEP and PEP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA236D8C4D2DB45238E2DBA69A88BBAB2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Evaluation of program</header><text>The Secretary shall develop measures to evaluate the effectiveness of activities conducted under this subsection that are aimed at increasing the number of health care professionals offering PrEP and PEP and reducing disparities in access to PrEP and PEP. Such measures shall evaluate availability of PrEP and PEP services, education and outreach activities, language services, workforce cultural competence, and other areas as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA16EF5388864CEF80D3C05773FE9D75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section and section 399V–9—</text><paragraph id="HD8A344374A0748BBBFF719C29711F820"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>PEP</term> means any drug or combination of drugs approved by the Food and Drug Administration for preventing HIV transmission after a sexual or other exposure associated with a high risk of HIV transmission; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BEF191202154E919C5D4257F80B6369"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>PrEP</term> means any drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the purpose of pre-exposure prophylaxis with respect to HIV.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C94561DC00D4610B60AE7F855F77F7F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H39984362E3764F428311FBC159BD189F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Patient confidentiality</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall amend the regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320d-2">42 U.S.C. 1320d–2</external-xref> note), as necessary, to ensure that individuals are able to access the benefits described in section 2713(a)(6) under a family plan without any other individual enrolled in such family plan, including a primary subscriber of or policyholder, being informed of such use of such benefits.</text></section><section id="H88AC8069FC454E0F970A3CAFAE20DDAF"><enum>7.</enum><header>Pre-exposure prophylaxis and post-exposure prophylaxis funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part P of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280g">42 U.S.C. 280g et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 5, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA395E2A4172C496D8D72BC373A687046"><section id="H0E9D17587643460BB02D8F3E42173CE4"><enum>399V–9.</enum><header>Pre-exposure prophylaxis and post-exposure prophylaxis funding</header><subsection id="HC0CBB7B6E3944C5B82FA32B2F33CE097"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the PrEP Access and Coverage Act, the Secretary shall establish a program that awards grants to States, territories, Indian Tribes, and directly eligible entities for the establishment and support of pre-exposure prophylaxis (referred to in this section as <quote>PrEP</quote>) and post-exposure prophylaxis (referred to in this section as <quote>PEP</quote>) programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2DE9D92A0F142F8B8B92C15E848FB4D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (a), a State, territory, Indian Tribe, or directly eligible entity shall—</text><paragraph id="HAD2218CD811947279622B63BF277D1EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a plan describing how any funds awarded will be used to increase access to PrEP for uninsured and underinsured individuals and reduce disparities in access to PrEP and PEP for uninsured and underinsured individuals and reduce disparities in access to PrEP and PEP; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D5F930F1CA94732B85CD1AB83227193"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appoint a PrEP and PEP grant administrator to manage the program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD797BE6790474714B88A057CAFB05ACE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Directly eligible entity</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>directly eligible entity</term>—</text><paragraph id="H84BA013F80F44A3EBC630D1EDF658F8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means a Federally qualified health center or other nonprofit entity engaged in providing PrEP and PEP information and services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACB8437EB11B495BBB8F2845976E473A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may include—</text><subparagraph id="H65B6567468954A059464C38CC4E83CA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Federally qualified health center (as defined in section 1861(aa)(4) of the Social Security Act);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H653C4EEEB44747C1865B376426089AE0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a family planning grantee (other than States) funded under section 1001;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15CAF26A9D544F01B4255AC3C817C6FC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a rural health clinic (as defined in section 1861(aa)(2) of the Social Security Act);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7B143BAC1F44886A584817935F72E53"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a health facility operated by or pursuant to a contract with the Indian Health Service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C969F37E90D421BB4B45E8AD006E9AC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a community-based organization, clinic, hospital, or other health facility that provides services to individuals at risk for or living with HIV; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE194A3F82AE94E60AED3F8349D82048E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a nonprofit private entity providing comprehensive primary care to populations at risk of HIV, including faith-based and community-based organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE31046F314524433821BD07DAB9ACD6B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Awards</header><text>In determining whether to award a grant, and the grant amount for each grant awarded, the Secretary shall consider the grant application and the need for PrEP and PEP services in the area, the number of uninsured and underinsured individuals in the area, and how the State, territory, or Indian Tribe coordinates PrEP and PEP activities with the directly funded entity, if the State, territory, or Indian Tribe applies for the funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="H084D2CAD9DEE48E5B7B465193061FA90"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><paragraph id="H86AB51ADC60340FA8E89852634B047F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any State, territory, Indian Tribe, or directly eligible entity that is awarded funds under subsection (a) shall use such funds for eligible PrEP and PEP expenses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21C96634E5454BD0BC284353423E85D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible prep expenses</header><text>The Secretary shall publish a list of expenses that qualify as eligible PrEP and PEP expenses for purposes of this section, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H1165B4B0B9814B51B1FE7D20EEA41560"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any prescription drug approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the prevention of HIV, administrative fees for such drugs, laboratory and other diagnostic procedures associated with the use of such drugs, and clinical follow-up and monitoring, including any related services recommended in current United States Public Health Service clinical practice guidelines, without limitation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3869FE7A6084F6E91A8AC4A16895BF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outreach and public education activities directed toward populations overrepresented in the domestic HIV epidemic that increase awareness about the existence of PrEP and PEP, provide education about access to and health care coverage of PrEP and PEP, PrEP and PEP adherence programs, and counter stigma associated with the use of PrEP and PEP;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3914CF4DBCC64630A4E27A22D8691E6C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>outreach activities directed toward physicians and other providers that provide education about PrEP and PEP; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59343FA4BE5B4E0AA0CDFDCA40B007F6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>adherence services and counseling, including personnel costs for PrEP navigators to retain patients in care.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H552B58B14D5D45849C20C0C343548236"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall, in each of the first 5 years beginning one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>PrEP Access and Coverage Act of 2023</short-title>, submit to Congress, and make public on the internet website of Department of Health and Human Services, a report on the impact of any grants provided to States, territories, Indian Tribes, and directly eligible entities for the establishment and support of pre-exposure prophylaxis programs under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDFA051A7604D4623AE8FB0F396B1B7D6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H197503D5FDA9415C98C77396F8F821D8"><enum>8.</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act, including the amendments made by this Act, shall apply notwithstanding any other provision of law, including <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/141">Public Law 103–141</external-xref>.</text></section><section id="H2FBEEBF293D24C168BF66A59EF700368"><enum>9.</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any person aggrieved by a violation of this Act, including the amendments made by this Act, may commence a civil action in an appropriate United States District Court or other court of competent jurisdiction to obtain relief as allowed by law as either an individual or member of a class. If the plaintiff is the prevailing party in such an action, the court shall order the defendant to pay the costs and reasonable attorney fees of the plaintiff.</text></section><section id="H8FC2CFBCFF8B453E8F8DEDDABB2BFEB4"><enum>10.</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subsection id="H89C7C04181C546C986F4447681F1C2DF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B014220BB3640328B334ADE3811E18F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issue guidance regarding the implementation of the coverage requirements established under this Act, including the amendments made by this Act, including with respect to implementation of such coverage requirements;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0A9FDCE41754F8493A04732958B7B9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and disseminate educational materials, including billing and coding documents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95516A27E83A4D79AE3D7F279DC13778"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to State insurance commissioners;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32499569E0934CB2B18CD6CAF9152965"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to eligible entities for regarding responding to consumer complaints and assisting in resolving such complaints; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5EDBC8F51B54917B3A6E5CCF802BE4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>work with other Federal agencies to assist in enforcement and compliance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43D37CCF00334BBF9C356576481CA22F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compliance</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9A2FC6C260A4E1E8BC47981298CA5AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Labor, and the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall monitor compliance by group health plans and health insurance issuers with coverage requirements established under title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg">42 U.S.C. 300gg et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 3) and shall take appropriate enforcement actions under the Public Health Service Act, the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, and the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1110DE670DB41688AA4016CAC52E1D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Insurer submissions to the Secretary</header><text>Beginning not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, each group health plan and health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall submit to the Secretary of Health and Human Services, at such time as such secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of the Treasury, shall require, but not less frequently than annually for the 10-year period beginning on such date of enactment, data demonstrating compliance with the coverage requirements described in paragraph (1), including aggregate data on the number of claims received by such plans and issuers for HIV prevention services and the cost-sharing for enrollees with respect to such claims.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDE5DBECE9EB4537AF2DDA9CB11FC9F2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the enactment of this Act and every 2 years thereafter for the 10-year period beginning on such date of enactment, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Labor, and the Secretary of the Treasury (collectively referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretaries</quote>) shall jointly submit to Congress and make publicly available a report to assess the prevalence of noncompliance with the coverage requirements described in paragraph (1). Each such report shall include—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HED3770E583564084B8B78499E0DA929E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aggregate information about group health plans and health insurance issuers that the Secretaries determine to be out of compliance with such requirements; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6347FDC258C74C178C79C3F9A0910C5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">steps the Secretaries have taken to address incidences of such noncompliance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6FF0AF40F3744D7AC2DAB54F11DF326"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>group health plan</term>, <term>health insurance coverage</term>, and <term>health insurance issuer</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2729 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

