<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H12736C6530204DC9800F9C5FCA7E203D"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>105 HR 4239 IH: Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4239</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 to establish the Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration and to amend the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act to establish the Rural Future Partnership Fund to invest in the rural areas of the United States to achieve their preferred future while maximizing their contribution to the well-being of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" id="id649A835785B74D04935D53D285BCD13C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="id438e390ac7dd42ee904d976eca063f94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to create the scale and capacity that enables rural areas to achieve their preferred future while maximizing their contribution to the well-being of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id99422913308e4d31bbf126b27a313627"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to recognize the significant contributions of rural areas of the United States to the success of the United States, including the leading role that the rural areas play in addressing the critical threat of climate change and building a resilient United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddf898d7063304f1cb3a792099f59fffb"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to make a national commitment to the rural communities and regions of the United States to ensure that the rural United States benefits from and contributes to the prosperity of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0b41a75b9859423a845d7882dd292df3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to establish a partnership with rural areas of the United States that provides flexible, long-term, and annual Federal investment for comprehensive, collaborative, and locally driven community and economic development that improves quality of life and economic competitiveness;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc3d887fe6e7e407ea96226f637bcfe9f"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to strengthen rural population centers through collaboration with neighboring rural areas that ensures economic integration and regional development;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id20976e67e7244b43bc76804c71ca504f"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to strengthen connections between rural and urban areas of the United States for mutual success and for the benefit of the economy of the United States and the quality of life of the people of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6e77fc05f3134d80a342a641d2d5514e"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to support asset-based development, maximizing the cost-effectiveness of existing infrastructure;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0E12FB66FD03432EB388F232F49600E2"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to ensure economic opportunities that create pathways to high-quality, family-sustaining jobs for all individuals in rural areas of the United States, including efforts to address population loss, to promote the use of cooperatives and other forms of public and employee ownership, and to expand and improve access to training, infrastructure, and investment to adapt to technological change, such as automation, for success in the digital economy;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idC0715CA4536A4EDC8592DAF5842C74D1"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide for the evolution and expansion of the role of the Department of Agriculture in ensuring that rural communities have a dedicated agency and a new delivery system for Federal assistance for disaster recovery and proactive mitigation and resiliency efforts;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id16F061362CD74877A06AB6D5E9C94968"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to rebuild and modernize infrastructure and expand investment to support local and regional food systems, sustainable agriculture production, and value added agricultural industries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idB1F6FF2E28DB4DC7B3DFC0CECA4AC73A"><enum>(11)</enum><text>to support infill development, preserve undeveloped land, and remediate brownfields and other contaminated properties for re-use; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ideee7646bc6c7440d9a09b4553140f159"><enum>(12)</enum><text>to support public health and improve quality of life in rural communities by delivering—</text><subparagraph id="id01FA6C551E634B22B81B26168E9EE640"><enum>(A)</enum><text>universal access to clean air and water;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id87093BFA33FD47B8A0EE7C210FC0588A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>healthy foods available through local and regional food systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id534D0478AC3D4BFEAF1998BAC78F3C87"><enum>(C)</enum><text>quality, affordable, and accessible health care services in the rural communities, including access to primary and emergency medical services, mental health care, and treatment for substance abuse;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id517dc4293f25429db6ece3ad407f5b1e"><enum>(D)</enum><text>affordable and reliable clean energy systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5fe817fd2d644787830aee0e66272952"><enum>(E)</enum><text>quality, affordable, and energy-efficient housing choices in the rural communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="id8935E191F0A94ABC90BEDB37EA11B619"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration</header><subsection commented="no" id="idA9C77B68A0C0404CBAF076058222666A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subtitle C of the Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6941">7 U.S.C. 6941 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0F597A2C3F4C450BB77BDFD29AB3EBF6"><section id="idCAC7103E6BA947E888A8DD54CDE495AF"><enum>237.</enum><header>Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration</header><subsection id="id386702A3920C4A17AF4DA5F04B0C3733"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish in the Department a Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration (referred to in this section as the <term>Administration</term>).</text></subsection><subsection id="id7994C0ACEEC14F419E5D10646364952E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrator</header><paragraph id="id2313E73C0D96450C94D6F8673E284928"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administration shall be headed by an Administrator of Rural Innovation and Partnerships (referred to in this section as the <term>Administrator</term>), who shall be appointed by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idDFE72500EF0249F2B95841E7908A338B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting to Under Secretary</header><text>The Administrator shall report to the Under Secretary for Rural Development.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id36D8C2BA500141FC8E286F01F5047481"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out through the Administration the functions of the Rural Future Partnership Fund established under subtitle I of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="idC1D2697EC8EA43728E924C2431ACAA9C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirement for State offices</header><text>In carrying out the functions of the Administration, the Secretary shall ensure that each State office of the rural development mission area is staffed with not less than 3 new employees to implement the Rural Future Partnership Fund established under subtitle I of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act, including providing—</text><paragraph id="idF1D19AF8EF4F43448A89A1FC43FFC4AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>technical assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id37B155FDE3F94ADE93BC4AE32F941147"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support for capacity building;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idB98FEA897F6E4A29989DAB75823FA703"><enum>(3)</enum><text>financial controls; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3214303D359E4A4E91028F918C7F6311"><enum>(4)</enum><text>performance oversight.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idCD6EFD6DA7E34381AA31C494B61614C0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination with Council on Rural Community Innovation and Economic Development</header><text>In carrying out the functions of the Administration, the Administrator shall coordinate with the Council on Rural Community Innovation and Economic Development established by section 6306 of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2204b-3">7 U.S.C. 2204b–3</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="id1C68F45F37044F788444A705AAA309CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph commented="no" id="id41110989929946A182BCA91208428E62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 296(b) of the Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7014">7 U.S.C. 7014(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idAA69FE1AC64F4C68B474B47B670B7ABE"><paragraph commented="no" id="id7C0E6ED5A6AE4F6E848832A94B418330"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The authority of the Secretary to establish and maintain in the Department the Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration under section 237.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id684C0C7EE70A44CE93A8D62FE0F7D936"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 6306(f) of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2204b-3">7 U.S.C. 2204b–3(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="id9854A0D32EEB41C5BC6FDC5CDCA3FD9F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idE465BCA0FD57480ABE977D85B12E4127"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="idB08496578D6C44B59DAA0472E65149B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idFD3C716BAE5E472B9A3813041CA689B4"><paragraph commented="no" id="id8D492E6BAF6944B1831EABCE5F1BAB38"><enum>(6)</enum><text>give priority to coordinating with the Administrator of Rural Innovation and Partnerships in carrying out the Rural Future Partnership Fund established under subtitle I of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id57112DE5058E437BA34DF8EA90D4589E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rural Future Partnership Fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1921">7 U.S.C. 1921 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idDD6807530CB54D53BC4D82A4B925DF40"><subtitle id="id823CEAF00ABC4D04B8A6F52F02711198" style="OLC"><enum>I<?LEXA-Enum I?></enum><header>Rural Future Partnership Fund</header><section id="id1AAE9F6BBC2E4CCFA34B83B42E3892D7"><enum>385A.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subtitle:</text><paragraph id="id046E89EA3F414D2B89967E06F4FF265B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Council</header><text>The term <term>Council</term> means a rural partnership council established under paragraph (1)(A)(i), (2)(A)(i), or (3)(A)(i), as applicable, of section 385C(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id25AEC12C4C644F61972DED558265D1FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible technical assistance provider</header><text>The term <term>eligible technical assistance provider</term> means an entity—</text><subparagraph id="id1F01F160B6FA48A1952177F3B0C82D70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with a demonstrated national or regional structure or capacity to deliver and support multiple rural planning activities across the United States or within a region of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id45137C8BBC984B0BB015D64468FDEB98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is—</text><clause id="id4b8dba7282b04cbf9b5c699d52a27474"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a federally recognized Indian Tribe;</text></clause><clause id="id929558DFD5C945909152C55D875DB922"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></clause><clause id="id55E1812B771C4392B377D801D23A3D19"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization; or</text></clause><clause id="id1AB7C0538D35494E87546C2E2DCD80B7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a private organization.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id894A6C1C6396402FB384ED1C8C147D19"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Fund</term> means the Rural Future Partnership Fund established under section 385B.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id50F17C5C56674382A82EB6BDC999370D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4D333105BDD44BA98409A6EC7C8D71B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id005CA36EB82E486A9E2625B9A74E21F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> includes—</text><clause id="id15B0EA4D9E0E4C92BAD638206FCD8C9C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>land-grant colleges and universities (as defined in section 1404 of the National Agricultural Research, Extension, and Teaching Policy Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3103">7 U.S.C. 3103</external-xref>)); and</text></clause><clause id="idE755314988024AFEA1FFB96E4BBD1CA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>associated cooperative extension services.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id308A82BD96D4466993A539B1EF130F2B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Plan</header><text>The term <term>Plan</term> means a rural partnership plan established under section 385E(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id44AAAEF871CC4876B22ED240BFE58A28"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reservation</header><subparagraph id="idD88D2F9D18C442A8B68799E1BD604BA3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>reservation</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian country</term> in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id910D381235D9471E97F6280F52BF3F58"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>reservation</term> includes land held by a Native group, a Regional Corporation, or a Village Corporation (as those terms are defined in section 3 of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1602">43 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id54C68EAC4DCE46729BC77667588158ED"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Rural partnership block grant</header><text>The term <term>rural partnership block grant</term> means a rural partnership block grant awarded under this subtitle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idE588BB6F551B4937AC8C2E2C28DDF4AA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary, acting through the Administrator of Rural Innovation and Partnerships.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc99911b381ab4ca9b1f608224e2f5e18"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Workforce housing</header><text>The term <term>workforce housing</term> means, with respect to housing for a family, housing the cost of which does not exceed 30 percent of—</text><subparagraph id="idd01c2c583f014ddbb5c607316e3171b3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to subparagraph (B), 120 percent of the median income in the area in which the family lives, as determined by the Secretary, with appropriate adjustments for the size of the family; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8236ddede4c740e1a6094009bef81f48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines that there are unusually high or low family incomes in the area in which the family lives, such other percentage, as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, of the median income in the area in which the family lives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="id62A832CB3158405EB87D98FEA76CA665"><enum>385B.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a program, to be known as the <term>Rural Future Partnership Fund</term>, under which the Secretary shall award rural partnership block grants in accordance with this subtitle.</text></section><section id="id29E49E9603094889AF78B52BFAD17A4C"><enum>385C.</enum><header>Eligibility</header><subsection id="idE5C2C739D4A540FBA934A8C87BA16B56"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="id5BB440068D774910B710DDE6D2DD61F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Micropolitan statistical areas</header><subparagraph id="idB40B6FB7507149C5B56C62673AC0A6AA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant—</text><clause id="idF943610D0E4F45B3A16CE45143306B64"><enum>(i)</enum><text>one or more units of local government that govern a micropolitan statistical area, as defined by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, shall establish a rural partnership council in accordance with subsection (b); and</text></clause><clause id="id663FC0BD72F14167BF632D20D40A663B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that Council shall submit an application to—</text><subclause id="id820E88A5C04E473AA6D80CFEADC788D4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</short-title>—</text><item id="idD7751CB4FA534519890DE23606A57DE1"><enum>(aa)</enum><subitem commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id23723E87F91C469E946AB988036D8FF8"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the applicable State; or</text></subitem><subitem id="idA2CC9F02EA624D5AB686D20DABBD8D48" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the applicable States, if the micropolitan statistical area spans more than 1 State; and</text></subitem></item><item id="id681C3477F74B4E6D88050353C32F57B1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area; or</text></item></subclause><subclause id="id530D4DCD4FD54585BE199F178331BAA3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>after the date described in subclause (I), the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7324B07B7835472A852E48214A93C3A1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Regional collaboration</header><clause id="idF7E6B8BBB3464A61B22D355F93FEE48F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receipt of an application under subparagraph (A)(ii)(I), the one or more States, in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, shall advise the applicant on the inclusion in the Council, if practicable, of one or more contiguous census tracts or counties that—</text><subclause id="id25B1B5A87A40483A83F2979C532E20DF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fall outside of a micropolitan or metropolitan statistical area; and</text></subclause><subclause id="idF73A2BE9876C48DFBC52512A01CC9843"><enum>(II)</enum><text>demonstrate evidence of economic, social, and cultural cooperation that enhances the potential for comprehensive, asset-based regional development.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idECFD82B77C1E48AC9B75D15AE4FB1CAB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Decision</header><text>After receipt of advice under clause (i), the applicant shall—</text><subclause id="idDA509864D43441A88F05EE78B91EE6D2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>decide whether to include one or more of the applicable contiguous census tracts or counties in the Council; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id558A3F67EDEC4A4D8962BF882B09AC74"><enum>(II)</enum><text>modify the application, as appropriate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id02002FD06B204F5BA9FDC764B0FF1BD4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Approval</header><clause id="id4A7DCB987B6C48A68E6619FA5AD42355"><enum>(i)</enum><header>States</header><text>The one or more States that receive an application under subparagraph (A)(ii)(I)(aa), in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, shall approve the Council as eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant if the requirements under subsection (b) for the composition of the membership of a Council are satisfied.</text></clause><clause id="id57DBE306E646452B924EFEE28CE069F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Not less frequently than once each year, the Secretary, in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, may approve applications received under subparagraph (A)(ii)(II) if the requirements under subsection (b) for the composition of the membership of a Council are satisfied.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id34E8755D14124296B833B4C919A9625C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Areas outside of micropolitan and metropolitan statistical areas; other rural areas</header><subparagraph id="id9B58DFEEB7FE4ABE8C96DFB2B91354F9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant—</text><clause id="id6CBAE95ECB3F4AD689871306245EB7C7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a rural partnership council shall be established in accordance with subsection (b) by one or more entities described in subsection (b)(1) that—</text><subclause id="id44009944AFFD4E859C7A1B8147DEBD71"><enum>(I)</enum><text>are located in, or represent, two or more contiguous census tracts or counties in an area that is—</text><item id="id42D1F680060C4E1E9D3722932965B279"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>not within a micropolitan statistical area or a metropolitan statistical area, as defined by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget; </text></item><item id="id4DE2BEA75C574DEF8DA743818021ABED"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>determined to be rural in character under section 343(a)(13)(D); or</text></item><item id="id8B799F4B86574978BA207FFF40B0BF86"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>excluded from not being in a rural area under section 343(a)(13)(E); and </text></item></subclause><subclause id="id79F7F4BCC70645B09F9C42EA5C1DC512"><enum>(II)</enum><text>are not represented by a Council established under paragraph (1)(A)(i) or (3)(A)(i); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="id96A70BFCCF104B54835B676CC8DA24C1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that Council shall submit an application to—</text><subclause id="id2AE409185B35483F86A5E1A66F00F875"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</short-title>—</text><item id="idD1D14C97872245BA9B04B0C6CDBC8A51"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the one or more applicable States; and</text></item><item id="id7CD5C99EF2B94B1BBEB87C3A8BB90F3A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area; or</text></item></subclause><subclause id="id5213AC7391CB43B08644120AE5D0CB8E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>after the date described in subclause (I), the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2C19D48B619547609607766736A6CF2A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approval</header><clause id="id2A581D08518344138AA95EF90A0DE478"><enum>(i)</enum><header>States</header><text>The one or more States that receive an application under subparagraph (A)(ii)(I)(aa), in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, shall approve the Council as eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant if—</text><subclause id="id390695BC8BDA4E73AECD7E2DCBE4E15E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the requirements under subsection (b) for the composition of the membership of a Council are satisfied; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id7FE2CEC5D959432ABC063F97A2F137B4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the area to be represented by the Council—</text><item id="idAB3E50DDEBDE4D5B8C8B43FCEC3308CF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is of practicable geographic size; and</text></item><item id="id18DEF779C015491193DF7CF30A131C16"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>demonstrates evidence of economic, social, and cultural cooperation that enhances the potential for comprehensive, asset-based regional development.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="idA1EEACA489F1404FA93A9FCC549FD464"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Not less frequently than once each year, the Secretary, in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, may approve applications received under subparagraph (A)(ii)(II) if the requirements described in clause (i) are satisfied.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id45FD29AB27254232AC05F669CFDF5ECA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian reservations</header><subparagraph id="id7AACC53889E24F22A8AEBF74F753AAF8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant—</text><clause id="id538A88B5DB11435CB9B7A85F550B2234"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe that has jurisdiction over a reservation shall establish a rural partnership council in accordance with subsection (b); and</text></clause><clause id="id357E0BA6966B4CB587338334AEC6B979"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that Council shall submit an application to the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6AF740CB90CF4F39B87658F76EBD36FF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approval</header><clause id="id338B7D5FE21F4DB49DF4F374256BAAC7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receipt of an application that was submitted under subparagraph (A)(ii) not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary, in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, shall approve the Council as eligible to receive a rural partnership block grant if the requirements under subsection (b) for the composition of the membership of a Council are satisfied.</text></clause><clause id="idDC1150EA2B1644F98C111FE199489AB3"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Subsequent applications</header><text>Not less frequently than once each year, the Secretary, in coordination with the applicable State offices of the rural development mission area, may approve applications submitted under subparagraph (A)(ii) later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rebuild Rural America Act of 2023</short-title> if the requirements under subsection (b) for the composition of the membership of a Council are satisfied.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idF63AAD0D20764F889B79F1BBB9276462"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>Each Council—</text><paragraph id="id87AE88C85304479DBB407F00195E7115"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall include one or more representatives of—</text><subparagraph id="idE118F2BAE46E44A997F8DE4F9734AD92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a District Organization (as defined in section 300.3 of title 13, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations)) or a comparable regional planning organization if there is no applicable District Organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9FA27613CD7E423FA475F601596D1B4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one or more units of local government, or one or more entities designated by a unit of local government, within the applicable area; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id26B6708BE68743CE845D710CD4B55A55"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a public or nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id928056B9628849D784F81DF93A943296"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may include one or more representatives of—</text><subparagraph id="id9270c6de59ef4c06893dd136400bee54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an economic development or other community or labor organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide9f029de3b62497c8c59fb816e73e16e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a financial institution, including a community development financial institution (as defined in section 103 of the Community Development Banking and Financial Institutions Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4702">12 U.S.C. 4702</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id429b31d3ec614a779c21805e50ab6577"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a philanthropic organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idaf123a99794d4d4e8c1ddd85c8422afc"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a rural cooperative;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id963ED099EC9F411A8822B13372D7C749"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an entity with experience in the development of cooperatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id53b6549cd05744c3ba1786888ec4dbc5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id252de5533b044e30a4dc32cc60a62e37"><enum>(G)</enum><text>elementary or secondary education and kindergarten or pre-kindergarten centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7B2585260C6640AC931B4CF68CBA54E5"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a private entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idD90478CBDBB74FD6A9611C7678767349"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a Tribal organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8beec87e7aa84e6a9f512f41132a8236"><enum>(J)</enum><text>a metropolitan planning organization (as defined in section 134(b) of title 23, United States Code);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1cd373ddf7aa431cba25a66db8bd9d7c"><enum>(K)</enum><text>any other regional planning organization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id646743437CE14BEBBD6FDEECC9742371"><enum>(L)</enum><text>any other entity, as determined to be appropriate by the Council; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id83A367CDFD2C44EE8C993410B39A7FC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall be composed of an odd number of members.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idA2D45D5AE1D04401B72332CE59EC5C2A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Revisions</header><paragraph id="idADC79648BD234CF1AAE1A2DF46484C7F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not more frequently than once every 5 years, a Council may submit to the one or more applicable States, or to the Secretary in the case of a Council established by an Indian Tribe, an application to revise the geographic boundary of the applicable area represented by the Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7DD8AABE4B3E479C91DCE216478548D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final approval by Secretary</header><text>An application submitted to one or more States under paragraph (1) shall be subject to final approval by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idCEBBBDB619F9493DB2AAF03880DC6E34"><enum>385D.</enum><header>Rural partnership block grants</header><subsection id="idD4743FEBA94148749C5842998966534E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allocation of funds</header><paragraph id="id4703F160B61B462B8D47AC3C6451207E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary shall allocate rural partnership block grant funds to Councils proportionately based on the population of each area represented by a Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2371BD0CCD50498888C4DDBFF4C1C5CF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>High poverty rates</header><text>The Secretary shall allocate to a Council an amount equal to 3 times the applicable amount under paragraph (1) with respect to each individual residing in a census tract, or a group of contiguous census tracts, that—</text><subparagraph id="idE89213918F234634ACABF42020A51697"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a poverty rate of 20 percent or greater; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7EB19DBB44464D8EB1574B2D33FB4CD0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is within or comprises the applicable area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idEFBCA1DFBB524BF09FBA49D676A6B68F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall distribute rural partnership block grant funds annually to each Council during the term of the rural partnership block grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="idCEA759A4E56744FB82633D7BF84C715B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Term</header><text>A rural partnership block grant—</text><paragraph id="idC1925480FECE4A91BE895165CB3CE3F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be for a term of 5 years; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idF31DF2EF179E4E679EA9BAA8B63C4D43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may be renewed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6D348771C213424B927F57FFB295D2C4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant agreements</header><paragraph id="idA41CEA0DF08C40F1BA90F602E40D2C65"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each Council shall enter into an agreement with the Secretary, under which the Council, in coordination with the Secretary, shall establish performance measures and reporting requirements that shall be met by the end of each year for which the Council receives funds under the Fund.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idBAA8034027134F95B2803D122285AE47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Violations</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a Council has failed to meet any requirements of the applicable agreement under paragraph (1), is not making reasonable progress towards meeting that requirement, or is otherwise in violation of that agreement, the Secretary may—</text><subparagraph id="id3E697482CF094D60ABF4B6EB85328919"><enum>(A)</enum><text>withhold funds under the Fund until the Council remedies the applicable violation; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idC7681C7858A5452AAC0EEC259B680BF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>terminate the agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id87A075E4DCFB4EA5A692715664FC43F4"><enum>385E.</enum><header>Rural partnership plans</header><subsection id="id63B9E45B044B49A8A1C04B8C2F32B5D1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Each Council shall establish, maintain, evaluate, and report to the Secretary progress on a rural partnership plan in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="ida64a0e4d95bb4aa7a946d21a51a66a86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with other plans</header><paragraph id="id5C02038E02034CF5A69C8E7F5E50506E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In developing a Plan under this section, a Council is encouraged to utilize existing Federal plans, and existing State, regional, or Tribal plans, so as to reduce duplicative efforts and align Federal investment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0939CDCC906C4869A34F0AA1D32B16B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal plans</header><text>Existing Federal plans referred to in paragraph (1) include—</text><subparagraph id="idd120749c729f43ada546a347324f999b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Comprehensive Economic Development Strategy of the Economic Development Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id14eb21444dc64e5aa20eb30c799f4385"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a local plan, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1f73c56db7d94befb89ed5344b37f94e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Consolidated Plan of the Department of Housing and Urban Development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id3df1d9b3807c4b9aae80611331515bab"><enum>(D)</enum><text>plans developed by metropolitan planning organizations under section 134 of title 23, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id928335CB4BE0408BA715746C6C3DD801"><enum>(E)</enum><text>plans developed by regional transportation planning organizations designated under section 135(m) of title 23, United States Code, or section 5304(l) of title 49, United States Code (commonly known as a <quote>rural transportation planning organization</quote>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="id2f0d1f5f664e4e4490428e0a08199f65"><enum>(F)</enum><text>emergency preparedness and hazard mitigation plans required by the Federal Emergency Management Agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd4c9b52e4846428bb477d02145e52194"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Drinking Water Action Plan of the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1EFB48AFAA3F4524AF5AE9151C6B4277"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a good neighbor agreement (as defined in section 8206(a) of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2113a">16 U.S.C. 2113a(a)</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0dc7dbf055f841f98caa0fa5f7671845"><enum>(I)</enum><text>strategic plans developed by Federal regional commissions, including—</text><clause id="id6b60f84661b74c04a09e3f54bc7e1f27"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Appalachian Regional Commission established by section 14301(a) of title 40, United States Code;</text></clause><clause id="ide1c283d5094d436e984a0e46424ad7e0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Delta Regional Authority established under subtitle F of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2009aa">7 U.S.C. 2009aa et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="id8de8cf5283cb4d908729e00612d7e9d1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Denali Commission established under the Denali Commission Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3121">42 U.S.C. 3121</external-xref> note; title III of division C of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/277">Public Law 105–277</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="id6d814923b90b4169810bd694cd2ce86c"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Northern Border Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(3) of title 40, United States Code;</text></clause><clause id="id8380170759f84872b3296fdae0baee58"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Northern Great Plains Regional Authority established under subtitle G of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2009bb">7 U.S.C. 2009bb et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="iddf4d40d1707348ba8b8ffd203c90df19"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Southeast Crescent Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(1) of title 40, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="id5b8547161f4f444fa047a4fa14103b57"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Southwest Border Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(2) of title 40, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id30EFC537B6C54673938E4768C7239EE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, a Plan shall include—</text><paragraph id="idf290e9bbb7584b21865a712a8d9e4303"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan to coordinate and build capacity across jurisdictions in the applicable area to develop and implement the Plan, including by targeting assistance to high-poverty and other struggling areas within that region;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id63e04d9555994db98619fa0c074f7317"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan that outlines feasible steps and achievable goals, timelines, and strategies for implementing the Plan, including making interjurisdictional agreements that provide for cooperative and coordinated approaches to achieving the goals of the Plan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idef0f3aeaa3f2490c86478910c4a780cc"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a prioritization of projects for funding and implementation, when practicable, including by providing—</text><subparagraph id="id0300F1BEF3E949869712A4938EAD8226"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of each prioritized project proposed to be carried out; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id45BC1A8210EB46F0B4746E93860C8996"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a budget for each project described in subparagraph (A) that includes—</text><clause id="id7CC339F46F7F43D39B0CED22F6D60B73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>preliminary actions that have been or must be taken at the local or regional level to implement the project;</text></clause><clause id="id1E32C21892B44F4E8D055AF584F3B2C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the anticipated Federal share of the cost of the project; and</text></clause><clause id="id1F8DB49129D24A5183518DDB877873C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a description of the source of the non-Federal share of funds or in-kind contributions for the project;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idf7670453c3114ddf97c4184f47dcc6ce"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assessment of current and future trends in the applicable area, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="idc17454c1055040999b258a49257dde78"><enum>(A)</enum><text>population growth or loss, and demographic changes, in the region;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id206b0d2bfff54876b68cebfbfdd1fb26"><enum>(B)</enum><text>accessibility of job centers within the region to public transportation facilities and housing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idaf6e1416e25a4cd1b81e7b3e467423f9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>infrastructure needs in the region, including—</text><clause id="id8DF76E10795D45498CE13173B5A21AAE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>projected water needs and sources;</text></clause><clause id="idB2591B4BE95640FB88E8320E497D4C21"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any need for sewer infrastructure;</text></clause><clause id="id9E5BAF587351456293481E51B886242A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the existence of flood plains;</text></clause><clause id="id8667F22A7B5F49F7B044486093E41F99"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the needs of local and regional food systems, agricultural producers, and value-added agricultural industries; and</text></clause><clause id="id7CD6F8021537408EA4A65203177C9944"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any need for affordable, high-speed internet, including new technologies for mobile internet services and for affordable, reliable cellular phone coverage;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6659d3c3d93d43498a3acbb17ad182fc"><enum>(D)</enum><text>challenges in basic services within the region, including pressing health challenges;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9881dd9cd9c04a0faa1156a31571f326"><enum>(E)</enum><text>skills and education for in-demand, quality jobs and for regional economic development, which may include retraining and education of incumbent or displaced workers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb785e657bb4347fead93b7f50d733f79"><enum>(F)</enum><text>access to private debt and investment capital;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id692886f5df9f405995d1edfd0f915af8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a plan to develop opportunities for economic diversification and innovation within the applicable area, with particular attention to—</text><subparagraph id="id9118FFC21F25409183585F0B79344673"><enum>(A)</enum><text>agricultural diversification and supply chain development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCEEA173933AE4537A8024D23362976CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the conversion of existing businesses to employee or local ownership, such as a cooperative;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9E5DD35D2E78499C8CC90ADE2DE4F93C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>entrepreneurial support;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idC00BDDF2E51240EAB127B8E7FC99CD85"><enum>(D)</enum><text>clean energy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id49950C40AC7046FBBC0DCE4D6B2D10BD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>manufacturing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4B5F98411AD34DD8BBEBA65F55428CAF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>technological innovation;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfe769c7afa8641288b96b31c5d1131ef"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a plan for improving environmental resiliency, efficient land use, remediation of brownfields and other contaminated properties for re-use, mixed-use development, and the preservation of agricultural, green, and open space, including—</text><subparagraph id="id809E5CA767324D7BAE791EEE07E02A61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of projected loss of agricultural and rural land and other green space to development; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id88282560B0974D3F9FA9B06644B04701"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of methods to minimize loss described in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id36ecb53ba5134d14a97f5d0c09e03e0d"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a plan for ensuring that no community or county in the applicable area is excluded from receiving assistance through the rural partnership block grant, including timelines and goals for targeting assistance to high-poverty census tracts included in the area;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id24ee18e34127412e9903bcbf071c6a32"><enum>(8)</enum><text>a plan for building greater collaboration between—</text><subparagraph id="id0f2392c1dd3e4f798f72c26befef914f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>rural population centers and neighboring rural areas of the applicable area; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4e46e35f99b14e1ba4462427286cf96a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the applicable area and neighboring urban areas;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id29431644bf0a4aa7adb58f744ba56192"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a plan for the creation and preservation of workforce housing and affordable, energy-efficient housing for all ages, incomes, races, and ethnicities, including—</text><subparagraph id="idCC6D1EC6DC8C4513BC28FD15AAC1E365"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cooperative housing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idD56652DA45194BB3B0B60DA3D3D8404E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>limited equity cooperative housing;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2996b58b127f406481aec0ca139d2004"><enum>(10)</enum><text>a plan to develop opportunities to revitalize existing communities, including infill development and utilizing existing assets, such as natural assets and public infrastructure; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc9ccd4ad633845e7977021106293c0fa"><enum>(11)</enum><text>such other information or plans as a Council or the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id004BCC70EE2D4446A6B3FB2D7BA17A8E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Approval</header><paragraph id="id783ECC794766438AAD8B55CC8FCB5F13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than annually, each Council shall approve a Plan by a majority vote of the members of the Council for submission to the Secretary for final approval under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3B33573451B94A559BEBB4DAB1B82A82"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Approval by Secretary</header><text>On receipt of a Plan under paragraph (1), the Secretary may approve or disapprove the Plan.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id9A777E1FBEC24808BC63F46B38EA9FD0"><enum>385F.</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><subsection id="id91DF55C7FBFD48E1ABDD73770E239556"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Planning</header><text>During the first 2 years of the term of a rural partnership block grant, a Council may use the funds for comprehensive planning and capacity building to implement a Plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="id753C54D67F7D4A0D950B82DB5AB9C2A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><paragraph id="idB5AA87AE60FC4BC394EFEAFECB767276"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A Council shall use funds under a rural partnership block grant to implement a Plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD40C37D5A2AE47AE9A6699446AA091C7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permissible uses</header><text>In using funds to implement a Plan under paragraph (1), a Council may use the funds—</text><subparagraph id="ida2732e79288147e28151ef05c3b5fd81"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to support the development of critical infrastructure necessary to facilitate economic development in the applicable area, including high-speed internet, including new technologies for mobile internet services and for affordable, reliable cellular phone coverage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id85692fd98c2840518d8fd13cec45a390"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to support activities to achieve greater economic and environmental resiliency, including for emergency preparedness, disaster recovery, and hazard mitigation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc86a2860dc96406cabf366f831fb57e6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to provide assistance to entities within the applicable area that provide basic public services, such as—</text><clause id="idFF9ED5F5C33544A9A97888E71F799FE8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>child care centers;</text></clause><clause id="idF9AD3597987C4BC4911A566BCC0B6C90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nonprofit health care, including community health centers, primary and emergency medical care, mental health, and substance abuse treatment providers;</text></clause><clause id="id69788934BF984F5BAF7DEFB1EDB56174"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>public libraries;</text></clause><clause id="idE2A7BB2825E54948AEE809D3BBCC496F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>community centers;</text></clause><clause id="idF8FDE6707E7042EAB4B6D4AB1BDFF439"><enum>(v)</enum><text>public schools; and</text></clause><clause id="id027A4C2BCFBB4EB387A726D6C4CA2F1A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>nonprofit technology centers, including business incubators and business accelerators;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd353da00caaf49b3a562acf9790098c0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to provide assistance with education, job training, workforce development, or other needs relating to the development and maintenance of a strong workforce and support of youth, unemployed, underemployed, dislocated, disabled, adult, and incumbent workers and individuals with a barrier to employment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfc9199d2155a468ab73354d446ad35c6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to provide assistance in the development of innovative collaborations that link public, private, and philanthropic resources to achieve collaboratively designed regional advancement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id681b40d2cd1048638cbdd732efbccc87"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to promote and use employee ownership, cooperatives, and local ownership in the development of infrastructure, businesses, and community services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8c37e2a282c14187868aa6fcf626c7d5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to acquire, or demolish improvements on, real property;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1e981db82fb448558ba78ca635ee7fc8"><enum>(H)</enum><text>to construct or rehabilitate residential or nonresidential structures;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6A1877A0B6974099AFA5A01F51158B43"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to develop new affordable low-income and workforce housing options that ensure mixed-income development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddbb2df90ff0248fd9e8dbfb51b855d64"><enum>(J)</enum><text>to construct public facilities and improvements, such as water and sewer facilities, streets, community centers, and the conversion of school buildings for other purposes that are eligible for funding under this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id514c67bd6d394b31a35a50112460d3a4"><enum>(K)</enum><text>to establish new connections between rural population centers and neighboring rural areas within the applicable area, and between the applicable area and urban areas, relating to systems such as the supply of clean energy, workforce sheds, food systems, supply chains, commuting patterns, and outdoor recreation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id097e84abd8ea4aa199515d207ad8e1ca"><enum>(L)</enum><text>to carry out activities relating to—</text><clause id="id543415D58E1345AEB79E5A2AA0B55A6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>energy conservation;</text></clause><clause id="id0047F58AEC90492F96685F1542C56207"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the development, storage, and use of clean energy resources; and</text></clause><clause id="id81F2ECF99C324B91B76755C8A2BA3BA8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>bio-based manufacturing;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida3463428d7b34284826612aaa10c325c"><enum>(M)</enum><text>to rebuild and modernize infrastructure and expand investment to support agricultural diversification and supply chain development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id396c3747ce70462baffd3506cd6b2beb"><enum>(N)</enum><text>to promote integrated transportation, housing, energy, and economic development activities carried out across policy areas and governmental jurisdictions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id255422a3516f4d479fa03fcf7e72eeaf"><enum>(O)</enum><text>to coordinate business development, land use, housing, transportation, and infrastructure planning processes across jurisdictions and agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddb553fd57b174056aef2ae71a42fcd16"><enum>(P)</enum><text>to address public health needs, including—</text><clause id="id0106D54EA724468E97A88E0C40108209"><enum>(i)</enum><text>access to mental health and substance abuse services; and</text></clause><clause id="idE7906B70671E49A394FDA90CD28DFED3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access to healthy, locally, and regionally grown foods;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idC47FA68BA88E47B2831572EDA16315A4"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>to encourage entrepreneurship and the scale-up of existing business operations by—</text><clause id="id05a7b3f9e03d4be09c0d094f0b92e5d2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improving access to capital, including market-based financing, such as angel, venture, equity, and equity-like capital;</text></clause><clause id="id49b9514d3a49406583e118526ae5c0c2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>facilitating collaboration between entrepreneurs and institutions of higher education and applied research institutions for the purposes of commercialization of research or adoption of technology or processes;</text></clause><clause id="id3c255063be0e4e38a113bae1ec41c7dd"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>assisting with integration into a supply chain; and</text></clause><clause id="ide65b449d612d492da56c02b2150ae46f"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>providing mentor, networking, and support services for entrepreneurs, including establishing business incubators or accelerators;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id30271c4fbf6d4394945715f9c28c0716"><enum>(R)</enum><text>to develop innovative public and private collaborations for investments in the applicable area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf14f9249b83b408b909e7a7b57a52280"><enum>(S)</enum><text>to use arts and culture for improvements in economic development, education, training, and quality of life;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ddc2874ac264e1c94ffc83aaef44349"><enum>(T)</enum><text>to revitalize downtown corridors and other community centers to create vibrant, mixed-use neighborhoods;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id358dafc6ec4144dba454eaa7306a2e58"><enum>(U)</enum><text>to expand access to domestic and international markets for businesses and agricultural producers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7eb57158114f44b49fd271546549def6"><enum>(V)</enum><text>to lead development programming for organizations or cohorts of organizations included in the Plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf85e58b349b1414abef177c28596958f"><enum>(W)</enum><text>to provide matching funds for other Federal funding if that other Federal funding is for a project that is in accordance with the goals of the Plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id77c0cdb940074fb28f688dd1376405b4"><enum>(X)</enum><text>to promote the use of energy efficiency in applicable projects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6b5d97dcb9b840e59d8e9965ec5a4a00"><enum>(Y)</enum><text>to provide technical assistance for cooperative conversions, startups, and expansions, including education on cooperative governance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id703DA1AC5B00433997837D339EBB245F"><enum>385G.</enum><header>Access to Federal programs</header><subsection id="idDC568C5F12D849F891F4014227A30E45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of rural development program</header><text>In this section, the term <term>rural development program</term> means—</text><paragraph id="idb8d9e309bc8d4659b03df7de15db6d8e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>community facility direct and guaranteed loans under section 306(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id051A8BD8F6FC46278C06B12A11C45A22"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">water or waste disposal grants or direct or guaranteed loans under paragraph (1) or (2) of section 306(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2d65440c77454f02bce9988adc8fc551"><enum>(3)</enum><text>community facility grants under paragraph (19), (20), or (21) of section 306(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD2EB88B02B4044B2B601254D7AD6DF4D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the rural cooperative development grant program established under section 310B(e);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id57E5FB71A37E4122B32222C7E3CB996E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">business and industry guaranteed loans under section 310B(g);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id097E7423EDBA4562A068491BA1D84F4B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the rural microentrepreneur assistance program established under section 379E;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida211a957fb634412990f25c1aba91d22"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the rural broadband access program established under title VI of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4C1EB26343AD4D368BDA2AAB340C4DF2"><enum>(8)</enum><text>value-added producer grants under section 210A(d)(5) of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1627c">7 U.S.C. 1627c(d)(5)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idA46A8DB886074DC4AF77127F6EC676D6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Healthy Food Financing Initiative established under section 243 of the Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6953">7 U.S.C. 6953</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id84DF0843553B4DC6AE23D871E03F7387"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the Rural Energy for America Program established under section 9007 of the Farm Security and Rural Investment Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/8107">7 U.S.C. 8107</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1A3D3396CF1B4103A6FE60498B193081"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the rural energy savings program under section 6407 of the Farm Security and Rural Investment Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/8107a">7 U.S.C. 8107a</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idDA06C462AB6B44F39B70CE1872F4CDF5"><enum>(12)</enum><text>rural rental housing direct loans under section 515 of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1485">42 U.S.C. 1485</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0C7DB9DC80E54CE29CD90A556965D98A"><enum>(13)</enum><text>the housing preservation grant program under section 533 of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1490m">42 U.S.C. 1490m</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idE35555DB01C3495A82CC9A5EA4D14D43"><enum>(14)</enum><text>loan guarantees for multifamily rental housing in rural areas under section 538 of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1490p-2">42 U.S.C. 1490p–2</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6054B403081F427991C7064CAA8CB705"><enum>(15)</enum><text>housing preservation and revitalization demonstration loans and grants provided by the Rural Housing Service; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3E5BD73EC3B6406796453730FBAD3CBA"><enum>(16)</enum><text>multifamily housing transfer and prepayment technical assistance grants provided by the Rural Housing Service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idC2E9F92F2A0B4ED7963C461541CB156F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver of matching funds requirements</header><text>The Secretary shall waive any matching funds requirement under a rural development program for a project that is carried out in an applicable area that is within or comprises a census tract, or a group of contiguous census tracts, that has a poverty rate of 20 percent or greater.</text></subsection><subsection id="id02798FB177E3463EB48EAD74D9354C58"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority consideration for other rural development programs</header><text>The Secretary shall give priority under a rural development program for an application for a project that—</text><paragraph id="id15DC838672F142DDA4127095B35AF502"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is included in and supports a Plan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idBCB28842057842769FB95E3D830FE6D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is eligible for the applicable program from which the funds were set aside; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id56DF6881B4C449A9A900AF382F9C8190"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is carried out in the applicable area covered by the Plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idD9E85397B73341CA9B75580DF5457B1F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other Federal agencies</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, acting as the Chair of the Council on Rural Community Innovation and Economic Development established by section 6306 of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2204b-3">7 U.S.C. 2204b–3</external-xref>), may invite a member of that Council to give priority under the programs carried out by the member for a project that satisfies the criteria described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (c).</text></subsection></section><section id="id8D11F64FC57949F7ADD82F9D474349F6"><enum>385H.</enum><header>Capacity building and technical assistance partners</header><subsection id="idFACB3830BAAD4E75BC13EFAB22E85DC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Capacity building</header><paragraph id="id8C832A0AAB19484D9A78080181752C69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to a Council training, education, support, and advice to enhance the technical assistance, research, organizational, and other capacities of the Council in carrying out activities under the Fund.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idB519F1ECC0BE4B8AB6808C8F01DF8503"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary, in coordination with the Rural Development Innovation Center established by the Secretary of Agriculture or through a contract for services entered into with an eligible technical assistance provider, may provide training, education, support, and advice that addresses—</text><subparagraph id="id0940EA2711734198BC5E4276D07996FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>emergent innovative opportunities that are not covered by an existing Plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCC39C0EA3EF54CA3951FB02498BF450B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>entrepreneurial opportunities to advance the goals of the Fund;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id02C5EC1136264287A2ED2B1E9DBA2845"><enum>(C)</enum><text>opportunities to advance a more integrative rural policy framework for the United States, including building regional connections between urban areas and rural areas;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1816E96682634A70A1795C321C6ABEF0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with support from the Chief Information Officer of the Department of Agriculture, the tracking, collection, and analysis of data and measurements for assessing the progress of Plans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id58E360F6FB524CF29FBC8B19025FACBF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>best practices based on—</text><clause id="idF43078231AD34BB082CA2883041D4CAA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the experiences of Councils; and</text></clause><clause id="id6A3BDD515BCF47D9ACD7F63504F07BE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>domestic and international rural development practices.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ided32905b00e14fa69222aff6eccb03e5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rural Future Leadership Institute</header><paragraph id="idF38776A972A14D96B7178464F44CA9FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a Rural Future Leadership Institute (referred to in this subsection as the <term>Institute</term>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id791E54A14B0A493B8690B20798C5812C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of entities</header><subparagraph id="id30A3484B469A4F92A45D0756257C5936"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the Institute, each year the Secretary shall select individuals to participate in the Institute.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7C2B1B59FF874CBDA70DFB8BF4188D37"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In selecting individuals to participate in the Institute under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall give preference to an individual residing in, or directly assisting, an area represented by a Council.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id49530606A04C4DAEB99E793707CAAE4B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to each individual that is selected to participate in the Institute under paragraph (2) year-long programming such as—</text><subparagraph id="idDD6F14505543429A8FFD5D6D425A340F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>skill-building seminars;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ED64AA160614C6CA08352DA667344AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>best practice reviews;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id686FF3B118B74A9DA789BB13223D9D78"><enum>(C)</enum><text>site visits;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id37DE0B391313448182FD508D5F2D02A0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>performance measurement and data analytics; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idAA8C2F5D3BB3414693FF9152B67189A8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>other training and capacity building activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id8B8D70E926744FBEACB6572953D6F5F6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Peer exchange program</header><text>In carrying out the Institute, the Secretary shall establish a peer exchange program within and across areas represented by Councils to promote industry-leading practices, innovations relating to the organizational development, program delivery, and regional initiatives of the Councils, and opportunities to build collaborative relationships between urban leaders and rural leaders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id66cb16926b4e41d4a9b57c3ad65d51f4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rural Future Corps</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idC61E161C5ABE4C80A4E68A86B778C36D"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definition of AmeriCorps participant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>AmeriCorps participant</term> means a participant under subtitle C of title I of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12571">42 U.S.C. 12571 et seq.</external-xref>) who received an approved national service position provided under section 121(b) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12571">42 U.S.C. 12571(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6B96245FC2B940819180E723F6560FC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Corporation for National and Community Service under section 121(b) of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12571">42 U.S.C. 12571(b)</external-xref>) to establish a Rural Future Corps in which AmeriCorps participants shall serve in areas represented by Councils, to implement the Plans of the Councils, including serving through—</text><subparagraph id="idFDCFBF9A6ABD4D21BF781AF386A7DA96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expansion of critical services such as child care, health, nutrition assistance, education, and job training; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id90CE1459EF5946E780D8F4C180376879"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strengthening the capacity of units of local government and economic, community, and cooperative development organizations to implement community and economic development activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id312caf4baed648449fe8a592b639a0f8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority for AmeriCorps participants from a rural area</header><text>In selecting AmeriCorps participants for the Rural Future Corps established under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall give priority to any individual who resides, or who has resided, in the area in which the individual seeks to serve.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id26857abfaa174bb582dd84803dd684e6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>In carrying out the Rural Future Corps established under paragraph (2), the Secretary, in coordination with the Corporation for National and Community Service, may enter into partnerships with private entities to build regional capacity, recruit participants, and engage in workforce development activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8A2F8011FB994359B51DD167ADECB52F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Retention</header><text>On completion of service of an AmeriCorps participant in the Rural Future Corps, the Secretary shall encourage the retention of the participant in the applicable area in which the participant served.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="idE853650B234449A9AB6770EAEE82DB5B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Relationship to national service programs</header><text>Notwithstanding section 122(a) of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12752">42 U.S.C. 12752(a)</external-xref>), for purposes of that Act, the approved national service positions provided under the agreement for the Rural Future Corps program will be considered to be used to support a national service program under section 122(b) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12572">42 U.S.C. 12572(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id211561B3F27B404CBC81648BE9A3B19B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Chief Information Officer of the Department of Agriculture, shall make publicly available on a website a map of areas represented by Councils, including, with respect to each area, the members of the Council.</text></subsection><subsection id="id644AE64C212A44958FFF4C978F60FBAC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical assistance partners</header><text>The Secretary may enter into a cooperative agreement under section 607(b)(4) of the Rural Development Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2204b">7 U.S.C. 2204b(b)(4)</external-xref>) with an eligible technical assistance provider to provide technical assistance to the Secretary and Councils in carrying out the Fund.</text></subsection></section><section id="id040399FAF47547BE974B375D3A3F1443"><enum>385I.</enum><header>Evaluation and reporting</header><subsection id="id0F0E68E1678940B3A8BDAAD981BC7F25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><text>Not later than the last day of the fourth year of the first rural partnership block grant awarded to a Council, and annually thereafter—</text><paragraph id="id1BFCCB91FC9646D49636B46CF62ACD61"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary shall evaluate the performance of the Council in carrying out the Plan of the Council in relation to the benchmarks established under subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idAA761D12E54C43ADB08B0AC2A4CEEAEB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Council shall use the evaluation under paragraph (1) in updating the Plan under section 385E(d)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id0C695EC9AD9345D1A13EA0D08A168E3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting benchmarks</header><paragraph id="idFB9B978A31394F3ABC8C5DFF07AF4DA5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with Councils and national providers of technical assistance under section 385H(e), shall establish annual reporting benchmarks relating to the purposes of the Fund.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id862B4D83FD054018A437EE9949DBF11A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Existing measures</header><text>In establishing reporting benchmarks under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider relevant existing performance measures used in programs of the rural development mission area—</text><subparagraph id="id433dfae54f8640f583f7053976c3b004"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to achieve alignment with those programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idCECA7A1015BF43F9943685354FC3075F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to allow for opportunities for a partnership block grant to leverage other funding provided under those programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id5336EDF6887648EFBF8FB19FDF97D902"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="id340BFF2E48284B69B5D87412C40B3B3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not less frequently than annually, prepare and submit to Congress a report describing—</text><subparagraph id="id6EBD878C0D5747C392C450F5234F0AB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the implementation of the Fund; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8A4FFADE88DE4152BF57D7AB3238A699"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of future goals for the Fund; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idD281EA48DA514106AE191BF1F06B4980"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include the assessment described in paragraph (1)(B) in the comprehensive rural development strategy under section 607(c) of the Rural Development Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2204b">7 U.S.C. 2204b(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id77439C9C09D44F5694E1C14DB4583C33"><enum>385J.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the Fund $10,000,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2022 through 2026, of which—</text><paragraph id="idFDA01E4314E747FAAAD05EB67D2FC2A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$100,000,000 for each fiscal year shall be used for administrative functions, including staff and information technology infrastructure, of the Rural Innovation and Partnership Administration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4476EA67B4EF4CB68082C15F4E659C9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$40,000,000 for each fiscal year shall be used to carry out section 385H.</text></paragraph></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

