<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9BFE62187429470BAF21D85C052A5302" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4962 IH: Justification and Examination of Transportation Staff's Executive Travel Costs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4962</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To limit the use of Department of Transportation aircraft for travel by the Secretary of Transportation or the Secretary&#8217;s executive staff, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1C98930381C34500B6F1C0C17C515E65" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1E09AF5C0C384218A1137D99EBB687F5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justification and Examination of Transportation Staff's Executive Travel Costs Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>JETSET Costs Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H874EC5D9D9BF4E44B9DF0E02FBA96F18"><enum>2.</enum><header>Executive travel on Department of Transportation aircraft</header> <subsection id="H1F13184330C34C209E423E1B7C2F7CF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Unless the Secretary determines that the cost of a flight to a destination on aircraft owned, operated, or maintained by the Department of Transportation is at least 5 percent less than the cost of a flight on a commercial airline to the destination, neither the Secretary nor the Secretary's executive staff shall travel to such destination on any aircraft owned, operated, or maintained by the Department of Transportation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDFB099F6A8A643178C397FC921CC9CDD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply in any case in which emergency travel is required and commercial service is unavailable after notifying the Inspector General of the Department of Transportation and the appropriate committees of Congress in writing not later than 7 days after such emergency travel is completed.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6054447B3CE64C449093C1902A5614A2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cost comparison</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall revise Order 2500.36N to reflect the true cost of flight operations. When calculating per-seat costs of a flight, the Department of Transportation— </text>
<paragraph id="HE138CB5A915F4126829892E83EE85105"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be prohibited from charging different rates to non-Department of Transportation officials; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H700B98DCF7414ABD88B8909F5B417EF1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall use the actual and full cost of a flight on aircraft owned, operated, or maintained by the Department of Transportation when comparing such flight to any commercial alternative.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2C62E8B694AA4E26AF1E4DABC5E82C5C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Not later than December 31 of calendar year 2023, and each calendar year thereafter, the Inspector General of the Department of Transportation shall submit a report to the appropriate committees of Congress that includes the following with respect to the calendar year:</text> <paragraph id="HA5A454444AF642279A22388C0B609679"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An itemization of each trip and flight in which the Secretary or the Secretary's executive staff traveled on aircraft owned, operated, or maintained by the Department of Transportation.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA43065F79DA845049EE5A67730A3DB78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A justification for any trip and flight included in the itemization required by paragraph (1), including, for each such trip and flight, documentation that the trip and flight was at least 5 percent less than the cost of a flight on a commercial airline to the destination involved.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF616804ED4C74ACB837CE079A2411700"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on personal or political use</header><text>Neither the Secretary nor the Secretary's executive staff shall travel on aircraft owned, operated, or maintained by the Department of Transportation for any trip that involves personal or political activities.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H780D6E1DE9344EE3AAA5135525D190A6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0558B639CB684505AF9A6B17A2999A9A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2420F0AB87644DDBB21F30C6B46C6D0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H759CF844214046D8892E3CD2FA75FB03"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

