<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8F78C79F0A3B4CB0B5AC001F616F2123" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3717 IH: MicroCap Small Business Investing Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3717</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a MicroCap small business investment company designation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDFB4FC96F9F445D3973D64E8F5F50DB4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H49FEDFD31D714568B5B27F2B5EC70D53" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>MicroCap Small Business Investing Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD0BCFCD8C5D54BA2B6D8836D84CE8CB8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>MicroCap small business investment company designation</header> <subsection id="H4145B149F3D9400987F45F46D8114FAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6804487174564FB29B11F54118D355D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 301(c), by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1EC225062D34458B56DAA937AF7C9EB"> <paragraph id="HD36C0751001D4C47AF813EF6016116FA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>MicroCap small business investment company license</header> <subparagraph id="H5FB84698E1364C11AD71C1575FCE353A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Administrator may approve an application and issue not more than 10 licenses annually under this subsection with respect to any applicant— </text> 
<clause id="H69D42DB7C616454D90AD91DEDD097FA6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that would otherwise be issued a license under this subsection, except that the management of the applicant does not satisfy the qualification requirements under paragraph (3)(A)(ii) to the extent that such requirements relate to investment experience and track record, including any such requirements further set forth in section 107.305 of title 13, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation; </text></clause> <clause id="HFBBFF30D5C7E4D85834DE1E73E0E4069"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for which the fund managers have—</text> 
<subclause id="H7A731BC3698842CF9A144466AE50DB21"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a documented record of successful business experience;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA05516395FDA452B9511BF80A5FBC1A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a record of business management success; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA952FD06B647438E977527B907B0CD3A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>knowledge in the particular industry or business in which the investment strategy is being pursued; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HB74B9E4CD07944759DD6F1E4AE4584BA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that, in addition to any other requirement applicable to the applicant under this title or the rules issued to carry out this title (including section 121.301(c)(2) of title 13, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation), will make not less than 25 percent of its investments in— </text> 
<subclause id="H2BB640D7EA934FE98229825EA1380183"><enum>(I)</enum><text>low-income communities, as that term is defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45D">section 45D(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; </text></subclause> <subclause id="HB8D86560F26A44D6B83D28AD9FD406A7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a community that has been designated as a qualified opportunity zone under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">section 1400Z–1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8F2CF6B55E4F4962906FBB5511D23A80"><enum>(III)</enum><text>businesses primarily engaged in research and development;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBEF14CD4F5564FE1917846DCF8AB43FA"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>manufacturers;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7915A1511E7840EDB817A89B630EB571"><enum>(V)</enum><text>businesses primarily owned or controlled by individuals in underserved communities before receiving capital from the applicant; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H49DD2376FAE94720A594FC52958A496B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>rural areas, as that term is defined by the Bureau of the Census.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7A9A46894F6343E5A8C55DBF961088A9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority; streamlined process</header><text>With respect to an application for a license pursuant to this paragraph, the Administrator shall—</text> <clause id="HB534B3CB3AD24167946D2AC9B05F88BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>give priority to an applicant for such a license that is located in an underlicensed State; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE96369A271D44C0BA6295CBA2A1DA7AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish a streamlined process for applicants submitting such an application.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0021BDF027EC4B2F96052C7378897654"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Timing for issuance of license</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (2), with respect to an application for a license submitted to the Administrator pursuant to this paragraph, the Administrator shall— </text> 
<clause id="H09B30887B9B34FF3A11F45E60FD341E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after the date on which the application is submitted to the Administrator, process and provide complete feedback with respect to any pre-license application requirements applicable to the applicant; </text></clause> <clause id="H2170AD8D46C24B938CC44D0EF044389F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not restrict the submission of any application materials; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H75A2F29D5DAC481391E0FE7876DD39A4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date on which the application is submitted to the Administrator— </text> <subclause id="H9717C22DF4B547B5843F3C4C4B978B7E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>approve the application and issue a license for such operation to the applicant, if the requirements for the license are satisfied; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H163135E46769493590C5EBCEE0AF9F43"><enum>(II)</enum><text>based upon facts in the record— </text> <item id="H51960D17A2E44152AF874ED86A0FE911"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>disapprove the application; and </text></item> 
<item id="H47D28E84C0FF4FB4AC7F068D608918CF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>provide the applicant with— </text> <subitem id="HF68C2795AA014516860A84611CBA6797"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>a clear, written explanation of the reason for the disapproval; and </text></subitem> 
<subitem id="H2FAFDC0999E7466D807C3FC779C5DB90"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a chance to remedy any issues with the application and immediately reapply, with technical assistance provided as needed and a new determination made by the Administrator not later than 30 days after the date on which the applicant re-submits the application.</text></subitem></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DBE490BC01949BEAD2B03E655F96BE5"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Leverage</header><text>A company licensed pursuant to this paragraph shall— </text> 
<clause id="H43DDF152BBD14D06AEA979EDAA62A16A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not be eligible to receive leverage in an amount that is more than $25,000,000; and </text></clause> <clause id="H6B4F4D88360C4670A7232E475DF422FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access leverage in an amount that is not more than 100 percent of the private capital of the applicant. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F89545E9D4546D69924100B1F018455"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Investment committee</header> 
<clause id="HA7177C0691824F1B83BB06D28A7E657D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each company licensed pursuant to this paragraph shall have not fewer than 2 independent members on the investment committee of the company in a manner that complies with the following requirements:</text> <subclause id="H6E4039A831D14732AE85C9E24ACE39D4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The independent members of the investment committee are or have been licensed managers of small business investment companies within the preceding 10-year period.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1C2C632922B44A9CA1A588D4617D7B80"><enum>(II)</enum><text>No small business investment company described in subclause (I) may adversely affected by the relationship of the independent members of the investment committee with the company licensed pursuant to this paragraph.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H06BC7C652602487E801653627A4606D6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The independent members of the investment committee are required to approve each investment made by the company.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB909965C316344F18AE9442FCAAE4DFC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The independent members of the investment committee shall not be paid a management fee, but may receive paid expenses and a portion of any carried interest.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H32337E26C1FA491B9C2D2870A3E2094C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Leverage limits</header><text>Any leverage associated with a company licensed pursuant to this paragraph shall not be counted toward the leverage limits of the independent members of the investment committee of the company under this title.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H59381252765E4A28B2982EB76CE9B862"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 303(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/683">15 U.S.C. 683(d)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>(or, with respect to a company licensed under section 301(c)(5), 50 percent)</quote> after <quote>25 percent</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H002FC0CFFD474C55A8E72BAC3C285A68"><enum>(b)</enum><header>SBA requirements</header> <paragraph id="HC1BE585BC491493395FB563800CC645F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8FE290E8297440E987D71DF4B2557A41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Small Business Administration; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAE3A4035B20F4F3DB74B5F6028E02705"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered company</term> means an entity that is licensed to operate as a small business investment company pursuant to paragraph (5) of section 301(c) of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681(c)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6FB89AF695D4C998A33D7D4F30D1CAA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rules</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall issue rules to carry out this section and the amendments made by this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H999C3D8EDAE847D8A69A3B50CCF8250C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Administrator shall publicly publish a report that details, for the year covered by the report—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA98D4EBADD2C4AADBA77C71FD807C872"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of covered companies licensed by the Administrator;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC99D3DBC35DB4D82887BF359A6FDA0D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the industries in which covered companies have invested;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H05EB9C61359244B0BA6A1921D512BACC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the geographic locations of covered companies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2983D5281359420B9A6C751199B570A6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the aggregate performance of covered companies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


