<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H65256450D2B2422C814A4218E2253003" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 927 IH: Supreme Court Ethics Act.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 927</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 28, United States Code, to provide for a code of conduct for justices and judges of the courts of the United States, establish an ethics investigations counsel, and require disclosure of recusals.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE195E48AA307421883C0CD9E4C9DD602" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H708A32F89D0A49A58C03683BBFCC3DDA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supreme Court Ethics Act.</short-title></quote></text></section> <section id="H45E2D19B479E4499BFDF641D40B26C4B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Code of conduct</header> <subsection id="HC6AABC729B614A18ADA2E52CD865D60C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/57">Chapter 57</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H87E6F0A9CCC74D979FC1C7236D55BECA" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H7542A00A7376410CB52A1BC43DC3EE16"><enum>964.</enum><header>Code of conduct</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Judicial Conference of the United States shall issue a code of conduct, which applies to each justice and judge of the courts of the United States, except that the code of conduct may include provisions that are applicable only to certain categories of judges or justices.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HEEF87E3BD63A43E796C9D0AE0136FDF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding after the item related to section 963 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H23A174AADB5F47DFBF86F54E498A6DA1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">964. Code of conduct.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H564486FEB85C430C8625264B2F34EFBE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of ethics investigations counsel and reporting protocol</header> 
<subsection id="HE0840E8A305F4AA48366B7B1166AF436"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the Judicial Conference of the United States issues a code of conduct under section 964 of title 28, United States Code, as added by section 2(a) of this Act, the Supreme Court of the United States shall appoint and fix the compensation of an Ethics Investigations Counsel who shall adopt rules providing for the enforcement of the code of conduct, including a process to receive from the public information about potential violations of the code of conduct by justices of the Supreme Court.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD24706B38BEB4A388935A72184339DEF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The Ethics Investigation Counsel shall serve a term of 4 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H531FED1AEF534F43ABDD5BA1F93591FA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>The Ethics Investigation Counsel may be removed for cause by the Supreme Court of the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H696541A15058426CB46257D16F574DD8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Process</header><text>The process shall include the establishment of a method for the submission of the information described in subsection (a) in electronic form.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H53625476E1424BC0BC15D14BE7A42B9E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Investigations</header><text>The Ethics Investigations Counsel appointed under this section shall conduct investigations into potential violations of the code of conduct described in section 964 of title 28, United States Code, as added by section 2(a) of this Act, and other conduct prejudicial to the ethical, effective, and expeditious administration of the business of the Supreme Court of the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6A008FD5F23D40E0A3E905D8EA30EEEB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assistants</header><text>The Ethics Investigations Counsel appointed under this section may, with the approval of the Chief Justice of the United States, appoint necessary assistants and fix their compensation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5C24ECDB68CE4D708E9A762684FFE6AF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Ethics Investigations Counsel appointed under this section shall issue an annual public report describing the complaints described in subsection (a) and any steps taken to investigate, resolve, or rehabilitate the conduct detailed in the complaint.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H7D121B6D50C64D48A586E9A8C1DBF901"><enum>4.</enum><header>Recusal of justices</header> <subsection id="H076FC2BAC4534C19B92B50DE7A965AF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any case in which a justice of the Supreme Court of the United States disqualifies himself or herself in a proceeding under section 455 of title 28, United States Code, the justice shall disclose in the public record of the proceeding the reasons for the disqualification.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCF4D279D23DC4842A86F211F56D5A141"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Denial of motion To disqualify</header><text>If a justice of the Supreme Court of the United States denies a motion brought by a party to a proceeding before the Court that the justice should be disqualified in the proceeding under section 455 of title 28, United States Code, the justice shall disclose in the public record of the proceeding the reasons for the denial of the motion.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

