<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6A72690FA4C04417BCF82E8E881B4DA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4526 IH: Smart Ship Repair Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4526</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230710">July 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure fairness and transparency in the processes used by the Navy to award contracts for ship maintenance and repair, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1FFEF4160A534B57A53CEAFEA4616509" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H575028108DF14F0DB2AC1139BCE374A3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Smart Ship Repair Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDFEDC6706D544783A64CDF037192ADC3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on use of Government-operated drydocks</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of the Navy shall ensure that no Government-operated drydock is eligible to compete for the award of a contract for private sector non-nuclear surface ship maintenance unless the Secretary determines, in accordance with section 2466 of title 10, United States Code, that there is not sufficient private sector dock competition.</text></section> 
<section id="H28C4B39668074600B8763B5A859C97AB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study on price differentials used in Navy ship repair solicitations</header> 
<subsection id="HDF15C3EF20FA41D99525E514DF9AEB43"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Secretary of the Navy shall seek to enter into an agreement with a federally funded research and development center to conduct a study to assess whether relevant price differentials used by the Navy in ship repair solicitations accurately reflect the true market value of the activity undertaken to complete the repair work involved in the absence of any such differential.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC05A01F85D3A456C8C7A856324839AA8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study under subsection (a) shall address all relevant price differentials used by the Navy in ship repair solicitations, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3E5949EC003D4EA8BC5299A559339615"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the use of government owned and operated dry docks;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E9E9340F1CF4B8EBE9E6C2386EC4962"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the use of inter-port differentials; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD4A92868F52B45E0AD2C4EE8A728EDED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the use of pier differentials.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA6042C84E1BA4AC3B9C70C74DB93808A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="H746FD873E1C64A509E0AA63D7B02B321"><enum>(1)</enum><header>FFRDC Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The federally funded research and development center that conducts the study under subsection (a) shall submit to the Secretary of the Navy a report on the results of the study.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AC30D7B42E84A589ED72038042CEE4D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submittal to Congress</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2024, the Secretary of the Navy shall submit to the congressional defense committees an unaltered copy of the report received by the Secretary under paragraph (1) together with a separate statement of the views of the Secretary on the results of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H35B21B75E43C4FE8A7F50C09B3220EC9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report on Navy policy for soliciting coastwide bids for certain repair availabilities</header> <subsection id="HF6CEC44DDDD448BA9EA09545E9EDD166"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than March 30, 2024, the Secretary of the Navy shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on the policy of the Navy for soliciting coastwide bids for repair availabilities longer than 10 months.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H67090E947EB8407081712C6665C71557"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall explain and assess each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="HAB2765AA147F415C97F7EDDBC8C11BFB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The intent of the policy described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6E05550CCD3B476880F5847E1AFD01D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The data the Navy uses to assess the efficacy of such policy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF80053980A4442D0906F83F0DB787189"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How the Navy estimates the cost of moving vessels out of their home port to complete the availability and the actual cost of moving vessels out of their home port to complete the availability.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF098C23789284B34B9EAEBB27E76F411"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How the Navy estimates the financial, labor force, servicemember and family well-being, berthing, and related costs associated with moving a vessel out of its home port to complete a repair availability longer than 10 months.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H004C7F04AF2C4FA2880AEEA6EC4CF2A3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report on use of Government docks for ship repair and maintenance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">On an annual basis, the Secretary of the Navy shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H91A3E86B29194B7FA659A742E543AA78"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies each instance in the year preceding the date of the report in which the Navy used a Government dock for a ship repair and maintenance availability when sufficient capacity was available in private docks during the period in which such repairs and maintenance were expected to be performed; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81428C077D484B4081674301F5091FD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each such instance, provides an explanation of the reasons the Navy used a Government dock rather than a private dock.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H9733B78852F348069945619118093DE2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

