<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF0319E8A0BE4479FAEAA92C032FD43F5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4238 IH: Stop Illegal Reentry Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4238</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to increase penalties for individuals who illegally reenter the United States after being removed, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE3FA183E43AD436796BCFC71444E0DA0" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H485A8D07AB6C484FB729BA2E1B1372EA"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short titles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Illegal Reentry Act</short-title></quote> or as <quote><short-title>Kate's Law</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDA85030C518B4F80A17F3EB2DD3EE225"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increased penalties for reentry of removed alien</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 276 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1326">8 U.S.C. 1326</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H457436034BDD427E85C3A9FD996E9DAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subsections (c) and (d) as subsections (d) and (e), respectively;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE6A8655EAEB1417ABA1FFDBD95224C42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (a) and (b) and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB074BFC65E1D463FA0FF7D6315F0A753">
<subsection id="H25C71616CCBF4F9FAA551770A3A78A06"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsections (b) and (c), any alien who—</text> <paragraph id="H7FDEDE6D4C19496D9468390AAFD1AAAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has been denied admission, excluded, deported, or removed or has departed the United States while an order of exclusion, deportation, or removal is outstanding; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD875400FB5A9488986C9735AEE8CC1CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">thereafter enters, attempts to enter, or is at any time found in, the United States, unless—</text> <subparagraph id="HF3417A695F6E4E0B9B57A71BF55989D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prior to the alien’s reembarkation at a place outside the United States or the alien’s application for admission from foreign contiguous territory, the Secretary of Homeland Security has expressly consented to such alien’s reapplying for admission; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF65979F13DA44172A8C39CEDBC39B741"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to an alien previously denied admission and removed, such alien shall establish that the alien was not required to obtain such advance consent under this Act or any prior Act,</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both. </continuation-text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3A4F49D457F0468F9F52EC5BA3660F44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criminal penalties for reentry of certain removed aliens</header> <paragraph id="H7AAE4BE0239C47958A1F96D489753BC8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the penalty under subsection (a), and except as provided in subsection (c), an alien described in subsection (a)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB36E07DFBA0E4A68949617A93C528D2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who was convicted before such removal or departure of 3 or more misdemeanors involving drugs, crimes against the person, or both, or a felony (other than an aggravated felony), shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned not more than 10 years, or both;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC2DDB0233684126A2027B361376AB5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has been excluded from the United States pursuant to section 235(c) because the alien was inadmissible under section 212(a)(3)(B) or who has been removed from the United States pursuant to title V, and who thereafter, without the permission of the Secretary of Homeland Security, enters the United States, or attempts to do so, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, and imprisoned for a period of 10 years, which sentence shall not run concurrently with any other sentence;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5D97E050860341998E5146ED7F6A16A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who was removed from the United States pursuant to section 241(a)(4)(B) who thereafter, without the permission of the Secretary of Homeland Security, enters, attempts to enter, or is at any time found in, the United States, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned for not more than 10 years, or both; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDEFD5860A94240399D37DBB06182678B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has been denied admission, excluded, deported, or removed 3 or more times and thereafter enters, attempts to enter, crosses the border to, attempts to cross the border to, or is at any time found in the United States, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned not more than 10 years, or both.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B3690C9C4184D58B5625591D1AA03E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Removal defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection and in subsection (c), the term <term>removal</term> includes any agreement in which an alien stipulates to removal during (or not during) a criminal trial under either Federal or State law.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2B9F67C2E94040FC80601FD0CF02D3F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mandatory minimum criminal penalty for reentry of certain removed aliens</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the penalties provided in subsections (a) and (b), an alien described in subsection (a)—</text>
<paragraph id="H9DD3D74850264664A791B466A9825312"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who was convicted before such removal or departure of an aggravated felony; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD85DFFC1840F4A32BE1F559AD2B00911"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who was convicted at least two times before such removal or departure of illegal reentry under this section,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">shall be imprisoned not less than five years and not more than 20 years, and may, in addition, be fined under title 18, United States Code.</continuation-text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H13451A37E34043E7B03300085384B564"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d), as redesignated by paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCADFA268D9414B0EB446D49A07CD3708"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>section 242(h)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 241(a)(4)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H933C22AB44E24E82923BB595A5D9E4F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Attorney General</quote> and inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

