<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6C7130A1441548EFA2FA70632C4B259B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4270 IH: Public School Green Rooftop Program</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4270</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Energy Policy and Conservation Act to authorize State energy conservation plans to include programs to provide grants for planning, designing, and installing green roofs on elementary school and secondary school buildings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFA9374BA862946859D0381002C732F7A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEF3F92E2C51A49AB867BBF1399C7297B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Public School Green Rooftop Program</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H706B534C78084AEB8662DB135B52C795" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0A03402EB3F94D468CC9AC317A46A0ED" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Department of Energy recognizes green roof technology is an effective, practical way to increase the energy performance of buildings.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B7253B1ACAF4E94B0E4ED4E9777D199" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Environmental Protection Agency acknowledges green roofs can reduce building energy use compared to conventional roofs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84C664621141484B8C9FD9B8153C4BE1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Greater weatherization and insulation offered by green roofs reduce the demand for electrical power needed to moderate the temperature of a building, as roofs can be the source of the greatest heat loss in the winter and heat gain in the summer in buildings.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40105D10EA08499EB595DF477CC066DB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Green roofs can produce greater energy efficiency on elementary school and secondary school buildings than on other structures because the dimensions of school buildings are unique and often have a significantly greater width than height.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43CB990E086A4439987D53615D295584" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The General Services Administration recognizes green roofs can last 40 years or more before requiring replacement compared to 10 to 15 years for a conventional roof.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H928D801563ED405C8572B2B32E4CFCF9" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The General Services Administration (GSA), Department of Energy, and Environmental Protection Agency all recognize the integral role of maintenance in a green roof’s continued energy efficiency benefits and cost savings, and the GSA Public Buildings Service accordingly provides ongoing maintenance training to maximize the benefits of green roofs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2E09C604161499E849456D5D62952B4" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Green roofs can provide economic benefits, including decreased energy costs, water use, stormwater runoff, landfill waste, and building operating expenses that can save taxpayers money.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6581D04FC61D473DB162CBCF65C7B8B9" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Green roofs can provide annual cost savings per square foot of the roof’s surface.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H484D9BE779B94B26A38A2A2DC05212AA" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Green roofs on educational facilities can provide accessible sites to teach students at all levels of education about various subjects including science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM), biodiversity, ecology, urban agriculture, stormwater management, sustainability, art, technology, and more.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC3856C89602649DE887C65690D8FF253" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Planning, designing, installing, and maintaining green roofs can generate employment opportunities for properly trained personnel, while specialized green roofs can also provide employment opportunities for urban agriculture operations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H62C4A19BEA1B461789F7F5401996B84D" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The Environmental Protection Agency, in collaboration with Green Roofs for Healthy Cities, acknowledges landscape architects as leaders in planning and designing green roofs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1281D4656A54EC7BE13895F1FD27D13" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Green roofs can help stabilize neighborhoods by providing community-wide benefits, including those that address public health, food security, urban development, and economic growth.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H272390D5E46046B085C6153E06C19DAC" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><text>By improving air and water quality and mitigating excess heat, among other benefits, green roofs can improve public health and lessen healthcare system stressors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2BB30533F57E4ED0AA6C54496182E931" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Green roofs can help reduce the impacts of climate change, including extreme heat and poor air quality, by sequestering harmful carbon and other pollutants in the atmosphere.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1DD348B61EC84A61B92FB818D024A76B" commented="no"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Green roofs can reduce the urban heat island effect and city-wide ambient temperatures by up to 5°F because green roof temperatures can be 30 to 40°F lower than those of conventional roofs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3743C199A3264826B2200557DF060A7B" commented="no"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration determined indoor summer building temperatures were cooler for buildings with green roofs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38CCDB3B7F8546E3A0E6B3E84DA3BAF9" commented="no"><enum>(17)</enum><text>As living systems, green roofs retain rainwater in the soil, plants, and drainage layer and therefore can reduce stormwater runoff rates by up to 65 percent and delay the time at which runoff occurs, resulting in decreased stress on sewer systems and streams at peak flow periods and decreased pollution in United States waterways.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA337E1A344C4A11B5FFD8F2629D2D89" commented="no"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Green roofs can enhance environmental justice by addressing the disproportionate impacts of excess heat and adding much-needed green space to the built environment in underserved communities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H575806AE262D42B99BB0CF368D94486E" commented="no"><enum>(19)</enum><text>Green roofs can enhance biodiversity by providing and creating habitats for various plants and wildlife such as pollinators and migratory birds.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HEE3D6121B7C4448E8D889AEBDE5C32FE" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Green roof grant programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 362 of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6322">42 U.S.C. 6322</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE13381601FD349CBB4996EA8B39563F7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCF03D36FCFC94688A4F06AFACAA0545D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (17), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD271AE25EE34657ADF43D1E1AAA2D8F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (18) as paragraph (19); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED57E7C5E6F14B688FDF6959EE233E58" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (17) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H504D13B485A84289B78C9443CA3674BD" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H400EC29193A74854BE684589FAA677F9" commented="no"><enum>(18)</enum><text>in accordance with subsection (h), programs to provide financial assistance, including grants, for planning, designing, installing, maintaining, and monitoring green roofs on elementary school and secondary school buildings; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD92226A81B1B443AA35970554268A15B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H68613960814540D289B1F1739DE45D87" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H82913DA53A5E468BAC6B07E6CC5FAA0F" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Green roof grant programs</header> 
<paragraph id="HFF25B7B7870B497FB3E6B73A14D3A3D5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants for planning assistance</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD7FA8F834023464FBB1CBD7495FDB0B7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Grant programs</header><text>Under a program to provide financial assistance as provided for under subsection (d)(18), a State may make grants to eligible entities to pay the costs of planning and design assistance for a green roof as described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H05CD492B83294DA69DFD971D7B658B2C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Allowable use of funds for grants for planning assistance</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant pursuant to subparagraph (A) may use the grant for any of the following purposes:</text> 
<clause id="H843C220027434319BA8A06CF773E3BA3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Identification of opportunities to use green roofs on elementary school and secondary school buildings, including performing site analyses for locating green roofs.</text></clause> <clause id="H699D23D3DFBF48048EB6193657B79F23" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Determination of, and plans to obtain, permits relating to a green roof on an elementary school or secondary school building.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H5411AAC138B34CF3AD2FC817CAFAE36C" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Architectural, landscape architectural, and engineering analysis for a green roof on an elementary school or secondary school building, including—</text> <subclause id="HCB851588CC084B619DD89B6A1B5E39B3" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">plans for assessing the structural loading capacity of the elementary school or secondary school building, accounting for vegetation; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB631949B2C344177A45D258451EBBDA1" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">design services, including the creation of design plans and construction documents for a green roof on the elementary school or secondary school building.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H7D3C6E47426D40F7B320E624ABC7FEB9" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cost estimation of the planning, designing, installing, and maintaining of a green roof on an elementary school or secondary school building, including an energy savings analysis.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H503F7A0E14F942A9B5C6B1C8E0DFA312" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Administrative costs, including reimbursement for grant writing services used to obtain a grant under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA45BE1F75D348CE9FDE7D2A3C0E8419" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public school green roof installation grant program</header> <subparagraph id="H41CAD7534FF340C5BB6D2D78146B5F3A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Public school green roof installation program</header><text>Under a program to provide financial assistance as provided for under subsection (d)(18), a State may award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to carry out projects to install a green roof on an elementary school or secondary school building.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H29B73E79F3EF4C4CA08B8928BE671910" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive a grant pursuant to subparagraph (A), an eligible entity shall submit to a State an application—</text> <clause id="H93D00AE845DA4432935113336A4816BB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>at such time, and in such manner, as the State may require;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8DABD51EFA4E493F8D45696D37957E68" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that includes—</text> <subclause id="HB7B8E2186B6048A49C2AC47E20C4EBC7" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a strategy for increasing energy efficiency and reducing heat reflection of the applicable elementary school or secondary school building; </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0A5885F5C70346E1AA0DB65145282DC7" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description and methodology of the eligible entity’s plan for the installation, operation, and maintenance of a green roof on an elementary school or secondary school building, including a plan to meet the requirements of title III of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq);</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA587FC459E8346B8A6075913512389EF" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a letter of compliance from each applicable local regulatory body that documents the green roof is planned and designed, and will be constructed in accordance with local standards and regulations, including occupancy, fire, stormwater compliance, and building codes;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEF0B81792E9747A2B7DBFB4FE36F9675" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>cost estimation of the planning, designing, installing, and maintaining of the green roof on the elementary school or secondary school building, including an energy savings analysis; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9CF836BAE0694635B2CE0FF66A0B78E8" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the hiring criteria and qualifications for personnel to design, construct, install, and maintain the green roof, including a plan for hiring—</text> 
<item id="HF0A7780B676A45E1BA50666EB6201882" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>local workforce trainees; </text></item> <item id="HFCC5AE001D1348DA8032A5B544F41C4E" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>at least one Green Roof Professional as accredited by the Green Roof Industry Association, or a professional licensed by a State or an appropriate accreditation; and</text></item> 
<item id="HE654C3901F82449D84884E20B7FDDDD8" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">low-income individuals, individuals registered with a one-stop center, and returning citizens.</text></item></subclause></clause> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB4B01E04859C4B8AAFE1246425BED0EA" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants pursuant to subparagraph (A), a State shall give priority to—</text> 
<clause id="H9BB0A56F3422456EB754C62A76B94A0A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>projects to install a green roof on buildings of elementary schools and secondary schools in which not fewer than 30 percent of students are from households with incomes below the poverty line;</text></clause> <clause id="H3901401BD9DB4CC2AB50BDE144C0E616" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>projects that meet minimum performance and nationally recognized standards for green roofs and walls, including—</text> 
<subclause id="H5A3E56F02DC44E61AE8D2D6805289D6F" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Living Architecture Performance Tool;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H699F23FDE1EE4F6AACE1885D42E46282" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Sustainable SITES Initiative®; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF0BD95FB5DFF4F728B09A5D8F1CA1D10" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other nationally recognized standards; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H140DC93C00C64405862A5180147BB142" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">projects to install a green roof on buildings of elementary schools and secondary schools located in a nonattainment area (as defined in section 171(2) of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7501">42 U.S.C. 7501(2)</external-xref>).</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H67DAB4B525044C99A11D1E309DDAD90F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Installation</header><text>Not later than 4 years after receiving a grant pursuant to subparagraph (A), an eligible entity shall complete installation of a green roof.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3C64653CB31B46F58DF0DDBE69687DD3" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Maintenance and monitoring of infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under a program described in subparagraph (A), in addition to receiving a grant under to install a green roof under such program, each eligible entity that meets the installation requirements of subparagraph (D) may receive additional funding for a 5-year period for maintenance and monitoring activities relating to the green roof, which activities may include the following:</text> 
<clause id="H4C4782823E6E4383B0BABF32F6317FA6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Monitoring and evaluating energy performance and cost savings of the green roof.</text></clause> <clause id="HB4FBE74F9A8D45B7BA84976E7B3A1288" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Monitoring and evaluating air temperature of the green roof.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H58E1431343C543BD8BBE33FA0647ABB2" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Conducting routine inspections throughout the year to assess the condition of the green roof, including plant health and replanting alternatives in consultation with a landscape architect, horticulturalist, agronomist, or other landscape professional as appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5ED1BB59276419F882A08F93AFB58F6" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HED04E830E5CE4E8AAAD72DE5D50664C7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Elementary school</header><text>The term <term>elementary school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE3D629D5E9B74940B5C558DC261DADCF" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> 
<clause id="H5FD8F5F83CDB4E53A9FCE28E2618F57D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a public elementary school or secondary school;</text></clause> <clause id="HB5B3E3D0982B415F93E26E5D96596DF3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a local educational agency; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H081FB8D762F843BBBD98F6EE6CABE724" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a partnership between a nonprofit organization and an entity described in clause (i) or (ii).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA081B3163B324532AE738973D7CAB676" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Green roof</header><text>The term <term>green roof</term> means a layer of vegetation planted over a waterproofing system or waterproof management practice that is installed on top of a flat or slightly–sloped roof that may support plant growth, including—</text> 
<clause id="HA07B6C25443A447E99955A2CD8B6D7DB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an extensive green roof with a growing media layer that is up to 6 inches thick; or</text></clause> <clause id="H5B60963CBE3B4CC1A20412A44EE80D3D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an intensive green roof with a growing media layer that is 6 to 48 inches thick.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H06549EEAAC874FA0A92FE32A2066215C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8460043FFAC74A3284E6F0E212F70923" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Low-income individual</header><text>The term <term>low-income individual</term> means, with respect to any calendar year, any individual who lives in a household that has a gross income that does not exceed 300 percent of the poverty line.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H53E2B57676FD47D389FA13C50CDC3EBF" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 which is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6441A9755FCB4F5799D58AE79C65E645" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><header>One-stop center</header><text>The term <term>one-stop center</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9BBD2D1A61D64FD8A209E3DC664E5628" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Poverty line</header><text>The term <term>poverty line</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDA9A39AE1EDB44B98D34A4556AAAB796" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Secondary school</header><text>The term <term>secondary school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

