<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H86986A5142A14D3EB0F4FD90DB2F84BC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 57 IH: Protecting Personal Data from Foreign Adversaries Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 57</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To regulate or prohibit transactions using mobile applications or software programs that engage in the theft of user data on behalf of a communist country, foreign adversary, or state sponsor of terrorism, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6311D62EAD47411E8F6CD8A0B66D6F6F" style="OLC"><section id="HB298263DA13B457088F7E91297021594" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Personal Data from Foreign Adversaries Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H745AA4B9450343F6955CFBDA63D3AA27"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorities to regulate or prohibit transactions using mobile applications or software programs that engage in the theft of user data on behalf of a communist country, foreign adversary, or state sponsor of terrorism</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE9C08B12019940D38387E1520D7D846D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DF4753F2EB5429C8BB42975F33D446D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="HEB748C6DB4A74FF39D2B49C8DF4F87AD" style="OLC"><subsection id="H45B0BE18EED5402D9C2DA24FD5888169"><enum>(c)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF3B3B61F42C8436B9D9542FEB412F5EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b), the authority granted to the President by this section includes the authority to regulate or prohibit transactions using mobile applications or software programs that—</text><subparagraph id="H50631BF652F443B59CEFDCE4CBA88967" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>engage in the theft of or transmits a user’s data in an unauthorized manner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4BCE8A45E094FD2B182E10C4EB41C1A" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide to a covered country, or covered foreign political party, access to such data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF88D4DF4658B45F59D73053D2226C0F5" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>covered country</quote> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H15BB7C1AAED048998CD6EDDB65182718"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A Communist country.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF000248B2844F5197C6FD8EE545D826"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A foreign adversary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20EE3CA84F75431E938E2AC417862F12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A state sponsor of terrorism.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H799C4D807DA146D48760F9CFFDFB9648" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="HDC1DF7871FBF4EB6AE29E3EC972DA3FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <quote>communist country</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 620(f)(1) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2370">22 U.S.C. 2370(f)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67FBE7A5DD9249089979C604F2DBA15F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <quote>foreign adversary</quote> has the meaning given such term in Executive Order 13920, issued on May 1, 2020, entitled <quote>Securing the United States BulkPower System</quote>, and including the list of foreign adversaries identified by the Department of Energy’s Office of Electricity pursuant to such Executive Order on July 7, 2020, as in effect on January 19, 2021.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F76662F24DA46D0911B34822C45CD5C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <quote>state sponsor of terrorism</quote> means a country the government of which the Secretary of State determines has repeatedly provided support for international terrorism pursuant to—</text><clause id="H00FFDE9EAC5D4FB2874ED0CE45C548AC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>section 1754(c)(1)(A) of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4813">50 U.S.C. 4813(c)(1)(A)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="HAC5916F0A5D14EDE96807710265F9FFB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="HA17DF1E549F14B84BD120B567FC22E17"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="H49724F3FF0E4423C8835C3CDFA39B6E7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other provision of law.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6BF43EB116E4B11995FB7EE94438544"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>covered foreign political party</quote> means the Chinese Communist Party (CCP).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HD558E4F9565444AB9697479638E20230"><enum>3.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to mobile applications or software programs that engage in the theft of user data</header><subsection id="H8A015C191F0145E1AEA06F801BD8FEAF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the President is authorized to impose the sanctions described in subsection (b) with respect to any foreign person that the President determines has developed, maintains, provides, owns, or controls a mobile application or software program that—</text><paragraph id="H4567E43888AE459EB74053DCD73074FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>engages in the theft of or transmits a user’s data in an unauthorized manner to servers located in China; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48D0BAE463DC4F84B7A052F6392FE034"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides to the Government of the People’s Republic of China (PRC), the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), or any person owned by or controlled by the PRC or CCP access to such data.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C0F66AF83C149178B850B2AEDD1BA76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><paragraph id="H8579EC34B5634D01BBBF16199C61303A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection with respect to a foreign person determined by the President to be subject to subsection (a) are the following:</text><subparagraph id="HEA0B863C32234EFCA955EE63253C9909"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Asset blocking</header><text>The President shall exercise all powers granted to the President by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of the foreign person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB614B7A30F9D4E7CB457D7A1B31EF012"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inadmissibility of certain individuals</header><clause id="HB6EA50E236FD4D81BBFB33F1D086D736"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header><text>In the case of a foreign person who is an individual, the foreign person is—</text><subclause id="H536DF7A2863C4147B5553871412DF925"><enum>(I)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF6EC569CA65E413BB6EFF10750C58467"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HCB991FC33E9648928B229F30C375D44B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HDCA19575978048BE8F2CFFFF300BE0F3"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><subclause id="H6BC0E96C72AB4BC3BD6D8FACC1930451"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a foreign person who is an individual, the visa or other documentation issued to the person shall be revoked, regardless of when such visa or other documentation is or was issued.</text></subclause><subclause id="H87FAFDBD90EA4C80B859228447F4B486"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Effect of revocation</header><text>A revocation under subclause (I) shall—</text><item id="H75841D333AA245DAB034243606010BB1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>take effect immediately; and</text></item><item id="HEBED878E3AAC4A72974AFFD367E5E658"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the person’s possession.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07F0040B72AE4ABDBEE080AD087B4D26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to a person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of regulations to implement this section to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of such Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDFD79E3D2B84977A7FE206173984740"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception to comply with united nations headquarters agreement</header><text>Sanctions under paragraph (1)(B) shall not apply to a foreign person who is an individual if admitting the person into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBA4B7C1AFF54DA88BFA645C58892790"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The President may, on a case-by-case basis and for periods not to exceed 180 days, waive the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this section if the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees not later than 15 days before such waiver is to take effect that the waiver is vital to the national security interests of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCCF9467B08C44906A3455CE98AAC40AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation authority</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided to the President under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) for purposes of carrying out this section. The exceptions to the President’s authority described in section 203(b) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, as amended by section 1, shall not apply to the President’s authority to exercise authorities under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8BDAF77F55B941DEB208A101B0949AF6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><paragraph id="H0274D9AE118341C9AA6797D254B1428A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This section shall terminate on January 1, 2026.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1018876E3DB40D6B1427889F5DA5E2B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply with respect to sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this section before January 1, 2026.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88E4D8BD837F46ED8185FF99B17ED70F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC4C33279E77748CD86C5AB5D5941C45F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Admitted; alien</header><text>The terms <quote>admitted</quote> and <quote>alien</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 101(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46337B002BB24DB4B6E95AB0DE3FF71A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H9FB9BB3D871046D0BE60F2E7A50A8722"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Ways and Means, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EA1D3F6D3D24AA39D22486C5F595105"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7331EF515004AD380F096C0FCAFC79C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term <quote>foreign person</quote> means a person that is not a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BF929AC24F94C04A6F629B4E6D3E2CB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>United States person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H911F04DB983B41C88455BBAF2CDB9E5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED628ABBDC38424EB402E851604E2B85"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction of the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD37C46DC417F4023AC232BD0DC848EA5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Determination with respect to the imposition of sanctions on WeChat and TikTok</header><subsection id="H4A9145C0D0E748CDAC63D757AD98E219"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a determination, including a detailed justification therefor, regarding whether WeChat, or any component thereof, or any entity owned or controlled by WeChat, or TikTok, or any component thereof, or any entity owned or controlled by TikTok, satisfies the criteria for the application of sanctions pursuant to—</text><paragraph id="HEAEB93A2CB844A12B23A4CAFF7F7777A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 2 of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H536C523F975A455FA9F353129EA67ABD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Executive Order 13694 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property of certain persons engaged in significant malicious cyber-enabled activities).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96781108315B41B5AE33A1F6643E79BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The determination required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7CCFD60613F249D5A7DA9AF1ABD74D34"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H6E90814D52624A50A5662B1440712804"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Financial Services, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A056A83D7A54A5296535DD499F6ACD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

