<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE4CAF5536BCA4FDF8A5D7F68F66295DD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3018 IH: Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3018</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To authorize the issuance of extreme risk protection orders.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4A2F6B3FB9304B6DBAED0F4D27670DB8" style="OLC">
<section id="H304163F648DD476BB78BA64113916DDF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDAE22453EF0C49F7B264F428B23E0A8D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal extreme risk protection orders</header> <subsection id="HFC37197D56DB44A0B4E3F03B3ED0329D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">Chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H49C775D902254F1C9996A585D7D77572" style="USC">
<section id="H450FBE1E1BC1495582D4E68C37891F33"><enum>935.</enum><header>Extreme risk protection orders</header>
<subsection id="H1FC5CD7292534C6892A3B230E1B6D926"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H8F9FAA6A0B814766B2F60FBCEAAAB753"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>court</term> means a district court of the United States;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEC66F2D08941468DB4DA6E61BEAF8641"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>designated law enforcement officer</term> means a law enforcement officer, designated by a United States marshal, who agrees to receive firearms, ammunition, and permits, as applicable, surrendered under subsection (f);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE5195312B72643ABA2970F52CE255D3A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB5FAA067E8964195AEC38F2C2D56792B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>ex parte Federal extreme risk protection order</term> or <term>ex parte Federal order</term> means a Federal extreme risk protection order issued under subsection (c);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDAF502223E344C94ADE585BA37864871"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal extreme risk protection order</term> means an order issued by a Federal court that enjoins an individual from purchasing, possessing, or receiving, in or affecting interstate and foreign commerce, a firearm or ammunition;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBE469D37133541029AE3061248AB2136"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>family or household member</term>, with respect to a Federal order respondent, means any—</text> <subparagraph id="HA89F845DE532439191F05B96B4A16C4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>parent, spouse, sibling, or child related by blood, marriage, or adoption to the respondent;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE87CB12C564247B8929FF6443D685332"><enum>(B)</enum><text>dating partner of the respondent;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF970FF3EFA1C4992B2B6113722D44EAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>individual who has a child in common with the respondent, regardless of whether the individual has—</text>
<clause id="H7A02A3C4A51C43EBB4836A411ACD9206"><enum>(i)</enum><text>been married to the respondent; or</text></clause> <clause id="HE5A29C219ED945EB9FEB9275289D2EF5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lived together with the respondent at any time;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCE1C6113A27142FDA670BF59476F4DF3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>individual who resides or has resided with the respondent during the past year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H19235475BE674079931BA1AD29513BDA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>domestic partner of the respondent;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8A4D87E7B92B44C6B72EAC72E2AED366"><enum>(F)</enum><text>individual who has a legal parent-child relationship with the respondent, including a stepparent-stepchild and grandparent-grandchild relationship; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H60D7FB0EAEE341DD916E7804A45BD088"><enum>(G)</enum><text>individual who is acting or has acted as the legal guardian of the respondent;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEC73E4AD71E04D6FB577ECC0ECD0F881"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal order petitioner</term> means an individual authorized to petition for an ex parte or long-term Federal extreme risk protection order under subsection (b)(1);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE94CD524EC254DF68754FD4BC3358AA2"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal order respondent</term> means an individual named in the petition for an ex parte or long-term Federal extreme risk protection order or subject to an ex parte or long-term Federal extreme risk protection order;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5CE38FC4226C4089A2C1ADE472D9EF28"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the term <term>long-term Federal extreme risk protection order</term> or <term>long-term Federal order</term> means a Federal extreme risk protection order issued under subsection (d);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H58631C5B79824CA6B1D53FFFB7D92526"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the term <term>mental health agency</term> means an agency of a State, Tribal, or local government or its contracted agency that is responsible for mental health services or co-occurring mental health and substance abuse services; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6443609721E7478FB3AA933D516633D8"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the term <term>national instant criminal background check system</term> means the national instant criminal background check system established under section 103 of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA14E98ADB89C4811B9D1B9880F0C4E27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Petition</header> <paragraph id="H6A1EC485B59E4762BC409C250F69AF0B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A family or household member of the applicable individual, or a law enforcement officer, may submit to an appropriate district court of the United States a petition requesting that the court issue an ex parte Federal extreme risk protection order or long-term Federal extreme risk protection order with respect to an individual.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8120A84ECC2C459CA59F293E859F1241"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No fees</header><text>A court or law enforcement agency may not charge a petitioner or respondent any fee for—</text> <subparagraph id="H3840B5B95181490083661A3DFA225139"><enum>(A)</enum><text>filing, issuing, serving, or reporting an extreme risk protection order; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5C4386EDF232483EB53483178D5B02B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a petition for an extreme risk protection order or any pleading, subpoena, warrant, or motion in connection with an extreme risk protection order; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD89BA47205BA4FE2B18E9E14DFB1D793"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any order or order to show cause necessary to obtain or give effect to this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB5CF1F0DCF040868CBEF70B01351A11"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>A Federal order petitioner who is a law enforcement officer may provide the identity of the petitioner’s sources, and any identifying information, to the court under seal.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB34158D95C840AE8D3B5F5FA17BF2BA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Ex parte orders</header> <paragraph id="HF9A590D6DBBF4697A82BC5658A8F6FF1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Timing</header> <subparagraph id="HF9AEC1ED1559400EBE85E5C138F8EC0E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), a court that receives a petition for an ex parte Federal order under subsection (b) shall grant or deny the petition on the date on which the petition is submitted.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0270E4BC754244E098E93D2466886103"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Late petitions</header><text>If a court receives a petition for an ex parte Federal order submitted under subsection (b) too late in the day to permit effective review, the court shall grant or deny the petition on the next day of judicial business at a time early enough to permit the court to file an order with the clerk of the court during that day.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F9F46A2D5B742F68C18C81368AD4F16"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evidence required</header><text>Before issuing an ex parte Federal order, a court shall require that the petitioner for such order submit a signed affidavit, sworn to before the court, that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H000D1F3F7CE044D49A9C71D3B9B937BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explains why such petitioner believes that the Federal order respondent poses a risk of imminent personal injury to self or another individual, by purchasing, possessing, or receiving a firearm or ammunition; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H64716DC40654447191B91F4979746B56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describes the interactions and conversations of the petitioner with—</text>
<clause id="H9905BF784DF04279BC87A0555699F71E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the respondent; or</text></clause> <clause id="H5C6BE68B2A034579941E7346F39CED1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>another individual, if such petitioner believes that information obtained from that individual is credible and reliable.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H13E7EAA91EA94D3B9371B32D64A70A8B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Standard for issuance of order</header><text>A court may issue an ex parte Federal order only upon a finding of probable cause to believe that—</text> <subparagraph id="H2276FC95AA5C4E94B73E2ED0993631D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federal order respondent poses a risk of imminent personal injury to self or another individual, by purchasing, possessing, or receiving a firearm or ammunition; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3803953DDA8C4374B3A98DCC6A64168F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the order is necessary to prevent the injury described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DA15F31E7094D49B28DA3B0579D2D82"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>An ex parte Federal order shall expire on the earlier of—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEA69C97A429640DE946A42E5A5EA9E01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date that is 14 days after the date of issuance; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69722B43B72D4578A97C56B9E3107A95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date on which the court determines whether to issue a long-term Federal order with respect to the respondent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HAC040BE69F604BF69A6B85E56558BEF7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Long-Term Federal orders</header>
<paragraph id="H69B18ED901444C018C59E888FB81A1D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hearing required</header><text>If a court receives a petition for a long-term Federal extreme risk protection order for a respondent under subsection (b), the court shall hold a hearing to determine whether to issue a long-term Federal order with respect to the respondent either—</text> <subparagraph id="H2B66A5E136C94917AD25FC8D88156EE2"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H92F0FE2DFC144D158D498EAA31CF2C13"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if the court issues an ex parte order with respect to the respondent, not later than 72 hours after the ex parte order is served on the respondent; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H2747124BFD2346A0B64AD1F681363B8F" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the respondent waives the right to a hearing within the 72-hour period under clause (i), or the court does not issue an ex parte order, within 14 days after the date on which the court receives the petition; or</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFE0AC28697274E92A7D7355765D846A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in no event later than 14 days after the date on which the court receives the petition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2B601D5285534808BFFD9C1AEA5B72A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity to be heard</header>
<subparagraph id="H037715AC8EFC49C98A25E52F8099E85A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court shall provide the Federal order respondent with notice and the opportunity to be heard at a hearing under this subsection, sufficient to protect the due process rights of the respondent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H09444097F46C45208CD0E25F65F164CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Right to counsel</header> <clause id="HD223917639BC4345A12E0A9214315306"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>At a hearing under this subsection, the Federal order respondent may be represented by counsel who is—</text>
<subclause id="HEA572741CC2D470E8ED51233C329CD4F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>chosen by the respondent; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0A02A43C37EC42D097F6FC7BC810D563"><enum>(II)</enum><text>authorized to practice at such a hearing.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H0A6A0CBD9B6B42029E35DB1498D5A094"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Court-provided counsel</header><text>If the Federal order respondent is financially unable to obtain representation by counsel, the court, at the request of the respondent, shall ensure, to the extent practicable, that the respondent is represented by an attorney with respect to the petition.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BB820FF6CBF4562B374DB3AEC5D25CC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Burden of proof; standard</header><text>At a hearing under this subsection, the Federal order petitioner—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF4F593B1615945E39C722C1BA8E9E732"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall have the burden of proving all material facts; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA0B5646840AE4ACA961DE1EB187DFF11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall be required to demonstrate, by clear and convincing evidence, that—</text>
<clause id="HF9D22F94C0C846CBBE6C7062196A4B6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the respondent to such order poses a risk of personal injury to self or another individual, during the period to be covered by the proposed Federal extreme risk protection order, by purchasing, possessing, or receiving a firearm or ammunition; and</text></clause> <clause id="H5573771BD1D9424D8623534F6F278021"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the order is necessary to prevent the injury described in clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3392B35AE68E4A978D3E326EF7B01684"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Issuance</header><text>Upon a showing of clear and convincing evidence under paragraph (3), the court shall issue a long-term Federal order with respect to the respondent that shall be in effect for a period of not more than 180 days.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDC8C2B6295B45DA82C109732EA095A5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Denial</header><text>If the court finds that there is not clear and convincing evidence to support the issuance of a long-term Federal order, the court shall dissolve any ex parte Federal order then in effect with respect to the respondent.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H248C4E6573B944C6A6B90740E736F28D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Renewal</header>
<subparagraph id="HA5F4910EEFBE4AE6B7AEA1136DE6F560"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice of scheduled expiration</header><text>Thirty days before the date on which a long-term Federal order is scheduled to expire, the court that issued the order shall—</text> <clause id="HD738C0A3CBE442FF92DD58B4112A4F4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>notify the petitioner and the respondent to such order that the order is scheduled to expire; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H9844C8798FF34F40B371E1BFBA83E70C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>advise the petitioner and the respondent of the procedures for seeking a renewal of the order under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD0A6CAA8526E453F8905045C733BA21A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Petition</header><text>If a family or household member of the Federal order respondent, or a law enforcement officer, believes that the conditions under paragraph (3)(B) continue to apply with respect to a respondent who is subject to a long-term Federal order, the family or household member or law enforcement officer may submit to the court that issued the order a petition for a renewal of the order.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H83FC0BB3DD9B42D187F5A169836C47D6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Hearing</header><text>A court that receives a petition submitted under subparagraph (B) shall hold a hearing to determine whether to issue a renewed long-term Federal order with respect to the respondent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF18317B20F14C6785433AA67F07E221"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Applicable procedures</header><text>The requirements under paragraphs (2) through (5) shall apply to the consideration of a petition for a renewed long-term Federal order submitted under subparagraph (B) of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAF975BB6EAEA43BF92AD7504B153AE0B"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Issuance</header><text>Upon a showing by clear and convincing evidence that the conditions under paragraph (3)(B) continue to apply with respect to the respondent, the court shall issue a renewed long-term Federal order with respect to the respondent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7BD5CC7814D049C19CD71271D79D689D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Factors To consider</header><text>In determining whether to issue a Federal extreme risk protection order, a court—</text>
<paragraph id="H96FE6C54BAF54AFD9D22F760F938BAE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall consider factors including— </text> <subparagraph id="H44ED7B0CE2BC48498FDB5DE3CAD508D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a recent threat or act of violence by the respondent directed toward another individual;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H03D8912B79C04591B7A3A54A9FEB5C1C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a recent threat or act of violence by the respondent directed toward self;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC3FC8C330B0649AAB2B4802D03C091B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a recent act of cruelty to an animal by the respondent; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8F9EB8A90DDC46D0AF840FCE2F9DF5AC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evidence of ongoing abuse of a controlled substance or alcohol by the respondent that has led to a threat or act of violence directed to self or another individual; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5AFC413031094A178A94E7E5E6C7B971"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may consider other factors, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1E0815F4383241C9A39BA2CAC3924AB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the reckless use, display, or brandishing of a firearm by the respondent;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5EDF79BB6A8B468C99B12F01B3F23E0B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a history of violence or attempted violence by the respondent against another individual; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB9E6049D85447CD945850D35FD275A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evidence of an explicit or implicit threat made by the person through any medium that demonstrate that the person poses a risk of personal injury to self or another individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCDAAAD0B23E94AC6BD4DBFCAC928964B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Relinquishment of firearms and ammunition</header> <paragraph id="HA654262B64454CBDB59083D5FEC177C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Order of surrender</header><text>Upon issuance of an ex parte Federal order or long-term Federal order, the court shall order the respondent to such order to surrender all firearms and ammunition that the respondent possesses or owns, in or affecting interstate commerce, as well as any permit authorizing the respondent to purchase or possess firearms (including a concealed carry permit), to—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB506FA6759A247F48561BDC522E0ECBB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the United States Marshals Service; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4BA01BE355B646CEACB7813916D095CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a designated law enforcement officer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68CA0AE9A2044F66910815ED7C374727"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Surrender and removal</header>
<subparagraph id="H880C8EC4BF1B4278B901041D36EF957E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Manner of service</header>
<clause id="H46C6148B21464E83BEDF77CE3B6E5DDE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Personal service</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), a United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer shall serve a Federal extreme risk protection order on a respondent by handing the order to the respondent to such order.</text></clause> <clause id="H71006EEB39A548098C3176775623ADC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Alternative service</header><text>If the respondent cannot reasonably be located for service as described in clause (i), a Federal extreme risk protection order may be served on the respondent in any manner authorized under the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEB70FF189FC740BE9F9D9DD8FE72407E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C), a United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer serving a Federal extreme risk protection order personally on the respondent shall—</text> <clause id="H471D278FA12947378635690D646FD82B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>request that all firearms and ammunition, in or affecting interstate commerce, as well as any permit authorizing the respondent to purchase or possess firearms (including a concealed carry permit), that the respondent possesses or owns—</text>
<subclause id="H016CBFDFE7AB4EB4AF5747D38AB554EE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be immediately surrendered to the United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAFC35D9A73A34F16A3D48086802224FA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>at the option of the respondent, be immediately surrendered and sold to a federally licensed firearms dealer; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HDEDEDDFFB9884EB6BDAD23498DB60960"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>take possession of all firearms and ammunition described in clause (i) that are not sold under subclause (II) of that clause, as well as any permit described in that clause, that are—</text> <subclause id="H5E1D46F751F3471BAE5FB73A35AECEEC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>surrendered;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H3175B35D822249A599B3E78ABD25BED1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in plain sight; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H408FB8FD35D2459EB84739A577CA556E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>discovered pursuant to a lawful search.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H376598506C604621BC668C2121D4B557"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Alternative surrender</header><text>If a United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer is not able to personally serve a Federal extreme risk protection order under subparagraph (A)(i), or is not reasonably able to take custody of the firearms, ammunition, and permits under subparagraph (B), the respondent shall surrender the firearms, ammunition, and permits in a safe manner to the control of a United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer not later than 48 hours after being served with the order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B405CA8F8574012BD7E627286556A3B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Receipt</header> <subparagraph id="HD3C2A7EE63EB4E6E84B3722BA731B864"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Issuance</header><text>At the time of surrender or removal under paragraph (2), a United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer taking possession of a firearm, ammunition, or a permit pursuant to a Federal extreme risk protection order shall—</text>
<clause id="HB80DE18A19BF4504BCFBE839E7EE9AF4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>issue a receipt identifying all firearms, ammunition, and permits that have been surrendered or removed; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCC3E0E33B8844A2D920AC522C147B49A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide a copy of the receipt issued under clause (i) to the respondent to such order.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H33702178618E44C69D3EE47E77CE86BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Filing</header><text>Not later than 72 hours after issuance of a receipt under subparagraph (A), the United States marshal who issued the receipt or designated another law enforcement officer to do so shall—</text> <clause id="H2E50D65F18A14C8E969CA0E20AD2B1BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>file the original receipt issued under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph with the court that issued the Federal extreme risk protection order; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H3671C16F98C04A7FA3A0765CD1CF8C4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that the United States Marshals Service retains a copy of the receipt.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54C06B8A84004FDA8567071D0AA891DF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Designated law enforcement officer</header><text>If a designated law enforcement officer issues a receipt under subparagraph (A), the officer shall submit the original receipt and a copy of the receipt to the appropriate United States marshal to enable the United States marshal to comply with subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7BB14BF7E855404FA7A06E16457BCE85"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><text>If a respondent knowingly attempts, in violation of a Federal extreme risk protection order, to access a firearm, ammunition, or a permit that was surrendered or removed under this subsection, the firearm, ammunition, or permit shall be subject to seizure and forfeiture under section 924(d).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA1EC6C0D265E4BA0BF281C8888DE312B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Return of firearms and ammunition</header> <paragraph id="H42333CD68B7B426D9775320C50146B9C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>If a Federal extreme risk protection order is dissolved, or expires and is not renewed, the court that issued the order shall order the United States Marshals Service to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H3374C382D0AD4E28B7A1FB1ACE20AD6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>confirm, through the national instant criminal background check system and any other relevant law enforcement databases, that the respondent to such order may lawfully own and possess firearms and ammunition; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8EC4B9AF91304685B7645D5543AC7624"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4A89E763BFC9474F9EE2A982AF85795D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if the respondent may lawfully own and possess firearms and ammunition, notify the respondent that the respondent may retrieve each firearm, ammunition, or permit surrendered by or removed from the respondent under subsection (f); or</text></clause>
<clause id="H7388C7C8544D4498846B2CF7AF02EE2A" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the respondent may not lawfully own or possess firearms and ammunition, notify the respondent that each firearm, ammunition, or permit surrendered by or removed from the respondent under subsection (f) will be returned only when the respondent demonstrates to the United States Marshals Service that the respondent may lawfully own and possess firearms and ammunition.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD6F94040F20346969BA8634A12C9617A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Return</header><text>If a Federal extreme risk protection order is dissolved, or expires and is not renewed, and the United States Marshals Service confirms under paragraph (1)(A) that the respondent may lawfully own and possess firearms and ammunition, the court that issued the order shall order the entity that possesses each firearm, ammunition, or permit surrendered by or removed from the respondent under subsection (f) to return those items to the respondent.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA7E4D1307CAA4A9B858D430671B4105B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Return of firearms and ammunition improperly received</header><text>If a court, in a hearing under subsection (d), determines that a firearm or ammunition surrendered by or removed from a respondent under subsection (f) is owned by an individual other than the respondent, the court may order the United States marshal or designated law enforcement officer in possession of the firearm or ammunition to transfer the firearm or ammunition to that individual if—</text> <paragraph id="H76A5DF12B2E8469191EED8AE1F07DD94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the individual may lawfully own and possess firearms and ammunition; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB74C4EBEDF094FF7A957AA1E9CB82B72"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the individual will not provide the respondent with access to the firearm or ammunition.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H81D9B26C01EC4817942784E1623790EC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Penalty for false reporting or frivolous petitions</header><text>An individual who knowingly submits materially false information to the court in a petition for a Federal extreme risk protection order under this section, or who knowingly files such a petition that is frivolous, unreasonable, or without foundation, shall be fined not more than $5,000, or imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both, except to the extent that a greater sentence is otherwise provided by any other provision of law, as the court deems necessary to deter such abuse of process.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H721E8F4361B2453D91F8F5800FB0EF6B"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Model policy</header>
<paragraph id="H35BA07FCFC174FDE8DD526071C7E8FDF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall draft a model policy to maximize the accessibility of Federal extreme risk protection orders.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDE2ABE8FFE84434A93CC4B62CC77BCD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>In drafting the model policy under paragraph (1), the Director shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF0C9253F5E3C4CBFB47162A8EEE7A18A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that State, Tribal, and local law enforcement officers and members of the public without legal training are able to easily file petitions for Federal extreme risk protection orders;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80DB72D863B344528D6C3E88C84ABBF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prescribe outreach efforts by employees of the district courts of the United States to familiarize relevant law enforcement officers and the public with the procedures for filing petitions, either—</text>
<clause id="H0F5584E179C4434DB90AE286750F9E44"><enum>(i)</enum><text>through direct outreach; or</text></clause> <clause id="H0C7C47C688FA4BB7A2716DE30121AF80"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in coordination with—</text>
<subclause id="H9F025F2E12E34ECAA8B83951F9FD0D28"><enum>(I)</enum><text>relevant officials in the executive or legislative branch of the Federal Government; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9600A6EAB45E4124BA47CCC7B951278A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with relevant State, Tribal, and local officials;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD26A5CFD244C4C6A94FDC38F0485B85C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prescribe policies for allowing the filing of petitions and prompt adjudication of petitions on weekends and outside of normal court hours;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H36801491DF924D88B5556E3BF78F56F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>prescribe policies for coordinating with law enforcement agencies to ensure the safe, timely, and effective service of Federal extreme risk protection orders and relinquishment of firearms, ammunition, and permits, as applicable; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9EB015FFAD6F42D18B78D31CA8032AA8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>identify governmental and non-governmental resources and partners to help officials of the district courts of the United States coordinate with civil society organizations to ensure the safe and effective implementation of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8D7844BA4E0A44E19D63A5775BBFB3DC"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Reporting</header> <paragraph id="H216035E8AF36468DBC7519F37F4F491B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Individual reports</header> <subparagraph id="HAA0086BFA8574EC2AF2BD37D351F31C6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 court days after the date on which a court issues or dissolves a Federal extreme risk protection order under this section or a Federal extreme risk protection order expires without being renewed, the court shall notify—</text>
<clause id="HAB9A1077257842EDA1D5C57CC261A095"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Attorney General;</text></clause> <clause id="H19BF838A2D9A4397B55CA30DD8D573EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each relevant mental health agency in the State in which the order is issued; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H8F9E4CA92F6E472F87840EFAD3A91358"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>State and local law enforcement officials in the jurisdiction in which the order is issued, including the national instant criminal background check system single point of contact for the State of residence of the respondent, where applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0AEFD453AAA24CA18CB4D65C3450B818"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Format</header><text>A court shall submit a notice under subparagraph (A) in an electronic format, in a manner prescribed by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H708B540935754335A90857B0B9D2029F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Update of databases</header><text>As soon as practicable and not later than 5 days after receiving a notice under subparagraph (A), the Attorney General shall update the background check databases of the Attorney General to reflect the prohibitions articulated in the applicable Federal extreme risk protection order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H52EA5E5DA9EC4814B9FB7C652DC7ADBC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023, and annually thereafter, the Director shall submit to the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives a report that includes, with respect to the preceding year—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4E9CF78A449041039F7E27E230DDD747"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of petitions for ex parte Federal orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied, disaggregated by—</text> <clause id="H2D2FB67E876346D78E1A42CCF94DA86F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the jurisdiction;</text></clause>
<clause id="HDB277C0AB9C4449EA4DF6663C95DA5DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the individual authorized under subsection (b) to petition for a Federal extreme risk protection order is a law enforcement officer, or a family or household member, and in the case of a family or household member, which of subparagraphs (A) through (G) of subsection (a)(6) describes the relationship; and </text></clause> <clause id="H517C233ACCD744C5BB12F3A35D76B3F4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alleged danger posed by the Federal order respondent, including whether the danger involved a risk of suicide, unintentional injury, domestic violence, or other interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H04BF3FF7D2B54CDF9F23EF8FE37C13E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of petitions for long-term Federal orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied, disaggregated by—</text> <clause id="HBA984737E92A46B3831165BC88A5FE3E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the jurisdiction;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD6609817F3944CDCBEA7C80C63D3FFBA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether the individual authorized under subsection (b) to petition for a Federal extreme risk protection order is a law enforcement officer, or a family or household member, and in the case of a family or household member, which of subparagraphs (A) through (G) of subsection (a)(6) describes the relationship; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD775B2DD9D984D1B98053F98B845980F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alleged danger posed by the Federal order respondent, including whether the danger involved a risk of suicide, unintentional injury, domestic violence, or other interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB1BE1E7B7EA41C58E74F8D035B18B79"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of petitions for renewals of long-term Federal orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1E0BBDA9E55A4EB69C81B7432532BA8E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of cases in which a court has issued a penalty for false reporting or frivolous petitions;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H719B809CE2A54A7CBC9B2F717FC059AE"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic data of Federal order petitioners, including race, ethnicity, national origin, sex, gender, age, disability, average annual income, and English language proficiency, if available;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA1618105457F43DABE1B9B141473C83E"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic data of Federal order respondents, including race, ethnicity, national origin, sex, gender, age, disability, average annual income, and English language proficiency, if available; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H87DC4A95D6D349A9B435ECF72EFEEBED"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the total number of firearms removed pursuant to Federal extreme risk protection orders, and, if available, the number of firearms removed pursuant to each such order. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H95F310F1454940F7B58E4EC39082BC10"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Training for Federal law enforcement officers</header> <paragraph id="H4A1C056757894BD1B043B0DE1EAF2680"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Training requirements</header><text>The head of each Federal law enforcement agency shall require each Federal law enforcement officer employed by the agency to complete training in the safe, impartial, effective, and equitable use and administration of Federal extreme risk protection orders, including training to address—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCD43E40332794C11A5E3B4388D4B5BA6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>bias based on race and racism, ethnicity, gender, sexual orientation, gender identity, religion, language proficiency, mental health condition, disability, and classism in the use and administration of Federal extreme risk protection orders;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE048DAA02C2E42FF8017C773C576A685"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the appropriate use of Federal extreme risk protection orders in cases of domestic violence, including the applicability of other policies and protocols to address domestic violence in situations that may also involve Federal extreme risk protection orders and the necessity of safety planning with the victim before law enforcement petitions for and executes a Federal extreme risk protection order, if applicable;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEB115C08F5C04D2480EF1EFFA6A28209"><enum>(C)</enum><text>interacting with persons with mental, behavioral, or physical disabilities, or emotional distress, including de-escalation techniques and crisis intervention;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1EF1DB1FB5A9403593B076FD3D3EC045"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">techniques for outreach to historically marginalized cultural communities and the development of linguistic proficiencies for law enforcement;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2D6A9ADC44054AE0A972BEE0BD611A85"><enum>(E)</enum><text>community relations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB1041E09B49C43B2B12BEA19A07B3C49"><enum>(F)</enum><text>best practices for referring persons subject to Federal extreme risk protection orders and associated victims of violence to social service providers that may be available in the jurisdiction and appropriate for those individuals, including health care, mental health, substance abuse, and legal services, employment and vocational services, housing assistance, case management, and veterans and disability benefits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H586CD370AAD24A228B793157BF0384BC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training development</header><text>Federal law enforcement agencies developing law enforcement training required under this section shall seek advice from domestic violence service providers (including culturally specific (as defined in section 40002 of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291</external-xref>)) providers), social service providers, suicide prevention advocates, violence intervention specialists, law enforcement agencies, mental health disability experts, and other community groups working to reduce suicides and violence, including domestic violence, within the State.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFEC34A557F0D4C959206F88479385C34"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to alter the requirements of subsection (d)(8) or (g)(8) of section 922, related to domestic violence protective orders.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE3CD5BFC2885460CA045E2CD95F304E7"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Preemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to preempt any State law or policy.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H589E8CDAEB66412793D4DC8EEF9DAE69"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header> <paragraph id="H639F3EA1A98E4AAEA0C2A75012A77BC0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Table of sections</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HD71BB614EA8A428680E45ECD8E24B34D" style="USC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">935. Extreme risk protection orders.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC65C3AFBAD8846FF8B83B995C2CD532E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><text>Section 924(d)(3) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H2BAA88D9BF0A42C68C3A4B453CAA5804"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC0272CF2714A4567BFC78613939C2341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6A95B2AF0E3348558C76AF683B23ED1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HE324290918604EF9A8200642931A7612" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H06705CD714EC4216AC2DA48B7B699396" indent="up1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any attempt to violate a Federal extreme risk protection order issued under section 935.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE4F14B147BF74579B177B50B67CA621B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Federal firearms prohibition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H45C864AA48E4403B8641339236875DA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <subparagraph id="HF19854272B0B4A9489D2685176C02C5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7E091BD0B1274D8FBB7BFFF930C464DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (11), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEF1DCE2C62E0475CA50E10C8890E44AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (11) the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HE8D7B13056414A298D780B773DD7320C" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="HD06E166E7AD94D3C9757197DE8F7E4EA"><enum>(12)</enum><text>is subject to a court order—</text> <subparagraph id="H3BE5F36BDBB74E709C0526FF0CE86512"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issued under section 935; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H40A439A1DBF74369AE2F8CA32832DE6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is an extreme risk protection order (as defined in section 4(a) of the Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H009B433504B44407B159AE49164D5CD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (g)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H94A5CECF57DA436DB208915C1524DE25"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (8)(C)(ii), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC71E25CB77FC492C84EBBEF61787D6B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by striking the comma at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE06B03B5A24F42D79485951F1A718A19"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (9) the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H101AC1F23F5E4770A968B297B7E02411" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H2063D7E1B187480692FBECE51EABBFA8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>is subject to a court order—</text>
<subparagraph id="H74E258754C1141F4B183B4A73271F0D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issued under section 935; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF96A38C8AEF24423940F9145E9A280F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is an extreme risk protection order (as defined in section 4(a) of the Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023),</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="H3BFC8C45D4684C69B7E86A60B86C974E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Extreme risk protection order grant program</header>
<subsection id="H558A026F14AB4D83A443127BDD5E3B34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H3E11E903B8304F7CAD1221DF34D8632F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H95F2309D04D14369B9D00ED6F367A90D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State or Indian Tribe—</text> <clause id="H2F83960FBE034D4BBE8BA8C012D4562D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that enacts legislation described in subsection (c);</text></clause>
<clause id="H62C93E5EE7FF4949BDACF18BFB83D485"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to which the Attorney General determines that the legislation described in clause (i) complies with the requirements under subsection (c)(1); and</text></clause> <clause id="H88F41E301D1A4616BA23D73DBAF95FA5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that certifies to the Attorney General that the State or Indian Tribe shall—</text>
<subclause id="HC52B46B36B9D4CD5B8C04C199827DCA3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>use the grant for the purposes described in subsection (b)(2); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC7D1000F779C4C3D9E7572DAA71472A2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>allocate not less than 25 percent and not more than 70 percent of the amount received under a grant under subsection (b) for the development and dissemination of training for law enforcement officers in accordance with subsection (b)(4); or</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE2F50579BA084A3399FDA295CA7D17A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a unit of local government or other public or private entity that—</text> <clause id="H9BA6AA68C2F54A6DA90F035E365AEBE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is located in a State or in the territory under the jurisdiction of an Indian Tribe that meets the requirements described in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (A); and</text></clause>
<clause id="HADDC8C26CB88486E8292008FA687B292"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>certifies to the Attorney General that the unit of local government or entity shall—</text> <subclause id="H88F9096267704231B39990E6E52879A3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>use the grant for the purposes described in subsection (b)(2); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H609B7C8564F04653A08BA5DB25922EC4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>allocate not less than 25 percent and not more than 70 percent of the amount received under a grant under this section for the development and dissemination of training for law enforcement officers in accordance with subsection (b)(4).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A78E2BFEEF14914827EF3592C1BE86C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extreme risk protection order</header><text>The term <term>extreme risk protection order</term> means a written order or warrant, issued by a State or Tribal court or signed by a magistrate (or other comparable judicial officer), the primary purpose of which is to reduce the risk of firearm-related death or injury by doing 1 or more of the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HA838DF6D01DA479186E041392B7928BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Prohibiting a named individual from having under the custody or control of the individual, owning, purchasing, possessing, or receiving a firearm.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7A6FDDF20BF14EF09D1E667B60922F14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Having a firearm removed or requiring the surrender of firearms from a named individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9846D05E8A554D8AB44E857128D21182"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Firearm</header><text>The term <term>firearm</term> has the meaning given the term in section 921 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA0C6215BC334BB7BE61BBBABDF199BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 1709 of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10389">34 U.S.C. 10389</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1FA760A3030F4907AE56AB117176A096"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Law enforcement officer</header><text>The term <term>law enforcement officer</term> means a public servant authorized by Federal, State, local, or Tribal law or by a Federal, State, local, or Tribal government agency to—</text> <subparagraph id="H3956DA60B4C84A23A87603951BF4A1C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, investigation, or prosecution of an offense; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFF115183007D4782AB138ABB485E0DEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supervise sentenced criminal offenders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6683FD00788E4570839DC833B830436C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Petitioner</header><text>The term <term>petitioner</term> means an individual authorized under State or Tribal law to petition for an extreme risk protection order.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H62BD5D16D8DE431792661492575FDAB1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Respondent</header><text>The term <term>respondent</term> means an individual named in the petition for an extreme risk protection order or subject to an extreme risk protection order.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2DC7615557F8409595076ED4206F7D54"><enum>(8)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4602199263A94224B3EDEB162A22A054"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DD63A0E854442B5B1EB3B67410DABAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H71E11A536C304DCF9127598431BA25DE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF097BB0DEC984B3B93DDDE627AC9997E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA7124C7F2652409BA4E6F5D49C63F637"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Unit of local government</header><text>The term <term>unit of local government</term> has the meaning given the term in section 901 of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10251">34 U.S.C. 10251</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF673236B7583431AAA107279F122D37F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program established</header> <paragraph id="H4559AFB1174D4BBF807D2EA0A14BFBD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services of the Department of Justice shall establish a program under which, from amounts made available to carry out this section, the Director may make grants to eligible entities to assist in carrying out the provisions of the legislation described in subsection (c).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9C1AFB8A65334B45AEF880CDC2BDAB7E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Funds awarded under this subsection may be used by an applicant to—</text> <subparagraph id="H89DF644FF7214F7689AD29383401F832"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enhance the capacity of law enforcement agencies and the courts of a State, unit of local government, or Indian Tribe by providing personnel, training, technical assistance, data collection, and other resources to carry out enacted legislation described in subsection (c);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA5136DFAAC84488DA666349A01E596E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>train judges, court personnel, health care and legal professionals, and law enforcement officers to more accurately identify individuals whose access to firearms poses a danger of causing harm to themselves or others by increasing the risk of firearms suicide or interpersonal violence;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H451D745A95BA4047891AA48775740F40"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop and implement law enforcement and court protocols, forms, and orders so that law enforcement agencies and the courts may carry out the provisions of the enacted legislation described in subsection (c) in a safe, equitable, and effective manner, including through the removal and storage of firearms pursuant to extreme risk protection orders under the enacted legislation; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF92FEA008AEB49558069E0B44B0516A3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>raise public awareness and understanding of the enacted legislation described in subsection (c), including through subgrants to community-based organizations for the training of community members, so that extreme risk protection orders may be issued in appropriate situations to reduce the risk of firearms-related death and injury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17D1FE3D35A944B791C6A71009830822"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this subsection shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing or accompanied by such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC57EFE3E768F4D1D8EF6939439AE1CCC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Training</header>
<subparagraph id="H9C60DEE6A0BE4E3BA6062EB7898F968F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this subsection shall provide training to law enforcement officers, including officers of relevant Federal, State, local, and Tribal law enforcement agencies, in the safe, impartial, effective, and equitable use and administration of extreme risk protection orders, including training to address—</text> <clause id="H5FA655B63A4B484D9F29D06B8E10BB72"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">bias based on race and racism, ethnicity, gender, sexual orientation, gender identity, religion, language proficiency, mental health condition, disability, and classism in the use and administration of extreme risk protection orders;</text></clause>
<clause id="HEC71F1E657E749CF8D7E67767CA7D0C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the appropriate use of extreme risk protection orders in cases of domestic violence, including the applicability of other policies and protocols to address domestic violence in situations that may also involve extreme risk protection orders and the necessity of safety planning with the victim before a law enforcement officer petitions for and executes an extreme risk protection order, if applicable;</text></clause> <clause id="HCD4B74C477784F488256ADB457A3B5C7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">interacting with persons with mental, behavioral, or physical disabilities, or emotional distress, including de-escalation techniques and crisis intervention;</text></clause>
<clause id="HCAA1DC2593A64B2CA02625805CE1360E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">techniques for outreach to historically marginalized cultural communities and the development of linguistic proficiencies for law enforcement; </text></clause> <clause id="HC4B740D5D2404C60B05687AA0617A574" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">community relations; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HF3315F1396E94195B26B4E3A45B53E92"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>best practices for referring persons subject to extreme risk protection orders and associated victims of violence to social service providers that may be available in the jurisdiction and appropriate for those individuals, including health care, mental health, substance abuse, and legal services, employment and vocational services, housing assistance, case management, and veterans and disability benefits.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H919F2DC21B904051AAB5E39544D1522E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation with experts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under this subsection, in developing law enforcement training required under subparagraph (A), shall seek advice from domestic violence service providers (including culturally specific (as defined in section 40002 of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291</external-xref>)) providers), social service providers, suicide prevention advocates, violence intervention specialists, law enforcement agencies, mental health disability experts, and other community groups working to reduce suicides and violence, including domestic violence, within the State or the territory under the jurisdiction of the Indian Tribe, as applicable, that enacted the legislation described in subsection (c) that enabled the grant recipient to be an eligible entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1143D3BA2146415DAFC417DF1210CE67"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Incentives</header><text>For each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, the Attorney General shall give affirmative preference in awarding any discretionary grant awarded by the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services to a State or Indian Tribe that has enacted legislation described in subsection (c) or to a unit of local government or other public or private entity located in such a State or in the territory under the jurisdiction of such an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE07911596F945A7957CDFC541D23FB4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8F5A24F17FE441CF84B05C57FBB6FCD6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility for extreme risk protection order grant program</header>
<paragraph id="H1062D8305319481CA4249E4EB4DBA2DF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Legislation described in this subsection is legislation that establishes requirements that are substantially similar to the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HA20A99F7BB6C4266B0A469E34CB6CE5E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application for extreme risk protection order</header><text>A petitioner, including a law enforcement officer, may submit an application to a State or Tribal court, on a form designed by the court or a State or Tribal agency, that—</text>
<clause id="HFA119D64D3B0409FB59D70CA4AB1965E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describes the facts and circumstances justifying that an extreme risk protection order be issued against the named individual; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA6FBCD5AEEFD4E56A19F38DF2E5FBAD0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is signed by the applicant, under oath.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H797114A8E79C44D1917873B7D2C04502"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice and due process</header><text>The individual named in an application for an extreme risk protection order as described in subparagraph (A) shall be given written notice of the application and an opportunity to be heard on the matter in accordance with this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5974FDC8191D4EBEA961EA09D53AB948"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Issuance of extreme risk protection orders</header> <clause id="H900484DCAD4842EAB7FE75A9A834D547"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Hearing</header> <subclause id="H04E230541A68462DBA5E58CED116C9B5"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon receipt of an application described in subparagraph (A) or request of an individual named in such an application, the court shall order a hearing to be held within a reasonable time, and not later than 30 days after the date of the application or request.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H28B645D73B904BFA84E13469EF599569"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>If the court finds at the hearing ordered under subclause (I), by a preponderance of the evidence or according to a higher evidentiary standard established by the State or Indian Tribe, that the respondent poses a danger of causing harm to self or others by having access to a firearm, the court may issue an extreme risk protection order.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8EC04FE2E27E4527A3F23B193C47B4DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Duration of extreme risk protection order</header><text>An extreme risk protection order shall be in effect—</text>
<subclause id="HA63BE12580B54B83B98705E77D099802"><enum>(I)</enum><text>until an order terminating or superseding the extreme risk protection order is issued; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF22A4E4B702D402DBF60E71FB88C44CC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for a set period of time.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H95D8375F61BC4205903D57D581913A58"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Ex parte extreme risk protection orders</header>
<clause id="H5074C0E50AA04627843A78423812FEBA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon receipt of an application described in subparagraph (A), the court may issue an ex parte extreme risk protection order, if—</text> <subclause id="HB57B87F79E8643D284BA496F28E77DD8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the application for an extreme risk protection order alleges that the respondent poses a danger of causing harm to self or others by having access to a firearm; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HDD7B0BDD43054C1A9ED79C58900681ED"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the court finds there is reasonable cause to believe, or makes a finding according to a higher evidentiary standard established by the State or Indian Tribe, that the respondent poses a danger of causing harm to self or others by having access to a firearm.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H38E122999D494881836D82DC52397619"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Duration of ex parte extreme risk protection order</header><text>An ex parte extreme risk protection order shall remain in effect only until the hearing required under subparagraph (C)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4E042AB5DB0C4E5CAC6E9BDDDC64AFFE"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Storage of removed firearms</header>
<clause id="HF450C0BBBFB245C18AFF04E4F05D8F28"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Availability for return</header><text>All firearms removed or surrendered pursuant to an extreme risk protection order shall only be available for return to the named individual when the individual has regained eligibility under Federal and State law, and, where applicable, Tribal law to possess firearms.</text></clause> <clause id="H23273DB923CA4C67B2B5040BC776D9A7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Consent required for disposal or destruction</header><text>Firearms owned by a named individual may not be disposed of or destroyed during the period of the extreme risk protection order without the consent of the named individual.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0BCD988E9F814642A5B14935255093B5"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Notification</header>
<clause id="HDF8C00A0F70D4798B75AB216DF228620"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header>
<subclause id="H2AEE4A244F294F1BAD0D059833E595E3"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>A State or Tribal court that issues an extreme risk protection order shall notify the Attorney General or the comparable State or Tribal agency, as applicable, of the order as soon as practicable or within a designated period of time.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H29A7CC353F64404AB6A3F4B5B592780A"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Form and manner</header><text>A State or Tribal court shall submit a notification under subclause (I) in an electronic format, in a manner prescribed by the Attorney General or the comparable State or Tribal agency.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H5FB293472DDD456CB42420BD6B6D10C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Update of databases</header><text>As soon as practicable or within the time period designated by State or Tribal law after receiving a notification under clause (i), the Attorney General or the comparable State or Tribal agency shall ensure that the extreme risk protection order is reflected in the National Instant Criminal Background Check System.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6CD40017B9A14748A3EA676B158410D1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional provisions</header><text>Legislation described in this subsection may—</text>
<subparagraph id="HFB6B55C24F1E4C92B02521CAD8E390BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide procedures for the termination of an extreme risk protection order;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H874244D522A84C7089760E33E9B4F8FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide procedures for the renewal of an extreme risk protection order;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDB5CA0C3CB7F4806BFE497A557D93B55"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establish burdens and standards of proof for issuance of orders described in paragraph (1) that are substantially similar to or higher than the burdens and standards of proof set forth in that paragraph;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC23F401C2C9C41939E6BC25AB5ADAC8C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>limit the individuals who may submit an application described in paragraph (1), provided that, at a minimum, law enforcement officers are authorized to do so; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC4241C8E615B4317AFCC1EA352AF6405"><enum>(E)</enum><text>include any other authorizations or requirements that the State or Tribal authorities determine appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H233D22EA4EDE485AB380357F08CD025D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which an eligible entity receives a grant under subsection (b), and annually thereafter for the duration of the grant period, the entity shall submit to the Attorney General a report that includes, with respect to the preceding year—</text>
<subparagraph id="H53BF2744CC1641C0AF1BF989AD55EF72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of petitions for ex parte extreme risk protection orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied, disaggregated by—</text> <clause id="H624F408C26B941C5AA010B6A65E61CF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the jurisdiction;</text></clause>
<clause id="H564C9E1161D74E52BF1DC5F4BDD69731"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the individual authorized under State or Tribal law to petition for an extreme risk protection order, including the relationship of the individual to the respondent; and</text></clause> <clause id="H60160734123F4C4C86B28FA0A3D977A0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alleged danger posed by the respondent, including whether the danger involved a risk of suicide, unintentional injury, domestic violence, or other interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1DA8F6278F06425BB45ECC8246DFD437"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of petitions for extreme risk protection orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied, disaggregated by—</text> <clause id="H8DC7474F224E4E9A9643D5DA057E0551"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the jurisdiction;</text></clause>
<clause id="H5F0924A9626D4045B961FB4850C0B5D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the individual authorized under State or Tribal law to petition for an extreme risk protection order, including the relationship of the individual to the respondent; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC8702A18D8E34C30BD0BB80A8E395954"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alleged danger posed by the respondent, including whether the danger involved a risk of suicide, unintentional injury, domestic violence, or other interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H48BD176CF836471FBA10032B8B479FE9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of petitions for renewals of extreme risk protection orders filed, as well as the number of such orders issued and the number denied;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3DCC2AAFA43478095B6683830EE3E48"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of cases in which a court imposed a penalty for false reporting or frivolous petitions;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3F96235B670A40919427E6FA0B098256"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic data of petitioners, including race, ethnicity, national origin, sex, gender, age, disability, average annual income, and English language proficiency, if available;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34B848D965DB44BDA619104FAE8F552B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic data of respondents, including race, ethnicity, national origin, sex, gender, age, disability, average annual income, and English language proficiency, if available; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC4F917C3F3294FD2A320577DE32A31AC"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of firearms removed pursuant to extreme risk protection orders, and, if available, the number of firearms removed pursuant to each such order. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H57646F091BF444C99271B772A467E9F7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Identification records</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Section 534 of title 28, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H31CC456A8C9C4525B19AC62F8991E222"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HA4B512B13C9845628D2355A92A0F15EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD09360F7B8924E4D801C8750EDD218CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (5) as paragraph (6); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0531D0145A424396B8096F8EA39E7EAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (4) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC1FC793F5758403A95F9C007EA9711FB">
<paragraph id="H059152AC566D416D889CBD35D23C6716"><enum>(5)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8B728B67184E405FB3926B1478A352A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to subparagraph (B), acquire, collect, classify, and preserve records from Federal, Tribal, and State courts and other agencies identifying individuals subject to extreme risk protection orders, as defined in section 4(a) of the Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB40CBE20591A4951933325FAEBB715FF" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>destroy each record acquired or collected under subparagraph (A) when the applicable extreme risk protection order expires or is terminated or dissolved; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80E324DEF1754A649ECD6C07BFA5B47B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>(a)(5)</quote> and inserting <quote>(a)(6)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBA8DBDD9B564446A16026BEF5737671"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE2F9021C0A47463C9F391F6666F1E0B3">
<subsection id="HB6B50E4005344DD49ED7994718104062"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Extreme risk protection orders in national crime information databases</header><text>A Federal, Tribal, or State criminal justice agency or criminal or civil court may—</text> <paragraph id="H0465004719E047D9B0E7302ACFEA8838"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include extreme risk protection orders, as defined in section 4 of the Federal Extreme Risk Protection Order Act of 2023, and Federal extreme risk protection orders, as defined in section 935 of title 18, in national crime information databases, as that term is defined in subsection (f)(3) of this section; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6379D5B85C9045ADA047D71EF73D5E83"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have access to information regarding extreme risk protection orders and Federal extreme risk protection orders through the national crime information databases.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HD5377B8B10B04794BE59B183B3E7FADA"><enum>6.</enum><header>Full faith and credit</header> <subsection id="H82AC6425192C4487BBBC78DBF3B31B1A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <term>extreme risk protection order</term>, <term>Indian Tribe</term>, and <term>State</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 4(a).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2E816872506A4920A6FA3AD7BAA50B11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Full faith and credit required</header><text>Any extreme risk protection order issued under a State or Tribal law enacted in accordance with this Act shall be accorded the same full faith and credit by the court of another State or Indian Tribe (referred to in this subsection as the <term>enforcing State or Indian Tribe</term>) and enforced by the court and law enforcement personnel of the other State or Tribal government as if it were the order of the enforcing State or Indian Tribe.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H375B3CC98D454125BC4B0B1BE0398F08"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability to protection orders</header> <paragraph id="H8B765946B6754CB187D463E22C1EF595"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (b) shall apply to a protection order issued by a State or Tribal court if—</text>
<subparagraph id="HDBC81BDE01A24D43B4FDC9828872E516"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the court has jurisdiction over the parties and matter under the law of the State or Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA86135A5E1E845A2BAC2B103C4AFD6D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reasonable notice and opportunity to be heard is given to the person against whom the order is sought sufficient to protect that person’s right to due process.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22BA886236434DC2BD355575CBBF477C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ex parte protection orders</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)(B), in the case of an ex parte protection order, notice and opportunity to be heard shall be provided within the time required by State or Tribal law, and in any event within a reasonable time after the order is issued, sufficient to protect the due process rights of the respondent.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC865BB84A01346A799BB1BC806884916"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Tribal court jurisdiction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, a court of an Indian Tribe shall have full civil jurisdiction to issue and enforce a protection order involving any person, including the authority to enforce any order through civil contempt proceedings, to exclude violators from Indian land, and to use other appropriate mechanisms, in matters arising anywhere in the Indian country (as defined in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code) of the Indian Tribe or otherwise within the authority of the Indian Tribe.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HA7C555F6D37744938AAE0890A139697F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3(1) of the NICS Improvement Amendments Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40903">34 U.S.C. 40903(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 922(g)(8)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (8) or (10) of section 922(g)</quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB5EDDE6E25144E35A36773B2DF61F102"><enum>8.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance, is held to be invalid, the remainder of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected.</text></section>
<section id="HEFDFA1991094400395D41E675C4A3DF4" commented="no"><enum>9.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

