<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEE5ACC93697A4CB28596B0827D47D3E7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2832 IH: National Land Bank Network Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2832</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation to establish a national land bank network, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0644A81B895746E898D5FFD6283DD633" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6C800E64C8374E7FAAD24B3736A254CF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Land Bank Network Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H45E45DD4E3704488BFB171C7D3DD7FD9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H6323F681AEA34105AFACC2468FA3A16C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Vacant and abandoned properties destabilize rural, suburban, and urban neighborhoods across the United States by creating fire and other public safety hazards, driving down property values, and draining local tax dollars.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13933D433F624FD59C163C0CF062E111"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The cost of repairs to maintain vacant and abandoned properties, as well as the potential unpaid taxes and public liens on vacant and abandoned properties, often exceed the property values of vacant and abandoned properties, driving away purchasers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5A463E36B720453097AF0EAE6221F6FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The lack of an insurable and marketable title frequently prevents vacant and abandoned properties from returning to productive use.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BC08F35491A455DB25E217BEFA67E18"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Low-income neighborhoods and communities of color disproportionately bear the burden of living near vacant and abandoned properties and the hazards associated with those properties.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDA01B0292746453893727DE4208ED2EA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Existing property disposition practices frequently prioritize the ease of disposition and maximizing sale prices instead of the needs of communities and homeowners.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD811589A72E4AF4A903881A00EC0DC5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Land banks—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1610B7778888416E9634A264B7FA6B03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have been developed to respond to the challenges posed by vacant and abandoned properties; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H04A284E28DBC42A99A2FBEB5F5C24A59"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are primarily focused on the return of vacant, abandoned, and tax delinquent properties to productive use in accordance with locally determined goals and priorities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H71667FE2C3684CB0A7429B53405CA2AD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Land banks, regardless of the location, size of inventory, or duration of existence of a particular land bank, share challenges in accessing best practices, research, technical assistance, and other resources.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H9F14520DA9254331A03ACF925BC92390"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that a national land bank network would provide the tools necessary to ensure that land banks—</text>
<paragraph id="H6001A3AD4D3D40F5B097EA868C21B1A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use best practices;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BFB5830FB8A4D0A97D827B84244EF54"><enum>(2)</enum><text>operate transparently;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H606BBB57A69841498981100336338E6E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prioritize positive community outcomes;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14A803C5A7504462AA1710A66C7756E2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop partnerships and programming to drive community redevelopment forward; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB7DB1B1C05064B119AD75239F8EC6B64"><enum>(5)</enum><text>access education, expertise, and research to strengthen the critical work of land banks in supporting equitable communities.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H4591D45135FE4E2F8DA9C974835645B0"><enum>4.</enum><header>National land bank network</header> <subsection id="H6E16D809583C45F9BD25423075FF9EA4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H49BA179A88E64844A92D81E61FD349FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Corporation</header><text>The term <term>Corporation</term> means the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation established under the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8101">42 U.S.C. 8101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3638AD7A47814353B05048A6F04F1366"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a national nonprofit organization that has demonstrated and established expertise—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9B8967AD6BB144269A64BF368C0843ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in supporting the creation, implementation, and operation of land banks; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2C37922831174EB59D153EABC2A6B16D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>relating to the systems, laws, and policies that impact vacant, abandoned, and other problem properties.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAEB1C1F5E0D94F3099422025E91F52BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Land bank</header><text>The term <term>land bank</term> means a government entity, agency, or program, or a special purpose nonprofit entity formed by 1 or more units of government in accordance with a State or local land bank enabling law, that has been designated by 1 or more State or local governments to acquire, steward, and dispose of vacant, abandoned, or other problem properties in accordance with locally determined priorities and goals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1967A68E46B444EA089E0727A01744E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Member land bank</header><text>The term <term>member land bank</term> means a rural, suburban, or urban land bank that is a member of the national land bank network.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2247FE130E16486EB7D597087A54F8F6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>National land bank network</header><text>The term <term>national land bank network</term> means the membership-based national land bank network established under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDAAEED823FD44813A0D1F0C0865B6D5B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National land bank network</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Corporation shall enter into a contract with an eligible entity to establish and operate—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H875F0D19755540F4B4334897868D9814"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a membership-based national land bank network; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0137001C56844F3A980E90C0C6E2A18"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the grant programs described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB4FF66FDB6514161935D63C3D72E699E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The duties of the national land bank network shall be to—</text> <paragraph id="H0F088934EAAF4CAD98D12668003B52E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to member land banks to support skills training, staffing support, and other operational capacity needs of member land banks;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA9722E85DCDB48068CB6D30A820924AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>work with rural, suburban, and urban communities that are considering whether a land bank would be an appropriate tool to address vacant, abandoned, and other problem properties in those communities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE8D7258B47B54C38A9D93548CF4C2CFC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide the communities described in paragraph (2) with technical assistance in the formation of a land bank;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8368DBF9ABC14C688B54053245B57954"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop partnerships and programming to advance the work of land banks;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H25E035B9AE2642A590B7E52C46D981C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support engagement between land banks and local communities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBC1FFDD3468F4C8689BB5DD0E8133311"><enum>(6)</enum><text>provide land banks with access to education, expertise, and research that support the work of land banks, including environmental hazard remediation, land reuse, and rehabilitation of commercial and residential properties;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD35EAE31FAB546599B970190FDFEEC9E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>support the participation of land banks in local community planning processes;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA60C2AEBD5A548138EBD3DB2F41BC920"><enum>(8)</enum><text>support the engagement of land banks with residents of neighborhoods in which land banks operate;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H69978794C6DE45708FF67ABD4586AD1E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>work with rural communities and land banks to ensure that the grant programs established under subsection (d) and education initiatives, expertise, and research of the national land bank network address the specific challenges of rural areas;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBEB6240D71674FC0AD0C39D90A07196A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>support data collection by land banks to track and evaluate the activities and outcomes of land banks; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E442403B3D64508BD624F8E507B54A1"><enum>(11)</enum><text>support the use of specialized technology by land banks—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8C3F1820227C40B2B49135EE3FDE4882"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to enable strategic and targeted property acquisition and disposition; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1290052E163A4FBCA8383678218EC4FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to facilitate the data collection described in paragraph (10) in a standardized manner that enables data to be aggregated and compared.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB5DAAABA6A5D4E90BC1AE19C8D922DD8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant programs</header>
<paragraph id="H5A293E10F770451CBF3ECFA713F26A2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The eligible entity with which the Corporation enters into a contract under subsection (b) shall develop and administer grant programs to support—</text> <subparagraph id="H81FE0EAEB68C4599913A0942A3F2865F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>land banks; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H689F221B4DB74024827CB4BFC96CC620"><enum>(B)</enum><text>communities in the creation of new land banks.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7046BAFCBD84846A852F1DF9E80623C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The eligible entity described in paragraph (1) may, with respect to the grant programs developed under this subsection—</text>
<subparagraph id="H57657C2B70E44E799C3F3974DDEC9AB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>design the grant programs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H98E5D65B2ED04E4FB75BA4810167BBE8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop eligibility criteria for the grant programs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H78E32EFE664C49F19DD4443FC84D7D4B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>disburse grant funds directly to—</text> <clause id="HE14B35D954F44E6BBA602B2C5EB38E5F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a land bank; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H9874A1560A7E4EFD8944ED412F530B82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization, a community organization, or 1 or more units of government for the purpose of establishing a land bank; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H515EB830BFD64722B45FBC873383E02D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>establish reporting requirements for recipients of the grants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE4FDB56CD0BB4B93B0EE1D90C4006FC7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A land bank or an entity described in subparagraph (C)(ii) desiring a grant from a grant program developed under this subsection shall submit to the eligible entity described in paragraph (1) an application that includes a plan for resident engagement in the use of any grant funds that has a direct impact on the community.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3504066E6EAA456AA90624FF20604D03"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which a land bank or an entity described in paragraph (2)(C)(ii) receives a grant from a grant program developed under this section, and annually thereafter until 1 year after the date on which the land bank or entity fully expends the funds from the grant, the land bank or entity shall submit to the national land bank network a report that includes a summary of the steps undertaken to engage neighborhood residents relating to activities funded by the grant that have a direct impact on the community.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC7D5335AC378466EB7D1D8262D01E4E9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Corporation shall submit to Congress a report describing, with respect to the preceding fiscal year—</text> <paragraph id="HDA089D699CD34B01956D35237204065F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the services provided to land banks by the national land bank network; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7E75EA4523814DC8AB542FF28C673C9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the outcomes, qualitative impacts, and quantifiable impacts that member land banks have had in the respective communities of those member land banks. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE461F7916229489EA33AA02233259738"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Corporation to carry out this section—</text>
<paragraph id="H3E464054E6A74C7C8C3FB16866D50B53"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$10,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, of which not less than $7,000,000 shall be used for the grant programs developed under subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA89911BE804C4B13B94F8D0A132822CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2034.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

