<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0529972EB2D349DAA7B318620527C742" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2900 IH: Apprenticeship Hubs Across America Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2900</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote registered apprenticeships, including registered apprenticeships within in-demand industry sectors, through the support of workforce intermediaries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1CA13693490846A19C56709F721F6686" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HF8EDD95C39434F528131ADB7F9C9A889"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Apprenticeship Hubs Across America Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H28CF6324166D412EB804C95929DEC6BE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H33063D1B85984ECEB97501F897533D30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Registered apprenticeship programs provide apprentices employment with structured on-the-job training, little to no student loan debt, competitive wages, industry-recognized credentials, direct access to jobs and careers, and in some cases, the potential to earn college credit toward an associate’s or bachelor’s degree.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1ACD3D37AB94E5A86E35C9762395D6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the Department of Labor, the average salary for an individual who completes an apprenticeship program is $77,000 annually. Apprentices who complete their program earn approximately $300,000 more during their career than peers who did not complete an apprenticeship.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H993AD41C5E8F477C9BEBD05FB051B293"><enum>(3)</enum><text>There are still very few apprenticeship positions in sectors with high projected job growth. According to data from the Department of Labor, professional, scientific, and technical services—all industries with high projected job growth—had only 1,827 apprentices in fiscal year 2021. The field of health care and social assistance had less than 14,000 apprentices, much lower than the future projected need in the field.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79E2113F398A471C9B576E4FB6106017"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A major barrier to expanding registered apprenticeships in high-growth job sectors is employers’ lack of familiarity with the process to establish, and the requirements of, registered apprenticeship programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCADEE30A822044B9AB6A2F0F8D567E80"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Workforce intermediaries, which are organizations at the national, regional, State, or local level that help ease the process for employers in developing and delivering new registered apprenticeship programs, can serve as a catalyzing force for creating and expanding registered apprenticeships in high-growth job sectors through technical assistance and capacity building for employers, labor organizations, educational institutions, and government entities.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H456A8DCC72AE4C67A8D79D3CC0111F82"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H91B048C9291641C196136A62AD446AD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprenticeship</header><text>The term <term>apprenticeship</term> means an opportunity in a registered apprenticeship program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0F153A9A2714041BEB5AF3FFECF4E04"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In-demand industry sector</header><text>The term <term>in-demand industry sector</term> means a sector described in subparagraphs (A)(i) and (B) of section 3(23) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(23)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H099D51771CDA41CB803DA8ECE69D1E41"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Industry or sector partnership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>industry or sector partnership</term> has the meaning given the term in paragraph (26) of section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>), except that clause (ii) of such paragraph (26) shall be applied as if <quote>, as appropriate</quote> has been struck. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C6ED4CB25C0401696B66DEC7EE09E54"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD194DD3B0EDF4CCDACAC9D917B227373"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Local board</header><text>The term <term>local board</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3(33) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(33)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H669103F59821425CA29AD0F08A5E7067"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Nontraditional apprenticeship occupation</header><text>The term <term>nontraditional apprenticeship occupation</term> means an occupation that has not traditionally engaged in carrying out registered apprenticeship programs, but which the Secretary determines would benefit from having such a program (such as an occupation in a financial services, advanced manufacturing, information technology, health care, or hospitality industry sector).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84D4D7064A524F6E92AE48E3776A178F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Registered apprenticeship program</header><text>The term <term>registered apprenticeship program</term> means a program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA0B88ED2DBC4325AA3499B6471B2EAB"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0D1968630334F8DBFF0875E70035CA0"><enum>(9)</enum><header>State board</header><text>The term <term>State board</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3(57) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(57)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB0CC038FE12464794BAC07CC3FD4360"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Workforce intermediary</header><text>The term <term>workforce intermediary</term> means an entity that, at the national, regional, State, or local level—</text><subparagraph id="HFB136B88CA2145458D94EE8594BED116"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAACC036485DA4F3DBFA6608742352DCA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>facilitates the establishment of a registered apprenticeship program; or</text></clause><clause id="H26D6167470B64407814B90E024EAC716" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has the capacity, and will work, to facilitate the establishment of a registered apprenticeship program;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5CF4A86509E4380BBA9836A89D09A50"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes representatives of labor organizations representing workers in the industry sector in which the registered apprenticeship is (or will be) established; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF16899B88F54433FBF36CD3831487DF8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may be a partnership that includes 1 or more of the following as partners: </text><clause id="HF767E298634D43B38F483811E0DBE6EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A business or industry organization.</text></clause><clause id="H15DB782923304DA482CEB55318955865"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A labor organization.</text></clause><clause id="HE4BCEC3479B5453AA3AF259D4C6C92D2" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A labor workforce intermediary. </text></clause><clause id="H42F02A2C773542B0B84C743A5F7A570A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A community-based organization.</text></clause><clause id="H516F6CC5A9EF449690CA5E70127A9A16"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A joint labor-management partnership.</text></clause><clause id="H9F7BF718E80E4CF3B2AFA58BACCF7281"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>An institution of higher education.</text></clause><clause id="HE159EF1BA00346C9BDC283D37942DBF3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>A State board or local board.</text></clause><clause id="H83DEB1C257D34C4AA77F0E72979F2E19"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>A nonprofit organization.</text></clause><clause id="H92C2F95DAA504428902D44314AE8CF95"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>An industry or sector partnership.</text></clause><clause id="H4B9FEFC9165344E8B1C28CB29E038ABA"><enum>(x)</enum><text>An industry association.</text></clause><clause id="HFA9AB43396564C44946A3282CD34FD23"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>A joint labor-management organization.</text></clause><clause id="HEC27691BBBC446679CC5EED9CA6FC991"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>A consortium of organizations that provide technical assistance to support and to increase the development of registered apprenticeship programs.</text></clause><clause id="H74D6E171A7B3484F88624DCF2D8DFE2B"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Any other entity that the Secretary considers to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H436ECC83A39F42CE90979E0A5ABED0EC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Workforce intermediaries grant program</header><subsection id="H720CF0AB2AE84E3483A5BC4CAA807FCE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>From amounts made available to carry out this Act, the Secretary shall establish and carry out a workforce intermediaries grant program by awarding grants, on a competitive basis, to workforce intermediaries, to enable the workforce intermediaries to engage a variety of stakeholders, such as local boards, secondary schools, institutions of higher education, and employers, to support, develop, and implement registered apprenticeship programs in accordance with section 6.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE3022817B0B4F7895EE55E18C149DEB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A grant awarded under this Act shall be for a period of not more than 4 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBC5FB7D3A63A4BD98017E90F3047CC75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>A grant awarded under this Act shall be in an amount of not more than $6,000,000, and such amount shall be determined based on the relative number of apprentices a workforce intermediary plans to facilitate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H50F4CDBBFC1049829B5FE09925D63183"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>In awarding grants under this Act, the Secretary shall ensure that there is geographic diversity in the areas in which activities will be carried out under the grants.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCAF6ECF9529844779F9ED5B21B5E0593"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Matching funds</header><text>A workforce intermediary receiving a grant under this Act shall provide matching funds, from non-Federal sources, for the activities supported under the grant. The matching funds shall be in an amount that is not less than 20 percent of the amount of grant funds provided under the grant.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA40736F5B64F46439C16998A3F7A756D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Applications</header><subsection id="HF2C77AEA13C2444087EC488A3D23435C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A workforce intermediary desiring a grant under this Act shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H72F906AB4B7D4F34AE08B5D6B7D2F06E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The application described in subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H739F1DA6EA194DFAA18FD703CF273323"><enum>(1)</enum><text>information regarding—</text><subparagraph id="H07353A116EA4402F9EFB5FD7B4CB8F28"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a workforce intermediary described in section 3(10)(A)(i), the extent to which the workforce intermediary is working, as of the date of the application, with stakeholders to provide activities such as the activities described in section 6; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B56EAF394A14F67AB5010818646551C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a workforce intermediary described in section 3(10)(A)(ii), the capacity of the workforce intermediary to begin providing activities described in section 6 upon receipt of the grant, including information demonstrating that the workforce intermediary would be successful in carrying out such activities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D2E2BD5642341038B8E42E299281696"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information regarding the extent to which the grant will help the workforce intermediary—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H147228A83E864FF38EB1FBC7A7F25288"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand apprenticeships for in-demand industry sectors that lack apprenticeships at the time of the application; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E4D430B069C413488F1BC3983DC9E2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>target populations that are underrepresented—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE00059B2B3E4E02A2D4D75D4D16EDA5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in apprenticeships generally; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H065F84B01466452E8AEB7B65E9A4681D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the fields in which the apprentices will be trained;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CE30F02F1F94C379B68273A417A8C78"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assurances that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCCE506C0DDA45A495303C4C3507F04F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the workforce intermediary will cooperate in the evaluation of the project conducted under section 7; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5455FA2B8B314D44BDD0E2D28E1330F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the workforce intermediary will meet the matching requirement under section 4(e);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FA45CB06E5A48A4BE5F7FC8120EC1DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>information about the workforce intermediary's—</text><subparagraph id="H82FC0DE2836C4FD891E6DD72EEAB3B6B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>experience in providing activities described in section 6 and capacity, or ability to develop or expand capacity, to provide such activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28F2EC12DD1E441C9AC46CF1CA92B0EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>experience working in a collaborative environment with government and nongovernmental entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DFE59F83F96441DA36DB496F462DE2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ability to raise or provide funding to cover operating costs for the long-term sustainability of the activities supported under the grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD9E0140B2194FA2A9466AD59672B02D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>capacity and infrastructure to track outcomes and measure results, including capacity to track and analyze program performance and assess program impact; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B86ED0CA03845AF9E905717777FFD4E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>information describing how the workforce intermediary will promote the diversity described in section 6(b)(1)(F).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB209A5ADCE764F6DB1DDE41D9C8EF8DD"><enum>6.</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subsection id="HB9CDC768C2AC4FD3839EAAFF7CAD75BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A workforce intermediary that receives a grant under this Act shall use the grant funds to carry out activities, which may include activities described in subsection (b) or other strategies as may be necessary, that support the development and successful implementation of registered apprenticeship programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H46EA3F340DD848A6AC32EB2010829E08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Suggested uses</header><text>A workforce intermediary may carry out subsection (a) through 1 or more of the following activities, as determined appropriate by the Secretary:</text><paragraph id="H27C9FAD036F44CB39D55B05C9F10355B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Outreach and marketing</header><text>A workforce intermediary may provide services to engage employers in registered apprenticeship programs, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H1F99EC234AA343A09B137D680418B759"><enum>(A)</enum><text>marketing apprenticeships regionally, to employers and to potential apprentices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6923644A0A014D77B8AE87C5F02507EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>marketing apprenticeships to secondary school students, counselors, school administrators, or parents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H228E3700770F4D45823AB51C8588CA57"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recruiting and evaluating candidates for apprenticeships;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE22066F872B74FA09803D4D96D687DA8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>conducting outreach to employers to persuade the employers to adopt the apprenticeship model;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H985810E38ED14F18A73535A32D9EC0C2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>matching employers with apprentices; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22A4A0357D6F44ABB3C36D15357871C6"><enum>(F)</enum><text>promoting diversity among apprentices by promoting outreach to underrepresented populations (such as women and minorities), youth, individuals with disabilities (as defined in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>)), and veterans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H976824EDA4904B309A2AC7D12AFD3CF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Employer engagement</header><text>The workforce intermediary may provide services to engage employers in, and develop curricula for, registered apprenticeship programs, which may include assisting a small or medium-sized employer with—</text><subparagraph id="H025B9F761F59484FAE8D3F5AABBF46C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>designing a curriculum for a registered apprenticeship program that blends occupation-specific skills and general industry skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5328ECC7AE2F4891A77ED9D6B8A39333"><enum>(B)</enum><text>designing a comprehensive training plan for apprentices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B70951AE2DB4764B4D46012AE8D3604"><enum>(C)</enum><text>navigating the registration process for the registered apprenticeship program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB7EA0E54C0D47D8B2734A70AA207885"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identifying skills, both technical and behavioral, needed to perform the occupation in question;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5196A67998F546B286E19E41C5985255"><enum>(E)</enum><text>providing training to managers and front-line employees to serve as trainers or mentors to apprentices in the registered apprenticeship program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4ABE4CF1459140D0AA3960FD23D9DCB7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>paying for the cost of off-site training provided to apprentices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA307D25AA73A4AF3B3F4F3459A8E2149"><enum>(G)</enum><text>coordinating activities between training instructors and worksite supervisors of apprentices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA23C434C335749869DF8B33E97519A90"><enum>(H)</enum><text>conducting or arranging for off-the-job training related to the apprenticeship;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9E080B3380E414493B35A9B38C66695"><enum>(I)</enum><text>convening employers to define skills for the registered apprenticeship program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8531D647F137493487803A34AB402403"><enum>(J)</enum><text>developing occupational standards that are nationally recognized and portable to help guide employers and sponsors in establishing new registered apprenticeship programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6F4A0E1FD3144B1912DE136B8D3A22C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Support services for apprentices</header><text>The workforce intermediary may provide support services for apprentices to assure their success in, and after, registered apprenticeship programs, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="HA983F86AF4974D648C9E4ACECCF6155F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing guidance to, mentorship to, and oversight of apprentices during the program, to ensure retention and completion;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D9CEACDB4DA474581417230F544C430"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing services to address challenges that surface for apprentices during the apprenticeship;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BC7FA3098C148E08C5D8B3B938B3D31"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing professional development training needed for apprentices to succeed in a full-time job after the apprenticeship;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7518E800B65493B9CA89BA416CC1CDE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>providing post-apprenticeship job counseling and job placement services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F5C8E1D95994D4CB7F7A1A048DB8FF9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>coordinating pre-apprenticeship training or off-the-job training related to the occupation involved in the apprenticeship; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47B9A8C81F344E799A222D977DC012FF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>arranging for an institution of higher education to provide training courses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBC424458FFF49FAAE5A0F509607612E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local and national support for registered apprenticeships</header><text>The workforce intermediary may support registered apprenticeship programs locally and nationally, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="HFAFE8885FAD049AA8148903139FD414F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>developing national guidelines and standards for registered apprenticeships in non-traditional apprenticeship occupations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD89824B25F4148DBA918D30A82B2A7DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>connecting multi-region efforts for registered apprenticeship programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE014FADAC1F495C9382EFD7E8E84A40"><enum>(C)</enum><text>documenting best practices in operating a workforce intermediary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4840784EB3014BB295F79B611C21B62F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>providing the ongoing infrastructure to support apprenticeships in an industry.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H9B4889BB0E7547E18AC1124BA0F8B73F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Emphasis on in-Demand registered apprenticeship programs</header><text>In carrying out activities under a grant under this Act, the workforce intermediary receiving the grant shall place an emphasis on supporting registered apprenticeship programs that lead to skilled jobs and wages in in-demand industry sectors.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5D62C4C850F447AF86335E4C21FC3F2B"><enum>7.</enum><header>Performance and evaluation</header><subsection commented="no" id="H44F8A26C33CA46908594F475E1433796"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Performance progress reports to the Secretary</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H4660CC33E71C4520874BE8A0F492D0FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary shall require each workforce intermediary receiving a grant under this Act to submit performance progress reports at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0F00B12C98B549E1A2AC0734C37FE985"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each self-evaluation performance report described in paragraph (1) shall include, at a minimum—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB1CD370F637B4B3993D6ED69F8616EBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the goals, plans, and accomplishments of the workforce intermediary;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7C8B8468FD4D445888467A8D42583765"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how grant funds have been used; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB6D19D3F57114E36AC578911A7C975A5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the workforce intermediary has furthered the purposes described in section 4(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A0E6B7F6BA34AD68E65434688814E88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><paragraph id="HF0664F2FC2364FEA8925B6586CE892D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an evaluation of each workforce intermediary that receives a grant under this Act 6 years after the date on which funds for the grant are first disbursed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF6090FD75264F55AE4789A0D5E3723C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of evaluation</header><text>The evaluation described in paragraph (1) shall include a critical analysis of the workforce intermediary—</text><subparagraph id="H984D95188E9045088C384B2C8F2FC7E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by addressing topics such as—</text><clause id="H6483AA7F429E4679ABBCA9131A97052B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the goals of the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H908B82D9742342CAAF563E8163E01C75"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the core competency training offered by the workforce intermediary, without regard as to whether such training was supported by grant funds;</text></clause><clause id="HFBF02CCFED7A4B4F8B97CA07D99F9C96"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the structure of the wage progression or career ladder for each registered apprenticeship program established or supported by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H94CD917E387F44269C3A4D754840ED3F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the major recruitment sources of apprentices for the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H9E2B63263C264AC383FFA09F851E6ACB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>information on how apprentices are selected by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="HCBB9EF8100C04CF687C99A767F32CD28"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the recruitment challenges that the workforce intermediary faces;</text></clause><clause id="HFD354468BC164501BBF5C1FAFDEBA665"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the demographic and educational characteristics of apprentices supported by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H3AE3B28AE25D4E8193E65DA11F19A9C1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the structure of the workforce intermediary, including the number of staff employed by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H8B17131271FD458DAF80C756766B1314"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the factors that contribute to a workforce intermediary’s sustainability and replicability; and</text></clause><clause id="H44348E9B8A2944548EC3AFEDAA855B95"><enum>(x)</enum><text>the number of apprenticeships facilitated by the workforce intermediary and the occupations involved in the apprenticeships; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B2581012343421FAF4CFC2BD3D24F33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that evaluates the workforce intermediary using information on—</text><clause id="HE87B4E0C5C754BB493CC39A1805695CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the levels of performance achieved by the workforce intermediary with respect to the performance indicators under section 116(b)(2)(A) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>), for all apprentices who complete a registered apprenticeship program supported by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H69B7F6DDD526419AB8B06E4DB7D46FA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the completion rates for apprentices in each registered apprenticeship program supported by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause id="H546B4DCCB74642DFA99F73F426EE4989"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>job retention of apprentices, based on 1 year after completing the registered apprenticeship program supported by the workforce intermediary;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89566F6478EE426594BB5169420B08D8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the income level of jobs obtained by apprentices after completing the apprenticeship program; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9BE0858D0014B46B05F6603793A927C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the occupations in in-demand industry sectors, and nontraditional apprenticeship occupations, that the workforce intermediary has successfully served through the grant by creating registered apprenticeship programs in those occupations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04F895502C354B0B8073995351A6C7C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope of evaluation</header><text>In conducting the evaluation under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall, to the fullest extent practicable, limit the evaluation to the efforts of the workforce intermediary supported under this Act, but shall also consider all of the efforts of the workforce intermediary to support registered apprenticeship programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5F1C3458C774023844D82F784387AFA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report</header><text>By not later than 90 days after the evaluation is completed, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the workforce intermediary, and make publicly available, a report that will contain—</text><subparagraph id="H46FDFE6B19934A80820114E2A718D12D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the evaluation, including the topics and information described in paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A5133428A14C1F9306EE31948A9E01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations on how to further improve the outcomes of the workforce intermediary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1CF995D46CA43DBA4343C682EEE0CBC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>The Secretary shall use the performance progress reports and the results of an evaluation under this section for a project to determine whether to renew a grant for the workforce intermediary for that project.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2091B26A90A74DF894781B95AF8E91A9"><enum>8.</enum><header>Workshops; best practices</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall use not more than 5 percent of the funds made available under this Act to—</text><paragraph id="HDA1708AF85F94D32B153D404D322E386"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">plan and conduct workshops throughout the United States to instruct interested organizations on how to create workforce intermediaries on a national, State, or local level, and navigate the grant process described in this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7CFE178DF988406587295954F5E42F98"><enum>(2)</enum><text>disseminate best practices on effective development and implementation of registered apprenticeship programs through workforce intermediaries.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6B3DA2A95047407089ECBF7A821F4530"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

