<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H033E39BF34A745D8812C9D187DA9FAD3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6444 IH: JADC2 Implementation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6444</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231117">November 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To accelerate the identification of solutions to the challenges of the Joint Force by assigning to specific components of the Department of Defense certain responsibilities for the delivery of essential integrated joint warfighting capabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H851D2297F1314B41BA1008AF43C5456E" style="OLC"><section id="HE9E9B65B84C04B72AE9D777325390F4D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>JADC2 Implementation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4C90D6F9D0BB46CA9BA7302AC8FB473A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Roles and responsibilities for components of Office of Secretary of Defense for joint all-domain command and control in support of integrated joint warfighting</header><subsection id="H8147AB54760B448DA08C2DE1D84647EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish the roles and responsibilities of components of the Office of the Secretary of Defense for development and delivery to combatant commands of capabilities that are essential to integrated joint warfighting capabilities, as follows:</text><paragraph id="HFC4B326DE2DF4090AC163C498752AEEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Deputy Chief Technology Officer for Mission Capabilities of the Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering (in this section referred to as the <quote>Deputy Chief</quote>) shall be responsible for—</text><subparagraph id="H25743DDBC511473987111796E7CCE51E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying new technology and operational concepts for experimentation and prototyping for delivery to the Joint Force to address key operational challenges;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7E4882EBB314E6A87B9CE02157304F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing technical support for the Joint Force in exploring and analyzing new capabilities, operational concepts, and systems-of-systems composition, including through advanced modeling and simulation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B7E48612D81491F96EB3B88CC9FA22A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>executing associated experimentation, through the Rapid Defense Experimentation Reserve (RDER) or another mechanism.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE670D7F7C5F420FA372721E3287F954"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Executive Director for Acquisition, Integration, and Interoperability of the Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment shall be responsible for—</text><subparagraph id="HEC3DD1CECFD1410795C20368BB116FF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enabling the acquisition of cross-domain, joint, and cross-system kill chains and mission capabilities, including resourcing of modifications necessary for integration and interoperability among kill chain and mission components; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDECAFED37F6474290E7248C7EFE1678"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring the effectiveness of cross-domain, joint, and cross-system kill chains and mission capabilities through analysis and testing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD30992FC7D14089A0FF0BAE9B0A2092"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer shall be responsible for creating and operating a factory-based approach for software development that allows for iterative, secure, and continuous deployment of developmental, prototype, and operational tools and capabilities from multiple vendors to test networks and operational networks for combatant commanders to—</text><subparagraph id="H80EFB3E66A67428DA49667D88145E503"><enum>(A)</enum><text>gain operational awareness, make decisions, and take actions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9589FD7CD984C3E9B551316359E045B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>integrate relevant data sources to support target selection, target prioritization, and weapon-target pairing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60302A2A572B45E4B1ED2C05E72974DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prosecute targets through military service and combat support agency networks, tools, and systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65017AD6FC8447FAA899E26FC054F0C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional Deputy Chief authorities</header><paragraph id="H15207C3AF8D94C1E8E0135B447A20564"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Deputy Chief may exercise the authorities described in paragraph (2) in accordance with this subsection to carry out the responsibilities of the Deputy Chief described in subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17788F40687E40BD8A742AA698C0A087"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorities described</header><text>The authorities described in this paragraph are—</text><subparagraph id="HA20234D2F4234330BF16B877E3660064"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the authority to enter contracts to acquire goods and services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H100984984FB8465F83E7AE5D525012B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as otherwise provided by this subsection, the authority to appoint, prescribe rates of pay for, and provide additional pay to highly qualified experts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA070280350E4D2B90AD4F5D92567483" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Acquisition authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The laws and regulations applicable to acquisitions of goods and services by the Secretary of Defense shall apply to the acquisition of goods and services by the Deputy Chief pursuant to paragraph (2)(A).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H508B4615233E4BD0BEE8CAC0F24E3157"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Hiring authorities</header><subparagraph id="HA730D67A08274A249E68C76CA971D600"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appointment limits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When exercising the authority described in paragraph (2)(B), the Deputy Chief may—</text><clause id="H28CFC13CE0DE4C25AD3296B4EC867F2C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appoint only individuals with demonstrated expertise in the development, testing, production, and delivery or integration of modular systems and major system components (as defined in section 4401(b) of title 10, United States Code), including autonomous vehicles, advanced sensors and radio systems, and software systems; and</text></clause><clause id="H70EB9D6B97424A6A8670C017DE9A25D2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appoint individuals to not more than 12 positions as program managers in the Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52D725843CDE42268006D7DF331F2093"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Term extension</header><text>The Deputy Chief may extend the period which an employee appointed pursuant to paragraph (2)(B) may serve by up to seven additional years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF18C431D57774CB787CAC6D58283149C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Excepted service positions</header><text>Each position to which the Deputy Chief may appoint an individual pursuant to paragraph (2)(B) shall be in the excepted service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD616300178AF42F896A3B978E7266DDC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The officials referred to in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a) shall coordinate and align their plans and activities to implement subsection (a) among themselves and with the combatant commanders.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3EDA75DB681A465EA5BB7319F6C11805"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Initial prioritization</header><text>In developing an initial set of capabilities described in subsection (a), the officials referred to in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of that subsection shall prioritize the requirements of the United States Indo-Pacific Command.</text></subsection><subsection id="H17D3B8E44EBC4617B28FC487940CBCAE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Briefings required</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter through December 31, 2026, the officials referred to in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a) shall provide briefings to the congressional defense committees on their plans and activities to implement subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0DCC9803228248A084DD1BA5E5558A2C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than March 1, 2024, the Chief Data and Artificial Intelligence Officer, in consultation with the Deputy Chief and the Executive Director for Acquisition, Integration, and Interoperability of the Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment, shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="HABCE60F5BB58416B9CA40E00685912BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan and associated timelines for deploying and demonstrating a joint data integration layer prototype in the United States Indo-Pacific Command area of operations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D523CBE6574422EADB0A4D963181FB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan and associated timelines for transitioning such a prototype, upon its successful demonstration, to fielding as soon as practicable given the urgent need for a joint all-domain command and control (commonly referred to as <quote>JADC2</quote>) capability;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF1F1456344D45E3A1B70D42F5B3338F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a plan and associated timelines for reaching initial operational capability for a joint data integration layer within the United States Indo-Pacific Command area of operations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE661B1ADEBA44401907F2400A5A80F7A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a plan and associated timelines for scaling that capability to future areas of operation across the combatant commands;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H732457F50DA248899223341DC995DC49"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment of the required type and number of personnel at the United States Indo-Pacific Command to enable sustained growth in JADC2 capabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88BF89AE62E847C9AA0D3F91924674F0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a plan and associated timelines for—</text><subparagraph id="HD690A3C5665343D380D7E0643C8D5D35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying specific critical effects chains necessary to overcome anti-access and area denial capabilities and offensive military operations of foreign adversaries; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA40343C873894CD8AF213B2FB0F6D0E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>creating, demonstrating, deploying, and sustaining such chains.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

