<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2017C528DB3A4EA4B6849B603E3D06BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4087 IH: Foreign Adversary Gain-of-Function Research Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4087</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230613">June 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of Federal funds to conduct or support certain gain-of-function research by a foreign adversary.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF6FCB00D4C954CA0801082D96C3D0299" style="OLC"><section id="H6A4603CE651D445280167E04F2FDC36E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Foreign Adversary Gain-of-Function Research Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF588C63D87374B1A91D1A265D44E0C83"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funding for certain gain-of-function research by a foreign adversary</header><subsection id="H5C3532B23E334055B73D12C6D48F35ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be made available, whether directly or indirectly, or used by an entity, to conduct or support any gain-of-function research involving a potential pandemic pathogen by a foreign adversary, including—</text><paragraph id="HBFF283BA44E84C00A0F9A4C2622AB191"><enum>(1)</enum><text>China, Russia, Iran, and North Korea; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE19E8C24A7F342E78DD736F542D85C91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other country the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, or any other appropriate Federal official, determines to be a foreign adversary for the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C55D83FE1224048B4B9781DAE705488"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding freeze for violations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of State determines that an entity has violated subsection (a), such entity—</text><paragraph id="HE15EA864D022418ABEFA0FEE52901F16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for the 3-year period beginning on the date of such determination, may not receive any award or subaward of a grant, cooperative agreement, loan, or contract from the Department of Health and Human Services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FF5D65FD1414344896D71785626372F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the 3-year period beginning on the day after the last day of the period described in paragraph (1), may not receive any award of a grant, cooperative agreement, loan, or contract from the Department of Health and Human Services unless the entity agrees, as a condition of receiving such award to—</text><subparagraph id="H50B34A289F3F4C2DA9887DDAF9DFCBC0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>give notice to the Congress before using such award to make any subaward; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C371F4E82EF4B13AFFDA7F5046E74D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include in any such notice the intended recipient and purpose of the subaward.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB3594487958419EA32BCB0F90EFF5CA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDE4B82CB947D413C942469E930036469"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gain-of-function research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>gain-of-function research</term> means any research that may be reasonably anticipated to confer an attribute to a pathogen such that the pathogen would have enhanced pathogenicity or transmissibility in mammals, including the creation of a chimera.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26DF816FB55E4CA994FE44FC9BF0881C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Potential pandemic pathogen</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>potential pandemic pathogen</term> means a pathogen that, as a result of any gain-of-function research—</text><subparagraph id="H5F0882A6FB984E85A8795AD4A3C7EF37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is likely more transmissible or likely capable of wide and uncontrollable spread in human populations; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCA8048DF3BC478CB266BF837621C11F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is likely more virulent or likely to cause modest or greater morbidity or mortality in humans; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D72113F4B3C4A0AB978CFB84FA66B02"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is likely to pose a severe threat to public health, the capacity of the public health systems to function, or national security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

