<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBE27852278534CE69379E248C85C47C2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>102 HR 289 IH: Protect Our Water Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 289</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To update requirements for the operation of the Central Valley Project and Klamath River Basin Reclamation Project by the Bureau of Reclamation.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H522C0AF2006A490CAD9575ADF3193C74" style="OLC"><section id="HF9808BBFFB8B4AF4AC0FAE02909F9378" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Our Water Rights Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H6ADDC05E66BE4FCAB1FF14D55DDF85E0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Allocations for Sacramento Valley contractors</header><subsection id="HC076F2BFE9E345AE8F35997284D2C3E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allocations; Conditions</header><paragraph id="HB73BF8CCFB12450C9F7527AA48BAF244"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Allocations</header><subparagraph id="H625B3928836A43EC8B009F00B4007B13"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Bureau of Reclamation (in this Act, referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) is directed, in the operation of the Central Valley Project, to allocate water provided for irrigation purposes to existing Central Valley Project agricultural water service contractors within the Sacramento River Watershed in compliance with the following:</text><clause id="H3A3C9D9EA7B447B69F874EA285014089"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Not less than 100 percent of their contract quantities in a <quote>Wet</quote> year.</text></clause><clause id="HD3A0A4108ED846EEBEA7A3FB8D774FCE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Not less than 100 percent of their contract quantities in an <quote>Above Normal</quote> year.</text></clause><clause id="H031FFCFCB30441A2ABC32CA3CF5B2011"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Not less than 75 percent of their contract quantities in a <quote>Below Normal</quote> year.</text></clause><clause id="HC5ABCADA9B1C44719474991385AAA2DF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Not less than 50 percent of their contract quantities in a <quote>Dry</quote> year.</text></clause><clause id="H3EBBCE12BD654BA7B6A33A74E450BF3B"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 50 percent of their contract quantities in a <quote>Critically Dry</quote> year.</text></clause><clause id="H5EC9B5DFCBC1432A8CBEDF4D79FBA89A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>In all years not identified in subparagraphs (A) through (E), the allocation percentage for existing Central Valley Project agricultural water service contractors within the Sacramento River Watershed shall not be less than (but may be more than) twice the allocation percentage to south-of-Delta Central Valley Project agricultural water service contractors, up to 100 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90D608A3A4E44207A2B2BD30F659EB97"><enum>(B)</enum><header>The year type terms</header><text>The year type terms used in subparagraph (A) have the meaning given those year types in the Sacramento Valley Water Year Type (40–30–30) Index.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H28820621678F445883C22627CD83A979"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The Secretary’s actions under paragraph (1) shall be subject to—</text><subparagraph id="H88D5DC89C4684F248C4464D065F4DA9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the priority of individuals or entities with Sacramento River water rights, including those with Sacramento River Settlement Contracts, that have priority to the diversion and use of Sacramento River water over water rights held by the United States for operations of the Central Valley Project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FB1E630ECFB464498A7CEFB14D449F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the United States obligation to make a substitute supply of water available to the San Joaquin River Exchange Contractors; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA0DD0B3E44A4C30920B1EA8B84A0DF4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary’s obligation to make water available to managed wetlands pursuant to section 3406(d) of the Central Valley Project Improvement Act, (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/575">Public Law 102–575</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8620C45B885A48A6A81AA95A12DF0C76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Protection of municipal and industrial supplies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a) shall be deemed to—</text><paragraph id="HA8480DB2D1294743A7742107820A2818"><enum>(1)</enum><text>modify any provision of a water service contract that addresses municipal and industrial water shortage policies of the Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30244DFB86974AE7B179E794D6FFEFA9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>affect or limit the authority of the Secretary to adopt or modify municipal and industrial water shortage policies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01143E3D46BE4E83A9452826BF8D5BBE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>affect or limit the authority of the Secretary to implement municipal and industrial water shortage policies; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H026D6147216F4F0E9902359CD65AFD43"><enum>(4)</enum><text>affect allocations to Central Valley Project municipal and industrial contractors pursuant to such policies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H61057B94426342809F9EBF72014F3CAD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Protection of operations and deliveries</header><text>Nothing in subsection (a) or the Secretary’s implementation of subsection (a) shall constrain, govern, or affect, directly or indirectly, the operations of the Central Valley Project’s American River Division or any deliveries from that Division, its units or facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3B19C3F4FA944C878992A9D202E8FAA1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No effect on allocations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H45FF876F6FD64A419776EB8019972CC5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>affect the allocation of water to Friant Division contractors; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB161B8C11B874B02885FE3116A01B7B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>result in the involuntary reduction in contract water allocations to individuals or entities with contracts to receive water from the Friant Division.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE13D12A907CD4BE8B5CA60A217999B91"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Term defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>existing Central Valley Project agricultural water service contractors within the Sacramento River Watershed</term> means water service contractors within the Shasta, Trinity, and Sacramento River Divisions of the Central Valley Project, that have a water service contract in effect, on the date of the enactment of this section, that provides water for irrigation.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7A535476708A45E3BE64A8A3BD1B251E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Annual Allocation Field Briefings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall hold not less than 1 in-person field hearing each county where a Central Valley Project water service contractor is located during the period that is after the initial water allocations for the Central Valley Project and before the final water allocation announcement for the Central Valley Project.</text></section><section id="H624009F2D06E4E48B4EE6A1B1B335CAB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Adjustment of cost requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The operation and maintenance costs required to be paid by Central Valley Project water contractors and the Bureau of Reclamation shall be reversed, such that—</text><paragraph id="H9F7CAA8DBD1045DD995D354E262A77C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the allocation percentage obligation held by the Bureau of Reclamation on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act shall be held by Central Valley Project water contractors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA211FF4788FC445A9B08C36FEF0462B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the allocation percentage obligation held by the Central Valley Project water contractors on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act shall be held by the Bureau of Reclamation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC2D7680FB52B4F92AD052C5BEFD5E9A3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes an account of amounts that irrigation districts and water user associations contracted with the Bureau of Reclamation for agricultural water deliveries owe to the Bureau of Reclamation related to debt incurred for construction of facilities and other aspects of the Klamath River Basin Reclamation Project.</text></section><section id="H990BEE532BE4430E9A6E83B970E8C77D" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Water operations in Upper Klamath Lake</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">When operating the Klamath River Basin Reclamation Project, the Secretary, in accordance with State-adjudicated water rights, shall—</text><paragraph id="H5712F76E269B4B9DAF49E2C32607D594" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>operate all water in Upper Klamath Lake above elevation 4136.0 feet solely for agricultural and refuge purposes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC023F5C2155431687EAA8311C876F13" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable when operating all water in Upper Klamath Lake in accordance with paragraph (1), maximize storage in the Upper Klamath Lake.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

