<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF80450CE964946E2B848BCE15FFD757B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 232 IH: Real Justice for Our Veterans Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 232</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230110">January 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to prioritize veterans court treatment programs that ensure equal access for racial and ethnic minorities and women, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD2F07043D9E04ECAAFBE91FAA8910D9E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H39BFA46621264976A16A69BC833823F2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Real Justice for Our Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HF848FA2FBE9849408980551BE5CA83DC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Equal access to veterans court treatment programs for racial and ethnic minorities and women</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2991(i)(2) of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10651">34 U.S.C. 10651(i)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7BADEE847E7B46848542C4F4B0F1138A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HB5862FE27FD24C8581AD2E39794652F5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this subparagraph, the Attorney General shall submit to Congress a report on the effectiveness of veterans treatment court programs. In preparing such a report, the Attorney General shall conduct a national multi-site evaluation of such programs, including an assessment of—</text> <clause id="H61C3ACEFB5BB4252AB4BD7973AF4AD75"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the population served by such programs;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H96E91C955D904BE88FF07499DDFD4D74"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether such programs use evidence-based treatments for substance use and mental health, including medication for addiction treatment;</text></clause> <clause id="HFC5F8B29485C405BB43E19D89ECF8F9B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>recidivism rates of participants in such programs;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1C5614722648434B868B3C6780299BC2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>program completion rates; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA828982BE6E74F0A927A66F54B029E83"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether racial and ethnic minorities and women have equal access to such programs and an equal opportunity to complete such programs, including by collecting and analyzing data related to admission in such programs and completion of such programs, to ensure there are not disparities related to race, ethnicity, or sex.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H96C23840F45B465B8D3A7F0DFFCC57AC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Veterans pilot program on promising retention models</header> 
<subsection id="HAE95E33BB69D4F0CAC5E86FD78C23F05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance, shall carry out a pilot program to make grants to eligible units of local government to improve retention in veterans treatment court programs (as such term is defined in section 2991 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10651">34 U.S.C. 10651</external-xref>)) and drug court programs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H21FC31006E67499F9A03273390875D75"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>In order to be eligible for a grant under subsection (a), a unit of local government shall operate a veterans treatment court program or a drug court.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H228A4C6492F946DCAA1A71B88875A1C2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A unit of local government seeking a grant through the pilot program under subsection (a) shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require, including—</text> <paragraph id="H69A24788EE7A4239B13952B408CBC38D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the therapeutic or treatment modality that the unit of local government plans to implement and data to support the use of the therapeutic or treatment modality, including information showing how the therapeutic or treatment modality will promote retention in and completion of veterans treatment court programs and drug court programs; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H416EC4EBF8AB47BFA3C9F63E19462D6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">detailed plans on how the applicant would test the efficacy of the therapeutic or treatment modality.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8D6A072601204808B18EEA80E2E7E117"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting metrics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after receiving a grant under subsection (a), a unit of local government shall submit to the Attorney General a report, which includes demographic information of participants in the veterans treatment court program, and completion rates of such participants. The Attorney General shall develop guidelines for the report required under this subsection. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDC78AA0F708149AFAEC70988F727081D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $3,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD79661F5842A4938A40A7CA5255C8076"><enum>4.</enum><header>Admission of veterans to drug courts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In the case of a jurisdiction that does not operate a veterans treatment court program (as such term is defined in section 2991 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10651">34 U.S.C. 10651</external-xref>)), but that does operate a drug court under part EE of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10611">34 U.S.C. 10611 et seq.</external-xref>), a veteran who would be eligible to participate in a veterans treatment court program may participate in the drug court, including a veteran who is a violent offender (as such term is defined in section 2953(a) of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10613">34 U.S.C. 10613(a)</external-xref>)). </text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

