<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2472F7BB112C49F6BFF16D9B88491E0A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1218 IH: Expediting Israeli Aerial Refueling Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1218</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230227">February 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Air Force to provide training to members of the air force of Israel on the operation of KC–46 aircraft, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCD91D782A5D7414E83F9CB40A4628666" style="OLC"><section id="H17162C98B0C646A3BDE465EB0A619BEE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expediting Israeli Aerial Refueling Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H18EE3899E99B4154A429FD953ED08A1A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Training Israeli pilots to operate KC–46 aircraft</header><subsection id="H2C51EBFE8CAA4CB3B12E62F1C1C252E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Air Force shall—</text><paragraph id="H1A0C379FE846430E99C4A37A18A0BA63"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make available sufficient resources and accommodations within the United States to train members of the air force of Israel on the operation of KC–46 aircraft; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB2AE48E0C6C4030898180B90426C73A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conduct training for members of the air force of Israel, including—</text><subparagraph id="HBBCABC4EC3D5452C963A705C6D016F53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>training for pilots and crew on the operation of the KC–46 aircraft in accordance with standards considered sufficient to conduct coalition operations of the United States Air Force and the air force of Israel; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A01D3B095194AF39E18566C16AD6FB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>training for ground personnel on the maintenance and sustainment requirements of the KC–46 aircraft considered sufficient for such operations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27FFD546B1014F2094CBEAFBEF55174F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>United States Air Force Military Personnel Exchange Program</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall, with respect to members of the air force of Israel associated with the operation of KC–46 aircraft—</text><paragraph id="H987FC6017BD7497DA532F185D2ACB7BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>before the completion of the training required by subsection (a)(2), authorize the participation of such members of the air force of Israel in the United States Air Force Military Personnel Exchange Program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1F8456D34B04B6F822E884F9CED4FF2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make the United States Air Force Military Personnel Exchange Program available to such members of the air force of Israel; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8941002DA287491CBA8927F8F341AA4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, ensure that such members of the air force of Israel may participate in the United States Air Force Military Personnel Exchange Program immediately after such members complete such training.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D96B8E09B504A3EBE6DD5BC8A29A808"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>This section shall cease to have effect on the date that is ten years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE600138CC5C043C49FC7480DAD436EB0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Forward deployment of United States KC–46 aircraft to Israel</header><subsection id="H4CDCBDE7E62E4485BC450099707ED0BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report that describes the capacity of and requirements for the United States Air Force to forward deploy KC–46 aircraft to Israel on a rotational basis until the date on which not fewer than four KC–46 aircraft procured by the military forces of Israel are commissioned into such military forces and achieve full combat capability.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B587CC4C0894E0AB88E77A8F8C2A25D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rotational forces</header><paragraph id="HA625FE9825C04A2E87ED18FC5D3C4BAF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary of Defense shall rotationally deploy one or more KC–46 aircraft to Israel until the earlier of—</text><subparagraph id="HA291887DE10341BDB4A3A1984FF14929"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date on which a KC–46 aircraft procured by the military forces of Israel is commissioned into such military forces and achieves full combat capability; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBAB94A3B88F4828AD27074E48D77F03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD555594A45448F59D45CD8656A83A6F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Description</header><text>The one or more KC–46 aircraft deployed under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H3311FCD8294F46969577A39908C17CAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may vary in size and number, as the Secretary of Defense considers appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB298413F979E4C21B73E0498795061C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>beginning in the year that is one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and in each year thereafter until the applicable date described in that paragraph, shall remain in Israel for a period not less than 270 days.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

