<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB0B8076B6F340DF978B70F34C73DEDE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4882 IH: Clinical Laboratory Price Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4882</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to promote laboratory price transparency under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA491D80CB38841D9A38D4BE2E96ECBE3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H21D4773AC1304DC4A772CBBF16759F90" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clinical Laboratory Price Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7FADF48E2ED14E5C9FC59DFDD478750C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Promoting laboratory price transparency under the Medicare program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part E of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD236FCBB2BB448294CF5FB8EFAF34D3"> 
<section id="H34507BA2299A4FA5857C44B5AD15322A"><enum>1899C.</enum><header>Laboratory price transparency requirement</header> 
<subsection id="H246CE01840DC436A9C6694B8AEFDAF39"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning January 1, 2025, each applicable laboratory that receives payment under this title for furnishing a specified clinical diagnostic laboratory test shall—</text> <paragraph id="H0010DFAEF2E341AD924056879A84DBCD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make publicly available (in a manner and form specified by the Secretary) on an Internet website the information described in subsection (b) with respect to each such specified clinical diagnostic laboratory test that such laboratory is so available to furnish; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC17EE624356449FA95C82406D1DB5CDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that such information is updated not less frequently than annually.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H263B48C12385498EA7728B6E2E48E1C7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the information described in this subsection is, with respect to an applicable laboratory and a specified clinical diagnostic laboratory test, the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9D750B5128B64BE3921AD81D5FA66A18"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The discounted cash price for such test (or, if no such price exists, the gross charge for such test).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADEB6E4EF6C74E95A18C718CD2D2483C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If required by the Secretary, the deidentified minimum negotiated rate in effect between such laboratory and any group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage for such test and the deidentified maximum negotiated rate in effect between such laboratory and any such plan or coverage for such test.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HCB88FC46F7374F529575A1927CA9F79F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Method and format</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2028, the Secretary shall establish one or more methods and formats for each provider of services and supplier to use in compiling and making public standard charges and prices (as applicable) pursuant to subsection (a). Any such method and format—</text> <paragraph id="HF3491CCFC23C48FC81E80B552F5187DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may be similar to any template made available by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services as of the date of the enactment of this subsection;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H410310246D464E6A88EF3D538E18530E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall meet such standards as determined appropriate by the Secretary in order to ensure the accessibility and usability of such charges and prices; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2E58113E2FD4DD3B825E901D420DC25"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall be updated as determined appropriate by the Secretary, in consultation with stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H33D8C50DB9394792A52FFE53875A2220"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Monitoring compliance</header><text>The Secretary shall, through notice and comment rulemaking and in consultation with the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services, establish a process to monitor compliance with this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2F05D7F8576C4BD68D704F829DE38063"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <paragraph id="HB4E1406182CD4B1496786015C6693154"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that the Secretary determines that an applicable laboratory is not in compliance with subsection (a)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H435D50CC572B4BB6AFD3F276E940204D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 30 days after such determination, the Secretary shall notify such laboratory of such determination;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE430FEA96EDC425EA7355DA1AF4A1E4A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>upon request of the Secretary, such laboratory shall submit to the Secretary, not later than 45 days after such request is sent, a corrective action plan to comply with such subsection; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAFD0612B838D46CDAEFEEAB5C4211AEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such laboratory continues to fail to comply with such paragraph after the date that is 90 days after such notification is sent (or, in the case of such a laboratory that has submitted a corrective action plan described in subparagraph (B) in response to a request so described, after the date that is 90 days after such submission), the Secretary may impose a civil monetary penalty in an amount not to exceed $300 for each subsequent day during which such failure to comply is ongoing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1793F225E00E4061AC2FC543DC8FF623" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Increase authority</header><text>In applying this paragraph with respect to violations occurring in 2027 or a subsequent year, the Secretary may through notice and comment rulemaking increase the amount of the civil monetary penalty under paragraph (1)(C).</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H54E8B19D1E6A4E9286243E944B59D4A3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application of certain provisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of section 1128A (other than subsections (a) and (b) of such section) shall apply to a civil monetary penalty imposed under this subsection in the same manner as such provisions apply to a civil monetary penalty imposed under subsection (a) of such section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H89C076022F834CAD93332FEC009DFCC5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authority to waive or reduce penalty</header><text>The Secretary may waive or reduce any penalty otherwise applicable with respect to an applicable laboratory under this paragraph if the Secretary determines that imposition of such penalty would result in a significant hardship for such laboratory (such as in the case of an applicable laboratory located in a rural or underserved area where imposition of such penalty may result in, or contribute to, a lack of access to care for individuals in such area).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H965B4213409748C8B961CAADB440BA82"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Clarification of nonapplicability of other enforcement provisions</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, this subsection shall be the sole means of enforcing the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE8438A7789F34B078FEF6F6573FECAB1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF630CE1205844BD6B188B5810C057A2A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable laboratory</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>applicable laboratory</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 414.502, of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC1A2F82996A34314B99AE1429AA5E8D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Group health plan; group health insurance coverage; individual health insurance coverage</header><text>The terms <quote>group health plan</quote>, <quote>group health insurance coverage</quote>, and <quote>individual health insurance coverage</quote> have the meaning given such terms in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H51610A6E1FA54099B3B71847568150F8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Specified clinical diagnostic laboratory test</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>specified clinical diagnostic laboratory test</quote> means a clinical diagnostic laboratory test that is included on the list of shoppable services specified by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services pursuant to section 180.60 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), other than such a test that is an advanced diagnostic laboratory test (as defined in section 1834A(d)(5)).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill>

