<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H94A833C0F8EF4BAF946EFEE88B0E686B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1206 IH: Federal Agency Sunset Commission Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1206</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230227">February 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the Federal Agency Sunset Commission.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H80E8382D342643F6BED3EF2F1FCE7FCD" style="OLC">
<section id="HA890D1D7003D4E168D96E14EFBD5D762" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Agency Sunset Commission Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2940A098B99C447DA9A99779541D4B3D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Review and abolishment of Federal agencies</header> <subsection id="HF67940B83B264827892A8EB2B3418F4D" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Schedule for review</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9008FAE0132D404A8AB47863C4E55EC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Agency Sunset Commission established under section 3 shall submit to Congress a schedule for review by the Commission of each agency that lists the date of abolishment for each agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE604A2A17C6F4094BE8EB267FB45D1FD" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such date of abolishment shall occur at least once every 12 years (or less, if determine appropriate by Congress).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H305DD115D3EA40538D2BAC5BE51FD102" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Schedule for review will be in the form of a joint resolution.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3A96AA60991F4F8999CFF74D4B7B851A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review of agencies performing related functions</header><text>In determining the schedule for review of agencies under subsection (a), the Commission shall provide that agencies that perform similar or related functions be reviewed concurrently to promote efficiency and consolidation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6CEBE894929A46DAA2CA230DE9F6BA8B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Abolishment of agencies</header> <paragraph id="H5867C74E42534A7FB00A6F7D338FBF1B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each agency shall be reviewed and abolished according to the schedule created pursuant to this section and approved under section 9, unless the agency is reauthorized by the Congress.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB656B79ACD7F4D2A92DB2EF1DB129722"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>The date of abolishment for an agency may be extended for an additional 2 years if the Congress enacts legislation extending such date by a vote of a supermajority of the House of Representatives and the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H856D7385DB334BAC9B95055C58CF7300"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Commission</header> <subsection id="HD23ED08C9C984FEEA34EE14EB0314474"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a commission to be known as the <quote>Federal Agency Sunset Commission</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H676A79C5246F446988DFE451DD069AD4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<paragraph id="H9E4182044F8F46E792ED99F553EBE756"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Commission shall be composed of 13 members (in this Act referred to as the <quote>members</quote>) who shall be appointed as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="HDA0D0425C0064FA7812D041EB300ECE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed by the President.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF98EA91912104432881DA6A51FA89BEB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>3 shall be appointed by the majority leader of the Senate, of whom—</text> <clause id="HD83E6037E89247C7AA2E49C350895C1C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 shall be from among Members of the Senate; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H4C417A7FBB2C4D55A10EEE09986B0E17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall not be Member of Congress and shall have expertise in the operation and administration of Federal Government programs.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB939754E56C4C2A9FDDBF7A8071F77E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>3 shall be appointed by the minority leader of the Senate, of whom—</text>
<clause id="H22719DBC57D948E0AE9500F51DE8A6E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 shall be from among Members of the Senate; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3882DB0ACA6946D8AD1DD841E6D2C6F1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall not be Member of Congress and shall have expertise in the operation and administration of Federal Government programs.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8C1A2FACCBBF4D17836B4BD72F35447E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>3 shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives, of whom—</text> <clause id="H113C9B1608954984AC9B7987BA687E22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 shall be from among Members of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H789020D8AE7344ABA1E7B4AB2D293852"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall not be Member of Congress and shall have expertise in the operation and administration of Federal Government programs.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95EE8A57B0304C259F81F50520FAC47A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>3 shall be appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives, of whom—</text>
<clause id="HF7CD15ECDE4C48808980E54666428060"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 shall be from among Members of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause> <clause id="H21534381EEFA42D9B4766BD7DD4A1C2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 shall not be Member of Congress and shall have expertise in the operation and administration of Federal Government programs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2DB2F464B58F4C9396DEB79CE5327034"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Continuation of Membership</header><text>If a member was appointed to the Commission as a Member of Congress and the member ceases to be a Member of Congress, that member shall cease to be a member of the Commission.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1ACE3CAF643E43588E12D1100B03B83C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Initial appointments</header><text>All initial appointments to the Commission shall be made not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H39DA872BEA9148EF8102DC66BBCFED63"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Terms of members</header>
<paragraph id="H8790E28E78484CA7AD4543499322CC50"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member appointed to the Commission shall serve for a term of 6 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB562AD3EEAC743358BFD6BD870A17C03"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy in the Commission—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9ACCC4B34EE644BD9AE90D9BF1526488"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not affect the powers of the Commission; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H99D791953CCE4CD78BC504857E7DC3AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment not later than 30 days after the date on which the vacancy occurs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7DC51C99D1F648539C5D2456436DF0EF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Chairman; vice chairman</header><text>The Commission shall select a Chairperson and Vice Chairperson from among the members of the Commission for a term of 4 years.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC69E50507F504A9B992FF91C376E4475"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Powers of commission</header> <paragraph id="HA1A2332917D0480A85B31E9E628F18E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hearings and sessions</header><text>The Commission may, for the purpose of carrying out this Act, hold such hearings, sit and act at such times and places, take such testimony, and receive such evidence as the Commission considers appropriate. The Commission may administer oaths to witnesses appearing before it.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA952FE3436AD4DDA9499AC2D54D85E3E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Obtaining information</header>
<subparagraph id="H7B5B451E09A74A579C151285825C3FB2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission may secure directly from any agency or advisory committee information necessary to enable it to carry out its duties under this Act.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAC30283E90434BF39EC1138AF6251D0C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Furnishing information</header><text>On request of the Chairperson of the Commission, the head of the agency, or the Chair of the advisory committee shall furnish information to the Commission in a full and timely manner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF08F35ADEFC54263B8F521F6E7FA0022"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Subpoena power</header>
<subparagraph id="H5763302F856743999A6B8F7E24CA6FA2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Authority to issue subpoena</header><text>The Commission may issue a subpoena to require the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of evidence relating to any matter under investigation by the Commission.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H111360EA07C149E99247E2C7287B5D92"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compliance with subpoena</header><text>If a person refuses to obey an order or subpoena of the Commission that is issued in connection with a Commission proceeding, the Commission may apply to the United States district court in the judicial district in which the proceeding is held for an order requiring the person to comply with the subpoena or order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA24A657F9F0B48C7A1DA124968521AA4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Immunity</header><text>The Commission is an agency of the United States for purposes of part V of title 18, United States Code (relating to immunity of witnesses).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D0D77BB5DB1415A89310470D1F31140"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><text>The Commission may contract with and compensate government and private agencies or persons for services without regard to section 6101 of title 41, United States Code (relating to advertising requirement for Federal Government purchases and sales).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB3243897DB644BADBA6FDA4CE4CBFE43"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Commission procedures</header>
<paragraph id="HDB122F3BC7BE4A0286561DEF1763D93E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial meeting</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date on which all members of the Commission have been appointed, the Commission shall hold the first meeting of the Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE373D7BE9F7F4496A7FDF94281CA99B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Commission shall meet at the call of the Chairman and not less than 2 times per year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2EC19F1991644C14977BE6C02A47651A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC15AF3CF5695428EAF59BA206274E44E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Voting</header><text>The schedule for review submitted pursuant to section 2(a) and the report and joint resolution submitted pursuant to section 4 shall have the approval of not less than a majority of the members of the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5B6FDC7F8E0B4D9295EC459B32A342AC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Personnel matters</header>
<paragraph id="HB10FA305E97A41889544B791051E8183"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>Members shall not be paid by reason of their service as members.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F9275B82EE14FC7A951B6CC69A3AB97"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9AB44B82B74443D7B21FEBD845FE4C48"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Commission shall have an executive director who shall be appointed and terminated by the Chairperson of the Commission.</text> <subparagraph id="HE63EB0C85355431DB7767451A0F56032"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The executive director must be confirmed by a vote of at least seven members of the Commission.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1D4BDDA185804E68A3F4FF76468B40D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Director may appoint and fix the pay of additional personnel as the Director considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51030140AAA3485B923DF08DB1FA25E0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability of certain civil service laws</header><text>The Director and staff of the Commission shall be appointed subject to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service, and shall be paid in accordance with the provisions of chapter 51 and sub-chapter III of chapter 53 of that title relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3D6B774AFA2B4E51BE4E7E45194B4728"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Other administrative matters</header>
<paragraph id="H9425921CA74E4F06857B62A1B6D487F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Postal and printing services</header><text>The Commission may use the United States mails and obtain printing and binding services in the same manner and under the same conditions as other departments and agencies of the Federal Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D5EB99E0E0B450294A58313BC98834D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative support services</header><text>Upon the request of the Commission, the Administrator of General Services shall provide to the Commission, on a reimbursable basis, the administrative support services necessary for the Commission to carry out its duties under this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC495C330F70C439C8017DF37133C0713"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Experts and consultants</header><text>The Commission may procure temporary and intermittent services under section 3109(b) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A31AD851830488ABDC196826953BA79"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Gifts</header><text>The Commission may accept, use, and dispose of gifts or donations of services or property.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H375DB4AFCE24425EA741E0EEAE696FAE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Review of efficiency and need for Federal agencies</header>
<subsection id="HE6E41C0300BD47138D7720CD82D7955F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall review the efficiency and public need for each agency using criteria described in section 5.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9B501B00D3AC468689348CACE7C4AA67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations; report to congress</header><text>The Commission shall submit to Congress and the President not later than September 1 of each year a report containing—</text>
<paragraph id="H6F90E8E42265412CA03BFFD6843FD92C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of the efficiency of operation and public need for each agency to be reviewed in the year in which the report is submitted pursuant to the schedule submitted to Congress under section 2;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5AA50FA61A946E7B913C2891CEAD2C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of authority claimed by the executive branch but not specifically authorized by statute;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A9C9002FF7E407EB8600CF00DBCEC68"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations on whether each such agency should be abolished, reorganized, or continued;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5884B31242024543BA42B6D683502DB3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations on whether the functions of any other agencies should be consolidated, transferred, or reorganized in an agency to be reviewed in the year in which the report is submitted pursuant to the schedule submitted to Congress under section 2; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE6AF757422694E3B9AB7C4ABEEF82C3C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>recommendations for administrative and legislative action with respect to each such agency, but not including recommendations for appropriation levels.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H27B07EB60DDA450FA286F5677D7613F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Joint resolution</header><text>The Commission shall submit to Congress and the President not later than September 1 of each year a joint resolution to carry out the recommendations of the Commission under subsection (b).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4DDC8748738E4628A72473C5011893D7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Information gathering</header><text>The Commission shall—</text> <paragraph id="H4C44AAAC3B5C465182759BD423AAE8DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct public hearings on the abolishment of each agency reviewed under subsection (b);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H98FCD95B0CE34689B2D868B28251A521"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide an opportunity for public comment on the abolishment of each such agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF64ECC2ED504C278E36F4299F0372A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>require the agency to provide information to the Commission as appropriate; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H268A311223DC49B6A2CCE6238930DE98"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consult with the General Accountability Office, the Office of Management and Budget, the Comptroller General, and the chairman and ranking minority members of the committees of Congress with oversight responsibility for the agency being reviewed regarding the operation of the agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H27A57AA94A534CB18E5290F58EAC4982"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of program inventory</header><text>The Commission shall use the program inventory prepared under section 9 in reviewing the efficiency and public need for each agency under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H127CC4740C804BEEB87E679BDC296DAD"><enum>5.</enum><header>Criteria for review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Commission shall evaluate the efficiency and public need for each agency pursuant to section 4 using the following criteria:</text> <paragraph id="H2A39263DA6B04AAE83BCA77CC82C2FB9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The effectiveness, and the efficiency of the operation of, the programs carried out by each such agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H971EE6E33B6D4DAA8A5213B3BF4FBDCD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Whether the programs carried out by the agency are cost-effective.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H582472BB22464A0588F19694A1AF607E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Whether the agency has acted outside the scope of its original authority, and whether the original objectives of the agency have been achieved.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H97CB60137110407C87B1C00B3F09132C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Whether less restrictive or alternative methods exist to carry out the functions of the agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF7AE359706724EC888DC28DA84D96DBA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The extent to which the jurisdiction of, and the programs administered by, the agency duplicate or conflict with the jurisdiction and programs of other agencies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22FACF7EBD614D85A99B1C0C5566AEC4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The potential benefits of consolidating programs administered by the agency with similar or duplicative programs of other agencies, and the potential for consolidating such programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C088E94AAC64A979B561C363A2E86AE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The number and types of beneficiaries or persons served by programs carried out by the agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H54CD39AF3A324ADFAAD7A1C1FC0D2A19"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The extent to which any trends, developments, and emerging conditions that are likely to affect the future nature and extent of the problems or needs that the programs carried out by the agency are intended to address.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB33E191B0564431BEADCA3316F770E0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The extent to which the agency has complied with the applicable provisions contained in the sections 1115, 1116, 1117, 1120, 1121, 1122, 1123, 1124, 1125, and the first 9703 of title 31, United States Code, section 306 of title 5, United States Code, and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/39/28">chapter 28</external-xref> of title 39, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA84B57B316ED44F981E0B6B271467F1E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The promptness and effectiveness with which the agency seeks public input and input from State and local governments on the efficiency and effectiveness of the performance of the functions of the agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H89479A5471C341F98E166B7340E2A158"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Whether the agency has worked to enact changes in the law that are intended to benefit the public as a whole rather than the specific business, institution, or individuals that the agency regulates.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B07D9488FCF43339CAF4B58ADA13CA5"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The extent to which the agency has encouraged participation by the public as a whole in making its rules and decisions rather than encouraging participation solely by those it regulates.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H255CB55D2A6B43F28F22C98747E5211E"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The extent to which the public participation in rulemaking and decision making of the agency has resulted in rules and decisions compatible with the objectives of the agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H105EBEB33D504813BF793F81659391C4"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The extent to which the agency complies with equal employment opportunity requirements regarding equal employment opportunity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FFBE7B6023549409CFE25D55714E320"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The extent of the regulatory, privacy, and paperwork impacts of the programs carried out by the agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB46D66740C7D4387B41790B480F02D50"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The extent to which the agency has coordinated with State and local governments in performing the functions of the agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4916693A291941F9AB10A90554F55D44"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The potential effects of abolishing the agency on State and local governments.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA1918273E74D465D97A9662AAB748F52"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The extent to which changes are necessary in the authorizing statutes of the agency in order that the functions of the agency can be performed in the most efficient and effective manner.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H71A287C846F94302AA766078467474AF"><enum>6.</enum><header>Oversight by Commission</header> <subsection id="H5DA57FC3A7B047F5972EC8AF7D5A6731"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Monitoring of implementation of recommendations</header><text>The Commission shall monitor implementation of laws enacting provisions that incorporate recommendations of the Commission with respect to abolishment or reorganization of agencies.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE7B3A15A3407431A8334845508084E83"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Monitoring of other relevant legislation</header>
<paragraph id="HBA76AEEDC6FC4761B64A4E74D14E5231"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall review and report to Congress on all legislation introduced in either house of Congress that would establish—</text> <subparagraph id="HFE1FA8A3709F4DC8920AACCE232EBD4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a new agency; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAFC6908F03AD442DA10A98BD9B72FE02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a new program to be carried out by an existing agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA03426AB4C347CCBC3EA8C792D490BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>The Commission shall include in each report submitted to Congress under paragraph (1) an analysis of whether—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB98E4D7498C447758D64600F4807700C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the functions of the proposed agency or program could be carried out by one or more existing agencies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H828209D8DAF74C5186B38E74318C7534"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the functions of the proposed agency or program could be carried out in a less restrictive manner than the manner proposed in the legislation; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1F6A9CEFD9FA49A1B61CF914ACCE8FA8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the legislation provides for public input regarding the performance of functions by the proposed agency or program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HF7DA3507F1F24DFE9CFBD7FA94D7461F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Disposition of agency affairs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President, in consultation with the head of an agency determined to be abolished pursuant to section 2(c), shall take such action as may be necessary to wind down the operation of such agency during the one year period following the date of abolishment for each such agency including the designation of an agency to carry out any ongoing authority, maintain custodial records, act as a party to unresolved legal actions or other obligations that cannot be resolved within one year.</text></section>
<section id="H153843B74C5E441B8F2FF7A231A2EF89"><enum>8.</enum><header>Program inventory</header>
<subsection id="H89FC1A65D2064F05A1AE358563BB9696"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Preparation</header><text>The Comptroller General and the Director of the Congressional Budget Office, in cooperation with the Director of the Congressional Research Service, shall prepare an inventory of Federal programs (in this Act referred to as the <quote>program inventory</quote>) within each agency.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFA05DA27042B4FFCA555118257FA3196"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the program inventory is to advise and assist the Congress and the Commission in carrying out the requirements of this Act. Such inventory shall not in any way bind the committees of the Senate or the House of Representatives with respect to their responsibilities under this Act and shall not infringe on the legislative and oversight responsibilities of such committees. The Comptroller General shall compile and maintain the inventory and the Director of the Congressional Budget Office shall provide budgetary information for inclusion in the inventory.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1ACA3B08779A4CC5B6A24D55F985379C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inventory content</header><text>The program inventory shall set forth for each program each of the following matters:</text> <paragraph id="H08F02D63EE184DD98FBBF9F7753C0820"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The specific provision or provisions of law authorizing the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6249D59B1CB74787B5BE12CA62E60412"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The committees of the Senate and the House of Representatives which have legislative or oversight jurisdiction over the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H634C397815F241A88EDEBDCFA931B532"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A brief statement of the purpose or purposes to be achieved by the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6EC30D7697984F4F92F0C289896BDB16"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The committees which have jurisdiction over legislation providing new budget authority for the program, including the appropriate subcommittees of the Committees on Appropriations of the Senate and the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C0562CC80814568846C21C693AE252C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The agency and, if applicable, the subdivision thereof responsible for administering the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6654016C2DB147DC85F8C95BF7CE6EF7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The grants-in-aid, if any, provided by such program to State and local governments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF800E4494174F4BB085778B12C9250A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The next reauthorization date for the program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF68F091501E74CCD9A9F65F36E14117A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A unique identification number which links the program and functional category structure.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98530AA53FA64A65B1DD8759B71025C9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The year in which the program was originally established and, where applicable, the year in which the program expires.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD97907E3FF2448608A214925C941B41B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Where applicable, the year in which new budget authority for the program was last authorized and the year in which current authorizations of new budget authority expire.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FBF0C4CCEEA4829A6DB53A8D3DDB6A0"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Any other information the Commission determines to be necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC66E97A6DBC4883B8C955FE6425142B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Budget authority</header><text>The report also shall set forth for each program whether the new budget authority provided for such program is—</text> <paragraph id="H99C5050D8712493FB3373E69BB9395EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>authorized for a definite period of time;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1140DC2BEA914932ADB9A122C210750B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>authorized in a specific dollar amount but without limit of time;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4D8B4AC5B62419A82BAB4BD7C3876FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>authorized without limit of time or dollar amounts;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB720F6B1672D41D5A30BA676C40B179C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>not specifically authorized; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA56DFE1D02F2450F9D450164D262A6B7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>permanently provided, as determined by the Director of the Congressional Budget Office.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA5B0BB7822EC49B2A136AAAFB2B9FABE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>CBO information</header><text>For each program or group of programs, the program inventory also shall include information prepared by the Director of the Congressional Budget Office indicating each of the following matters:</text> <paragraph id="H3BF7D6A06B8D49AEAA4C2370F064177C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The amounts of new budget authority authorized and provided for the program for each of the preceding four fiscal years and, where applicable, the four succeeding fiscal years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7EC95FC7269B48299F08DBB87BF69DEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The functional and subfunctional category in which the program is presently classified and was classified under the fiscal year 2020 budget.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE27CF1DCD2E4F16B6BF0D6D6595A037"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The identification code and title of the appropriation account in which budget authority is provided for the program.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6ED1555568D7421C9EDFFE632FC5A745"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Mutual exchange of information</header><text>The General Accountability Office, the Congressional Research Service, and the Congressional Budget Office shall permit the mutual exchange of available information in their possession which would aid in the compilation of the program inventory.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5599511CBB364BA2AD5309AD6197CADF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Assistance by executive branch</header><text>The Office of Management and Budget and the agencies (and the subdivisions thereof) shall, to the extent necessary and possible, provide the General Accountability Office with assistance requested by the Comptroller General in the compilation of the program inventory. Such communications shall be treated as confidential until a report is issued under section 4(b).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H45D8539FE7454A7194DB5F38E9708B16"><enum>9.</enum><header>Expedited consideration for schedule for review</header>
<subsection id="H1C1186D2B35E4AEEBAEB0C359F0621EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Introduction and committee consideration</header>
<paragraph id="HE7D779086EE2424FBFF71836329AEF58"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Introduction</header><text>A joint resolution shall be introduced in the Senate by the majority leader, or the majority leader’s designee, and in the House of Representatives, by the Speaker, or the Speaker’s designee not later than 60 days after the date on which the proposed legislation is submitted to Congress. Upon such introduction, the Commission schedule for review bill shall be referred to the appropriate committees of Congress under paragraph (2). If the joint resolution is not introduced in accordance with the preceding sentence, then any member of Congress may introduce such legislation in their respective House of Congress beginning on the date that is the 5th calendar day that such House is in session following the date of the submission of such aggregate legislative language provisions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC160EA212E984C87989E4ACB781EA8C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Committee consideration</header> <subparagraph id="H41C63FC5B7C64212AB3FA96E49BF3017"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Referral</header><text>The joint resolution introduced under paragraph (1) shall be referred to any appropriate committee of jurisdiction in the Senate and the House of Representatives. A committee to which the joint resolution is referred under this paragraph may review and comment on such legislation, may report such legislation to the respective House, and may not amend such legislation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC73B31066FCF420CB71CAF024D37B020"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Not later than 30 calendar days after the introduction of the joint resolution, each Committee of Congress to which the joint resolution was referred shall report the legislation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5F727A70F31F4135A183E9EF3AAB8AAE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Discharge of committee</header><text>If a committee to which a joint resolution is referred has not reported such legislation at the end of 30 calendar days after its introduction or at the end of the first day after there has been reported to the House a joint resolution involved a joint resolution, whichever is earlier, such committee shall be deemed to be discharged from further consideration of such legislation and such legislation shall be placed on the appropriate calendar of the House involved.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6F295FF0B2254E40ACD8CC908A0C358A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expedited procedure</header>
<paragraph id="HCA12A2DA9E1140A6A22BE199E6160002"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consideration</header>
<subparagraph id="HBC34F707C8B04B99B8129C4743336CD8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 calendar days after the date on which a committee has reported a joint resolution or has been discharged from consideration of a joint resolution, the majority leader of the Senate, or the majority leader’s designee, or the Speaker of the House of Representatives, or the Speaker’s designee, shall move to proceed to the consideration of the joint resolution. It shall also be in order for any Member of the Senate or the House of Representatives, respectively, to move to proceed to the consideration of the joint resolution at any time after the conclusion of such 5-day period.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H63CC63F0E8314394AB81B3F81FFC60E9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Motion to proceed</header><text>A motion to proceed to the consideration of a joint resolution is highly privileged in the House of Representatives and is privileged in the Senate and is not debatable. The motion is not subject to amendment or to a motion to postpone consideration of the joint resolution. If the motion to proceed is agreed to, the Senate or the House of Representatives, as the case may be, shall immediately proceed to consideration of the joint resolution without intervening motion, order, or other business, and the joint resolution shall remain the unfinished business of the Senate or the House of Representatives, as the case may be, until disposed of.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE1650D0867C242088CA90FB8CAACDB2C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limited debate</header><text>Debate on the joint resolution and on all debatable motions and appeals in connection therewith shall be limited to not more than 10 hours, which shall be divided equally between those favoring and those opposing the joint resolution. A motion further to limit debate on the joint resolution is in order and is not debatable. All time used for consideration of the joint resolution, including time used for quorum calls (except quorum calls immediately preceding a vote) and voting, shall come from the 10 hours of debate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F0AAA1792C044ECAC5FEF811CCEA026"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Amendments</header><text>No amendment to the joint resolution shall be in order in the Senate and the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H73C01F8F843B4EF3B6D2CC25BB2E3766"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Vote on final passage</header><text>Immediately following the conclusion of the debate on the joint resolution, the vote on final passage of the joint resolution shall occur.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC129072F6990407E8A3DA1A204796DC1"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Other motions not in order</header><text>A motion to postpone consideration of the joint resolution, a motion to proceed to the consideration of other business, or a motion to recommit the review joint resolution is not in order. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the joint resolution is agreed to or not agreed to is not in order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H444D865957F649FB99A931519499843B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration by other house</header><text>If, before the passage by one House of the joint resolution that was introduced in such House, such House receives from the other House a joint resolution as passed by such other House—</text> <subparagraph id="HEBFC21B2F3FA4A7FA5398A6AA8543A3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the joint resolution of the other House shall not be referred to a committee and may only be considered for final passage in the House that receives it under subparagraph (C);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6359783C56064613B1C5A5F92EA9075B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the procedure in the House in receipt of the joint resolution of the other House, shall be the same as if no joint resolution had been received from the other House; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8469D76C68145F7968EE3FEC80DC90B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>notwithstanding subparagraph (B), the vote on final passage shall be on the joint resolution of the other House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H37C661417B284514A312EA6534A58374"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disposition</header><text>Upon disposition of a joint resolution that is received by one House from the other House, it shall no longer be in order to consider the joint resolution that was introduced in the receiving House.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9A4C721F863E4876875073DA91F33C08"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rules of the senate and the house of representatives</header><text>This section is enacted—</text>
<paragraph id="H16A5BC4021B54D33B163348DF440EBAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and the House of Representatives, respectively, and is deemed to be part of the rules of each House, respectively, but applicable only with respect to the procedure to be followed in that House in the case of the joint resolution, and it supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H087FBE28BA53481FB742DE588E849FCD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as they relate to the procedure of that House) at anytime, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HDBEDFD6527674E04AB1A4A4AA779D283"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Fallback provision</header><text>If the Senate and the House of Representatives fail to act within one year from the date of introduction, the joint resolution takes effect.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H67E01642E00048D9AC27AABB8FD2A8A9"><enum>10.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H2626EFB432B044EDAEB50D92DCE08166"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency </term> has the meaning given the term Executive agency in section 105 of title 5, United States Code, except that such term includes an advisory committee.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H230FE4C49B0E49299B42C97F3DB611A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Calendar day</header><text>The term <term>calendar day</term> means a calendar day other than one on which either House is not in session because of an adjournment of more than 3 days to a date certain.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFBB07457C366407D903938C3536DD760"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Agency Sunset Commission established under section 3.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7DE545EA6444D2A8C251EE0D7EB0C0A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Supermajority</header><text>The term <term>super-majority </term> means an affirmative vote of two-thirds of the Members, duly chosen and sworn.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3753529CE49444E7A73A155592754928"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Advisory committee</header><text>The term <term>advisory committee</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1001 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H44D0F5B3A207409787F7E3B8DEFBF789"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Joint resolution</header><text>The term <term>joint resolution</term> means a joint resolution consisting of the proposed legislative language submitted by the Commission under section 4(a)(3) and introduced or reintroduced under section 7(a).</text></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


