<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE8646772C5EE4B2EAEDA84E1D2F0FBF7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2496 IH: Protecting Gold Star Spouses Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2496</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Committee on Appropriations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide interim appropriations for the Coast Guard Retired Serviceman&#8217;s Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plans for each fiscal year after fiscal year 2022, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1759853C72C41C2854B866D2ECF4414" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0C78988FC53F4C60A30449073AB64099" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Gold Star Spouses Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBDA65A8115284990ACC12D77351B2BDE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interim appropriations for the coast guard retired serviceman’s family protection and survivor benefits plans</header> <subsection id="H1869C682A3FA4F54B0E71A82A863E9F4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are hereby appropriated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for each fiscal year after fiscal year 2022, such sums as necessary for payment of the Coast Guard Retired Serviceman’s Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plans, as are described in the provision regarding Coast Guard retired pay in title II of division F of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>), at a rate for operations and under the terms and conditions provided by the most recent law making full-year appropriations for such Coast Guard Retired Serviceman’s Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plans.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDA9242F4E3D04174834C8BCA6CE826F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effect of enactment of subsequent appropriations</header><text>If an appropriation for such Coast Guard Retired Serviceman’s Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plans, or a general appropriation bill providing appropriations for the Coast Guard without provision for such Coast Guard Retired Serviceman’s Family Protection and Survivor Benefits Plans, is enacted into law on any date after the date of the enactment of this Act that provides for appropriations during a fiscal year following the expenditure of funds during such fiscal year pursuant to this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HAFD7B4A82A6B4377BD4453A161A9C673"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such expenditure shall be charged to such appropriation (if any); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE2CA5064A0ED454EB5900EE46A7D1E8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appropriations made available for such fiscal year pursuant to this Act shall not be available after the date of enactment of such appropriation or general appropriation bill.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

