<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9C7B6B84BE1948CD8D74D3B70759D36B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1204 IH: Protect Access to Justice for Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1204</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230227">February 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Sergeant First Class Heath Robinson Honoring our Promise to Address Comprehensive Toxics Act of 2022 to limit attorney fees available under the Federal cause of action relating to water at Camp Lejeune, North Carolina, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H54CD011C4DC44F28808CE62720076DAE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9A50792398364A87A38870E948CDAA32" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Access to Justice for Veterans Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H0A7FF1066BBB430C959315B7792F2F68"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on attorney fees for Federal cause of action relating to water at Camp Lejeune, North Carolina</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 804 of the Sergeant First Class Heath Robinson Honoring our Promise to Address Comprehensive Toxics Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/168">Public Law 117–168</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/2671">28 U.S.C. 2671</external-xref> note prec.) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EC288EDFE11405D853A485669827C1B"> 
<subsection id="H92586AB2A59C4660A963E12D71E48CAC"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Attorney fees</header> 
<paragraph id="H6AA45063ACF24D24BBCAFEBE2B8FD0E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>No legal representative of an individual who brings an action under subsection (b) or who presents a claim under section 2675 of title 28, United States Code, pursuant to subsection (h) shall charge, demand, receive, or collect for services rendered in bringing such action or presenting such claim, fees in excess of—</text> <subparagraph id="H0BC38D3D38454329A8DFF6A8EEC4CD77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>20 percent of an award, compromise, or settlement made or reached within 180 days after presenting a claim under section 2675 of title 28, United States Code, pursuant to subsection (h); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H844E1B77581546EAB40331D9B28B1862"><enum>(B)</enum><text>33.3 percent on a claim that is resolved by settlement, compromise, or judgement after the initiation of an action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H87F04B3FB3A84C51AB1FFCE1991455F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms for payment of fees</header><text>Any judgment rendered, settlement entered, compromise made, or other award made with respect to an action brought under subsection (b) or a claim presented under section 2675 of title 28, United States Code, pursuant to subsection (h) by a legal representative of an individual shall require the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H45AC5920B4364B588C9183D12AFC95D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>All funds from the judgment, settlement, compromise, or other award shall be deposited into an account held in trust for the individual in accordance with all applicable provisions of State law. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H380F07484EA947178B8E1528CB00962C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The legal representative shall—</text> 
<clause id="H294A152CF4B54EFF9A614A9C016E441F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>once any funds described in subparagraph (A) have been deposited into an account pursuant to such subparagraph, notify the individual of such deposit; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBA39988927EF47379DC653AA12816F02"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>promptly deliver to such individual such amount of such funds as the individual is entitled to receive.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1D3567BD03D241E5B1C5A27E7E19C035"><enum>(C)</enum><text>That no funds shall be paid from the account described in subparagraph (A) to a legal representative of the individual as compensation for services rendered to such individual until the relevant funds from such account have been disbursed to the individual in accordance with subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D5C41AC6DDF4D868A00B51F024AE729"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Penalties</header> <subparagraph id="H0C933070445A4D3C8AEBB029C327238F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Fee limitations</header><text>Any legal representative who charges, demands, receives, or collects for services rendered in connection with an action under subsection (b) or a claim under section 2675 of title 28, United States Code, pursuant to subsection (h), any amount in excess of that allowed under paragraph (1) of this subsection, if recovery be had, shall be fined not more than $5,000. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB6FFD5C24CAD4BE397296A9570629C01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Terms for payment</header><text>Failure of a legal representative subject to paragraph (2) to comply with a requirement of such paragraph shall be punishable consistent with the penalties provided in section 2678 of title 28, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0AEABB902583490CBAC6B0B85BD91EBB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to annul, alter, affect, or exempt any person from complying with the laws of any State or locality with respect to the practice of law, except to the extent that those laws are inconsistent with any provision of this subsection, and then only to the extent of the inconsistency. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


