<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H39393CACFBE54693BD0FD10FB47BA734" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 3792 IH: U.S.-Israel Partnership and Abraham Accords Enhancement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3792</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230601">June 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modify and extend certain authorities relating to cooperation between the United States and Israel, expand and strengthen the Abraham Accords, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC5AED332D75445A6BA38A39B86346358" style="OLC"><section id="H019D495F1944457B89DE56D6161CE0BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>U.S.-Israel Partnership and Abraham Accords Enhancement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8812189BC5D14CA5B3D0264BC2A6321F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to—</text><paragraph id="H9066864C5FC444E5A7BC5DEF707124A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support the democratic, Jewish state of Israel’s right to self-defense, including through Foreign Military Financing and security cooperation programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95EF19D2B99C4F7EB096B395170F123B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>seek a successor to the current U.S.-Israel Memorandum of Understanding reflecting the United States’ unshakeable commitment to Israel’s security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H793C75C427C54487955FF473C1AA0247" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage the expansion and strengthening of the Abraham Accords, in accordance with the Israel Relations Normalization Act of 2022 (division Z of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>), to urge other nations to normalize relations with Israel and ensure that existing agreements reap tangible security and economic benefits for the citizens of those countries and all peoples in the region;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF545ACACF054D618503B04D9DA09B5A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support Israel’s full participation as an equally treated member of the community of nations, including by expanding the Abraham Accords and opposing anti-Israel bias at the United Nations and other international fora; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5946F5818CB449459E399C9097553118"><enum>(5)</enum><text>continue to expand the United States-Israel relationship to deepen existing economic and people-to-people ties, including through cooperative programs.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H26877A9DF67A4CAFB6BE5BB5D5E7D690"><enum>3.</enum><header>Extension of War Reserves stockpile authority</header><subsection id="HF649E05DCD2A44C389BDE9FBFCCEA0E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Department of Defense Appropriations Act, 2005</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 12001(d) of the Department of Defense Appropriations Act, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/287">Public Law 108–287</external-xref>; 118 Stat. 1011) is amended by striking <quote>after September 30, 2025</quote> and inserting <quote>after September 30, 2028</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD2DA11833CE34F3EB2AD248FB6CE24A7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Foreign Assistance Act of 1961</header><text>Section 514(b)(2)(A) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2321h">22 U.S.C. 2321h(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>or 2025</quote> and inserting <quote>, 2025, 2026, 2027, or 2028</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4CBE732CEF394E64B0B54FEA938EFD60"><enum>4.</enum><header>Extension of authority to finance cooperative projects among the United States, Israel, and certain developing countries</header><subsection id="H3704ED0B6AF44B4389F7A958891F5137"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 106(e) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151d">22 U.S.C. 2151d(e)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>through 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>through 2026</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDE4464E875CD46FEA9EDA600BD994321"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State and Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on cooperative projects financed under section 106(e) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended by subsection (a). </text></subsection></section><section id="H3114B689E4EA4FDC8856697FC21CA9D4"><enum>5.</enum><header>United States-Israel energy cooperation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 917 of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/17337">42 U.S.C. 17337</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HCC29B93207794190A8E1A68A35641CF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(6), by inserting <quote>United States and</quote> before <quote>Israeli</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69DB9C33F2754DE1B331D6934C3F9C8D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="HB1B17495C7C84187ABCF7E282A943687"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H5578E19AD5974614BBFF3EB2E12BADC5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HF2A3CEAB581E45D6BB0CDA14FFDAF91E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></clause><clause id="HEE07AE0812664CB9B34CDA2641249A51"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9C743A43B7954100AAFAE6F733C9BAA4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H4E0AB3C0AB3142BEA4B2FA203C894EEE"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advanced nuclear technologies, to include nuclear fusion; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B3C475735574A5AAA8D7C01F16FFBE3"><enum>(K)</enum><text>carbon capture, utilization, and storage.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EBDFAC5A251478FA6E737CD2CD13CB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H92051EE931C4442BAC15358973A9D96F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H74DB19F67C2E424F88AF11DD69387EC4"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Cost-sharing; reimbursement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, to the maximum extent practicable, require a recipient of a grant provided under this subsection to share the costs of feasibility studies and other planning services with respect to a project for which the grant is provided.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H663CE38A827D42E6BC0F31C6D07B3A01"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Prohibitions relating to sanctions</header><text>The Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H134A210E4B4D4B6CB2AF6D7B5F1E9E3C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is prohibited from all dealings related to any grant under this Act that is prohibited under United States sanctions laws or regulations including dealings with persons on the list of specially designated persons and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury, except to the extent otherwise authorized by the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary of State; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE94151696A4D482AA5D9F8C10008CA4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not provide a grant under this subsection to any applicant that is receiving support under this section unless such applicant certifies that the applicant, and any entity owned or controlled by the applicant, is in compliance with all United States sanctions laws and regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D9E75D2B3394C41B28F4D90C23F8B9D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (e) as subsection (g);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE0D2C28BC3345D68F7E9D7A408D64F9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (d) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBB0A83301ED54D349590ACD2EF234D2D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HA5ED47FEE11E4F2EA406359E1D90DA54" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Research security</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (enacted as division B of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>)).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6BACDC8A9AFA4C94B4DE29EC3B101CD0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the congressional committees specified in subsection (c)(3) an annual report that describes the activities undertaken pursuant to subsections (b) and (d) during the preceding year.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FE002CA4F4F44E4B1CEBA3A9ED35217"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (g), as redesignated by paragraph (3), by striking <quote>September 30, 2024</quote> and inserting <quote>September 30, 2029</quote>. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HB8BC6606A0B6443CA30C87F9A7DA37D3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on regional security cooperation</header><subsection id="HE2B433BC27D544C08310F1AE6CB8F6AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for 7 years, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on bilateral and multinational cooperation on regional security between Israel and other countries in the Middle East and North Africa region, including with respect to arms transfers, joint technology development, military drills, and information sharing.</text></subsection><subsection id="H03C00D1BA40B4C7CB354AF463D46312D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The determination required by subsection (a) shall be provided in an unclassified form but may contain a classified annex provided separately.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF66F8C8C66FB47C6A419A2F572CD2BAD"><enum>7.</enum><header>Middle East Partnership Initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State should consider as part of the Middle East Partnership Initiative programming to expand people-to-people ties between Israel and other countries in the Middle East and North Africa region so as to further the goal of expanding and deepening the Abraham Accords.</text></section><section id="HD0EB4D03748843D9A9F74B632D42D14C"><enum>8.</enum><header>Middle East regional cooperation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall ensure that applicants from countries participating in the Abraham Accords are eligible for assistance under the Middle East Regional Cooperation competitive grant program managed by such Agency.</text></section><section id="H2D00D6651582436AB36979D07746805E"><enum>9.</enum><header>International Visitor Leadership Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State should consider as part of the International Visitor Leadership Program programming to expand people-to-people ties between current and emerging leaders in Israel and Muslim-majority countries so as to further the goal of expanding and deepening the Abraham Accords.</text></section><section id="HF3507673C2AD4317AC1CFF72B0B15FD2"><enum>10.</enum><header>Politically-motivated investigations by the International Criminal Court</header><subsection id="HE43B44DEEC374D94A3C22F64DC9F66F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB0EAFA72A4F347F181AA22C49E337990"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Neither Israel nor the United States is a state party to the International Criminal Court (ICC). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H857DA27D0D6F4B168B0DD5D9BC2DB151"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The ICC has pursued investigations against both the United States and Israel despite not having legitimate jurisdiction in such cases. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H25EEA513701A4ADDA27317762B257EAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for 7 years, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on United States diplomatic efforts to oppose politically-motivated investigations against the United States and Israel at the ICC.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD905977654544F80A53708BFDC89A4D6"><enum>11.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on the African Union</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that reinstating Israel’s observer status at the African Union would be of benefit to both Israel and African countries.</text></section><section id="H77C6A1B93E6A41E8B34C6017C35E8640" commented="no"><enum>12.</enum><header>Report on United States Government tools to support the I2U2 Group</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report regarding appropriate tools that the Department of State, the United States Agency for International Development, and the United States International Development Finance Corporation can utilize to support India’s participation in the grouping of India, Israel, the United Arab Emirates, and the United States (commonly referred to as the <quote>I2U2 Group</quote>). </text></section><section id="H16B585C3D13E4BD6A40DA3F4EDD28AFF" commented="no"><enum>13.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on international religious freedom</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H6113300712244AE5B63465F0551A08CE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>fostering support for the Abraham Accords and the normalization of diplomatic relations with Israel among the general public in Arab and Muslim-majority countries is in the interest of the United States; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6EDFC0F60CF435DB415D87C5647E271" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>additional opportunities for interfaith dialogue may help increase support for normalization of diplomatic relations with Israel; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9A29A845A064E48B599C68894AD3BAE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promoting cultural and societal understanding of international religious freedom in Arab and Muslim-majority countries with the goal of increasing public acceptance of the Abraham Accords is consistent with the statutory duties and responsibilities of the Ambassador at Large for International Religious Freedom and the Office on International Religious Freedom established by section 101 of the International Religious Freedom Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/6411">22 U.S.C. 6411</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H58D1DBBCC2084BE5BF7D7C4D64980878" commented="no"><enum>14.</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H60E5A15B46A14BE99B1AC972BD9FDD16"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H143507E2F319446483A46E996D6822C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

