<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDDE1A26E68894F53B66B414D72411FD2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6034 IH: Safer Homes and Families Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6034</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231024">October 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committees on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To criminalize stalking using an unauthorized geotracking device, modify the 10-year marriage rule relating to spouse’s and surviving spouse’s insurance benefits in cases of domestic violence, ensure that healthcare providers can assist survivors of domestic violence, provide additional housing protections for survivors of domestic violence, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1290B2D5BD344276B94A801DF4082D8B" style="OLC"><section id="H241853FD86594F04A6C94F8A645B7201" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safer Homes and Families Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4258738DB0BB46A8B80821DD0D3E1D48"><enum>2.</enum><header>Stalking penalty</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2261A of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE53A22608D214131B3646A6A64ABE18D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Whoever</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">In general.—</header-in-text>Whoever</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1953A9169C744920B34B105A6D234D59"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after <quote>uses the mail,</quote> the following: <quote>uses an unauthorized geotracking device</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54E2EC6CC14E44AEACC35416434C31FD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H1E1807A1BDB24809AF40D331C3F50C03" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H0ABC5A91E2C34C41B4DD36B6CBB15D37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HED9813B0BB9B4774992FB87711C40996"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>geotracking device</quote> means an electronic or mechanical device that permits a person to remotely determine or track the position and movement of another person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63D90614CB0D4990A9ADD69A87C14EB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>unauthorized</quote> means, with respect to a geotracking device, that the person on whom the geotracking device is being used has not consented to such use or otherwise revoked consent to such use.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H70EB293186FA499C95A8B20AFB10FA09"><enum>3.</enum><header>Modification of 10-year marriage rule in cases of domestic violence</header><subsection id="HB1EE10994C154F009820CDB109E60BC9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 216(d) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/416">42 U.S.C. 416(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3CDFEB84453B4AE5A184D3BCDE69889A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HAF378D02915C4DBEAA2E81C15C027DBA"><enum>(9)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H13D740A911814ECF9322CF9D5F02A4E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a divorced woman described in paragraph (1) or (2) or a divorced man described in paragraph (4) or (5) who provides to the Commissioner of Social Security a finding made by a court of law that the divorced woman or divorced man was the victim of domestic violence committed by the spouse during the course of the marriage, such paragraph as may be applicable with respect to such divorced woman or divorced man shall be applied for purposes of this title by substituting <quote>5 years</quote> for <quote>10 years</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73925E84DD3A4858B9F9199E555EA244" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <quote>domestic violence</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDF7840B7691A4D828E450F35DD765B22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination of wife’s insurance benefits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/402">42 U.S.C. 402(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4D4B780CC4564E9297CFA37402FD6C3C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HFF0A9397D6D44F66A0AE9F4740F10D25" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any divorced wife who provides to the Commissioner of Social Security a finding made by a court of law that the divorced wife was the victim of domestic violence (as defined in section 216(d)(9)(B)) committed by the spouse during the course of the marriage, clause (ii) of paragraph (1)(G) shall be applied by substituting <quote>5 years</quote> for <quote>10 years</quote>. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCD41F00E20EC4A4289D1253AC5F0735D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination of husband’s insurance benefits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202(c) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/402">42 U.S.C. 402(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H77DE56727C2F472387EB42BD1E9D1991" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H5DE030331BE84A7485EB225C72048EE3" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any divorced husband who provides to the Commissioner of Social Security a finding made by a court of law that the divorced husband was the victim of domestic violence (as defined in section 216(d)(9)(B)) committed by the spouse, clause (ii) of paragraph (1)(G) shall be applied by substituting <quote>5 years</quote> for <quote>10 years</quote>.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCCA5D6E3787C4196B2FEF744F5303A41"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to monthly insurance benefits for months beginning at least 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H87D72A2750B64893A8A7DB6F42AF67B2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Demonstration program on trauma-informed, victim-centered training for healthcare providers</header><subsection id="HF69C48A371AA428591754F79A61D424D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle Q of title IV of the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12513">34 U.S.C. 12513 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBF575149EB56483782B81DF0FC46334B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5830D22F2DD14CDFBC2A29D49F492FF0"><enum>41702.</enum><header>Demonstration program on trauma-informed, victim-centered training for healthcare providers</header><subsection id="H7362CA4F7DEC4A86A8E9B9665DDCCB85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text><paragraph id="H8C8870B07AE14B3D808FD0C11BD74A2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Attorney General</term> means the Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Office on Violence Against Women;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB23617C6BEC94D97A8F3814CE7482EF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E880AFB1E404890B97DE94898067DF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual who interfaces with victims of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking, including—</text><subparagraph id="H5872A4AEAEFC4944A913D2FF6A19742E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual working for or on behalf of an eligible entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA849BD440C0A49FC824F8717C3AB88D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an administrator or personnel of a school, university, or other educational program or activity (including a campus police officer or a school resource officer); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12171A5CA4474A5895E3992AF970D9DE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an emergency services employee;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49A130D8BF154114A83F6816BA78D608"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a facility as described in paragraph (1), (2), (4), (5), or (6) of section 1624 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300s-3">42 U.S.C. 300s–3</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AE31116829145C083DACF229EA89324"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>mandatory partner</term> means a national, regional, or local victim services organization or agency working in collaboration with a facility described in paragraph (4). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEA6DB9032FCC46729C7E918592F33AE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><paragraph id="H2D132BCBB070431C8443A7028C0C01A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to collaborate with their mandatory partners to carry out the demonstration program under this section by implementing evidence-based or promising investigative policies and practices to incorporate trauma-informed, victim-centered techniques designed to—</text><subparagraph id="H6169923AAADC4D2F8838B23D1828111C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevent re-traumatization of the victim;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D2A783560CD415B98ED5E1590D76CD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that covered individuals use evidence-based practices to identify, respond to, and treat cases of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FE56F395E7A4A88A0AB069D3E5198D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increase collaboration among stakeholders who are part of the coordinated community response to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47F81C590FC442BC82CBA385867F60FA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evaluate the effectiveness of the training process and content.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H258FEA8EAACF4F239A2B88C51F642121"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Award basis</header><text>The Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall award grants under this section to multiple eligible entities for use in a variety of settings and communities, including—</text><subparagraph id="HB1B432BC4A3F4430920E818F0623B2FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>urban, suburban, Tribal, remote, and rural areas;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97DEB8464CF0464BA02342E8D373A5C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>college campuses; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12514F5A6D684E89B5DE93D9C15F43DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>traditionally underserved communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5A8B8A4EFE44EA78986EA221EABAF2D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant to—</text><paragraph id="H51A569BEE71E4C429C3C2721F9E1133B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>train covered individuals associated with the eligible entity to use evidence-based, trauma-informed, and victim-centered techniques to identify and treat individuals who have experienced domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, or stalking, including by—</text><subparagraph id="H0D771A3B34D04C08A01EAC0151BDB0FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>customizing treatment approaches to ensure a culturally and linguistically appropriate approach to the community being served;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A740DD61019447EBAE2D3CAAEA3D630"><enum>(B)</enum><text>becoming proficient in understanding and responding to complex cases, including cases of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, or stalking—</text><clause id="H6E6CA85DB99C4C29B850B9CF1A2EB05E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>facilitated by alcohol or drugs;</text></clause><clause id="H7CD16BD9850347448DFBCD868ED6B9D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>involving strangulation;</text></clause><clause id="HAC381FF9D5574859B573BFFBA9AAC207"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>committed by a non-stranger;</text></clause><clause id="H7B1110BECEFD46559D384E777C184991"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>committed by an individual of the same sex as the victim;</text></clause><clause id="HBFEA413576664499BD7DAFA72E3A1F56"><enum>(v)</enum><text>involving a victim with a disability;</text></clause><clause id="HE8A89CC2493E4B29B3880198734E3237"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>involving a male victim; or</text></clause><clause id="HCB9B465A1A534EAEA17265AE1E2BA8DD"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>involving a lesbian, gay, bisexual, or transgender (commonly referred to as <quote>LGBT</quote>) victim;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF92F7C3D6E24A9AABC23132D5041AFC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developing collaborative relationships between—</text><clause id="H5C5EFF4C49544800B6D7F0202F039F86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>healthcare providers, law enforcement officers, and other members of the response team; and</text></clause><clause id="H8C5C9425C6734C7390FD07C97BC8F63F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the community being served; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64DD29FDBD864559A99E7D15E18ACA38"><enum>(D)</enum><text>developing an understanding of how to define, identify, and correctly classify a report of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, or stalking; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70AE6B9790AE4E9BAB0B8628E75B9453"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote the efforts of the eligible entity to improve the response of covered individuals to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking through various communication channels, such as the website of the eligible entity, social media, print materials, and community meetings, in order to ensure that all covered individuals associated with the eligible entity are aware of those efforts and included in trainings, to the extent practicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10FBFBE485BF4A729775888E125DFA19"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Demonstration program trainings on trauma-Informed, victim-Centered approaches</header><paragraph id="HE36FDB59E11B4163941311D5E1260571"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall identify trainings for covered individuals, in existence as of the date on which the Attorney General begins to solicit applications for grants under this section, that—</text><subparagraph id="HA09BF3095DBC4396B79CA93673693BD1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employ a trauma-informed, victim-centered approach to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4401703B6EFA442ABC8D94E349812054"><enum>(B)</enum><text>focus on the fundamentals of—</text><clause id="HF3CE9FB1864A455CB14AE7452050E785"><enum>(i)</enum><text>trauma responses;</text></clause><clause id="HAADD611E2DA44DF79C0C95E674D4AD8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the impact of trauma on victims of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking; and</text></clause><clause id="HD835CCD9649C4338AFCAA8C60761A508"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>techniques for effectively treating the medical consequences of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D0623905D734196AC5FE00ED2A7CFA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall select one or more of the approaches employed by a training identified under paragraph (1) to test at the eligible entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4227E85CC99645499B63232856DB549A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><paragraph id="H97B9E71169044FD399FA4171F00AC4E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General and the Secretary, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Justice, shall require each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section to identify a research partner, preferably a local research partner, to—</text><subparagraph id="H9A0877FDC6D84297B7E1F5711207C06F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>design a system for generating and collecting the appropriate data to facilitate an independent process or impact evaluation of the use of the grant funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABA99AEFAE294353B16D98EB5E97DE23"><enum>(B)</enum><text>periodically conduct an evaluation described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB662C0FD7BA842B899B19A1DE0244850"><enum>(C)</enum><text>periodically make publicly available, during the grant period—</text><clause id="H7D7D0A9CC7D44C84896DADA55EF232CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>preliminary results of the evaluations conducted under subparagraph (B); and</text></clause><clause id="H84290F24507044BFAEB8BD12014AA8D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>recommendations for improving the use of the grant funds.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CF8F1FB9B924A58AB75CC4DD11D3B17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GAO Report</header><text>Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this section, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committees on Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Judiciary and on Finance of the Senate a report summarizing the implementation of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79EE515883AF4B559EE05A4E4946C28B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Attorney General $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H16DE7EDA011E4053A0FA017BB0E2D781"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after the item related to section 41701 the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAE1CD0C08A7448478051E472EE136E6C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">41702. Demonstration program on trauma-informed, victim-centered training for healthcare providers. </toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H08B4E911199E49858AA0CA4F76133FFC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibition on the imposition of fees for early lease termination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41411 of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12491">34 U.S.C. 12491</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE590D6EB2A974A3EA3D09412FFBBE320" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HD6B4BA3183B74F65BEDC70D901B48EB7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Prohibition on the imposition of fees for early lease termination</header><paragraph id="HA8C2E3C6E23F41C381622BC1460C4519"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voluntary exit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An applicant for or tenant of housing assisted under a covered housing program may voluntarily exit a lease for housing earlier than the end date of such lease on the basis that the applicant or tenant has been a victim of domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, or stalking. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2DA1BD97DF740D1BF59ACE26E1F5123"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fee prohibition</header><text>Notwithstanding any lease agreement, an applicant or tenant described in paragraph (1) may not be charged a fee for exiting a lease for housing earlier than the end date of such lease on the basis described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

