<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC3A866D0DFD54C2F87BDEB0005010542" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 580 IH: American Innovation and Manufacturing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 580</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a small business and domestic production recovery investment facility, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H268217697C7543248520AF24F02D2317" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBB504174EB934F558206AD7CA6E47BE0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Innovation and Manufacturing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H33D76FA524EF475E9EDBA7E835C1E557"><enum>2.</enum><header>Small business investment company program</header> <subsection id="H355B567CF24A4454B9864E18CD8F0A44"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part A of title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6F6CB02A26EC4BA1930FD82996CD441C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 302(a)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/682">15 U.S.C. 682(a)(1)</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H6AB26A2B750444DF9A0323D2333A22F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE98C1198DAB4FE5AC59E32F30804165"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H701E915D9DA84E50A998744E5A85D65F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB330E24463634CCEB93F801BD0FE5213"> 
<subparagraph id="HD787CA4DA5E743C9817E099374351C5C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$20,000,000, adjusted every 5 years for inflation, with respect to each licensee authorized or seeking authority to sell bonds to Administration as a participating investment company under section 321.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD230CE06C23B4122A1BC40EC38173525"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAAECBEF43B1C4A7E9941D7F244690C9A"> 
<section id="H20E5DD9976D04FFBBA1C0243BCBA987F"><enum>321.</enum><header>Small business and domestic production recovery investment facility</header> 
<subsection id="H8D4285440E6C4530B2793475535140B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H050459A561C14408957F6C85D91DED56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible small business concern</header><text>The term <term>eligible small business concern</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA7AC20C8D9294B69AF2BE692962C8CB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a small business concern that is a manufacturing business that is assigned a North American Industry Classification System code beginning with 31, 32, or 33 at the time at which the small business concern receives an investment from a participating investment company under the facility; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEF0ECFB75B79440488ED3438529198B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an entity described in section 7(a)(37)(A)(iv)(III) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/636">15 U.S.C. 636(a)(37)(A)(iv)(III)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H417CFD786D834131B40C0BA1659C6393"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Facility</header><text>The term <term>facility</term> means the facility established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H15931F53D1504AE78F32E21AF3B46F34"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fund</header><text>The term <term>Fund</term> means the fund established under subsection (h). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB26F4B752428411790CE2DB0EE80AA75"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Participating investment company</header><text>The term <term>participating investment company</term> means a small business investment company approved under subsection (d) to participate in the facility.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A18748717794E9C97C7F52A2F4ABB27"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Protégé investment company</header><text>The term <term>protégé investment company</term> means a small business investment company that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB2767BFA30E14946976EB9789DE8BC50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is majority managed by new, inexperienced, or otherwise underrepresented fund managers; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6133F1FD22554EECAF9A0485A836A355"><enum>(B)</enum><text>elects and is selected by the Administration to participate in the pathway-protégé program under subsection (g).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF3B0E5EC0C34482A82D381CB72BF6C47"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text>The term <term>small business concern</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC132C876B9F5481B844B5D83A4747599"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="H2F153170823341ECA7E3332B8C27B81E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Facility</header><text>The Administrator shall establish and carry out a facility to increase resiliency in the manufacturing supply chain of eligible small business concerns by providing financial assistance to participating investment companies that facilitate equity financings to eligible small business concerns in accordance with this section. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF0B17114D34B4EE78FDB8A5B6D5D47CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administration of facility</header><text>The facility shall be administered by the Administrator acting through the Associate Administrator described in section 201.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA53D0F15330342948C26AE4B353AAB59"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header> <paragraph id="H8AF30A937B3F4D20A4F5B969DC75FC87"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any small business investment company may submit to the Administrator an application to participate in the facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7BA416FFE74744858D33537CC9C1A2AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for application</header><text>An application to participate in the facility shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HA97FC0121EA04466BD89D61F185D918E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A business plan describing how the applicant intends to make successful equity investments in eligible small business concerns. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA3B8BBA43464FE2875B29FB8CF4EA45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information regarding the relevant investment qualifications and backgrounds of the individuals responsible for the management of the applicant.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6A29BF4A10D94BDC855579FB79226B46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the extent to which the applicant meets the selection criteria under subsection (d)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE25BE165AC349F79462264A9D0759FD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exceptions to application for new licensees</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall reduce requirements for applicants applying to operate as a participating investment company under this section in order to encourage the participation of new small business investment companies in the facility under this section, which may include the requirements established under part 107 of title 13, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation, relating to—</text> <subparagraph id="H6076BF03D3D44740934160DAA6D228F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the approval of initial management expenses;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC1A014CA612F41F6B83558E942CC40A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the management ownership diversity requirement;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC9497AC4F8C343869768193660E8D2CF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the disclosure of general compensatory practices and fee structures; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H54B8AEAF268041DC91CF47BD069577FD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other requirement that the Administrator determines to be an obstacle to achieving the purposes described in this paragraph. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8237965A427C4315B639F6D59348DEFD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of participating investment companies</header> <paragraph id="HBC338BFE92BE40C5A2472FC8FE04DDE6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination</header> <subparagraph id="H5C30BA0CA2454206853EE65065255C1B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (3), not later than 60 days after the date on which the Administrator receives an application under subsection (c), the Administrator shall— </text> 
<clause id="HB0DC8963CD2146509D8F74EA7534641C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>make a final determination to approve or disapprove such applicant to participate in the facility; and </text></clause> <clause id="H3149161B6C4243B389390DB1259A67BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>transmit the determination to the applicant in writing.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5A2E2621BE634A5DA972EF60563D2D5C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Commitment amount</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (3), at the time of approval of an applicant, the Administrator shall make a determination of the amount of the commitment that may be awarded to the applicant under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H028125D8C37F4B9FB4E680E3F19DC574"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>In making a determination under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall consider—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0437973E67B44D1D8CAB96D164EBABD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the probability that the investment strategy of the applicant will successfully repay any financial assistance provided by the Administration, including the probability of a return significantly in excess thereof;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA44DE7018C974EF49E1F18EED6E9491F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the probability that the investments made by the applicant will—</text> 
<clause id="H4B22A7AE3962467D9540BBCAB4AB2E2D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide capital to eligible small business concerns; or</text></clause> <clause id="HA7AA6EBD29E647E082F434E3D3947DB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>create or preserve jobs in the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H83667F89B09849EBA121DFB92620C3E9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the probability that the applicant will meet the objectives in the business plan of the applicant, including the financial goals, and, if applicable, the pathway-protégé program in accordance with subsection (g); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDE7BD018CF0D43B78146F5BD84708126"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the probability that the applicant will assist eligible small business concerns in achieving profitability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5B8257DA0DBA451BBDE02BFC5A9E53B2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Approval of participating investment companies</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD6208528F78E4EACA2838BBD1455C47F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Provisional approval</header> 
<clause id="HB8CB13B8B6AE49D09A8AFC066773D4FB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), with respect to an application submitted by an applicant to operate as a participating investment company under this section, the Administrator may provide provisional approval for the applicant in lieu of a final determination of approval and determination of the amount of the commitment under that paragraph.</text></clause> <clause id="H1D321087A31140ADB41B711F47BA8356"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of a provisional approval under clause (i) is to—</text> 
<subclause id="H47DD9E57D6B845E5877B8789C6AA44D1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>encourage applications from investment companies with an investment mandate from the committed private market capital of the investment company that does not conform to the requirements described in this section at the time of application;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF8DD90BF115244FB8652D0D578829ACD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>allow the applicant to more effectively raise capital commitments in the private markets by referencing the intent of the Administrator to award the applicant a commitment; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCD0E6C67C6F3447CBCC4943290C8F5BB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>allow the applicant to more precisely request the desired amount of commitment pending the securing of capital from private market investors.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H9B9105848B934CC8ABFC2111D143EEDF"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Limit on period of the time</header><text>The period between a provisional approval under clause (i) and the final determination of approval under paragraph (1) shall not exceed 12 months.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0D4B25CBA3374CF6B973228CC6490720"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Commitments and SBIC bonds</header> 
<paragraph id="H82DAECE14C0D46C9B8CC73D59B939DD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may, out of amounts available in the Fund, purchase or commit to purchase from a participating investment company 1 or more accruing bonds that include equity features as described in this subsection. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B8B7064BDEF46B9884F8D7A6F2ADD2B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bond terms</header><text>A bond purchased by the Administrator from a participating investment company under this subsection shall have the following terms and conditions:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7F08E2F5E717497396B83C0D3811AAC0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Term and interest</header> 
<clause id="HA9FAFDB895C3429D8344442D2064B92A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The bond shall be issued for a term of not less than 15 years and shall bear interest at a rate determined by the Administrator of not more than 2 percent. </text></clause> <clause id="HC5F4327CAE6A46469BC05AD02A84D39B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Accrual of interest</header><text>Interest on the bond shall accrue and shall be payable in accordance with subparagraph (D).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H107DABB3D58D4B3A8E34FA5123D12233"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Prepayment</header><text>The bond shall be prepayable without penalty after the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date on which the bond was purchased.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD7F101CAD82949878583A8F307B3D352"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Profits</header> <clause id="H6CA3032AE13B455CBF667B744211284B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administration shall be entitled to receive a share of the profits net of any profit sharing performance compensation of the participating investment company equal to the quotient obtained by dividing—</text> 
<subclause id="HEDAE8B6AC67244FA813FCCAAF717C9D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>one-third of the commitment that the participating investment company is approved for under subsection (d); by </text></subclause> <subclause id="HF86ACDCC877D4411943FB0A990A3D91C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the commitment approved under subsection (d) plus the regulatory capital of the participating investment company at the time of approval under that subsection. </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H394EB7CF4E07490C87D6A8C1EC60B087"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determination of percentage</header><text>The share to which the Administration is entitled under clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="H4036185A427C42EC9E03EA11629CF07A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall be determined at the time of approval under subsection (d); and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2A21A3B07FF6493C87D344BDF9EE0512"><enum>(II)</enum><text>without the approval of the Administration, shall not be revised, including to reflect subsequent distributions of profits, returns of capital, or repayments of bonds, or otherwise.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE26FB7B2E65D4582B632A98A1AC1AABF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Profit sharing performance compensation</header> <clause id="H46EE07A02DA3463881F468107D182C79"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Receipt by Administration</header><text>The Administration shall receive a share of profits of not more than 2 percent, which shall be deposited into the Fund and be available to make commitments under this subsection.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H369A00150F29447F9571A9F55E1000CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Receipt by managers</header><text>The managers of the participating investment company may receive a maximum profit sharing performance compensation of 25 percent minus the share of profits paid to the Administration under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85C63DA36E064FF1839ADFB815473D88"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Prohibition on distributions</header><text>No distributions on capital, including profit distributions, shall be made by the participating investment company to the investors or managers of the participating investment company until the Administration has received payment of all accrued interest on the bond committed under this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAE61E5DD963742BC990F7750F29D3ED0"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Repayment of principal</header><text>Except as described in subparagraph (F), repayments of principal of the bond of a participating investment company shall be—</text> <clause id="H8EBEE7DACFD4445FA952768877D52EE3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>made at the same time as returns of private capital; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H7BD7ADB73BFC41B18EB4C8F6D3569C91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in amounts equal to the pro rata share of the Administration of the total amount being repaid or returned at such time.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF7DE99C4AD6648B9AA9D347A769F3A3B"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Liquidation or default</header><text>Upon any liquidation event or default, as defined by the Administration, any unpaid principal or accrued interest on the bond shall—</text> 
<clause id="HA27A2CDF63D64FC48C2E5C68960FE745"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have a priority over all equity of the participating investment company; and</text></clause> <clause id="H9F10BD5970364717BAD6084BCC069371"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be paid before any return of equity or any other distributions to the investors or managers of the participating investment company.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49370F832E7E443D85AF231857FD9663"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amount of commitments and purchases</header> 
<subparagraph id="H8E25A54810664C27AAC913A8BBED4337"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The maximum amount of outstanding bonds and commitments to purchase bonds for any participating investment company under the facility shall be the lesser of—</text> <clause id="H7E6D8A5449A940969426742822B2AE18"><enum>(i)</enum><text>twice the amount of the regulatory capital of the participating investment company; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD6D5DB209751456F90066EA7E2D36CB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$200,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA722DED7C8C4C9F9C38DE704881EBBB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Commitment process</header><text>Commitments by the Administration to purchase bonds under the facility shall remain available to be sold by a participating investment company until the end of the fourth fiscal year following the year in which the commitment is made, subject to review and approval by the Administration based on regulatory compliance, financial status, change in management, deviation from business plan, and such other limitations as may be determined by the Administration by regulation or otherwise.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD4C8AD50CDFE496EBF4948FE6A8882FB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Commitment conditions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5C008A1851D34A69B1EB12A27C0E2093"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As a condition of receiving a commitment under the facility, not less than 50 percent of amounts invested by the participating investment company shall be invested in eligible small business concerns.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7DF06070B7964D26BC8FCCBF31AED775"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Examinations</header><text>In addition to the matters set forth in section 310(c), the Administration shall examine each participating investment company in such detail so as to determine whether the participating investment company has complied with the requirements under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE2FC2D0F9B934B25A840CC80ABD0307B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Distributions and fees</header> 
<paragraph id="H6055D18507DD4327828A534358E89334"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Distribution requirements</header> 
<subparagraph id="H279086F6B90B45C6946FBD28FD036557"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Distributions</header><text>As a condition of receiving a commitment under the facility, a participating investment company shall make all distributions to the Administrator in the same form and in a manner as are made to investors, or otherwise at a time and in a manner consistent with regulations or policies of the Administration. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3758F073490A41B89A3B4A8A22A93E64"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Allocations</header><text>A participating investment company shall make allocations of income, gain, loss, deduction, and credit to the Administrator with respect to any outstanding bonds as if the Administrator were an investor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF8F4099262C49BBB2449BF7A4837CD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fees</header><text>The Administrator may not charge fees for participating investment companies other than examination fees that are consistent with the license of the participating investment company.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1AF128229FFE4E27972A1BAA14EDFFED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Bifurcation</header><text>Losses on bonds issued by participating investment companies shall not be offset by fees or any other charges on debenture small business investment companies.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H81FF56BA06FF478C8497CFBAFCF97F80"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Protégé program</header><text>The Administrator shall establish a pathway-protégé program in which a protégé investment company may receive technical assistance and program support from a participating investment company on a voluntary basis and without penalty for non-participation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE605FE2755F54FBC8B27ACBB55DE9DBC"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Loss limiting fund</header> <paragraph id="HF28179AF3BB4476C81D87C5CA6DF002F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established in the Treasury a fund for making commitments and purchasing bonds with equity features under the facility and receiving capital returned by participating investment companies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D76C77B87AC458AAECBB189C13FBE92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Amounts appropriated to the Fund or deposited in the Fund under paragraph (3) shall be available to the Administrator, without further appropriation, for making commitments and purchasing bonds under the facility and expenses and payments, excluding administrative expenses, relating to the operations of the Administrator under the facility.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBC37CBCDA8844C8FBE7388E3349A96E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Depositing of amounts</header> <subparagraph id="HAE5B28D0D15248D780972C1C3938F571"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All amounts received by the Administrator from a participating investment company relating to the facility, including any moneys, property, or assets derived by the Administrator from operations in connection with the facility, shall be deposited in the Fund.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA9096274109846B7A94498E78E64C7E9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Period of availability</header><text>Amounts deposited under subparagraph (A) shall remain available until expended.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6C2711D243BF4BCB996162A9FA5C6A5D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Application of other sections</header><text>To the extent not inconsistent with requirements under this section, the Administrator may apply sections 309, 311, 312, 313, and 314 to activities under this section and an officer, director, employee, agent, or other participant in a participating investment company shall be subject to the requirements under such sections.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA966894A4C6E4008A5EA11A73A5ACC37"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for the first fiscal year beginning after the date of enactment of this part $10,000,000,000 to carry out the facility. Amounts appropriated pursuant to this subsection shall remain available until the end of the second fiscal year beginning after the date of enactment of this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8354D5BDA01B47349532E2FF695EA5F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approval of bank-Owned, non-Leveraged applicants</header><text>Section 301(c)(2) of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD0A59D61DD09439ABE93359E0CBB8D16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>Within</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in subparagraph (C), within</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H506BAE41FF484FEE9DC59134184739C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H611311BCEBA24C1A964D5150F34AC484"> 
<subparagraph id="HD8F143593CE446D88567AD36140130B8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception for bank-owned, non-leveraged applicants</header><text>Notwithstanding subparagraph (B), not later than 45 days after the date on which the Administrator receives a completed application submitted by a bank-owned, non-leveraged applicant in accordance with this subsection and in accordance with such requirements as the Administrator may prescribe by regulation, the Administrator shall—</text> <clause id="HF2C90B5AB8F74A55857B0E5B5EEFAD8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>review the application in its entirety; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H374064CEE3AF46CDB175F25252A663DD"><enum>(ii)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE95DD870F23C4B71B1DEEF8D794CDA28"><enum>(I)</enum><text>approve the application and issue a license for such operation to the applicant if the requirements of this section are satisfied; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0C8DA7860FFA4755AC78DD457C311F5A" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>disapprove the application and notify the applicant in writing of the disapproval.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDDB75FFF24084DDA9A508466A4037CCF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Electronic submissions</header><text>Part A of title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a) of this section, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06AD49BF49304AB79D2F9B65DD3DBC0E"> <section id="HE3FEBBBF4C9345F7B694C8A16E722414"><enum>322.</enum><header>Electronic submissions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administration shall permit any document submitted under this title, or pursuant to a regulation carrying out this title, to be submitted electronically, including by permitting an electronic signature for any signature that is required on such a document.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

