<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF439418B0A5E4A6BB3B600019A4D626A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2700 IH: Employee Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2700</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230419">April 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001093">Mrs. Houchin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001108">Mr. Comer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reform the labor laws of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC0CC28B7AB834A6C9E9F88BD99BDB0D1" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HCF129912C4264CE984B84763E4DABE29"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Employee Rights Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9FAAB733E3604BF1934395FDEFE199EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhanced employee rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The National Labor Relations Act is amended in section 9(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/159">29 U.S.C. 159(a)</external-xref>) by striking <quote>designated or selected for the purposes of collective bargaining</quote> and inserting <quote>for the purposes of collective bargaining selected by secret ballot in an election conducted by the Board,</quote>.</text></section><section id="H35D2F34C19DD482394FB376EE6CB11F6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Employee privacy</header><subsection id="H2E8ADB77FA4944F6A26EAF321B634E23"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notice of rights and protections; voter registration lists</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8 of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/158">29 U.S.C. 158</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5104CA72935940108D97D99DC49AE6F2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H4A1A8ECF68C142C59AE952D669E8AC71"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever the Board directs an election under section 9(c) or approves an election agreement, the employer of employees in the bargaining unit shall, not later than two business days after the Board directs such election or approves such election agreement, provide a voter list to a labor organization that has petitioned to represent such employees. Such voter list shall include the names of all employees in the bargaining unit and not more than one additional form of personal contact information for the employee (such as a telephone number, an email address, or a mailing address) chosen by the employee in writing. The voter list shall be provided in a searchable electronic format generally approved by the Board unless the employer certifies that the employer does not possess the capacity to produce the list in the required form. Not later than nine months after the date of enactment of the Employee Rights Act, the Board shall promulgate regulations implementing the requirements of this paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECCCDEF0B795439598B4246A32D561EB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be an unfair labor practice for an employer to violate any requirement under this subsection.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H58A4D1DFB9FB456AAFF5F356CAF75C03"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Labor organization use of personal information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(b) of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/158">29 U.S.C. 158(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H136829ADA30D4E2E849F13B0303255E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE09827CA984B4E9A8C95B5DA03A85E0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>8(b).</quote> and inserting <quote>8(b); and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91C09E66977042AF9659264809C8EFA1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HFFE1ACCBADB44281AA08E02131E98F5F" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H9A64AD9D6430445282388D3AC1DF3D4C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to fail to protect the personal information of an employee received for an organizing drive, to use such information for any reason other than a representation proceeding, or to use such information after the conclusion of a representation proceeding.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC48D560CCEBF45769C4AFE27E77A84BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Right not To subsidize labor organization nonrepresentational activities</header><text>Title I of the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/411">29 U.S.C. 411 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H9AF31D5B6E76430B9448723463838961" style="OLC"><section id="H52AF1191D0FB4AD8A9856464622C631B"><enum>106.</enum><header>Right not to subsidize labor organization nonrepresentational activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No employee’s labor organization dues, fees, assessments, or other contributions shall be used or contributed to any person, organization, or entity for any purpose not directly related to the labor organization’s collective bargaining or contract administration functions on behalf of the represented unit employee unless the employee member, or nonmember required to make such payments as a condition of employment, authorizes such expenditure in writing, after a notice period of not less than 35 days. An initial authorization provided by an employee under the preceding sentence shall expire not later than 1 year after the date on which such authorization is signed by the employee. There shall be no automatic renewal of an authorization under this section.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H9B93B4199A704BF2A1202DE306414B5C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Employment relationships</header><subsection id="H0E3E78FB34FD40189A3B095B2EB100B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendments to the fair labor standards act of 1938 To harmonize the definition of employee</header><paragraph id="HA4F1AA85C1DF4AF0A7211CFF785B7E09"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of employee</header><text>Section 3(e)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting before the period the following: <quote>, as determined under the usual common law rules</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CF8489A3D304066A71BC8281734236A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition of employ</header><text>Section 3(g) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203(g)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>an employee</quote> after <quote>permit</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H020F979D60664EC9B61C41C580284E6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification of joint employment</header><paragraph id="HCA156E61D37B4A5AB764957041925F68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National labor relations act</header><text>Section 2(2) of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H53B209C0A8384BE9B02D80A7F0E131F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The term <quote>employer</quote></quote> and inserting <quote>(A) The term <quote>employer</quote></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19FAE61ADC88444CB3EEDBD1B1A51B34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HC6375ADE352A466699CFA4B1E70D48FE" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H36958B0FC5994343B45F80F8EE938923"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An employer may be considered a joint employer of the employees of another employer only if each employer directly, actually, and immediately, and not in a limited and routine manner, exercises significant control over the essential terms and conditions of employment of the employees of the other employer, such as hiring such employees, discharging such employees, determining the rate of pay and benefits of such employees, supervising such employees on a day-to-day basis, assigning such employees a work schedule, position, or task, or disciplining such employees.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0F67E513C7D450DAD6950E52514D500"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fair labor standards act of 1938</header><text>Section 3(d) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H6FC8404391EE43B6BB97D5FF5DC36CB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote><quote>Employer</quote> includes</quote> and inserting <quote>(1) <quote>Employer</quote> includes</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B86982948914E5D9B2F145932C28C39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7B449A79D6F240F3A94FCA45805EAB2B" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H362B2DB26CF04A9A9DB6FA1EC592986D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An employer may be considered a joint employer of the employees of another employer for purposes of this Act only if each employer meets the criteria set forth in section 2(2)(B) of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152(2)(B)</external-xref>) except that, for purposes of determining joint-employer status under this Act, the terms <quote>employee</quote> and <quote>employer</quote> referenced in such section shall have the meanings given such terms in this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H33715E27944342F4A2238C8793132556"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Provision of technical assistance</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/201">29 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>), the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/151">29 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>), or any other Federal law, none of the following may be construed, alone or in combination with any other factor, as establishing an employer and employee relationship between a franchisor (or any employee of the franchisor) and a franchisee (or any employee of the franchisee):</text><paragraph id="H593F36DAE7CC4CA79A24969ABB028B98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The franchisor (or any employee of the franchisor) provides the franchisee (or any employee of the franchisee) with, or requires such franchisee (or any employee of the franchisee) to use, a handbook, or other training, on sexual harassment, human trafficking, workplace violence, discrimination, or opportunities for apprenticeships or scholarships.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3216283E309B4036A272BBD262F535D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The franchisor (or any employee of the franchisor) requires the franchisee (or any employee of the franchisee) to adopt a policy on sexual harassment, human trafficking, workplace violence, discrimination, opportunities for apprenticeships or scholarships, child care, or paid leave, including a requirement for such franchisee (or any employee of the franchisee) to report to the franchisor (or any employee of the franchisor) any violations or suspected violations of such policy.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H17E32B3E2C02421FA538150A40F3DDD0"><enum>5.</enum><header>Tribal sovereignty</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2 of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HEFB30C2E23EB4A25A4DDD7C5FB35ED64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>or any Indian Tribe, or any enterprise or institution owned and operated by an Indian Tribe and located on its Indian lands,</quote> after <quote>subdivision thereof,</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49E0BCC83F6B43639279127402DE3751"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H0568ED636E77462799E3CEE5BA467133" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HC54B5AE0A39A4A14992BCFEED736C1BC"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The term <quote>Indian Tribe</quote> means any Indian Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, or other organized group or community which is recognized as eligible for the special programs and services provided by the United States to Indians because of their status as Indians.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H333CDA5AC04D4672B5E53472B9545E6B"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The term <quote>Indian</quote> means any individual who is a member of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40066DD9762E4142A018D895584F70EC"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The term <quote>Indian lands</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H033A3101CAC04E10BDE255ADB40BAE0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all lands within the limits of any Indian reservation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A7C5D2C8D134B4D9FE8927D67C180CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any lands title to which is either held in trust by the United States for the benefit of any Indian Tribe or Indian or held by any Indian Tribe or Indian subject to restriction by the United States against alienation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4F2403202DC45F0A2FB1177CAD39CB2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any lands in the State of Oklahoma that are within the boundaries of a former reservation (as defined by the Secretary of the Interior) of a Federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

