<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7B641091CCE7486EBEB329BDCC453C6D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5168 IH: To authorize the President to award the Medal of Honor to Joseph M. Perez for acts of valor while serving as a member of the Army during the Vietnam War.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5168</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230808">August 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the President to award the Medal of Honor to Joseph M. Perez for acts of valor while serving as a member of the Army during the Vietnam War.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE4E699FE6B4F442EBE0B4D5995EC2BB8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD8345F2CCA304C778BB7519F65FBF3AE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Authorization of award of medal of honor to Joseph M. Perez for acts of valor as a member of the Army during the Vietnam War</header> 
<subsection id="H046669691BDC46949DAFB892946B3A2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Recognition of Acts of Valor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress recognizes the following acts of valor by Joseph M. Perez:</text> <paragraph id="H26BC88C0FB304C05AFCB0C5085F6D781"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Joseph M. Perez distinguished himself by valorous actions against overwhelming odds while serving as a Sergeant in the Army, with Company C, 3rd Battalion, 8th Infantry Regiment, 4th Infantry Division, in South Vietnam.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF90D8BE69AFD4F65A3EDE288B61D1F02"><enum>(2)</enum><text>On May 26, 1967, during the Vietnam War, Sergeant Perez acted as the fire team leader with the Commanding Officer of Company C led an infantry unit conducting a search and destroy task near the Cambodian border. When the unit reached the top of a hill, they were suddenly under attack from a concealed sniper.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED203577DC664941986958F0C993AA36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>During the initial phase of battle, Sergeant Perez and the unit took cover to assess and decide the strength of the enemy and determine the erection of where the attack was coming from. The fire team returned fire, when the enemy launched a hand-grenade. Without hesitation or concern for his personal safety, Sergeant Perez absorbed the full lethal explosion and shielded his fellow soldiers from the blast. The explosion caused Sergeant Perez to lose his right eye and severed his right hand.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD63038469004DB2BC2F5F3D358C7443"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The fire team moved to relocate to a safer area, leaving Sgt Perez alone. Once Sgt Perez regained consciousness, he crawled to safe ground twenty meters to be able to be treated by medics. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H930E2F2345F342BB824568BDEA0E6FD8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Sergeant Perez’s personal leadership in intense close combat resulted in a major win for his battalion against overwhelming odds, though he lost his eye and hand and nearly lost his life, he saved the lives of three of his fire team members from death and serious injuries from the explosion.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB8B606EBF6F94DAB93458D51773DA2B6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Sergeant Perez’s selfless devotion to duty, his extraordinary heroism, conspicuous gallantry and intrepidity, and numerous risks of his life above and beyond the call of duty, are all in keeping with the highest traditions of the Army, and reflect great credit on himself, the Armed Forces, and the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0A3314EA376D4286A4F0AFCD1E2F77BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
<paragraph id="HD796B6093DDC4D6CBBB98D6270550C68"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When awarding him the Distinguished Service Cross, Sergeant Perez’s chain of command was unaware of the full extent of his valorous actions and the numerous risks he took for his soldiers, all above and beyond the call of duty.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H877DECC3685C49438C763D4A5242010F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Although Sergeant Perez absorbed the lethal explosion of a hand grenade, once he regained consciousness, he continued to move with his battalion against devastating and overwhelming enemy fire.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0D876A209C654D15A38C13F891685E41"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the time limitations specified in section 7274 of title 10, United States Code, or any other time limitation with respect to the awarding of certain medals to persons who served in the Armed Forces, the President is authorized to award the Medal of Honor, under section 7271 of such title, to Joseph M. Perez for the acts of valor described in subsection (d).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9729198039D84B92B450BD1E99E4E139"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Acts of valor described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The acts of valor described in this subsection are the actions of Joseph M. Perez on May 26, 1967, while serving as a member of the Army during the Vietnam War, for which he was previously awarded the Distinguished Service Cross.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

