<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4ECC2A0D036849B99BC6BC20C5443386" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4865 IH: IDB Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4865</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase transparency regarding the activities, and reduce the malign influence of, the People&#8217;s Republic of China in the Inter-American Development Bank, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF49DC7252E0546B98F0B22E85B5B631D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H748F5B4D2D26473187386AE1CA0C3B4A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>IDB Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H784CED4E1F8E4EE1A6D4DF728805C822"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on influence of the People’s Republic of China at the Inter-American Development Bank</header> <subsection id="H24272952A3744D388E0320C81FCC842F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Within 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H099E5F2890C745D399868D2F7A4B70D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The scope and scale of the influence of the PRC and PRC companies in the IDB, including in—</text> <subparagraph id="H38B7C51ABE884F7991DE30FE558115AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the organization and personnel of the IDB;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF819E48821E14E8698AADC98C84FFFA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>IDB governance and transparency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAD51940D10A941F1B1FF92A464D447FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the financing of the IDB;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5356285410F5429D90E48775368A6848"><enum>(D)</enum><text>determinations around which projects to fund or finance;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCDAD7F8717DB496B867E2FED91F5E676"><enum>(E)</enum><text>deliberations regarding the involvement or membership of Taiwan in the IDB; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0763C1CEF34C413189A60F43641143C0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other modes through which the PRC or PRC companies influence the IDB.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D5119EC734941748F212F488EB2FC6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A complete list of all projects of the IDB that include financing or funding from the PRC, PRC companies, or PRC trust funds created at the IDB since the PRC joined the IDB as a member country on January 12, 2009, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC3D76FE5E014469A881F572B95ECFA37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the title and identification number of the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC78F3733D84E403497814076BDE4ECBE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0BA9C90E780D4CC389E0B54C404C851C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the location of the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H47DC4DA691F94CFAB5D0A564A00A31BF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the amount of funding or financing initially allocated for the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6FB4D467074D4FD8930D6CD5190F755D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the amount of funding or financing disbursed under the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1977023124B4B61B335F0DAB107C725"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a summary of the status of the implementation of the project; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H19621ABD65624B428C1938C80E4C4E25"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a description of any incidents in which funding or financing for a project has been disbursed, but has not been implemented or completed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68251634119C47CE9A5F6B2E7559C87E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A complete list of the projects of the IDB in which PRC companies participate, whether through direct or indirect procurement or other contracting, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFB6BFBB645BA44BF8F03CE1D154F7B5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the title and identification number of the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF975091B1E584EDC8DED3A4C9873A0C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5AFC4F46DCC940CABBDC1593697ACA70"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the location of the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A184CB569BA470581FEC2507E3847DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the amount of funding or financing initially allocated for the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3EE19B99CD0A4DAFA783478128BB0342"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the amount of funding or financing disbursed under the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD06EBAE4C10942A09211519DDC6789CF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the name of the participating PRC companies and, in the case of each such company, whether the participation consists of direct or indirect procurement or other contracting;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H24E220FF58CC461699E7E5DD46652CEA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the amount of funding or financing received by the PRC companies under the project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB51F13D48BC64473B320B7C3EAE1D739"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a summary of the work conducted by the PRC companies as part of direct or indirect procurement or other contracting; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H750685104DB94AFDB56747B5536A296D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a description of any incidents in which the PRC companies received funding or financing as part of a direct or indirect procurement or other contracting, but required work has not been implemented or completed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1953EBC8BB84CEFA5BBB5E288D053A1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A full review of projects described in paragraphs (2) and (3) to assess whether any of the projects featured any human rights abuses, delays, corruption, or poor results, and an analysis of the procurement practices involved in the projects.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F2E738B3A1E41BB95A16F8CA47E15BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The extent to which—</text> <subparagraph id="H4E0DB0913CAD40CBAB5EF107F0387FE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the IDB uses equipment or services produced by technology providers covered by section 2 of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 or PRC companies on the list of entities set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations, set forth in subchapter C of chapter VII of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulations; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9879A82C7FF54505B6DAF0A52D711493"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projects funded or financed by the IDB use technology provided by the providers or entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H068B3ABDE15B404B826F4BC463959039"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A review of how and to what extent the PRC has used the IDB to, within IDB member countries—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBF2D803C492A4668A8C4A64FF08B800F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">spread the diplomatic, economic, and military influence of the PRC;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2C0DA947C1654B09ABFD74BD4DCA01E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promote the adoption and use of technologies of PRC companies; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H99E56E31D3F6473694973B0FF3356F9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promote the preferred values of the PRC.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H669270B06B104557A9AA3F19F4F47838"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An action plan for the Executive Director to work to reduce the involvement of the PRC and PRC companies in the IDB and projects funded or financed by the IDB, as determined under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H774A730FC3674F4990AFE631A1585021"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The extent to which PRC persons sanctioned by the United States serve in leadership or management positions in PRC companies working on IDB-funded or IDB-financed projects.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD853658185D438582732C9B6A02772A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The extent to which the PRC has used its voice, vote, and influence in the IDB to promote the interests of the PRC at the expense of regional development interests.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF84B5C06075541A99F99F4CB901177E3"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A summary of the in-depth reviews conducted under section 3(a)(2)(A) of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H598B0C6AE7DD44AABDE630FB282575C1"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of IDB projects funded by the PRC or PRC companies assessed to pose a risk to United States interests due to their proximity to a cooperative security location, a United States military installation outside the contiguous United States, or a military installation of a partner or ally of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9422888B19A945458BBC4905CB7B4911"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subsequent reports</header><text>Within 2 years after the Secretary submits the report required by subsection (a), and every 2 years thereafter for 8 years, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text> <paragraph id="H2803C681510C49B49E2039DA4B834C30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any updates to information included in all reports submitted under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B36F3DED13D4D748F93D6A61A1D94F6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any new information related to the matters described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H75C61AD2CFAF46E99D71F0B7D7A19D6B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Format</header><text>The reports required under subsections (a) and (b) shall be submitted to the appropriate congressional committees in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H66DC090400794F1EB4D7CB2B099E28C9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Not earlier than 60 days, and not later than 90 days, after the Secretary submits a report required by subsection (a) or (b), the Secretary shall post an unclassified summary of the report on a public-facing web page of the Department of the Treasury.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC4A3F6EEB919470C944CEEFA01DB6E65"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required use of United States voice, vote, and influence at the Inter-American Development Bank</header> <subsection id="HBC9BA5AC9ED949E69CBFF89206A4D8B1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall instruct the United States Executive Director at the Inter-American Development Bank to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States to do the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H704F540763234CCAACD1E6B464FD9D23"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Facilitate greater IDB transparency about the role of the PRC and PRC companies in the IDB, including by fostering a more open release policy toward working papers, past evaluations, and other IDB documents.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAFFEBB334A294692B2F8D95BC6F516AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Reduce the influence of the PRC and PRC companies in all IDB deliberations, activities, and projects, including by—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7E959B3669B24F65930682760BEC6BD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting an in-depth review of all projects, financing, loans, and grants in which at least 10 percent of—</text> <clause id="H5F8129F4C1694452AE7649DCF7C98EC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the funding or financing for such a project, financing, loan, or grant comes from the PRC or PRC companies; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC72A32D6C8804CFC94ADD4C04F766161"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the value of direct or indirect procurements or other contracting for such a project, financing, loan, or grant is provided to PRC companies; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1C2E9B23C91474D823A0E92A4FAC45C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>voting against or taking action to prevent a quorum for all votes related to—</text> 
<clause id="H0A9719394A75428895637576E227FE87"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any project, financing, loan, or grant for which the in-depth review required in subparagraph (A) determines presents risks to United States national interests; and</text></clause> <clause id="H822A678E71AA48728DAA6EEDF2ACA2F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any project, financing, loan, or grant that would include the participation of PRC trust funds created with the IDB.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C9D7C83C45144BFBA4F6C2FCBE12765"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 180 days after date of the enactment of this Act, if the Secretary has failed to submit the report required by section 2, vote against, or take action to prevent a quorum for all votes related to, IDB budgets until the IDB provides the Secretary with the information required for the Secretary to prepare and submit the report.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H004BB35F0BEB43B4BB02F4A2A381050F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Vote against, or withhold quorum for all votes related to, the issuance, sale, or transfer of additional shares of stock in the IDB to the PRC.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC3FC4B8D87AB44A5A21621E42FD4EAE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirements of subsection (a)(3) on a case-by-case basis if the Secretary certifies and reports to the appropriate congressional committees before the waiver is exercised that the waiver would serve a national interest of the United States or address basic human needs.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC9B703A425F74AA480BAFC09B1573EC8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HC2D2EA2AD79340C58823BC49CFD2A27F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H265437AB39434748BA981DE2A811F72E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF31A107B78B44EEF889D408848D3BBB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services and the Select Committee on the Strategic Competition Between the United States and the Chinese Communist Party of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB7CFF5F7D1B46D5B5444B37DF9325E2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text>The term <term>Executive Director</term> means the United States Executive Director at the IDB.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7FD374A69C349329844769F701EB4EA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>IDB</header><text>The term <term>IDB</term> means all of the current and former institutions in the IDB Group, including the Inter-American Development Bank, IDB Invest, IDB lab, and any related predecessor entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD1BD9CD706B471F9091D5B3F837E9FA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>PRC</header><text>The term <term>PRC</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3517024A8B594A79AB21951376EB45D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the People’s Republic of China; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0B5E9B259EBA4D4BBD45B99C9B4196AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any and all Special Administrative Regions of China, including Hong Kong and Macau but not including Taiwan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB043E89A2D6A4527B9742C45A1D101C7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>PRC companies</header><text>The term <term>PRC companies</term> means any corporation, company, limited liability company, limited partnership, business trust, business association, or other similar entity owned by, controlled by, or subject to the jurisdiction or direction of the Government of the PRC.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC02F027E9D2447D39F477C0E5461F15A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Treasury. </text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

