<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H61BAD2C9424545D4ADF21E634D5EE1C1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3436 IH: Support Our Election Workers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3436</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Election Assistance Commission to establish a program to make grants to States to provide increased pay for election workers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBDD026DFA43A477DA49D035A157A9590" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H9E930F9C1FF84B2481608FA4D9EB54BF"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Support Our Election Workers Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H485B419FE8E54A15B4C6EE98B7550182"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program for grants to support election workers</header><subsection id="H02FEF935A18842E4A057499A699B0548"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle D of title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21001">52 U.S.C. 21001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6BB37849F990429ABD910BA9BFA1E524"><part id="H47098684B45E4DF4A9AD4132AE77EB58"><enum>7</enum><header> Payments to help support election workers</header><section id="HC34BE29EF39F42FF93657EDE1E59C756"><enum>297.</enum><header>Establishment and operation of grant program</header><subsection id="HA79E90A24D99426FBDD2EFEFB30F106D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall establish and operate a program under which the Commission shall make payments to eligible States for providing increased pay for election workers, including individuals serving as election officials or poll workers on a temporary or unpaid basis.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFC68F5CA1D6C4C9DB3D5D2DCA894EBED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amount of payment</header><paragraph id="H91B58BC27B834E80AF28FD9E502A7A6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount of a payment made to a State under the program established under this part shall be equal to the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="H45FAA982B2AB44D6989FFBE8DE0E44FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the reasonable costs the State expects to incur in providing increased pay for election workers, as determined by the Commission taking into account the information provided by the State in the plan described in section 297A; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3635BE4699C462DADC18C1FFCF46C57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the minimum payment amount described in paragraph (2) with respect to the fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9869B5BE5B884EF68D64D4A895C33340"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum payment amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minimum payment amount described in this paragraph with respect to a fiscal year is equal to one-half of 1 percent of the aggregate amount made available during the fiscal year for payments under the program established under this part.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A21F4776ACD4B42B58D2567399F649A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>In order to be eligible to receive a payment under the program established under this part, a State shall submit to the Commission, at such time and in such form as the Commission may require, an application containing a description of a plan for how the State will use the payment to provide increased pay to election workers, as described in section 297A, together with such other information and assurances as the Commission may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC967AFAF26B4B249910DDC95D4CA466"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>A State receiving a payment under the program established under this part shall submit to the Commission such reports on the State’s use of the payment as the Commission may require.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7C62FE9D707B4D2684123D728AFB8AB5"><enum>297A.</enum><header>State plan for providing increased pay to election workers</header><subsection id="HAF58B7F55DA54DF0866FF58F3B99E75A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Elements of plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State’s plan for providing increased pay to election workers shall include the following elements:</text><paragraph id="H27BF17F762B3411293C8A7854AE012EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of how the State will use increased pay to retain qualified election workers and to recruit new election workers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9CA3D715D604B9C8A592497D0C6C932"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The requirements an individual must meet in order to be eligible to receive increased pay under the plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0754BF8E7F444C49EF9B12E7067843C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of the reasonable costs the State expects to incur in providing increased pay for such eligible individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H207A45E3CD9F4148A9C53B71BB45328D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The procedures for carrying out the plan, including the extent to which State and local election officials will be responsible for carrying out the plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3FEAE0D0A67040A382D51462FB2DD3D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Opportunity of all election workers To receive pay</header><text>Under the State’s plan, the State may not treat an election worker as ineligible to receive increased pay solely because the individual does not interact directly with voters, individuals attempting to vote, or individuals attempting to register to vote. </text></subsection></section><section id="HA29CB1945F96427F86EBE78A5408BA70"><enum>297B.</enum><header>Coverage of Commonwealth of Northern Mariana Islands</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands shall be considered a State. </text></section><section id="HE842D1A029024D628E4DD42789D3EB16"><enum>297C.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated for payments under this part such sums as may be necessary for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HEBF6B9AC2B7E4170961F8DA957DF7663"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the items relating to subtitle D of title II the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD8C1049392E845AC9FEA736E112EEF0B"><toc><toc-entry level="part" idref="H47098684B45E4DF4A9AD4132AE77EB58">PART 7— Payments to help support election workers </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HC34BE29EF39F42FF93657EDE1E59C756">Sec. 297. Establishment and operation of grant program. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H7C62FE9D707B4D2684123D728AFB8AB5">Sec. 297A. State plan for providing increased pay to election workers. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HA29CB1945F96427F86EBE78A5408BA70">Sec. 297B. Coverage of Commonwealth of Northern Mariana Islands. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HE842D1A029024D628E4DD42789D3EB16">Sec. 297C. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

