<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H467D08A4EC394A58865672E02AB789A2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1702 IH: To amend PROMESA to include certain ethics provisions to provide for the disqualification of certain advisors to the Financial Oversight and Management Board, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1702</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend PROMESA to include certain ethics provisions to provide for the disqualification of certain advisors to the Financial Oversight and Management Board, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5D1546F8B08D46D1A732C5445F36D208" style="OLC"><section id="H83A66975E3534214ACFCABD1BB256E91" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Disqualification of certain advisors to the financial oversight and management board</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 109 of PROMESA (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/2129">48 U.S.C. 2129</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A86DB8B344743E3AB12040E9B6E60DC"><subsection id="HFC23D3B14D0E4BEE8E3DFA01CFE2212B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disqualification of certain advisors</header><paragraph id="H71AF127536D54CA39E8676725A61D8BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of covered contract</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>covered contract</term> means a contract with the territorial government or an instrumentality of the territorial government, the performance of which is within the jurisdiction of the Oversight Board under section 204(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90388B9FC15B4F579BA6C364908A272B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disqualification</header><text>In accordance with the rules adopted by the Oversight Board under paragraph (3), any third-party advisory or consulting firm shall be disqualified from advising the Oversight Board for the duration of any period during which the firm has as a client, or provides advisory or other consulting services in any capacity to, an individual, corporation, association, organization, or other business entity, including a subsidiary, that is competing for, or is performing, a covered contract.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD74D68A77D6243BBA84A1FB6B13D2A62"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rules</header><text>For purposes of carrying out paragraph (2), the Oversight Board shall adopt rules to carry out the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF0341437F74B4EEDB98C2CB2AAECCA2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To be eligible to advise or consult the Oversight Board with respect to the review, procurement, or performance of a covered contract, a third-party advisory or consulting firm shall certify to the Oversight Board that the third-party advisory or consulting firm is not disqualified from advising the Oversight Board under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7021CF622B7C49E79E3538CC8CE5D016" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any officer or employee of a third-party advisory or consulting firm who prepares, presents, or certifies any information or report with respect to the certification of the third-party advisory or consulting firm under subparagraph (A) for the Oversight Board, or any agent of the Oversight Board, that is intentionally false or misleading, or, on learning that any such information is false or misleading, fails to immediately advise the Oversight Board or an agent of the Oversight Board in writing, shall be subject to prosecution and penalties under law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDADC47642FE416D85481ABCCB74C8FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>If, after an investigation conducted by the Oversight Board, the Oversight Board determines that a third-party advisory or consulting firm has provided services to the Oversight Board in violation of paragraph (2), has failed to submit a certification required under subparagraph (A), or is in violation of subparagraph (B) (including any rules adopted under subparagraph (A) or (B)), the Oversight Board shall immediately refer such information to the Attorney General for the covered territory and the Office of the United States Attorney for the covered territory.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

