<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H7988243E0DC04F8EA86865129F16DE56" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6570 RH: Protect Liberty and End Warrantless Surveillance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code>
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 248</calendar>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6570</legis-num>
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–307, Part I]</associated-doc>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231204">December 4, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000289">Mr. Jordan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000478">Mr. Fry</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor></action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc>
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc>
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on December 4, 2023</action-instruction>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 to reform certain authorities and to provide greater transparency and oversight.<pagebreak/></official-title>
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HJU00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H6A8FADBE83C042648B951956940F9402"> 
<section id="H7B5A035C4D834CC6A454F52F929C9DFC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Liberty and End Warrantless Surveillance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H33A685863BB64AB5B856ACA5B7C2CA6A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Query procedure reform</header> <subsection id="HE11CC303F21B4AFCA2D3F5FFE9FB07E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on eligibility to conduct queries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 702(f)(1) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a(f)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7F07FF0441D44684930AFF2F882B269B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HEFDE7EBC6A9045729251BEFC35CAF623"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation on eligibility of FBI personnel to conduct United States person queries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall ensure that the procedures adopted under subparagraph (A) limit the authority to conduct queries such that—</text> <clause id="H42AE78EB27354D9B9952FFB4E140C195"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each field office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the most senior official whose primary duty station is that field office is authorized to designate not more than five individuals whose primary duty station is that field office who are eligible to conduct a query using a United States person query term; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6280A38EA8F8433895010076D8509116"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the headquarters of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation is authorized to designate not more than five individuals whose primary duty station is the Headquarters of the Federal Bureau of Investigation who are eligible to conduct a query using a United States person query term.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H54444646BAEA46D59E3121F0722A1EE5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on warrantless queries for the communications of United States persons and persons located in the United States</header><text>Section 702(f) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a(f)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), is further amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF9E4F73415DD4EFDA61423B2524B2A40" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HAA32E725D1174B4DA217CC8E58235626"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and the limitations and requirements in paragraph (2)</quote> after <quote>Constitution of the United States</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H30BCFCA013084A5CBAC117D14DABA8C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>United States person query term used for a query</quote> and inserting <quote>term for a United States person or person reasonably believed to be in the United States used for a query as required by paragraph (3)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E7D002F1A764C82B8BDA0B4E4A1680B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (6); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H86778D6C01CE40DFBC7A14E94893C3A0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H15AE6A00AB874F999D6338D2A0EF4ACE" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HA138E6D59B6B42E2A848C42C3B2CF978"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on warrantless queries for the communications and other information of United States persons and persons located in the United States</header> <subparagraph id="HC981D43AE1FA49FAA986928C635BEA37"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraphs (B) and (C), no officer or employee of the United States may conduct a query of information acquired under this section in an effort to find communications or information the compelled production of which would require a probable cause warrant if sought for law enforcement purposes in the United States, of or about 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or creation of the information.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1AE6BD175C844E82B4C4964BA2FEFC47"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions for concurrent authorization, consent, emergency situations, and certain defensive cybersecurity queries</header> 
<clause id="H54D755FAAD024EE08CF9A27EAB4CE9A4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to a query related to a United States person or person reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or creation of the information if—</text> <subclause id="H523FFF89B2FD4733B1A94BEA95153014"><enum>(I)</enum><text>such person is the subject of an order or emergency authorization authorizing electronic surveillance or physical search under section 105 or 304 of this Act, or a warrant issued pursuant to the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure by a court of competent jurisdiction authorizing the conduct of the query;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H61EC8A4272EB4173B533804FA3DF389C"><enum>(II)</enum> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H27AE4782170C47C4A3AC592364A46DFB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the officer or employee carrying out the query has a reasonable belief that—</text> <subitem commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28FE980A4EB744BE9108C94EAE545958" indent="up1"><enum>(AA)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an emergency exists involving an imminent threat of death or serious bodily harm; and</text></subitem> 
<subitem commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE7E499B82012482EA3CB1BE0BA250489" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in order to prevent or mitigate this threat, the query must be conducted before authorization pursuant to subparagraph (I) can, with due diligence, be obtained; and</text></subitem></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB378D170B2264359A4E1876C5A0AC8E6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the query is provided to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court and the congressional intelligence committees and the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate in a timely manner;</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEA8656C5C28E4F1F907B5E861BE309FB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>such person or, if such person is incapable of providing consent, a third party legally authorized to consent on behalf of such person, has provided consent to the query on a case-by-case basis; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H22FED18183124C68B08BB8657FCE8EDA"><enum>(IV)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD47FC3F01EB64DA99F46C3FA5D6E0023"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the query uses a known cybersecurity threat signature as a query term;</text></item> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93CCD377461F4BDC804A4F34F1AC33A7" indent="up5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the query is conducted, and the results of the query are used, for the sole purpose of identifying targeted recipients of malicious software and preventing or mitigating harm from such malicious software;</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19B2B634B741468AAAD7CC592785AED3" indent="up5"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no additional contents of communications retrieved as a result of the query are accessed or reviewed; and</text></item> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H99F532F84B7F4D89818565169809BAD8" indent="up5"><enum>(dd)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">all such queries are reported to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court. </text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HB3AA01C3677F4F1AAE8339006A7360AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitations</header> <subclause id="H4F5601D4D75B450883CD512C07CCA6BF" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Use in subsequent proceedings and investigations</header><text>No information retrieved pursuant to a query authorized by clause (i)(II) or information derived from such query may be used, received in evidence, or otherwise disseminated in any investigation, trial, hearing, or other proceeding in or before any court, grand jury, department, office, agency, regulatory body, legislative committee, or other authority of the United States, a State, or political subdivision thereof, except in proceedings or investigations that arise from the threat that prompted the query. </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9FFAC61BD71945F89392AA0764924CAF"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Assessment of compliance</header><text>The Attorney General shall not less frequently than annually assess compliance with the requirements under subclause (I). </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4C79C230A9F14704924732001D811ED3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Matters relating to emergency queries</header> <clause id="H44079B9A9A2B4EA9A4FBE1D6197DA0A4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Treatment of denials</header><text>In the event that a query for communications or information, the compelled production of which would require a probable cause warrant if sought for law enforcement purposes in the United States, of or about 1 more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or creation of the information is conducted pursuant to an emergency authorization described in subparagraph (B)(i)(I) and the application for such emergency authorization is denied, or in any other case in which the query has been conducted and no order is issued approving the query—</text> 
<subclause id="HE40B357687B94E68AD7C9C02874682D5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>no information obtained or evidence derived from such query may be used, received in evidence, or otherwise disseminated in any investigation, trial, hearing, or other proceeding in or before any court, grand jury, department, office, agency, regulatory body, legislative committee, or other authority of the United States, a State, or political subdivision thereof; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H49BF3E89E30643F486319BB2F31550A4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>no information concerning any United States person or person reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or the creation of the information acquired from such query may subsequently be used or disclosed in any other manner without the consent of such person, except with the approval of the Attorney General if the information indicates a threat of death or serious bodily harm to any person.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H893F60B6F19F433BAEF9024A2FD054F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Assessment of compliance</header><text>The Attorney General shall not less frequently than annually assess compliance with the requirements under clause (i). </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8F6EF593AC3B40FC834A064105DFBB9C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Foreign intelligence purpose</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B)(i), no officer or employee of the United States may conduct a query of information acquired under this section in an effort to find information of or about 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or creation of the information unless the query is reasonably likely to retrieve foreign intelligence information. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5CA2F95473614C539AE4B0EEF726B8EF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Documentation</header><text>No officer or employee of the United States may conduct a query of information acquired under this section in an effort to find information of or about 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of query or the time of the communication or the creation of the information, unless first an electronic record is created, and a system, mechanism, or business practice is in place to maintain such record, that includes the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HBC398F653582483A9FEC4E02CC0370CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each term used for the conduct of the query.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H50BBA3ED48034D84BA26D4A6010F250B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The date of the query.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H628C224B534B4BD8B070400FB65ECBC7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The identifier of the officer or employee.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC5BF910C01B84130A049246AE2BA822B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A statement of facts showing that the use of each query term included under subparagraph (A) is—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02E6D30E15814D198D31D9A322B38F4C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reasonably likely to retrieve foreign intelligence information; or</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H555F7DDEA29E4939AAF206AC4C3B538F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in furtherance of the exceptions described in paragraph (2)(B)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H330D5D3541BA48EC962262D2632AEAB5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition on results of metadata query as a basis for access to communications and other protected information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a query of information acquired under this section is conducted in an effort to find communications metadata of 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or communication and the query returns such metadata, the results of the query shall not be used as a basis for reviewing communications or information a query for which is otherwise prohibited under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1536D7DBEFFD4BB988397A980ADB79E5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federated datasets</header><text>The prohibitions and requirements in this section shall apply to queries of federated and mixed datasets that include information acquired under this section, unless a mechanism exists to limit the query to information not acquired under this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2D022F01DFFE4946BD7E62951423DAE0" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limitation on use of information obtained under section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 relating to United States persons and persons located in the United States in criminal, civil, and administrative actions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of section 706(a) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881e">50 U.S.C. 1881e(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB0E7FD5488734999AE569C05DFE849FF" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HB3AE14CB47074D0DA0A3D1D585397C76"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on use in criminal, civil, and administrative proceedings and investigations</header><text>No information acquired pursuant to section 702(f) of or about a United States person or person reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication may be introduced as evidence against such person in any criminal, civil, or administrative proceeding or used as part of any criminal, civil, or administrative investigation, except—</text> <subparagraph id="H802CD4520E6B478FB39600E794A72335"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with the prior approval of the Attorney General; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H75389ADE2DF74583A6B87A3CCC847DF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a proceeding or investigation in which the information is directly related to and necessary to address a specific threat of—</text> <clause id="HF136F8C1458247AF9D61A6632E57D255"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the commission of a Federal crime of terrorism under any of clauses (i) through (iii) of section 2332b(g)(5)(B) of title 18, United States Code;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC582B15CE0454623A01CDF3DFFF75310"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>actions necessitating counterintelligence (as defined in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>));</text></clause> <clause id="HE88C34FE7C414014BC5D6215BAF08F86"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the proliferation or the use of a weapon of mass destruction (as defined in section 2332a(c) of title 18, United States Code);</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC1C085FDB71740418906953129E8B364"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a cybersecurity breach or attack from a foreign country;</text></clause> <clause id="HA8F1DF43FF704085929EA856493162EE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>incapacitation or destruction of critical infrastructure (as defined in section 1016(e) of the Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism (USA PATRIOT ACT) Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>));</text></clause> 
<clause id="H05B7F4772A744FEDA5565CB0D13B193A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>an attack against the armed forces of the United States or an ally of the United States or to other personnel of the United States Government or a government of an ally of the United States; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD272A40057DD41C9AC7ECA845D3751B1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">international narcotics trafficking.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="H52F4F9C7430C45DF96FBDC6766376075"><enum>4.</enum><header>Repeal of authority for the resumption of abouts collection</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB61B4D3EE68247E19894D8C1378EE943"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 702(b)(5) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a(b)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>, except as provided under section 103(b) of the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017</quote>. </text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F20061FCD414D849196D52080D6891C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB92613FDF79148058E6122583E6FD7CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978</header><text>Section 702(m) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a(m)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H56DFC581C14C4B64969B0EFC1E53203F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">Reviews, and Reporting</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">and Reviews</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E2B994F8D5E473BACB3589A468ABA74"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEEAF0C3AC7E84E1C859424F567245E01"><enum>(2)</enum><header>FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103 of the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/118">Public Law 115–118</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBBA0A5A6532C4A6D91D224B9815E4888"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7532D6F1BAAA41B1ACF9D19E35B4EB3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(a) </enum-in-header>In general.—</header-in-text></quote>. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HCF23290729FB474194FA17BD69326447"><enum>5.</enum><header>Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court reform</header> <subsection id="HE4B6FABF728348FDABB4D5CC6484E154"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for same judge to hear renewal applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(a)(1) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>To the extent practicable, no judge designated under this subsection shall hear a renewal application for electronic surveillance under this Act, which application was previously granted by another judge designated under this subsection, unless the term of the judge who granted the application has expired, or that judge is otherwise no longer serving on the court.</quote>. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEF95F549B6AE48108FC7F25111B456FF" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of amici curiae in Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court proceedings</header> 
<paragraph id="H532668C1CB9A4CACA778E59E2743B913" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Expansion of appointment authority</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9C722B96F66C4E74A1AEBDEF18DC2745" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i)(2) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(i)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <clause id="H37C413D89A1A49D3A52E3D14FE5A8DBC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H979002EAC823462B873E782D84BECFAA"> 
<subparagraph id="H2C90A836565740538E525091B7623742" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall, unless the court issues a finding that appointment is not appropriate, appoint 1 or more individuals who have been designated under paragraph (1), not fewer than 1 of whom possesses privacy and civil liberties expertise, unless the court finds that such a qualification is inappropriate, to serve as amicus curiae to assist the court in the consideration of any application or motion for an order or review that, in the opinion of the court—</text> <clause id="HDC3E142B96DA4792A1F4AE45E3A6D5DA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">presents a novel or significant interpretation of the law;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H380889C40F7C43838FBDFCF45DB96673" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">presents significant concerns with respect to the activities of a United States person that are protected by the first amendment to the Constitution of the United States;</text></clause> <clause id="H77FA464B94B642F29E8FFFB59B71D2CB" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">presents or involves a sensitive investigative matter;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF650D996355242C985CB04ED868E51DB" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>presents a request for approval of a new program, a new technology, or a new use of existing technology;</text></clause> <clause id="HEB3FAD47295848D6B76C36E9CDBB8F68" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>presents a request for reauthorization of programmatic surveillance; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H79280879C87148D3BB7392B1C352C787" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise presents novel or significant civil liberties issues; or</text></clause> <clause id="HDFD4E570477540FD8A93C58F44BDA1C3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise involves the activities of a United States person; and</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> 
<clause id="HDC6328D285B24470B44946D214D94296" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>an individual or organization</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>1 or more individuals or organizations</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8331B43D9B24FEB99CC19F05CE9E2FF" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition of sensitive investigative matter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(i)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B1078A101564CED873E4853D3282033"> 
<paragraph id="H8673E700818A443299680E0F0DFD310E" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>sensitive investigative matter</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H26F235BAB45845CBB66D05620C44BC1D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an investigative matter involving the activities of—</text> 
<clause id="HBD995D3975E742B38D4D3B832872F97A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a domestic public official or political candidate, or an individual serving on the staff of such an official or candidate;</text></clause> <clause id="H420F5827F80149628A5B20BFB1555471" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a domestic religious or political organization, or a known or suspected United States person prominent in such an organization; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFC2F10DEF6BB4C5881016CCB6C738632" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the domestic news media; or</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H50E3630810C74AB1A3BE7D8CA33F7492" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other investigative matter involving a domestic entity or a known or suspected United States person that, in the judgment of the applicable court established under subsection (a) or (b), is as sensitive as an investigative matter described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1EAAE1B993BE4585BED2C72181D131F5" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority To seek review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(i)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a) of this section, is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HE86CAF0BBD844740980D7F7437FB2340" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text> 
<clause id="HBD55167B91EC4E7CBAA125B76EC4C286" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">; authority</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Duties</header-in-text></quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H4E0B08BD888F44F9B3C8CEC583255F91" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) as clauses (i), (ii), and (iii), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H61CCC3CFD95542B4B2CC16C80EC04A5E" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>the amicus curiae shall</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAD63014E7AEA4983966E6943D3F76C4F"><text>the amicus curiae—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H876D4A808F024A6998A4B401B9C7FC0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> <clause id="H7C2F9BD74C824148B23BA995F5800170" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(i), as so redesignated, by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, including legal arguments regarding any privacy or civil liberties interest of any United States person that would be significantly impacted by the application or motion</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE5C68E1F56E64EECAADB6608813C44E9" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4AB5482F68564F90B734B6654A6614E9"><text>; and</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H98FEDF278B1749E9AD776D140A589B54"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may seek leave to raise any novel or significant privacy or civil liberties issue relevant to the application or motion or other issue directly impacting the legality of the proposed electronic surveillance with the court, regardless of whether the court has requested assistance on that issue.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49A4E74B7CBD4343B4DF6E96D95C42F2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (7) through (12) as paragraphs (8) through (13), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7EB516B40834EC8AA6CE542DFD7EF6B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (6) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2E61F11BC76465D86EE4F495977AE9F"> <paragraph id="H9433BE7EA96B47089A0E3285F897E389" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Authority to seek review of decisions</header> <subparagraph id="H7AE2C1C3AD89486DAAC38CD7E638354F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>FISA court decisions</header> <clause id="H715453869DFD404EB441D977A8199B40" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Petition</header><text>Following issuance of an order under this Act by the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court, an amicus curiae appointed under paragraph (2) may petition the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court to certify for review to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review a question of law pursuant to subsection (j).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF3D46A2AB2774E35A75A7B272C37A9CF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Written statement of reasons</header><text>If the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court denies a petition under this subparagraph, the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court shall provide for the record a written statement of the reasons for the denial.</text></clause> <clause id="HFD4E757FA2F74D10ADEEFEE14FABBF46" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>Upon certification of any question of law pursuant to this subparagraph, the Court of Review shall appoint the amicus curiae to assist the Court of Review in its consideration of the certified question, unless the Court of Review issues a finding that such appointment is not appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD345E78F04B04EBF9B189C3316B4F1D2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>FISA Court of Review decisions</header><text>An amicus curiae appointed under paragraph (2) may petition the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review to certify for review to the Supreme Court of the United States any question of law pursuant to section 1254(2) of title 28, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H88017F913D0F41FFB1A4072CDBEC0CE1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Declassification of referrals</header><text>For purposes of section 602, a petition filed under subparagraph (A) or (B) of this paragraph and all of its content shall be considered a decision, order, or opinion issued by the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court or the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review described in paragraph (2) of section 602(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H022BF05EA1F54D80BEBA7EC88126E50C" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Access to information</header> 
<subparagraph id="HAAF71F0AEBBC415B8D8A43B538E35BE6" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application and materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i)(6) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(i)(6)</external-xref>) is amended by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H37CCAF1460DC49C4A28D6611783D94D6"> <subparagraph id="H45B7CDF6CF85422CA158D0F13CC53A1C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header> <clause id="HDB0A3636DFCE4F6A90DEFD4A20B326B0" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Right of amicus</header><text>If a court established under subsection (a) or (b) appoints an amicus curiae under paragraph (2), the amicus curiae—</text> 
<subclause id="H92DED56F54AC486EAA5FE7799F687349" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall have access, to the extent such information is available to the Government, to—</text> <item id="HE2FEFFCDE4674E6C9B4245257D7438B1" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the application, certification, petition, motion, and other information and supporting materials, including any information described in section 901, submitted to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court in connection with the matter in which the amicus curiae has been appointed, including access to any relevant legal precedent (including any such precedent that is cited by the Government, including in such an application);</text></item> 
<item id="H573695C1C828437AA89DC0C06001D639" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an unredacted copy of each relevant decision made by the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court or the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review in which the court decides a question of law, without regard to whether the decision is classified; and</text></item> <item id="H7E930960279348D78281BDEEB3670BD6" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>any other information or materials that the court determines are relevant to the duties of the amicus curiae; and </text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3A93E6F839D94087BB65545B922715CD" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may make a submission to the court requesting access to any other particular materials or information (or category of materials or information) that the amicus curiae believes to be relevant to the duties of the amicus curiae.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HCC81B4D9176D4341B6018008D28EC6DD" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Supporting documentation regarding accuracy</header><text>The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court, upon the motion of an amicus curiae appointed under paragraph (2) or upon its own motion, may require the Government to make available the supporting documentation described in section 902.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74E82247898F446F90AEAD96DC521E98" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification of access to certain information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i)(6) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(i)(6)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <clause id="HA8B6E83094634AF4A6D976AD405E9567" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>may</quote> and inserting <quote>shall</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCCD7EBACC825499F96ACA9CC18E79CA6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (C) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBDEA7BE87C0449B9962E4A739BE7BFD1"> <subparagraph id="H9BC077B6810841928C6006B7084DD046" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>An amicus curiae designated or appointed by the court shall have access, to the extent such information is available to the Government, to unredacted copies of each opinion, order, transcript, pleading, or other document of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court and the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review, including, if the individual is eligible for access to classified information, any classified documents, information, and other materials or proceedings.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H186A4B19FA4B48DF987A5378C34D7B63" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act and shall apply with respect to proceedings under the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) that take place on or after, or are pending on, that date.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H99544B1ED09C418FBDA1313C1D9E5E90"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application for an order approving electronic surveillance</header> <subsection id="HA8BC3DEF3F634D7A8E72A3E758351125"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Disclosure requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 104(a) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1804">50 U.S.C. 1804(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6E57310944BF43AB8BE41B9295010456"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)(E)(ii), by inserting before the semicolon at the end <quote>(and a description of such techniques)</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84829B23CCF44F1B996DCB39669A4158"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H23AC58E21DEC4362BC955419DC829791"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote> ; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB61B7815132F48A7ADE0A3F3B70E9BE6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (9) the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3ACE6748089748EFAC81551DD44BB36F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H2DC52F660F8D48C0BD10CDDC01CA0970"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">all information material to the application, including any information that tends to rebut—</text> <subparagraph id="HC783563E40544065A407180D5358A61B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any allegation set forth in the application; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F7F90D2B0E14E67B73EF589C6800AE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the existence of probable cause to believe that—</text> <clause id="H0EECF7D6A9D744B28B042383E6C38439"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the target of the electronic surveillance is a foreign power or an agent of a foreign power; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H647DE0F52558407EB3DD1A997BE545BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each of the facilities or places at which the electronic surveillance is directed is being used, or is about to be used, by a foreign power or an agent of a foreign power.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5923D35E52654CBA8408D392943F2312"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of certain information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 104 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1804">50 U.S.C. 1804</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE1C5A305EBA847F09E4F7EB6527ECFB9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H29A803D4E46C466DBD82AEDB901E1D0D" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The statement of facts and circumstances under subsection (a)(3) may only include information obtained from the content of a media source or information gathered by a political campaign if—</text> <paragraph id="H633D6FDA768D40CB9E089759F7CF3476" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such information is disclosed in the application as having been so obtained or gathered; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3920FE8A50B44B5FBB0EDE6BAB1CD556"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such information is not the sole source of the information used to justify the applicant’s belief described in subsection (a)(3). </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HC52BD76D3FDF446E93B4D201082CD1E7" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation on issuance of order</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 105(a) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1805">50 U.S.C. 1805(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF3E96B5933F24D93ABE4FCF5AA7A1094" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2244C3357F1442D9933DF95F05099927" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H66CDC0EAD5994008A28CD6759A4D0DF5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H36186F46271440CC9AE476B3BE918332" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HE34CF99973804ADBA1F9B03A1AEF3D0F" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the statement of facts and circumstances under subsection (a)(3) may only include information obtained from the content of a media source or information gathered by a political campaign if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H693F2932AF144149AD7831EF7EE00B26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such information is disclosed in the application as having been so obtained or gathered; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H15C271664D564BC1A094DA3871E7A168"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such information is not the sole source of the information used to justify the applicant’s belief described in subsection (a)(3). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HFE1FF8DEB0B84360B4BE8454030C268C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Public disclosure and declassification of certain documents</header> 
<subsection id="H8D3AD53CD5954531B231EA36713A8B95"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 601(c)(1) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1871">50 U.S.C. 1871(c)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including declassified copies that have undergone review under section 602</quote> before <quote>; and</quote>. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HD1D73407897B459AA7126423A47755FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timeline for declassification review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 602(a) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1872">50 U.S.C. 1872(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H360B3863291540A5803E4B1151E29FA6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>shall conduct a declassification review</quote> the following: <quote>, to be concluded not later than 45 days after the commencement of such review,</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H58BFBEFC138448A2B51F59D6893E5588"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>a significant construction or interpretation of any provision of law</quote> the following: <quote>or results in a change of application of any provision of this Act or a novel application of any provision of this Act</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB928899125174540A1ABBEF2991A4767"><enum>8.</enum><header>Transcriptions of proceedings; Attendance of certain Congressional officials at certain proceedings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 103(c) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA17DFE9F002E46F980466DC1D0A84CF8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Proceedings under this Act</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>(1) Proceedings under this Act</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77B7A7B03E8047B185BE06E926304652"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>including applications made and orders granted</quote> and inserting <quote>including applications made, orders granted, and transcriptions of proceedings,</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF5B8F86F3ED46249F122C60D4A6EB5C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H641C1725614C4756A26DCC33E32960AB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HEF7B3F60DBA943AF82FE46E0CDFE07F5" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The chair and ranking minority member of each of the congressional intelligence committees and of the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate shall be entitled to attend any proceeding of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court or any proceeding of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review. Each person entitled to attend a proceeding pursuant to this paragraph may designate not more than 2 Members of Congress and not more than 2 staff members of such committee to attend on their behalf, pursuant to such procedures as the Attorney General, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence may establish. Not later than 45 days after any such proceeding, a copy of any application made, order granted, or transcription of the proceeding shall be made available for review to each person who is entitled to attend a proceeding pursuant to this paragraph or who is designated under this paragraph. Terms used in this paragraph have the meanings given such terms in section 701(b).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HB998536F5FD043678528956C5CD1589D" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>9.</enum><header>Annual audit of FISA compliance by Inspector General</header> <subsection id="H3B0A6D3BF3A846E8A954287A8299F8B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VI of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1871">50 U.S.C. 1871 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB10342776E8F4264A5F010ED58D32E50" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H787FE9667FF5464D8DCBED1B3FEAABA4"><enum>605.</enum><header>Annual audit of FISA compliance by Inspector General</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning with the first calendar year that begins after the effective date of this section, by not later than June 30th of that year and each year thereafter, the Inspector General of the Department of Justice shall conduct an audit on alleged violations and failures to comply with the requirements of this Act and any procedures established pursuant to this Act, and submit a report thereon to the congressional intelligence committees and the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HF58A23DCBDB14293AE39D53040592637"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFD722F6FF22C42DCBA3ECBEBB5C8635F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">605. Annual audit of FISA compliance by Inspector General.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4C054DCA1FF24216A9A3D96580166F03"><enum>10.</enum><header>Reporting on accuracy and completeness of applications</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 603 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1873">50 U.S.C. 1873</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H9B3781A5FDC349A08BC1156C9F2609CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA52E6A00E46842D481E3A643071B9254"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (F) as subparagraphs (C) through (G) respectively; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H41430309A86B487EA1BAE798916B4FD8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1D0C1A3C40CF4277B590CA0EDC5717C6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H17EC2318DBCC48A0B001002727FEF3C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of the accuracy and completeness of such applications and certifications submitted;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA82C57F6B0434DCB9899CA7A43710002"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2), by striking <quote>subparagraph (F)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (G)</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H90A3BB5642844067B77CB17AEA5B2655"><enum>11.</enum><header>Annual report of the Federal Bureau of Investigation</header> 
<subsection id="HF2674BFCC4544DEDA6600EEA09D7E020"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VI of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1871">50 U.S.C. 1871 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0F12AADCBF50451DB0BCE191305DBDA8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H5DFCE076C7DF454A96387F9AC17B357F"><enum>606.</enum><header>Annual report of the Federal Bureau of Investigation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation shall submit to the congressional intelligence committees and the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5C0AF04D43F044D8B5357B1B36EC491E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a report on disciplinary activities taken by the Director to address violations of the requirements of law or the procedures established under this Act, including a comprehensive account of disciplinary investigations, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H40D1D40DBC534BF0970E18F636FA6BDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all such investigations ongoing as of the date the report is submitted;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1A321EE6393E4E9382F9E8C78DDD9E3F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the adjudications of such investigations when concluded; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD572CC1994BE4367A5E45E71D8F7982D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>disciplinary actions taken as a result of such adjudications; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2A55C2BACFF4243BFF18D7E5A2F1093" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a report on the conduct of queries conducted under section 702 for the preceding year using a United States person query term, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HFC42194BDE22439BBED4B74482257863" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of such queries conducted;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H605E5C65AF5D4E10808EDCCCDBE7277B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>what terms were used;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3742C427211A4E109321707C21AAF62B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of warrants issued and denied under section 702(f)(1); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H35DD150ABBE34BFFA4D0042A08BBE257" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of times exceptions were alleged under 702(f)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HAD24651806924AC3A92AA2521A6C6AEF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDBFECD04747C4B46A7E5FEBFCABFC3BA" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">606. Annual report of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC0387193E5EB48C28F13DA9E021B5CBB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>12.</enum><header>Extension of title VII of FISA; expiration of FISA authorities; effective dates</header> 
<subsection id="H9602F600EC304A7980F3EFB22FA6E212"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 403(b) of the FISA Amendments Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/261">Public Law 110–261</external-xref>; 122 Stat. 2474) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H219E3534FEB2412BB62F810A5C41D7F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H643013A8DAEE4AC68AA4790F490DAED9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>December 31, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2026</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H199B485B77024212A2FE20F11B81B4D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, as amended by section 101(a) and by the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017,</quote> and inserting <quote>, as most recently amended,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF7E14947FBDF43A8B7C7B5152DD96444"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2) in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>December 31, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2026</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6D8AD49843C34AF8A7B113E64BB43FD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming Amendments</header><text>Section 404(b) of the FISA Amendments Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/261">Public Law 110–261</external-xref>; 122 Stat. 2476), is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H585F4AE5891849CA8AE383B67922BAB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H7F0C7CFB82D948A3A75DD5A33C283238"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">December 31, 2023</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">December 31, 2026</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H03C5952523E649B7AB2728826D5C3197"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>, as amended by section 101(a) and by the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017,</quote> and inserting <quote>, as most recently amended,</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0A1DAD9C236B45B69F9F2B8F730E9B44"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>, as amended by section 101(a) and by the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017,</quote> and inserting <quote>, as most recently amended,</quote>; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9D41FD6FE5524FBDBE0383F49FDB3886"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE6DF7A251DA3466290E0A50F99B157C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, as added by section 101(a) and amended by the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017,</quote> both places it appears and inserting <quote>, as added by section 101(a) and as most recently amended,</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H70A3CF23177841409A022CF6072611C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>, as amended by section 101(a) and by the FISA Amendments Reauthorization Act of 2017,</quote> and inserting <quote>, as most recently amended,</quote> both places it appears. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HAEC5F1BA510F404C8A89566410BC85C5"><enum>13.</enum><header>Criminal penalties for violations of FISA</header> <subsection id="H0BCEEBD3A13F421F899F255E4FF4B96C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 109 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1809">50 U.S.C. 1809</external-xref>) is amended as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H59D37B1800B141B99F6A9D9695D79D2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Additional offenses</header><text>In subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H02339D9A8C70437F9D428C67BFF6B197"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>intentionally</quote>; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DE1FD4F8E1741D9AFA533AEAC9F4486"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="H84BF1B51219D4507895FA04409B6D89C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>intentionally</quote> before <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H823D1BED246441ADB9DD986B86634BC7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFD15D6C3C4B74BC3A771F1A2837B2A53"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<clause id="H7885B77B2AE94230B01D4F6B76DB7D0E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>intentionally</quote> before <quote>disclose or uses</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H771B1F655BC14BFCB3D67ADE69EC0872"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9A2F417FC31F4BC0A6C9487D325E6A25"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC382EEEA800441FFB3DB4E69569F6383" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HDE399F82AB054903B7D01C51BAD012A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly submits any document to or makes any false statement before the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court or the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review, knowing such document or statement to contain—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDF6A35BC0C87408CA84B0CB00177D89B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a false material declaration; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H084C1B5B74E049CC89874157B19B12F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a material omission; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE119E4079BBC4619BC1A5BCC4253C47D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly discloses the existence of an application for an order authorizing surveillance under this title, or any information contained therein, to any person not authorized to receive such information.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D54A039DF7643E3A5674E49D917A12D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enhanced penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In subsection (c), is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEEA37041480848098450EA897D7B1CF3" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H78474A717E524C1684096E62B6EEDA72"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an offense under any of paragraphs (1) through (4) of subsection (a), the offense is punishable by a fine of not more than $10,000 or imprisonment for not more than 8 years, or both. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCAC72FFFFC7D46E9BCFBFF39ED8C23D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act may not be construed to interfere with the enforcement of section 798 of title 18, United States Code, or any other provision of law regarding the unlawful disclosure of classified information.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEF7BADE04FDD4B85941EFD03CCF21563"><enum>14.</enum><header>Contempt power of FISC and FISC–R</header> 
<subsection id="HF90654D410224141AA99EE2A113DF36B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/21">Chapter 21</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA33022A663C14E9B8C6B29C7C1E8C751"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 402, by inserting after <quote>any district court of the United States</quote> the following: <quote>, the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court, the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review,</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB618CF9FBAD342089735608E9DED80B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H77DD274EA204485FB89A1C0B8C8DF8BB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H53970693F349433C93650968FB284547"><enum>404.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this chapter—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDA4AA12C3EE947A28271C880A408B482"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>court of the United States</term> includes the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court or the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H554F0BACA82F4C50B4E5DC162D2570CD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the terms <term>Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court</term> and <term>Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 601(e) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAC4ACE46BB78481681AA04A6C5EE8D78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for such chapter is amended by inserting after the item pertaining to section 403 the following: </text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H2FFCE9666347457095155F832ADF31CC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">404. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD05ECE33F7E945F6B2B1317D494C0FDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment, and annually thereafter the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court and the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court of Review (as such terms are defined in section 601(e) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978) shall jointly submit to Congress a report on the exercise of authority under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/21">chapter 21</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, by such courts during the previous year. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD952703F7A9F495BA33BCBB14249DCD8"><enum>15.</enum><header>Increased penalties for civil actions</header> 
<subsection id="H57C8D9045706454B93DC659A7DFA1BDD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increased penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 110(a) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1810">50 U.S.C. 1810(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4A1A11B3C7EC495EAF9FBCBD8F1FE3EF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H5C650555DE674EE4B8BD6D693828EB6D" indent="paragraph"><enum>(a)</enum><text>actual damages, but not less than liquidated damages equal to the greater of—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCA938248F9494D60A22F8FB8AF75F8FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if the aggrieved person is a United States person, $10,000 or $1,000 per day for each day of violation; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2DAF0639067A4DD18CBD17EE9EC8EE43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for any other aggrieved person, $1,000 or $100 per day for each day of violation;</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD50A7D091984CBF9C170AE974F0307C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 is amended by inserting after section 110 the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD907FB52505C4EB3B533E3C13F44A5AF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H6CBC65CB5F7F4D43B02A79AF5373C1A0"><enum>110A.</enum><header>Reporting requirements for civil actions</header> <subsection id="H17C8DF1DC0784FB3B455ED63C649D637"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a court finds that a person has violated this Act in a civil action under section 110, the head of the agency that employs that person shall report to Congress on the administrative action taken against that person pursuant to section 607 or any other provision of law.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD9C0020726F54B599F366E111DEE544E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>FISC</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a court finds that a person has violated this Act in a civil action under section 110, the head of the agency that employs that person shall report the name of such person to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court. The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court shall maintain a list of each person about whom it received a report under this subsection. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HFC217191D9384366AF30DB3C89178223" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>16.</enum><header>Accountability procedures for incidents relating to queries conducted by the Federal Bureau of Investigation</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42E027BF973A4534AF7D4939A29B9E61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title VII of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881">50 U.S.C. 1881 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block id="HD7B170A7A6864597B750CCE4699DC6F3" style="OLC" act-name=""> 
<section id="HCB87F03099034C89B9040ABC3319F980"><enum>709.</enum><header>Accountability procedures for incidents relating to queries conducted by the Federal Bureau of Investigation</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5176B32C0B3F4600B9F4D3208B1B07CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation shall establish procedures to hold employees of the Federal Bureau of Investigation accountable for violations of law, guidance, and procedure governing queries of information acquired pursuant to section 702.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCEC601AC93844D09A3FF23657917B906"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The procedures established under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4ED88D2C2D324AC891B9A1A58D82BE2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Centralized tracking of individual employee performance incidents involving negligent violations of law, guidance, and procedure described in subsection (a), over time. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H765B7D9704174075B901BB36359B46FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Escalating consequences for such incidents, including—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A95BC3382734090B24F58558F5F7BD1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consequences for initial incidents, including, at a minimum—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC29A14DEC4B4E828283390A08BF3B96"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">suspension of access to information acquired under this Act; and </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5167932A62914037836775EFF68D6C2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">documentation of the incident in the personnel file of each employee responsible for the violation; and </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6163B3EB510145C091BAD6DF5FB31A7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consequences for subsequent incidents, including, at a minimum—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9312A1569FF54DB9823564E8489A8CEE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">possible indefinite suspension of access to information acquired under this Act;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H136455F3B684408380A62EE72897E39E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reassignment of each employee responsible for the violation; and </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9795E32B0CBE4E6CAF4FF04D94D8631A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">referral of the incident to the Inspection Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for review of potentially reckless conduct.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEF4D9896A5E494788BDD8094F7A44C5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clarification of requirements for referring intentional misconduct and reckless conduct to the Inspection Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for investigation and disciplinary action by the Office of Professional Responsibility of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H778704A99FC84189AD95CF685EB36168"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for such Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 708 the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3CFC9CF3E0242EFB96DB01828EF357C"> <toc> <toc-entry level="section" bold="off">709. Accountability procedures for incidents relating to queries conducted by the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B15BF005F0D4D81ABA89D24A58E32A4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report required</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60CDF7E41AC64B1198506100BC2A3ED0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation shall submit to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate and to the congressional intelligence committees (as such term is defined in section 801 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1885">50 U.S.C. 1885</external-xref>)) a report detailing the procedures established under section 709 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978, as added by subsection (a). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H132212D5024A4F7595157134341BE476" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Federal Bureau of Investigation shall submit to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate and to the congressional intelligence committees (as such term is defined in section 801 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1885">50 U.S.C. 1885</external-xref>)) a report on any disciplinary actions taken pursuant to the procedures established under section 709 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978, as added by subsection (a), including a description of the circumstances surrounding each such disciplinary action, and the results of each such disciplinary action. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BF325DBE6A647F7B9FCB5332C8A06D3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The reports required under paragraphs (1) and (2) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex to the extent necessary to protect sources and methods. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF3545ED60E8B4D14A530835F44478458"><enum>17.</enum><header>Agency procedures to ensure compliance</header> 
<subsection id="H24AA543382A745E09A56F552173CB916"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agency procedures to ensure compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VI of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1871">50 U.S.C. 1871 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2CFB33B929A14F23B8FF7C94524D418E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H3FC966E664694A648C148E3DE1F7FD65"><enum>607.</enum><header>Agency procedures to ensure compliance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The head of each Federal department or agency authorized to acquire foreign intelligence information under this Act shall establish procedures—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1A9726F47A424C43B168BC048EBB1348"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">setting forth clear rules on what constitutes a violation of this Act by an officer or employee of that department or agency; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C44FC57ABA5497CA90BF09E4A8609FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for taking appropriate adverse personnel action against any officer or employee of the department or agency who engages in such a violation, including more severe adverse actions for any subsequent violation.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H15F71E132B2D4B5B941F3D2A511C278A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDD77108F014A47458380095EFA908BF9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">607. Agency procedures to ensure compliance.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0672380485CF49B68EFAA5ECED9680DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each Federal department or agency that is required to establish procedures under section 607 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 shall report to Congress on such procedures.</text></subsection></section> 
<section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H72898799BF5D4FC3842F61407A1F95C6"><enum>18.</enum><header>Protection of records held by data brokers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B595B570E1D4D0A9130597C4FFDAF52"> <subsection id="H0597B49C1E4A474FBBFC96A51FE2AAD8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on obtaining in exchange for anything of value certain records and information by law enforcement and intelligence agencies</header> <paragraph id="H3855D0C4B41E43C8A0553A7C1090BF93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5BAEC66C0A0C47639E40D3777C9EC0F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>covered customer or subscriber record</term> means a covered record that is— </text> <clause id="H2A0711951817495A8992F8807D7DE23B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>disclosed to a third party by— </text> 
<subclause id="HD94F05D3F579483A94BC6B90F7AEB308"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a provider of an electronic communication service to the public or a provider of a remote computing service of which the covered person with respect to the covered record is a subscriber or customer; or </text></subclause> <subclause id="HE20C16C840EF4975B5868607E8909A8B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an intermediary service provider that delivers, stores, or processes communications of such covered person; </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HC4D3746CD74C4FA4BE4EF007EF4801CE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>collected by a third party from an online account of a covered person; or</text></clause> <clause id="H85EE51437BE94D9CA09546CB3DF3A870"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>collected by a third party from or about an electronic device of a covered person;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF63E3D3181F64187BB1790F19A7D78B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered person</term> means—</text> <clause id="H979666D4663F415A8B0DB910DE27F496"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a person who is located inside the United States; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDAE2C7949C8A4C16B4609EB759DF3AD4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a person— </text> <subclause id="HD9A0FC53224548F1A8C1E370705F1B61"><enum>(I)</enum><text>who is located outside the United States or whose location cannot be determined; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD1BEDABC3B4D4B7089CB8E9A6D6F88CE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>who is a United States person, as defined in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>);</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8FCA7C1FEC442F2922C470B5EC1E060"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>covered record</term> means a record or other information that— </text> 
<clause id="H222051632F254723A60B24B7B378E5A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>pertains to a covered person; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC30E750453D540FEA859C6DE48817192"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is— </text> 
<subclause id="H696B7F3B23814276BF063271F196530D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a record or other information described in the matter preceding paragraph (1) of subsection (c); </text></subclause> <subclause id="HF8DD10075612485CB77E80E34B126579"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the contents of a communication; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H06D2620BFF3B4C6D856E4A305229CE39"><enum>(III)</enum><text>location information; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H138D90DF43E94B669BBB506DA89AA247"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the term <term>electronic device</term> has the meaning given the term <term>computer</term> in section 1030(e); </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97021749730749E8B48E22081600D049"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the term <term>illegitimately obtained information</term> means a covered record that— </text> <clause id="H4E1512DC067143D5AC36945517F66367"><enum>(i)</enum><text>was obtained— </text> 
<subclause id="H10EC99F6216445F0AE5D644152504ADE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>from a provider of an electronic communication service to the public or a provider of a remote computing service in a manner that— </text> <item id="HB8E6AADCEDD34649A59E36A9AEF96B38"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>violates the service agreement between the provider and customers or subscribers of the provider; or</text></item> 
<item id="HBB393BD129194A419791210C7DCA4AE1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is inconsistent with the privacy policy of the provider; </text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HB7D0678A34E14925AB382CC5FF064C40"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by deceiving the covered person whose covered record was obtained; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9A8FF3F2ACF645C9A32595FB8C4764C2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>through the unauthorized accessing of an electronic device or online account; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC1E6E7ED900E4988AE694483CA682798"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was—</text> 
<subclause id="HB010CE08FD5C48AC84264D3A26AE95CC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>obtained from a provider of an electronic communication service to the public, a provider of a remote computing service, or an intermediary service provider; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="HC5715E6C3E4541FCB382F77FE32E0F1A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>collected, processed, or shared in violation of a contract relating to the covered record; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5CBF7F767ABF430EA7460372243E2DD4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the term <term>intelligence community</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95F55184D3844553BE1C7FA8AB07C52E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the term <term>location information</term> means information derived or otherwise calculated from the transmission or reception of a radio signal that reveals the approximate or actual geographic location of a customer, subscriber, or device; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE95B5AB9BBE6471ABF0CA140D8A6DCAF"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the term <term>obtain in exchange for anything of value</term> means to obtain by purchasing, to receive in connection with services being provided for consideration, or to otherwise obtain in exchange for consideration, including an access fee, service fee, maintenance fee, or licensing fee; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDFC119249042460894467E84B75A8298"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the term <term>online account</term> means an online account with an electronic communication service to the public or remote computing service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2BCD7737A5094D09982CB1D7EDC516BF"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the term <term>pertain</term>, with respect to a person, means—</text> <clause id="HA5E75821687D4CD49F43B13943B16F46"><enum>(i)</enum><text>information that is linked to the identity of a person; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6DD51C31D66946A897B34AFD501A756C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>information— </text> <subclause id="HE5FB21CD4F2E4DD4B1C608B7B8D10C61"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that has been anonymized to remove links to the identity of a person; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HABE714FC7117451FAC40F5C4B59B6AF3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that, if combined with other information, could be used to identify a person; and </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFB6D211267D4480A9225E164727BAAD"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the term <term>third party</term> means a person who—</text> 
<clause id="H828289E107D5464CB518748F0FAF9A25"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not a governmental entity; and</text></clause> <clause id="HDDA76B79D77B4E3CA770B6C9ED8CC583"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in connection with the collection, disclosure, obtaining, processing, or sharing of the covered record at issue, was not acting as— </text> 
<subclause id="HA5FF90C4B16648C1AC53AD0F0557E1B0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a provider of an electronic communication service to the public; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H560EF0F81D924EE3BAED482DF4EEB9C4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a provider of a remote computing service.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74951DC9BF604E6EBAC46B1CF91E8F8A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H81A35403BE384694B2896EB7C01438E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A law enforcement agency of a governmental entity and an element of the intelligence community may not obtain from a third party in exchange for anything of value a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8988CADDE85F4622930657B5D343426F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Indirectly acquired records and information</header><text>The limitation under subparagraph (A) shall apply without regard to whether the third party possessing the covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information is the third party that initially obtained or collected, or is the third party that initially received the disclosure of, the covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD75BB4AB063A4AB7996D430CCADE47AC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limit on sharing between agencies</header><text>An agency of a governmental entity that is not a law enforcement agency or an element of the intelligence community may not provide to a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or an element of the intelligence community a covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information that was obtained from a third party in exchange for anything of value.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C51CEF0BDF144B8A08CA7D4F63BE55A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition on use as evidence</header><text>A covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information obtained by or provided to a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or an element of the intelligence community in violation of paragraph (2) or (3), and any evidence derived therefrom, may not be received in evidence in any trial, hearing, or other proceeding in or before any court, grand jury, department, officer, agency, regulatory body, legislative committee, or other authority of the United States, a State, or a political subdivision thereof.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2089F401A7C44F98A946D578D6DB371B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Minimization procedures</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5DC35216EE154EEE9588F4316C58F76C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General shall adopt specific procedures that are reasonably designed to minimize the acquisition and retention, and prohibit the dissemination, of information pertaining to a covered person that is acquired in violation of paragraph (2) or (3).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE59CDC7C15B84E20B40F743AE6B24BB0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use by agencies</header><text>If a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or element of the intelligence community acquires information pertaining to a covered person in violation of paragraph (2) or (3), the law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or element of the intelligence community shall minimize the acquisition and retention, and prohibit the dissemination, of the information in accordance with the procedures adopted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HBA08442A14774C12A7A5F0B132EDE284"><enum>19.</enum><header>Required disclosure</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2703 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB7229D0FA604DF1A12A23A432837092"> <subsection id="H8F4F6A99D70044ECA7B07E89D12FEA6A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Covered customer or subscriber records and illegitimately obtained information</header> <paragraph id="H75A31A8558AA4B94ADC0468C4278ACFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>covered customer or subscriber record</term>, <term>illegitimately obtained information</term>, and <term>third party</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2702(e).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBA27977968CD4AEAAC017265A1A1656E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Unless a governmental entity obtains an order in accordance with paragraph (3), the governmental entity may not require a third party to disclose a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information if a court order would be required for the governmental entity to require a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public to disclose such a covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information that is a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6ED062C104F94D3C8DFDC6A66EB2A637"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Orders</header> <subparagraph id="H9F2153E438C346E2A643EE8C0D86AD9D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court may only issue an order requiring a third party to disclose a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information on the same basis and subject to the same limitations as would apply to a court order to require disclosure by a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public of a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA553CD16C0454F808E67B1CC0C22CC70"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Standard</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), a court shall apply the most stringent standard under Federal statute or the Constitution of the United States that would be applicable to a request for a court order to require a comparable disclosure by a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public of a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H06A5DCEEE15E4D0C899862729B0F214C"><enum>20.</enum><header>Intermediary service providers</header> <subsection id="H986243835E94426AB2CFEBDCFE48E36A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 2711 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0A52B3328B514DB08AA81805AD7D37F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84A83D93ECED4C8A86D66E6AFD3F4112"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD532632A4A164E01AF432727E73D7783"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF672EF24A01E40C4A5FB1E1367AFFCCA"> <paragraph id="H7C2161F0FFBB4BDCB2A3ECA514192AF6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>intermediary service provider</term> means an entity or facilities owner or operator that directly or indirectly delivers, stores, or processes communications for or on behalf of a provider of electronic communication service to the public or a provider of remote computing service.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H33FFB2FEF9E5412A9CB05C5B3F090F14"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Section 2702(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HCE53C36B3624483FA8F7944E8DDD4AB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C65352EAFE44A108FD3B30DA028DD32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB233A18CFBD4F08A73E7A96B4FD8B20"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H306D16314D704B80A0BDEE1485E6A3E5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0FE8267E46A74A4EACC3E9FB36743690"> <paragraph id="HE17679DB50DF489E9F5BB8904BDC6E16"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an intermediary service provider shall not knowingly divulge—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8D4713F40AC142E9B420A09080CD4DC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to any person or entity the contents of a communication while in electronic storage by that provider; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9A140D254D184E90BE09BD61A0CDF75A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to any governmental entity a record or other information pertaining to a subscriber to or customer of, a recipient of a communication from a subscriber to or customer of, or the sender of a communication to a subscriber to or customer of, the provider of electronic communication service to the public or the provider of remote computing service for, or on behalf of, which the intermediary service provider directly or indirectly delivers, transmits, stores, or processes communications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H435B05BA8DB04A08BF06FB697A03D6E6"><enum>21.</enum><header>Limits on surveillance conducted for foreign intelligence purposes other than under the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978</header> 
<subsection id="HD4D8D175D7A442E297A671F6FA43B36A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2511(2)(f) of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8D93E199285946AA96C6266C74DC5972"> <subsection id="HEF0C1FE8B6F946F182AB527FB1586352"><enum>(f)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1CF75416AF224EE3B97EC71441C8B150"><enum>(i)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H40D13D8596614BF78F71480206C20892"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Nothing contained in this chapter, chapter 121 or 206 of this title, or section 705 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be deemed to affect an acquisition or activity described in clause (B) that is carried out utilizing a means other than electronic surveillance, as defined in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE72DD4D8FCE442A6A6DCF794086D09C2" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An acquisition or activity described in this clause is—</text> <clause id="H86DF695E4A934A5D8E87042F865BF181"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an acquisition by the United States Government of foreign intelligence information from international or foreign communications that—</text> 
<subclause id="H9115C18298C347B686E687DC2228DDE7"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is acquired pursuant to express statutory authority; or </text></subclause> <subclause id="HF982CEBB18FF4136A76C8AD0040FF0FB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only includes information of persons who are not United States persons and are located outside the United States; or </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HAF0E8556B1B244C98DC10208BA25D213"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a foreign intelligence activity involving a foreign electronic communications system that— </text> <subclause id="H12CF9AEADA724404816127144E31FCC5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is conducted pursuant to express statutory authority; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE6809874A59B4137867D4E87FF8ECFE7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only involves the acquisition by the United States Government of information of persons who are not United States persons and are located outside the United States.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D490982A63C4999A0DB47049E9B7836" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The procedures in this chapter, chapter 121, and the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be the exclusive means by which electronic surveillance, as defined in section 101 of such Act, and the interception of domestic wire, oral, and electronic communications may be conducted.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2F8ADF6F7E8347AD9EB8E655126353F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to communications records</header><text>The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be the exclusive means by which electronic communications transactions records, call detail records, or other information from communications of United States persons or persons inside the United States are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes inside the United States or from a person or entity located in the United States that provides telecommunications, electronic communication, or remote computing services.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H072829165D8E4F32B08E2BECD10F3B6E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to location information, web browsing history, and internet search history</header> <paragraph id="H1975E9897CCF4506A87A0FBA01647E31"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>location information</term> has the meaning given that term in subsection (e) of section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8E92552F0B7F4B70BFE343ED3B98A57E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusive means</header><text>Title I and sections 303, 304, 703, 704, and 705 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>, 1823, 1824, 1881b, 1881c, 1881d) shall be the exclusive means by which location information, web browsing history, and internet search history of United States persons or persons inside the United States are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes inside the United States or from a person or entity located in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0CBAE82FCAD44E1FA92F8B1907A1E3B2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to fourth amendment-Protected information</header><text>Title I and sections 303, 304, 703, 704, and 705 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>, 1823, 1824, 1881b, 1881c, 1881d) shall be the exclusive means by which any information, records, data, or tangible things are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes from a person or entity located in the United States if the compelled production of such information, records, data, or tangible things would require a warrant for law enforcement purposes.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEF574B9DA1A54CB3B4A32ADFBE7B02E4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>United States person</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>). </text></subsection></section> <section id="H19517FEF99BC4D768B07552055F88799"><enum>22.</enum><header>Limit on civil immunity for providing information, facilities, or technical assistance to the Government absent a court order</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2511(2)(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5F26ED9747A54C5B83630745046BE4A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (ii), by striking clause (B) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B6E8570A773449A98DC0998A5B33133"> <subparagraph id="H1E25D6C5411C4A4BBA39E2FB781C0DF4" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a certification in writing—</text> 
<clause id="H290A143F416C4B3199EAD1482B6374F0" indent="clause"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by a person specified in section 2518(7) or the Attorney General of the United States; </text></clause> <clause id="HA10764B3D13A4B20B480572133C9545A" indent="clause"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that the requirements for an emergency authorization to intercept a wire, oral, or electronic communication under section 2518(7) have been met; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE1D4CA8D124D4EF797946F71122D70B5" indent="clause"><enum>(III)</enum><text>that the specified assistance is required,</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H409BC62A499A418398D214BD3D9F0FEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (iii) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0B2D0D94F0C044CDB3E068E3E819D54B"> 
<clause id="HAC39ED1F462446768D8F375B9B42252E" indent="up3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>For assistance provided pursuant to a certification under subparagraph (ii)(B), the limitation on causes of action under the last sentence of the matter following subparagraph (ii)(B) shall only apply to the extent that the assistance ceased at the earliest of the time the application for a court order was denied, the time the communication sought was obtained, or 48 hours after the interception began.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDB2BF28507E4363870BC260CEB8B65A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>23.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prohibition on reverse targeting of United States persons and persons located in the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5BC2B612E0974A35BD4179353C1E3274"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7A52CB36690C460A96DAD5C42DF4362D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>may not intentionally</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0402135612544D7B82D8BBDE47C08356" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not—</text> <subparagraph id="HE42B8597C360457F8E77B54559AEA49A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">intentionally</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H40D5D92F836A4146B831BBC554C22399"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), as designated by subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, by striking <quote>if the purpose of such acquisition is to target a particular, known person reasonably believed to be in the United States;</quote> and inserting the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6F0ADFF2EF6D4C33992A74BE8E9E34E4" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if a significant purpose of such acquisition is to acquire the information of 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication, unless—</text> 
<clause id="H003B86868CBF4F0EB21608D86DB28393"><enum>(i)</enum> 
<subclause id="HB3F175E14321470AA009FE8EE567640A" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>there is a reasonable belief that an emergency exists involving an imminent threat of death or serious bodily harm to such United States person or person reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of acquisition or communication;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE76B48FCB9014BBDBAA278C81E704177" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the information is sought for the purpose of assisting that person; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H13D50F0C7D1B4CEA9818BB20A007B983" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a description of the targeting is provided to the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court and the appropriate committees of Congress in a timely manner; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H302ECFC1D6BA4EEE8D495243CF11D219"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the United States person or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication has provided consent to the targeting, or if such person is incapable of providing consent, a third party legally authorized to consent on behalf of such person has provided consent; and</text></clause> 
<subparagraph id="H8CB4F75E415742DE8F0074E93F1E85F9" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of information acquired pursuant to subparagraph (A)(i) or evidence derived from such targeting, be used, received in evidence, or otherwise disseminated in any investigation, trial, hearing, or other proceeding in or before any court, grand jury, department, office, agency, regulatory body, legislative committee, or other authority of the United States, a State, or political subdivision thereof, except in proceedings or investigations that arise from the threat that prompted the targeting;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC66673E29B2347059D91D290D272B32B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(1), by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H71ACDCC868EF44918C1F99D6E984DB8C"> 
<subparagraph id="H964BDCAD07A34A1087607095E33396AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE0EE8E78FB24E13A66AD91DE679EA8B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any acquisition authorized under subsection (a) is limited to targeting persons reasonably believed to be non-United States persons located outside the United States; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H74847A9E071C4366ADB70AB9D003F1B2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>except as provided in subsection (b)(2), a significant purpose of an acquisition is not to acquire the information of 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication; and</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC3AB97172B8348B8A97812C9E3934BC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (h)(2)(A)(i), by amending subclause (I) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8AB0EEB5B2C4E24A534BD83BF36F714"> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D9B5B2678864B1C81EACCD16DC5E325"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that—</text> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H653C2F9B5807402B8067E633319B5301"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an acquisition authorized under subsection (a) is limited to targeting persons reasonably believed to be non-United States persons located outside the United States; and</text></item> 
<item id="H33A481252B894AFDAEFEA66EBA4AE4B2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>except as provided in subsection (b)(2), a significant purpose of an acquisition is not to acquire the information of 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication; and</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5117071A04AE4508935AA69856750F7B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (j)(2)(B), by amending clause (i) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7316CAEE25734667A2589359C62D82EB"> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE08F60B081A4CD5854DF138939E71F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC6781B616D841CB80505A1DCDBC198A"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an acquisition authorized under subsection (a) is limited to targeting persons reasonably believed to be non-United States persons located outside the United States; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEC5070E986074C60822B17412C357512"><enum>(II)</enum><text>except as provided in subsection (b)(2), a significant purpose of an acquisition is not to acquire the information of 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be in the United States at the time of acquisition or communication; and</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H21215F56313349559B411DF766A4C0F4" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>24.</enum><header>Required disclosure of relevant information in foreign intelligence surveillance act of 1978 applications</header> <subsection id="H52F018F84E1D47EB9F41117C907FA493"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3891562980334BF7B52C6282AC876801" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<title id="H4EA0A73B1F614BDC92DDED8E5A48CCD3"><enum>IX</enum><header>Certification regarding accuracy procedures</header> 
<section id="H1E9F9EBEEA1D4C1F81D3B819E724FBF6"><enum>901.</enum><header>Certification regarding accuracy procedures</header> 
<subsection id="H7108A01A32CB4857BB927CE1DCB4B78D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of accuracy procedures</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>accuracy procedures</quote> means specific procedures, adopted by the Attorney General, to ensure that an application for a court order under this Act, including any application for renewal of an existing order, is accurate and complete, including procedures that ensure, at a minimum, that—</text> <paragraph id="H2CBF48110E0745B59F430149F0FC204A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the application reflects all information that might reasonably call into question the accuracy of the information or the reasonableness of any assessment in the application, or otherwise raises doubts about the requested findings;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H975D1CBDF8E34878BF9F316C51FE28B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the application reflects all material information that might reasonably call into question the reliability and reporting of any information from a confidential human source that is used in the application;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46FFD9A06704453F93CC26BA3A6CD16E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a complete file documenting each factual assertion in an application is maintained;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H36CBF792017D4E99AFD56F4848B8D410"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the applicant coordinates with the appropriate elements of the intelligence community (as defined in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>)), concerning any prior or existing relationship with the target of any surveillance, search, or other means of investigation, and discloses any such relationship in the application;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BB43ADE8B5040D0B29153A00A98218F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>before any application targeting a United States person is made, the applicant Federal officer shall document that the officer has collected and reviewed for accuracy and completeness supporting documentation for each factual assertion in the application; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA00DE1B6CABA44168C2D8178A7F800AA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the applicant Federal agency establish compliance and auditing mechanisms on an annual basis to assess the efficacy of the accuracy procedures that have been adopted and report such findings to the Attorney General.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H39BAF88437A8483EB375A4C57EDA9ED6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement and certification of accuracy procedures</header><text>Any Federal officer making an application for a court order under this Act shall include with the application—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8AE3547C24A149F89D849A0F026ECBF5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the accuracy procedures employed by the officer or the officer’s designee; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H939885885ECF40A095F45701D8899203"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a certification that the officer or the officer’s designee has collected and reviewed for accuracy and completeness—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE8638A7B21AA4DA89F36C5C09C17E907"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supporting documentation for each factual assertion contained in the application;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29A38DFD3EA74E7692CD263196082517"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all information that might reasonably call into question the accuracy of the information or the reasonableness of any assessment in the application, or otherwise raises doubts about the requested findings; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H90625C9B08EE493B83F85E25F07C80D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>all material information that might reasonably call into question the reliability and reporting of any information from any confidential human source that is used in the application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HABC2774405C34561BDECEAA5EFE034D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Necessary finding for court orders</header><text>A judge may not enter an order under this Act unless the judge finds, in addition to any other findings required under this Act, that the accuracy procedures described in the application for the order, as required under subsection (b)(1), are actually accuracy procedures as defined in this section.</text></subsection></section></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5CF16689A058432A882517D185FF128E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2FD5900B98DE4D65BDDD134B4A449146" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="title">TITLE IX—Certification regarding accuracy procedures</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 901. Certification regarding accuracy procedures.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H4E942B60F99D45838AD023AD56F442EE" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>25.</enum><header>Enhanced annual reports by Director of National Intelligence</header> <subsection id="HC3831A15C9CE445591F63F0B52B77F11"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 603 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1873">50 U.S.C. 1873(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H675F8B654B4647A087DA20A2904FB4FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(C), by striking the semicolon and inserting <quote>; and</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H90146C8265DB406786F8C1BBD3FDE25E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (3) through (7) as paragraphs (6) through (10), respectively;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6AF36D2D5A7C458EA9A96FE79FB76A8A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3BAE5831A738419BBEFCE7983D501D5D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H47197501FEA848F6A1A48EB45D8D50E0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the subject matter of each of the certifications provided under section 702(h);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82858599E3F54697BF46CEA6FF5255D6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>statistics revealing the number of persons and identifiers targeted under section 702(a), disaggregated by certification under which the person or identifier was targeted;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB869DE3FEBB64B92811CA1847FE0C50F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the total number of directives issued pursuant to section 702(i)(1), disaggregated by each type of electronic communication service provider described in subparagraphs (A) through (E) of section 701(b)(4);</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC433F904BD7C4845BFB4A27AA1F56902"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (9) (as redesignated in paragraph (2) of this subsection), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8DD26C99D43A483BBC4FAFD250433D4E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (10) (as redesignated in paragraph (2) of this subsection), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFEBA015D302E40B3B0B922693F3A2685"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3F87FC9312C846DDB10D77C5D6F9AA7B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HEC511FB238B243A5AC2242F19E265C54"><enum>(11)</enum> <subparagraph id="H13CD9BE4423849BAAB02911C42D3FC10" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection pursuant to section 702 containing the identities of United States persons regardless of whether the identities of the United States persons were openly included or masked;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H95498D2A8EDE444E8CBF837015BC1B60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection not authorized by this Act containing the identities of United States persons regardless of whether the identities of the United States persons were openly included or masked;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H91E198EE711C4FDDBEEECC8FF2A1ED3A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection pursuant to section 702 containing the identities of United States persons in which the identities of the United States persons were masked;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2811C126667A4126AE4036803B50AF70"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection not authorized by this Act containing the identities of United States persons in which the identities of the United States persons were masked;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H876039839FBE46ADAB0A8A3CFE58A6A4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection pursuant to section 702 containing the identities of United States persons in which the identities of the United States persons were openly included; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2B05735455F748A7A648C59C89D4A92B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the total number of disseminated intelligence reports derived from collection not authorized by this Act containing the identities of United States persons in which the identities of the United States persons were openly included;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1F3D9F5704EB458A8E473453C9BBC69C"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the number of queries conducted in an effort to find communications or information of or about 1 or more United States persons or persons reasonably believed to be located in the United States at the time of the query or the time of the communication or creation of the information, where such communications or information were obtained without a court order, subpoena, or other legal process established by statute;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB65466C48D874A979C32D14C950DD87E"><enum>(13)</enum><text>the number of criminal proceedings in which the Federal Government or a government of a State or political subdivision thereof entered into evidence or otherwise used or disclosed in a criminal proceeding any information obtained or derived from an acquisition conducted without a court order, subpoena, or other legal process established by statute; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H92B1ECDA1F844FD7A1B67002285E8CE3"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a good faith estimate of what percentage of the communications that are subject to the procedures described in section 309(b)(3) of the Intelligence Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1813">50 U.S.C. 1813(b)(3)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF671A1BCE34A40889D72DB66C669B4C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are retained for longer than 5 years; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC3B4C89190294F84BC7E8F89E45385B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are retained for longer than 5 years in whole in part because they are encrypted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H05708A29B3564E79A6ABD421BA8E7C97"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal of nonapplicability to federal bureau of investigation of certain requirements</header><text>Subsection (d) of such section is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H2A13DE2ACFCB4019A8692A17EAB0C76B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E0F3AD557F44B84A76B95552328AC91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H86AA9558AB6540799A76168F17E6D252"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Subsection (d)(1) of such section is amended by striking <quote>paragraphs (3), (5), or (6)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (6), (8), or (9)</quote>.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1A9CC95249744CE38F106445E03E7A57" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>26.</enum><header>Quarterly report </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 707 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881f">50 U.S.C. 1881f</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H93956D4FCA484DF3A5B2374C8ADBE5DF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H08378CA3B73D41CA98507AE47A332ED2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Quarterly report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence, shall submit a report, each quarter, to the congressional intelligence committees and to the Committees on the Judiciary of the Senate and of the House of Representatives, which shall include, for that quarter, the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H73EC8276A8E443A486641B45F4E71E9B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The total number of warrants issued to conduct a query of information acquired under section 702.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72D16484E487484B82174466A6920B23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The total number of times a query was conducted pursuant to an exception under section 702(f)(2)(B) and which exceptions applied.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H117CBD5247A642228AE4D1236D17417D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The total number of queries of information acquired under section 702 that were conducted using a United States person query term or a query term pertaining to a person reasonably believed to be present in the United States as of the date such query was conducted, disaggregated by the agency that conducted the queries.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> <endorsement display="yes"> <action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date> <action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc> <action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date> <action-desc>Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement> </bill> 

