<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4EB546668B164E95B797F1121EDF53D8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3117 IH: Hotel to Housing Conversion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3117</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a program for the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development to make grants to States and continua of care to carry out conversions of structures for use as emergency shelters and housing for homeless persons and families, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H184EFD72CF4E425090EF78ACB17D5D12" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H54AE7B721CDC4E9D994DD4591E97CE3B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hotel to Housing Conversion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD5C1DB66F4244519A8EBB30256B63DE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants for converting structures for use as emergency shelters and housing for homeless persons and families</header> <subsection id="H6F1A920E35D74088B678D55DA59B5744"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to States and continua of care for distribution to units of local government and private nonprofit organizations to assist in carrying out conversions of structures for use as emergency, temporary, and transitional housing and emergency shelters for homeless persons and families. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEA3BB4A7AF0647739A302B35C6C0F689"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grant amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under this section shall be used only in connection with the conversion of hotels, motels, or vacant, blighted, or unused residential properties for use as housing or shelter as provided in subsection (a), including for—</text> <paragraph id="H05042AC431D64386872B1B070B8D2BFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the acquisition (by purchase or lease), rehabilitation, renovation, or other conversion of such structures;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1687B381CFF647A589CA36CA32AA7E7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>operating costs in connection with use of such structures as housing or shelters; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H053DB61FD1C44C62A7B3EA629292118C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>providing supportive services, as such term is defined in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>), homelessness prevention services, and housing counseling services in connection with the converted housing or shelter.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H906629E8367840299218AC1E534ECA9C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application; selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for States and continua of care to apply for grants under this section and shall select States and continua of care to receive such grants based on a competition that takes into account—</text> <paragraph id="HFAED767081FF426F8D5968D616785622"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the level of housing instability in the jurisdiction of the applicant and the need—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8C92F583053E4A838C872E587971C413"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for emergency, transitional, or permanent housing or emergency shelters for homeless persons and families;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCAB115425ECF4727BBAC7613B9989C39"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to address safety and public health needs of such persons and families; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5EEF7D0E023347ECA176A44FDECE56EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for supportive services for such persons and families; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2CF85E8694548B28C5DD41DDC36DC02"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effectiveness of the proposed method of distribution of grant amounts to units of local government and private nonprofit organizations in addressing such needs.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC4C420DFF8E3437F8456713961DA414B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall require each recipient of a grant under this section to submit a report to the Secretary, upon the expiration of the 12-month period beginning upon the award of such grant, detailing how grant amounts were used and describing the effect of such use on the level of homelessness in the jurisdiction of the recipient.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD12DE13DE2D8421CA062CA25A7C4A5D2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H7E4866DEF1A345C89506509117B4954F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Continuum of care</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>continuum of care</quote> means a collaborative applicant established and operating for a geographic area for purposes of the Continuum of Care Program under subtitle C of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11381">42 U.S.C. 11381 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCFC04F7B6AD94E4C9E66315E5643BB04"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emergency housing</header><text>The term <quote>emergency housing</quote> means housing that is provided on a short-term and temporary basis to address emergency situations. Such term does not include transitional or permanent housing, as such terms are defined in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32799902FA2C42C9B913AD513FB117B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Emergency shelter; private nonprofit organization; State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>emergency shelter</quote>, <quote>private nonprofit organization</quote>, and <quote>State</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 321 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11351">42 U.S.C. 11351</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8479AAA1AA57444DB3FA81C6287CB14E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Homeless</header><text>The term <quote>homeless</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 103 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11302">42 U.S.C. 11302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD061A468D7B74EEF8ADCF303899AEC8F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H1910F3041FB448738BF0AC000F87F17F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Permanent housing; transitional housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>permanent housing</quote> and <quote>transitional housing</quote> have the meanings given such term in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H92E6CFFADA7F492196F5C64688BAF9A6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under this section $750,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection> </section> </legis-body></bill>

