<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA7B05676F5D94D3085C52868CCCCBBD3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3686 IH: Stopping Harmful Image Exploitation and Limiting Distribution Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3686</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that it is unlawful to knowingly distribute private intimate visual depictions with reckless disregard for the individual’s lack of consent to the distribution, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H275D9BA22F2A4FBA80A63361B6D81A09" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H2E5E117E14D3417D9A899EAA7EDA3A0C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stopping Harmful Image Exploitation and Limiting Distribution Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SHIELD Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="HF820661D84384EB6A2E568E67B5B2FC7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certain activities relating to intimate visual depictions</header><subsection id="H879DF9A1F47A43E6835E8FF1F9422E75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/88">Chapter 88</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H31A012BF59C146F898DBA1048E4DC236"><section id="H65F47E6F144F4E1C84DE8DDB386F6616"><enum>1802.</enum><header>Certain activities relating to intimate visual depictions</header><subsection id="HC9453960EBC94A37A4EE15D159FAB7EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H41313C3737234803AA21E343582287AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Communications service</header><text>The term <quote>communications service</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H0A82B5F822C540DCB69376C100E3D36C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a service provided by a person that is a common carrier, as that term is defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>), insofar as the person is acting as a common carrier;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA73B4D29173C452EA94338D3F1C90564"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an electronic communication service, as that term is defined in section 2510;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7067219E92994EE4ABE0E0B0F4097F34"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an information service, as that term is defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2DB3DD9740D40E6851876C254471E10"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an interactive computer service, as that term is defined in section 230(f) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230(f)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H63BB629A853C46089E60CD551C26BC1E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information content provider</header><text>The term <quote>information content provider</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 230(f) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230(f)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0D26165FA1A4C42A6EAE2C7D95C732B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Intimate visual depiction</header><text>The term <quote>intimate visual depiction</quote> means any visual depiction (as that term is defined in section 2256(5)) of an individual who is recognizable by an individual other than the depicted individual from the intimate image who has attained 18 years of age at the time the intimate visual depiction is created and—</text><subparagraph id="HACDC1B09945F43CFAADFDA09FE689DD1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is depicted engaging in sexually explicit conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39890D8BA8C84B0BAF5119691AF39948"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whose genitals, anus, pubic area, or female nipple are unclothed and visible.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H98986EE04B8F4C12A8E377F7C17CE37F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Visual depiction of a nude minor</header><text>The term <quote>visual depiction of a nude minor</quote> means any visual depiction (as that term is defined in section 2256(5)) of an individual who is recognizable by an individual other than the depicted individual from the intimate image itself or information or text displayed in connection with the intimate image who was under 18 years of age at the time the visual depiction was created in which the actual anus, genitals, or pubic area, or post-pubescent female nipple, of the minor are unclothed, visible, and displayed in a manner that does not constitute sexually explicit conduct.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38EDC0339F4F4B91B57B01238A21FF8A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Sexually explicit conduct</header><text>The term <quote>sexually explicit conduct</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 2256(2)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H58D8D417B9C3401B91365C9D5FD30AF6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Offenses</header><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3EF49E04D534935B89F33363A16BBB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (d), it shall be unlawful to knowingly mail, or to knowingly distribute using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, an intimate visual depiction of an individual—</text><subparagraph id="H02426B5F6A024DD990992AFA7157CA1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with knowledge of the lack of consent of the individual to the distribution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4C939884A244B998400C96907EEC33D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>where what is depicted was not voluntarily exposed by the individual in a public or commercial setting; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E6B9EA90D314F86801B4C41460B39AE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>where what is depicted is not a matter of public concern.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">For purposes of this paragraph, the fact that the subject of the depiction consented to the creation of the depiction shall not establish that that person consented to its distribution. </continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DC8A44FA7474FE599097F3AA91DAEBE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minors</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (d), it shall be unlawful to knowingly mail, or to knowingly distribute using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, a visual depiction of a nude minor with intent to abuse, humiliate, harass, or degrade the minor, or to arouse or gratify the sexual desire of any person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65F915D17A0F4DE896DA023CB07F075A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalty</header><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA5CF8D2735B9466580A5F6DC03A05158"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who violates subsection (b), or attempts or conspires to do so, shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD4ED2F0BB5B419BA668BA1F83EF21FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><subparagraph id="H338F9103C416469280A23C35C40970C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The court, in imposing a sentence on any person convicted of a violation involving intimate visual depictions or visual depictions of a nude minor under this section, or convicted of a conspiracy of a violation involving intimate visual depictions or visual depictions of a nude minor under this section, shall order, in addition to any other sentence imposed and irrespective of any provision of State law, that such person forfeit to the United States—</text><clause id="H6209124BCBA644D4A89C05E21A6591BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any material distributed in violation of this section;</text></clause><clause id="HD87D604EC1604F819F54A6AE83A4FD51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such person’s interest in property, real or personal, constituting or derived from any gross proceeds of such violation, or any property traceable to such property, obtained or retained directly or indirectly as a result of such violation; and</text></clause><clause id="H0B44DE2EDA0E4D3D97258B834F3BF941"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any property, real or personal, used or intended to be used to commit or to facilitate the commission of such offense.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAF2CB129A0C439E937AC27B2FE4E333"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Section 413 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/853">21 U.S.C. 853</external-xref>), with the exception of subsections (a) and (d), applies to the criminal forfeiture of property pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1AACB09974A40BC9D50365856A7AD5C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Restitution</header><text>Restitution shall be available as provided in section 2264 of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEF052F4E8EA74FC2B01CA067DA278E6E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="H5ADF475F44AE455F8CF713FBE57647DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Law enforcement, lawful reporting, and other legal proceedings</header><text>This section—</text><subparagraph id="HEFB4753904A3402992C9622447219276"><enum>(A)</enum><text>does not prohibit any lawfully authorized investigative, protective, or intelligence activity of a law enforcement agency of the United States, a State, or a political subdivision of a State, or of an intelligence agency of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BBB585E3FF049138251149CACE84733"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not apply in the case of an individual acting in good faith to report unlawful or unsolicited activity or in pursuance of a legal or professional or other lawful obligation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74A9077050F944BBAB57EF2A16E401AA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall not apply in the case of a document production or filing associated with a legal proceeding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H559F0B260AC24515AF8C5067761279EC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service providers</header><text>This section shall not apply to any provider of a communications service with regard to content provided by another information content provider unless the provider of the communications service intentionally solicits, or knowingly and predominantly distributes, such content.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H11BD290BC3A8461793BDE8D85E45BCBD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Threats</header><text>Any person who threatens to commit an offense under subsection (b) shall be punished as provided in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6EB643DB6E9B49C2B0FE0F33B24B9100"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Extraterritoriality</header><text>There is extraterritorial Federal jurisdiction over an offense under this section if the defendant or the depicted individual is a citizen or permanent resident of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF69C3D94103F4290911BB423AFE9CA6D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the application of any other relevant law, including section 2252 of this title.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H726927E142D74160BB0293F290770E81"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/88">chapter 88</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/1801">section 1801</external-xref> the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCBF98C40E686417D9805BABDABAF3791"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">1802. Certain activities relating to intimate visual depictions.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H0B6533AD3FD74436A03CECCA10CAF213"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 2264(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, or under section 1802 of this title</quote> before the period.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

