<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDFC64175A52348B0A21D02411DD1D3B4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6684 IH: Improving Efficiency to Increase Competition Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6684</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Comptroller General to submit a report on the disclosure process for intellectual property created under a Federal grant, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0FC30FCE74904997A8C5F58513282075" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H63EB3261CB854A6990F332C687574F24" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Efficiency to Increase Competition Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE240F19DB9814C9F9C9AE8D1122D1043"><enum>2.</enum><header>GAO study on the impact of Bayh-Dole Act regulations on contractors in the United States</header> <subsection id="H4E32A57A444143CE87F730E303AC8B7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall brief the relevant committees, with a report to follow on a mutually agreed upon date that is not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, that reviews the implementation of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/35/18">chapter 18</external-xref> of title 35, United States Code, (commonly referred to as the Bayh-Dole Act), specifically with regard to the requirements under that chapter and implementing regulations that a contractor under a funding agreement with the Federal Government must follow with regard to patent disclosure. The report shall include, to the extent practicable, information on the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0FFB5464F21346ED84783F3083788387" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The percentage of inventions that are not elected by contractors to retain within the time period provided following the disclosure of an invention under part 401 of title 37, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA593E89D6E64BDFBBC0F0F85076026A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After any automatic extension has been granted and in a case in which a contractor requests an additional extension, the number of time extensions that are granted by Federal agencies for disclosure, election, and filing and the average response time by each agency for any such extension.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD33A6D17E5BC4875B466DF21B5EAC889"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How the reporting requirements in such chapter impact the ability of a contractor to compete with foreign competitors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H165A352B6B4740719C1A3832C54689F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How the Government uses Federal reporting under such chapter by contractors and suggested improvements to ensure there is an improved public-private partnership.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF71085A8B9F467081F7853C918FCEAE"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Barriers that Federal reporting requirements create for contractors to develop inventions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97046476583E44CD9FA0A836099A186B" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The time and effort institutions of higher education must use for the management and reporting required under such chapter, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H833F704EDF4240D8B9286CDBD7A6E0E9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">input from contractors with various sizes, budgets, geographical positions, and specialties;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HABE2612EA9BA45EE8963CD7463F07833"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to any institution of higher education included in the report, a consideration of the specific research designations for such institution, including R1 and R2; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F9BEAA912FE4392BAA18C31901649CD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how such contractors vary on the their ability to efficiently comply with the requirements under such chapter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAAE0EDC3C7949338996975A20F6B50D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Difficulties contractors encounter in using the iEdison system and recommendations to address these difficulties.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H439F4CF5C2D443A3850273995BD49032"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any other Federal agency does not use the patent reporting system deployed by the National Institute of Standards and Technology, commonly known as iEdison, whether such agency would benefit from using a singular standard Federal reporting system and whether such agency can effectively standardize reporting requirements in order to streamline processes required by contractors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49AA51928F764995BC596390D308BE3D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The number of disclosure systems used throughout the Federal Government, listed by what system is used by each Federal agency, and the various disclosure requirements made by each such agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H53D575DCAE544CB394D980048FF9A555"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H4127B604804E41C88FE75BCFB3B254F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>ability</term> means time, resources, staff, and any other metric determined necessary for compliance under the contract requirements described in the Bayh Dole Act, including any regulation issued under such Act. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB9EE00CFA3444E8CA7DA25D664816C4C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contractor; Federal agency; funding agreement</header><text>The terms <term>contractor</term>, <term>Federal agency</term>, and <term>funding agreement</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 201 of title 35, United States Code. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40468B543E374B8C9C1BB661ACA162C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE67AFB43A10744A78A3F754FB9B0A1E1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Relevant committees</header><text>The term <term>relevant committees</term> means the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H4B2B7168AA434642860141E048A5C2F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H012B8C6125AB472199A169ED0D0B05BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D827445ECEE49BDA87D49330C3E25D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H432B3B1A676E49F5996F0BB20FDF9811"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA408E05719A4427E83F434D54ADEAB8D"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H27178C37006541E5AFF09E3B28D347E0"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

