<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC4FCAF5B19C41EDB3A0C0598FB39E0D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5825 IH: Care is an Economic Development Strategy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5825</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 to require eligible recipients of certain grants to develop a comprehensive economic development strategy that directly or indirectly increases the accessibility of affordable, quality care-based services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8DB7C7F9EF224BF8849C627E9EE390B0" style="OLC"><section id="H75CC2730C9A64D189942D4F75F0CD130" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Care is an Economic Development Strategy Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CEDS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H859EEAF67F8443E2BD7B519FEA68701A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Comprehensive economic development strategies</header><subsection id="H88D9DA9FA5784F9198DD803DA1F71B75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 302(a)(3)(A) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3162">42 U.S.C. 3162(a)(3)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H345D17AF87D743DFA285A841E12295B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> before <quote>balances resources</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6ED37869C90478DA2E6E15B732F9DA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and directly or indirectly increases the accessibility of affordable, quality care-based services, including child care, early childhood education, disability and long-term care, and elder care</quote> after <quote>sound management of development</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1641B094F356485CA49A82921D1A09FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><paragraph id="HEAF5D3FA166C47F4A3DE7584F40184A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall issue guidance on implementing the amendments made by subsection (a), to include how to increase access to the affordable, quality care-based services described in section 302(a)(3)(A) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3162">42 U.S.C. 3162(a)(3)(A)</external-xref>) in a comprehensive economic development strategy developed under section 302 of such Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2783500CBA584EBDACB812F0172642D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Existing comprehensive economic development strategies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In issuing the guidance under paragraph (1), with respect to a grant recipient whose comprehensive economic development strategy has been approved under section 302 of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3162">42 U.S.C. 3162</external-xref>) before the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall ensure that such grant recipient is only required to update such comprehensive economic development strategy to comply with the amendments made by this Act when a regularly scheduled update to such comprehensive economic development strategy is required. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

