<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD0444796A8834F9AA49EC3D53E9112F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3306 IH: Federal Broadband Permit Coordination Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3306</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To facilitate Federal broadband permit coordination, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9B5B3DE26FE8451EA58729D5F0401B8C" style="OLC"><section id="H6AE2022D6E0143D49B9A894D30AFD89C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Broadband Permit Coordination Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB482CEC67D8C46369A8648E69BDB1F61"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal broadband permit coordination</header><subsection id="HCDFB3FD9A2F34974B9D633FBC1F4028B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in consultation with the National Conference of State Historic Preservation Officers and the National Association of Tribal Historic Preservation Officers, shall enter into, in accordance with this section, a memorandum of understanding with—</text><paragraph id="H2E17D72E10D544AA9CD8DBE88C1D7B2D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior (as the case may be);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5534E812EF7485C97618E85DF97CF59"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H356B6DA44E1E4E9FB8FFEB01C595CE4E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3EC8F447E0654A37B289F29659DEAE0A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the memorandum of understanding entered into under subsection (a) shall be to coordinate and expedite permitting decisions for broadband projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3E9822BA996649FC8664B8C38D24D807"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State or Tribal participation</header><text>The Secretary concerned may request that the Governor of a State or the officer designated by the governing body of an Indian Tribe with one or more broadband projects be a party to the memorandum of understanding entered into under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H22B48A3559D64B5E9428F6DC3B726EB3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Designation of qualified staff</header><paragraph id="HA1271DE487D64742BCAFD831CFA9C9D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of entrance into a memorandum of understanding under subsection (a), the head of each Federal agency that is a party to the memorandum of understanding (other than the Secretary concerned) may, if the head of the Federal agency determines it to be appropriate, designate to each State or regional office (that has been delegated responsibility by the Secretary concerned for issuing permits for broadband projects) an employee of that Federal agency with expertise in regulatory issues relating to that Federal agency, including, as applicable, particular expertise in—</text><subparagraph id="H6D39DB31F9E84E398A1A3CF938CBD938"><enum>(A)</enum><text>planning under the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1600">16 U.S.C. 1600 et seq.</external-xref>) and planning under the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1701">43 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE112A9E11DF0458A9417F893EFC92F30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the preparation of analyses under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF54B8BEBCCC440C2B11B07D7FFD83370"><enum>(C)</enum><text>consultation and the preparation of biological opinions under section 7 of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1536">16 U.S.C. 1536</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4807F3D9088C4DFEA3D7E2E51F1796EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment of streamlining team</header><text>If employees are designated under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall establish a broadband permit streamlining team, comprised of such employees, in each State or regional office that has been delegated responsibility by the Secretary concerned for issuing permits for broadband projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H955B49EE25F84297BF72AF119321C533"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>Each employee designated under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H0E71462F87F94ED28A1529110DD83F03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be responsible for any issue relating to any broadband project, within the jurisdiction of the State or regional office, under the authority of the Federal agency from which the employee is assigned; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H324EC03FB0AE4046833D5D46DF9F05F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>participate as part of the team of personnel working on one or more proposed broadband projects, including with respect to planning and environmental analyses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H28FAE38F3C594643939188121335A96A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HE35ED04D713F4072BA7A87CDEB12E416"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Broadband project</header><text>The term <term>broadband project</term> means an installation, by a broadband provider on Federal land, of wireline or wireless broadband infrastructure that enables a user to originate and receive high-quality voice, data, graphics, and video telecommunications, including copper lines, fiber optic lines, communications towers, buildings, or other improvements.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97B6A3A1E2D24E949DF326BA8277EA56"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Broadband provider</header><text>The term <term>broadband provider</term> means a provider of wireline or wireless broadband infrastructure that enables a user to originate and receive high-quality voice, data, graphics, and video telecommunications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0218DBB5B6A84E07BECCB65DCC90EA9C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF7B0BDEBB3A4B52864D1A92F5A248D7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>National Forest System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>National Forest System</term> has the meaning given that term in section 11(a) of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1609">16 U.S.C. 1609(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H301F30ACD2B844DB92CDAA05D9299911"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HEAE4EA553CEA4D79B8CBEF9C369CF3FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture (acting through the Chief of the Forest Service), with respect to National Forest System land; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC198862394A043959D20E3EA21F7E03E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to land managed by the Department of the Interior (including land held in trust for an Indian Tribe).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD548CEB6EFB646529B385ADCDDE16B6F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, and each territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

