<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H30C5F605D9DF43AA83F64C0C41C0005C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>91 HR 4013 IH: Advancing the Quality and Understanding of American Aquaculture Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4013</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a regulatory system for sustainable offshore aquaculture in the United States exclusive economic zone, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4565839D552F42868C0A5CC2B64A5C51" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HBF0B025103AF4639A22BA770CC827C0B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="HE09A829E60AF4AE2972F40BD221C495F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing the Quality and Understanding of American Aquaculture Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AQUAA Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H21F0CB51190E41CDB72E3032248DE800"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="HBF0B025103AF4639A22BA770CC827C0B">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H38E7A870DFA841D68C0A4454C6B3570B">Sec. 2. Purposes.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H0124FE6616434D0CB2F08C0735688226">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HD0AC32F0966148D8ABFB6DED0225EFCB">TITLE I—National standards</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H76C1F651F88E475E8F42683552E6ED47">Sec. 101. National standards for sustainable aquaculture.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HFEBE2BCF2A4445758A5DF009C6BD3E53">Sec. 102. National plan to identify and designate aquaculture opportunity areas.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H125B95ABFF5A43D29C17FBAE8433E407">Sec. 103. Aquaculture outside of an aquaculture opportunity area.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HA5EC92D6C5364CC39C92A6357E28CEC0">TITLE II—Core activities</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H046F4221D6624BCBB8697BC8A9A5F596">Sec. 201. Aquaculture management plans.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H6598C9BBA03E4CD2B235060689935DE2">Sec. 202. Offshore aquaculture permits.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF74E21EBA90144E9ABC3F7BF2F1C6100">Sec. 203. Research and development grant program.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H1718FF11883F410CA918F3952EC25685">Sec. 204. Economic soundness.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="H9BE7AB1E7ECF4FB29C9599CA57A17453">TITLE III—Refinements</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HEFC7197A1F994456AF4C3616A6F1F96B">Sec. 301. Recordkeeping, inspections, and access to information.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HD71E5D2A36D949CB8D4E9895280EDBD4">Sec. 302. Marine feed standards.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H72B2520B564E4200B7EFB3CB741D5CE6">Sec. 303. Marine use rights.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HB158F945CB4947629831C83BF891247B">TITLE IV—Administrative provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HFE9B1FA483684C4FBC87439DC6F43A24">Sec. 401. Office of Aquaculture.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H37041F2B2F754ABD9FF6A3E3B2902A8E">Sec. 402. Support for industry.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H3BED84B45E924380BA90ADCAB3DD24C1">Sec. 403. Outreach and education.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H9FB700C189E7475EA248F768EED98F72">Sec. 404. Administration.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H2CFA427DEBD94AA7AAB998AB6806CC23">Sec. 405. Report and permit terms.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H7BAE535D9B5449CCB4E75C62088C2318">Sec. 406. Federal coordination.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H60E172D3D9884222B434BC99852A4689">Sec. 407. Prohibited acts.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HA58016C4061144EAAA0880868A0EECEB">Sec. 408. Enforcement.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H3D8B1E61A3334A378D2BC9F6866AFC15">Sec. 409. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H38E7A870DFA841D68C0A4454C6B3570B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="H5946652163B84FC2AC579D11F338AFBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support the development of a sustainable marine aquaculture industry in the United States and enhance access to investment capital;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EB80B1D620B47578AC07EC84695723D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to develop sustainable marine aquaculture to complement sustainable fisheries and ecosystem-based management;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC62CE9D01B6A44AC8A784858DB901D9E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to clarify the Federal regulatory regime for sustainable offshore aquaculture and safeguard the marine environment, wild fish stocks, and our coastal communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0C05CDC8F5841DEB4EF16EF892066FE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to support research and technology development to further these goals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5712CC8C18C4C6E82715393C72902C3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to create new jobs, and support existing jobs within the seafood industry of the United States, including jobs for traditional fishing industry participants; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09B372B54B6C481BB3AC5BC8F37342CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to reduce the United States seafood trade deficit by expanding the domestic supply of seafood through the production of sustainable offshore aquaculture.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0124FE6616434D0CB2F08C0735688226"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H98250D48948F4ED0ABE3EBDDB287783E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Aquaculture</header><text>The term <term>aquaculture</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H96A08845210F4CD180752F5DD3C91410"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any activity involved in the propagation, rearing, or attempted propagation or rearing, of cultured species, including the capture and rearing of broodstock; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H877A770A85904EBD8D12AA090D8AF216"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include the practice of capturing juvenile finfish to rear to maturity in an aquaculture facility for subsequent commercial sale; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2608A81BE205453692D3FB9439CFE1C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not include the practice of rearing and releasing cultured species for the purpose of enhancing wild populations. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA133C61CBCC438FB641C0ADCC8B8BB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Aquaculture stakeholder</header><text>The term <term>aquaculture stakeholder</term> means owners and operators of offshore aquaculture facilities, Regional Fishery Management Councils, interstate fisheries commissions, conservation organizations, fisheries associations, State, county, and federally recognized Indian Tribes, and other interested parties. The term also includes other Federal agencies that have interests in aquaculture. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD602EB8709D4945A18ABBF08195F19D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coastal State</header><text>Except as otherwise specifically provided, the term <term>coastal State</term> has the meaning given the term <term>coastal state</term> in section 304(4) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1453">16 U.S.C. 1453(4)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4468A63A3378433282BC43FE5DA6E641"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Cultured species</header><text>The term <term>cultured species</term> means any species propagated and reared for marine aquaculture. The term includes larval marine shellfish species that self-recruit in the offshore environment. The term excludes any member of the class aves, reptilia, or mammalia. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CF673B9354441C3A8CB349B8623E25D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exclusive economic zone</header><subparagraph id="H7903C04C55FC47ACB5E2FF01B8D0C2DA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Unless otherwise specified by the President in the public interest in a writing published in the Federal Register, the term <term>exclusive economic zone</term> means a zone, the outer boundary of which is 200 nautical miles from the baseline from which the breadth of the territorial sea is measured (except as established by a maritime boundary treaty in force or being provisionally applied by the United States or, in the absence of such a treaty, where the distance between the United States and another country is less than 400 nautical miles, a line equidistant between the United States and the other country).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B4527E9E0A242BEB8E13F15AA7C1784"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inner boundary</header><text>Without affecting any Presidential proclamation with regard to the establishment of the United States territorial sea or exclusive economic zone, the inner boundary of the exclusive economic zone is—</text><clause id="HDFF653F884C14597BF617F1D71AA1ABA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of the coastal States, a line coterminous with the seaward boundary of each such State, as described in section 4 of the Submerged Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1312">43 U.S.C. 1312</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="HBF18A1A3A11B48E3991BE2EEAE58EB00"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, a line 9 nautical miles from the coastline of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico;</text></clause><clause id="H95087116B0EA460A89A842D4D852BA82"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, or Guam, a line 3 geographic miles from the coastlines of American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, or Guam, respectively;</text></clause><clause id="HD6057F560749475B82D1C247D451F595"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands—</text><subclause id="HC7075939896047349CF88B3AD78ACF96"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the coastline of the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, until the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands is granted authority by the United States to regulate all fishing to a line seaward of its coastline; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HAE59FF8EC6404B34A4FE63A1A06F55E0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>upon the United States grant of such authority, the line established by such grant of authority; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8E7D8C6B31CE4E918561A94EBC2D3510"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for any possession of the United States not under clause (ii), (iii), or (iv), the coastline of such possession.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC75D24007BFC41518D4991C68865BF6E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this definition may be construed to diminish the authority of the Department of Defense, the Department of the Interior, or any other Federal department or agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H83DA9C291B2A4273B24BFA948627787F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Healthy target stock</header><text>The term <term>healthy target stock</term> means a component of a fishery managed in a similar or equivalent way to fisheries managed under the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1801">16 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) or by a United States interstate marine fisheries commission, or a component of a fishery targeted for harvest that is not overfished or experiencing overfishing. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64A7D817B9744BCDA9110675EBD9A0EC"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Lessee</header><text>The term <term>lessee</term> means any party to a lease, right-of-use and easement, or right-of-way, or an approved assignment thereof, issued pursuant to the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AD532A1399643F6B3022CABED57E1C6"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Multi-trophic aquaculture</header><text>The term <term>multi-trophic aquaculture</term> means an assemblage of cultured species grown in close enough proximity to one another so that cultured species provide ecosystem services to one another. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0768C69FEBE841A2AB6FB89CFE9F8789"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Offshore aquaculture</header><text>The term <term>offshore aquaculture</term> means aquaculture conducted in the exclusive economic zone.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1688232E90EA4FAE84F51C033A2B428A"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Offshore aquaculture facility</header><text>The term <term>offshore aquaculture facility</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HDC1B35D67EDD47FEA6D7F7940FE88F33"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an installation or structure used, in whole or in part, for offshore aquaculture; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DFFA51A63D949629847B1D780D31994"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an area of the seabed, water column, or the sediment used for offshore aquaculture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H078D164B28EF444F96DF51C3792B42EC"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Except as otherwise specifically provided, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H469835168CDC4E5EB89F2E40C6985851"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Sustainably managed fishery for aquaculture feed</header><text>The term <term>sustainably managed fishery for aquaculture feed</term> means a fishery that is used for feed and that is managed in such a manner to maintain healthy target stocks, to protect marine ecosystem structure, productivity, function, and diversity, and to minimize impacts to nontarget stocks.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HD0AC32F0966148D8ABFB6DED0225EFCB" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>National standards</header><section id="H76C1F651F88E475E8F42683552E6ED47"><enum>101.</enum><header>National standards for sustainable aquaculture</header><subsection id="H5CA56D9417CC435EB8D5D494F85C3225"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relation to current law</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed in derogation of applicable law, and offshore aquaculture operations shall comply with all applicable statutes, rules, and regulations. In order to ensure that implementing regulations for applicable statutes appropriately account for the unique considerations arising from offshore aquaculture, the Secretary shall comply with the following: </text><paragraph id="H946D1DB32EF8486B8032CA8725CE644F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>With respect to regulations administered by the Department of Commerce or National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Secretary shall review such regulations in accordance with this subsection and update any regulations as appropriate or necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B3C3864671B4BDB92F2D92D4248B16A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to Federal regulations not administered by the Department of Commerce or National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Secretary shall confer with appropriate officials to review such regulations in accordance with this subsection. After such review, the Agency that administers the regulations may, as appropriate or necessary, update such regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10B62EFC2DDA4DEFBBCC71FAB1329496"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National standards</header><text>Any designation and establishment of an aquaculture opportunity area, any aquaculture management plan prepared, any regulation promulgated, and any permit granted, pursuant to this Act, shall—</text><paragraph id="H8C3A4DE865244C44A71F3FFF4FB135EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encourage development of United States offshore aquaculture while remaining consistent with environmental requirements established by law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EBBCDA01C6F4518A45FB72A9306C330"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be based on the best scientific information available, taking into account traditional knowledge;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B4A0DCF9D7A4FC9B5C0E340B722D4C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be adaptive to offshore aquaculture development, accounting for updates in technology and changes in environmental conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EFA0B6B3CF9449B8475EC6DB0F55540"><enum>(4)</enum><text>prefer species that are native or historically naturalized to the region; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C1404D01FFE4A4CA1C3CC13C739EAD3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>prioritize the health of cultured species. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9D0B351DCA44D91905FB322D02236F3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Guidelines</header><text>The Secretary shall establish advisory guidelines (which shall not have the force and effect of law), based on the national standards, to assist in the development of aquaculture management plans, and regulations promulgated and permits granted pursuant to this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4A36F09118394B4D8EE30FB023B3910A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Periodic review</header><text>The Secretary shall periodically review the advisory guidelines established under subsection (c), as needed, but not less often than once every 5 years, to determine whether changed circumstances, advances in science, or improved management practices warrant an amendment or update to the guidelines. </text></subsection></section><section id="HFEBE2BCF2A4445758A5DF009C6BD3E53"><enum>102.</enum><header>National plan to identify and designate aquaculture opportunity areas</header><subsection id="H99CAE1EF8BCD468DB4420F90B500A0FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relation to current law</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed in derogation of applicable law in effect on the date of enactment of this Act regulating or restricting the use of the exclusive economic zone, and the Secretary shall comply with all such applicable law when proposing, designating, and operating an aquaculture opportunity area under this section. In order to ensure that implementing regulations for applicable statutes appropriately account for the unique considerations arising from offshore aquaculture, the Secretary shall comply with the following: </text><paragraph id="H62E7274E6FBC4F51A895B6C35A080061"><enum>(1)</enum><text>With respect to regulations administered by the Department of Commerce or National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Secretary shall review such regulations in accordance with this subsection and update any regulations as appropriate or necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85AD8332B56C437EAB0234CAFA3A7124"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to Federal regulations not administered by the Department of Commerce or National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Secretary shall confer with appropriate officials to review such regulations in accordance with this subsection. After such review, the Agency that administers the regulations may, as appropriate or necessary, update such regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4042CFF7EB14C45A476E24431000459"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National plan</header><paragraph id="H77A5FCC2CFF14920A52DA37B78117455"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, consistent with this section, develop a plan and timeline to systematically—</text><subparagraph id="H7C1B758C7D8E45939A246FC71EC91865"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the exclusive economic zone;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F64749E5FD84CEF9E3036022B4F5AD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prepare an inventory of sites suitable for aquaculture opportunity areas; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5AE5FE841A34B8CA1D84B12D552FC11"><enum>(C)</enum><text>designate aquaculture opportunity areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3295DEFE7FB74C56B0AD68359753B665"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The Secretary may designate an aquaculture opportunity area prior to completion of the entire inventory under paragraph (1)(B) for locations where the Secretary has completed the assessment under paragraph (1)(A) and developed an aquaculture management plan as required under subsection (f)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4712F2B8192D48F2981948BA031EA3B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment of the exclusive economic zone; inventory</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct the assessment and prepare the inventory described in subsection (b) using relevant scientific, social, and economic data, and engagement with aquaculture stakeholders and the public as provided in subsection (e). In conducting the assessment, the Secretary may consider a cluster of locations in close proximity with similar conditions as a single inventory item, provided that each of the locations meets the criteria established in this section. Based on the factors listed in subsection (d) and the national standards in section 101, the Secretary shall make a determination based on the totality of the circumstances whether a site under consideration is suitable for sustainable offshore aquaculture. If the Secretary determines that a site is suitable, then the site shall be listed in the inventory, along with—</text><paragraph id="HAD7ABBA2927949AB944747D43BA4C3AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the site, including its coordinates and a map;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07FEB2A2636E46FDA08650F1F47DD54A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a thorough evaluation of each factor described in subsection (d), and the Secretary’s findings regarding each of those factors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H630C4E6756ED4127921007B88AFDCB5A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an analysis of how these findings justify the Secretary’s determination that the site is suitable for sustainable offshore aquaculture.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3CE913C9CF77411E9333D52166B3FE13"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Factors for assessment</header><text>In order to conduct the assessment in subsection (c), the Secretary shall consider the following factors:</text><paragraph id="H16499AECB13D49708C3D31036C58B533"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The oceanographic characteristics of the site.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0E492CDD3064DEFA1A302C14708B89B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The bathymetry and availability of areas for anchors, moorings, and other gear.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE1DD4E0F96B40E68390747511C39B05"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Current and possible future human uses of the site, and the areas in reasonable proximity to the site.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H333454D483084B20B9311DDD78CAD18D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Current and possible future conservation uses of the site, and the areas in reasonable proximity to the site.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55CCCAC0879B452AAEF1E2A006F9C507"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Potential impacts to wild fisheries from the escape of cultured species, or from cultured species becoming invasive or hybridizing with wild stocks within the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7316A33FFF5B4F4D83C0444E0753631B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Potential benefits from multi-trophic aquaculture, where cultured species provide ecosystem services to one another.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1F15F270DE94028B6C843DEE668DDC6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Availability of shore-side fishery infrastructure and other land-based support facilities to support offshore aquaculture operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6158250011F84656876E8FA9A5FD53D1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Expected socioeconomic impacts from operations on adjacent coastal communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36F9F87423F346CFB622979EE81E65CA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Other factors that the Secretary determines are appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE12C8C128DE648C7A5CB7E0BAC3AD2B1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Engagement</header><text>In conducting the assessment and inventory under subsection (c), the Secretary shall conduct engagement with aquaculture stakeholders and the public as follows:</text><paragraph id="H2164B277BC9B419B99F47D2F7960B525"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public meetings and workshops</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct public meetings to inform interested aquaculture stakeholders about the intent to include a site in the inventory, share information about the process, and solicit public feedback, including written comments. In addition to public meetings, the Secretary may, consistent with the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.), convene workshops of particular aquaculture stakeholders or aquaculture stakeholder groups to provide insight, information, and comments to support the assessment and inventory process.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H47E020EB08F146FB9604E6B217F24503"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation with States, Tribes, and territories</header><text>The Secretary shall consult with States, federally recognized Indian Tribes, and territories adjacent to or within 100 miles of a site under consideration for the inventory. Such States, federally recognized Indian Tribes, and territories may submit comments to the Secretary, and the Secretary shall consider such comments in the assessment and inventory process.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFCF09C50A3274CFF82EE7C83E04B29D6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Designation and establishment of aquaculture opportunity area</header><paragraph id="HD8329A6437CB45E2AF516C54CF622B8C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>In order to designate and establish an aquaculture opportunity area, the Secretary shall select a site from the inventory prepared under subsection (c), and develop an aquaculture management plan under section 201. In the event that the Secretary determines the site is not viable during the development of the aquaculture management plan, the Secretary may abandon consideration of the site, and revise the inventory accordingly. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H848CEEC73D7F48778D638DFDF68E1DBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State petition</header><text>The Governor of any coastal State or territory, or a Tribal government in a fisheries management region under the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1801">16 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), may submit a request in writing to the Secretary to petition for locating an aquaculture opportunity area, or a group of aquaculture opportunity areas, in reasonable proximity to the location of the requesting State, territory, or Tribal government. The Secretary shall evaluate the petition and may designate an aquaculture opportunity area or group of aquaculture opportunity areas as provided in this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA54B49E4D1A04EA88929C5FCC43B7EFB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Initial and subsequent establishment of aquaculture opportunity areas</header><text>The Secretary shall initially establish at least 2 aquaculture opportunity areas from the inventory developed under subsection (b) not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act. Each year thereafter, the Secretary shall establish not less than 1 additional aquaculture opportunity area from the inventory until all sites from the inventory have been considered.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99E3E865F250496AAB636A5F6AB4837E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Adjustment of existing aquaculture opportunity areas</header><text>The Secretary may adjust the dimensions of an established aquaculture opportunity area as necessary, while accounting for impacts to operating aquaculture facilities, the state of science, the cost-benefit ratio of the adjustment, and comments from aquaculture stakeholders and the general public.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CB3CCE28CEA4F2AAA009787DE07C5AB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Demonstration projects</header><text>In order to test the viability of sustainable offshore aquaculture in a site listed on the inventory, the Secretary may support demonstration projects in an inventory site to assist in developing the required contents for an aquaculture management plan. Such demonstration projects shall be carried out in a manner that is consistent with the national standards in section 101. Demonstration projects may include multidisciplinary research to revive and adapt traditional aquaculture systems, such as open sea ponds, to support the needs of modern communities. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9D2C366123F74007AF1B3F5ACFA64821"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Study on aquaculture opportunity areas in State waters</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall conduct a study of the feasibility of allowing States to petition for aquaculture opportunity areas in their waters. The study shall include information and analysis on the benefits of aquaculture opportunity areas in State waters and identify barriers to implementation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3E8BA943DE594C809C849FA0036A9915"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary may promulgate regulations governing the process for implementing this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H907568CDDCA042CCB31FF004BA102F1D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Spatial data</header><text>To support the implementation of this section, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall collect and curate spatial data relevant to aquaculture and make such data publicly available, unless otherwise restricted by law.</text></subsection></section><section id="H125B95ABFF5A43D29C17FBAE8433E407"><enum>103.</enum><header>Aquaculture outside of an aquaculture opportunity area</header><subsection id="H8D359E71B61E4CDBB5C2660AF7206CD1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HDE50BE72353944BEA7566A9819C76089"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>site proponent</term> means a nongovernmental entity that assesses a site and develops an aquaculture management plan for that site in accordance with subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67FF808E652D4FA58B02937DD3840029"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>notice of intent</term> means a written document that communicates the site proponent’s intention to develop an offshore aquaculture site, and includes the location, type of aquaculture, cultured species, and other information the Secretary requires.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDA6C93E0FA541BEBAAC8AD7807EB998"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Aquaculture outside of an aquaculture opportunity area</header><text>Offshore aquaculture may be conducted outside of an aquaculture opportunity area only as provided in this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9438AD7B0DA04AD79C49C8C20DDBD051"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Process and regulations</header><paragraph id="H3347CFF33D5B47E0BDA07893EEB5085B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary shall develop a process and promulgate regulations, consistent with this section, to allow a site proponent to, at its own expense—</text><subparagraph id="HC6BA51418382405BA0A27A53D1F50AAF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess sites smaller than an aquaculture opportunity area for offshore aquaculture in an exclusive economic zone; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5B3338820AC4E97BE8F1D87E5362DA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop aquaculture management plans for those sites; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A8C3CA03BA24D26B1D2F5249D01882D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>submit a notice of intent and application to the Secretary requesting approval to conduct aquaculture at the site; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBF796955620438C96D0564FEDA8E492"><enum>(D)</enum><text>apply for a permit under section 202.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H26430A969FDF41D18B039AD78179CA42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Process</header><text>The process developed by the Secretary shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H3A694216067242AFAA264FEBEA1798C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the process for submitting a notice of intent, publishing the notice of intent, and soliciting comments under subsection (d); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24176D83B10A4573BBC67B745D0340F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the form of application to be used by the site proponent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CB4D62C9B334F42BF491001C6DC05E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the required contents of the application, including an analysis of the factors in section 102(d) and the items in section 201(c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB630588394B4F64BBEC743A68EA6480"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a process for submitting the comments received under subsection (d), along with the disposition of each; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE12DC75EC5F0458CB48465AA7BD4B0A0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a timeline for the Secretary’s consideration and action on the application, which may be either to approve, deny, or request more information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H03E4458E88BD419D90EE38443DA71DD8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notice of intent</header><paragraph id="HBEC38EF0481A4271B0266CEEA6FEF79B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary shall require each site proponent that is assessing a site under subsection (c)(1) to submit a notice of intent before developing an aquaculture management plan or submitting an application under this section. The Secretary, acting through the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5B53D4C347AF4AE4B687B0A6F45EE85B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish the notice of intent, together with information on the process under subsection (c)(2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC6DEE0E61FA4DF98F7BB3882BC1C4D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>deliver the notice of intent, together with information on the process under subsection (c)(2), to—</text><clause id="H10082706ABB34710B123C3A3116413C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>States and federally recognized Indian Tribes within 100 miles of the proposed site; and</text></clause><clause id="H75DE105D40C2441DA868FD47B822F92F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any local governments within 10 miles of the proposed site;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B42D201053F43F9AF517F2136E7C2A8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>convene meetings with aquaculture stakeholders and the public—</text><clause id="HE8F033D2093C4959B1EDD6B3B7BE305B"><enum>(i)</enum><text> to solicit public comment, including written comments, to be shared with the site proponent; and</text></clause><clause id="HBBC47D1130C64A73811EE8023AD22176"><enum><italic></italic>(ii)</enum><text>including, at a minimum—</text><subclause id="H1DE67FF2764E435AA80E3759BFB1C13D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>at least 1 public meeting for aquaculture stakeholders; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC97349E8B50D4EF4A30C5A1803BF5B51"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meetings with State, local, and Tribal government representatives; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FC330F770634A20BA7C8B917D5747EB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consult with interested Federal agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3547627095D242F782E1F2E062EF0BB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comments</header><text>States, federally recognized Indian Tribes, and local governments described in paragraph (1)(B) may submit comments on the notice of intent to the Secretary, which shall be shared with the site proponent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H348EF705A38743098D8EF424EBF48FE2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Management plan</header><text>Each site proponent shall include all comments received under subsection (d) in the aquaculture management plan, along with a disposition of each.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HA5EC92D6C5364CC39C92A6357E28CEC0" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Core activities</header><section id="H046F4221D6624BCBB8697BC8A9A5F596"><enum>201.</enum><header>Aquaculture management plans</header><subsection id="H5F20349669EE48768DCB737AF1D7E359"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development and adoption</header><text>In order to implement this Act, the Secretary shall develop and adopt for aquaculture opportunity areas established under section 102, or locations where multiple aquaculture opportunity areas may be suitable for establishment— </text><paragraph id="HAE9DCDE2D9794E1890D4CA5FAF69BABB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an aquaculture management plan; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD70642AE265840ABA22F427E1CC1E418"><enum>(2)</enum><text>amendments to each such plan that are necessary from time to time. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52C2F0CB017C483E80070FCF41274834"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Overlapping management areas</header><text>The Secretary may use a single aquaculture management plan for multiple aquaculture opportunity areas where such areas are within reasonable proximity to each other and sufficiently similar. </text></subsection><subsection id="H89532EEC2AE847ED9D5E8EC98AF487C6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Engagement</header><text>Prior to developing, adopting, or amending an aquaculture management plan under this section, the Secretary, acting through the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall meet with aquaculture stakeholders and the public to solicit their comments, and consult with interested Federal agencies. Such comments shall be duly reported in an addendum to the aquaculture management plan, along with a disposition of each. At a minimum, meetings under this subsection shall include—</text><paragraph id="H415F499B08A9442D9DC2B88249757058"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at least one public meeting for aquaculture stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AC51EEACCEC41F9AD056DCD08296421"><enum>(2)</enum><text>meetings with State, local, and Tribal government representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1692CEFC8C054B5B948099421A2D2268"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Required contents</header><text>An aquaculture management plan that is prepared by the Secretary under this title shall— </text><paragraph id="H45C1757F09A049D4AEA5425795647320"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include information and analysis that the Secretary determines is appropriate to establish common reference points for conducting aquaculture in the aquaculture opportunity area;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF33B8397EBDE43F299DB1D8DBA8FE9C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>specify parameters and guidance for conducting aquaculture in the aquaculture opportunity area, based on the information and analysis under paragraph (1), including—</text><subparagraph id="H7B73092FCEC348F082BDE26AF3F762F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the geographic boundaries of the aquaculture opportunity area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBEDFB12A5AF4C50BE90B9A80A9DD964"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of sites that each aquaculture opportunity area will support;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC628111D34824647A87838755EB0C0D6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the species allowed for aquaculture in the aquaculture opportunity area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D90E1847B8A454499BEDC891566947D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>standards for the structural integrity of aquaculture facilities to prevent the escape of cultured species; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7491A74407A44EE6A098687D085E1E29"><enum>(E)</enum><text>contingency plans that will be required, along with standards for such plans, for events including—</text><clause id="HACE2B39B4FAE414AA9421603311C1894"><enum>(i)</enum><text>severe weather;</text></clause><clause id="H2DDD2E5EA589426D96880AEA02538848"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>escape of cultured species;</text></clause><clause id="H5A7B502616BA4815BF567EA1C9A6919F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>situations affecting, or compromising, the health of cultured species; and</text></clause><clause id="H5CB8CD9BCB2D4A2E9A89AC26DED03128"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other contingencies the Secretary identifies;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F75D9C7BBEC4F9CB0F0D8AB9F80D38F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>describe how the Secretary will monitor aspects of aquaculture in the aquaculture opportunity area in order to support compliance with this Act, including—</text><subparagraph id="H178012D69994415B84ED7841BA4FAAAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>escape of cultured species;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07A9C9F51C4B4E00AF76382914D65639"><enum>(B)</enum><text>situations affecting, or compromising, the health of cultured species;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BEBBAEBFBE845BC8BCACFBF82A8C456"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the economic and commercial productivity of the aquaculture opportunity area; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H304DD29ABEAF458C9FBB34192BB5D935"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other matters the Secretary identifies; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H12A022DC251446909BC5E54FE068F14D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>prescribe such other measures, requirements, or conditions and restrictions as are determined to be necessary and appropriate for implementation of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFFBD9FD105B2491080FC747D51D9956C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementing regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and adopt regulations determined to be necessary and appropriate to implement an aquaculture management plan or plan amendment developed under this section. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7FDC559C62464D028AB69B670F56C375"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Periodic review</header><text>The Secretary shall periodically review plans developed under subsection (a) as needed, but not less often than once every 5 years, to determine whether changed circumstances, advances in science, or improved management practices warrant an amendment or update to the plan.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6598C9BBA03E4CD2B235060689935DE2"><enum>202.</enum><header>Offshore aquaculture permits</header><subsection id="HBB7F2320C4644E46ACE5750AAD41C809"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After the Secretary promulgates final regulations under section 404(a), the Secretary may issue an offshore aquaculture permit if the Secretary determines that—</text><paragraph id="HAA94F82248894F6C9D2D48AFE2151181"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the proposed offshore aquaculture facility, type of aquaculture operation, and cultured species are consistent with the purposes in section 2 and the national standards for sustainable offshore aquaculture in section 101;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39915284A07A4522B8E61425AF7068F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the proposed offshore aquaculture facility, type of aquaculture operation, and cultured species are consistent with an established aquaculture management plan, or the permit applicant has provided the Secretary with sufficient information and analysis, such as would be included in an established aquaculture management plan, to merit issuance, if the permit is intended to be located outside of an aquaculture opportunity area; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2E5555381B044AF8A9AC038AF556C61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the applicant is able to comply with this Act and any terms and conditions prescribed under section 404(a), is financially responsible, and will operate the offshore aquaculture facility using the best practicable technology and maintain it in good working order; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64FA2B5D9B974231A9BA8EFD6DFBF26D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>issuance of the offshore aquaculture permit is not prohibited under section 407.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74BC603B52374F8FB49BDFB95D119C2B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header><text>An offshore aquaculture permit holder shall be authorized to conduct offshore aquaculture consistent with—</text><paragraph id="HAB1743FF00994A679A0ADE4CF48FEECE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>this Act, including regulations promulgated to carry out this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B5E036D3598439381C6B946F063A345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>other applicable provisions of law, including regulations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90260C670A664328AE4222B402FA7730"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any terms or conditions imposed by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF51400EAC5DB41AFAA5024223B802E99"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Permit procedure</header><paragraph id="HA1E6782661614FF9BA0A8D4B1BA0D429"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An applicant for an offshore aquaculture permit shall submit an application to the Secretary. The application shall specify—</text><subparagraph id="H531451C58A9E4C619096FF032A879955"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the proposed location of the offshore aquaculture facility and the location of on-shore facilities used for propagation or rearing of cultured species, such as hatcheries or research operations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H323CE8A079504DDD9E610F1A1D266C10"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the type of aquaculture operations that will be conducted at all facilities described in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88823CC47E6C48538C4DF755BA6A7C38"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the cultured species, or a specified range of species, to be propagated or reared, or both, at the offshore aquaculture facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9091FF8D03C4D8C8552B1C71D99660A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the source of eggs, larvae, or juvenile cultured species that will be used in aquaculture operations, an analysis of the likely impacts on wild populations and habitats, such as prevention of the spread of pathogens, and the information upon which the assessment was made; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65AB949FB656456D8233B80B264DA3C4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>plans to respond to—</text><clause id="HD205B7022B91444080F99C064574781B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a natural disaster;</text></clause><clause id="H5E2B24D34D5B4C49B1828F19ADBB1BF6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an escapement; </text></clause><clause id="HD56CB70C595B4B7CAB69CF7635BC3491"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>disease; and</text></clause><clause id="HA1629D15CA7A49E3A062828F810D30B7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other circumstances designated by the Secretary; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42D0AE70213F47148AEF0ADE75657023"><enum>(F)</enum><text>such other design, construction, and operational information as the Secretary may require to ensure the integrity of the applicant’s operations and contingency planning.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8EF7D6B9D564BABB59FE5FD145584B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Whenever the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration receives an offshore aquaculture permit application, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCDA3DC1408784CB3BBD9875354716E5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide notice and a copy of the application to the Governor of every State or territory adjacent to or within 100 miles of the proposed site and to the federally recognized Indian Tribes within those States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H853BBE51667848A0BB9B92700E50139D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide public notice and an opportunity for public comment for a period of not less than 60 days for each offshore aquaculture permit application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C0E374A176D43A290CB496D2E95948C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Comments and consultation</header><text>The Secretary shall take any comments submitted by Governors and the public into consideration, and shall consult with interested aquaculture stakeholders as warranted before making a final decision on the disposition of an offshore aquaculture permit application.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD204E98970E54E66830847DB4416E864"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deadlines for consideration of applications for permits</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Secretary receives an offshore aquaculture permit application, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HEBE2E615214E419B9214CCC3AD83F3CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notify the applicant that the application is complete; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25952E61FB90463D911BE48851ABD248"><enum>(B)</enum><text>notify the applicant that information is missing and specify any information that is required to be submitted for the application to be complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H39BAC18BE990403A8274D32C1BA92FCE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Issuance or deferral</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the period for public comments on a completed application has concluded, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HFB6CDFE3A5D04F38883B22551CFB5F52"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issue the permit, if the application complies with the provisions of this Act, including the national standards for sustainable offshore aquaculture in section 101, requirements under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>), and other applicable law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CEC2E2402BC4C7EB53FEDA4C800570D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>defer the decision on the permit, if the Secretary determines that the application can be improved to meet the requirements of paragraph (1), and provide to the applicant a notice that specifies any steps that the applicant could take for the permit to be issued; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H152880D8A52B4AB98650809802550E37"><enum>(C)</enum><text>deny the permit, providing a justification for the Secretary's determination that the application does not meet the requirements of paragraph (1), or any other applicable law, and that these issues cannot be remediated.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0C37C8B4AA9427699EDA649394AF5AC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Extension of review</header><text>The Secretary may extend the review period for an additional 90 days if the Secretary determines that further time is needed to analyze the application. The Secretary may further extend the review period beyond the extension provided in the preceding sentence if the Secretary determines that the Department of Commerce needs more time to comply with applicable Federal law, provided that the Secretary’s determination states the specific actions the Department must undertake, together with deadlines for completing such actions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7048016EABD148A6B1871227E554746D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Permit requirements</header><paragraph id="H3A3B6525E8D14C0F9EF890FC5149A08A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An offshore aquaculture permit holder shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H7EC2A8E893CD421299BBDAB15B54D4B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a citizen or permanent resident of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCE5A249559342D7AD777124570A4F45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a corporation, partnership, or other entity that—</text><clause id="H0E0127E678CF422CB983DD35DCB2CFA0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is organized and existing under the laws of the United States or a U.S. State; and</text></clause><clause id="H799E10ADE65A459F95FECF1CBD9906F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not owned by a foreign nation or majority-controlled by a foreign nation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B8E4DC1DD9B466F828530E19E7E5B2D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header><text>Subject to subsection (n), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H8CB846A581804FE2BBFC2FDF6FCB43BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prescribe the terms and conditions that apply to each offshore aquaculture permit to achieve the national standards for sustainable offshore aquaculture in section 101, and an applicable aquaculture management plan and implementing regulations developed under section 201; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5FA40137A9D4FD2916296207A2F09B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>specify in each offshore aquaculture permit the duration, size, and location of the offshore aquaculture facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7DE9BEB9F5A466C940E9AC61D021C04"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Statutes and regulations</header><text>Offshore aquaculture permits are subject to this Act, regulations promulgated pursuant thereto, and other statutes and regulations in existence upon the effective date of the permit. When promulgating regulations, the Secretary shall indicate whether and to what extent the regulations apply to existing offshore aquaculture permits. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD76082CB5393446A94AF5763272EF4F8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duration</header><paragraph id="H1E0AFA5AC9DF4B45A2317D3E6C353B2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), an offshore aquaculture permit shall have an initial 15-year duration, and may be renewed subject to the terms of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E0CC430C596407FBE563B6D8A6569EA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="H74A8210AF64F48F7AC2AFDF017F95D6F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Aquaculture opportunity areas</header><text>A permit issued for offshore aquaculture to be conducted in an aquaculture opportunity area as provided in section 102 shall have an initial 25-year duration. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF748F0B2E5154FBCB91A0B8C09EDBC26"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Outer continental shelf</header><text>The Secretary shall develop the duration of an offshore aquaculture permit subject to subsection (o)(1), in consultation with the Secretary of the Interior, except that the permit shall expire not later than the date that the lessee or the lessee’s operator submits, to the Secretary of the Interior, a final application for the decommissioning and removal of an existing facility upon which an offshore aquaculture facility is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8FBF269AB4524981B8EFDA5A12E0592A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Transfer</header><text>A permit may be transferred as provided under this subsection, provided that the permit is still valid, and has not been amended due to emergency circumstances. To propose a transfer, a permittee shall submit an application to the Secretary, and the Secretary shall review and make a determination of whether to approve, deny, or request additional information not later than 60 days after the date of receipt of the application. The application shall include—</text><paragraph id="HF493087E282F490EB290DCCB01FB75D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>notice to the Secretary of the intention to transfer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EF119AAC9F74B7B94F7E07A1E95FD69"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the reason for the transfer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB504A27B409341398451E1F1109C8DB6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the identity of the transferee, and whether the transferee holds, has held, or is applying for a permit under this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA2C8E5BB2184541A5262C88DAA2ACBE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the transferee’s assumption of responsibility, coverage, and liability for activities performed under the permit, as of the effective date of the transfer; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E1394C0C2EF47C5B452121790736481"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any additional information requested by the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C08DF2DC4DF49F9B296527D4C43A4E0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>The Secretary may renew an offshore aquaculture permit that has not been revoked for an additional 15-year period, as provided in subsection (e), before the end of the original permit’s duration, if—</text><paragraph id="H834569FCBD7545EDAA0F641E92A5E070"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the permit or amended permit complies with existing requirements;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8006D8B0207546F9B92A344BB12FB2C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the permit holder has not been subject to sanctions under section 408 or committed a prohibited act under such section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DDDA90F225C48BA831FCF828A753026"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the permit has not been modified because of emergency considerations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E166C687DAD443A984E012E33A2BB09"><enum>(4)</enum><text>notice under subsection (c)(2) has been given.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD4154E844C4348A0A44CF4724754B5FD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>The Secretary may, pursuant to regulations issued under this Act, revoke an offshore aquaculture permit, if—</text><paragraph id="HCB141F8A420342C08AE944D7FF625CD8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the permit holder commits a prohibited act under section 407;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29387E83DEB34597B7471CF253A525B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the permit holder fails to begin offshore aquaculture operations within 2 years from the date the required Federal permits are obtained; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1501E8B476F74D919A720623D376255A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>there is an interruption of offshore aquaculture operations of at least 2 years in duration that is unrelated to best management practices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9DA9F7AEDF834433A7A9BE4ED905718D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Expiration or revocation</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the expiration or revocation of an offshore aquaculture permit, a permit holder shall—</text><paragraph id="H91E03E8705F5461FAD450AB8EA76B0E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>remove all structures, gear, and other property from the offshore aquaculture facility site; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA97C44E3CF1445C290DF97172E4FF41C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>take such other measures to restore the site, as the Secretary considers necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F9FF4B46E884FD39550B6660019221C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Emergency determination</header><text>If the Secretary determines that an emergency exists that poses a significant risk to the safety of humans, to the marine environment, to cultured species, or to the security of the United States and that requires suspension, modification, or revocation of an offshore aquaculture permit, the Secretary may suspend, modify, or revoke the permit for such time as the Secretary determines is necessary to address the emergency. The Secretary shall afford the permit holder a prompt post-suspension, post-modification, or post-revocation opportunity to be heard regarding the suspension, modification, or revocation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC3ED9F2FCAEA46FAA03A0F6FDDD1D51D"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Fees</header><paragraph id="HBBB66AFF210F415A818E80C301EF0F45"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><subparagraph id="HA49099B6AD864558BE67ED7F75FCE1EB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may establish, by regulation, application fees and annual offshore aquaculture permit fees under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7A6ED5EE93041C38FF2E613992E3588"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deposit and collection</header><text>The fees described in subparagraph (A) shall be deposited as offsetting collections in the operations, research, and facilities account of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. Fees may be collected and made available to the extent provided in advance in appropriation Acts.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE0533D5A2C84F97B1A8F5201B479FD7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Setting of fees</header><text>The fees described in subparagraph (A) shall be set as an amount such that the total revenue from such fees does not exceed the amount required to cover the costs of management, data collection, analysis, annual inspection, and enforcement activities related to permits under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H21119EEC6C704367A67688B1F17F6D50"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary may waive, in whole or in part, any fee under this section if an offshore aquaculture facility is used primarily for research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF379B17C24ED41D98887E4CA6C93A846"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Guarantees</header><text>The Secretary shall require a permit holder to post a bond or other form of financial guarantee in an amount determined by the Secretary, to be reasonable and commensurate with the offshore aquaculture operation and as sufficient to cover, without duplication—</text><subparagraph id="H85A21BE0E1CD4CA5B6A43E039C8D60FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any unpaid fees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A74FECD118F490CA8FB64C1F6017C4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the cost of removing an offshore aquaculture facility at the expiration or revocation of an offshore aquaculture permit; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD49CCDBBB7A94856952525923BDB2CE0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the cost of site remediation for impacts arising from authorized activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5BF2DA527CAC4EA4BE1248693067A3F2"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act</header><text>Beginning on the effective date of the final regulations promulgated under section 404, the conduct of offshore aquaculture that is in accordance with an offshore aquaculture permit issued under this section shall not be considered fishing for purposes of the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1801">16 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), but shall be considered a fishery under section 3 of the Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1362">16 U.S.C. 1362</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDBA0ED81576F4951920AE2600DB2D100"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Compatibility with other uses</header><text>Each Federal agency implementing this section, person subject to this section, and coastal State seeking to review a permit application under this section shall comply with the applicable provisions of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>), including regulations promulgated to carry out such Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAF2333E3473548A596B16ABA3A6C4DB1"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Statutory construction</header><text>An offshore aquaculture permit issued under this section shall not supersede or substitute for any other authorization required under Federal or State laws.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBF2B9DDAADD1449F901F5142F3B3AEE6"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Actions affecting the outer continental shelf</header><paragraph id="HBD3E6364C0E94F39AD0B3382958E2677"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification of Secretary of the Interior</header><text>The Secretary shall notify the Secretary of the Interior for each application for an offshore aquaculture permit that is located on the outer continental shelf.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CFED650588D4729A2AFE0F378C95195"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prior consent required</header><text>An offshore aquaculture facility may not be located on a lease, right-of-use and easement, or right-of-way authorized or permitted under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>) without the prior consent of any lessee and other owner of operating interest.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCA65AA60E084B82A6335BDA348B63C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance review</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall review each agreement between a prospective offshore aquaculture operator and a lessee. The Secretary of the Interior shall approve such agreement if it is consistent with the Federal lease terms, the Department of the Interior regulations, and the Secretary of the Interior’s role in the protection of the marine environment, property, and human life or health. An agreement under this subsection shall—</text><subparagraph id="H14793FC0E83F43ABBF54A7F742F5E9F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be part of the information reviewed under paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CF0F51937CF422DADF6521F22EE1194"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not be subject to a separate Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>) review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D1DFAFCDB994DC5A7DA680B5AAC80FF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordinated Coastal Zone Management Act review</header><subparagraph id="H4E3B00980F27440E85F25E4FD43A31F3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>State review</header><clause id="HF6F4731702CB48DB87058D2B6AD22B5B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A coastal State’s review under the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>) shall include any modification or change to a lessee’s approved plan that results from, or is necessary for, the issuance of an offshore aquaculture permit if the State simultaneously receives—</text><subclause id="H683D00B707A048AB95BEE94FF806E8FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the information related to the modification or change; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF25AFA29EF6E4117BC109574ABBD7F3B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the offshore aquaculture permit applicant’s consistency certification.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H002B1E6F78DF493DA5FEE0CF0712B8A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Simultaneous receipt</header><text>If the coastal State simultaneously receives the information related to a modification or change to a lessee’s approved plan and the offshore aquaculture permit applicant’s consistency certification, then—</text><subclause id="H87F5904B0DA243F486EA8E1C28B3DC0C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a lessee shall not be required to submit a separate consistency certification for the modification or change under section 307(c)(3)(B) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1456">16 U.S.C. 1456(c)(3)(B)</external-xref>); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D432F4C5B074F359D65E5FD6A6F84C2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the coastal State’s concurrence (or presumed concurrence) or objection to the consistency certification for the offshore aquaculture permit under section 307(c)(3)(A) of such Act shall apply both—</text><item id="H7E66AAD153C44B67BCBCECF34331CA8A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>to the offshore aquaculture permit; and</text></item><item id="H41E1E0CE32634294B478B6976D132FF8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>to any related modification or change to a lessee’s plan approved under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AAE78ACB2924F5192F735432C8130CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State review under section <enum-in-header>307(c)(3)(B)</enum-in-header> of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972</header><text>To the extent that a coastal State is not authorized by section 307(c)(3)(A) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1456">16 U.S.C. 1456(c)(3)(A)</external-xref>) to review an offshore aquaculture permit application submitted under this Act, then a modification or change to a lessee’s approved plan shall be subject to coastal State review under section 307(c)(3)(B) of such Act if a consistency certification for the modification or change is required under applicable Federal regulations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A388ACA286849CF9C6A8AA7B35C8AD3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text><clause id="HD148E3B2A6CA4DF6908E14CCD25F5430"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Lessee’s approved plan</header><text>The term <term>lessee’s approved plan</term> includes a document for which a consistency certification is required under applicable Federal regulations, such as a change to the approved plan for decommissioning a facility.</text></clause><clause id="H43F02DD10A2B478F9A15EA6527B9A2E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Offshore aquaculture permit applicant</header><text>The term <term>offshore aquaculture permit applicant</term> means an applicant for an offshore aquaculture permit under this section that—</text><subclause id="HCE0E970EE85349168FCAAE0B18DE67D6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>will locate the proposed facility in an area that would require consent from the lessee as described in paragraph (2); and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE0E2D99A07E6402989006B4544ADA0D5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is required to submit a consistency certification for its offshore aquaculture application under section 307(c)(3)(A) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1456">16 U.S.C. 1456(c)(3)(A)</external-xref>) to the coastal State.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4C0CF1C648D949CB93CE3BC88F59D487"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Offshore aquaculture permit application</header><text>The term <term>offshore aquaculture permit application</term> means an application for an offshore aquaculture permit under this section that will locate the proposed facility in an area that would require consent from the lessee as described in paragraph (2).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6262B899019948DD9AC5ADEEAE1F18D2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Joint and several liability</header><text>For offshore aquaculture located on a facility described under this subsection, a permit holder and each party that is or was a lessee of the lease on which the facility is located during the term of the offshore aquaculture permit shall be jointly and severally liable for the removal of any construction or modification related to the offshore aquaculture operations if a bond or other form of financial guarantee under subsection (j)(3) for aquaculture operations is insufficient to cover those obligations. This paragraph shall not affect any obligation to decommission the facility under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A46653779CE4F0F8FFBDB6214BB99A9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Additional authority</header><subparagraph id="HD04184E17F31408582D19E2D834578D6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior may, to carry out this subsection—</text><clause id="HF894C29C8C744EFEB29406AC75BEB2BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>promulgate rules and regulations as necessary and appropriate;</text></clause><clause id="H00C31581BF964D27A3273C113FA89B83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require and enforce any additional terms or conditions that the Secretary of the Interior considers necessary to ensure the compatibility of aquaculture operations with activities for which permits, authorizations, leases, negotiated agreements, right-of-way, or right-of-use and easement were issued under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="HFAE7C22D69E9435B89B5BF47909F86F7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>issue an order to an offshore aquaculture permit holder to take any action the Secretary of the Interior considers necessary to ensure safe operations on the facility, and to protect the marine environment, property, or human life or health;</text></clause><clause id="HDD64C51BAB6F445AA5441975B16B832A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>require and enforce any additional terms or conditions that the Secretary of the Interior considers necessary—</text><subclause id="HA88D4DF974864EAFA62740ED21F286F0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to protect the marine environment, property, or human life or health; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0D1EDF393AFE4BECB0ED736030C7E875"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to ensure the compatibility of aquaculture operations with activities for which permits were issued under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H186C353B93B84980815EC245A4677B70"><enum>(v)</enum><text>enforce all requirements contained in the regulations, lease terms and conditions, and orders under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41957FB2D4444A7D90F9CD596EFE0E73"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Interpretation</header><text>Failure to comply with any order issued under subparagraph (A)(iii) shall constitute a violation of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDEDC44F4909743B3AB54D4BEFBB14ED0"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Assurance of animal health</header><paragraph id="H568C6D77D12B4325A93FF38CBE718224"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this section shall affect the authority of the Secretary of Agriculture to—</text><subparagraph id="HEF97DFBA8CB94CB6BAF6771F5ACD1580"><enum>(A)</enum><text>carry out the Animal Health Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/8301">7 U.S.C. 8301 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to cultured species in the exclusive economic zone; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BEB60B62F6D44C4A13B5AEE9470DA48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operate as the lead Federal agency for providing animal health oversight for cultured species in the exclusive economic zone, including animal health and disease risk assessments.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10742D158FDC48BE809751289793A873"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contingency plans</header><text>As part of an application for a permit for offshore aquaculture or as part of an aquaculture management plan established in section 201, the Secretary of Agriculture may approve contingency plans, along with standards for such plans, for events relating to situations affecting the health of cultured species.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0EE2B8D6ACF423580692296775759C5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria for practicing veterinary medicine in waters outside State jurisdiction</header><text>A veterinarian may practice veterinary medicine in waters outside State jurisdiction if the veterinarian—</text><subparagraph id="H2B5C5DBA24ED4A3FB8062546963CE4BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is licensed and in good standing to practice veterinary medicine in any State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91F56523CE564A7EABEA410FD9D487BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holds a category II veterinary accreditation from the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C530BD636204774A54CB78C296CF598"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has a valid veterinarian client-patient relationship with the facility in which the individual is practicing veterinary medicine.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H986415BA74464ABE991D6ECF80D95CFF"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall supersede permit applications in process on the date of enactment of this Act or permits that are in place on the date of enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="HF74E21EBA90144E9ABC3F7BF2F1C6100"><enum>203.</enum><header>Research and development grant program</header><subsection id="H5F8DC678FE4545AAA0F59B13F8B55AF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish, in consultation with applicable Federal agencies, coastal States, federally recognized Indian Tribes, Regional Fishery Management Councils, academic institutions, and interested aquaculture stakeholders, a research and development grant program to further the purposes of this Act. In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary shall consider using existing programs that leverage State and local partnerships and take advantage of the extramural research community, including the National Sea Grant College Program under the National Sea Grant College Program Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1121">33 U.S.C. 1121 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H8CFD7E5E6A31404B9128E8512313049C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Components</header><text>The research and development grant program described in subsection (a) shall include research conducted internally by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and through the award of competitive, peer-reviewed grants to fund research and extension services—</text><paragraph id="HCD7509EDB20D4BA1B3C1A4E322BEDD5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to create innovative design and engineering solutions to common obstacles within the offshore aquaculture industry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CF11E99A072403BA849C38DD2F9B60B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to enable the transition of innovative aquaculture technologies, including technologies focused on the commercialization of high-value marine species, from controlled studies to commercial use;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H820E85550020412FA55362E13A5564E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to evaluate the role of genetics in relation to the development of improved lines of brood stock, disease resistance, and interactions between cultured species and wild stocks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2B1031157A84D82AAB249F95DE45814"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to advance research into the management, mitigation, and prevention of cultured species diseases;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H426A13BFC25B4C419084CE30FFE672E2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to develop cost-effective feeds to optimize the sustainable use of protein and lipid sources originating from wild fish, plants, and other sources, maximize growth and production performance of cultured species, prevent the spread of pathogens and parasites, and maintain the human health benefits of cultured seafood; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H635A02E15FC148579C3CDB2A8FE849BD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to improve techniques for monitoring, assessing, and addressing environmental impacts of offshore aquaculture and develop and evaluate methodologies to prevent, minimize, and mitigate potential adverse environmental impacts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H574C303A512B4F1C9606862065289702"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to evaluate the potential for offshore aquaculture to serve as a tool for environmental management, including connections to water quality, watershed management, and fishery conservation and management;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98690E83CBBD48F7AF13E3DA3644330F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to evaluate the potential impact of offshore aquaculture on the economies of coastal communities, particularly those dependent on traditional fishery resources;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H638D67CD9B2F4F5B9A08116D64907B3A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>to identify barriers to entry in the offshore aquaculture industry and propose solutions to overcome them;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9EC8C212E4B4513A6E84177F6369E23"><enum>(10)</enum><text>to study the traditional aquaculture methods and practices of Native Americans, Alaska Natives, and Native Hawaiians to evaluate economic, environmental, and sociological impacts; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E9C3800B68E4B92BF6FB2E2C11033DC"><enum>(11)</enum><text>to investigate other priority issues identified by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9A0D847C4E74BD19C0F73366A9653A1"><enum>(12)</enum><text>to evaluate economic aspects of offshore aquaculture, including production costs and market development. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0CD0A08761B44F65A13C7C5E5F3DFFFF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination with other Federal programs</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H28C5CA0627A54FB6A7F5E1558FD356D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate aquaculture research and development intramural programs and grants within the Department of Commerce and with other Federal intramural and extramural programs that provide grant funding for purposes similar to those under subsection (b), such as grants administered by the National Sea Grant College Program and the National Institute of Standards and Technology; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D7A47F759874A9490F36F25E02ED1F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate the research and development grant program established in this section with the interagency aquaculture coordinating group established under section 6 of the National Aquaculture Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2805">16 U.S.C. 2805</external-xref>) and with the research and development conducted through the Cooperative Extension System of the Department of Agriculture.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A8053175B974A6793573B0367AF3225"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cooperative research agreement</header><text>To carry out this section, the Secretary may enter into a cooperative agreement with a State, institution of higher education, or other private institution or research center.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1718FF11883F410CA918F3952EC25685"><enum>204.</enum><header>Economic soundness</header><subsection id="H1813101D5FF540649727F255204F76AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 53708 of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE27C27433B444FCA86DEAFE3A929253A"><subsection commented="no" id="H538938242DC044AB9E7848D376C4531C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Aquaculture</header><text>In making the findings under subsections (a) and (b), the Administrator and the Secretary may take into account factors such as—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H0AC16E7B1766431CBDF6B72AB57798C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text> the transferability of an aquaculture permit; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H03EAC4F1AA114378A5007B71868F70E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assessment of the shore-side seafood economy where the borrower will be operating; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H625D6F182BDC43D6B8E427C5C017DF1F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the existence of a formal technical assistance program administered by a governmental agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></title><title id="H9BE7AB1E7ECF4FB29C9599CA57A17453" style="OLC"><enum>III</enum><header>Refinements</header><section id="HEFC7197A1F994456AF4C3616A6F1F96B"><enum>301.</enum><header>Recordkeeping, inspections, and access to information</header><subsection id="HABF5E16FA3304A5BA305A63CC9503B53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary, after consultation with other interested Federal departments and agencies, shall prescribe by regulation—</text><paragraph id="HA8D1438EA99E4E5DA70BDDAB9A093EFA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the records that an offshore aquaculture permit holder is required to establish and maintain;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD25204CDAA7742448A0C4A3CFC44D1EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the reports that an offshore aquaculture permit holder is required to make;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H470BDCF60F964912B3156C3062D37F6F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the information that an offshore aquaculture permit holder is required to provide, which shall at a minimum include—</text><subparagraph id="H43DDFC806C8E483AA5DAE830129A2739"><enum>(A)</enum><text>data regarding escape events;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10548C0C78374955A1920E2CB8EC2DEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the prevalence of disease in the offshore aquaculture facility, including a description of veterinary services provided for treatment; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD7DAEC801154D25B5399144AE02C697"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a copy of any required incident or annual report required under a permit necessary for aquaculture operations under other Federal law; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8340A821371E4267BD95D56D81A8E246"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other information, as the Secretary may require; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DB2BA9D2432464DB7B1BC0C9D4F3739"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other recordkeeping that an offshore aquaculture permit holder is required to satisfy, as necessary to carry out this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B7A9C8FB73D43E48905FB4B8D0D120F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulatory consistency</header><text>The regulations under subsection (a) may not amend, contradict, or duplicate regulations under any other Federal law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H624C2CE3E9A94A6597B58FFD7C77B4E0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Recordkeeping</header><text>An offshore aquaculture permit holder shall—</text><paragraph id="HBE1A5EB7395E45D680F2DE9FCBB349EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>comply with the recordkeeping regulations under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71FA6C2FE10D4BE7B0D533EF5AAFAF86"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit such reports, and make such records and information available as the Secretary may request.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE4DC7FEB1B44E979A301063559A809F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Inspections</header><paragraph id="H705E8179EBD04A08BFD4A0621548DED5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an annual inspection of offshore aquaculture facilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4456A3DC09546E5A40D8DCE44C922AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The Secretary shall provide reasonable notice prior to site inspections at offshore aquaculture facilities pursuant to paragraph (1). The Secretary shall take into consideration biosecurity concerns and work with the permit holder to ensure best inspection practices to ensure safety and protect cultured species.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38A203AEC4A34551B16574EED09B7F02"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Facilities located on the outer continental shelf</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior, or a designee of such Secretary, is authorized with inspection authority under this section for offshore aquaculture facilities located on the outer continental shelf. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB845937BD0A5405998E829156DB0E6EF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Government access</header><text>Any Federal Government official representing an agency with authority for implementing and enforcing Federal law applicable to offshore aquaculture shall have reasonable access to an offshore aquaculture facility for which a permit is issued under this Act for the purpose of enforcing the Federal law under the official’s jurisdiction or otherwise carrying out the official’s responsibilities. Such an official, relative to their jurisdictional authority, may inspect, at reasonable times, appropriate records, files, papers, permits, processes, controls, and the offshore aquaculture facility and may test any feature of the offshore aquaculture facility, provided testing does not risk incurring damage or potentially compromise the structural integrity of the facility or the health of cultured species. Each inspection shall be conducted with reasonable promptness. The permit holder shall receive timely notification, in writing, of the results of the inspection. </text></subsection><subsection id="H1FFA8CB1775046B9959C26079C657721"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Public access</header><text>The Secretary shall make reports and other information received under this Act available to the public unless the Secretary determines it is necessary to withhold disclosure to protect confidential business information or sensitive personal information. The Secretary shall establish procedures to protect confidential business information and sensitive personal information from being disclosed.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD71E5D2A36D949CB8D4E9895280EDBD4"><enum>302.</enum><header>Marine feed standards</header><subsection commented="no" id="H53A2D38156D249E38DCF104403CE6C30"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relation to current law</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed in derogation of applicable law regarding the production of animal feed, and offshore aquaculture operations shall comply with all applicable law (including regulations).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC1F78AACF4C6403A80295717CA912729"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements for fisheries-Derived marine feed ingredients</header><text>The Secretary shall require that fish meal, or any fisheries-derived marine feed ingredients (both first-use and trimmings), used at offshore aquaculture facilities in the exclusive economic zone—</text><paragraph id="HEB6598A90B154CDF90BE419965DD8030"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are sourced from a sustainably managed fishery for aquaculture feed; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4A62B2E11A647C79B626B17764A24B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>employ traceability sufficient to credibly demonstrate the ingredients were sourced from a sustainably managed fishery for aquaculture feed; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H896542838E8A44298B469CBA914C71E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>are harvested and produced without convict, forced, or indentured labor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE985C9F049744B3ACCA28FF2A77D414"><enum>(4)</enum><text>are delivered to the cultured species as part of a formulated feed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA5D4937B48DD49889FDD83011C70E72D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Study on best practices for marine feed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Advancing the Quality and Understanding of American Aquaculture Act</short-title>, the Secretaries of Commerce and Agriculture, through the coordinating group, shall conduct a study of the best management practices related to sustainable, economic feed for the United States marine aquaculture industry. The study shall— </text><paragraph commented="no" id="H133C91E97B59475DB6D49691425B17B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recommend best practices for sourcing fish meal from sustainably managed fisheries for aquaculture feed;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H773F918DD1094BB6BF0705CB65FA6598"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommend best practices to provide traceability on the source of fish meal ingredients;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6352DF1EC88C4FF28131B1E5DF2FADE0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommend best practices for sourcing formulated feed ingredients from domestic sources; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCF372B9BE9C74910B3038469DC58062F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommend best practices for harvesting and producing fish meal so that it can be known that it is harvested and produced without convict, forced, or indentured labor.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H57F5D6C10CE74F2290D6A697C5639819"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Upon completion of the study under subsection (c), the Secretaries of Commerce and Agriculture shall prepare and submit a report containing the recommendations described in subsection (c) to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives.</text></subsection></section><section id="H72B2520B564E4200B7EFB3CB741D5CE6"><enum>303.</enum><header>Marine use rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The permit established under section 202 shall be considered a marine use right, offering security of tenure for purpose of obtaining investment, transferring permit to other authorized users, and allowing for operations.</text></section></title><title id="HB158F945CB4947629831C83BF891247B" style="OLC"><enum>IV</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header><section id="HFE9B1FA483684C4FBC87439DC6F43A24"><enum>401.</enum><header>Office of Aquaculture</header><subsection id="H4CB1AF8F54B744428832E05BC261A730"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office of Aquaculture</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and provide resources for—</text><paragraph id="H616BF5AB3B1748928F34EBFC923ED2AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an Office of Aquaculture within the National Marine Fisheries Service at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration headquarters to implement this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A31AE1ECDB041969AEEE37A75698C29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an Office of Aquaculture presence in each of the regional fisheries offices of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, which presence shall, at a minimum, be sufficient to fulfill the duties under subsection (b), but may be increased to the extent warranted by the activity and interest of aquaculture stakeholders in the region.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B6D46F11625499F86163583AFB31F16"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office of Aquaculture duties</header><text>The Office of Aquaculture shall—</text><paragraph id="HE5B523403BF34601AA0E2E8711E5BE25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure the implementation of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9579016F1BBD486DA6E048725A8821D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate regulatory, scientific, outreach, and international issues related to aquaculture within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7400FF3BCC0040B589E005395C0BF22E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>collaborate with and leverage existing efforts by the National Sea Grant College program to—</text><subparagraph id="HA1D42F61298347AF999D58D9420F9266"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct aquaculture outreach, education, extension services, and training efforts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22121F8D70E74DB583F16B79A7B4E706"><enum>(B)</enum><text>engage with aquaculture stakeholders and, from time to time, convene conferences for aquaculture stakeholders to exchange information and ideas; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CBCCD35655343F18B8BE3E61EB8A01C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>maintain aquaculture capacity in each of the regional fisheries offices of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, including at least one Regional Aquaculture Coordinator in each such office.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D9F2EFE1FF446E3A5461BD7C27AC224"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Aquaculture research program and duties</header><text>In addition to the resources required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall establish and provide additional resources for an aquaculture research program that draws upon the scientific capacity of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration programs such as the Fisheries Science Centers, Sea Grant, and the National Centers for Coastal and Ocean Science to support the Office of Aquaculture’s efforts to implement this title. Specifically, the program shall—</text><paragraph id="HC58FA9E0726449D2A27D4CAED0D156A7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that offshore aquaculture operations permitted under this title are scientifically monitored to support the implementation of this Act, evaluate data, and conduct additional research to support the development of sustainable offshore aquaculture in accordance with this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE74FAD4C147D498A9C23CFEA70C173F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administer the research and development grant program under section 203. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H177E3732AF154B278E3A7CC8016F1CC8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Aquaculture Subcommittee</header><text>The Marine Fisheries Advisory Committee shall designate the Aquaculture Subcommittee as a permanent, standing subcommittee to serve as an external board to advise the Secretary on offshore aquaculture. The Aquaculture Subcommittee shall coordinate with the National Sea Grant Advisory Board, as appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H80767DC7A7C64C61A174FB71BE024708"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Budget presentation</header><text>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall transmit its budget request for the Office of Aquaculture as a separate line with the National Marine Fisheries Service.</text></subsection></section><section id="H37041F2B2F754ABD9FF6A3E3B2902A8E"><enum>402.</enum><header>Support for industry</header><subsection id="HAE451ED2B1854D418E9B284296904C65"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall support the development of sustainable marine aquaculture, consistent with this Act and other applicable Federal law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5DE08ADC9E794CE2A37F7F2294CD5D66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Marketing and promotion grants</header><text>The Secretary shall, in consultation with industry, establish and administer a grant program to support the sale and public perception of cultured species domestically and internationally.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4E3180E4B1994CB1B9896CB3386422B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Workforce development</header><text>The Secretary shall, in consultation with industry, academic institutions, and the National Sea Grant College Program, develop and manage a grant program to support the education and training of individuals with the skills needed to manage and operate aquaculture facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA53B39395D154185A3860FCD5A3ACDF7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regional networks</header><text>The Secretary shall organize through each regional fisheries office of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration a network of—</text><paragraph id="HE0C97D8A39DB403EBB90FD43ECBEB81D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>regional experts and Federal agency contacts, in coordination with relevant organizations (including the National Sea Grant College Program under the National Sea Grant College Program Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1121">33 U.S.C. 1121 et seq.</external-xref>), the Department of Agriculture Regional Aquaculture Centers, institutions of higher education, and the Cooperative Extension System of the Department of Agriculture) to provide technical expertise and extension services on offshore aquaculture and information on Federal permit requirements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21F8410338E74C0BB591B102E7AB528E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>individuals and businesses interested in aquaculture operations and products to facilitate professional development, marketing, mentoring opportunities, and agency outreach and education on aquaculture. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H130509A74EC94DA180D104276630919C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Aquaculture database</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and maintain within the Office of Aquaculture an aquaculture database. The aquaculture database shall include information on research, technologies, monitoring techniques, best practices, and advisory board recommendations. The Secretary shall make the aquaculture database available in a manner that safeguards confidential business information. The inclusion of information in the database under this subsection shall not be considered to be publication for purposes of subsection (a) or (b) of section 102 of title 35, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H63DDE0D962694269B1F1F0F9586C63D8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical assistance for operators</header><text>The Secretary shall organize through the Office of Aquaculture and the Regional Aquaculture Coordinators, a program to provide technical assistance to operators in each regional fisheries office of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. The programs shall be tailored to meet the unique needs of each region, but shall conduct individual consultations with each operator in the region on a regular basis to assess the status of the operator’s business, and if appropriate, identify available resources to support the operator, such as regional experts, university extension agents, and grant opportunities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3031135E631349AC8A23A137CBD35C01"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Capital markets</header><paragraph id="HD0F654E13C2B4C179A7344551FF7B137"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Outreach to financial institutions</header><text>In order to enhance access to capital markets, the Secretary shall provide financial institutions and investment firms with objective, science-based information on offshore aquaculture and the Federal regulatory regime that governs it.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A7A2D6B941F4EB2846AA3F5E2143B34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Economic analysis</header><text>In addition, the Secretary shall provide economic analysis to answer queries regarding the value of offshore aquaculture assets to secure financing, such as equipment, governmental permits, inventory, and intellectual property.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69327F3EE4214DD1AEAA3EF997BAE730"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In order to achieve the goals of this subsection, the Secretary is encouraged to collaborate with the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of the Treasury, and the regional networks established under subsection (d). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3BED84B45E924380BA90ADCAB3DD24C1"><enum>403.</enum><header>Outreach and education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct outreach on sustainable offshore aquaculture to promote understanding, science-based decision making, and commercial adoption. The Secretary shall use appropriate means to engage—</text><paragraph id="HB3636D802FB54CE5B2001475DF13DA9F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the general public;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB028429A110845A7A7959A6DA6D860D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>community leaders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D29AD6D84E74F3EA3A00F0400EFC1BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>governmental officials;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD193238891E448D49FFDC1CC5C9CF8EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the business community;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E8AD6C001DA4687A10A9F68C822DA84"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the academic community; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B3EDFD6346C4C0BBE554E887F20F5A5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the nonprofit sector.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H9FB700C189E7475EA248F768EED98F72"><enum>404.</enum><header>Administration</header><subsection id="H615A3968C33D4713BFA3A966926F95EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary—</text><paragraph id="H163C8109E5A846728C652FEBA19627C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall initiate a rulemaking process, not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, after consulting with relevant Federal agencies, coastal States, federally recognized Indian Tribes within the meaning of such term in Executive Order 13175 (65 Fed. Reg. 67249), the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Regional Fishery Management Councils as established under section 302 of the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1852">16 U.S.C. 1852</external-xref>), and interstate fisheries commissions to implement this Act, including— </text><subparagraph id="HCAB5971E3121433AB9A8C40D6BFBFF26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>procedures to issue, modify, deny, revoke, or suspend an offshore aquaculture permit in accordance with this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27F5D3AD1E524B4EA9EFF80E4D68782A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>procedures to coordinate the offshore aquaculture permitting process, with similar or complementary activities administered by other Federal agencies, federally recognized Indian Tribes, and coastal States; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4D62D2B088640D2920F4B8885D8D980"><enum>(C)</enum><text>procedures to monitor and evaluate permit compliance to verify and confirm compliance with the requirements of this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H453BE9F695344CBF9EC31B0ED8A300D8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>procedures to transfer an offshore aquaculture permit from an original permit holder to a person that meets the requirements under section 202;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A4B557AC3614DEC8E033510E360D16B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>procedures to minimize conflicts with existing uses in the exclusive economic zone;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFCA1994C35B4027BF4F5D4BFE88F691"><enum>(F)</enum><text>procedures to consider public-private partnerships; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71255C62E4CB46528D86B3210C93E7C1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>standards for determining what types of feed may be employed in an offshore aquaculture facility in accordance with the requirements of section 302;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FBF8750FD2649599FB3FF6DBC7935CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall promulgate such additional regulations as are necessary and appropriate to carry out this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37F18A7DA73D4D099A46077196C54E75"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may amend a regulation at any time.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H702353F58D1341CCB6F75F676AB7FAA8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>The Secretary may enter into and perform such contracts, leases, or cooperative agreements, and make and receive such grants or funds, as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F674DA004364249AC87753DA89F9C99"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of contributed governmental resources</header><text>For enforcement under this Act, the Secretary may use, with consent and with or without reimbursement, and consistent with applicable law, the land, services, equipment, personnel, and facilities of—</text><paragraph id="HEAAA316B3590419BB13815D4D9B9D646"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1823910BCB4D4AAA9EC01667A8288B95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any State, local government, Tribal government, territory, or possession (or any political subdivision thereof);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE91E7265663840AC9B81B146134B1AB5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any foreign government; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28F4B6480CE541F4A291F976F056427F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an international organization.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE58147E7CC534ED6B6BFA96318AA3C4B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority To use grant funds</header><paragraph id="H5D211EFE15C04D58ABC5FE83A732B938"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided under paragraph (2), the Secretary may apply for, accept, and obligate research grant funding from any Federal source operating a competitive grant program if the funding furthers the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA107C784C7154D2181AB77E274FB75C1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Secretary may not apply for, accept, or obligate any research grant funding under paragraph (1) if the granting agency lacks authority to grant funds to Federal agencies or for any purpose, or subject to any condition, that is prohibited by law or regulation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18E488CD49EE44A69429EDA4E247E39C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Matching grant funds</header><text>Appropriated funds may be used to satisfy a requirement to match grant funds with recipient agency funds, except that no grant may be accepted that requires a commitment in advance of appropriations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B5AD01849044EF8BF70F299A89763F7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Accounts</header><text>Funds received from a grant shall be deposited in the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration account that serves to accomplish the purpose for which the grant was awarded.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7FC1D26186CE4359BAD36786854885BC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reservation of authority</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to displace, supersede, or limit the jurisdiction, responsibilities, or rights of any Federal or State agency, or Indian Tribe or Alaska Native organization, under any Federal law or treaty.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2CFA427DEBD94AA7AAB998AB6806CC23"><enum>405.</enum><header>Report and permit terms</header><subsection id="H1F80C133DF1F41439F8E8120DFCF7077"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue a report to the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives regarding implementation of this Act. The report shall include—</text><paragraph id="H0A5609410FF844ED865B08C1CE4A5F97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of offshore aquaculture permits applied for, granted, denied, and retired, together with a brief description of the circumstances of each;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E7B1CC6DE7B41D29113571E7D7C6910"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any and all enforcement actions undertaken, and the disposition of each;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9613341A638A49B79301B1BA033E59A4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of aquaculture opportunity areas established under section 102, together with a brief description of the circumstances of each; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CE429C4095F4AAE8789E891B46FEA71"><enum>(4)</enum><text>results from any grants awarded under this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA3D820F175440D4BEEABBB0E1C9D8D5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Secretary’s assessment of the state of offshore aquaculture in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61C366F522B9401D899224145047CA0C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Secretary’s assessment of United States offshore aquaculture in comparison to offshore aquaculture in other nations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C02E48AB2FF4FD58FC8E54DB4554D41"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Secretary’s recommendations to improve United States offshore aquaculture.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BB9A23302FD4CD292C99F36C5A98B37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination regarding permits</header><text>In addition to the requirements of subsection (a), the Secretary may make the following determinations regarding permit terms for offshore aquaculture:</text><paragraph id="H41978703CFCD4BAEAF5EFAB11F3222F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The effect of shortening or lengthening permit terms on the risk of harm to the environment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AC77203FCC84A059A5B1E0F28ABF109"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The effect of shortening or lengthening permit terms on industry’s access to capital markets.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF67C7E378154AB980B826254D14EB9B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Whether a change to the permit terms established in this Act is warranted.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7BAE535D9B5449CCB4E75C62088C2318"><enum>406.</enum><header>Federal coordination</header><subsection id="H033735D30FEE42428F877276379BBECC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relation to current law</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed in derogation of law in effect on the date of enactment of this Act that is applicable to offshore aquaculture operations, and the unified permitting and review process established under this section shall not affect the timelines or standards established under other laws.</text></subsection><subsection id="H36F6742DDB9C41F8A7026C5688190E65"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>Subject to subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce shall coordinate with the Department of the Interior, the Department of Agriculture, the Environmental Protection Agency, the Army Corps of Engineers, the Food and Drug Administration, and the department in which the U.S. Coast Guard is operating to simplify the Federal permitting process for offshore aquaculture. The Secretaries of the Interior, Agriculture, Health and Human Services, and the department in which the U.S. Coast Guard is operating, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Chief of Engineers shall cooperate with the Secretary of Commerce to implement this section. </text></subsection><subsection id="H80D6BB9D59914F739CEAE13CD9C7C9D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unified permitting and review process</header><paragraph id="H71A416CB09C242F9BD5D1CEF1C2CC5DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretaries of Commerce, the Interior, Agriculture, Health and Human Services, and the department in which the U.S. Coast Guard is operating, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Chief of Engineers shall, through the Secretary of Commerce, initiate, subject to the requirements of subsection (a), a rulemaking for all permits administered by such agency heads relating to offshore aquaculture for a unified process, public notice, and public comment for— </text><subparagraph id="H1A459FB197AF40E688EF186F7442DC02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>initial issuance of permits;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9F74CE9A77940098B902E5AB54D65B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>renewal of permits; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8A76DB73892472A85D03CAE1BFE2FEA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transfer of permits. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4BE0685642040DE95C86F254E36572C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, through the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall serve as the lead Federal agency for purposes of providing information on Federal permitting requirements for aquaculture in Federal waters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11A406BB9BD44F81A67170CDA03E45EF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Informal review and compatibility analysis</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, acting through the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall convene representatives of the Department of the Interior, the Department of Agriculture, the Environmental Protection Agency, the Army Corps of Engineers, and the Department in which the U.S. Coast Guard is operating to provide prospective permit applicants an opportunity for informal consultation with Federal agencies. The Secretary of Commerce may invite representatives from other Federal agencies as necessary or advisable. Nothing in this subsection shall preclude an applicant or a prospective applicant from contacting Federal agencies directly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2619CA15619403188DDD634554E2DCC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Environmental analysis</header><text>To the extent allowable under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>), any environmental analysis or environmental impact statement required under such Act for offshore aquaculture activities shall be conducted through a single, consolidated environmental review and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, through the Office of Aquaculture and associated divisions, shall serve as the lead Federal agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BC2B5F76A2947F69D8EB8E98649145C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Coordination of permit reviews</header><text>To the extent practicable under this Act and all other applicable laws and regulations, Federal agencies with permitting requirements applicable to offshore aquaculture facilities shall coordinate their review processes in order to provide a timely response to applicants.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H60E172D3D9884222B434BC99852A4689"><enum>407.</enum><header>Prohibited acts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is unlawful for any person—</text><paragraph id="H50CCB761AE874D73A28AA73775ACEF8F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to violate any provision of this Act or any regulation or permit issued pursuant to this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2751822F0A044215BB8FD05B808971DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to refuse to permit any officer authorized to enforce the provisions of this Act (in accordance with section 408) to access an offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance, subject to such person’s control, for purposes of conducting any search or inspection in connection with the enforcement of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B188CC968FF43B985859A9071BEE9D6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to assault, resist, oppose, impede, intimidate, or interfere with any such authorized officer in the conduct of any search or inspection described in paragraph (2);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BD4636BD2904257BE6B8FC0E3C781BA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to resist a lawful arrest for any act prohibited by this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AAAF2B0D65641B086C712F4A0DD0272"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to ship, transport, offer for sale, sell, purchase, import, export, or have custody, control, or possession of, any cultured species produced, taken, retained, or possessed in violation of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8BD0BB3E816416290DAB93105C629B0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to interfere with, delay, or prevent, by any means, the apprehension or arrest of another person, knowing that such other person has committed any act prohibited by this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H632BE537E2C84C04AE153DC6DC89D23D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to make or submit to the Secretary or the Governor of a State false information regarding any matter that the Secretary or Governor is considering in the course of carrying out this Act; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68449F17F8DF4AD9901FD4A1EA29AD42"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to make any false statement or provide any false information on, or in connection with, an application, declaration, record, or report; or </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18F923F0B790458A879395E2945DF69C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>without authorization, to remove, damage, or tamper with or attempt to remove, damage, or tamper with—</text><subparagraph id="H2D3307D0F8F54EF08AD67FA9CF2AF438"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an offshore aquaculture facility owned by another person, which is located in the exclusive economic zone, including any component thereof; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB76A9B91A91E41C98503F8624DEC491F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cultured species contained in such facility or component thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HA58016C4061144EAAA0880868A0EECEB"><enum>408.</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subsection id="H4F74C26B037E4E5BAC052B3635EDFC52"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Responsibility</header><text>The provisions of this Act shall be enforced by the Secretary and the Secretary of the department in which the Coast Guard is operating. In enforcing this Act, such Secretaries may by agreement utilize, on a reimbursable or non-reimbursable basis, the personnel, services, equipment (including aircraft and vessels), and facilities of any other Federal agency, including all elements of the Department of Defense, or of any State agency. Such Secretaries shall, and the head of any Federal or State agency that has entered into an agreement with either such Secretary under this section may (if the agreement so provides), authorize officers to enforce the provisions of this Act or any regulation promulgated under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB933DB532B784A21A58242E704FF9A56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Powers of authorized officers</header><text>Any officer who is authorized under subsection (a) to enforce the provisions of this Act may, with or without a warrant or other process, as authorized by law—</text><paragraph id="H88B052DD08BD4FDEABF3190087F011CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>arrest any person, if the officer has reasonable cause to believe that such person has committed an act prohibited by section 407;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC620FBBA00C43A18B3DC928D8106387"><enum>(2)</enum><text>board, search or inspect, any offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance (including its gear, furniture, appurtenances, stores, records, and cargo) which is subject to the provisions of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11FD266DDC954DCEBA376A6E085E11BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>seize any vessel, or other conveyance (together with its gear, furniture, appurtenances, stores, records, and cargo) used or employed in, or with respect to which it reasonably appears that such vessel was used or employed in, the violation of any provision of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16BA3221E1F044909104CAADE21F5E28"><enum>(4)</enum><text>seize any cultured species or seafood product (wherever found) taken, produced, imported, exported, transported, sold, received, acquired, or purchased in any manner, in connection with or as a result of the violation of any provision of this Act; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA42FB73CDFE4D9598D6138866B629A4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>seize any evidence related to any violation of any provision of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF0A2173FB5345F6A9D51C1D01C1A233"><enum>(6)</enum><text>detain any cultured species or seafood product to determine compliance with this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE574DCA2FD55497DBE7BF68527061A16"><enum>(7)</enum><text>search and seize, in accordance with any guidelines which may be issued by the Attorney General;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED1ABC8C0BE7495994383CAF9AE97208"><enum>(8)</enum><text>access, directly or indirectly, for enforcement purposes any data or information required to be provided or reported under this Act or regulations promulgated under this Act, including data from vessel or facility monitoring systems, automatic identification systems, long-range identification and tracking systems, or any similar system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAA04CAED9AF4F3AB1A0C549D1F370D6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>execute and serve any subpoena, arrest warrant, search warrant issued in accordance with Rule 41 of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, or other warrant or civil or criminal process issued by any officer or court of competent jurisdiction; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85DEA42EC9964E2CA1D89E04380D7445"><enum>(10)</enum><text>exercise any other lawful authority.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF3E5F0E1C6A4C6AB4452B4E8259F47B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Issuance of citations</header><text>If any authorized officer finds that a person, offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance is engaging or has been engaged in the violation of any provision of this Act, such officer may issue a citation to the owner or operator of such vessel in lieu of proceeding under subsection (f), (g), or (h). If a permit has been issued pursuant to this Act for such facility or conveyance, such officer shall note the issuance of any citation under this subsection, including the date thereof and the reason therefor, on the permit. The Secretary shall maintain a record of all citations issued pursuant to this subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="H042AD2F61E354C8FA5C430AFAF52636B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Subpoenas</header><text>For the purposes of conducting any investigation or hearing under this Act, or any other marine resource law enforced by the Secretary, the Secretary may issue subpoenas for the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of relevant papers, photographs, records, books, and documents in any form, including those in electronic, optical or magnetic form, and may administer oaths. Witnesses summoned shall be paid the same fees and mileage that are paid to witnesses in the courts of the United States. In case of contempt or refusal to obey a subpoena served upon any person pursuant to this subsection, the district court of the United States for any district in which such person is found, resides, or transacts business, upon application by the United States and after notice to such person, shall have jurisdiction to issue an order requiring such person to appear and give testimony before the Secretary or to appear and produce documents before the Secretary, or both, and any failure to obey such order of the court may be punished by such court as a contempt thereof.</text></subsection><subsection id="H686C5DC2AFE04B20B6E3996AA972C17B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>District court jurisdiction</header><text>The several district courts of the United States shall have jurisdiction over any actions arising under this Act. For purposes of this section, for Hawaii or any possession of the United States in the Pacific Ocean, the appropriate court is the United States District Court for the District of Hawaii, except that in the case of Guam and Wake Island, the appropriate court is the United States District Court for the District of Guam, and in the case of the Northern Mariana Islands, the appropriate court is the United States District Court for the District of the Northern Mariana Islands. Each violation shall be a separate offense and the offense shall be deemed to have been committed not only in the district where the violation first occurred, but also in any other district as authorized by law. Any offenses not committed in any district are subject to the venue provisions of section 3238 of title 18, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H64986D0B2B1F4649BD2B30A058EBC690"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Civil enforcement</header><paragraph id="H7D55D18562FB45B1ACFADDBECA833EDA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil administrative penalties</header><subparagraph id="H260D81A079BC4FA1856CD4AB85A50683"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person who is found by the Secretary, after notice and opportunity for a hearing in accordance with section 554 of title 5, United States Code, to have committed an act prohibited by section 407 shall be liable to the United States for a civil penalty. The amount of the civil penalty shall not exceed $37,500 for each violation. Each day of a continuing violation shall constitute a separate offense. The amount of such civil penalty shall be assessed by the Secretary, by written notice. In determining the amount of such penalty, the Secretary shall take into account the nature, circumstances, extent, and gravity of the prohibited acts committed and, with respect to the violator, the degree of culpability, any history of prior offenses, and such other matters as justice may require. In assessing such penalty the Secretary may also consider any information provided by the violator relating to the ability of the violator to pay, provided that the information is served on the Secretary at least 30 days prior to an administrative hearing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BA27DFC38D24FD0B9534FA34CF11871"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compromise or other action by Secretary</header><text>The Secretary may compromise, modify, or remit, with or without conditions, any civil administrative penalty which is or may be imposed under this subsection and that has not been referred to the Attorney General for further enforcement action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H74CB4FEE351B4831AB750475E32A09FE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In rem jurisdiction</header><text>An offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance (including its gear, furniture, appurtenances, stores, records, and cargo) used in the commission of an act prohibited by section 407 shall be liable in rem for any civil penalty assessed for such violation under this section and may be proceeded against in any district court of the United States having jurisdiction thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCF00600A47E4BC8BC86EB541C9E911D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Collection of administrative penalties</header><text>If any person fails to pay an assessment of a civil penalty under paragraph (1) after it has become a final and unappealable order, the Secretary shall refer the matter to the Attorney General, who shall recover the amount assessed (plus interest at current prevailing rates from the date of the final order) in any appropriate district court of the United States. In such action, the validity and appropriateness of the final order imposing the civil penalty shall not be subject to review. Any person who fails to pay, on a timely basis, the amount of an assessment of a civil penalty shall be required to pay, in addition to such amount and interest, attorney's fees and costs for collection proceedings and a quarterly nonpayment penalty for each quarter during which such failure to pay persists. Such nonpayment penalty shall be in an amount equal to 20 percent of the aggregate amount of such person's penalties and nonpayment penalties that are unpaid as of the beginning of such quarter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AC004C579994869A8D394343A451543"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Permit sanctions</header><subparagraph id="H8C52D8EC43114260A797F9592FE6283F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to any case in which an offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance was used in the commission of an act prohibited under section 407, the owner or operator of an offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance (or any other person who has been issued or has applied for a permit under this Act) has acted in violation of section 407, or any civil penalty, criminal fine, or amount in settlement of a civil forfeiture imposed under this Act on a person, offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance that has been issued or has applied for a permit under this Act has not been paid and is overdue, the Secretary may—</text><clause id="HEA479FE83E344386BB4ED4DF691A6A3E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>revoke any permit issued with respect to such person, offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, other conveyance, with or without prejudice to the issuance of subsequent permits;</text></clause><clause id="HD2369DE764A34EF9AC3E40C9080C0DC3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>suspend such permit for a period of time considered by the Secretary to be appropriate;</text></clause><clause id="H52C61301DC8B4A30B7B944CF78478DE9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>deny such permit; or</text></clause><clause id="H65205956326C49FAA2C46503345894CF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>impose additional conditions and restrictions on such permit.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C66D66864334CBEA4CAED04B4EB3E03"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In imposing a sanction under this paragraph, the Secretary shall take into account the nature, circumstances, extent, and gravity of the prohibited acts for which the sanction is imposed and, with respect to the violator, the degree of culpability, any history of prior offenses, and such other matters as justice may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC414B60967A245B7A2E804D047F83387"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Effect of transfer of ownership</header><text>Transfer of ownership of an offshore aquaculture facility, associated onshore facility, vessel, or other conveyance, by sale or otherwise, shall not extinguish any permit sanction that is in effect or is pending at the time of transfer of ownership. Before executing the transfer of ownership of a facility or conveyance, by sale or otherwise, the owner shall disclose in writing to the prospective transferee the existence of any permit sanction that will be in effect or pending with respect to the facility or conveyance at the time of the transfer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H259EA223A28A4B939305B754B81FD7D7"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Payment of penalty or fine</header><text>In the case of any permit that is suspended under this paragraph for nonpayment of a civil penalty or criminal fine, the Secretary shall reinstate the permit upon payment of the penalty or fine and interest thereon at the prevailing rate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EF3AE68496F4C768010F77F7CDC62AF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Hearing</header><text>No sanction shall be imposed under this paragraph unless there has been a prior opportunity for a hearing on the facts underlying the violation for which the sanction is imposed, either in conjunction with a civil penalty proceeding under this section or otherwise.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H954E9FD667A44A85B7D396D6428EA9F0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Review of civil penalty</header><text>Any person against whom a civil penalty is assessed under this subsection or against whom a permit sanction is imposed under this subsection (other than a permit suspension for nonpayment of penalty or fine) may obtain review thereof in the United States district court for the appropriate district by filing a complaint against the Secretary in such court within 30 days from the date of such order that constitutes a final agency action. The Secretary shall promptly file in such court a certified copy of the record upon which such violation was found or such penalty imposed, as provided in section 2112 of title 28, United States Code. The findings and order of the Secretary shall be set aside by such court if they are not found to be supported by substantial evidence, as provided in section 706(2) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDA86EE097614CAF9A54D6A3E6D69D74"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Injunctive relief</header><text>Upon the request of the Secretary, the Attorney General of the United States may commence a civil action for appropriate relief, including a permanent or temporary injunction, for any violation of this Act (including regulations).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8567C126FF834E04BE8B558CDD6D50B6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><paragraph id="H80B393358D74415797D73001F08A3ED1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Criminal forfeiture</header><subparagraph id="H19DCC4CB173D491AAE4D3F2476A32C6B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A person who is convicted of an offense in violation of this Act shall forfeit to the United States—</text><clause id="HE33707C65B7944DF9F68127E9C48E9BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any property, real or personal, constituting or traceable to the gross proceeds taken, obtained, or retained, in connection with or as a result of the offense, including, without limitation, any cultured species (or the fair market value thereof); and</text></clause><clause id="HCAB65964DA214460A261011F7A20D5A0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any property, real or personal, used or intended to be used, in any manner, to commit or facilitate the commission of the offense, including, without limitation, any vessel (including the vessel's equipment, stores, catch and cargo), vehicle, aircraft, or other means of transportation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD092726525264DDB81C92DE50689D01A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicability of controlled substances act</header><text>Pursuant to section 2461(c) of title 28, United States Code, the provisions of section 413 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/853">21 U.S.C. 853</external-xref>) other than subsection (d) thereof shall apply to criminal forfeitures under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H010A2724BBDD4F529699AC186E963B8C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Civil forfeiture</header><subparagraph id="HEAE730FFF4F4498592E4006EF9850043"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The property set forth below shall be subject to administrative or judicial forfeiture to the United States in accordance with the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/46">chapter 46</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, and no property right shall exist in it:</text><clause id="H78E98E06D5D7446F8F90B54B9ADBA6A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Any property, real or personal, constituting or traceable to the gross proceeds taken, obtained, or retained, in connection with or as a result of a violation of this Act, including, without limitation, any fish (or the fair market value thereof).</text></clause><clause id="HFBA9707B051F4D4C8CDD1B198354138D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Any property, real or personal, used or intended to be used, in any manner, to commit or facilitate the commission of a violation of this Act, including, without limitation, any vessel (including the vessel's equipment, stores, catch and cargo), vehicle, aircraft, or other means of transportation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0438A745E1B1457894675640B8E995C7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application of the customs laws</header><text>All provisions of law relating to seizure, summary judgment, and forfeiture and condemnation for violation of the customs laws, the disposition of the property forfeited or condemned or the proceeds from the sale thereof, the remission or mitigation of such forfeitures, and the compromise of claims shall apply to seizures and forfeitures incurred, or alleged to have been incurred, under the provisions of this Act, insofar as applicable and not inconsistent with the provisions hereof. For seizures and forfeitures of property under this section by the Secretary, such duties as are imposed upon the customs officer or any other person with respect to the seizure and forfeiture of property under the customs law may be performed by such officers as are designated by the Secretary or, upon request of the Secretary, by any other agency that has authority to manage and dispose of seized property.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8695D16D598C4E218C4F08C5B81983CD"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Presumption</header><text>For the purposes of this section there is a rebuttable presumption that all cultured species, or components thereof, found in an offshore aquaculture facility or on board a vessel or other conveyance that is used or seized in connection with a violation of this Act were produced, taken, obtained, transported, or retained in violation of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2CA40BAB47349E0904360B56564BDF4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Criminal enforcement</header><paragraph id="H1BA374D2379740149C9F5CB00634C831"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Imprisonment</header><text>Any person (other than a foreign government agency, or entity wholly owned and controlled by a foreign government) who knowingly commits any act prohibited under section 407 shall be imprisoned for not more than 5 years or fined not more than $500,000 for individuals or $1,000,000 for an organization, or both, except that, if in the commission of any such offense the individual uses a dangerous weapon, engages in conduct that causes bodily injury to any officer authorized to enforce the provisions of this Act, or places any such officer in fear of imminent bodily injury, the maximum term of imprisonment is not more than 10 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD6DE8878D4941D289F59163572596F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fine and imprisonment</header><text>Any person (other than a foreign government agency, or entity wholly owned and controlled by a foreign government) who violates a provision under section 407 and who, in the exercise of due care should know that such person's conduct violates such provision, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, or imprisoned not more than one year, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9AB3549FB59B432AA131E7D91B23BDC2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Joint enforcement agreements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E0CF29C859D4E7C9F260EB94D781016"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor of an eligible State may apply to the Secretary for execution of a joint enforcement agreement with the Secretary that will authorize the deputization and funding of State law enforcement officers with marine law enforcement responsibilities to perform duties of the Secretary relating to law enforcement provisions under this title or any other marine resource law enforced by the Secretary. Upon receiving an application meeting the requirements of this subsection, the Secretary may enter into a joint enforcement agreement with the requesting State.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77AF0D4FC3144638AFF551DFEF371B2C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible state</header><text>A State is eligible to participate in the cooperative enforcement agreements under this section if it is in, or bordering on, the Atlantic Ocean (including the Caribbean Sea), the Pacific Ocean, the Arctic Ocean, the Gulf of Mexico, Long Island Sound, or one or more of the Great Lakes.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7826AE99EEC44995AA0CF616181091BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Joint enforcement agreements executed under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H118426A3AD98445996BE01A069893927"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be consistent with the purposes and intent of this section to the extent applicable to the regulated activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71C574BF4B1F4F19B2BE66740381A9B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include specifications for joint management responsibilities as provided by the first section of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/91/412">Public Law 91–412</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1525">15 U.S.C. 1525</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD9E11E17B714EAE87028BF325B15B64"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall provide for confidentiality of data and information submitted to the State under this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1477CEBB3D064EE1A14F70EF4F096C44"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Allocation of funds</header><text>The Secretary shall include in each joint enforcement agreement an allocation of funds to assist in management of the agreement. The allocation shall be fairly distributed among all eligible States participating in cooperative enforcement agreements under this subsection, based upon consideration of Federal marine enforcement needs, the specific marine conservation enforcement needs of each participating eligible State, and the capacity of the State to undertake the marine enforcement mission and assist with enforcement needs. The agreement may provide for amounts to be withheld by the Secretary for the cost of any technical or other assistance provided to the State by the Secretary under the agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3D8B1E61A3334A378D2BC9F6866AFC15"><enum>409.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for the purpose of carrying out this Act—</text><paragraph id="H597751497C41403094FC7B978F8082FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$60,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D1B89AB9EAB4C35B2B01CCC6D70B671"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$65,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0ECBB85A6B834870A5C00C582CFAA5B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$70,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF908213ABCE4E2E9248222806D5CA29"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$75,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DCBE7550C164F08882885BB1E9563BA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$80,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

