<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H72462C7527F54B35B38BC02942624300" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>99 HR 3980 IH: National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3980</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000491">Mr. Lucas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000459">Mr. Fleischmann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To formally establish within statute an independent scientific research and development agency known as the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD3AC0F858CAD443BBC3AB21AD85E0052" style="OLC"><section id="HA9668D68A0D34DB19530159CB5431487" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H1A6D475CA6FC4F3BA1F17B877A94F523"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4F17F30DB75444C081E90CB77D9A73BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act is as follows: </text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HA9668D68A0D34DB19530159CB5431487" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0AA91436B3454F4CBCEAEBBC064F5593" level="section">Sec. 2. Purpose.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H33F2AC43D9544C42ACEA8D956D9F0B2F" level="title">Title I—National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H101CC59253BA4EE487794C60A6A41CBE" level="section">Sec. 101. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEBB806AE00474161913B838FDB40BDAF" level="section">Sec. 102. Functions of the Administrator.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H77E43E94F3014B729224D76B1B55F2F4" level="section">Sec. 103. Authority of the Administrator.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H027FAB6EE60444838E23A81F85D68891" level="section">Sec. 104. Science advisory board.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1AF6DB5E91BF495082D6AC351C6F4B1A" level="title">Title II—General Provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6B4551C0912543179E99877CBB9B0AA4" level="section">Sec. 201. Recommendations to Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE78D6526287F4490AB07A646E0027527" level="section">Sec. 202. Conforming repeals.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H96CF6DD544364F90B23A0B3267250373" level="section">Sec. 203. Savings provision.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H90EDB479691947329990E3A787CBB7D2" level="section">Sec. 204. Reorganization plan.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCF5A78757AE74494853CED9AC7D8FBE5" level="section">Sec. 205. National Weather Service.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0D08E77396654EFCB9B276B9FEB052B8" level="section">Sec. 206. Office of Space Commerce.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H023A9018784D418A99370226EA36F266" level="section">Sec. 207. Study.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD8C76B95DBC549B98398097C8EFC6445" level="section">Sec. 208. Effective date.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H0AA91436B3454F4CBCEAEBBC064F5593"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to establish the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration as an independent scientific research and development agency with an overarching statutory framework that focuses on Earth system science, maintaining the Administration’s core mission and functions while allowing it to restructure and prioritize under an organic statute.</text></section><title id="H33F2AC43D9544C42ACEA8D956D9F0B2F"><enum>I</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</header><section id="H101CC59253BA4EE487794C60A6A41CBE"><enum>101.</enum><header>Establishment</header><subsection id="HC9B57663517E4CE2A37B92350D09C257"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the executive branch an independent agency to be known as the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Administration</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6F43FA7C73DD489DB5F89E6928F98449"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrator</header><paragraph id="H837500F3BF9344E1A24B12547788E850"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administration shall be headed by an Administrator (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>), who shall be appointed by the President with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Administrator shall carry out the functions described in section 102 and, in the performance of those functions, shall have the authorities described in section 103.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82AF8CB7D85743A3AA59CF79F6B131EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any authority, power, or function vested by law in the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, or in any officer, employee, or part of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, or vested by law in the Secretary of Commerce and delegated to the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, or their designee, is vested in, and may be exercised by, the Administrator or their designee, as appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2394079889864975BF248BC1AC4BF876"><enum>(3)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any reference in law or regulation to the <quote>Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the Administrator.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE94781D1CAD843549D886ED811699A4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Positions</header><text>There shall be in the Administration the following:</text><paragraph id="HB2FC19E2AF654C55BFFC9AD0465EC073"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A Deputy Administrator, to be appointed by the President with the advice and consent of the Senate, who shall carry out such duties as the Administrator may prescribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27BF211E1D6D423999A514D002AB701D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An Associate Administrator for Environmental Observation and Prediction, to be appointed by the President with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H562C855379FE4BC49D2B64E29AB42051"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Chief Scientist, to be appointed by the Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FE2A8B03CF04C7A8E530BBB7EA2A9BE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A General Counsel, to be appointed in accordance with section 5316 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEBB806AE00474161913B838FDB40BDAF"><enum>102.</enum><header>Functions of the Administrator</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="H3774303B853D421BB8394DAE05A990C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>plan, direct, and conduct—</text><subparagraph id="HD1A5CF1BAB054394B1F2DD0C5C1A3FD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">atmospheric, oceanic, hydrologic, Great Lakes, coastal, geodetic, geomagnetic, biological, and social science and research, including monitoring, analyses, education, research to operations, and operations to research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB7F413DB73F4CC0BE2AEE89E64F6B4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Earth observations and space physics operations, which include space-based observations of the earth and sun;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDF70F7FFC0047E582866C7C2CBC7D65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ocean exploration, mapping, and characterization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H188AFDD50C994B8C888310EC71B410FD"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">atmospheric, terrestrial and space weather, climate, oceanic, hydrologic, Great Lakes, and coastal forecasting;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FB6270AC59F4B3A9BBCB133A4CA0BED"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conservation, management, and protection of oceanic, hydrologic, Great Lakes, and coastal resources, and science, research, and analysis related to such resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5E1D0277E524DE48449B3FB58CDB309"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">oceanic, hydrologic, Great Lakes, and coastal response and restoration; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E841AB9B6854E5DBF8F162296A26062"><enum>(G)</enum><text>education, outreach, and associated activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB08E1CDCC81490BAFE88EB958111764" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other areas of research related to the preceding items as determined appropriate by the Administrator; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE249C94151684DB7996F328FCA4B2904" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>enforcement of any other provision of Federal law that assigns enforcement authority to the Administration;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB443BD58CB049B38E66169A59CEE14D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the widest practicable participation by the scientific community, including participants in the private sector, academia, Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial governmental entities, Indigenous peoples, and other appropriate domestic and foreign governmental and non-governmental entities, in carrying out the activities described in paragraph (1), including through the acceptance by the Administration of private resources, which may include data, models, vessels, aircraft, satellites, buoys, and other related infrastructure, to carry out such activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC32CEDB4F1FF4F1B8166405C9BCAEB45"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide for full and open public dissemination of information regarding activities, initiatives, methods, data, and results of the Administration, as appropriate, and in compliance with applicable law, including the acquisition of commercially sourced data; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H410013D8BC6A4DAFA3682E09EFBB8C6C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establish and promote an inclusive culture of scientific excellence and integrity.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H77E43E94F3014B729224D76B1B55F2F4"><enum>103.</enum><header>Authority of the Administrator</header><subsection id="HFA21B08AC98F44F890F7E0F48034A773"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Officers and employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in accordance with title 5, United States Code, may appoint and fix the compensation of such officers and employees as the Administrator determines appropriate, within the regulations and guidelines established by the Office of Personnel Management.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E10C8070E5447B4BCBB9373E11167C3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Property</header><text>The Administrator may—</text><paragraph id="H528DFA7938E5437EB789ADCEA0B4F384"><enum>(1)</enum><text>procure, acquire, construct, improve, repair, operate, and maintain such laboratories, research and testing sites and facilities, equipment, vessels, aircraft, buoys, satellites, surface observing sites, other similar infrastructure, autonomous or unmanned vehicles, and office and educational facilities as the Administrator deems necessary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE06CC36BD9349F6B8A662214061F09B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>lease real and personal property;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF76B333158344CC7A470482C69821018"><enum>(3)</enum><text>sell and otherwise dispose of real and personal property and reinvest any proceeds from such sale or disposition of property into recapitalization of property; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EDF49038735464D97C746619C7D3EDC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide by contract or otherwise for necessary amenities for the welfare of employees and maintenance of property of the Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C45BC6EE7214CFBAFA43D4D681673A4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Gifts</header><text>The Administrator may accept gifts or donations of services for the benefit of the agency, including money or property, whether real, personal, or mixed, and whether tangible or intangible.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFB0030C2D51244F2BFAA7C751D269CF4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Contracts, leases, and agreements</header><text>The Administrator may enter into and perform such contracts, leases, agreements (including cooperative agreements), or other transactions as may be necessary in the conduct of the work of the Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAFDB4A9C96DD427798FA0C02F2D65A21"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Cooperation with Federal agencies and others</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator—</text><paragraph id="HF0FD13AD9737469BB5A233CCA5C54500"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may use the services, equipment, personnel, land, and facilities of Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial governmental entities, Indigenous peoples, and other appropriate domestic and foreign governmental and non-governmental entities, with consent and with or without reimbursement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H700A8E092BFB4C3498C6CB38092E56FA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall cooperate with such entities to permit their use of Administration services, equipment, land, and facilities in a manner consistent with the Administration’s mission.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF2FBBD1F16C14948B4B22AE8964205CC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>International cooperation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administration, under the foreign policy guidance of the President, may engage in a program of international cooperation in work done pursuant to the Act, and in the peaceful application of the results thereof, pursuant to agreements made by the President with the advice and consent of the Senate. </text></subsection><subsection id="HBE58F974F9084435A30BF747FC9AD9BE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Advisory committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may appoint such advisory committees as the Administrator considers appropriate to provide consultation and advice.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF74A01DA7F54841BDE1CEEDBE2E0286"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Offices and procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may establish within the Administration such offices and procedures as may be appropriate to provide for the greatest possible coordination of its activities with related public and private agencies and entities.</text></subsection></section><section id="H027FAB6EE60444838E23A81F85D68891"><enum>104.</enum><header>Science advisory board</header><subsection id="HCFCD8B644B8B443DB727F262ABC875B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be within the Administration a Science Advisory Board, which shall provide such scientific advice as may be requested by the Administrator, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, or the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA765BE8DA804897BB49E545A678AB3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the Science Advisory Board is to advise the Administrator and Congress on long-range and short-range strategies for research, education, and the application of science to resource management and environmental assessment, observation, and prediction.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8E1C8BAE28D642AAA7FFAA48BB4DF32F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Members</header><paragraph id="H63AE2CDF939A49F9AF78EBE80E46EF1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Science Advisory Board shall be composed of at least 15 members appointed by the Administrator. Each member of the Board shall be qualified by education, training, and experience to evaluate scientific and technical information on matters referred to the Board under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70FECED07DF04756AEB2B9C9A48EE87C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms of service</header><text>Members shall be appointed for 3-year terms, renewable once, and shall serve at the discretion of the Administrator. An individual serving a term as a member of the Science Advisory Board on the date of enactment of this Act may complete that term, and may be reappointed once for another term of 3 years unless the term being served on such date of enactment is the second term served by that individual. Vacancy appointments shall be for the remainder of the unexpired term of the vacancy, and an individual so appointed may subsequently be appointed for 2 full 3-year terms if the remainder of the unexpired term is less than 1 year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC72D0211F01047E3A59D71535283CC90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Administrator shall designate a chairperson from among the members of the Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H687AA09077CC4B5D962D64C159481A89"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>Members of the Science Advisory Board shall be appointed as special Government employees, within the meaning given such term in section 202(a) of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0EF1DECA1F342B49238B207918317B6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header><paragraph id="HDDC11EF3F7CC4EE793EC04C4AB8CDEF7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrative support</header><text>The Administrator shall provide administrative support to the Science Advisory Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CEAD792716F45AA978411B44CDC17FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Science Advisory Board shall meet at least twice each year, and at other times at the call of the Administrator or the Chairperson.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H940ED14A38EC40B5BED11BF81D461E8A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compensation and expenses</header><text>A member of the Science Advisory Board shall not be compensated for service on such board, but may be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27F8BCDA950D4BFD9AD929B284185912"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Subcommittees</header><text>The Science Advisory Board may establish such subcommittees of its members as may be necessary. The Science Advisory Board may establish task forces and working groups consisting of Board members and outside experts as may be necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF55F6D9E4BAA4FC99A433A3E3D72780C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Expiration</header><text>Section 14 of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Science Advisory Board.</text></subsection><subsection id="H987B33E7BB6B497FBD74EEF8F635E242"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Strategic plan for research and development</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and once every 5 years thereafter, the Administrator shall consult with the Science Advisory board to develop a strategic plan for research and development at the Administration. The plan shall include—</text><paragraph id="H5497F0A0A629468983E88F3920660983"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of the science and technology needs of the Administration based on the Administration’s operational requirements and on input provided by external stakeholders at the national, regional, State, and local levels; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB6A5BBC7CA445138EC31E80ED022497"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a strategic plan that assigns specific programs within the Administration the responsibility to meet each need identified under paragraph (1) and that describes the extent to which each need identified in paragraph (1) will be addressed through—</text><subparagraph id="H99094833A33E4E18830A1C236D3F61AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>intramural research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H814364D9C8304948AF88DC7831846659"><enum>(B)</enum><text>extramural, peer-reviewed, competitive grant programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3472B1D047F14B1DA3E164CCA127D097"><enum>(C)</enum><text>work done in cooperation with other Federal agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3CFE1C71C20401A9F8A905EB40D745A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>National academy of sciences review</header><text>The Administrator shall enter into an arrangement with the National Academy of Sciences for a review of the plan developed under subsection (f).</text></subsection><subsection id="H26AA324002E34686BE6D0CD1876F35E3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Transmittal to congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall transmit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate the initial strategic plan developed under subsection (f) and the review prepared pursuant to subsection (g). Subsequent strategic plans developed under subsection (f) shall also be transmitted to those committees upon completion.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H1AF6DB5E91BF495082D6AC351C6F4B1A"><enum>II</enum><header>General Provisions</header><section id="H6B4551C0912543179E99877CBB9B0AA4"><enum>201.</enum><header>Recommendations to Congress</header><subsection id="HE630C005084945B9A543D6F81458F3BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and at any appropriate time thereafter, the Administrator shall provide to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives recommendations for technical, conforming, or other amendments necessary—</text><paragraph id="H0872F2EE3E0C4DB89F3F4549C2D034DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to assist the transition of the Administration to an independent agency; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B83FB4100A490BB90FE448E1A5E061"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to further the policy and purpose of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C9A785A5DA14F03BEEB670EA48239D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing any recommendations pursuant to subsection (a), the Administrator shall consult with the Office of the Law Revision Counsel of the House of Representatives.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE78D6526287F4490AB07A646E0027527"><enum>202.</enum><header>Conforming repeals</header><subsection id="H87BAF25706EC4B46876171BD12BFA0BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Effect of reorganization plan</header><text>Reorganization Plan No. 4 of 1970 shall have no further force and effect.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDC0E0446A584414D9DC7D62C0C486DEF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>NOAA officers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (a) and (b) of section 407 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/99/659">Public Law 99–659</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1503b">15 U.S.C. 1503b</external-xref>; 1507c) are hereby repealed.</text></subsection></section><section id="H96CF6DD544364F90B23A0B3267250373"><enum>203.</enum><header>Savings provision</header><subsection id="HE241EE99666A40A9A3F1DFFF1E40A67C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Existing requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All rules and regulations, determinations, standards, policies, agreements, contracts, including collective bargaining agreements, certifications, authorizations, appointments, delegations of authority, results and findings of investigations, and other decisions or actions duly issued, made, or taken pursuant to or under the authority of any statute or executive order which resulted in the assignment of functions or activities to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, or to any officer, employee, or part of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, or to the Secretary of Commerce and delegated to the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, or their designee, that are in effect immediately before the date of enactment of this Act shall continue in full force and effect after the effective date of this Act until modified or rescinded.</text></subsection><subsection id="HED76D670210F418D8742F31A91BFA127"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Suits, appeals, judgments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any action or proceeding relating to the functions or activities described in subsection (a) pending on the date of enactment of this Act, the rights of the parties at issue in such proceeding shall, to the maximum extent practicable, be undisturbed by this Act. For purposes of any such action or proceeding, the provisions of Reorganization Plan No. 4 of 1970 and subsections (a) and (b) of section 407 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/99/659">Public Law 99–659</external-xref> as in effect on the day before such date of enactment shall apply.</text></subsection><subsection id="H30FE1FD6C3694D2CA36AB8B144C78B8F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Discussion of research</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to limit the ability of an Administration employee to discuss scientific research performed by that employee in accordance with the Administration’s scientific integrity policies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD6B4E6F64D1B4756AEC86E1B57928769" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Existing authorities under law</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to modify any authority under law existing immediately before the date of enactment of this Act, except as explicitly provided herein, including by—</text><paragraph id="H45BA9C07CCED430886DA15E56A595390" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>altering the responsibilities or authorities of any other Federal agency;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19E7746EBD2F4C55A8B346C8433C0C96" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorizing or prohibiting the transfer of any program, function, or project from other Federal agencies to the Administration; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06CCE848D2A242F1BC2801C48D424BC8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanding, modifying, or superseding any existing regulatory or other authority of the Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H78FF50C6E3A24E47B4793465F9FC0218"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorities with respect to public buildings</header><paragraph id="H885799B0FCB44C8C9473DF8EDF56208B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to grant the Administrator any authority to construct, alter, repair, or acquire by any means a public building (as defined in section 3301 of title 40, United States Code) or to grant any authority to lease general purpose office or storage space in any building.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45513FEA1EC44AECB69B94DCD944C4A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interaction with other similar authorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to diminish any authority the Administrator has immediately before the date of enactment of this Act to construct, alter, repair, or acquire by any means a public building (as defined in section 3301 of title 40, United States Code) or to diminish any authority the Administrator has immediately before the date of enactment of this Act to lease general purpose office or storage space in any building (regardless of whether those authorities are derived from laws, executive orders, rules, regulations, or delegations of authority from the Secretary of Commerce).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H90EDB479691947329990E3A787CBB7D2"><enum>204.</enum><header>Reorganization plan</header><subsection id="HDF9631D8ECFE4ED49B7BC97598E78A0E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Schedule</header><paragraph id="HE27B666B3109488DA869BA47EEAE1364"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial plan</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall develop a reorganization plan for the Administration in accordance with this section and shall publish the plan in the Federal Register. The Federal Register notice shall solicit comments for a period of at least 60 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC72BDCE09656473DB46B9F25BC32FDF6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revised plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the expiration date of the comment period described in paragraph (1), the Administrator shall transmit to Congress a revised version of the plan that takes into account the comments received. The Administrator shall also publish the revised plan in the Federal Register. The Administrator shall transmit and publish, along with the plan, an explanation of how the Administrator dealt with significant issues raised by the comments received.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DFDCD327D6B4DA788376D99421B5B03"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The Administrator shall implement the plan not later than 180 days after the plan has been transmitted to the Congress.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8F4523442754896A456AD1CD319060D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content</header><text>The plan, to the greatest extent practicable, shall—</text><paragraph id="H362FAAA738344DB9A6730191668C71AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consistent with the other provisions of this Act, maximize the efficiency with which the Administration carries out the core functions of—</text><subparagraph id="HFC2270AA45344A34A5774FE7D9296BC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>science and research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H277F0B49A1694BDAA1CB24260D6584E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02734FE7130C4B92A472151EFE95A471"><enum>(C)</enum><text>predictions and forecasts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H406B143C1D764803A6C9B79046AA6D31"><enum>(D)</enum><text>products and services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33781DFDC7764511A83ACCCFCDC3A96B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>education and outreach;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62B830F938F14E3AB2BEB3577C4AC416"><enum>(F)</enum><text>earth observations and space weather observations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE30DBB1A5F849C3A9549869F4E772BF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>resource management; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6361F7A1C0B243F78F48712F80A36826"><enum>(H)</enum><text>enforcement;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB550B4A647943B194C4B07460C3425B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improve the sharing of research and other information that is of use across programmatic themes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF17353C77353432090299DF18335C9B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">minimize duplication of effort or overlapping efforts and promote coordination among offices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB601FEE1E3A42CFB9105F52AB411860"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the plan, the Administrator shall consult with interested parties, including other Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial governmental entities, Indigenous peoples, and other appropriate domestic and foreign governmental and non-governmental entities, academia, industry, and Administration employees, contractors, and grantees.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCF5A78757AE74494853CED9AC7D8FBE5"><enum>205.</enum><header>National Weather Service</header><subsection id="H71993EF73B3C4EB5A80A6AFBCA655F9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall maintain within the Administration the National Weather Service.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DCDDC2436674100BDD0F8AAFF3430FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the National Weather Service is to provide weather, water, climate, tsunami, and space weather forecasts and warnings for the United States, its territories, adjacent waters, and ocean areas for the protection of life and property and the enhancement of the national economy. In carrying out the mission of the National Weather Service, the Administrator shall ensure that the National Weather Service—</text><paragraph id="H3EF0F2960A034C7D855510B14180AF34"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides timely and accurate weather, water, climate, tsunami, and space weather forecasts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H175DFED5835546DCB4A08A406F8E8C7E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides timely and accurate warnings of natural hazards related to weather, water, climate, and tsunamis, and of space weather hazards.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H13318D92196744B79DDB0BD4D70D8DFB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The functions of the National Weather Service shall include—</text><paragraph id="HDA47E70E9D76463797DE8C0E748EF3E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintaining a network of local weather forecast offices, river forecast centers, and center weather service units;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51F45A08AF584FFB8E31B61F15854ED3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>maintaining a network of observation systems to collect weather and climate data;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86A937952A8045A0A758E1EEE80C6B24"><enum>(3)</enum><text>operating national centers to deliver guidance, forecasts, warnings, and analysis about weather, water, climate, tsunami, and space weather phenomena for the Administration and the public;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD402A166FB34EB1A36C055E11D78B9D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing information to Federal agencies and other organizations responsible for emergency preparedness and response as required by law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE43738A0B4314B70B0884F5AA7697117"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conducting and supporting applied research to facilitate the rapid incorporation of weather and climate science advances into operational tools; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H518F6860C1354AD38F4DC88540CC5863"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other functions the Administrator determines to be necessary to serve the mission of the National Weather Service described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0D08E77396654EFCB9B276B9FEB052B8"><enum>206.</enum><header>Office of Space Commerce</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (b) of section 50702 of title 51, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE4F2F76ECB2C42448D638FB700CEF358"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Office shall be headed</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7A817B4AA783424F80725D8625217758" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HFFE90985303F45748F38A3986FA6806C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office shall be headed</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H395AF6F689784E7D9079FAAC11E63847"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H08393AB1EB4E42C49276846BD86EC296" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H5B1EEFE43EB74F318BADC1D7F5CCF4A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Direct report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall report directly to the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H023A9018784D418A99370226EA36F266"><enum>207.</enum><header>Study</header><subsection id="H6F795A73E011469B84DC4B77E398BD76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall contract with the National Academy of Public Administration to conduct a study examining the feasibility and merits of transferring parts or all of the Endangered Species Act (ESA) and Marine Mammal Protection Act (MMPA) management functions into a single agency or department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC8E20A5D8A5349ACB9D9713AE90281E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report on the results of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="HD8C76B95DBC549B98398097C8EFC6445"><enum>208.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall take effect on the date that is 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

