<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9B3F275899784C6A8AC1E323D1F3D2EB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3776 IH: Family Stability and Opportunity Vouchers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3776</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize a new type of housing choice voucher to help achieve the goals of ending homelessness among families with children, increasing housing opportunities, and improving life outcomes of poor children.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3CB80E550A1348A3B00B9BF9341FB1AB" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF1E02FB0270248B18A203126C923E6DA"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Family Stability and Opportunity Vouchers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H75B571C6A855404BB33768AD6FDB1E1B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Family stability and opportunity vouchers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>), as amended by section 601(a)(2)(B) of division AA of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>; 136 Stat. 5543), is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA43BC71942854813B103D4177791149E"> 
<paragraph id="H8C110E1BAF8D4CA0981B77FF291957CD"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Family stability and opportunity vouchers</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9479C8C9139B4CDCBBC61C722AB4F7E5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> <clause id="HAAE3A042C996468697F52D1AE2827E75"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The term <term>area of concentrated poverty</term> means a census tract in which the poverty rate is not less than 30 percent, as most recently determined by the Bureau of the Census.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HA1E4D608290E45A29F2AC13F51128A59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The term <term>at risk of homelessness</term> has the meaning given the term in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>).</text></clause> <clause id="H9CB484742DF84182BC5695196916C71B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible family</term> means a family that—</text> 
<subclause id="H5ECED834234F494183A00FD402EC17E0"><enum>(I)</enum> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE96F3E8C09F4457780BFF470B4031E0F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>will welcome a minor child through birth or adoption in the next 300 days; or</text></item> <item indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5062EB7B2BA543299C20AB97BFBBA3D7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has not less than 1 child under the age of 6;</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9F662CE05CEF4574AF4A1B92B0CF16EE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meets all applicable eligibility requirements under this subsection; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4C3FC0C9F3A54C4F83BEEC0BC415FC38"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is—</text> 
<item id="H65CEF8627E0C46128B0DE006C3223ADC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>homeless;</text></item> <item id="H0376A7A3B7184C9A8AAE2FEA18A41223"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>unstably housed;</text></item> 
<item id="H7A69A0B0B4CD487E8A03856A96A64D29"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>living in an area of concentrated poverty; or</text></item> <item id="H93904C0015774DA88C741EC162B308B2"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>at risk of displacement from—</text> 
<subitem id="H45AFD79B21934D17A5EB1E6A5EE7BA27"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>an opportunity area for children; or</text></subitem> <subitem id="HF6546AB7DC8A468EA589FF60DD5AC939"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>an area rapidly transitioning to become an opportunity area for children.</text></subitem></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HFBA774429DA14B4DAB8AE3AE2288834C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The term <term>high-performing school</term> shall have the meaning given the term by the Secretary, using the best available evidence. </text></clause> <clause id="HA4311CCA105042E49B2DEB0348CCC700"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The term <term>homeless</term> has the meaning given the term in section 103 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11302">42 U.S.C. 11302</external-xref>).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H424CD074F35247378B550CB3C60376F9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The term <term>opportunity area for children</term> shall have the meaning given the term by the Secretary, using the best available evidence.</text></clause> <clause id="HA225F16E80324BA69ED746153ABA012C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The term <term>unstably housed</term>, with respect to a family, means a family who—</text> 
<subclause id="H42B253DC2AB14FC9A4B26801A14F05C5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is at risk of homelessness;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2B447F22E1C440719EC0A4FDE82840CA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has moved not less than twice during the 12-month period ending on the date on which a public housing agency selects the family from a waiting list to receive assistance under this paragraph;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9B423F7502394B588E661C05A59EF614"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is living in a unit not accessible to a family member with a disability;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF324BD7B5621469C88D5C336FAA23C0B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>is experiencing trauma or a lack of safety relating to, or fleeing or attempting to flee, domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, stalking, or another dangerous, traumatic, or life-threatening condition relating to violence against a member of the family or an individual in the housing situation of the family, including an instance in which the health and safety of a child is jeopardized; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HC39B4754F1E84103A79E8D30BCE33575"><enum>(V)</enum><text>is living in housing conditions that are dangerous or life-threatening.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4AA9FE0280E84570A5933FF09AEE74F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Competitive award</header> <clause id="HB859A9781FA945B2B1EC88F327002819"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In each fiscal year for which amounts are authorized to be appropriated under subparagraph (F), the Secretary shall provide assistance to public housing agencies on a competitive basis to be used for—</text> 
<subclause id="HD01A253609EE412DB6F22E4CF1F22301"><enum>(I)</enum><text>incremental vouchers for eligible families; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H229EAFFCBDD14188A154DA1F251362DE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>additional fees for the cost to the public housing agencies of providing mobility-related services to eligible families.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H27978EFB2DC64E46BEE5AF705492864F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>For the second fiscal year in which the Secretary provides assistance under this paragraph, and each fiscal year thereafter, in selecting public housing agencies to receive assistance under this paragraph, the Secretary shall—</text> <subclause id="H88AB31BB476E46F3AED54C6ACAF8D047"><enum>(I)</enum><text>consider the performance of public housing agencies in implementing this paragraph; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H68A5B18B28B943069B7C1E9555D355A2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>give preference to public housing agencies that partner with organizations that provide home visiting services, such as the services authorized under section 511 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/711">42 U.S.C. 711</external-xref>) or locally funded initiatives, if those services are available in the service area of the public housing agency.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3EA4AB82A0B463693BB5C1D3C52706A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Services required to be offered to families receiving vouchers</header> <clause id="H71D852E9DC9740C49B006B03525631DB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A public housing agency that receives assistance under this paragraph—</text> 
<subclause id="H458BC65FEDF74349B593800B833B1CEC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall offer, to each eligible family that the agency selects to receive a voucher, mobility-related services to help the family move to an opportunity area for children with access to—</text> <item id="H56C3CF1301DB4AE5B118B168DE42B478"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a high-performing school; or</text></item> 
<item id="H028FE70EA0D5401C825911C0851536E1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>high-quality childcare and early education;</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H7CCEAD8AE7C44FF5BF175D305BC9C480"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may not require an eligible family to participate in the mobility-related services described in subclause (I) as a condition of receipt of a voucher; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H93CCE3805FAD410B91CFAA8167229A9A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>shall adopt mobility-related policies, to be specified by the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H63FCA7F189F84B30BC31CD741F75E424"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Minimum assortment of services and policies</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a minimum assortment of types of mobility-related services that a public housing agency shall offer, and mobility-related policies that a public housing agency shall adopt, under clause (i) based on promising practices and evidence of the effectiveness of the services and policies.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4A63E2760FF24EBDA77B282450A4B0E1"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Specific services</header><text>The types of mobility-related services required to be offered under clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="H7651D9D3B3C34AD0A9D7AC0E646A72E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall include a customized approach to enable a successful transition to opportunity areas for children; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2A0C7B1592C6454FBBA7F318D0DC5A7D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may include counseling and continued supportive services for families.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H5EC9604D32B64E28AD8243B769576776"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Opportunity areas for children; high-performing schools; high-quality child care and early education</header><text>The Secretary shall establish criteria for areas, schools, and child care and early education to qualify as opportunity areas for children, high-performing schools, and high-quality child care and early education, respectively.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0D20BFBD09894070898055D1E26F2A97"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Manner of providing services</header><text>A public housing agency may provide mobility-related services as required under clause (i) directly or through a local partnership or contract.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2EC06844C4234E7CB7845D74276C4FEA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Other requirements</header> <clause id="H02E08A752D05433F99DF61DC969BD131"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Turnover</header> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB9A024888B747E38C65B4F1A3D66EBB"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon turnover of a voucher issued by a public housing agency using assistance received under this paragraph, the public housing agency shall issue the voucher to another eligible family under this paragraph.</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9E5BB971E1F417DB1282C29698C66E3"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Mobility services</header><text>A public housing agency turning over a voucher as described in subclause (I) shall provide any available mobility services to the eligible family receiving the voucher.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H6A5C13DE252A48119EEE03A2B6A1D23A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Recapture and reallocation by Secretary</header><text>If a public housing agency that receives assistance to be used for vouchers and fees under this paragraph determines that it no longer has an identified need for the assistance, the public housing agency shall notify the Secretary, who may recapture the assistance and reallocate the assistance in accordance with this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H42DF0938A8CE4F68BC62A90C9621FED4"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Implementation</header> 
<clause id="HA055E0191E314179A18DC8D1E7C3B166"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall publish a notice for public comment in the Federal Register that includes any definitions or other specifications required or authorized under this paragraph.</text></clause> <clause id="H127B73EF3DB44404BDF211F3B9107A0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Allocation of funding</header> <subclause id="HBA273670135D41048490A2038A59C9B6"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Initial year</header><text>For the first fiscal year for which amounts are appropriated to be provided to public housing agencies for incremental vouchers under this paragraph, the Secretary shall allocate the amounts to public housing agencies not later than 2 years after the date on which the amounts are appropriated.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H55648F2458554C4E8D1ED7C06CDEB244"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Subsequent years</header><text>For any fiscal year after the fiscal year described in subclause (I), the Secretary shall allocate amounts to public housing agencies for incremental vouchers under this paragraph not later than 180 days after the date on which the amounts are appropriated.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H03F6EF7E9A3244D58EBB0912A63C579A"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029 such sums as may be necessary to provide assistance to public housing agencies under this paragraph to be used for—</text> 
<clause id="H23470D2B397B4528B10357E94BF3029D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not more than 50,000 incremental vouchers each fiscal year, as described in subparagraph (B)(i)(I); and</text></clause> <clause id="H7A64456FF1F047D0A5F3610836560355"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fees for the cost of administering the incremental vouchers described in subparagraph (B)(i)(I) and other mobility-related expenses.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

