<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H16A249FEBFE1402FB2660A41D8BBAC5B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 986 IH: Coordinating Our Local Liaisons And Bringing Out Related Agency Technical Expertise Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 986</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230210">February 10, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Small Business</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense and the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to enter into an agreement to coordinate government contracting assistance offered by small business development centers and APEX Accelerators, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HAC90BEE194F841FFA8D1CC15B4428666" style="OLC">
<section id="H283E1ACF5D3542338E535400926D764D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Coordinating Our Local Liaisons And Bringing Out Related Agency Technical Expertise Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COLLABORATE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1C6CADF881C94F5A95D1FA4F5208B285"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interagency agreement on government contracting assistance</header> <subsection id="H3FC326336B064B3FB5931FEC66F15146"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, acting through the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment, and the Administrator of the Small Business Administration shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H5C997DD4C5DF47C3A06714EB5D8BDDDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into an interagency agreement to coordinate the government contracting and procurement assistance offered to small business concerns by small business development centers and APEX Accelerators; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H15A5271ED57C42C396290B05EFA47F85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>jointly submit to the Committees on Armed Services and Small Business of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Armed Services and Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate such interagency agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE3311510AB99467A9F85E3767A983258"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The interagency agreement required under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H5888A4DF923747FAAA99A4DABEDCD966"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that government contracting and procurement assistance provided by covered centers is provided by employees of the covered center who have training on government contracting and procurement;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4DE60366B1CD435580B7DBE2BAC8FDA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for the allocation of resources and responsibilities between small business development centers and APEX Accelerators to—</text> <subparagraph id="H265319AB242142B1905185D864198049"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevent small business concerns from receiving duplicative assistance or contradictory or confusing information from covered centers;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDF656EC228344C9AA1D69842538D4E91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that the activities of a covered center, including any assistance or other services provided by such covered center, are attributed only to such covered center; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7FAB7F4593224CE2820F070F4BFD2906"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">clarify the responsibilities of employees of small business development centers and the responsibilities of employees of APEX Accelerators when a small business development center and APEX Accelerator share a location; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE7A9E5D4DE7A44608667344561662641"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide a framework enabling small business development centers and APEX Accelerators to coordinate the provision of government contracting and procurement assistance to small business concerns, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB9F36D28FC854C2F89B0BA06C0B84352"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Progress report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of Small Business Administration shall submit to Congress a report on the efforts of the Administrator and the Secretary of Defense with respect to the establishment of the interagency agreement required under subsection (a).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7475E5834A3846BCACC54B3990A86BA6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HAB1D35B6A99141D68447197229B03AFF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>APEX Accelerator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>APEX Accelerator</term> means a center operating under a cooperative agreement with the Office of Small Business Programs to provide procurement technical assistance pursuant to the authority provided in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/388">chapter 388</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF4A3E66696E42BE95A5163EEE414508"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered center</term> means a small business development center or an APEX Accelerator.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFED22539EC9E4B2D9E1553AADB73E69D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Office of Small Business Programs</header><text>The term <term>Office of Small Business Programs</term> means the office established within the Office of the Secretary of Defense under section 15(k) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/644">15 U.S.C. 644(k)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H73B66F402805485996B346C8B91AE92E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text>The term <term>small business concern</term> has the meaning given such term under section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFAB499A3319342E3B461A1B94A60766B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Small business development center</header><text>The term <term>small business development center</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


