<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6E3ED7ACDAB242F898DA4C091A931BB3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 215 IH: Working to Advance Tangible and Effective Reforms for California Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 215</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001165">Mr. McCarthy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To provide long-term water supply and regulatory reliability to drought-stricken California, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H093223FE2D6F4FD399F36AF864057DED" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H559AEA7DB06941519FF96EAE204E7EF5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Working to Advance Tangible and Effective Reforms for California Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>WATER for California Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H84B4A9E2E24A407082C956421B30E5A8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="H559AEA7DB06941519FF96EAE204E7EF5" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H84B4A9E2E24A407082C956421B30E5A8" level="section">Sec. 2. Table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0F56BBAA96AF41B2B24EC1086C71514D" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HDF1EF3012CEC41A894E1B72378B2BFE5" level="title">Title I—CVP AND SWP OPERATIONS</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HCE6D2BC5E6B2446BB08BE9EC8F6E06BA" level="section">Sec. 101. Operation of the CVP and SWP.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC713102E431543AC8F15FBE1365BEF4E" level="section">Sec. 102. Operations and reviews.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6DB6228F6AE942F6A79B4F16D3BD9934" level="section">Sec. 103. Application of State laws.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H5DF0B389400A4EA6A8A49B62B5291BB0" level="section">Sec. 104. Reconsultation of NOAA Biological Opinion and FWS Biological Opinion.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HA59DB91FE75045FEA507BD551678D3C2" level="section">Sec. 105. Sunset.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H1F0CD0023E01413AACD48E046424307E" level="section">Sec. 106. Consultation on coordinated operations.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H3878A061D63E448BB728DF835BAF93D2" level="title">Title II—ALLOCATIONS FOR SACRAMENTO VALLEY CONTRACTORS</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC60A6BD1041B4FF9B00B61A886A42E34" level="section">Sec. 201. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H649BAFBDCD15438E8454FCF959A392D5" level="section">Sec. 202. Allocations of water.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8ABEF3D3E15F4B33B68B939EE0B60BF9" level="section">Sec. 203. Protection of refuge, municipal and industrial and other contractors.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC8BE18622C7342D4B35E9A3222C1E6DF" level="section">Sec. 204. Other contractors.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD85331ED659D48EF8FF1FB31F192DD89" level="title">Title III—INFRASTRUCTURE</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFA1A837573164898ADCB5C124111633F" level="section">Sec. 301. Shasta Reservoir enlargement project.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HED9FF1E55D3F4777A3B80148A42D55BC" level="section">Sec. 302. Water supply plan; projects.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H2CA1D3E360AE438391E0E8EE583E60EB" level="section">Sec. 303. Conservation fish hatcheries.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8309580F49BC4BAF9123E69A3ECA8CC9" level="section">Sec. 304. Storage; duration.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9BCB8E2224B44608A1356D8C6DE4DC79" level="section">Sec. 305. Shasta Dam enlargement.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H40E3E0A47916460FB159C7BE878D91DF" level="title">Title IV—CVPIA ACTIONS</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H92528323C11C41C2AFED26CE6EA11467" level="section">Sec. 401. CVPIA restoration actions.</toc-entry></toc></section> 
<section id="H0F56BBAA96AF41B2B24EC1086C71514D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="H87FD5A525AEA4548ADD043563A42D4B0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>CVP</header><text>The term <term>CVP</term> means the Central Valley Project.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H22D101E654D44539802B8EA264A01A0B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CVP contractor</header><text>The term <term>CVP contractor</term> means any public water agency, water user organization, or person that has entered into a contract with the United States for water service from the CVP, whether in the form of a water service contract, repayment contract, water rights settlement contract, exchange contract, or refuge contract.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE587273B2B1744EAB2A3FD4BE77F3B71"><enum>(3)</enum><header>FWS biological opinion</header><text>The term <term>FWS Biological Opinion</term> means the United States Fish and Wildlife Service <quote>Biological Opinion for the Reinitiation of Consultation on the Coordinated Operations of the Central Valley Project and State Water Project</quote> (Service File No. 08FBTD00–2019–F–0164) signed on October 21, 2019.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5DA45AF16244E9A8ECE63DA164FC970"><enum>(4)</enum><header>NOAA biological opinion</header><text>The term <term>NOAA Biological Opinion</term> means the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Fisheries <quote>Biological Opinion on the Long-term Operation of the Central Valley Project and the State Water Project</quote> (Consultation Tracking Number: WCRO–2016–00069) signed on October 21, 2019.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF3CA52D310340EFA62C1272A8D23F04"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Preferred Alternative</header><text>The term <term>Preferred Alternative</term> means the Alternative 1 (Preferred Alternative), as described in the Final Environmental Impact Statement on the Reinitiation of Consultation on the Coordinated Long-Term Operation of the Central Valley Project and the State Water Project, issued by the Bureau of Reclamation, and dated December 2019.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0369F2C5431D4864A0B624E26EBD7F2D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>SWP</header><text>The term <term>SWP</term> means the California State Water Project.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6DE7C7E6B2044CA98A63035B1212647F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>SWP contractor</header><text>The term <term>SWP contractor</term> means a public agency that has entered into a long-term water supply contract with the California Department of Water Resources for water service from the SWP.</text></paragraph></section> 
<title id="HDF1EF3012CEC41A894E1B72378B2BFE5"><enum>I</enum><header>CVP AND SWP OPERATIONS</header> 
<section id="HCE6D2BC5E6B2446BB08BE9EC8F6E06BA"><enum>101.</enum><header>Operation of the CVP and SWP</header> 
<subsection id="H8723BF0E8F724AB9AA7C64EFBF4FE9A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Congressional direction regarding CVP and SWP operations</header><text>The CVP and the SWP shall be operated in accordance with the Preferred Alternative and FWS Biological Opinion and NOAA Biological Opinion.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H77E9D041FCFA49BCB03F7DA76CE62FE3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application of laws and regulations to others</header><text>Operation of the CVP and SWP shall proceed pursuant to subsection (a) except to the extent changes to operations are undertaken pursuant to one or more agreements, which are voluntarily entered into, approved, and implemented by CVP contractors, for operations of the CVP, and SWP contractors, for operations of the SWP, with all applicable Federal departments and the State of California, including any agency or board of the State of California.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5351F718F7504DB7BF1BFE92A3BC9198"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>No cost, including water supply, financial, mitigation-related, or otherwise, associated with the implementation of any agreement under subsection (b) shall be imposed by any Federal department or agency or the State of California, including any agency or board of the State of California, directly or indirectly on any CVP contractor, SWP contractor, or any other person or entity, unless such costs are incurred on a voluntary basis.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H52DC9F7F85BD4B3BBFC4DCD03AE3AA85"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Endangered Species Act</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b), implementation of subsection (a) shall not conflict with the FWS Biological Opinion and the NOAA Biological Opinion.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H576B38D8821843D98CCA63619B5AB459" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Native species protection</header><text>The State of California shall not impose any bag, catch, or size restriction or limit on the take or harvest of striped bass or any species of black bass, including largemouth bass, smallmouth bass, and spotted bass, that occupy the Sacramento-San Joaquin Rivers Delta or its tributaries.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC713102E431543AC8F15FBE1365BEF4E"><enum>102.</enum><header>Operations and reviews</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In carrying out section 101(a), the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Commerce shall implement their statutory authorities in a manner that improves water supply reliability and enables the CVP and SWP to provide the maximum quantity of water supplies practicable to CVP agricultural, municipal, and industrial contractors, water service or repayment contractors, water rights settlement contractors, exchange contractors, refuge contractors, and SWP contractors, in accordance with the Preferred Alternative, NOAA Biological Opinion, and FWS Biological Opinion.</text></section> 
<section id="H6DB6228F6AE942F6A79B4F16D3BD9934"><enum>103.</enum><header>Application of State laws</header> 
<subsection id="HE5E1C7C466104AE88E066AF4CDA0B057"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reduced water supply</header><text>If, as a result of the application of applicable State law or regulation, the State of California (including any agency or board of the State of California) alters operation of the SWP in a manner that directly or indirectly results in reduced water supply to the SWP as compared with the water supply available under the Preferred Alternative, and as a result, CVP yield is greater than it otherwise would have been under the Preferred Alternative, then that additional yield shall be made available to the SWP for delivery to SWP Contractors to offset that reduced water supply. If it is necessary to reduce water supplies for any authorized uses of the CVP or CVP Contractors to make available to the SWP that additional yield, such reductions shall be applied proportionately to those authorized uses or CVP contractors that benefit from that increased yield.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H17AC6E6823624F888D5454A780527282"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No restriction of certain water rights</header><text>The State of California (including any agency or board of the State of California) shall not restrict the exercise of any water right obtained pursuant to State law, including but not limited to a pre-1914 appropriative right or riparian right in order to offset any impact resulting from the implementation of this title on any species affected by operations of the CVP or the SWP.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5DF0B389400A4EA6A8A49B62B5291BB0"><enum>104.</enum><header>Reconsultation of NOAA Biological Opinion and FWS Biological Opinion</header> 
<subsection id="HB19EF78C592846BC845BC865EC8BFB65"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for reconsultation</header> 
<paragraph id="HD6DA4E7BFAA546789A146A6EC0550BB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Neither the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Commissioner of Reclamation, nor the Secretary of Commerce or their designees shall commence, complete, or request reinitiation of consultation on the coordinated long-term operation of the Central Valley Project and the State Water Project that will result in changes to or the replacement of the documents listed in paragraph (2) unless—</text> <subparagraph id="H0CD3ED73A8E44C5A8D37C02905D84AB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>more than 75 percent of California has experienced 4 consecutive years of D3 or D4 level drought, as defined by the U.S. Drought Monitor;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAEEF5BDF85A2416D9EDD8B2A8EC290DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Commissioner of Reclamation identifies one specific factor or combination of factors under section 402.16 of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AF80042356D4D6A8655D104DD424647"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not fewer than 120 days before officially commencing or requesting reinitiation, the Secretary of the Interior notifies the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate, in writing, of—</text> 
<clause id="HA287C52F6227450A88E5BC6BFF84E1A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the intent to commence or request reinitiation under this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA4CBB4E9F3394FBFB4BDF5D2ED85736F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the detailed justification for the identification of the specific factor or combination of factors under section 402.16 of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations, that was identified to satisfy the requirement in subparagraph (B).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FECA4833AC74B4BB69593BD07BF3A91"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Documents</header><text>The documents referred to in paragraph (1) are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HDB36EADC4A754615AB431670C5B9F8FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The FWS Biological Opinion.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA7681527FA4D4D4194B61A2F77F8CB84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The NOAA Biological Opinion.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFC0F1D03F884440D95B55E5987951C13"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Record of Decision for the Reinitiation of Consultation on the Coordinated Long-Term Modified Operations of the Central Valley Project and State Water Project, signed on February 18, 2020.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H394965080B7A466CBDFEE5BE97CB6B25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicable procedures and review</header><text>For the purposes of this Act, before reinitiating consultation on the Long-Term Operation of the CVP and SWP, a request by the Secretary of the Interior, the Secretary of the Commerce, or any other Federal employee, to reinitiate consultation shall be made in writing and considered a rule under section 551 of title 5, United States Code, and subject to the requirements of sections 801 through 808 of that title.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE7CB67F3107746EDA7CA78245652DC4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cooperation</header><text>In implementing this section, the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Commerce shall comply with requirements included in section 4004 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0158FA8C8C6F4A8E93B9D555430EB976"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (b), in implementing this section, section 801(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HA59DB91FE75045FEA507BD551678D3C2"><enum>105.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Sections 101 through 104 shall have no force or effect on and after the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section> 
<section id="H1F0CD0023E01413AACD48E046424307E"><enum>106.</enum><header>Consultation on coordinated operations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Water Infrastructure Improvements for the Nation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4D1E5F657F974E468D5181BB29FD9189"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 4004(a)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8F5A403C64954710A6BE841DCB2F106F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or proposed action</quote> after <quote>biological assessment,</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79F2D7685B2E43EA901CFC1D756FBCC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>or proposed action</quote> after <quote>biological assessment,</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFF66F78A248E4E9C9E097E4FCED3A3EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (3) through (6) as paragraphs (4) through (7), respectively;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H048ADF845AD946338D02A09E8C872F12"><enum>(D)</enum><text>after paragraph (2), by inserting the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H28D3D8B08B634EC088A8918A76FDF189" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H54B1A385C0224E13A60D89B9BAEA310C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>receive a copy of the proposed action and have the opportunity to review that document and provide comment to the action agency, which comments shall be afforded due consideration during development;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0E4DB9A9594F422C915628A56BFA75F3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), as redesignated by subparagraph (C) of this paragraph—</text> 
<clause id="HD81E46A046484F93A09BFE01C67B23F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>action agency proposes a proposed action or</quote> before <quote>the consulting agency</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H4E274FABDF8541D1B1B73042D311BBEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>proposed action or</quote> before <quote>alternative will</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H651C82C1D93B49688B81A2BE1421D7CB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>alternative actions</quote> and insert <quote>actions or alternatives</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB642A3BBD2514EC9B1F05B678E7EC633"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 4013, by deleting <quote>section 4004, which shall expire 10 years after the date of its enactment;</quote> and inserting <quote>section 4004, which shall expire on December 16, 2033;</quote>.</text></paragraph></section></title> 
<title id="H3878A061D63E448BB728DF835BAF93D2"><enum>II</enum><header>ALLOCATIONS FOR SACRAMENTO VALLEY CONTRACTORS</header> 
<section id="HC60A6BD1041B4FF9B00B61A886A42E34"><enum>201.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title, the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="H73E9A41BCE6E4D828D890C8AC02F8B06"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>existing CVP agricultural water service or repayment contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed</term> means any water service or repayment contractor within the Shasta, Trinity, or Sacramento River division of the CVP that has in effect a water service or repayment contract on the date of enactment of this title that provides water for irrigation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAAD08598355C4BD08B09B37CD2E308EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <term>Above Normal</term>, <term>Below Normal</term>, <term>Dry</term>, and <term>Wet</term>, with respect to a year, have the meanings given those terms in the Sacramento Valley Water Year Type (40–30–30) Index.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H649BAFBDCD15438E8454FCF959A392D5" commented="no"><enum>202.</enum><header>Allocations of water</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subject to section 203, and notwithstanding any changes to operations of the CVP or SWP voluntarily agreed to, approved, and implemented by CVP contractors, the Secretary of the Interior shall make every reasonable effort in the operation of the CVP to allocate water provided for irrigation purposes to each existing CVP agricultural water service contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed in accordance with the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5D725FF600F645F1A5F62264D412DBC4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not less than 100 percent of the contract quantity of the existing CVP agricultural water service contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed in a Wet year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H663161EF6F7147F6A0E1984E768B05F8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not less than 100 percent of the contract quantity of the existing CVP agricultural water service contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed in an Above Normal year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H137FE500DEE644AAA739D0132E9B9CC0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Not less than 100 percent of the contract quantity of the existing CVP agricultural water service contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed in a Below Normal year that is preceded by an Above Normal or Wet year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3B3167CD126E427ABF8116795731635B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Not less than 50 percent of the contract quantity of the existing CVP agricultural water service contractor within the Sacramento River Watershed in a Dry year that is preceded by a Below Normal, Above Normal, or Wet year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE18544EED0C54658BF7EA5E6F52DB833" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In any other year not identified in any subsections (a) through (d), not less than twice the allocation percentage to south-of-Delta CVP agricultural water service contractors, up to 100 percent.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H8ABEF3D3E15F4B33B68B939EE0B60BF9"><enum>203.</enum><header>Protection of refuge, municipal and industrial and other contractors</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in section 202 shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5C0E10D882A943AFB8E73B418E67E86C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>adversely affect any protections for the environment, including the obligation of the Secretary of the Interior to make water available to managed wetlands pursuant to section 3406(d) of the Central Valley Project Improvement Act (title XXXIV of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/575">Public Law 102–575</external-xref>; 106 Stat. 4722);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB41F3CF495974CA29967CAAF9861A856"><enum>(2)</enum><text>adversely affect any obligation of the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce under the FWS Biological Opinion or the NOAA Biological Opinion;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD0CDF756FCF646869A788C7811CB6562"><enum>(3)</enum><text>modify any provision of a water service contract that addresses municipal or industrial water shortage policies of the Secretary of the Interior;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6490BB2F212D4315AA8A57A4D708C552"><enum>(4)</enum><text>affect or limit the authority of the Secretary of the Interior to adopt or modify municipal and industrial water shortage policies;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA9A5FEC4EF84C1AB199320A6E641538"><enum>(5)</enum><text>constrain, govern, or affect, directly or indirectly, the operations of the American River division of the CVP or any deliveries from that division or a unit or facility of that division; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE08E9EC84D248FE84E9BB9117003F81"><enum>(6)</enum><text>affect any allocation to a CVP municipal or industrial water service contractor by increasing or decreasing allocations to the contractor, as compared to the allocation the contractor would have received absent section 202.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HC8BE18622C7342D4B35E9A3222C1E6DF"><enum>204.</enum><header>Other contractors</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in section 202 shall—</text> <paragraph id="H665422184B9D4AAAB747FA0E993B3D24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>affect the priority of any individual or entity with a Sacramento River settlement contract over water service or repayment contractors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C134FDF0153469E8B0628833E145AD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>affect the United States ability to deliver water to the San Joaquin River exchange contractors from the Sacramento River and the Delta via the Delta-Mendota Canal or modify or amend the rights and obligations under the Purchase Contract between Miller and Lux and the United States and the Second Amended Exchange Contract between the United States, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Reclamation and Central California Irrigation District, San Luis Canal Company, Firebaugh Canal Water District and Columbia Canal Company;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H486FB045E88D461C9DBD8453C9C499AD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>affect the allocation of water to Friant division contractors of the CVP;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7082A1E2ECC84F9FBC115A63A745C48C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>result in the involuntary reduction in contract water allocations to individuals or entities with contracts to receive water from the Friant division;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD50DE73697C74B7EB6AC650415470BBA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>result in the involuntary reduction in water allocations to refuge contractors; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8213C973E7584CF6BC6552529AE100EC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>authorize any actions inconsistent with State water rights law.</text></paragraph></section></title> <title id="HD85331ED659D48EF8FF1FB31F192DD89"><enum>III</enum><header>INFRASTRUCTURE</header> <section id="HFA1A837573164898ADCB5C124111633F"><enum>301.</enum><header>Shasta Reservoir enlargement project</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 40902(a)(2) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/58">Public Law 117–58</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6D16470ACEEF426BA6A9536ACD6B7F72"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B)—</text> <subparagraph id="H0FA6459D8C3E451B8B82A5BB6F73B07A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>this Act, except for any project for which—</quote> and inserting <quote>this Act; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73161BF696A74184965534EC9AB40E0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking clauses (i) and (ii); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5891E8858D164883AF0ED5F2F31E0C80"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>(except that projects described in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (B) shall not be eligible)</quote>. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HED9FF1E55D3F4777A3B80148A42D55BC"><enum>302.</enum><header>Water supply plan; projects</header> 
<subsection id="H11ED0AE5E7574C58BD8A310BD14B1806"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner of Reclamation shall develop a water deficit report, which shall identify—</text> <paragraph id="HD2DBA8D38B1842DC963C712E4DD05884"><enum>(1)</enum><text>projected water supply shortages in the State of California for irrigation water service, municipal and industrial water service, water supply for wildlife refuges supplied by the CVP or the SWP; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34A37D134F1F4237BCB0C36B314AB545"><enum>(2)</enum><text>infrastructure projects or actions which, if taken, would—</text> <subparagraph id="HC847B6D06550428CB87B7A4537A9C73F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>significantly reduce or eliminate the projected water supply shortage; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3BD346E78CD4392A86BEADAE80D8D4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fulfill water allocations consistent with agricultural, municipal and industrial contractors, water service or repayment contractors, water rights settlement contractors, exchange contractors, and SWP contractors with water delivery contractors on the CVP and SWP.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF6C5F48E380D4DE9A2D93EA91C01A5EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>The Commissioner of Reclamation shall provide a report described in subsection (a) to the House Committee on Natural Resources and the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources upon its completion.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2CA1D3E360AE438391E0E8EE583E60EB"><enum>303.</enum><header>Conservation fish hatcheries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4010(b)(5) of the Water Infrastructure Improvements for the Nation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HAC037FD04214436CA386C71100BBC4B1" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HED402EE869E84348907F3AB0C75D1101"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Semi-annual report</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Commerce shall submit to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate semi-annual reports that detail activities carried out under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H8309580F49BC4BAF9123E69A3ECA8CC9"><enum>304.</enum><header>Storage; duration</header> 
<subsection id="H90A9AEB6B4724E2C9303F45BCE9370D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Storage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4007 of the Water Infrastructure Improvements for the Nation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H711B2BFD21D8487CB3D06F8D2CC6DC7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1), by striking <quote>or any public agency organized pursuant to State law</quote> and inserting <quote>any public agency organized pursuant to State law, or any stakeholder</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF29ECB3E9C8143798491650E7402113F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (i), by striking <quote>January 1, 2021</quote> and inserting <quote>January 1, 2028</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9FCB649B2ADC4E3496F5F2C70A85443D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4013 of the Water Infrastructure Improvements for the Nation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7944AD8AFC49472FA1B4D9814C8C6375" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17CE27B82DE647BC9C0E3F9D91FC5458" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H823AAE37532942A8AAAF1AFB736599F0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H68286E3F149F44DB8A745C32AB546072" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HB7A0DB91805A400FA49CC6D13329C52C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 4007, which (except as provided in paragraph (3)), shall expire on December 31, 2028; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9BCB8E2224B44608A1356D8C6DE4DC79"><enum>305.</enum><header>Shasta Dam enlargement</header> 
<subsection id="H47AB58491BC74EF4AAE30091CE377C2E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>In accordance with section 4007 of the Water Infrastructure Improvements for the Nation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/322">Public Law 114–322</external-xref>), and as recommended by the Secretary in letters dated February 13, 2019; June 22, 2020; and December 3, 2020; funds made available in the Water and Related Resources account for the Bureau Reclamation in Acts of appropriation for fiscal years 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, and 2021 shall be made available to the Shasta Dam and Reservoir Enlargement Project.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H114870C65989478EAEE98CAF48517556"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>No provision of State law shall preclude or otherwise prevent any public water agency, including a public agency of the State, that contracts for the delivery of CVP water from assisting or cooperating with, whether by loan, grant, license, or otherwise, the planning and construction of any project undertaken by the Bureau of Reclamation to enlarge Shasta Dam.</text></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="H40E3E0A47916460FB159C7BE878D91DF"><enum>IV</enum><header>CVPIA ACTIONS</header> 
<section id="H92528323C11C41C2AFED26CE6EA11467"><enum>401.</enum><header>CVPIA restoration actions</header> 
<subsection id="HCC541D812F7E4563B8C66ED42BDF3D31"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Refuge water supply program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Interior shall complete the refuge water supply program under section 3406(d) of the Central Valley Project Improvement Act (title XXXIV of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/575">Public Law 102–575</external-xref>; 106 Stat. 4722) and shall, within that two-year period, give priority to completing the refuge water supply program when making funding decisions from the Central Valley Project Restoration Fund established under section 3407 of the Central Valley Project Improvement Act (106 Stat. 4726), the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/25">Public Law 117–25</external-xref>), the Land and Water Conservation Fund Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/88/578">Public Law 88–578</external-xref>), and other sources of funding.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6146FF02086546C092ABD595105CB318"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restoration actions deemed complete</header><text>Upon completion of the refuge water supply program pursuant to subsection (a), or September 30, 2025, whichever occurs first, the Secretary of the Interior shall deem complete the fish, wildlife, and habitat mitigation and restoration actions mandated under section 3406 of the Central Valley Project Improvement Act (title XXXIV of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/575">Public Law 102–575</external-xref>; 106 Stat. 4714).</text></subsection></section></title> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


