<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H389035BFB56A4E0E853F1E3EA65C896C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2486 IH: Closing the Congressional Revolving Door Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2486</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit former Members and elected officers of Congress from lobbying Congress at any time after leaving office, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC8E447335BF64047AF5D18E19F894ED2" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8B1F5850556C4DBBAD0B39869E219A6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Closing the Congressional Revolving Door Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCCF879232F154DE687BDB72591D7C2FE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting former members and officers of congress from lobbying congress</header> <subsection id="HD772E4AC60C543A18A110B2B58A5629A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Section 207(e)(1) of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB3322F7BF3CA4035AF92B932AA2FEBD8" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H390FE3D7AE434FDDB147E55A64B3DF7C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Members and elected officers of congress</header><text>Any person who is a Senator, a Member of the House of Representatives, or an elected officer of the Senate or the House of Representatives and who, after that person leaves office, knowingly makes, with the intent to influence, any communication to or appearance before any Member, officer, or employee of either House of Congress or any employee of any other legislative office of the Congress, on behalf of any other person (except the United States) in connection with any matter on which such former Senator, Member, or elected official seeks action by a Member, officer, or employee of either House of Congress, in his or her official capacity, shall be punished as provided in section 216 of this title.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HF058EC9C21B34172A53BA6180D20AB56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 207(e)(2) of such title is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9756C415A4304C4B88FB32F177001A24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph">Officers and staff</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph">Staff</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B5B4DB2CF2548588131F630AD0BF347"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an elected officer of the Senate, or</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDEBD49970F9B4C0D9F0C2B520CD622EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>leaves office or employment</quote> and inserting <quote>leaves employment</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64C72514907B40F3B88D0A404411C718"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>former elected officer or</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2F130EC74A274EE79AB3A6C0EFD1CCC5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to an individual who leaves office on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H40BCC91752C442249B4C699EA1F130C8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Benefits and services provided to former members of the house of representatives</header> <subsection id="HDDF6C267F15E400EB99A459B2B17AF0D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Benefits and services described</header><text>The House of Representatives may not make any of the following benefits and services available to an individual who becomes a former Member of the House (except to the extent such benefits and services are made available to members of the public):</text> 
<paragraph id="HD50FA843A42849E5828F13B59C38237D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Access to the Hall of the House.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7F47DD527F048459C4F60488276BE7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Access to athletic facilities and other facilities available for the use of Members of the House.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB301EE611D37422991F371A08235CE20"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Access to the Members’ Dining Room located in the House of Representatives wing of the United States Capitol.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC5C20870DB9541D69E5D9CBC41EE2613"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Access to parking spaces.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35F98B25CA7D40CD87B48D3C73C6EA15"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Access to material from the House document room.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67A5F92B149145C7934FC13029783694"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Use of the collections in the House Legislative Resource Center without borrowing privileges.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7963756A1B5A412781DBA0CE7381967A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header> 
<paragraph id="H826CE47F7D5446799B4A50AA61F9E028"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to waive elimination of benefit or service</header><text>The Speaker and the minority leader of the House of Representatives may jointly, on a case-by-case basis, grant a waiver of subsection (a) with respect to a former Member of the House and a benefit or service described in such subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0FDC8692151429EAF6B9B4343F59519"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication in congressional record</header><text>If the Speaker and the minority leader jointly grant a waiver under paragraph (1) to make a benefit or service available to a former Member, the Speaker and minority leader shall, not later than 24 hours after the waiver is granted, caused to have published in the Congressional Record a statement identifying the former Member and the benefit or service involved.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

