<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9007A02B86CE40BCB2536463A68059BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6031 IH: Safe Schools Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6031</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231024">October 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000468">Mrs. Fletcher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. C&#225;rdenas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To address and take action to prevent bullying and harassment of students.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H815B7FA985C54D02A3F85568357AC5D5" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF81F38D0C8AF4FAF8300212FA75DE404"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Schools Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H85083CBB12A84535B382899F25DF105E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5F1EE9BF3C694623A68C81B3075844DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Bullying and harassment foster a climate of fear and disrespect that can seriously impair the physical and psychological health of its victims and create conditions that negatively affect learning, thereby undermining the ability of students to achieve their full potential.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H013CC100FBA34CFCB7ADCF345BBA5D4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Bullying and harassment contribute to high dropout rates, increased absenteeism, and academic underachievement.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD3B6B2E84C1428893EEB5257633928E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Bullying and harassment include a range of behaviors that negatively impact a student’s ability to learn and participate in educational opportunities and activities that schools offer. Such behaviors can include hitting or punching, name-calling, intimidation through gestures or social exclusion, and sending insulting or offensive messages through electronic communications, such as internet sites, e-mail, instant messaging, mobile phones and messaging, telephone, or any other means.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9993B0284B414C5299C9FCBA3BA99BDD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Schools with enumerated anti-bullying and harassment policies have an increased level of reporting and teacher intervention in incidents of bullying and harassment, thereby reducing the overall frequency and number of such incidents.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9CAA0C6AD6143A492C14A619F3719F8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Students have been particularly singled out for bullying and harassment on the basis of their actual or perceived race, color, national origin, sex, disability status, sexual orientation, gender identity, sex characteristics (including intersex traits), or religion, among other categories.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C7B3B92540F4B6D8D758B5AA49F6FE7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Some young people experience a form of bullying called relational aggression or psychological bullying, which harms individuals by damaging, threatening, or manipulating their relationships with their peers, or by injuring their feelings of social acceptance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FB631ED089A43EF9C8EC2F2BDAA7FFE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Interventions to address bullying and harassment should incorporate evidence-based discipline policies and practices, such as Positive Behavior Interventions and Supports (PBIS) and other restorative practices that can minimize suspensions, expulsions, and other exclusionary and harmful discipline policies to ensure that students are not <quote>pushed-out</quote> or diverted to the juvenile justice system.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D6C1FDA489A4AE4B2BBA7E795904E56"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Perpetrators of bullying and harassment often have a history of trauma or psychological distress, or have been bullied themselves. These students, often discussed as <quote>bully-victims</quote>, require additional trauma-informed interventions and consideration. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H9C7C3DB8AAA14D0097BCBCEDF3AB099D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Safe Schools improvement</header> 
<subsection id="HF90585B010F54880B5EF8A7ABC3FE463"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title IV of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7101">20 U.S.C. 7101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H31EC8C5FC28E449480FD7541F703C18B"> <part id="HA30483F589C34CBB83AFA04DA11DCE04"><enum>G</enum><header>Safe Schools improvement</header> <section id="H24959249D54A4ECC94E113DCB0D9E6F6"><enum>4701.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this part is to address the problem of bullying and harassment conduct of students in public elementary schools and secondary schools.</text></section> 
<section id="H110C3930972E4188947CDB158F2D7F4E"><enum>4702.</enum><header>Anti-bullying policies</header> 
<subsection id="H103DB43E4AE8439DA2E6F906185A1288"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Bullying</header><text>In this part, the term <term>bullying</term> means conduct that adversely affects the ability of one or more students to participate in or benefit from the school’s educational programs or activities by placing a student in fear of harm. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H8328C0F52ED740AAA280DA7348726F02"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Policies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State that receives a grant under this title shall require all local educational agencies in the State to carry out the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H8D6D05C72C2F412E96CF07D3FA97B9AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Establish policies that prevent and prohibit conduct, including bullying and harassment, that—</text> <subparagraph id="H17542CBEF1C64D34B96AB7741BBC9911"><enum>(A)</enum><text>limits a student’s ability to participate in, or benefit from, a program or activity of a public school or local educational agency; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA49C62388B88411CA0F785722F9EA8FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>creates a hostile or abusive educational environment, adversely affecting a student's education, at a program or activity of a public school or local educational agency, including acts of verbal, nonverbal, or physical aggression or intimidation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H781FF52A421049A4892E7C51DB8E6AF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The policies required under paragraph (1) shall include a prohibition of bullying or harassment conduct based on—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0BF3B39B287C476B9FA60115B1285096"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a student’s actual or perceived race, color, national origin, sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), sex characteristics (including intersex traits), disability, or religion;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78A2C5AA2E724CB592C37752D24E3F30"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the actual or perceived race, color, national origin, sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), sex characteristics (including intersex traits), disability, or religion of a person with whom a student associates or has associated; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1F86201024DD4591836A37BFB27F57F4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other distinguishing characteristics that may be defined by the State or local educational agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D9FA17A16884F00807891432D5196BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Provide—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4C1AD5BEA9D54ABCBD71C99699D76894"><enum>(A)</enum><text>annual notice to students, parents, and educational professionals describing the full range of prohibited conduct contained in such local educational agency's discipline policies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBBFA6F786C8545DAB00F460EA8ABBA4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grievance procedures for students or parents to register complaints regarding the prohibited conduct contained in such local educational agency's discipline policies, including—</text> 
<clause id="HCB679C8578CD4AF5B2B879F5F2BAF5DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the name of the local educational agency officials who are designated as responsible for receiving such complaints; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7E5533E1C88C4E0782B259B7DB60D424"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>timelines that the local educational agency will establish in the resolution of such complaints.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F8B721243A5440CBF2B44A2016319F1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Collect annual incidence and frequency of incidents data about the conduct prohibited by the policies described in paragraph (1) at the school level that are accurate and complete and publicly report such data at the school level and local educational agency level. The local educational agency shall ensure that victims or persons responsible for such conduct are not identifiable. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDADE44681A844E02A0455632997F3D01"><enum>4703.</enum><header>State reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The chief executive officer of a State that receives a grant under this title, in cooperation with the State educational agency, shall submit a biennial report to the Secretary—</text> 
<paragraph id="H205165646913434EB06BEEE9325FEAED"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the information reported by local educational agencies in the State pursuant to section 4702(b)(4); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A34EECD9BC443F4879F504965BD58E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describing the State's plans for supporting local educational agency efforts to address the conduct prohibited by the policies described in section 4702(b)(1).</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF4891563DFE1468FA524A0256C13C268"><enum>4704.</enum><header>Evaluation</header> 
<subsection id="HAA2EF08661224B7FB2C28DF3CD3F7ADB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Biennial evaluation</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an independent biennial evaluation of programs and policies to combat bullying and harassment in elementary schools and secondary schools, including implementation of the requirements described in section 4702, including whether such requirements have appreciably reduced the level of the prohibited conduct and have conducted effective parent involvement and training programs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H01533D25B3B3482F93E9F125EB6B878E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data collection</header><text>The Commissioner for Education Statistics shall collect data from States, that are subject to independent review, to determine the incidence and frequency of conduct prohibited by the policies described in section 4702.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAAABAE1BDA5E449A9ECF419A28CA2DA8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Biennial report</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2024, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the President and Congress a report on the findings of the evaluation conducted under subsection (a) together with the data collected under subsection (b) and data submitted by the States under section 4703.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H81AF2DDD5A9C4AA49BAD308E69FF24A3"><enum>4705.</enum><header>Effect on other laws</header> <subsection id="H909EE55A46FD408D92535864B42CB7C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal and state nondiscrimination laws</header><text>Nothing in this part shall be construed to invalidate or limit rights, remedies, procedures, or legal standards available to victims of discrimination under any other Federal law or law of a State or political subdivision of a State, including title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>), title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), section 504 or 505 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>, 794a), or the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>). The obligations imposed by this part are in addition to those imposed by title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>), title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), and the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBAE4299599D44912A918645A1FD45A12"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Free speech and expression laws</header><text>Nothing in this part shall be construed to alter legal standards regarding, or affect the rights (including remedies and procedures) available to individuals under, other Federal laws that establish protections for freedom of speech or expression.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H72D46FCDF3F1496C9F7F0814073354B8"><enum>4706.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this part shall be construed to prohibit a State or local entity from enacting any law with respect to the prevention of bullying or harassment of students that is not inconsistent with this part.</text></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7A51E79377BA4F89854F65A2CD72AB3D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents in section 2 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 4644 the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H887168E415824D0FB83DA108F9AA7853"> <toc> <toc-entry idref="HA30483F589C34CBB83AFA04DA11DCE04" level="part">Part G—Safe Schools improvement</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4701. Purpose.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4702. Anti-bullying policies.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4703. State reports.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4704. Evaluation.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4705. Effect on other laws.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4706. Rule of construction.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

