<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1C0BA8D876FA42A6A52817575C7F89FF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3459 IH: Increasing Competitiveness for American Drones Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3459</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000067">Mr. Yakym</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 49, United States Code, to establish certain rules relating to unmanned aircraft systems and operations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB4D16F55A916452BB8995F6E2FDF7351" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HE82B0018DA02439EAB717C1C9C1AEE74"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Increasing Competitiveness for American Drones Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD93ED86FAAA3495DB4094D979B366A57"><enum>2.</enum><header>Beyond visual line of sight operations for unmanned aircraft systems</header><subsection id="HC03E32AC1F4A455291660897847F718B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/448">Chapter 448</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F8A379685AB4B7A8B94BB7F6F39E68E"><section id="HCDE7185A8C6C4EBFA0DC1ADE9CC4B393"><enum>44811.</enum><header>Beyond visual line of sight operations for unmanned aircraft systems</header><subsection id="HF92ADFD213344C2B90B05EFC23B220F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration (in this section referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) shall issue a notice of proposed rulemaking establishing a regulatory pathway for certification or approval of unmanned aircraft systems to enable commercial beyond visual line of sight (in this section referred to as <quote>BVLOS</quote>) operations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H27F59C2586774AA286AD33FF621569D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><paragraph id="HDAEF5E8600E44F84B68DDD7050A1B777"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), in promulgating the rule under subsection (a), the Administrator shall implement the final report and recommendations of the Beyond Visual Line of Sight Aviation Rulemaking Committee which were submitted to the Administrator on March 10, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE044936941904796B412C72FD2F9F6DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If the Administrator determines not to implement 1 or more of the recommendations described in paragraph (1), the Administrator shall provide to the appropriate committees of Congress a statement of explanation for such determination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2FD7A24D98F4EE0990C2B8B88E0985A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Final rule</header><paragraph id="H9A63D78BB6D34AEC8D44E60406A839C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall issue a final rule establishing a regulatory pathway for certification or approval of unmanned aircraft systems to enable commercial BVLOS operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC2546D861F04644A91854C315D351B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The final rule described in paragraph (1) shall, at a minimum, do the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF1798A11C3B04D60B8658B59FB94956B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Establish an applicable risk assessment methodology for the authorization of BVLOS unmanned aircraft system operations that includes quantified measures of acceptability which sufficiently account for the total air and ground risks associated with such operations and the means for mitigating such risks, taking into account an aircraft's size, weight, speed, kinetic energy, operational capability, proximity to airports and populated areas, operation over people, and operation beyond the visual line of sight, or operation during the day or night, including consideration of unmanned aircraft using an approved or accepted detect and avoid system appropriate for the class and type of airspace in which the operation is being conducted.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FF9609981E04692893D3E0F951D0902"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Establish remote pilot certification standards for remote pilots for BVLOS operations, taking into account varying levels of automated control and management of unmanned aircraft system flights.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H726788AE418E449289B1AB1D82CEC6B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Establish an airworthiness process for small unmanned aircraft systems that requires a manufacturer’s declaration of compliance to a Federal Aviation Administration accepted means of compliance, which shall not require type or production certification or the issuance of a special airworthiness certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5AB1255278D4262876CAE6AA51883C0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Establish a special airworthiness certificate to be issued upon a manufacturer’s declaration of compliance to a Federal Aviation Administration accepted means of compliance, which—</text><clause id="H8DB8FBB8014D46FEA9F054D44AEBDDC8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not require type or production certification;</text></clause><clause id="HAED0F21797984736B5016C7C0B5585C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall, at least, govern airworthiness of any unmanned aircraft system that—</text><subclause id="HC4E314E3573B45718BFFED94D4BA91F7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not—</text><item id="HC37EB506CC79434CA36104361EC6AEE2"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a small unmanned aircraft system; and</text></item><item id="HAB3C64B8369445C280B2D02CC99E9B58"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>appropriate for the process described in subparagraph (C), as determined by the Administrator;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HF9A59EB7572B44F6BB8F44CE037CAEB1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has a maximum gross weight of not more than 1,320 lbs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H370975EDF7104469AA8A21DF2D22ABD4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has a maximum speed of 100 miles per hour; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H229CDA4540F5481BB585C4AD5F9A11D1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>may require unmanned aircraft systems subject to the certificate to operate in the national airspace system at altitudes below at least—</text><subclause id="H7BB1E93ECF7645099D94CAE0445DADCA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>400 feet above ground level; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H2CBAB88D363D457F897F727D955C094E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to an unmanned aircraft system flown within a 400-foot radius of a structure, 400 feet above the structure's immediate uppermost limit.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23D03C84B9DF4255969C50A1AB70A39A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Amend the Code of Federal Regulations to establish generally applicable standards for the type certification of unmanned aircraft systems that the Administrator determines pose higher air or ground risks such that those unmanned aircraft systems are not appropriate for approvals under the processes described in subparagraph (C) or (D).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB0E472F420B480B98153819C101DA57"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Establish operating rules for—</text><clause id="H3DE11EFCBDF54D2D83A34BA2F54B07DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the operation of the unmanned aircraft systems described in subparagraph (C), (D), or (E); and</text></clause><clause id="H72DCE5F5DBD642B8AEB6ABE883612B90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>certain unmanned aircraft systems to enable lower-risk BVLOS operations without airworthiness requirements in a manner consistent with the final report and recommendations of the Beyond Visual Line of Sight Aviation Rulemaking Committee described in subsection (b)(1).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD622A8EA2DB4A20860E16D26647758A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall prohibit the use of the manufacturer declarations of compliance required under paragraph (2)(C) for other unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H48A1CD6BACBF4096B3FDE06F6CC22E40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/448">chapter 448</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44810">section 44810</external-xref> the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H6C0BA76BE2EA462680599DFA5EBFCC89" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">44811. Beyond visual line of sight operations for unmanned aircraft systems.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H2159DF78863247B19799FB0DB6A2E266"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Associate Administrator of UAS Integration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 106 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0929F765770345DE9ECAC2CDD5585EB6"><subsection id="H78DC956DDF9C458E976821F247DA5645"><enum>(u)</enum><header>Office of the Associate Administrator of UAS Integration</header><paragraph id="HC83963204F5144B59F887F07D269ECEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Federal Aviation Administration the Office of Associate Administrator of UAS Integration (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD351EDAB2904BFA94260BBF32096CF7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Associate Administrator</header><text>The Office shall be headed by an Associate Administrator, who shall—</text><subparagraph id="H33F077A0D58741ADB987A651912B36C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be appointed by the Administrator, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA369C47938624ABF8FA3ED9DA7947646"><enum>(B)</enum><text>report directly to the Administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4843EF1D7F2B426598190D4C0D0F72C8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the Office are to—</text><subparagraph id="H376A202709364DA683786CF54BC8944B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure and oversee the safe integration of UASs into the national airspace system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H376B5D045E81409DB08FA8DE87679800"><enum>(B)</enum><text>encourage and facilitate a commercially viable UAS industry and the leadership of the United States in UAS;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE9738C0DC8D48CABCE8EBF406CBDFAF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increase overall safety of the transportation system on a mode-neutral basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H476B99D6B81B41778CB34C12D025A614"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promote the global leadership of the United States in advanced aviation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H401FA7F78E7C43EB8895E45A1177117E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>manage the UAS Integration Office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9BC53EE2AD24909BDAA7356634DEEED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Associate Administrator shall—</text><subparagraph id="HC2212C2E9E7D4CAEB020247D97FAB2CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct rulemaking proceedings with respect to UASs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8E9CFED057B4CA6B2B7D99E483FC5C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>review submissions under the processes established in subparagraphs (C) through (E) of section 44811(c)(2) and, as appropriate, grant certifications and other operational approvals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC49535BFBB9F40BF99D1C625F9D5587E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>review, modify, accept, or approve industry-developed standards, means of compliance, and declarations of compliance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H926705F974F74454B13C0900F7BFF935"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consult and coordinate with subject matter experts from all relevant lines of business and staff offices in carrying out the duties described in this paragraph in a timely and efficient manner;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H10A81DC369854FB88601CE9E32D03871"><enum>(E)</enum><text>hire full-time equivalent employees, as appropriate, to build expertise within the Office in assessing new technologies and novel risk mitigations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0DB95B790C324986A319605792A644A1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>manage the UAS Certification Unit (as described in subsection (v)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5E8E5378B97F4F10A44423C1675F74C5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>engage in any other activities deemed necessary by the Associate Administrator to carry out the purposes described in paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4458312C71F942FEA50AB54E65B8DA83"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4997675ED2394110AA6F46B6DE752E7F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Beyond visual line of sight; BVLOS</header><text>The terms <term>beyond visual line of sight</term> or <term>BVLOS</term> mean the operation of a UAS beyond the capability of the flightcrew members to see the UAS with vision unaided by any device other than corrective lenses (such as spectacles or contact lenses).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5F0AA7498D6D4951B5BB2BAF7B502F38"><enum>(B)</enum><header>UAS</header><text>The term <term>UAS</term> has the meaning given the term <term>unmanned aircraft system</term> in section 44801.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HEA994EDE16F4489FBB2EE217720B5DA0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of UAS Certification Unit</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 106 of title 49, United States Code, as amended by section 3, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE24E4240AE264045A7D8304CBE47742D"><subsection id="HDC72E19A92B84B2B95C4AFDDAAB07BF0"><enum>(v)</enum><header>UAS Certification Unit</header><paragraph id="HF5C5E619F0524EB09DBA6C366B60F121"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Office of Associate Administrator of UAS Integration (as established in subsection (u)) the UAS Certification Unit (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Unit</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H631F73CC5B7D4F45B2222C4534D1A433"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><subparagraph id="HF480F114B69641BC91753CF68F264A38"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Employees</header><text>The Unit shall include not less than 1 employee from each relevant line of business of the Federal Aviation Administration, including the UAS Integration Office, the Aircraft Certification Service, the Flight Standards Service, Air Traffic Control, the Office of Chief Counsel, the Office of Environment and Energy, and any other office deemed appropriate by the Associate Administrator.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA30E55D0DD2D4FC594101B51BB89282E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Leadership</header><text>Out of the employees described in subparagraph (A), the Associate Administrator of the Office of Associate Administrator of UAS Integration may designate a director and steering committee to lead the Unit, which shall consist of not less than 1 employee from each line of business participating in the Unit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CEFBD41FF504A75A4F9CDE0BA0EB178"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Unit shall develop and implement the unmanned aircraft system certification or approval processes described in section 44811 by—</text><subparagraph id="H86545061E2444810A8C5FFE446FC8792"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reviewing and accepting industry-based airworthiness standards and means of compliance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7D5437B91364BD58A25C257218A71FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>engaging with applicants on the certification or approval process;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4045082FBB874CB9954878F5E97F601A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing clear and consistent guidance to industry standards organizations, including setting either a target level of safety or an acceptable level of risk;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49380BBF1301433FA3F64683503B7379"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promptly responding to questions from any person seeking an approval described in subparagraphs (C) through (D) of section 44811(c)(2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BBE4A9DF39C4F22B86DE62DE011383E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>taking all necessary steps to move the unmanned aircraft system certification and acceptance processes forward without avoidable delay.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H939396952F1A4995A8AA334197ED9473"><enum>(4)</enum><header>UAS Special Airworthiness Certificate Approvals</header><text>The Associate Administrator shall have the authority to grant or deny an application for any approval described in section 44811, upon review of the recommendations of the Unit and after consultation with the managers of the Aircraft Certification Service and Flight Standards Service, if either manager requests consultation.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HA43F4AF884184663A5B1ED436C0A4A35"><enum>5.</enum><header>Use of modeling and simulation tools in unmanned aircraft test ranges; program extension</header><subsection id="H0A2E1DB374454E51B7FAB8697C4D7276"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of modeling and simulation tools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 44803(b) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA0CF4F44A26649479FB16F3B9F9D041A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (11), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71AA09301C3242E99E70ABCB1D8174C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H37E4C132A71C405ABC004118C723F88C"><paragraph id="H605BB1B019DA43D2881116470281E79D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>use modeling and simulation tools to assist in the testing, evaluation, verification, and validation of unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF5A8C438AE4543A990787EFEDB0D5A4F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program extension</header><text>Section 44803(h) of title 49, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>September 30, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>September 30, 2028</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HEE97E2E4733940868BD45D3B648025B3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Extension of special authority for unmanned aircraft systems</header><subsection id="HEDA211D168034B01810FD748EC1BDF0E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H5E3294BBB1F24819B5950E664E7093C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the lack of appropriate certification standards, rules, and processes set by the Federal Aviation Administration for airworthiness determinations and operational approvals of unmanned aircraft systems (as defined in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code) puts the United States at a disadvantage in global competitiveness and delays the integration of promising new technology into communities in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB343A603655B44E692EAD3A9F5693B35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>this lack of progress on a standardized airworthiness and operational approvals approach compels the extension of authority to issue exemptions under section 44807 of such title 49; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80A9096DBCC1410D91D928FF648ACAB8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such section 44807—</text><subparagraph id="HFB4A8EBF583B4859B7290DEBF19E7347"><enum>(A)</enum><text>should continue to use a risk-based approach to authorize operations that do not fit within part 107 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0C038B3AA1642B69769833205584024"><enum>(B)</enum><text>should not be limited to type certificate applicants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H98F6E3B747D745E5B8025C590135F771"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>Section 44807(d) of title 49, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>September 30, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>on the date the rules described in section 44811 take effect</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H28299F1EE10E47E8B703A9107CD1BF57"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>Section 44807(a) of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>or chapter 447</quote> after <quote>Notwithstanding any other requirement of this chapter</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E2F2173D30D4F318CBD672F25A5D477"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expedited exemptions</header><text>In exercising authority under section 44807 of title 49, United States Code (as amended by subsection (b)), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall, taking into account the statutory mandate to ensure safe and efficient use of the national airspace system and without requiring a rulemaking or imposing the requirements of part 11 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, grant exemptions to enable—</text><paragraph id="H01105287E15C47178D4977F54900E6E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>low-risk beyond visual line of sight operations, such as certain package delivery operations or shielded operations within 100 feet of the ground or a structure; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE180B30F2554C67A5235DE8979720C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>extended visual line of sight operations that rely on visual observers to keep the aircraft or airspace within view.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88A831B357A0480B9C90B89379F3873E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clarification of status of previously issued rulemakings and exemptions</header><paragraph id="HF6D5A487EA7F4965B7B3C33A4C08E22C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rulemakings</header><text>Any rulemaking published prior to the date of enactment of this Act under the authority described in section 44807 of title 49, United States Code, shall continue to be in effect following the expiration of such authority.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E2E2A9AA0874C0596165748190D2782"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text>Any exemption granted under the authority described in section 44807 of title 49, United States Code, and in effect as of September 30, 2023, shall continue to be in effect until the date that is 3 years after the date of termination described in such exemption.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3269089F6C6548B6BA1BF64A3E179409"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Delegation</header><text>The authority granted to the Secretary of Transportation in such section 44807 may continue to be delegated to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration in whole or in part.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC9A6F6D7DC94DDD84ADBD99D73FB8C9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to interfere with the Secretary of Transportation's—</text><subparagraph id="HD986FEF214C24E45AC1A229D9D07F2E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>authority to rescind or amend the granting of an exemption for reasons such as unsafe conditions or operator oversight; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD714025D6C4F47ADB89E2FBA523CAD31"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ability to grant an exemption based on a determination made pursuant to such section 44807 before the expiration of that provision.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

