<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="H26B0D649B6B941D3867E34DD5A588135" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3848 EH: HOME Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3848</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To make certain improvements in the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs relating to homelessness, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="H395FDE47ABC540AC972B66C9EAB5D70B"> 
<section id="H2DBF332FAFBE4CAFBD9E9A39ECEC8883" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Housing our Military Veterans Effectively Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote>HOME Act of 2023</quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE57651FB6EDE4D5E93760474388C92AF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Per diem payments provided by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for services furnished to homeless veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2012 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEAA8885870F44BC5968C26B718E3BCF0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB1ED54150FE5440E9FE5D468A6BAFBF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B)—</text> 
<clause id="H19E83BD60A774C07BA856F14CB7BB21F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i)(II)(aa)(BB), by striking <quote>115 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>133 percent</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H97E2641CB22A424FBC0E6BC178B2E7A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H302965D842A747B0B11A140CDE91AC50" style="OLC"> 
<clause id="H01FBC050010844579B93DF0B6453D81F" indent="up3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, the Secretary may waive the maximum rate for per diem payments under clause (i)(II)(aa)(BB) or (ii) and, subject to the availability of appropriations, provide such payments at a rate that does not exceed 200 percent of the rate authorized for State homes for domiciliary care under subsection (a)(1)(A) of section 1741 of this title, as the Secretary may increase from time to time under subsection (c) of that section if the Secretary notifies Congress of such waiver.</text></clause> <clause id="H524BD41CF5B0495EB5271D586A774432" indent="up3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not, pursuant to clause (iii), waive the maximum rate described in such clause for more than 50 percent of all grant recipients and eligible entities in a fiscal year.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H41F04EBACAE644508A53FE18DBF37118"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H96706446C46B4814BE666E309186B010" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H0582FBA9C13F4A1B9C27C9E9E7F9E11B" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not provide more than 12,000 per diem payments under this section in a fiscal year.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6DB7514E9AEE4FDAAB2A04B69382C57B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block id="HC813B988DA3A48F99D420CEE6FAFFA19" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HA5AB272290B046ABB96F2FF545DF0AD8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports required</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the HOME Act of 2023, and not less frequently than twice each year thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the rate for per diem payments under this section that includes, for each Veterans Integrated Service Network of the Department, the following data:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6614BF8A1ABD4A8191AE4E7A7581CB16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The average rate for such a payment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7314F12927AC42A2BE8915C63AE0FC6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of locations where the rate for such a payment is within 10 percent of the maximum rate for such a payment authorized under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FFA592B3BD44EABA7C6D3565B126906"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The average length of stay by a veteran participating in a program described in section 2012(a) of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HEFE159EE69AB4AA0A62D3315F431B3CE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization for Secretary of Veterans Affairs to use of certain funds for improved flexibility in assistance to homeless veterans</header> <subsection id="H033E41D89285498DAA402931EFDCAF80"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may use amounts appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs to carry out section 2011, 2012, 2031, or 2061 of title 38, United States Code, to provide to a covered veteran, as the Secretary determines necessary—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0B892DFA5BC94B4E9F608D60817B3FA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>food, shelter, clothing, blankets, and hygiene items required for the safety and survival of the veteran;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0FD3ECA9DF1542EAA9E8665C502799D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>transportation required to support the stability and health of the veteran for appointments with service providers, the conduct of housing searches, and the obtainment of food and supplies; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5977C11105184012A5F23AD23DFC143E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>tablets, smartphones, disposable phones, and related service plans required to support the stability and health of the veteran through the maintenance of contact with service providers, prospective landlords, and family members.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAA45698CBDAB4373970EA92A0CB20B3D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Homeless veterans on Department of Veterans Affairs land</header> <paragraph id="H5B38B9D1D2EB448BA97ED6E647DE9F35" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may collaborate, to the extent practicable, with one or more organizations to manage the use of land of the Department of Veterans Affairs for homeless veterans for living and sleeping.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H864BCA829DDA491CB47DAC282EE9D892"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forms of collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collaboration under paragraph (1) may include the provision by either the Secretary or the head of the organization concerned of food services and security for property, buildings, and other facilities owned or controlled by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB09DCB031CAF4B1F96AA26E587101E1A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every six months thereafter until the date specified in subsection (d), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes, with respect to the period covered by such report—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1FA1731D2925451498CCA3EADF7F2875"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a statement, disaggregated by each medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs, of the amount of funds under this section—</text> <subparagraph id="HD982CD3D8DAB4A80AFA99326BBD4AC0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each such medical center requested from the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0A85EC97F9BD43ED9DF5616671C65EC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to which the Secretary provided each such medical center;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9C1AC9AF92DA424F9F85C9889967CB75"><enum>(2)</enum><text>data, disaggregated by each such medical center, relating to how each such medical center used amounts provided by the Secretary under this section;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7E35D3A73204C76AE4FA362069DF874"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of covered veterans to which the Secretary provided assistance under this section;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FF7F957CC0848E9B4C29137B0DAAEC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total amount of assistance the Secretary provided to covered veterans pursuant to subsection (a)(3) for communications equipment, broken down by the type of equipment provided;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4386B2B485F74CA5A3816AEC8C828D4C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the total amount of assistance the Secretary provided covered veterans pursuant to subsection (a)(2) for ridesharing;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE13CB86621CA4535881D851598E381E4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the number of covered veterans who received such assistance; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6F19E7AEAAAD4ACBB40730ED446C8EE3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a description, for each rideshare used by a covered veteran with such assistance, of the reasons such covered veteran used such rideshare.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5DC7C589AF9A476DB60056E4AD9AB62A"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of covered veterans who lived or slept on Department land;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H26DD2CA911BC483D892E15B7878B6EE8"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the amount of funds used to make available Department land for covered veterans to live and sleep;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11FAC91D332C429381D6A01E893BFA80"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the number of Department employees whose primary responsibilities involved providing services for covered veterans living or sleeping on Department land;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H996D947A27BF407E91BBA643F4F65DD6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the average length of time a covered veteran lived or slept on Department land, and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H827E834FD3D24CC0B821DC7D57C67980"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the period of time the Secretary expects Department land will be made available for covered veterans to live and sleep.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7314AD2194284F26AC806328EE6D2CC2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority under this section shall terminate on September 30, 2024.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCD291946439D4D9ABCA888AA35851CB3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered veteran</quote> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1750FE461AC04094A9B6E18586D30C66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a homeless veteran; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1DCBE33A09BA4F9B9C723AF496240DC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a veteran participating in the program carried out under section 8(o)(19) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(19)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2B6C4A406ADE48CBAEBD28F3B88E67E5" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Modification of certain housing loan fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The loan fee table in section 3729(b)(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>November 14, 2031</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>May 18, 2032</quote>.</text></section> </legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20231205" legis-day="20231205" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives December 5, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> <endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> </bill> 

