<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0CD80BEC153C43F0872AEE3479E38C66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3370 IH: Reclamation of War Powers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3370</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit funds available for the United States Armed Forces to be obligated or expended for introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H91A6ADE9BE824ED6AF5D77A05D7C0869" style="OLC"><section commented="no" id="HD64863CAD4294779ACD78FA0383E9B1B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reclamation of War Powers Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4EC71D0439334193A9DBEC2F0A17DC7C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose and policy</header><subsection id="HD09FC0D9444B4171AB0E79D692FE96F1"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the purpose of this Act to fulfill the intent of the Framers of the Constitution of the United States and ensure that the collective judgment of both Congress and the President will apply to the introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, and to the continued use of such forces in hostilities or in such situations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9FD33BB69FCA4F0787E47A4F07B8C10D"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Under article I, section 8, of the Constitution, it is specifically provided that Congress shall have the power to make all laws necessary and proper for carrying into execution, not only its own powers but also all other powers vested by the Constitution in the Government of the United States, or in any department or officer thereof.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2398626DCC9D424D958E6E64D35C5456"><enum>(c)</enum><text>The constitutional powers of the President as Commander-in-Chief to deploy United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, may be exercised only pursuant to—</text><paragraph id="HADCCF1E516BF4F8B9E1C1DCEFB7357C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a declaration of war;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12DB7F22494B4BAD858AA3AAF00EDD32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>specific statutory authorization; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AB716998460482D914077304E71672C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a national emergency created by attack or imminent threat of attack upon the United States, its territories or possessions, or its Armed Forces.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF89609ED2CAB4EE7982E3614A5137B39"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><subsection id="H2C19D21C7E1F4D46B2059F8C1DF692D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation</header><paragraph id="H28F2F81F012E464CB827EC2831234B88"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No funds available for the United States Armed Forces may be obligated or expended for introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, in the absence of—</text><subparagraph id="HC365EAB9402B491399995171618433BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a declaration of war;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB9EBFE2541A46009361FEBBD2B8F65E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>specific statutory authorization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBA9790C6E99438A8004D870C5EF2FF9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a national emergency created by an attack or imminent threat of attack upon the United States, its territories or possessions, or the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7046572685F5427F91E7677A7CAA4B89"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional limitation relating to national emergency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds available for the United States Armed Forces may be obligated or expended for introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, by reason of a national emergency created by an attack or imminent threat of attack upon the United States, its territories or possessions, or the Armed Forces only during the 60-day period beginning on such date of introduction of United States Armed Forces.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H51D3CE9F80574EC0B319532044D9D802"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on consideration of bill or joint resolution in violation of subsection <enum-in-header>(a)</enum-in-header></header><paragraph commented="no" id="H9F3CD99D68D64D1DA362C383E35BE60A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>It shall not be in order in the House of Representatives or the Senate to consider any bill or joint resolution that would make funds available in violation of subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H75CA3656582741E1B1E7F9513F2B7751"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enactment as exercise of rulemaking power of House of Representatives and Senate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection is enacted by Congress—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC9170FBFA0D7448F9E82FD9B7657E0F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the House of Representatives and the Senate, respectively, and as such are deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, and such procedures supersede other rules only to the extent that they are inconsistent with such other rules; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB25C607E739640BE929F6233F2187854"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4F6471413AB04E5D91D44DB703524497"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><subsection id="HEA8D434F5A114DF7A2523C833E2FD71B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report relating to declaration of war or specific statutory authorization</header><paragraph id="HA68BB7F0E94E4A3F8044DEF612EDAA15"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall, in the case of a declaration of war or specific authorization for introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, submit to Congress a report on the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5DFF8188B90746139919D0ADD656D9B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An analysis of the threat to be countered by the use of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H599A7BC4117049B880CCE625B9CA02A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The specific objectives and justification for such objectives to be achieved by the use of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A0FCCC4C2174C8F928367FD54EED6FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the scope and duration, cost, and likelihood of success of the use of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5C347FBD1D444FBFDFBC7CBF82C020"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text>The initial report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted to Congress not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of a bill or joint resolution that provides for a declaration of war or specific authorization for introduction of United States Armed Forces as described in paragraph (1), and an update of such report shall be submitted to Congress every 90 days thereafter until the United States Armed Forces are no longer engaged in hostilities or situations as described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HFFDD424E2B234BC29559D35425E221E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report relating to national emergency</header><paragraph id="HAC9C836D8A2F4FB0A3B3DC54DE637C30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall, in the case of introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, by reason of a national emergency created by an attack or imminent threat of attack upon the United States, its territories or possessions, or the Armed Forces, submit to Congress a report on the matters described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EFEF93F493E426A80BBD640E7103CF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted to Congress not later than 48 hours after introduction of United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, as described in paragraph (1), and an update of such report shall be submitted to Congress not later than 60 days after the date of submission of the initial report.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H513B0F9118414317A1CB9732D31D1F63"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed—</text><paragraph id="H66F78C9409D64446913A604B9D3D113D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to alter the constitutional authority of Congress or of the President, or the provisions of existing treaties; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF809789D92674BFFAE07CF7802EE3AF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to apply to those activities approved and reported pursuant to section 503 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3093">50 U.S.C. 3093</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD67602DD7C624A18A8FCF851BD45BE78"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>introduction of United States Armed Forces</term> includes the assignment of members of such Armed Forces to command, coordinate, participate in the movement of, or accompany the regular or irregular military forces of any foreign country or government when such military forces are engaged, or there exists an imminent threat that such forces will become engaged, in hostilities.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

