<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD3650EC58E954F8D9E2F5C372CF6B98A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5097 IH: Producing Real Opportunities for Technology and Entrepreneurs Investing in Nutrition Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5097</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 to direct the Secretary of Agriculture to establish research centers of excellence for alternative protein innovation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEF191AACD89448498F01FBC469B6EA2C" style="OLC"><section id="H5449377F206A4C0B9DCD826F0B080D5B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Producing Real Opportunities for Technology and Entrepreneurs Investing in Nutrition Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD4A6DE588F934DBB89E3FD151EE44934"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H87EF1D0456E64FBC98F12AF988CDF62B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Protein innovation that produces the characteristics of animal protein using plants, animal cell cultivation, and fermentation is an essential component of the bioeconomy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC256BAC1F3BB42E78AED80B7423E7436"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States has produced several groundbreaking biotechnological breakthroughs across the alternative protein sector in the last decade.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H536916CED2304A778599C5C4698A3BE8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In recent years, multiple countries have dramatically increased public investments into alternative protein research and development while government spending in the United States is still extremely modest.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A1A7DC5FDFD439981849C6642A3FD60"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the United States Department of Agriculture, every one dollar of investment into agricultural research results in twenty dollars of economic productivity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C7F0C78888343CA93911367A82334EB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>As of 2019, the plant-based food industry supported over 55,000 jobs in the United States, and the alternative protein sector could create as many as 10 million jobs globally by 2050.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A935375DCCD48919500FE63CA61FF32"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Diversifying the protein supply of the United States will increase domestic supply chain resilience, decrease reliance on foreign grain and other commodities, and provide more choices to American consumers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73E4290F3C7B42EB8B450F8AD184928A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The global demand for meat is predicted to double by 2050, thus increasing the need for additional food sources such as alternative proteins.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B79C9B2810845969B5FD8E61F47ACD6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Widespread adoption of alternative proteins would decrease the risks associated with antibiotic resistance and zoonotic disease.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30B80818968244D5AA1FC4C8D4E00838"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Widespread adoption of alternative proteins would improve global and domestic food security. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H642E14F051AB495CA73E01A8874D9BED"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Widespread adoption of alternative proteins would improve the nutritional quality of the United States food system, contributing to improved health outcomes. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F7CD35C1FE642829DC84DF82603D75F"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Widespread adoption of alternative proteins would likely help the United States’ food system become more climate-friendly and sustainable.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H40CC759842D74D5D907832596181F7E2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Research centers of excellence for alternative protein innovation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1673 of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5926">7 U.S.C. 5926</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0989F6AECD6B4B429604A4363C42A5EC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HFF720E74C85A4177B46EFF54ACC57271"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Centers of Excellence for Alternative Protein Innovation</header><paragraph id="H43042D42AE7B4F5485E125E05C3F1BB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recognition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall recognize not fewer than 3 centers of excellence, one of which will be led by an 1890 Institution (as defined in section 2 of the Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7601">7 U.S.C. 7601</external-xref>)), to focus on the advancement of alternative proteins in the areas described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34121A13BD8A43A8B2C251C8EE524F63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Areas of focus</header><subparagraph id="HE9638828E8C84546AD078C82DA911C59"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Alternative proteins research and development</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A center of excellence recognized under paragraph (1) may carry out research, development, and education programs that support the quality, production, or cost-effectiveness of foods with the characteristics of animal meat using plants, animal cell cultivation, or fermentation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18DEBF2272F745D4AD1484BFDB8AA376"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Student success and workforce development</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A center of excellence recognized under paragraph (1) may engage in activities to ensure that students have the skills and education needed to work in the alternative proteins industries, including agricultural science, technology, engineering, mathematics, and related fields of study.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H25445285AA1D43A6877EBBFF5F862D70"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H087C926647554E63A2AC2A61502608EC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Producing Real Opportunities for Technology and Entrepreneurs Investing in Nutrition Act</short-title>, and every year thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report describing—</text><subparagraph id="H349EFC49161B484CB0239A47319A9287"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the resources invested in the centers of excellence recognized under paragraph (1); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE10B31DCCEB4DCFB2FAA53FF9AEF1CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the work being done by such centers of excellence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HE66A1B0DE7D04724A40641697AA03FC9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Agriculture and Food Research Initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2(b)(2)(E) of the Competitive, Special, and Facilities Research Grant Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3157">7 U.S.C. 3157(b)(2)(E)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE5479EA0810E4DE08D3FC5E96D7A91ED" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (ii) through (v) as clauses (iii) through (vi), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1539DE9DD998469194F430312C40A075"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (i) the following new clause: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4AB048C9B298455590E96A998BE51360"><clause id="H17620535AF164B3AB4213EE17CF7C102"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">characteristics of animal meat using plants, animal cell cultivation, or fermentation;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H4604711F1F3E4A56AFF990D5B587EA18"><enum>5.</enum><header>Agricultural Research Service</header><subsection id="HFCE53661747D4693A684CF9E0FA3F84E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of national program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Administrator of the Agricultural Research Service (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), shall establish a new national program dedicated to the research of alternative proteins that is focused on developing knowledge and enabling commercially-viable technologies related to foods with the characteristics of animal meat using plants, animal cell cultivation, or fermentation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE40560A2A3DC44578443FBC073F7F095"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the program $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H863A307FBE3B45ECAAEB9C5B60B20056"><enum>6.</enum><header>Alternative protein advanced manufacturing and production grant program</header><subsection id="H3DEAEE2604B249329FB856CA7E7D8DA3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a grant program to ensure that the United States has a viable domestic manufacturing and production capability to support and sustain increased global demand for alternative proteins. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA5AC34C948B64E17BB5782EF28CFDAFC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity is eligible to receive a grant under subsection (a) if—</text><paragraph id="HF0E29227E1374A0A8249EB38596CD358"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such entity is—</text><subparagraph id="H9BFB23202155430EB62830CC631D9A8C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nonprofit or for-profit private entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3269FACDB934467FBB4F488B868C5EE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H613E806358664DE6B3132841B4F6D6DB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a National Laboratory;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2B0D0073E1B484FB5A7C15EB9295731"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a State or local government; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A1856C221BA41D9982A86CE5EB82584"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (D); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE20FC5299F9046AFA600D4917382F3A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such entity—</text><subparagraph id="HF8A5D055FB534585A6BFB0CAD50EB18F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is headquartered in the United States and operates primarily within the United States; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H871AB08D1A6B4613B8EC8DABE3313846"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is at least 51 percent owned and controlled by 1 or more individuals who are citizens of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDEB8BCE0EF546EDBE0DE966355803A1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>deploys intellectual property and content that is owned by United States individuals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C3068F72278474D956763B565049C94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants</header><paragraph id="H836E6E7AE0EC44B28F00681AA3DC18D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity that receives a grant under this section shall use funds received through the grant—</text><subparagraph id="HD9F50B330D414E64A880CD9A7ED999C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to carry out 1 or more demonstration projects for the advanced manufacturing, production, or processing of alternative protein; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EF6B257B4114788BD5F41AE365B8639"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to construct 1 or more new commercial-scale facilities for the advanced manufacturing, production, or processing of alternative protein in the United States; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB5CC6DCD2184B98B0B99F14A34A0203"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to retool, retrofit, or expand 1 or more existing facilities located in the United States and determined qualified by the Secretary for advanced manufacturing, production, or processing of alternative proteins.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCF0FB1604FC4401975FFC1D191066C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of a grant awarded under this section shall be not less than $10,000,000 for an eligible entity carrying out 1 or more projects described in paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3C28CDE0E8A4A258C41CC4A2050F138"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out the program $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H0FC1DF32D8A64A289291BC13BDC5020C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Alternative protein workforce development grant program</header><subsection id="H8FC8285EEB0844C3A4974120952AE3FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a competitive grant program to support alternative protein workforce development.</text></subsection><subsection id="H464A0D38FB5A4D999EF5AE6414426647"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity is eligible to receive a grant under this section if the entity is—</text><paragraph id="H1988AE8C37BB4618867F3B3906AA27CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a governmental entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED2951734BE84F22B55B75C943765292"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a public, private, or cooperative organization organized on a for-profit or nonprofit basis; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H829AFA66CC2141BB95CB2AE0CE18A673"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an Indian Tribe (as defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>)) on a Federal or State reservation or any other federally recognized Indian Tribe<italic></italic>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H056AC63427564A629B79F37B444261D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity to which a grant is made under this section may use the grant funds to—</text><paragraph id="HB3E1927B26D04FE78E8B5FD82C36E82F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>train new and existing employees on alternative protein production and processing methods;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H196D2F52134642D99ECC311781562FAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a center for training, technology, and trade that will provide training to employees who process alternative protein;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB2A8D6F45B04B3B959EAF343D051856"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide higher-education scholarships to students pursuing careers in alternative protein production and processing, including at community colleges;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H144E207CAACC40B3BF922B4A37AF1A59"><enum>(4)</enum><text>conduct regional, community, and local economic development planning and coordination for the purpose of increasing alternative protein production and processing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H640D054D904245AC848322F6593DC099"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to gain compliance with Federal, State, or local regulations related to alternative protein production and processing; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H692E06ED325A4AD4A76AFEA58D85AF05"><enum>(6)</enum><text>facilitate business and lending opportunities related to alternative protein production and processing, including identifying relevant information necessary for obtaining—</text><subparagraph id="H8712B99728E04BCE9E7FFC6E2F0C9C96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>private capital investments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CDDC00381C848E592B7D355947A0481"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal and State loan guarantees; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H661C88A7A6D3495486DD2ACF6AB10981"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Federal and State direct grants; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC11F42D61E7046EA93A4E834548DCCE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other financial support mechanisms from Federal and State entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9D24113E9DC1417F9966DD4E630ABAE7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC57A42717A7440AEB3705A1F17421EA9"><enum>8.</enum><header>National strategy on alternative proteins</header><subsection id="H403F6D922CD74A2AB8210764826518BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of a national strategy on alternative proteins</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall—</text><paragraph id="H771BC021ECE84E479CBF5FAC32734B6C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a national strategy on alternative proteins in coordination with the Secretaries concerned that meets the requirements of subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D8CF9569AF943959793C414EC01F55D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, finalize such strategy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE73FDF0889FD4B0DB92EED8AB1B0A70B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When developing the national strategy under subsection (a), the Secretaries concerned shall consider—</text><paragraph id="H8C3E6A0317E54B398C4553747306CB43"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the best available science related to products with the characteristics of animal meat using plants, animal cell cultivation, and fermentation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE2031052A0040CE9A10E73F1D067D91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the societal benefits of expanding research, development, and production of alternative proteins relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H205257ED89C54C1DB406A6D45C5FB8E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>personal and public health;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50B7A540CB8B494E837EED1EA50514FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>climate change and energy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC185889A2F3E40E0B812481C1C088C6F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>food and agricultural innovation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H181ED8636FBC42D5A52FFEF10606A0A3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>resilient supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02EF600546EF483DAE47507C006C90A7"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cross-cutting scientific advancements; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1EBDA626FD0416E9F5EFE6C1E31DA5A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>global competition and the economic benefits of alternative proteins relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H9CB368C8D86C498EAFC384DCB9C92128"><enum>(A)</enum><text>future economic productivity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F5AE379399541BD8FDEE98396CAFA83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>job creation in the biotechnology sector; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H097EED422CBC4E87B0F81AF185AADF8F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>existing public investments and strategies of competitor countries; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD30199374F4A4B47A231229DCC8A50E5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>existing policies and programs offered by the Federal and State governments that—</text><subparagraph id="H8C49410D494349EEAC31F206531C8221"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fund open-access research and development at higher-learning institutions and government agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H168E1BE599E94A6A99211A56CF143E61"><enum>(B)</enum><text>incentivize private sector research and development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0A274E3A81E4F899760CFA0868DC41E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support new and existing alternative protein producers and manufacturers; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1F1F80C7534464DA3D91A7B413714EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support farmers in the United States that produce outputs related to alternative proteins; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0411DB1EBFF46A5962B0B338D53E426"><enum>(E)</enum><text>represent a barrier for effective—</text><clause id="H54FC9DD2CD0348F780D7E4C594B795AD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>open-access alternative protein research and development;</text></clause><clause id="H939EE8B1DADC494A9E08FA56D685EEB3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>scale-up of alternative protein production and manufacturing; and</text></clause><clause id="HD304A938C154433BA79AD56E5E0F59F7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>regulatory oversight.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF77E4F615804AA3BC5CC33B644BC650"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The national strategy shall—</text><paragraph id="H01D59DB024AE42A28BBEB8283B0FD357"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use a whole-of-government approach to ensure that the United States remains the global leader of alternative protein research, development, production, and workforce development for future generations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A1B9090C9BF43148BDE5DC212BB2CEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include—</text><subparagraph id="HB6DF9E5E6C124321B3171FF80A8F4D20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>objectives to fulfill the purpose of the national strategy specified in paragraph (1), including interagency coordination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H235712F2590342D69FCC9FDA6551AA76"><enum>(B)</enum><text>barriers to fulfill such purpose; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6522FC09980A4D6D88A29EA48D65EEE8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>solutions to the barriers identified in subsection (b)(4)(E); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27F9C63541A04CDFBF9B8EEC7ED8A405"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a plan for the implementation of the national strategy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6705984CE470438C9AF1D4991B3A1478"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Secretaries concerned defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Secretaries concerned</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H0D5C249C5F5B4BC5B6B354C27096EA62"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Defense; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD00785F77549414DBC43C0F6E60C7B6E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H342CB7CF459946C6A6D02AF3AD3B115E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96024DD5A38246A8B651CDC81FC54766"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Director of the National Science Foundation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C755140515F4FA6B1B071E3ABE2A9CE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Director of the National Institutes of Health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CB678312F444E3BBCC7E826838D8584"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Commissioner of Food and Drugs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1357ED1E888748DFB1DE96B0D2EBA854"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5745E0258B5F4A4A92AABE8A68A08FCF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H318B0480D05C4EB98A56AC8EBD4D84E1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9954625A9F134097BF014EB369738AFB"><enum>9.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, shall be construed to support the production of insects for food or animal feed.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

