<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCC6612B49CBD46E2BC30F1F7133947C6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6614 IH: Maintaining American Superiority by Improving Export Control Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6614</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 relating to licensing transparency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7DB76EBC05A845319E954897A886EFB6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7FB5184C7241422587541DD85677DC3F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maintaining American Superiority by Improving Export Control Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H61F1AD9EDD08432E8BBC1CA026124989" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Licensing transparency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1756 of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4815">50 U.S.C. 4815</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE385FBCBF54C4CD9BE404936F86B89CA" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H153A00941352467E8BF672BB82A9EE8A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H55CF4054B4BB4059B0E8124B4CB6F23D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, and not less frequently than every 90 days thereafter, the Secretary, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on license applications, enforcement actions, and other requests for authorization for the export, reexport, release, and in-country transfer of items controlled under this part to covered entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6830001E9E434167883033C990AD6B66"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by paragraph (1) shall include, with respect to the preceding 90-day period, the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1F81B50BE6E347348D73ECC90FE34B50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For each license application or other request for authorization—</text> <clause id="HFDB0BD78AE694B1791916469303ACEDB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the name of the entity submitting the application (both parent company as well as the subsidiary directly involved), a brief description of the item (including the Export Control Classification Number (ECCN) and level of control, if applicable), the name of the end-user, the end-user’s location, a value estimate, decision with respect to the license application or authorization, and the date of submission; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA204CFF97F8047F09B2FA5054BD170C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date, location, and result of site inspections, monitoring, and enforcement actions to ensure compliance with United States export controls.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC008B1BE86A4C3A8E9500750EB59A83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Aggregate statistics on all license applications and other requests for authorization as described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAB92E115A212495D9D30EFC7985F11C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>For each license denial in which items in category EAR99 constitute at least 50 percent of the financial value of the license application, a list detailing what specific items are being denied a license.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56B13DA0677F449BB630D886863DB091"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8E1A403EE868448AA50695B35D7EE04F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term ‘appropriate congressional committees’ means—</text> <clause id="H1258B87056E64283A324D1DCCBEA97AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA198F4B822864A3F82C41B041F9CCE3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AB0D7186D9E42D0853C677DAEF8D1BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term ‘covered entity’ means any entity included on—</text> 
<clause id="H3ACD50276B684485AC7718C2FB4F587D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the list maintained and set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations;</text></clause> <clause id="HBC02FD6FEF6F40B2850A166AE517A1EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the list maintained and set forth in Supplement No. 7 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDFA5EA57A0564DA492A2B9910D0AE2F0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the list maintained and published under section 1260H of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/113">10 U.S.C. 113</external-xref> note).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill>

