<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H2C3215FFF83A4CBA874FB2A15D0298C9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5721 RH: Rape Kit Backlog Progress Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 206</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5721</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–256]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000597">Ms. Lee of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on September 26, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to require certain reporting on sexual assault kit testing.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HJU00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H7FB4BC8BBCB24D0A894949963A33BDEC"><section id="H96339F629D4B47768A9DF4D38467389E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rape Kit Backlog Progress Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCB49E3AE66EF4E24B70B6CA2E9A18932"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H79B31B9AFB95432DAEAF4B12A0E4AFA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sexual assault kit includes a sexual assault forensic exam, meaning an examination provided to a sexual assault patient by a health care provider who has specialized education and clinical experience in the collection of forensic evidence and treatment of these patients, which includes—</text><subparagraph id="H23838E4688824AE0B82163558BDE32B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>gathering information from the patient for the medical forensic history; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E8254197A90417799AE2B7779E68BC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an examination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B0F3F00B4AB4B3796F864144490DC8C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordinating treatment of injuries, documentation of biological and physical findings, and collection of evidence from the patient; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4C33E1EDB6A41F5B087305FC8239D95"><enum>(D)</enum><text>documentation of findings; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFEAA065766D437B82363FF533D48D9E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>providing information, treatment, and referrals for sexually transmitted infections, pregnancy, suicidal ideation, alcohol and substance abuse, and other non-acute medical concerns; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H006197AA0D734B3083A4C312578D5F80"><enum>(F)</enum><text>providing follow-up as needed to provide additional healing, treatment, or collection of evidence. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1962876BAA294E82B442A8E23F775663"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A sexual assault kit is an important forensic tool used by law enforcement and prosecutors to investigate and prosecute sexual assault and other crimes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6BEFEAB42984ECAB01FD19752A1B3A4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>It is estimated that there are currently well over 100,000 untested sexual assault kits in America, but the exact number is not known.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A126C7C90464B7AAB5A455DE8904D1C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Untested sexual assault kits means that there are sexual assaults unprosecuted, sexual assaults occurring that could have been prevented, and a delay in uploading DNA to Combined DNA Index System (commonly known as <quote>CODIS</quote>) that can assist law enforcement in solving other violent crimes. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H28537F3FB5C5483DBE7F51A740BA08B1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report to Attorney General required on sexual assault kit testing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 502 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10153">34 U.S.C. 10153</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H71C242E396C24095A0E4732D51A80C64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE07E98CE87AE40ABAFBAE5EFB9F21680" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HJU00"><paragraph id="HE85EBBE4378D4DE69D3A740DF0D92521"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A report indicating whether—</text><subparagraph id="H810A44AE5BFE4AF2AA881CB9413C7CDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State or unit of local government has conducted a comprehensive sexual assault kit inventory, commonly known as a ‘backlog inventory’, to identify the physical location, untested or tested status (or full sexual assault kit status, if available), and any individual test kit identification or tracking information of each sexual assault kit in the possession of such State or unit of local government, or that has been otherwise transmitted by a State or unit of local government to a third-party, such as for testing, storing, processing, or handling;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF96C48E6C4F34F8CB55412779E335555"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to each sexual assault kit that the victim has consented to have collected, the State or unit of local government has submitted each such sexual assault kit to a laboratory for DNA analysis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H164824EEBB9D4622B543F38F7CD11EF5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">results of any such DNA analysis were uploaded to the Combined DNA Index System;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2513D4EE26004D77930D4116B8363522"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the State or unit of local government has established an electronic tracking system for a victim to identify the physical location of their sexual assault kit and the results of any DNA analysis that was performed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D73CAAD84A34871B341A30CDE7818E5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the State or unit of local government has established a victim notification protocol for informing a victim of the status of their sexual assault kit, including where their sexual assault kit was analyzed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCD175F5F70243D791CEAAE126945B24"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State or unit of local government has in place a comprehensive sexual assault kit inventory system to identify sexual assault kit status, physical location, and any test kit identification or tracking information of each sexual assault kit in the possession of such State or unit of local government, or otherwise transmitted by a State or unit of local government to a third-party, such as for testing, storing, processing, or handling; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8AA7895D1D4415DB828F13C2CCCA685"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the information in any comprehensive sexual assault kit inventory system described in subparagraph (F) is updated, and how and when it is updated.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H76F58A784E9743F1A36BD4640D5B3F43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H372A6AA652B14BAB964BC3A56FB56D04" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HJU00"><subsection id="H240BD357B01D4EF2A4A0EDC4A073059E" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination by Attorney General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> Between the receipt of a grant application and deciding on such application, the Attorney General shall determine—</text><paragraph id="H3FF4A85694F64A4E8A661AB2AA54FA57" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the State or unit of local government has completed the conduct described under subsection (a)(7); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H707D20ACBA7245D89B15AC07B47AC63C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such conduct has not been completed, the reason that it has not been completed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H349B99788D6A47A6A1672F53EA4AEF95"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or unit or local government shall only be eligible for a grant under this subpart if the Attorney General determines such State or unit of local government has completed the conduct described under subsection (a)(7).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9568BBFFF285486AAACD48ED2A97DFA2" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirement for grant recipients</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or unit of local government that has been awarded a grant under this subpart as of the date of the enactment of the <quote>Rape Kit Backlog Progress Act of 2023</quote> shall have one calendar year from such date of enactment to complete the conduct described in subsection (a)(7) or such State or unit of local government shall become ineligible for a grant under this subpart.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB0DDA742C04D4847A3A642197E70BDB8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H56632E21E17D4D598D83A53F6184D6B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sexual assault kit</header><text>The term <term>sexual assault kit</term> means evidence gathered by a medical professional from a victim following a sexual assault, which evidence may—</text><subparagraph id="H91437249D5F04656A0EADC9D54C19B54"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include swabs, test tubes, microscopic slides, and evidence collection envelopes, for hairs and fibers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E59A6FC44A64158A124CE4E3510C674"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">vary in accordance with the circumstances of the sexual assault and with any applicable rules or procedures of the jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF297027B2F84812BD9FDB0CB17FC79E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sexual assault kit status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>sexual assault kit status</term> means whether an individual sexual assault kit is—</text><subparagraph id="H2560B65317374599B8C01572FA32C231"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collected and untested;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43ECC8D310114F0B8B5DF044B7913A3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>collected and tested;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA20BDBED3D8042C7A00EAF37DA01FE03"><enum>(C)</enum><text>lost or missing, expired or spoiled; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD11F638A4BB647C39CD42E7F380B03F2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>tested and results reported to the victim, proper authorities, and the Combined DNA Index System.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H38021ED106D642F2947A47EA2B3D8932"><enum>4.</enum><header>Attorney General Public Report on Rape Kit Backlogs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7581C3619BEA4BD495B29878346ED573" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HJU00"><section id="HCDD6D2E876A3473583E54C3CDC9021C5"><enum>510.</enum><header>Attorney general public report on rape kit backlogs</header><subsection id="H4FDBF84D170A483C80E1E96489249B9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than two years after the date of the enactment of the <quote>Rape Kit Backlog Progress Act of 2023</quote>, and annually thereafter, the Attorney General shall make publicly available on the internet website of the Department of Justice a report, including—</text><paragraph id="H9B00C204A0424188A414E8BF5D405665"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each report on the conduct described under section 502(a)(7) received from an applicant for a grant under this subpart; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB9E85C525854E16A3666B0C10A78BFF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an aggregate analysis of the reports described under paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7EEF503CEAE4F4683103F0724AB58E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if an applicant for a grant under this subpart has been awarded a grant; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H807F734C15C5431CBCFF28A692E8931F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if an applicant for a grant under this subpart completed the conduct described under section 502(a)(7) and if it has not completed the conduct described under such subsection, the reason that the conduct has not been completed. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF66FA2FFE0BD45C193A53EBC153C96C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on personally identifiable information</header><text>Any information published by the Attorney General pursuant to this section may not contain the personally identifiable information of a victim and if such information was erroneously published, it shall be removed from the website of the Department of Justice immediately upon discovery. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

