<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1BA19BDF8DE2410588052E9CF141DD5C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2393 IH: Combating Cartels on Social Media Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2393</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Homeland Security to implement a strategy to combat the efforts of transnational criminal organizations to recruit individuals in the United States via social media platforms and other online services and assess their use of such platforms and services for illicit activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B0541320A124CE88F8C495896509C0C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2C75774FB4C9410E8E89404AB636B155" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combating Cartels on Social Media Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H21E44AC4F7A54070A0B7A0493EEA2D7A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HF0587672EF864B8693B2569F70D2F82C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H96488E3CE7514FF7970BCF3EF196A26F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6FE6D3C4C97F46939B01C8FCDA6404D2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HABA848CD02974D689CBEF25EA66E7118"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered operator</header><text>The term <term>covered operator</term> means the operator, developer, or publisher of a covered service.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCA847FE170F745E8A4F1D32655D3EEF2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered service</header><text>The term <term>covered service</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H3685D31C39184E3C8C99095273A3F3E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a social media platform;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAA1A4DA2C4F041E08EFAB9AD2B0729D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a mobile or desktop service with direct or group messaging capabilities, but not including text messaging services without other substantial social functionalities or electronic mail services, that the Secretary determines is, has been, or will be used by transnational criminal organizations in connection with matters described in section 3; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D0CD48585CA4C22B361BE585218D3E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a digital platform, or an electronic application utilizing the digital platform, involving real-time interactive communication between multiple individuals, including multi-player gaming services and immersive technology platforms or applications, that the Secretary determines is, has been, or will be used by transnational criminal organizations in connection with matters described in section 3.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6BA820DBE5F344828D7070144D7A4DA4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A90B6A87B214BF9B7B9730070285971"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H07248697C3FF4E9F91C03DC27B4276F1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Assessment of illicit usage</header>
<subsection id="H0FA90D9E9A554CFAB1B356713A0DDBD9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an assessment describing the following:</text> <paragraph id="HCACB3F9515DD47AFBBE6204096D80CA8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The use of covered services by transnational criminal organizations or criminal enterprises acting on their behalf to engage in recruitment efforts, including the recruitment of individuals, including individuals under the age of 18, located in the United States to engage in or provide support with respect to illicit activities occurring in the United States, Mexico, or otherwise in proximity to an international boundary of the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A511305B7D349C4A19666873995104D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The use of covered services by transnational criminal organizations to engage in other illicit activities or other conduct in support of illicit activities, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HEC4C9AAC7C4242938341DF283B33F516"><enum>(A)</enum><text>smuggling or trafficking involving narcotics, other controlled substances, precursors thereof, or other items prohibited under the laws of the United States, Mexico, or another relevant jurisdiction, including firearms; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5828CA41524E4CD88AC51AABDD572D86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>human smuggling or trafficking.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H57D4D99477C748619A6FA43B1E8813B7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The existing efforts of the Secretary and relevant government and law enforcement entities to counter, monitor, or otherwise respond to the usage of covered services described in paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H97383F2247E344A4A6949ACF0623F9B9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The existing efforts of covered operators to counter, monitor, or otherwise respond to the usage of covered services described in paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H017F83EFAC974CE58BF0AF7977E5C890"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The existing cooperative efforts between the Secretary, other relevant government entities, and covered operators with respect to the matters described in paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HBF01CF0C94B94884BAA8E5526FC14346"><enum>4.</enum><header>Strategy to combat cartel recruitment on social media and online platforms</header>
<subsection id="HB1925BB9CA414643B4BAF248BB49C88B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a strategy, to be known as the National Strategy to Combat Illicit Recruitment Activity by Transnational Criminal Organizations on Social Media and Online Platforms, to combat the use of covered services by transnational criminal organizations or criminal enterprises acting on their behalf to recruit individuals located in the United States to engage in or provide support with respect to illicit activities occurring in the United States, Mexico, or otherwise in proximity to an international boundary of the United States. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H74C1D57B03D5466DA65270B3E1E98139"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header> <paragraph id="H59C183DE2A77496388FF808E3D85D739"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall, at a minimum, include the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H88C5623EB5764F88B2F625B35026960D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A proposal to improve cooperation and thereafter maintain cooperation between the Secretary, relevant law enforcement entities, and appropriate covered operators with respect to the matters described in subsection (a).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7BF7820D3A194F65AC5404F9C8B7FBD8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Recommendations to implement the requirement under section 5(a)(2) to establish a centralized mechanism for reporting information regarding the United States recruitment efforts of transnational criminal organizations involving covered services.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H16E271DD48D04037BDC05CC0CF30FE9A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A proposal to improve intragovernmental coordination with respect to the matters described in subsection (a), including between the Department and State, local, and Tribal governments.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA794319833DB4A7E9762AE0F4D974AA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A proposal to improve coordination within the Department and between the components of the Department with respect to the matters described in subsection (a).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE2C2C3125BDC44E0A99DD6AFBB314EDD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Activities to facilitate increased intelligence analysis for law enforcement purposes of efforts of transnational criminal organizations to utilize covered services for recruitment purposes.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEE23A410D322441BBAB3A9573798DCE1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Activities to foster international partnerships and enhance collaboration with foreign governments and, as applicable, multilateral institutions with respect to the matters described in subsection (a). </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0DD682F675D24C5F9390B8F91CB6309D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Activities to facilitate proactive law enforcement and other governmental efforts relating to the efforts of transnational criminal organizations to utilize covered services for recruitment purposes, including activities intended to preempt through outreach and engagement the commission of criminal offenses by individuals located in the United States who are targeted for recruitment by those transnational criminal organizations.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9B1B3C16B7194C6F9ACC8CD780629367"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Activities to specifically increase engagement and outreach with youth in border communities, including regarding the recruitment tactics of transnational criminal organizations and the consequences of participation in illicit activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0DEE633BB80B4025A67B27BB081BDCBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall not include legislative recommendations or elements predicated on the passage of legislation that is not enacted as of the date on which the strategy is submitted, including with respect to encryption policies or reforms to section 230 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDD83288307EC4CB58AA3887D2A6752F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In drafting and implementing the strategy required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall, at a minimum, consult and engage with the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H166C1653DD874094B79342B5EECB1032"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The heads of relevant components of the Department, including the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H8F34650A991D490187ADE6A6C9E98C96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H261D052A05E4413B9E8C92AE533022A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D506EBFBC814A38B4EFDABBE3E63E3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Under Secretary for Science and Technology.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2C1BA2DCBAB64E11980DDE0F4C754DD2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F231050B2E048E296B25EC4E76CC344"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Officer for Civil Rights and Civil Liberties.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H323B4C025209475183E1B2F491060D0D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Privacy Officer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61344900343E41F4B01DF765B91E61E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary of State.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC0E12063BE1149FBA53F6C74A9AA2F84"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4ECED461456444B6BEA7F7E1629C3808"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD457379D868B4A32A497E70A1171B948"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Representatives of border communities, including representatives of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H9589F731D7F44C7FB2BD28DAC2481244"><enum>(A)</enum><text>State, local, and Tribal governments, including school districts and local law enforcement.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCC7E4F5A01034FA79EE3B0A7B3591AA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Nongovernmental organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CD2F57FE01E4563928D3023ECED1D5A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Covered operators, including representatives of the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HADD367A3D88B43B6AAC5A8D5F7DC97CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Social media platforms, including operators of platforms or applications—</text> <clause id="H5842DAE14B904E1BBFE376182654AD26"><enum>(i)</enum><text>displaying short-form videos created by users or third parties;</text></clause>
<clause id="H78D08F34FE2141889ECE59F71C6B8F30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing ephemeral content transmission services; or</text></clause> <clause id="HB3A7D8A26DCE4577A347B159F5EA19CC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>using algorithms or other means of content prioritization to display a feed of content or advertisements created by users or third parties to other users.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H40FA8FF23FD54B7EBE1AF8620F90B460"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Interactive entertainment platforms and publishers.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H062576BDA8FD406CAA564C7EBC81B8F3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Companies developing immersive technology platforms and applications on those platforms.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC755AC43FEA34372B4C1A8A765718640"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Nongovernmental experts in the fields of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H76C2C36F76AE40EDAD4D153BA5AED05D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Civil rights and civil liberties.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD93B8BE34C4B46B9B4EDFE89DB91B425"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Online privacy.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF776D15B0F345AFA9A5B4154433D081"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Humanitarian assistance for migrants.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5C64B185F7E24A48B4D0062AB8DA9959"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Youth outreach and rehabilitation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7E53C04309744D2A955FF366F2C32808"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="HA186A7B25BBE4121A0731D62EC0EE453"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the strategy required under subsection (a) is submitted to the appropriate congressional committees, the Secretary shall commence implementation of the strategy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0B566208ABE5473287B67D41994A4E4D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header>
<subparagraph id="HF8213317576343DE90AAB968E8A00B69"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the strategy required under subsection (a) is implemented under paragraph (1) and semiannually thereafter for five years, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report describing the efforts of the Secretary to implement the strategy and the progress of those efforts, which shall include a description of the following:</text> <clause id="H686E2399FD964BE3BE06A49532F11717"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The recommendations, and corresponding implementation of those recommendations, with respect to the matters described in subsection (b)(1)(B) relating to the mechanism required under section 5(a)(2).</text></clause>
<clause id="H6096F605B7A14383BA73216389DC7A50"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The interagency posture with respect to the matters covered by the strategy required under subsection (a), which shall include a description of collaboration between the Secretary, other Federal entities, State, local, and Tribal entities, and foreign governments.</text></clause> <clause id="H83DABAC3064543C3A99F9F68B8EC4DD5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Actions taken pursuant to subsection (c) that occurred between the Secretary and the entities described in paragraphs (5) through (7) of that subsection, provided that such summaries are provided only in a classified or other non-public manner.</text></clause>
<clause id="HB4B0CEBAB1F84FE1842F320EE30352ED"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The threat landscape, including new developments related to the United States recruitment efforts of transnational criminal organizations and the use by those organizations of new or emergent covered services and recruitment methods. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H196DB0F808F947A097215B2F72C5734C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required under subparagraph (A) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H612253588B4D42E0B8BD9505F673299E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Intelligence collection and dissemination</header>
<subsection id="H233A93C7470B467DB31C0F81EDC90ACF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the strategy required under section 4(a) is required to be submitted to the appropriate congressional committees, the Secretary shall identify a designee—</text> <paragraph id="H42C35B17BAD54A81AAEA6DF793A6C7B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to receive, process, and disseminate information and communications involving the use of covered services by transnational criminal organizations or criminal enterprises acting on their behalf to recruit individuals located in the United States to engage in or provide support with respect to illicit activities occurring in the United States, Mexico, or otherwise in proximity to an international boundary of the United States; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBD19C9522529415DBB024A9F7D15F6E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to establish a mechanism, or if the designee determines appropriate, multiple mechanisms, for covered operators to voluntarily report relevant information or communications described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H366B372E36734324A53E62AD9D4E5D7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>Upon the identification of the designee and the establishment of the voluntary reporting mechanism required under subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall notify appropriate covered operators in writing regarding the voluntary reporting mechanism, including information regarding how to contact the designee and utilize the voluntary reporting mechanism.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4AE1D57DDAC542628E8095233A69CA5B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Placement</header><text>The designee identified under subsection (a) shall be located in U.S. Customs and Border Protection. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HC66B4ED374C94D3298417CA8E2EACCAA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The designee identified under subsection (a) shall utilize the information and communications received pursuant to this section to—</text>
<paragraph id="H929902F9DB33419F8DB3231B99E31DCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide Federal, State, local, and Tribal entities with intelligence to assist with outreach and engagement efforts intended to preempt the commission of criminal offenses by individuals located in the United States who are targeted by transnational criminal organizations for recruitment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H10A6DA91302A404A9D98E1DBF914C851"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide Federal, State, local, and Tribal law enforcement with actionable intelligence for law enforcement relating to the United States recruitment efforts of transnational criminal organizations; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2C5BC8BA25224740BA0BB19ED6AD8196"><enum>(3)</enum><text>further other appropriate government functions involving efforts to prevent the recruitment of individuals located in the United States by transnational criminal organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

