<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0B28B9008E3948D5A1032A4F92D7EAC6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3942 IH: Lifetime Income For Employees Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3942</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 to permit default investment arrangements in annuities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H908231E08BF846559890697F5831AC37" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD82D82FF4D7440A584C30D9DFAD7CD45" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Lifetime Income For Employees Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H052D6F06EE2847DBADEB0D3D8DD81165"><enum>2.</enum><header>Default investment in annuity contracts</header> <subsection id="H563828826B8049F0B30C99567B8D06EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 404(c)(5) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1104">29 U.S.C. 1104(c)(5)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H7D62662EDFE543C48FED79C1F2102199"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE45B5C2C1F5E4599AEACB7367B79C43C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or subparagraph (C), as appropriate,</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (B)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H90264BAC1D854FF19A43398A7A1C9139"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or in a covered annuity contract</quote> after <quote>by the Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7799EF46761242FDAEC75A4A00F219D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H11F7CFBBDD754B24A87AB900D070163E" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="HB2B8669B67034484B9F6122D0836D22C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Covered annuity contract</header>
<clause id="H565EAD95220647BE809850EC872CA92F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>covered annuity contract</quote> means an investment in an annuity contract that meets the following requirements:</text> <subclause id="HC4017DCE42A440F5AD88F6FD373F3171"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The annuity contract does not impose a liquidity restriction on the transfer of invested amounts during the 180-day period beginning on the date of the initial investment in such contract by the participant or beneficiary.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H0CE7723ACBEE496EA8F20C960878B8BD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The fiduciary ensures that each participant or beneficiary is provided notice in writing in accordance with clause (ii).</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE33FB776D00F4BFD891773C6BE56B162"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The fiduciary allocates not more than 50 percent of any periodic contribution or, immediately after a rebalancing of account investments, 50 percent of the value of the assets of the account, to the annuity contract (or, as applicable, to the portion thereof to which a liquidity restriction applies after the 180-day period in subclause (I)).</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HD703E7B6A7C240B88AABF9E92E65AE26"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notice requirement</header><text>For the purposes of this subparagraph, each participant or beneficiary shall be provided notice in writing in a manner that is reasonably designed to be understood by the average plan participant, as follows:</text> <subclause id="H31B29763749447AFA7810902A43A5A6E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Not later than 30 days in advance of the initial investment, a notice that includes—</text>
<item id="H11F7B50A24244DBEA859874B7210A3F2"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>an explanation of the circumstances under which assets in the account may be invested on behalf of the participant or beneficiary in the annuity contract, including an explanation of the targeted range and maximum amount or percentage of such assets to be invested;</text></item> <item id="H67180D99EB0A4AF3AF4A8A9F72742C2C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an explanation of the rights, and any limitations or restrictions thereon, of a participant or beneficiary to direct or transfer amounts invested, or to be invested, in an annuity contract to other investment alternatives available under the plan;</text></item>
<item id="HC3347E8A174F413F80A5699CB9CB6641"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a general description of the annuity contract, including the duration of guaranteed payments and identification of the insurer;</text></item> <item id="H1B6C1BCDA2B342E39F498DB4630240DD"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>an explanation of how a participant or beneficiary may obtain additional information in writing about their investment alternatives; and</text></item>
<item id="H6124120D06574043AB2F9EBDCD1EE1F3"><enum>(ee)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how to obtain a copy of the annuity contract.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H257ABF5965A84CD6B8991CBD03D9FA38"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Not later than 30 days before the date of the imposition of a liquidity restriction described in subclause (i)(I), that includes—</text>
<item id="HD255B5B0AE7C4A039C3BED6B53F05AB3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a statement explaining that the participant’s or beneficiaries’ contributions will shortly become subject to liquidity restrictions;</text></item> <item id="H59D793432B1C44D2B7BF8F024C2B9054"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an explanation of the rights of the participant or beneficiary to direct or transfer amounts to be invested in alternatives under the plan; and</text></item>
<item id="H24881AFF706341F3A9F36E9E38727564"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>an explanation of how a participant or beneficiary may obtain additional information about their investment alternatives.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HAA7D1802B62A439D8F20ECBE07519493"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Definition of annuity contract</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>annuity contract</quote> means a contract (or provision or feature thereof) that—</text>
<subclause id="HC2812D2C85134FCE952AB8951028FEDB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is issued by an insurer qualified to do business in a State; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC175FC2803E447B3B97969669542CB2B"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides for the payment of guaranteed benefits annually (or more frequently) for a fixed term or for the remainder of the life of the participant or beneficiary or the joint lives of the participant and the participant’s designated beneficiary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE16C21315C304EFEBC9023FECBF068C2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to investments made on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

