<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H047D4A0D8615407EAAE3A287D26947B3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6237 IH: To allow Federal State Department employees to file a confidential or open report on any fiscal waste that they come across and establishes an award program for exemplary employees who file non-confidential reports on wasteful spending.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6237</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To allow Federal State Department employees to file a confidential or open report on any fiscal waste that they come across and establishes an award program for exemplary employees who file non-confidential reports on wasteful spending.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBB9410572E39411B857646AF84826510" style="OLC"><section id="HD0AE1306F70A483A8EA09E40E964EB7A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of fiscal waste self-reporting program and fiscal responsibility award</header><subsection id="H46799E7C4A4A4DDF9A9A9D8254A2F52F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Fiscal waste self-Reporting program</header><paragraph id="H19E214BEB7F74203A0675BF0DE100CE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Department of State Under Secretary for Management shall work with the Director of the Budget and Planning Bureau and the Director of Global Talent in the Global Talent Management Bureau, among other persons, to establish a program for employees to self-report fiscal waste they observe in their course of employment. Within 60 days of receiving a report, the Under Secretary for Management shall—</text><subparagraph id="HA1D70206AB3345D5AED6AA1B377C7DF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>investigate the substance of the report and determine if it identifies fiscal waste; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64FC8A6D70B5475DACECB47DF347C40D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rectify all instances of fiscal waste identified by the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87348C5B80344968A680E13438D52AD3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>Employees shall have the opportunity to mark their submissions to the fiscal waste self-reporting program as confidential. Information in reports marked as confidential shall—</text><subparagraph id="H921083783B15490A919E3D42A3A9F440"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be accessible only to staff responsible for administering the fiscal waste self-reporting program and be shared only insofar as is necessary to investigate or rectify the report. Staff administering the program shall not share the name or other identifying information of the submitting employee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC55892DD5324204BBF32E0655A212A2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not be used in the promotion, demotion, or termination of or other employment decisions relating to the submitting employee.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC11F1527F7A441F7851E941D1AF708EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The Under Secretary for Management shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an annual report detailing—</text><subparagraph id="HB9F4AD165BA64DD9947C3230BC1990EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all submissions to the fiscal waste self-reporting program that year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD74BB3A6A2994E62B138713D30365A53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the findings of all investigations into those submissions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8A42B3B3B2646159F5A8FA172D2E327"><enum>(C)</enum><text>all rectifying actions taken in response to those submissions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88353CD323284347A513538671E699EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fiscal responsibility award</header><paragraph id="H29847C14D73D4877B4909DE93CBCF49E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary for Management shall work with the Director of the Budget and Planning Bureau and the Director of Global Talent in the Global Talent Management Bureau, among other persons, to establish a departmental award for any exemplary employee who—</text><subparagraph id="HD6E4708D87D74E5A92308A27A55F91E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recommends or adopts significant cost saving measures in program implementation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4552BEDCD754897A6232894F07D746C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifies instances of fiscal waste within a program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCC6C0828B314849B9EB4BDFA4F761EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>cancels, or recommends cancellation of, programs resulting in fiscal waste; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4C18C584E1945E887182B9B0B1F7673"><enum>(D)</enum><text>proposes a plan for reallocation of resources in lieu of requesting greater appropriations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C299E6E9DA84B8F9A7479C622C8BC1D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Self-reports</header><text>An employee’s non-confidential submissions to the fiscal waste self-reporting program, particularly those resulting in rectification, shall be considered in determining that employee’s eligibility for this award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89F11CB22BA54C7B925A06FE44B65413"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text>Eligibility for this award shall be determined on at least a quarterly basis.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H532AEF82180F488E8AE43220FA4448AE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act: </text><paragraph id="HC54151F85EEE4AF5A9FAF48CC81F76F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the House Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9630B2E7971A452E87975A039E4D1F5A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fiscal waste</header><text>The term <quote>fiscal waste</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H951160B5E61546479957996452124E7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any inefficiency in the spending patterns or objectives of a program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFC115A760D64DDFB82EAA28DD26817F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any program which consistently does not adequately achieve its stated objectives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF91A52526A0D4673B390EFD503792024"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any program which no longer holds relevance or has become obsolete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

