<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2738B818C14E4DE082B47FA55DD82EE1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4173 IH: Advancing Automation Research and Development in Agriculture Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4173</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 to direct the Secretary of Agriculture to establish a specialty crop mechanization and automation initiative, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HA12C393F12694445B92B63C167305F99" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3E572B6DBAAB4DF38946765AEB20599B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing Automation Research and Development in Agriculture Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H81FB28E272404826A23391094BAE0568"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mechanization and automation for specialty crops</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7601">7 U.S.C. 7601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE7AAAEBED6FF44EFA849578EA95AFCF4" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HEC858E4AAA3246D6BB1D884198B9CEA4"><enum>412A.</enum><header>Mechanization and automation for specialty crops</header> 
<subsection id="H6027776B449846559637F946365C4780"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish within the Department a stand-alone competitive research and extension grant program to increase the competitiveness of specialty crops in the United States through the advancement and acceleration of the mechanization and automation, including—</text> <paragraph id="H0B94E78197984D03B873E095E25E62C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Projects that create or improve cost-effective technologies to reduce a specialty crop grower’s manual labor requirements and increase the efficiency of crop production, resource management, harvesting, processing, post-harvest technologies, and packaging through mechanization, automation, and other innovations and technologies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB00148CD2EC4596A2DBA5A191412D71"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Projects that increase adoption of mechanization and automation technologies by:</text> <subparagraph id="H2AF37A849525462FBD73695BDAF61DA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Emphasizing adoption drivers that could include but are not limited to connectivity, autonomy, reliability, durability, in-field validation, and cost-effectiveness.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17EC8278E2264426A97F91067EB3C0BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Investing and developing human capital to increase the specialty crop sector’s capacity to work with new technologies, and to manage a more tech-focused farm workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1CAC5752B5049E4BF0AE1AB344DC48A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Projects that accelerate automation and mechanization through prototype development, in-field trial testing, ongoing industry engagement, and rapid commercialization.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD9F21944A694F67998B896BA6DA77F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>The Secretary may carry out the section through eligible entities described in subsection (c). </text></subsection> <subsection id="HFA4A9F60E9BB4086902438A90D1D1670"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible entities described in this subsection are—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5793217F117D47428F16B19CDDFBB0C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Federal agencies;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFAB8666EA1C427DA837CC0B9656584F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>national laboratories;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19B31FE3B99D4AFDAD15E3A9545E4513"><enum>(3)</enum><text>colleges or universities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H96AE7965360C401D8C66C89FEC1416B9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>research institutions or organizations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H447F0A26FA2443348ACCEDDD6C0C2B14"><enum>(5)</enum><text>private organizations or corporations;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA8A6F679E654FF6AAB4F556575046C0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>State agricultural experiment stations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0F2379C38BA3417B800B1FD6A6C74E00"><enum>(7)</enum><text>individuals;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE215B0B2D594F0AA2D8E41A70B87FCA"><enum>(8)</enum><text>organizations representing specialty crop growers; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB1E3223D936D4CFB815F0E34E1EA0A1F"><enum>(9)</enum><text> groups consisting of 2 or more entities described in paragraphs (1) through (8).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFE1129D2ACFB4517BB9A2DB99CF24563"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Review of Proposals</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary shall award competitive grants on the basis of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H68671269933247AC96849622FDDAD389"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a scientific peer review conducted by a panel of subject matter experts from Federal agencies, non-Federal entities, and the specialty crop industry; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD908700A9F6E4381A0426550ABF2CB60"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review and ranking for merit, relevance, and impact conducted by a panel of specialty crop industry representatives for the specific specialty crop.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H85CCD6B705644451A530B3D68EFBAB76"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fiscal year, before conducting the scientific peer review described in paragraph (1) of subsection (d) and the merit and relevancy review described in paragraph (2) of such subsection, the Secretary shall consult with the specialty crops committee regarding such reviews. The committee shall provide the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="H3EA0DE56570C491780CE62EBE380EA64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the first fiscal year in which that consultation occurs, any recommendations for conducting such reviews in such fiscal year; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7FA7B2D73B94C40AF3B223A973C7C0F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in any subsequent fiscal year in which such consultation occurs—</text> <subparagraph id="H2EF3F4BB9036422EBADC64E89F67D225"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the procedures and objectives used by the Secretary for such reviews in the previous fiscal year;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC80C0F00989C432599DDBDB6DE5FB1B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations for such reviews for the current fiscal year; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8FFD4AF88244E61851B1CA98E3F9D99"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any comments on grants awarded under subsection (d) during the previous fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDEC0397227FE4A1C84475CF336F24A46"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report on—</text> <paragraph id="HE620134234CE4E6B948BCBBB5B8C951B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the consultations with the specialty crops committee conducted under subsection (e);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H073A007657AA4281AE1C492811DC9A40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the specialty crops committee’s recommendations, if any, provided to the Secretary during such consultations; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E537BA0D97544EB88AD2270A64767E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the specialty crops committee’s review of the grants awarded under subsection (d) in the previous fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE1C709901A0741699BB2F54BF6A3ECAD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Administration</header> 
<paragraph id="H7C122316CF7F48EBB6B65F695C84BA01"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to grants awarded under this section, the Secretary shall seek and accept proposals for grants.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02D211C9790748F895C6C3CB0A35F3C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The term of a grant under this section may not exceed 10 years.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B068E692A5640D9AE5E29E9A38B6D76"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header> 
<subparagraph id="H4DBA11CB9C9F434EBB2D577479C10B6D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity receiving a grant under this section shall provide non-Federal matching funds (including funds from an agricultural commodity promotion, research, and information program) equal to not less than 15 percent of the amount of the grant.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D4C37B4A97146778BD2EA53FA2962D2"><enum>(B)</enum><header> In-kind support</header><text>Non-Federal matching funds described in subparagraph (A) may include in-kind support.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H423C2F76F21243ED92D14BE8536ADC93"><enum>(C)</enum><header> Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the matching requirement under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61195ACFB5DA4770B3CFE131EABDE40E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other conditions</header><text>The Secretary may set such other conditions on the award of a grant under the program under subsection (a) as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1E5176E1054E46DA8A2AAE7D6C4EF4C6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text>In making grants under the program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall provide a higher priority to projects that—</text> <paragraph id="H6CF20C2BCDB14977BF61131D2D2800A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include proposals that address the training or retraining of farm workers to operate, repair, program or otherwise maintain resulting automation solutions; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H51C6926476C145F0AC0DB62C4773B146"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include explicit mechanisms to communicate results to producers and the public.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEE8322FC60234B21B7D89DA436E2B37E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Buildings and Facilities</header><text>Funds made available under this section shall not be used for the construction of a new building or facility or the acquisition, expansion, remodeling, or alteration of an existing building or facility (including site grading and improvement, and architect fees).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3EE2B71FAB1D4F978F00ED44013B6EDF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H848B6D7E052442349ADB0396B399A29F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Specialty crop</header><text>The term <quote>specialty crop</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the Specialty Crops Competitiveness Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1621">7 U.S.C. 1621</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/465">Public Law 108–465</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1480E981C8B14A13ADAA9C53C8698020"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specialty crops committee</header><text>The term <quote>specialty crops committee</quote> means the committee established under section 1408A of the National Agricultural Research, Extension, and Teaching Policy Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3123a">7 U.S.C. 3123a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85377B4642C345F1BC473AECA2C823D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <quote>program</quote> means the Specialty Crop Mechanization and Automation Research and Development Program established in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H702737157690417C93B0CEDF079A1DAE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Mandatory Funding</header><text>Of the funds of the Commodity Credit Corporation, the Secretary shall use to carry out this section $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter, and shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

