<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBE5B3AFA110B40AFA3FC125C55BD97B6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5750 IH: Green Nuclear Fertilizer Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5750</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230927">September 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture to collaborate to determine the feasibility of creating the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H00F26A4AFF214D71B28D86BAAB8F6576" style="OLC"><section id="H2198806EFBE14ED08AA8E74141549A2D" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Green Nuclear Fertilizer Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCC3055F2315B4F91A24B2B65580C73BA" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD2F3CD44242A4E33BBBCB015F11A4A5D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Green fertilizers, such as those produced by energy generated by an advanced nuclear reactor, are nitrate-based mineral fertilizers with the same chemical and physical composition as fertilizers produced with fossil fuels, but have a lower carbon footprint.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42F27E98AD9546FC9D27C3907C8558F6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Pink hydrogen is hydrogen that is produced through electrolysis generated by nuclear energy, including energy generated by advanced nuclear reactors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2DF853DD652418E8024B417FBE1EDD9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In 2023, approximately 95 percent of the hydrogen produced in the United States came from natural gas through a process called steam methane reforming.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FE5A85839AF44E88CF9EA0B753C0927" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Hydrogen is an essential feedstock for ammonia production, which is very energy intensive process, but this process could be augmented with advanced nuclear technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H400D065023FA41C2B009A91B63948833" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Ammonia is a commodity chemical used for fertilizers, and is produced through a high-pressure, high-heat catalytic reaction of nitrogen and hydrogen.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AC685025C7140C8808EDAE1CB1DD270" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The ammonia market is expected to be one of the early deployment opportunities for advanced nuclear reactors through the sale of pink hydrogen.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5EDFE14955F477EB54EF6DA1FEA1F77" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the International Renewable Energy Agency, ammonia is the second-most produced chemical in the world by mass.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46FEBC1EDDB4416EB6021251F7B71FEA" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The International Energy Agency estimates ammonia production capacity will need to increase nearly 40 percent by 2050 to account for expected global population and economic growth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC947F7EE1E74CA5A3E44C90B0C6926C" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>According to the U.S. Geological Survey, 88 percent of ammonia consumption in the United States is for fertilizer production.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95CB73FED3964EA2A809BE1A28281E32" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In 2021, the United States had 35 active ammonia production plants across 16 States, with 60 percent of production capacity located in Louisiana, Oklahoma, and Texas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51A47516BC884C3195FFEEBB8854859E" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>China produces almost a third of the world’s ammonia supply, using coal as the primary hydrogen feedstock.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF01AA98C84EB4020B8627AE825C28539" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that Congress—</text><paragraph id="H8143E6EFE5454A6CA8D189605E569EC2" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>understands the potential for the United States to be a global leader in producing pink hydrogen, zero-emissions ammonia, and green nuclear fertilizer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D8F1AFDF337444AB9F32CF54C7C8A13" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>believes the pink hydrogen market for ammonia in fertilizer products could be a considerable early market opportunity to assist with providing assurance to nuclear supply chain manufacturers while decreasing market risks associated with deploying advanced nuclear reactors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AD65BF79F1541C2ACF4C0DDFB391499" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>encourages the United States to take advantage of this global leadership opportunity, both by assisting with advanced nuclear reactor deployment and providing farmers throughout the United States and rest of the world with green nuclear fertilizer; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H961C38EF8BF24228B7C3B4BAE158D866" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recognizes the positive environmental impacts that green nuclear fertilizer can have.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H2A8ED155CDBC433F9E70B7FDD3748473" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Examination of feasibility of Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture shall collaborate to jointly examine—</text><paragraph id="HA81AEF3A0B4C450A95225C1BE55F5F69" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the feasibility of establishing and carrying out a program, to be led by the Secretary of Agriculture and to be known as the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program, under which the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture would—</text><subparagraph id="H19B1310B93644073A30520F6D4362E4B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>act as a liaisons between the energy generating industry, the hydrogen production industry, the ammonia production industry, the fertilizer industry, and the agriculture industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7713900E3700468DA18F2BFFBA9355A5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the extent authorized, ease regulatory restrictions associated with green nuclear fertilizer, including regulatory restrictions associated with licensing and deploying advanced nuclear reactors; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03B8B708424A410BA28C499A4166F5D1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>act as a single source of contact for stakeholders interested in producing, purchasing, or selling green nuclear fertilizer such that stakeholders could contact and receive necessary information on green nuclear fertilizer, including safety information, information about the environmental benefits of green nuclear fertilizer, and other information;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H14A71234B000403B9CE32667B71D4F64" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if establishing and carrying the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program is determined to be feasible under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H508C622B3E494496BD41CA657B8EF4D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>what the goals of the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program should be; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5835998DE95349A5A20AD700DC045A59" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who will have access to the Green Fertilizer Program in both the nuclear industry and the agriculture industry, including advanced nuclear reactor developers, electric utilities, farmers, and fertilizer producers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD325E86577344DA8B5E5F5F09BCBC90C" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program could provide resources or other assistance in establishing industry agreements for green nuclear fertilizer, including power purchase agreements, offtake agreements, or other contractual arrangements for green nuclear fertilizer;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5791950CC9A64A80B47AFC73A2E43427" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the economic impacts, both domestically and internationally, of producing and using green nuclear fertilizers compared to fertilizers that are not produced with zero-emissions ammonia;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B6C182415884F1DB3D169609F06808E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the health impacts associated with using green nuclear fertilizer, and a comparison of such health impacts to the health impacts of using fertilizers that are not produced with zero-emissions ammonia; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F0F4BA128314871B65B5C5192B7BD48" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>whether there is any impact on crops and overall yield associated with using green nuclear fertilizer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H473EB44D66844AE4B09E793407C70D7B" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>regulatory changes needed to ease the way and prepare for the creation, sale, and procurement of green nuclear fertilizer; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13F35A7DA4EF4E1EB551D4B769C4F2C1" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issues relating to infrastructure for the production of green nuclear fertilizer, including—</text><subparagraph id="H113FE4942FC14ABCA850B3013AD8B735" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether use of advanced nuclear reactors to produce pink hydrogen would impact existing fertilizer production infrastructure;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD599F661E585417C974D2CBBEA263897" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how advanced nuclear reactors could be used with existing infrastructure, including currently operational, retiring, and retired infrastructure, to produce pink hydrogen;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9AECC04387E467AAAD9CB56260FB06C" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">challenges associated with retrofitting existing infrastructure to deploy advanced nuclear reactors to be used for variable purposes, such as providing electricity to the electric grid and hydrogen production, based on necessity; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33F0663A6D404B1D83E2FC490922F767" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">challenges associated with constructing new pink hydrogen production facilities that are powered by an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HD971096C2C484F8C9C7E3782F6E5761F" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 365 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the examination conducted under section 4, including—</text><paragraph id="HF8932CF10A9741C0B10C34F11ECCD2B0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a determination on whether the establishment of the Green Nuclear Fertilizer Program is feasible and—</text><subparagraph id="HB0B5E661BB984239ACB2B7E22A4752BD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if it is determined to be feasible, a plan to develop the Program, and a description of steps for Congress to take to make the Program successful; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB325DAE0A244FF6881CFF133F51CF1E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if it is determined not to be feasible, a description of why it is not feasible, and possible solutions to make the Program feasible; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA5A5FBFF5FB4F688DB9C686A918FC39" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of how such a Program would—</text><subparagraph id="H124F19B3465C4F93A71AEF6EC6DC341A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increase market demand for the deployment of advanced nuclear reactors in the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05E7500ED7084A75A20ABF22034885B7" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>benefit the agriculture industry.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H37801315CD5E45A99BEA54084AC9318B" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4F93BC85124C44F6A501404B89273ABD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advance nuclear reactor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>advanced nuclear reactor</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3(1) of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2215">42 U.S.C. 2215</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EE7E32865564C0F90F562769A9EC5CA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HD69F1D533C06492EA40DE3178BBC4433" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28BFC3564AEC496E9E2793FF953DA9BD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Environment and Public Works, the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A115913999640F480C5F42E8F8BB76F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Green nuclear fertilizer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>green nuclear fertilizer</term> means fertilizer that is produced with zero-emissions ammonia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H732E604D3811456D82E9D9E435AEB66C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Pink hydrogen</header><subparagraph id="H2764F1D311C34360BCC9B31EBDE5B6AA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>pink hydrogen</term> means hydrogen that is produced through electrolysis generated by nuclear energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D8DD42D41134F44A6D50686A27160EB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <quote>pink hydrogen</quote> does not include thermal hydrogen. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC0864BFC36544FDA08C270BEF4BDEA8" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Zero-emissions ammonia</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>zero-emissions ammonia</term> means ammonia that is produced with pink hydrogen and nitrogen.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

