<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59A56204316741B4960E6332D2BF02E3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5511 IH: Opening Doors for Youth Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5511</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide subsidized summer and year-round employment for youth who face systemic barriers to employment and viable career options and to assist local community partnerships in improving high school graduation and youth employment rates, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0DDB62DA035A4A7197DE6AAF8FB206A8" style="OLC">
<section id="H521B21ADCC9942F592F599225732989A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Opening Doors for Youth Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" id="HAF56EC6F975E49149FC131D35861130A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Labor to carry out this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="HE9F2F5106E6548D39A1482FA2BA410DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$1,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0FF7FE6A4C54254B1B67ACAD486E505"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$1,050,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H004FEA3D66DC4EFE80E4F3AED8282BB7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$1,100,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H62B38D96C3BA4275B83F42536694E434"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$1,150,000,000 for fiscal year 2027;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAC28C683C581460AA4520644BDD1127B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$1,200,000,000 for fiscal year 2028; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD28389A97C274F76A3105094FBDAF320"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$1,250,000,000 for fiscal year 2029.</text></paragraph></section>
<section commented="no" id="H42A4810DB3E944B49603C565666B060C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Availability of funds</header>
<subsection id="H9A80EE0F35444ECF86FA783F51BCDC78"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reservation of funds for administrative and other purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amount available under section 2, the Secretary of Labor shall reserve—</text> <paragraph id="HB84F20CC93334116B55F8F4AD23095CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not more than 5 percent to carry out innovation and learning activities under section 9;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HACD0C4D2058C4D3AB284A2511CEB06A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not more than 5 percent for the costs of Federal administration of this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H16BF17E9AFED4682814BE3027177D0C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not more than 2 percent to carry out evaluations under section 10.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA32BC14293FB42B486CF3CA615C72B2B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution of funds</header><text>Of the amount made available under section 2 and not reserved under subsection (a), the Secretary of Labor shall use—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H34DC6C68DA4740748483F46C999DEE19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>30 percent of such amount to carry out section 4;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H95D33F37B1584E1DB904B841738C1E41"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">35 percent of such amount to carry out section 5; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H78F4C36AB65F43E1A35FFB64A330EB05"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">35 percent of such amount to carry out section 6.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H5BFBD5A786E54329AEA9479C8C5A5675"><enum>4.</enum><header>Summer employment opportunities for youth</header>
<subsection id="H77CBCF9D0E4743BF9B18A916B065CD36"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amount available under section 3(b)(1), the Secretary of Labor shall, for the purpose of carrying out summer employment programs under this section—</text> <paragraph id="HB9E406EE0D434311BF383E7B67479D3D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">after making the reservations described in paragraphs (2) and (3), make an allotment of the remainder of such amount in accordance with section 127(b)(1)(C)(ii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3162">29 U.S.C. 3162(b)(1)(C)(ii)</external-xref>) to each State that meets the requirements of section 102 or 103 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3112">29 U.S.C. 3112</external-xref>; 3113);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7CC7A60FD1A0400999F250EF9135FEBA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reserve not more than one-quarter of 1 percent of such amount to provide assistance to the outlying areas; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD34DF337035247DE84F0B7DBA96F5B99"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reserve not more than 1<fraction>½</fraction> percent of such amount to make grants to, or enter into contracts or cooperative agreements with, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, Alaska Native entities, Indian-controlled organizations serving Indians, or Native Hawaiian organizations, to carry out the activities described in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H179C17B1CB9E4D0C90536A95EFE5293F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Within State allocations</header>
<paragraph id="HD7FBC4078A9C47C1819045989BC2422F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor of a State, in accordance with the State plan developed under section 102 or 103 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3112">29 U.S.C. 3112</external-xref>; 3113), shall allocate the amount that is allotted to the State under subsection (a)(1) to local areas meeting the requirements under subsection (c) in accordance with the allocation described in section 128(b)(2)(A)(i) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3163">29 U.S.C. 3163(b)(2)(A)(i)</external-xref>) for the purpose of developing and expanding summer employment programs under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA05EC0279E924A55818A34C7FDE12755"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reallocation among local areas</header> <subparagraph id="HA4B652A07CD9458B8C70DE1BC162829E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor may, after consultation with the State board, reallocate to eligible local areas within the State amounts that are made available to local areas from allocations made under this section (referred to in this paragraph as a <term>local allocation</term>) and that are available for reallocation in accordance with this paragraph.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEC2898DAAFCC44DEAB78617A18BF693E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount available for reallocation for a program year is equal to the amount by which the unobligated balance of the local allocation, at the end of the program year prior to the program year for which the determination under this paragraph is made, exceeds 20 percent of such allocation for the prior program year.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCAC8821414F94D5082D066376243FD30"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>In making reallocations to eligible local areas of amounts available pursuant to subparagraph (B) for a program year, the Governor shall allocate to each eligible local area within the State an amount based on the relative amount of the local allocation for the program year for which the determination is made, as compared to the total amount of the local allocations for all eligible local areas in the State for such program year.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H76615D731BFA47A48D88865DE401F5D2"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Eligible local area</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>eligible local area</term> means a local area that meets the requirements under subsection (c) and does not have an amount available for reallocation under subparagraph (B) for the program year for which the determination under such subparagraph is made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74ECF984FFCB4F3F9A76EFDE01AE6E86"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Local reservation</header><text>Of the amount allocated to a local area under paragraph (1)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H50BF8A3840DE4ADBA29216B48C10188D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 10 percent of such amount may be used for the administrative costs of carrying out a summer employment program under this section, including costs for participating in regional and national opportunities for in-person or virtual peer learning under section 9; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE33209D0FE224D4B9CBF0E15559D1316"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 5 percent of such amount shall be used to provide direct financial assistance to eligible youth through grants to support their financial needs to enter, remain enrolled in, and complete the program, such as support for supplies, transportation, child care, and housing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD2F3F278BE6C4EC69EE92671347689CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Local plans</header>
<paragraph id="HCF988F208CE44AF984354441C839CBC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order for a local area to be eligible for funds under this section, the local board of the local area shall develop and submit to the Governor in accordance with paragraph (2) a 4-year plan for the summer employment program. Such plan shall, at a minimum—</text> <subparagraph id="HDE4FFAC5C7FC41CE9DE3350DDA0031F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not conflict with the local plan submitted by the local board under section 108 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3123">29 U.S.C. 3123</external-xref>), as determined by the Governor; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H86B5CFB1575B495EB85A5BC0B0995A8C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contain the contents required under paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36EDB99A279B4FEBA7624CB0518A99F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission</header> <subparagraph id="H044A3B2553D040BAB53BE884023A4FC5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A plan required under this subsection shall be submitted by the local area to the Governor of such area at such time and in such manner as the Governor may reasonably require.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HA217E2F8A35B404EAC867CB3D7027BE5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Combined plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a local area is seeking funds under this section and section 5, the plan required under this subsection may be submitted in combination with a plan under section 5, in lieu of the local area submitting 2 separate plans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D717D4BD39C43529D636079B101544A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>At a minimum, each plan required under this subsection shall include—</text>
<subparagraph id="H84F85A152D7646D4805ED008D8C80C7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the local area will carry out the activities described in subsection (d) for each program year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H113419C6986540DA80B4389D399E7BB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the local area will recruit eligible youth into the summer employment program, including how the local area will prioritize recruitment of individuals with barriers to employment;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2D63FA404479401FAD5A25BB17E06B9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth expected to participate in the program each program year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49939D6394854A27B9B53C4D4292D14B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the services, including supportive services, that the program is expected to provide to eligible youth, including how the local area will partner with community-based organizations to provide such services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H604EF9476A8A4DFE9870DB7940BB1A71"><enum>(E)</enum><text>performance accountability goals, as measured by the primary indicators of performance described in subsection (e)(1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAE338896D84941E2889853ED8575566B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assurance that the program will be aligned with the youth workforce investment activities provided by the local area under chapter 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3161">29 U.S.C. 3161 et seq.</external-xref>), and to the extent practicable, the career exploration, information, and guidance activities provided by such local area in accordance with section 134(b)(3) of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2354">20 U.S.C. 2354(b)(3)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBC64A5126527409E803CB97DEDF4ECC9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an assurance that the local area will adhere to the labor standards described in section 7;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9607B885F8174E6E8AB4015A001E833A"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of program alignment to work-based learning opportunities, or plans to create work-based learning opportunities, and a description of whether the program awards academic credit towards a secondary school diploma or its recognized equivalent, or a recognized postsecondary credential, as applicable;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3B165E164E2E4FBE9531449037FB0032"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of programs being offered that align to high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1D7429E155FA4DE29DEEC2D827C18786"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other information as the Governor may reasonably require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H17CDEDE1424D41AD83B2D5F59CB0EBA5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Local use of funds</header>
<paragraph id="H6C0D0380117F4C3E9758F6199AF1F4CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local area that receives an allocation under this section shall use such allocation for development activities or expansion activities with respect to a summer employment program in accordance with this subsection. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB46C254B3A114078B2F83BD7A5AA152E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a local area that, at the beginning of the first program year covered by the local plan submitted under subsection (c), is not carrying out a summer employment program described in paragraph (4), the local board of such local area—</text>
<subparagraph id="H87DB351B097B4AC69351896B8B098CB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall use the amount allocated under this section to such local area to—</text> <clause id="H4352D41318D24A9A929D7089391A09AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>plan, develop, and carry out a summer employment program described in paragraph (4);</text></clause>
<clause id="HEEB9CF0C7C654143AC25D531BB00BB4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage or establish industry or sector partnerships to determine local summer job needs to inform the establishment of such program; and</text></clause> <clause id="H214614F797A545AE9CE828000759CC7A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct outreach to eligible youth and employers; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H00C421EFF23C4F6985C4BB4B5B6BA803"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may—</text> <clause id="HCB3CCFE7B24A41CA978A8AE9945E5661"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use such amount to develop technology infrastructure, including data and management systems, to support such program; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB39CC5E527454D26AAF4B98988CAE38B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>use not more than 25 percent of such amount to subsidize not more than 75 percent of the wages of each eligible youth participating in the program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCC639507F77D47FB816535EE0DD04FC3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expansion activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a local area that, at the beginning of the first program year covered by the local plan submitted under subsection (c), is carrying out a summer employment program described in paragraph (4), the local board of such local area—</text>
<subparagraph id="H74E247A5B051445BBA0DFA4652878518"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall use the amount allocated under this section to such local area to—</text> <clause id="H9B795847AC7B41D5AFE4B96E1FD6AF70"><enum>(i)</enum><text>increase the number of summer employment opportunities offered through such program, including unsubsidized or partly subsidized opportunities and opportunities in the private sector;</text></clause>
<clause id="H17414AED1EDD46979C99FD6C343E6679"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conduct outreach to eligible youth and employers; and</text></clause> <clause id="H0FEBD0DA27444EAEAE5B9B409DA35BBD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>subsidize not more than 50 percent of the wages of each eligible youth participating in the program; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3DE4B93A0FCB4A6A8EC7B4A9532FED72"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may use such amount to enhance the activities required under paragraph (4)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98BEA41535B34CEFBEBC92D9BB3442C1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text>A summer employment program described in this paragraph is a program that meets the following requirements:</text>
<subparagraph id="H9139E23E760744F99376D001B142B46E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Program design</header><text>Each eligible youth participating in the program is matched with an appropriate employer, based on factors including the needs of the employer and the age, skill, and aspirations of the eligible youth, for a high-quality summer employment opportunity, which may not—</text> <clause id="H93AA28BFDCF34BD9B0D161AA172D9942" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be less than 4 weeks; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HAA74C6F22A174859A091DD0C988EAE7D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>pay less than the greater of the applicable Federal, State, or local minimum wage.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB60BA4E76BED4062A60A12868E0AA8D3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Program elements</header><text>The program includes the following program elements:</text>
<clause id="H4C2CFF674DFE4D08BAD1A71F0C8B2196" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Work-readiness training and educational programs for eligible youth to enhance their summer employment opportunities, including digital literacy and online work-readiness opportunities, as appropriate, and support obtaining documentation needed for employment, such as identification or licenses.</text></clause> <clause id="H62151E8ED2FC44F3B599109547B04B0E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coaching and mentoring services for eligible youth participating in the program to enhance their summer employment opportunities and encourage completion of such opportunities through the program, which may occur prior to, during, or after the summer employment program.</text></clause>
<clause id="HDEA1F7CEEA5A4E70B3BB218796E05053" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coaching and mentoring services for employers on how to successfully employ eligible youth participating in the program in meaningful work, including on providing a safe work and training environment for all participants, regardless of race, color, disability, age, religion, national origin, political affiliation, belief, marital status, sex (including sexual orientation or gender identity), pregnancy, childbirth, or a related medical condition, or status as a parent.</text></clause> <clause id="H4B7B72952F8D455FAAC83C87522F455F" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Career exploration, career counseling, career planning and postsecondary education planning services for eligible youth participating in the program.</text></clause>
<clause id="HA75B48060EC04134BF723E3CF7E275FE" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">High-quality financial literacy education for eligible youth participating in the program as described in section 129(b)(2)(D) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(b)(2)(D)</external-xref>), and including education on the use of credit and financing higher education, savings, and access to safe and affordable banking accounts with consumer protections.</text></clause> <clause id="H541B47B446A14E58A9FFC1DAF7DB0722" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Providing supportive services to eligible youth, or connecting such youth to supportive services provided by another entity, to enable their participation in the program.</text></clause>
<clause id="H99554F3AD26D456AA9077F4FAF8AC92F" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Follow-up services for not less than 12 months after the completion of participation, as appropriate.</text></clause> <clause id="H00882AB67A304CAB84ACD59124A38210" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Integrating services provided by the program with year-round employment programs, youth development programs, secondary school programs, career pathways, career and technical education programs, youth workforce investment activities provided under chapter 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3161">29 U.S.C. 3161 et seq.</external-xref>), work-based learning, and skills training programs funded by the State or Federal Government, as applicable.</text></clause>
<clause id="HACDB5F46DC874DE380236226872645B7" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Connecting eligible youth participating in the program to providers of youth services, adult employment and training services, vocational rehabilitation services, adult education and literacy services under title II of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>), career pathways, or skills training programs funded by the State or Federal Government, as applicable for each eligible youth.</text></clause> <clause id="H1FF573D6E79F4FF492CFDACF08C6277E" commented="no"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Express, written commitment from mayors and county executives to support the execution of the program as described in the plan submitted under subsection (c).</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9DEF884C831C4F13AC70BC0BAC94315F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information and referrals</header>
<clause id="H119716EC5ED24F418E216C4661FEC3B5" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each local board shall ensure that each participant of a summer employment program receiving assistance under this section shall be provided—</text> <subclause id="H3A6B2EB2899348599E7C8D38E2B420F2" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the full array of applicable or appropriate services that are available through the local board or other eligible providers or one-stop partners, including those providers or partners receiving funds under this Act; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCFDE51B9872947AA894396F33F23A7CB" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">referral to appropriate training and educational programs that have the capacity to serve the participant either on a concurrent or sequential basis.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H0D2A6D54614B4080ADA51AFD4DA3EB04" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Further assessment and referral</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each local board shall, in a manner consistent with section 129(c)(3)(B) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(c)(3)(B)</external-xref>), ensure that eligible youth who do not meet employment requirements for the summer employment program shall be referred for further assessment, as necessary, and referred to appropriate programs in accordance with clause (i) to meet the basic skills and training needs for such employment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD27D85535161479C8A19CF33F5314452" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In carrying out a summer employment program receiving assistance under this section, a local board shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HFD26261FA5944849BDE4802A36CE1594" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>give priority to summer employment opportunities offered under such program—</text>
<clause id="HB2B790B774D540D9BF9935A356811C19" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in existing or emerging high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations; or</text></clause> <clause id="H46820F93D61348B985155EC4A1CE519D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that meet community needs in the public, private, or nonprofit sector; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6C43BDC28DEA481493F9112079AC553C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for any program year, use not less than 75 percent of the amount allocated under this section to provide summer employment opportunities under such program for eligible youth that are in-school youth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H105465F7C5D0460FBB42CB0576A21AC6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Performance accountability</header> <paragraph id="H25E3AEA0451F46AFA473BDE639C4D001"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Primary indicators of performance</header><text>For each local board carrying out a summer employment program funded under this section, the primary indicators of performance, with respect to each such program, shall include—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC02B2C3563E3474EA08A0BD14ECF0C00"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the performance metrics described in clause (i)(V), and subparagraphs (I) and (II) of clause (ii), of section 116(b)(2)(A) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1FD1B50957934188A083CB1B7EA2357E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of eligible youth completing the program; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H51C6FFE18A3A45DDA1C7298169FB6E5D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of youth having participated in work-based learning.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2C29F24FC6E4BF2BC897CF45C21145B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to meet local performance accountability measures</header> <subparagraph id="HC3775D7EC95E48E4953BEA805B391E2A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a local area fails, for any program year, to meet a performance accountability goal identified in its local plan under subsection (c)(3)(E), with respect to a summer employment program receiving assistance under this section, the Governor, or, upon request by the Governor, the Secretary of Labor, shall provide the local board with technical assistance, which may include assistance in the development of a performance improvement plan for such summer employment program.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFCB947F3B5AB4886AE8309D3479CD464"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Corrective action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a case in which such local area fails to meet such performance accountability goal with respect to the program for a third consecutive year or fails to implement the improvement plan, the Governor shall take corrective actions, which may include, after notice and opportunity for a hearing, the withholding from the local area all, or a portion, of the allocation under this section. Such funds shall be used to provide summer employment activities in such local area under alternative arrangements that are consistent with the program elements described in subsection (d)(4)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFB4D12BC29DC41759DB5265D803E64E5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement and not supplant</header><text>Any funds made available for a local area for summer employment programs under this section shall supplement and not supplant other State or local public funds expended for summer employment programs or other youth activities funded under section 129 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE93D4D2EB5F14859A36CA4B772BDB006"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reports</header>
<paragraph id="H49ECEC0AAA2942A7A6BCDA0207FA129E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each year that a local area receives an allocation under this section to carry out a summer employment program, the local board shall submit to the Secretary of Labor and the Governor a report with—</text> <subparagraph id="H19A4C9CA18B2490AA6FE5784DFA77A3F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth participating in the program, disaggregated by the number of such youth that are in-school youth and that are out-of-school youth;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7ED20639D3CF43178F086E401D5A0146"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth participating in the program who complete a summer employment opportunity through the program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H84182DBBD94145FBB39328C773ED92D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the expenditures made from the amounts allocated under this section, including expenditures made to provide eligible youth participating in such program with supportive services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5648F9BF25BC4FE795E3F5BA9B35CD48"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of how the local area has used amounts allocated under this section to develop or expand a summer employment program, including a description of program activities and services provided to eligible youth, including supportive services provided and the number of eligible youth participating in such program and accessing such services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD13FA59441834DDBA70715A49ADA5627"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for youth participants with a subsidized wage, the amount and source of the subsidy, including the amount of the subsidy covered by grant funds under this section; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H33D7C82088D8460F82E4AEFDA6725B9D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information specifying the levels of performance achieved with respect to the primary indicators of performance for the program described in subsection (e)(1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95AE64CF32744EE2A9239812E3B13D33"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the average number of hours and weeks worked and the average amount of wages earned by eligible youth participating in the program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE010D3F4063947FFAA4009C65B756901" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the average number of hours spent on—</text> <clause id="HB2204A8BFFB0484A974C4EDAAEE28651"><enum>(i)</enum><text>recruitment and retention strategies; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H4648080A2E094D439D6E540D34085675"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support for participating youth, such as time management, career planning, and financial literacy training;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H50CD2EC9806A4A9191FD8D26770CD7C7"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percent of eligible youth participating in the program that are placed in—</text>
<clause id="H7414206608174C43AEA1558DFE682D81"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the nonprofit sector;</text></clause> <clause id="H6F6992E92BB74A8DACF5577D3567BD43"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the public sector; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H1948BC5235574CC5A3098FE480ABCD97"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the private sector; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFD2A775675E44010B7F232E5D1A46BFB"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary of Labor determines necessary to monitor the effectiveness of the summer employment program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H68492B06880043A390F295A48FF611AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text>The information required to be reported under subparagraphs (A), (B), and (G) of paragraph (1) shall be disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, age, and the subpopulations described in subclauses (I) through (VI) of section 129(a)(1)(B)(iii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(a)(1)(B)(iii)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0067316324E840539D25BAE88F97D69E" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Eligible youth defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible youth</term> means an individual who, at the time the eligibility determination is made, is an out-of-school youth or an in-school youth.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H9D4A446EE1F1427DB9A7515E01224E71"><enum>5.</enum><header>Year-round employment opportunities for youth</header>
<subsection id="H59276E8F285A46139A130E2A286E8A9A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amount available under section 3(b)(2), the Secretary of Labor shall, for the purpose of carrying out year-round employment programs under this section—</text> <paragraph id="H4EAD79C08BDE47AA93B141536F340D7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>after making the reservation described in paragraph (2), make an allotment of the remainder of such amount in accordance with section 127(b)(1)(C)(ii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3162">29 U.S.C. 3162(b)(1)(C)(ii)</external-xref>) to each State that meets the requirements of section 102 or 103 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3112">29 U.S.C. 3112</external-xref>; 3113); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H70F5598E2FF24B3CAE06B4DC775FAFFE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reserve not more than one-quarter of 1 percent of such amount to provide assistance to the outlying areas.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H726487BAE36F453AAB04F28F7F149EA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Within state allocations</header> <paragraph id="HA0E9BF6284854CDF922C18D9765B5796"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor of a State, in accordance with the State plan developed under section 102 or 103 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3112">29 U.S.C. 3112</external-xref>; 3113), shall allocate the amounts that are allotted to the State under subsection (a)(1) to local areas meeting the requirements under subsection (c) in accordance with the allocation described section 128(b)(2)(A)(i) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3163">29 U.S.C. 3163(b)(2)(A)(i)</external-xref>) for the purpose of developing and expanding year-round employment programs under this section.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD423915EE1EF4961B58F663B0E4CFE96" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reallocation among local areas</header>
<subparagraph id="H8B45F138C8B84D29843027C6C8AD5A92" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor may, after consultation with the State board, reallocate to eligible local areas within the State amounts that are made available to local areas from allocations made under this section (referred to in this paragraph as a <term>local allocation</term>) and that are available for reallocation in accordance with this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85A8EDDF68474031940A17050CBCC0D6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount available for reallocation for a program year is equal to the amount by which the unobligated balance of the local allocation, at the end of the program year prior to the program year for which the determination under this paragraph is made, exceeds 20 percent of such allocation for the prior program year.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7AD17D70B9414E7C9D91A0177A33289F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>In making reallocations to eligible local areas of amounts available pursuant to subparagraph (B) for a program year, the Governor shall allocate to each eligible local area within the State an amount based on the relative amount of the local allocation for the program year for which the determination is made, as compared to the total amount of the local allocations for all eligible local areas in the State for such program year.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADE840249827425B8471A682C48DFEC8"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Eligible local area</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>eligible local area</term> means a local area that meets the requirements under subsection (c) and does not have an amount available for reallocation under subparagraph (B) for the program year for which the determination under such subparagraph is made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1C02FE3BBDA4047A7FFE262E8EB63F4"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Local reservation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amount allocated to a local area under paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HA1537AD18D714D17BE4ACFFB95DE932E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 10 percent of such amount may be used for the administrative costs of carrying out a year-round employment program under this section, including costs for participating in regional and national opportunities for in-person or virtual peer learning under section 9; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2EFDED00C42F44D3BDF3FBCBDA21B639"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not less than 5 percent of such amount shall be used to provide direct financial assistance to eligible youth through grants to support their financial needs to enter, remain enrolled in, and complete the program, such as support for supplies, transportation, child care, and housing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H46C11763CC71479BA918E4A893BC7C6D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Local plans</header> <paragraph id="H08BA0BBB2E7C4F918B07E163EE5E1CCD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order for a local area to be eligible for funds under this section, the local board of the local area shall develop and submit to the Governor in accordance with paragraph (2) a 4-year plan for the year-round employment program. Such plan shall, at a minimum—</text>
<subparagraph id="H86E44EC3EFB9467AB6CC7299B36B790B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not conflict with the local plan submitted by the local board under section 108 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3123">29 U.S.C. 3123</external-xref>), as determined by the Governor; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F7F0C2E2BDE414C9083FD443B250E09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contain the contents required under paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2BA54D3D14584A1A956AE2E21E8A6B3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission</header>
<subparagraph id="HE1A7DBC0F2574AA983D293CC33646426"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A plan required under this subsection shall be submitted by the local area to the Governor of such area at such time and in such manner as the Governor may reasonably require.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H683754B1CB1C4ACA8E31AA7A8DF4F82D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Combined plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a local area is seeking funds under this section and section 4, the plan required under this subsection may be submitted in combination with a plan under section 4, in lieu of the local area submitting 2 separate plans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5795D405C704D7A98E9407C98C77330"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>At a minimum, each plan required under this subsection shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H8C918C8E507A40FBA82CC41F9D788B81"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the local area will carry out the activities described in subsection (d) for each program year;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA84C9C5BBB4C49248C3391DE474D54E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the local area will recruit eligible youth to participate in the program, including how the local area will prioritize recruitment of individuals with barriers to employment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06AD2EBE08F348F79C6D5BBC5F67FFFB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth expected to participate in the program each program year;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9A4607C9A27D47148834808B9C2C82BA"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the services provided, including supportive services, that the program is expected to provide to eligible youth, including how the local area will partner with community-based organizations to provide such services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCACE4FDAEB1747ED9D1361D156BDBAB0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>performance accountability goals, as measured by the primary indicators of performance described in subsection (e)(1);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H54AF1BED1E7546439D6877F60E869670"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an assurance that the program will be aligned with the youth investment activities provided under chapter 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3161">29 U.S.C. 3161 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3AD3BC1F160A41D9BB5E2D60142AB851"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an assurance that the local area will adhere to the labor standards outlined in section 7; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC9F3EBC965164E8C8A88001DA30A44B8"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the alignment of the program to work-based learning, or plans to create work-based learning opportunities, and whether the program will award academic credit towards the fulfillment of a secondary school diploma or its recognized equivalent, or a recognized postsecondary credential, as applicable;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7A5B8D2982154BB6B5DC71AB17ED17CB"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of programs being offered that align to high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H94B187003AF5460981726068F1336415"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other information as the Governor may reasonably require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD5D71248B01D4258AC03E375180E2154"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Local use of funds</header> <paragraph id="HE54C5E1C50C64A79801E3B3161AAAFB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local area that receives an allocation under this section shall use such allocation for development activities or expansion activities with respect to a year-round employment program in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1703B038A5FC4CC7B1D5E5F3152467D0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a local area that, at the beginning of the first program year covered by the local plan submitted under subsection (c), is not carrying out a year-round employment program described in paragraph (4), the local board of such local area—</text> <subparagraph id="HA4A868790EDB4201A51AB0EA1FD8B4DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall use the amount to—</text>
<clause id="H0D89F3CA69F74718A7453A489C15FB00"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">plan, develop, and carry out a community-based year-round employment program that meets each such requirement, that to the extent practicable, are evidence-based; </text></clause> <clause id="H15D3C5FF04F74EAEB03E1E5FC0AA62C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage or establish industry or sector partnerships to determine year-round job needs to inform the establishment of such program; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H1D138F6FDCF94759A264AE2D51C00C82"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct outreach to eligible youth and employers; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA49C8C20992D4F1D8EA52B55DF18430D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may—</text>
<clause id="HB02E5C143562461EB43AB904BB5DFB2C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use such amount to develop technology infrastructure, including data and management systems, to support such program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD4A411AEBA2640BAB2BCBDE1AEDAF3B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>use not more than 50 percent of such amount to subsidize the wages of each eligible youth participating in such program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE1AE96D417704FBA88F9A02ABC02E0D1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expansion activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a local area that, at the beginning of the first full program year covered by the local plan submitted under subsection (c), is carrying out a year-round program described in paragraph (4), the local board of such local area—</text> <subparagraph id="HC39304A86AD64CABAAEAB6DDBE6634C4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall use such amount to—</text>
<clause id="H13F860A3914B42F5B9922CB96635902F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the number of community-based, year-round employment opportunities offered through such program, including unsubsidized or partly subsidized opportunities and opportunities in the private sector, that to the extent practicable, are evidence-based;</text></clause> <clause id="HCE9B8DEB0C874C47915C19750249859B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conduct outreach to eligible youth and employers; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HE3B680AD3765483DA6D6F3184CEB0BC9" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>subsidize the wages of eligible youth participating in such program; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB282F9B50EDE405FADF51BE64CF19C59" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may use such amount to enhance the activities required under paragraph (4)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1152844BAFC14C74AFD3F481A026FAC6" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program requirements</header>
<subparagraph id="H939FE4203C5448D6891C022E8B1C2585" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Program Design</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A year-round employment program described in this paragraph is a program that meets the following requirements:</text> <clause id="H15134A59E4B14060BC2E6AEFF8F845DA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each eligible youth participating in the program is matched with an appropriate employer, based on factors including the needs of the employer and the age, skill, and informed aspirations of the participant, for high-quality, year-round employment, which may not—</text>
<subclause id="H822AE265FEA44581A18B13C03BDE139C" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be less than 180 days and more than 1 year;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA4A4720BFE2B4800B1137F5FF0D7906C" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>pay less than the greater of the applicable Federal, State, or local minimum wage; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H13F2AD9927E74CD3B8D70E4D59409167" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>employ the eligible youth for less than 20 hours per week.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HB77C67B4D9AA4D85902C53A16B463114" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Employer share of wages</header><text>Not less than 25 percent of the wages of each eligible youth participating in the program are paid by the employer, except this requirement may be waived for not more than 10 percent of eligible youth participating in the program that have a significant barrier to employment, as defined by the State board.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7E63CC9F27C04BC3BA7D32154DF71872" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Program elements</header><text>The program includes the following program elements:</text> <clause id="HFD5E17DBCD66438F8D717B6761BEAFB7" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Work-readiness training and educational programs aligned to career pathways for eligible youth to enhance their year-round employment opportunities, including digital literacy and online work-readiness opportunities, as appropriate, and support obtaining documentation needed for employment, such as identification or licenses.</text></clause>
<clause id="HAC9E83B3A5134AB3B947E57476806710" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Coaching and mentoring services for eligible youth participating in the program to enhance their year-round employment opportunities and encourage completion of such opportunities through the program.</text></clause> <clause id="HC93C205A85214AD8B0E888580BD2082E" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coaching and mentoring services for employers on how to successfully employ each eligible youth participating in the program in meaningful work, including on providing a safe work and training environment for all participants, regardless of race, color, disability, age, religion, national origin, political affiliation, belief, marital status, sex (including sexual orientation or gender identity), pregnancy, childbirth, or a related medical condition, or status as a parent.</text></clause>
<clause id="H0784B356EACC41528A68D00989F99B86" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Career exploration, career counseling, career planning, and college planning services for eligible youth participating in the program.</text></clause> <clause id="H2F05F45F9F5342BFB73C828B907A99AC" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">High-quality financial literacy education as described in section 129(b)(2)(D) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(b)(2)(D)</external-xref>), for eligible youth participating in the program, including education on the use of credit and financing higher education, and access to safe and affordable banking accounts with consumer protections, including from local credit unions.</text></clause>
<clause id="H0D2D9D437A4F49049D7C3274AEF7DFDB" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing supportive services to eligible youth, or connecting such youth to supportive services provided by another entity, to enable participation in the program, which may include food and nutrition services, and health and mental health care supports.</text></clause> <clause id="HFBDED1EF8F6D4AD2BB0642DFD058ED15" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Follow-up services for not less than 12 months after the completion of participation, as appropriate.</text></clause>
<clause id="H7D447101065D4D0CAD48576A98058161" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Integration of services provided by the program with youth development programs, secondary school programs, career and technical education programs, youth workforce investment activities under chapter 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3161">29 U.S.C. 3161 et seq.</external-xref>), and skills training programs funded by the State or Federal Government, as applicable.</text></clause> <clause id="HCE1936ED5B9142E490CFC11B60A13ED5" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Connecting youth participating in the program to providers of youth services, adult employment and training services, vocational rehabilitation services, and adult education and literacy services under title II of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3271">29 U.S.C. 3271 et seq.</external-xref>), career pathways, postsecondary education, or skills training programs funded by the State or Federal Government, as applicable.</text></clause>
<clause id="HBE87118CD1E7461D8BF3527896150148" commented="no"><enum>(x)</enum><text>A rigorous evaluation of such program using research approaches appropriate to the level of development and maturity of the program, including random assignment or quasi-experimental impact evaluations, implementation evaluations, pre-experimental studies, and feasibility studies.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HCDEFF71F749B4316A9CC73D47AC47FF3"><enum>(xi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Commitment and support from mayors or county executives to support the execution of the program as described in the local plan submitted under subsection (c).</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3D3778B4DF6D4258A72091D1014BACC1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information and referrals</header>
<clause id="H1CBFEC2479BF4A44A03E82C0C53C17BB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each local board shall ensure that each participant of a year-round employment program receiving assistance under this section shall be provided—</text> <subclause id="H2C05A381404D4FA58EAA4C3EF181C389" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the full array of applicable or appropriate services that are available through the local board or other eligible providers or one-stop partners, including those providers or partners receiving funds under this Act; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H719F06B213A14F22AB0F55C4E58B777E" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">referral to appropriate training and educational programs that have the capacity to serve the participant either on a concurrent or sequential basis.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HBE6B9510E4744C79A320727EA29F5E02" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Further assessment and referral</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each local board shall, in a manner consistent with section 129(c)(3)(B) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(c)(3)(B)</external-xref>), ensure that eligible youth who do not meet the employment requirements for the year-round employment program shall be referred for further assessment, as necessary, and referred to appropriate programs in accordance with clause (i) to meet the basic skills and training needs for such employment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD34619F0CB8F41268EB8FABE09B63117"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In carrying out a year-round employment program receiving assistance under this section, a local area shall give priority to year-round employment opportunities offered under such program—</text> <subparagraph id="HD430D5F9946746218DF0CE9E3361B578"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in existing or emerging high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA787C1A1270542D885976C45BCD547C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that meet community needs in the public, private, or nonprofit sector.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0B5E0D65D8FC4C77B8C989C26536E5F8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Performance accountability</header> <paragraph id="H2F793452941E40BEA884D08E283AB63A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each local area receiving an allocation under this section, the primary indicators of performance, for each year-round program receiving assistance under such allocation, shall include—</text>
<subparagraph id="H956596E3F18E49D5AE2D842A2EB84FDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the performance metrics described in section 116(b)(2)(A)(ii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)(ii)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H15E3A289D6C640E395CE805A20117DB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of eligible youth completing the program; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDBB61D53F365475D8AE6D179402C4146"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of eligible youth having participated in work-based learning.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD66629A696BA4104A1404F5A3D08D67F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to meet local performance accountability measures</header> <subparagraph id="H55DF87FF7BD54310AB20762DE63AEC98"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a local area fails, for any program year, to meet a performance accountability goal identified in its plan under subsection (c)(3)(E) with respect to a year-round employment program funded under this section, the Governor, or, upon request by the Governor, the Secretary of Labor, shall provide the local area with technical assistance, which may include assistance in the development of a performance improvement plan for such program.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC3DF7184E58440F2A32BEFEF3BD5B015"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Corrective actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a case in which such local area fails to meet such performance accountability goal with respect to the program for a third consecutive year or fails to implement the improvement plan, the Governor shall take corrective actions, which may include, after notice and opportunity for a hearing, the withholding from the local area all, or a portion, of the allocation under this section to provide summer employment activities in such local areas under alternative arrangements that are consistent with the program elements described in subsection (d)(4)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7BA1B2311BFD4988B37EFBF5EBAD941F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement and not supplant</header><text>Any funds made available for year-round employment programs under this section shall supplement and not supplant other State or local public funds expended for year-round youth employment programs or other youth activities funded under section 129 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H33BDFE69BF9947A5BF76E791A3027522"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reports</header>
<paragraph id="H78E7DC43F6E04A2DAC8C45E13F5B635E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each year that a local area receives an allocation under this section for a year-round employment program, the local area shall submit to the Secretary of Labor and the Governor a report with—</text> <subparagraph id="HC58F4CE75A684153A908C06D2E5C61E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth participating in the program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9869DC3181D947C58748912F6B111B17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of eligible youth participating in the program who complete a year-round employment opportunity through the program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H367E0D1B585143AC98DF5778EFF2E6F3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the expenditures made from the amounts allocated under this section, including expenditures made to provide eligible youth participating in the program with supportive services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD3EF99B2697947209C1D37BD0F8AB9F7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of how the local area has used amounts allocated under this section to develop or expand a year-round work-based learning employment program, including a description of the program activities and services, including the supportive services provided and the number of eligible youth participating in the program and accessing such services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE6513B7FB8FB400C854E2AD2C2EB270C"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each youth participant with a subsidized wage, the amount and source of the subsidy, including the amount of the subsidy covered by grant funds under this section;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H04A1CD4935624464AD4AD58B8721B3D5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information specifying the levels of performance achieved with respect to the primary indicators of performance described in subsection (e)(1) for the program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC3934512C724533B5480CF48CFD09AB"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the average number of hours and weeks worked and the average amount of wages earned by eligible youth participating in the program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB09B44F3C1174E7B8F5C76498DE9D46B"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the average number of hours spent on—</text> <clause id="HDEA3DECA3F754242B20775033EE25875"><enum>(i)</enum><text>recruitment and retention strategies; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HEFC8BBC7394D4F6DA33A330E405C9B3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support for participating youth, such as time management, career planning, and financial literacy training;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE3751E55ADA040098BF53ADE9E498938"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percent of eligible youth participating in the program that are placed in—</text>
<clause id="HC10D0A1778CD4361B03A9060B95419F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the nonprofit sector;</text></clause> <clause id="HC02FA05BBE32485D810F953E619AAE06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the public sector; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HD0028BE8C82C478B94FF45D58FFCD62C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an employment opportunity in the private sector;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H98446CAC51274C6FA8B2E213FEC46912"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of eligible youth participating in the program who are asked by the employer to remain employed by the employer after the end of the year-round employment program and the number of youth participants remaining employed by the employer for not less than 90 days after the end of the year-round employment program; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC7D24B75FF194F459F32F60E27A9D3FB"><enum>(K)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary of Labor determines necessary to monitor the effectiveness of the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2237C4A03B4940FCA079790F552703B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text>The information required to be reported under subparagraphs (A), (B), and (G) of paragraph (1) shall be disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, age, and each subpopulation described in subclauses (I) through (VI) of section 129(a)(1)(B)(iii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(a)(1)(B)(iii)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1E54CB24DE954887822C139DB698CF3A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Eligible youth defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible youth</term> means an individual who, at the time the eligibility determination is made, is an out-of-school youth.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H1AF5E60C13174D159D3DCB4C11F2D354"><enum>6.</enum><header>Connecting-for-opportunities competitive grant program</header> <subsection id="HC51742EE13394499839F4730C8DB6F27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amount available under section 3(b)(3), the Secretary of Labor shall, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, award grants on a competitive basis to local community partnerships to assist such local community partnerships in improving high school graduation and youth employment rates.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H83970F4BF63D40AD83BA74FF298438C0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Local community partnerships</header>
<paragraph id="HF3B147DFFCC4428DB0181E4B09D246D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mandatory partners</header><text>In this section, the term <term>local community partnership</term> means a partnership among at least the following entities: </text> <subparagraph id="H03FAD321E1E24086955C4715DF71707F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A unit of general local government.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD2DE492D8BEC447F81F197CB169B26AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A local educational agency.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42495F9AAC4342A88B13EFDA562A261F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H81FDE8DBB21E44ADB6EB383F3AFFEDC3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A local board.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4819474841DD43E99190B796DD952477"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A community-based organization with experience or expertise in working with youth.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4D036600D72A45E1926E3FAC7FE5AF0D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A public agency serving youth or young adults under the jurisdiction of the juvenile justice system or criminal justice system.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5040D99708544DDA4F06A863B013FE1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A State or local child welfare agency. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7C2C0049ED4E4EDE8A2ECE86B730DC79"><enum>(H)</enum><text>An agency administering programs under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC9C74B6C9C30471FA50BD1512A1B1AA9" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>An industry or sector partnership, to the extent practicable.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6A33D0E36FBB45689494313D7B66FB23" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>A labor organization or joint labor-management organization, to the extent practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1DC16A1320514737B483DE4D11780CB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Optional partners</header><text>The following entities may be included as part of the partnership among the entities listed in paragraph (1):</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H68BA81E5C5DD4F37B60606F5C3AE4F21"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One-stop operators.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAA135F6384AC416BBCFFAEFFCBE1E925"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Employers or employer associations.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H01DCE89D9672482CAEF8193CEEB742CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Entities that carry out programs that receive funding under the Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/11101">34 U.S.C. 11101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE05DC039798F46DCA95B1864B30D62FC"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public agencies or community-based organizations with expertise in providing evidence-based trauma support services, counseling, or mental health care to youth, including trauma-informed and gender-responsive counseling.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3EC3E076F19D435183585356BADCADCA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Public housing agencies, collaborative applicants (as defined in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>)), or private nonprofit organizations that serve homeless youth and households or foster youth.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF8B2E7D1E3224CE9BB093A886B18FC4B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Other appropriate State and local agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC63F315250C84AB7BDC1C0D2839A707F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A local community partnership desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary of Labor an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require. At a minimum, each application shall include a comprehensive plan that—</text> <paragraph id="H28FEE4EBDE6B4677953B486B119A4E8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>demonstrates sufficient need for the grant in the local population, which need may be demonstrated—</text>
<subparagraph id="HDC7F5BA9902D440BA45794C998034EA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the basis of high school dropouts in the local area to be served by the partnership, as compared to the total number of unemployed individuals ages 16 to 24 in local areas in all States; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H01D4BFA372CB4E41896CBACB7B3DA1BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the basis of the relative number of unemployed individuals ages 16 to 24 in the local area to be served by the partnership, as compared to the total number of unemployed individuals ages 16 to 24 in local areas in all States; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3255EFA28644446EAA09AD99EE42E088"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the basis of the relative percentage or number of low-income individuals in the local area to be served by the partnership, as compared to the total percentage or number of low-income individuals in local areas in all States;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFEBA8A9B797D41D081E1BCE2998164FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifies and describes the role of each entity in the partnership, including the fiscal agent in the partnership and the role of each such entity in carrying out the activities described in subsection (d);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5D628930AD1C463AA9E4FE58A4EBF800"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not conflict with the local plan submitted by the local board in the local area served by the local community partnership under section 108 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3123">29 U.S.C. 3123</external-xref>), the applicable local plan for career and technical education programs under section 134 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2354">20 U.S.C. 2354</external-xref>) (if not part of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act local plan), and the applicable State plan for programs under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB817F7BC15D04C9DB93DC868043AE7A3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>includes an assurance that the partnership will adhere to the labor standards outlined in section 7.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFC2FD75C8CDE4F8BA7D4DAB70B436DB7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A local community partnership receiving a grant under this section shall use the grant funds—</text> <paragraph id="H1D11A8760D5C4174B41A1F6F22A6D454"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to target and serve individuals not younger than age 14 or older than age 24, prioritizing individuals with barriers to employment;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4D1899F058154B889AECB82FBCEE798F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to make appropriate use of education, child welfare, social services, and workforce development data collection systems to facilitate the local community partnership’s ability to target and serve the individuals described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE73B42B321A942A786D639D5C5415095"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to develop wide-ranging pathways to postsecondary education and employment, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5284754D2A2F4DC58516FA8003457092"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using not less than 50 percent of the grant funds to help individuals described in paragraph (1) complete their secondary school education, including through high-quality, flexible programs that utilize community-based, and, to the extent practicable, evidence-based interventions and provide differentiated services (or pathways) to students—</text> <clause id="H1B7773712D0C4E98B8A1940E614F7A4C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who are returning to education after exiting secondary school without a secondary school diploma or its recognized equivalent; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H1ED6C11CBFA742358BD5CE3A89440B6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who, based on their grade or age, are significantly off track to accumulate sufficient academic credits to meet high school graduation requirements, as established by the State;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3428620811B64DA1B064B893F8174E16"><enum>(B)</enum><text>creating career pathways, focused on paid work-based learning consisting of on-the-job training and classroom instruction, that—</text>
<clause id="H3D0293AB21AB45F388C722A92694C217"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">will lead to the attainment of a recognized postsecondary credential; and</text></clause> <clause id="H76601E356534499EB24D546E005A9D50"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes, to the maximum extent practicable, learning through apprenticeship programs and pre-apprenticeship programs;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF034F11B01924468BF48F04CE2209A98"><enum>(C)</enum><text>connecting individuals described in paragraph (1) with professionals who can provide such individuals with pre-employment and employment counseling and assist such individuals in—</text> <clause id="H2BC2D547D7394867B8CB581B4E69DFCC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>finding and securing employment or work-based learning opportunities that pay not less than the greater of the applicable Federal, State, or local minimum wage;</text></clause>
<clause id="HFEF8F7A7A70E4495BBE6322A1629FD0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identifying and assessing eligibility for training programs and funding for such programs;</text></clause> <clause id="HBF1EFBD068DF41F0BEA416026C15FBDD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>completing necessary paperwork for applying for and enrolling in such programs; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H7CDB4E1C3B4A4CE896F5483462114023"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identifying additional services, if needed;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5E7BFB22EA3453C8D4A603203F8E9F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>connecting individuals described in paragraph (1) with providers of—</text>
<clause id="H2B3C1F9426894E3E96361E430B864D88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>youth services, adult employment and training services, vocational rehabilitation services, and adult education and literacy services, under the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause> <clause id="HFF07E02686704D249B657B7D3CB9C1B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>career planning services; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H6AB34816500F4B18B4BC1E361E183235"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>federally and State-funded programs that provide skills training; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7DCE7E46759649B480FB7EBBF6C7F64C"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring that such individuals successfully transition into pre-apprenticeship programs, apprenticeship programs, or programs leading to recognized postsecondary credentials in high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB860263301E64B70B77245BD88CAAF6A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide a comprehensive system of supportive services aimed at preventing the individuals described in paragraph (1) from disconnecting from education, training, and employment, and aimed at re-engaging any such individual who has been so disconnected, by—</text> <subparagraph id="HE07B8CC7DB4C4336A63F0F50069BD49F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing school-based dropout prevention and community-based dropout recovery services, including establishing or improving school district early warning systems that—</text>
<clause id="H36C1E7FF2F8C47E183AF7CBE971074B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">connect such systems to data gathering and reporting systems established under the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>) for the purpose of identifying the individuals described in paragraph (1) so long as such data does not reveal personally identifiable information about a program participant or would not reveal such information when combined with other released information; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4EA1D204CED44C2A99D916A6027CA047"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage any such identified individual using targeted, community-based, and, to the extent practicable, evidence-based interventions to address the specific needs and issues of the individual, including chronic absenteeism; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEF71CC16BE5E435EA87580A65BF3CB05"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing the individuals described in paragraph (1) with access to re-engagement services for training programs and employment opportunities and, to the extent practicable, using providers of youth services under the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>) to conduct intake and refer such individuals and their families to the appropriate re-engagement service; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA235446290C541DFBE7E182699C7E0F1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to provide a comprehensive system of support for the individuals described in paragraph (1), including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA91665AF44A6496AA6CFA0F11AD6F747"><enum>(A)</enum><text>connecting such individuals with professionals who can—</text> <clause id="H9450DCAC146D4A9C961B6DF91465D5B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide case management and counseling services; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H4FE39CC125C745858E04A2B6B925D372"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assist such individuals in—</text> <subclause id="HE43075896E6B4713AA69ADE00682A62F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>developing achievable short-term goals and long-term goals; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HA2D04B4D16804C01AE6730BA305B2B8E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">overcoming any social, administrative, or financial barrier that may hinder enrollment in the program or the achievement of such goals; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2D552CE682E493B91AD424B0A7619BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing or connecting participants with available supportive services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF411AFFBC6E74FDFAAC532F028BFB837"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority in awards</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary of Labor shall give priority to applications submitted by local community partnerships that include a comprehensive plan that—</text> <paragraph id="HC50A95A3F2A94853A1A01D0E76EFDF51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>serves and targets communities with a high percentage of low-income individuals and high rates of high school dropouts and youth unemployment; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD947FA7786664C5A84EBA613C74C1787"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allows the individuals described in paragraph (1) to earn academic credit through various means, including high-quality career and technical education, dual or concurrent programs, virtual learning, or work-based learning.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4988F38EE7114CB99C17B54B525A0D05"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that consideration is given to geographic distribution (such as urban, Tribal, and rural areas) in awarding grants under this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H41B95273BA634CEAAC3AE209E6BB35F4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Performance accountability</header><text>For activities funded under this section, the primary indicators of performance shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H883DDFCC39994FFEA810369754B85E4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the performance metrics described in section 116(b)(2)(A)(ii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)(ii)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7DD2C3A6A5D243D9904FEABF1AB184FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the four-year adjusted cohort graduation rate and the extended-year adjusted cohort graduation rate in a State that chooses to use such a graduation rate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FD76B82ACFE4283BB7A75ED36B508AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the rate of attaining a recognized equivalent of a diploma, such as a general equivalency diploma.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H46E5701B8E274394A5920D0F77D1C842"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header>
<paragraph id="HAF96C8BE3990404D8E83FE6D97479BF5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each year that a local community partnership carries out activities and services with a grant under this section, the partnership shall submit to the State board in which the partnership is carrying out activities under this section, and to the Secretary of Labor, a report on—</text> <subparagraph id="H8483390C014C4C408931BCAF1DB92594"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of youth participating in activities under subsection (d), including the number of in-school and out-of-school youth;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HADCE2C4E92D84FBCBAA53E4FBB047916"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the expenditures made from the grant awarded under this section, including any expenditures made to provide youth participants with supportive services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8535501C35E45CD9189B1642E4D9C1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the activities and services assisted under this section, including supportive services provided and the number of youth participants accessing such services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H63D4D816AA5F4B4CB74280BAE413A5E1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>information specifying the levels of performance achieved with respect to the primary indicators of performance described in subsection (g) for the program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7BA5356C7701423F9D93AD8C320A2063"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary of Labor determines necessary to monitor the effectiveness of the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6D0AA3C799334EC29D37E4448355131C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information required to be reported under subparagraphs (A), (C), and (D) of paragraph (1) shall be disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, age, and status as a subpopulation described in subclauses (I) through (VI) of section 129(a)(1)(B)(iii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3164">29 U.S.C. 3164(a)(1)(B)(iii)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HEE3D76A530BF47EAB9E41116EBBB0A6C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Labor standards</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any activity receiving assistance under this Act shall be subject to—</text>
<paragraph id="H9B9DDAF1D4CC4F5888E69B0EE703BD46"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the requirements and restrictions, including the labor standards, that apply to activities under title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3111">29 U.S.C. 3111 et seq.</external-xref>) as provided under section 181 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3241">29 U.S.C. 3241</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA63BA0CA53094C8FAD4A4F8B26AF9E0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the requirements for nondiscrimination that apply to activities under such title as provided under section 188 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3248">29 U.S.C. 3248</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2FB27800983F4CC7805816AECDF48859"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other applicable Federal law.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H727BEF4C91DC4C1793D0581066B5B3ED"><enum>8.</enum><header>Privacy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H61B0AA10B1BA4C6DA11C4D5FA3E4DBC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be construed to supersede the privacy protections afforded parents and students under section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74EE2D44D88E4E38984C4D8EE4C94503"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be construed to permit the development of a national database of personally identifiable information on individuals receiving services under this Act; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEF46DCA6C29C49768796647663F9152F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall require the disaggregation of data when the number of individuals in a category is insufficient to yield statistically reliable information or when the results would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual, or would reveal such information when combined with other released information.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H81896578861B464FB44668B0BB6533A3"><enum>9.</enum><header>Innovation and learning</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Out of the amount reserved under section 3(a)(1), the Secretary of Labor shall—</text>
<paragraph id="HECB40A29D8D54E819E30A44D8B4F74FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to ensure each State, local area, and local community partnership receiving funds under this Act have sufficient organizational capacity, staff training, and expertise to effectively implement the requirements under this Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49BB89B02489403098A88458AADE155C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>create regional and national opportunities for virtual or in-person peer learning; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1D0D995F8E474170B3BF45518A4080F7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide, on a competitive basis, grants to States and local areas to—</text> <subparagraph id="H03DD24755C914E899289BFE4FB04B245"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct pilot programs and demonstration programs using emerging and evidence-based best practices and models for youth employment programs; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE00E1E47C8294277AE1C66B1BCBF3AEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluate such programs using designs that employ the most rigorous analytical and statistical methods that are reasonably feasible.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HF071F8B56B8B4B1E9D1B51A96D3E6EEF"><enum>10.</enum><header>Evaluation and reports</header> <subsection id="HA158C37366494DF298A5514570C5CC1A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall conduct, on an annual basis, a rigorous evaluation of the programs administered under this Act using research approaches appropriate to the level of development and maturity of the program, including random assignment or quasi-experimental impact evaluations, implementation evaluations, pre-experimental studies, and feasibility studies. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HC25E1DB659E74CCF866736E769B609F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the completion of the first program year after the date of enactment of this Act for which funds are expended to carry out this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Labor shall transmit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and make publicly accessible, the reports described in sections 4(g), 5(g), and 6(h), and a final report on the results of each evaluation conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H1064FDEDE52940B4B7F23204B8082ECF"><enum>11.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act: </text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H733669EE975D4E73BF3E603979A74CAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided, any term used in this Act that is defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>) shall have the meaning given the term in such section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA88597F6AD85436B9A70E9EDD0096E80"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Apprenticeship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprenticeship</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the “National Apprenticeship Act”; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H26A71ECBF4AB4925999E78B606840814"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>dual or concurrent enrollment</term>, <term>extended-year adjusted cohort graduation rate</term>, <term>evidence-based</term>, <term>four-year adjusted cohort graduation rate</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7A799F8241F4EC7A0E2DCE25215ABDF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Native American terms</header><text>The terms <term>Alaska Native entity</term>, <term>Indian</term>, <term>Indian tribe</term>, <term>National Hawaiian organization</term>, and <term>tribal organization</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 166 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3221">29 U.S.C. 3221</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H55BC0C55F5E4489596B7DA4F1AED416A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in sections 101 and 102(a)(1)(B) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>, 1002(a)(1)(B)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE912B37DC2A34E22B6A1EB241EF6A561"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Pre-apprenticeship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pre-apprenticeship</term> means a training model or program that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD93FB4B2C5734B9B9B3A5B6C3345122E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is designed to prepare participants to enter an apprenticeship program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE0490E84B83D4217952507510C93A04B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is carried out by a sponsor that has a written agreement with 1 or more sponsors of apprenticeship programs that would enable participants who successfully complete the pre-apprenticeship program—</text>
<clause id="H6502C23AAEC640B28901EC7BC3332293"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to enter into the apprenticeship program if a place in the program is available and if the participant meets the qualifications of the apprenticeship program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HDA1F1F92999C4BF585A1609AB3ACACF5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to earn credits towards the apprenticeship program; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB2F33E4CF3FD4D369F3342EADCC05F80"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes—</text> <clause id="HF8BD321604914EE5813EF027610BBBB8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">training (including a curriculum for the training) aligned with industry standards related to an apprenticeship program created in consultation with sponsors of the apprenticeship program that are parties to the written agreement under subparagraph (B), and that will prepare participants by teaching the skills and competencies needed to enter 1 or more apprenticeship programs; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H8F0822F4DC13415095494F6447D5BDD7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>hands-on training and theoretical education for participants that do not displace a paid employee.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13E33E32C7AB43B398A548E95AB169F2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Program year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>program year</term> as used in this Act is used in the manner as such term is used with respect to youth workforce investment activities under subtitle B of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3161">29 U.S.C. 3161 et seq.</external-xref>) and activities under section 171 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3226">29 U.S.C. 3226</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA4EC5BF74D5A47E5809E6A763DF6FE89"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Supportive services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>supportive services</term> means services such as transportation, child care, dependent care, housing, needs-related payments, food and nutrition services, and health and mental health care supports that are necessary to enable an individual to participate in activities authorized under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE473BF5F5A7B44278659328E04492E44"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Work-based learning</header><text>The term <term>work-based learning</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


