<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79EEE7F0FBB64F1FA216D6B9CC044F3F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 770 IH: ESP Family Leave Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 770</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish eligibility requirements for education support professionals and school support staff under the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1D132A70C7A64A25B0C6DA67BAAE0A4D" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HFA1D14B1A11B4E96A01FBEB28CB6DF04"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>ESP Family Leave Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF203A664B6544525A909E56D48FC4029"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eligibility for education support professionals and school support staff</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 101(2) of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2611">29 U.S.C. 2611(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFF79D1DFBEC44C88784F23DB9F65C22"><subparagraph id="H00B29810125E455CBF2A2793EE52489F"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Education support professionals and school support staff</header><clause id="HD9A7E4E7A8E14D47B63D6AD225712D8C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>For purposes of determining whether an employee who is an education support professional meets the hours of service requirement specified in subparagraph (A)(ii), the employee will be considered to meet the requirement if the employee has worked a number of hours equal to not less than 60 percent of the applicable total monthly hours expected for the employee’s job description and duties, as assigned for the previous school year.</text></clause><clause id="H9E92CD27B9394D319A4046A0AAD3A23A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>File</header><text>Each employer of an education support professional shall maintain on file with the Secretary (in accordance with such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe) information specifying the total monthly hours expected for the employee’s job description and duties for each school year.</text></clause><clause id="H7E1CC0E311354852AEC0E4EF33C23316"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subparagraph: </text><subclause id="H6CDF1EDABA1E4FBDACD3B308D74B3C64"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Education support professional</header><text>The term <term>education support professional</term> (who may also be known as <quote>school support staff</quote>) means an employee employed by an employer, as defined in paragraph (4), whose work takes place primarily within a public school or public institution of higher education, which may include—</text><item id="HE1142FEA91CD430C9E9DFE6485A1B9DC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>paraeducators that provide instructional and non-instructional support;</text></item><item id="H4970D5A6A26B4CE0A24B9E60701662FB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>secretarial, clerical, and administrative support staff;</text></item><item id="H3AA66F981F96490FBB4D08204ECB1D6E"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>custodians and maintenance service workers that provide building and grounds maintenance and repair;</text></item><item id="H3E13E528C038462AB02064B88FCE507E"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>skilled trade workers that provide services in schools, such as electricians, carpenters, and workers who operate machinery;</text></item><item id="HA56CC5C714FD42988BD9081ABA44CAB7"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>workers who provide food service, including preparation and serving of food;</text></item><item id="H361DB7E8EC964456997E84A0E98E8DF9"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>workers who provide school transportation and delivery services;</text></item><item id="H3EBCE3953614423292EE1D579CEDD192"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>computer, audiovisual, and language technical support staff;</text></item><item id="H872A8988605047B7802D9CBCFC96636E"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>security staff;</text></item><item id="H43F6DC8959234BB8B02B99B332A1A00B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nursing, health, and therapy support staff, who may also provide community, family, parent and welfare services; and</text></item><item id="H9501654C9789452596D9DF0A3ED541A3"><enum>(jj)</enum><text>other staff that may serve public education students.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HF652278E00DA413E88988FC3E42AD0BB"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Employer</header><text>The term <term>employer</term> includes a public school or public institution of higher education that meets the definition of employer in paragraph (4).</text></subclause><subclause id="H94526A22C968438D902496365A639F99"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Public school</header><text>The term <term>public school</term> means a school that is maintained at public expense for the education of the children of a community or district and that constitutes a part of a system of free public education commonly including primary and secondary schools, including special education cooperatives, alternative schools, and other similar facilities.</text></subclause><subclause id="HDA2FD1C1C8CB4CC986A3B77260EF7516"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Public institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>public institution of higher education</term> means an institution of higher education, as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>), that is funded, at least partly, by State taxpayers.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H39EA018396DE4568AB669E9C2B116D78"><enum>3.</enum><header>Entitlement to leave</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 102(a) of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E80EE60F00D4E629B3ADE4DE2FE5DCF"><paragraph id="H366EAA89AC0843F399FE5E7D2AB08B30"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Calculation of leave for education support professionals</header><text>The Secretary may provide a method for calculating the leave described in paragraph (1) with respect to employees described in section 101(2)(F).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

