<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H018A2E58812D4CD388742BCF3F2969BE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4637 IH: Jaime’s Law</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4637</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prevent the purchase of ammunition by prohibited purchasers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3CFF580331B946D3ADD331BF44630591" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB48C01B62B15485181871FB48FE89E62" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Jaime’s Law</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE8F6DA77F1AF4819A311C1CA0D8DA5AA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to enhance the background check process in the United States to prevent the purchase of ammunition by individuals who are prohibited from doing so under Federal and State law.</text></section> 
<section id="H90E6661406734FB493B42BCC762C6798"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transfers of firearms or ammunition</header> 
<subsection id="H0888D70502CC4467831796D1E3ABF0BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H56C785588CDA46A9916A92DDAF26E0A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subsection (s) and redesignating subsection (t) as subsection (s); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H12FA1F1DF93243968127F68DC3A607B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (s) (as so redesignated)—</text> <subparagraph id="H43E8B5FBCD15461AAFDA404162ADE17C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or ammunition</quote> after <quote>firearm</quote> each place it appears;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H72FA5C2C3314449D8206D50D7E7C65D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B)(ii), by inserting <quote>in the case of a firearm,</quote> before <quote>3</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCFB05741B69B4DBD8F07F7FCAD8F9509"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(C), by inserting <quote>a firearm and</quote> before <quote>a person less</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9522F2C7343B4F2C89B1903B3CB45932"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H3793299937F9467C81D5B147E0B5F01E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H82C1D84B86A74B10BC71E72056587E0B" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum> <subparagraph id="HBF9FD884CF84405F845D335773BF8A80" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause id="HD76A3320913B40A7B14117990B3ACF09" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for any person who is not a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer to transfer ammunition to any other person who is not so licensed, unless a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer has first taken possession of the ammunition for the purpose of complying with this subsection.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H218121D957924F3F90A1D0E997689097" indent="up2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Upon taking possession of ammunition under clause (i), a licensee shall comply with all requirements of this chapter as if the licensee were transferring ammunition from the inventory of the licensee to the unlicensed transferee.</text></clause> <clause id="HF598B1E77FCC43759C71FC645E79A5F7" indent="up2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>If a transfer of ammunition described in clause (i) will not be completed for any reason after a licensee takes possession of the ammunition (including because the transfer of the ammunition to, or receipt of the ammunition by, the transferee would violate this chapter), the return of the ammunition to the transferor by the licensee shall not constitute the transfer of ammunition for purposes of this chapter.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8181FD37A334B7293D02AAFA25A0EB6" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to—</text> <clause id="H8E0427F3DFF44D7E9BAADB9158ECE6E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a law enforcement agency or any law enforcement officer, armed private security professional, or member of the armed forces, to the extent the officer, professional, or member is acting within the course and scope of employment and official duties;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD8358BA151054522A22BE21F13E1B0AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a transfer that is a loan or bona fide gift between spouses, between domestic partners, between parents and their children, between siblings, between aunts or uncles and their nieces or nephews, or between grandparents and their grandchildren;</text></clause> <clause id="H793BEC2E5B504171B5E5407A7A5A9E66"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a transfer to an executor, administrator, trustee, or personal representative of an estate or a trust that occurs by operation of law upon the death of another person;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB8899C4336A545CCABDE2575116E6708"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a transfer if the transfer is necessary to prevent imminent death or great bodily harm, if the possession by the transferee lasts only as long as immediately necessary to prevent the imminent death or great bodily harm; or</text></clause> <clause id="H911DABC74036401C9E74943D1A19B9FE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a transfer, if the transferor has no reason to believe that the transferee will use or intends to use the ammunition in a crime or is prohibited from possessing ammunition under State or Federal law, and the transfer takes place and the transferee’s possession of the ammunition is exclusively—</text> 
<subclause id="H4B4260AF3F3B437DBA38D60B518000AD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>at a shooting range or in a shooting gallery or other area designated for the purpose of target shooting;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H851A1C1FE71A42BE92D86B75D9DDD96B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>while reasonably necessary for the purposes of hunting, trapping, or fishing, if the transferor—</text> 
<item id="H5B2D3C3436424F0AAE16186061C91B99"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>has no reason to believe that the transferee intends to use the ammunition in a place where it is illegal; and</text></item> <item id="HECAB1F393CB14247B2449CD4F0F9FC54"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>has reason to believe that the transferee will comply with all licensing and permit requirements for such hunting, trapping, or fishing; or</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H41ABFFC46010442D923ABD1CF97077AA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>while in the presence of the transferor.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0996D591634648F1A30F3F852F6EDE2A" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum> <clause id="H33C8A5D5A5E0422181A99EB991CEAF3A" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, the Attorney General may implement this subsection with regulations.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDC3ACC07F6D74789BF35D82E4ED53889" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Regulations promulgated under this paragraph may not include any provision—</text> <subclause id="H12B37551F70D4B888846BA623A1CCD61"><enum>(I)</enum><text>requiring licensees to facilitate transfers in accordance with subparagraph (A);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB4D71BF6A8834007BCA2E9BC86EFEE9E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>requiring persons not licensed under this chapter to keep records of background checks of ammunition transfers; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H000601C564564F41B1A3527291AA9FB1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>limiting the amount of any fee a licensee may charge to facilitate transfers in accordance with subparagraph (A).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H451FAE08C8E04768BD23A2BB705E03CD" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer to transfer possession of ammunition to another person who is not so licensed unless the importer, manufacturer, or dealer has provided such other person with a notice of the prohibition under subparagraph (A), and such other person has certified that such other person has been provided with this notice on a form prescribed by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HD88B4CC4D7CB430FADE74B0151D0C51D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header> <paragraph id="H62415AEB61B44C31B3B3065669C624D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Section 922</header><text>Section 922(y)(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended, in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>, (g)(5)(B), and (s)(3)(B)(v)(II)</quote> and inserting <quote>and (g)(5)(B)</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDFEB658D291442A9AA2AD008F55226C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consolidated and further continuing appropriations act, 2012</header><text>Section 511 of title V of division B of the Consolidated and Further Continuing Appropriations Act, 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901</external-xref> note) is amended by striking <quote>subsection 922(t)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subsection (s) or (t) of section 922</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H35B347568F3E4CEF8C383B61CD0F6678"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or any amendment made by this Act, shall be construed to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H51243B397B1E4B3BB30F86500EA3EE8C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>authorize the establishment, directly or indirectly, of a national firearms or ammunition registry; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84BA0982687C461DA1F2F256B2D6F818"><enum>(2)</enum><text>interfere with the authority of a State, under section 927 of title 18, United States Code, to enact a law on the same subject matter as this Act.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF4513032155E4FC79ED37995965C9D9B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

