<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H13D79E05F4584FE385FA30AC53CA163E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6718 IH: City of Ridgecrest Land Exchange Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6718</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231212">December 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001165">Mr. McCarthy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize, direct, expedite, and facilitate a land exchange in California, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3D252EDFF1FD4F9AA5D1C58B855B6E61" style="OLC"><section id="H3D79615F8EFC46B0BF45CC27AC2DC190" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>City of Ridgecrest Land Exchange Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HC20A0660F8E14DEDBB8CACC86A2CF77B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H9C8B089B19904B9DAD94C00A76D8EBC5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>City</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>City</term> means the City of Ridgecrest, California.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H812518DBCE384C97B6F4D8C64C746416"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal land</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal land</term> means the approximately 500 acres of Federal land generally depicted as <quote>Proposed BLM to City of Ridgecrest Land Transfer</quote> on the Federal land map. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CE2105953374C529558B035E7636751"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal land map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal land map</term> means the map titled <quote>Proposed Bureau of Land Management to City of Ridgecrest Land Exchange</quote> and dated October 5, 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00CBC708261A4371972E2871836AF80B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Non-Federal land</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>non-Federal land</term> means the approximately 640 acres of land in California, generally depicted as <quote>Proposed City of Ridgecrest to BLM Land Transfer</quote> on the non-Federal land map. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B6B9B9DDCAA41FC9471C7A54EECEEE3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Non-Federal land map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>non-Federal land map</term> means the map titled <quote>Proposed City of Ridgecrest to Bureau of Land Management Land Exchange</quote> and dated August 31, 2023. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA8137C3E95B468788792BE9E9B4BE46"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H2DCF4922F4704B269E5739096602C9FC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Land exchange</header><subsection id="H3464FF4D99564D03B9E1B3BD1E407BC4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the City offers to convey to the Secretary all right, title, and interest of the City in and to the non-Federal land, the Secretary shall accept the offer and, as soon as practicable, but not later than 1 year after receiving the offer from the City, convey to the City all right, title, and interest of the United States to the Federal land.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFB34D11E6C45472B83190F96021DFE2B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Title approval</header><paragraph id="HC3B2007847654449A4CA2918AD52C5CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title to the land to be exchanged under this section shall be in a format acceptable to the Secretary and the City.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE08071228F8D46AEB02498F633409469"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-Federal land</header><text>Title to the non-Federal land conveyed to the Secretary under this section shall conform to the title approval standards of the Attorney General of the United States applicable to land acquisitions by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6CE2D4E404C64D7496F0A7D76EDC64F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Maps, estimates, and descriptions</header><paragraph id="H42B5A5AE0A8A424FBBC06B2B58C0619A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Minor errors</header><text>The Secretary and the City may, by mutual agreement—</text><subparagraph id="H1E64AEC8C61F49A6A5B61D61F014B6B5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>make minor boundary adjustments to the Federal land and non-Federal land involved in the exchange; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E6873E800C04773B2ED8E0404846C07" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>correct any minor errors in any map, acreage estimate, or description of the land to be exchanged. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H099F0616AC9A4810ACE8B38B8AF22F4E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conflict</header><text>If there is a conflict between a map, an acreage estimate, or a description of land under this section, the map shall control unless the Secretary and City mutually agree otherwise. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAFA274F021F4F4A879134EEDBC3D596"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability of maps</header><text>The Federal land map and non-Federal land map shall be kept on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate office of the Bureau of Land Management.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H244FA00F833D4E5E9F0D61ED3935A989"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Survey</header><text>The exact acreage and legal description of the land exchanged under this section shall be determined by a survey satisfactory to the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H481F74FBF8DE4C05AA02CEFD6BC05589"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Costs of conveyance</header><text>As a condition for the land exchange under this section, the City shall pay the reasonable costs incurred by the Secretary for—</text><paragraph id="HC3BA7AC135E04FDA9B99685EFCB720B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the survey required by subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H276AE012A2404707B520F513706B6CF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any environmental analysis or administrative expenses related to the exchange.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BC7E523791849678BDE11E55C11DC77" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effect; Terms and conditions</header><text>The land exchange under this section—</text><paragraph id="H504E1CF0BD5F4AEABEA30E392FD9733B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not subject to section 206 of the Federal Land Policy Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1716">43 U.S.C. 1716</external-xref>); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF00216AF76A34F46A0ECA8574C05B172"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not affect the administration or ownership of any highways;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB379F341B2F44EAB8631C247243810F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not affect and shall further reserve for the continued and perpetual benefit of utilities all those existing rights on or to the land exchanged under this section, including any easements, and rights-of-way for electrical transmission and distribution poles, lines, and other appurtenances, regardless of whether such rights were created by patent, prescription, contract, or applicable law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9F77E0B5E5149F888C1D7808FC6AA58"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is subject to the condition that, with respect to Federal land conveyed to the City, the City shall, to the extent practicable, maintain access—</text><subparagraph id="H6DA6BCF5E9EF4BB689ABCA09843D626D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to all officially designated motorized routes depicted on the Federal land map; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69C7715115874FFC8530EC30EFD64F5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for non-motorized recreation activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3DB8600AF49548F0B8936E558C5F5B4B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Restriction on gaming</header><text>The Federal land conveyed to the City under this section shall not be eligible, or used, for any class II or class III gaming (as such terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Gaming Regulatory Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2703">25 U.S.C. 2703</external-xref>)). </text></subsection><subsection id="HE5E98A98DD7048D4A313EB7522D991DD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Management of land</header><text>Land acquired by the Secretary under this section shall become part of the Owens Peak Wilderness Area and be managed in accordance with the laws, rules, and regulations applicable to that wilderness area.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

