<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBEB71EE9C34241AB98AE46599F2B7505" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1711 IH: Rural America Health Corps Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1711</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a demonstration program to provide payments on eligible loans for individuals who are eligible for the National Health Service Corps Loan Repayment Program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9C4E7BA8A4774CE3B97AEFE148D38AB4" style="OLC"><section id="HB18F7BD9744042948090551F14C99A0A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural America Health Corps Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H273800D074C94DB3BDB4B168D1500475"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Health Service Corps rural provider loan repayment demonstration program</header><subsection id="H2E86D483FD144FF584FB338F531D3708"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H4FA1136364D947358275A4A73E9F2C2A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a demonstration program to provide payments on the principal of and interest on any eligible loan for eligible individuals described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B23302A47EA4D92A71A593CE6F786C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible individuals</header><text>To be eligible for payments under the program under this section, an individual shall—</text><subparagraph id="H9753991648134FF686A08822445CD872"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be eligible to participate in the Loan Repayment Program under section 338B of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254l-1">42 U.S.C. 254l–1</external-xref>), but not be participating in such Loan Repayment Program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04191D8C01B84D96BD1E07C7B138203D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agree to the requirements described in subsection (b)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C194933C0714130B4453562775FDB5C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedure</header><paragraph id="HFDD5E373BFCF431EBE72EE560EE0EA8D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>To be eligible to receive assistance under this section, an eligible individual shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2F4058ED7C394CC0B05AA125EDD7D56A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>comply with all rules and requirements described in section 338B of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254l-1">42 U.S.C. 254l–1</external-xref>), except for the period of obligated service described in subsection (f)(1)(B)(iv) of such section and as provided in paragraphs (2) and (3) of this subsection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F4BB9BF4D764C2196A358EAB9536DE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agree to a period of obligated service of 5 years of full-time employment in a health professional shortage area that is a rural area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B79F6AB8665436180579ABA23277296"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payments</header><subparagraph id="HF597DDB6D2DE4E31A38F4F2A22543F15"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Service in a rural area</header><text>The Secretary shall pay—</text><clause id="H14B77130C0A843589DA9FB47C993E77B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for each year of obligated service by an individual pursuant to an agreement under this section, <fraction>1/5</fraction> of the principal of and interest on each eligible loan, as determined by the Secretary, which is outstanding on the date the individual began service pursuant to the agreement; and</text></clause><clause id="H7C537F476A444E4E8C75E2AD6E29EDC3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for completion of the fifth and final year of such service, the remainder of such principal and interest.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88C2761E5B1645488AD9F27C760300B7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The total amount of payments under this section to any individual shall not exceed $200,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC55C134826CC446FA6ADCA98E5D0DAC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Breach</header><subparagraph id="H505932270B304ADE8343FFD41495CF0B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Liquidated damages formula</header><text>The Secretary may establish a liquidated damages formula to be used in the event of a breach of an agreement entered into under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B74047BA9A54E8FB79B3684DBF6D0EF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The failure by an individual to complete the full period of service obligated pursuant to such an agreement, taken alone, shall not constitute a breach of such agreement, so long as the individual completed in good faith the years of service for which payments were made to the individual under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB90C9CBFF464C8AB5055CAB5BA7D3B3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability of loan repayment program provisions</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, all provisions in subparts II and III of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/241">42 U.S.C. 241 et seq.</external-xref>) pertaining to the administration of, and other requirements with respect to, the Loan Repayment Program described in section 338B of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254l-1">42 U.S.C. 254l–1</external-xref>) shall apply to the demonstration program under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAB0F960303C84F7383CBFE17F1EB87D2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Designations</header><text>The demonstration program under this section, and any providers who are selected to participate in such program, shall not be considered by the Secretary in the designation of health professional shortage areas under section 332 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e</external-xref>) during fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB272B72F226143C98615FD4806EAD66C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that evaluates the demonstration program established under this section, including the effects of such program on health care access in rural areas.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE98CEE067254AC1B03095BD6C7656CE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Health professional shortage area</header><text>In this section, the term <term>health professional shortage area</term> has the meaning given such term in section 332 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H7A034B6A62AE450880D375FA26018E6A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section, $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

