<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFB8DC8B2A7642CA88E335D441377BB1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6562 IH: Restore Everyone’s Sleep Tonight Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6562</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231201">December 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a nighttime airport access restriction, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H374BD2ACE3104BA0B9462AF04FB4A793" style="OLC"><section id="HE325D28CC2D843D2A7649054D893C6F1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restore Everyone’s Sleep Tonight Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>REST Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9F86DA65B4144A32A9E1F27EE906D89A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Airport access restriction</header><subsection id="HD1027BFD84AA49B596D9C0B5762CD20C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law and except as provided in subsection (b), an airport may impose an access restriction between the hours of 10 p.m. and 7 a.m. for aircrafts.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC43613D943CD40F2B95C8208BE6BCFA0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Accommodations for certain flights</header><paragraph id="H034936F5AA034609BDEBD4625DF8C268"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Types of flights</header><text>In imposing an access restriction under subsection (a), an airport shall permit, within the hours of such access restriction, the operation of military, law enforcement, and Coast Guard flights.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F95548AB534EE388709280B79348B1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptional circumstances</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In imposing an access restriction under subsection (a), an airport may not prohibit access for—</text><subparagraph id="H436C6755E7CF4C0B80AF5E6A4A330E49"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a flight that is scheduled to arrive or depart during hours not covered by the access restriction imposed under subsection (a) and which arrives or departs during such access restriction due solely to weather or the safe operation of the aircraft, including compliance with any safety-related requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4B399D64CA547ADBFDC0489B900FC31"><enum>(B)</enum><text>emergency flights;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E67C19171564DA497FCE578452BBD3E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>flights to evacuate natural disasters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6946C0F7EABE4D6AB5995B18013097B2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>flights for the purpose of the preservation of life, health, or safety.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H590052AE5D37408A85F72686FE5C34F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><paragraph id="H631FBD7FCA1A4802A1F754731CDC1769"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An airport may impose a noise deterrence penalty on an air carrier or aircraft operator for a violation of the access restriction imposed under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC8B717C6D7341D684CD0B807CA8C3F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of penalty</header><text>An airport applying penalties under this subsection shall set a base level for a noise deterrence penalty under paragraph (1) at an amount sufficient to deter future violations of the access restriction imposed under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F8616E7464C4E91A1C4F68478E535CA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Increase in penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The airport applying penalties under this subsection may increase a penalty for a violation of the access restriction imposed under subsection (a) above the base amount set under paragraph (2) if an aircraft takeoff or landing resulted in noise to residents of any unit of local government exceeding 80 dBA, as evidenced by a noise monitoring device recognized as authoritative by the airport.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AB63E52845D4E06B99814C22238D7BB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Considerations for a penalty increase</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining whether to increase the penalty above the base amount set under paragraph (2), an airport may consider the following:</text><subparagraph id="HDDD8A3D5E4764DAEAE1777FC3D95DF39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The certified noise level and engine model of the aircraft.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2C09D0DB22547918E52B41DC887C49A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The time of violation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26E9858092374FB3B4ADE2229517B15F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Repeat violations by the air carrier or aircraft operator.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB525550FD3740ADA0DD192D373D250C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any other criteria that the airport determines reflects the noise impacts to residents of the unit of local government impacted by the violation of subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50E2C58A615B4C328E055B02C2F94B8A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of penalty</header><subparagraph id="HB22A111456B3454CA3EBE0C44BF84810"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C), penalties collected for a violation of the access restriction imposed under subsection (a) shall be remitted to the unit of local government that experienced the impact of the noise deterrence violation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51E21C6F9D9A433E93F8F95AA44CFB00"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Multiple units of local government</header><text>If multiple units of local government are impacted by a violation of the access restriction imposed under subsection (a), an airport shall remit the penalty to the jurisdictions impacted in equal parts.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21CB059ABC96455CB9914670666123C9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An airport may deduct reasonable costs of administering a noise deterrence penalty from a penalty collected under this paragraph before remitting the penalty under subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H814042F961524453A976E0C0A95DFE99"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any action taken in carrying out this section, the airport is not required to seek the approval or comment of the Federal Aviation Administration or the Secretary of Transportation, any air carrier or aircraft operator or any other entity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6124C36A0B1F4B4FB964ED48190667BE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition of weather</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>weather</quote> is defined as the state of the atmosphere at a location or along a route over the short-term.</text></subsection><subsection id="H830F8387242944BBBA4EB9B82D470AB1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definition of access restriction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, an access restriction is a prohibition on the landing or takeoff of aircraft.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

