<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H7C0170DBD3DC493582E634A35E489762" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6245 RH: Holding Iranian Leaders Accountable Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 273</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6245</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–334]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor> and <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on November 6, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Treasury to report on financial institutions’ involvement with officials of the Iranian Government, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HBA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H99F2C457426A40D5B5F552CF0DC6B4BC"><section id="H524542931F784544902C6D89FE91C5AC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Holding Iranian Leaders Accountable Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDFDCD6457595402B8BE3A03049B3BEEA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H467F9C8CEE5C47849264E3B67F5434BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Iran is characterized by high levels of official and institutional corruption, and substantial involvement by Iran’s security forces, particularly the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC), in the economy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H365793639E6144AFB29821082833CEA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Department of Treasury in 2019 designated the Islamic Republic of Iran’s financial sector as a jurisdiction of primary money laundering concern, concluding, <quote>Iran has developed covert methods for accessing the international financial system and pursuing its malign activities, including misusing banks and exchange houses, operating procurement networks that utilize front or shell companies, exploiting commercial shipping, and masking illicit transactions using senior officials, including those at the Central Bank of Iran (CBI).</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAC43897FAC145A89B93E987129C636F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In June 2019, the Financial Action Task Force (FATF) urged all jurisdictions to require increased supervisory examination for branches and subsidiaries of financial institutions based in Iran. The FATF later called upon its members to introduce enhanced relevant reporting mechanisms or systematic reporting of financial transactions, and require increased external audit requirements, for financial groups with respect to any of their branches and subsidiaries located in Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BBB91EF5639417D8A1157F89644B985"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the State Department’s <quote>Country Reports on Terrorism</quote> in 2021, <quote>Iran continued to be the leading state sponsor of terrorism, facilitating a wide range of terrorist and other illicit activities around the world. Regionally, Iran supported acts of terrorism in Bahrain, Iraq, Lebanon, Syria, and Yemen through proxies and partner groups such as Hizballah and Hamas.</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H64F3F7D836BC4FD59A0CCDFE606DE05C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on financial institutions and assets connected to certain Iranian officials</header><subsection id="HE606798FA6164651A06E5237572263B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Financial institutions and assets report</header><paragraph id="HE29F34D4EE544419AA761B35B8234F3B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 2 years thereafter, the President shall submit a report to the appropriate Members of Congress containing—</text><subparagraph id="H7A2FBADDAB5748B6B6B287DEDE86C290"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the estimated total funds or assets that are under direct or indirect control by each of the natural persons described under subsection (b), and a description of such funds or assets, except that the President may limit coverage of the report to not fewer than 5 of such natural persons in order to meet the submission deadline described under this paragraph;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99ABEF83F5294D16BE9A16310409413E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of how such funds or assets were acquired, and how they have been used or employed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EAD5C96183B419599EA5005F5BF4927"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of any non-Iranian financial institutions that—</text><clause id="H54E4FB5CBAF14C559C968D14E82BE9D9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maintain an account in connection with funds or assets described in subparagraph (A); or</text></clause><clause id="H7BEDB9AAA292439386A2A3044684F4C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>knowingly provide significant financial services to a natural person covered by the report; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6861C31D46254020B398CEF2CC7F96D0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of any illicit or corrupt means employed to acquire or use such funds or assets.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07BFB6287022446B839CBC5AEB12F63F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text>The requirements described under paragraph (1) may not be applied with respect to a natural person or a financial institution, as the case may be, if the President determines:</text><subparagraph id="H3EDADA001C614202BF6822DBF6A7C1E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The funds or assets described under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (1) were acquired through legal or noncorrupt means.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63F45E54DC954C06A23B4399DCAB2BF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The natural person has agreed to provide significant cooperation to the United States for an important national security or law enforcement purpose with respect to Iran.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0506090108874A1CA378D038ED68978B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A financial institution that would otherwise be listed in the report required by paragraph (1) has agreed to—</text><clause id="H3D1BB0999A784352BF22089BE07D7199"><enum>(i)</enum><text>no longer maintain an account described under subparagraph (C)(i) of paragraph (1);</text></clause><clause id="H126C4674C0BF4197BA9CAE395EACD027"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>no longer provide significant financial services to a natural person covered by the report; or</text></clause><clause id="HD63F45C11FF549BBACE58177AEE5696E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provide significant cooperation to the United States for an important national security or law enforcement purpose with respect to Iran.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A913F4B0EA043578E6B2A209D82F5AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The President may waive for up to 1 year at a time any requirement under paragraph (1) with respect to a natural person or a financial institution after reporting in writing to the appropriate Members of Congress that the waiver is in the national interest of the United States, with a detailed explanation of the reasons therefor.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5ACB58472C2D413393876557CEF2936B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Persons described</header><text>The natural persons described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H13CAD3ECFE2047F8841B2C6F0D1865AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Supreme Leader of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE19C01C326574AF3838DE30E312BC0C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The President of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0A7F41AB09C482583F75410454D1B59"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The members of the Council of Guardians.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C7BB1C641414E7982169DE2576A33DD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The members of the Expediency Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H855279E70F7D48B5B78C437C158510F6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Minister of Intelligence and Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H685E996EB9A54959ABEE3E030EF3D16F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Commander and the Deputy Commander of the IRGC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FEFDD4D388943FB9DD150A132903135"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Commander and the Deputy Commander of the IRGC Ground Forces.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A7B5A55FCB04DD1B09B40F7FA6542BC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Commander and the Deputy Commander of the IRGC Aerospace Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9831257E6AF84C67906BBB41CF8978D4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Commander and the Deputy Commander of the IRGC Navy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D1BB52A9C374C9A882702BA40B6413E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The Commander of the Basij-e-Mostaz’afin.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97DFDD8839B0470BB9F5BE14FA5D397A"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The Commander of the Qods Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H955E672F29AF40B399F665405FE6F8EB"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The Commander in Chief of the Police Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56B17504478F48B1AC2BA7187D6D9250"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The head of the IRGC Joint Staff.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2588FAC781404C71A19AC7D6F918B525"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The Commander of the IRGC Intelligence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50438692F5F14C66B9BB7BB30B63C4E0"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The head of the IRGC Imam Hussein University.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24E69D245C1647C985960B916AA31A3A"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The Supreme Leader’s Representative at the IRGC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H521538841D5B49AA98CF6593121C8FE8"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The Chief Executive Officer and the Chairman of the IRGC Cooperative Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A368916B96A4BE6B86EC9CC620BCBB5"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The Commander of the Khatam-al-Anbia Construction Head Quarter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H443CC64BD0E848509150228BCEB445F4"><enum>(19)</enum><text>The Chief Executive Officer of the Basij Cooperative Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE40353ADA3F41EB84567E012B856B19"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The head of the Political Bureau of the IRGC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AB6F9D26C3F4E9CB0B5441351198076"><enum>(21)</enum><text>The senior leadership as determined by the President of the following groups:</text><subparagraph id="HDDF96BA6643D4F5882E99398D3E1C145"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Hizballah.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4152FCEF04D74841ADE9336BA1C14438"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Hamas.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA104B39751F4567B041F38901DB036A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Palestinian Islamic Jihad.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H305A5499F5254BAF9346EF9A325D9297"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Kata’ib Hizballah.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3C5389989DA4DC3BB842C3A7666B383"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form of report; public availability</header><paragraph id="H175C80902F8D4764BEF670A04D0C9010"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) and any waiver under subsection (a)(3) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCCBA836F62B406A834F22114CE8CB69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make the unclassified portion of such report public if the Secretary notifies the appropriate Members of Congress that the publication is in the national interest of the United States and would substantially promote—</text><subparagraph id="HDD061885EFB64A07ACA984E8CD91B503"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deterring or sanctioning official corruption in Iran;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DB48AECD6E848E7B1A725E7B245CB8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holding natural persons or financial institutions listed in the report accountable to the people of Iran;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H464BFCE26E7B41EBBD597A0FCCFA4265"><enum>(C)</enum><text>combating money laundering or the financing of terrorism; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H749043373CAC4377858B57A42CAF6B44"><enum>(D)</enum><text>achieving any other strategic objective with respect to the Government of Iran.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7EDCCDA26C2B44E0A25DC48B71B26A0F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Format of publicly available reports</header><text>If the Secretary makes the unclassified portion of a report public pursuant to paragraph (2), the Secretary shall make it available to the public on the website of the Department of the Treasury—</text><subparagraph id="H3695FFE48CB64E93AAB96020F6EE7B0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in English, Farsi, Arabic, and Azeri; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3703A1F3D98643309E41F2780442A15E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in precompressed, easily downloadable versions that are made available in all appropriate formats.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA55BE5E870FF463E87A05456C6DF1698"><enum>4.</enum><header>Restrictions on certain financial institutions</header><subsection id="HCF93233B2DC048A9A8981BE63829C163"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the date that is 90 days after submitting a report described under section 3(a)(1), the Secretary shall undertake the following with respect to a financial institution that is described under section 3(a)(1)(C) and listed in the report:</text><paragraph id="HDBC7218288B446C3B7609492188CF096"><enum>(1)</enum><text>If the financial institution is a United States financial institution, require the closure of any account described in section 3(a)(1)(C)(i), and prohibit the provision of significant financial services, directly or indirectly, to a natural person covered by the report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H876C62E993F64EAA8CACFC35CAE9C56B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>If the financial institution is a foreign financial institution, actively seek the closure of any account described in section 3(a)(1)(C)(i), and the cessation of significant financial services to a natural person covered by the report, using any existing authorities of the Secretary, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H815B90EAAA144899806C8018235B63A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Suspension</header><text>The Secretary may suspend the application of subsection (a) with respect to a financial institution upon reporting to the appropriate Members of Congress that the suspension is in the national interest of the United States, with a detailed explanation of the reasons therefor.</text></subsection></section><section id="H68B712FFC35E4BF1ACE569F17B0EF9E5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Exceptions for national security; implementation authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The following activities shall be exempt from requirements under sections 3 and 4:</text><paragraph id="HA258CACEACA3444A977FF8DB98451892"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>), or to any authorized intelligence activities of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BF9665BA66A4221B880D492B135EAD6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The admission of an alien to the United States if such admission is necessary to comply with United States obligations under the Agreement between the United Nations and the United States of America regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, or under the Convention on Consular Relations, done at Vienna April 24, 1963, and entered into force March 19, 1967, or other applicable international obligations of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H617FB2C4B56D4C13B43B0A25B4681950"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The conduct or facilitation of a transaction for the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices to Iran or for the provision of humanitarian assistance to the people of Iran, including engaging in a financial transaction relating to humanitarian assistance or for humanitarian purposes or transporting goods or services that are necessary to carry out operations relating to humanitarian assistance or humanitarian purposes.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4B709AA65D2A4593B9A2CE875ABE9AB6"><enum>6.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall have no force or effect on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H1447BD7CF2E94AB48F126D693A822714"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53C1F8BD76104C06BB0D37A4D5E604A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>30 days after the Secretary reports in writing to the appropriate Members of Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="H5F3F49D5BBE046FDB204A20C6E5A09D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Iran is not a jurisdiction of primary money laundering concern; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB99D5078A5FF42D49989AA65A3381DAE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Government of Iran is providing significant cooperation to the United States for the purpose of preventing acts of international terrorism, or for the promotion of any other strategic objective that is important to the national interest of the United States, as specified in the report by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HF2B7C1CAA9084A8EAE0E3518898C3857"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act:</text><paragraph id="H99516418E541498F82294736EC937814"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate Members of congress</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate Members of Congress</quote> means the Speaker and Minority Leader of the House of Representatives, the Majority Leader and Minority Leader of the Senate, the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, and the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE7C8673DDFA49ACAF38FD85D1E10D55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Financial institution</header><text>The term <quote>financial institution</quote> means a United States financial institution or a foreign financial institution.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA16A219B737149CFBE82BE4CE3E0B02A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign financial institution</header><text>The term <quote>foreign financial institution</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 561.308 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H490129AFE7C54D8B8B16739B9225BC91"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Funds</header><text>The term <quote>funds</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H150B2C2EAA4344F1A541B36E5F69FC37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cash;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB796DAA8FA4C4F509571CA8A135BB0D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>equity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA812E5C1B1E042E787596EC4340963ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other asset whose value is derived from a contractual claim, including bank deposits, bonds, stocks, a security as defined in section 2(a) of the Securities Act of 1933 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/77b">15 U.S.C. 77b(a)</external-xref>), or a security or an equity security as defined in section 3(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H501328E6E6B04CF9B5AE3111A4817E97"><enum>(D)</enum><text>anything else that the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H16F0CE7CB0B546FFB6B7A6903B183C7E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text>The term <quote>knowingly</quote> with respect to conduct, a circumstance, or a result, means that a person has actual knowledge, or should have known, of the conduct, the circumstance, or the result.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7603D46A2468449AA1C189330062189E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Treasury.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC76D02438384EB69EE900CA10E78501"><enum>(7)</enum><header>United states financial institution</header><text>The term <quote>United States financial institution</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>U.S. financial institution</quote> under section 561.309 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

