<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0995CFE173D44BBA8E0CE492B5DA9A37" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2737 IH: Stop the Invasion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2737</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the President to suspend the entry of aliens into the United States when the average number of <quote>encounters</quote> exceeds a certain number, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC2FB0B8FE4EB42AC923275AFE025302C" style="OLC"><section id="H916E7E26F79040D698F511DF3EC7A7E1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop the Invasion Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF2CC54942CBE4C958A7A0E8EF06ED27C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HA09E7D6F0C4041749ECDF4DA250AB31A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The U.S. Customs and Border Protection Agency (in this Act, referred to as <quote>CBP</quote>) <quote>encountered</quote> 251,978 illegal aliens at the Southwest border in December 2022, the highest monthly total ever recorded; this represented 10 consecutive months of over 200,000 illegal alien <quote>encounters</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF61F344B11C049579A202556501A4578"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Since the creation of the Department of Homeland Security, the number of monthly <quote>encounters</quote> had never crossed the 200,000 threshold; the Biden administration is responsible for the 6th highest and 8 of the 10 highest months ever recorded.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66C486776E5A4F48A3E92344D17704BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While January 2023 <quote>encounters</quote> fell below 200,000, that number reached 156,274, a record high for the month of January.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F91ED3D7C524D6C8B9FA16B6F19119F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">February 2023 saw 154,998 <quote>encounters</quote> at the Southwest border, the 24th consecutive month that <quote>encounters</quote> exceeded 150,000. Nearly half of the February total stemmed from expulsions under title 42.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H721AD14803884BB28CD9693D8274367D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In fiscal year 2022, CBP <quote>encountered</quote> nearly 2,380,000 illegal aliens at the Southwest border (excluding a reported 600,000 known <quote>gotaways</quote>) and more than 2,700,000 nationwide. CBP data indicates that from February 1, 2021, through February 28, 2023, nearly 4.85 million illegal aliens have been <quote>encountered</quote> at the United States Southwest border.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7B1F89E3F814D5A99F7445EC3B1419E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the first 5 months of fiscal year 2023, CBP has <quote>encountered</quote> 1,029,953 illegal aliens at the Southwest border, putting the Department of Homeland Security on pace to <quote>encounter</quote> nearly 2,500,000 illegal aliens this fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA316DCA7EC0A478D838060AEFA638B38"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to congressional testimony provided by U.S. Border Patrol Chief Raul Ortiz on March 15, 2023, the number of known <quote>gotaways</quote> since January 20, 2021, has exceeded 1,300,000, bringing the total number of aliens attempting to cross the Southwest border well in excess of 6,000,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F213DF837D44ACA8B092C8174E31FA7"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Six million is a greater population than the populations of 31 of the 50 States. It is more than the populations of North Dakota, South Dakota, Rhode Island, Alaska, Vermont, Delaware, and the District of Columbia combined.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H083DF15AFACB4859AF861F1B143CC2F4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The ongoing border crisis has inflicted harrowing costs on the welfare of women and children. The number of unaccompanied alien children <quote>encountered</quote> by CBP at the Southwest border in fiscal year 2017 was 48,681. In fiscal year 2022, that number stood at 152,057, a 212 percent increase. Hundreds of thousands of vulnerable children have been <quote>encountered</quote>, trafficked, and smuggled across the Southwest border in the 2 years since President Biden took office, representing hundreds of children every day.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7430A8136B543B2A5D762150FF70F0A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to CBP, migrant deaths at the Southwest border of the United States totaled 856 in fiscal year 2022, the deadliest year on record.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1491D1AF0C0840DC8FB0698B8F640B0A"><enum>(11)</enum><text>A May 2017 report from Doctors Without Borders indicated that out of the number of women surveyed, nearly one-third had been sexually assaulted as they approached the Southern border.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D25C22EEE484044AB0B8904C221C733"><enum>(12)</enum><text>According to Drug Enforcement Agency statistics, over 50,600,000 fentanyl pills were seized in 2022, including over 10,800 pounds of fentanyl powder; these fentanyl seizures are enough to kill over 379,000,000 people. Recent data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention indicate that 107,735 Americans died of a drug overdose in the 12-month period ending July 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DD3E9CCB61346FEAC1B8E74809683FB"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Due to rampant drug trafficking at our Southern border, the leading cause of death for Americans aged 18–45 can now be attributable to fentanyl overdoses; in 2020 and 2021, fentanyl was responsible for killing more Americans in this age group than COVID–19, car accidents, cancer, and suicide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H634733AD9BE945DB902A9942F3BF4D0D"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to CBP data, in the first five months of fiscal year 2023, 106,000 pounds of drugs were seized at the Southwest border, including 11,000 pounds of fentanyl. The first five months of fiscal year 2023 have seen a 179.3 percent increase in fentanyl seizures over the same time frame in fiscal year 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9151ABE153CF49738425A030717AF54E"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The historic crisis at the Southwest border demands decisive action on the part of Congress.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB0681644B2C64F42AC4A8CF019664DB0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Moratorium</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 212(f) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H85DDB959AD0F4782ABDA214AD2E0E7DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Whenever</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(1)</enum-in-header></header-in-text> Whenever</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80DC7B0DB4F545A29141A79AD5E0FF6A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4ABFDE8D5D5B4BDFB400E7EEB2C41311" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H826B6B151C1E400787B8EB34E4ADAC5A"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6BAF9C61E79F44D19508872B9A0186E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if the average number of apprehensions and findings of inadmissible aliens documented by U.S. Customs and Border Protection exceeds an average of 30,000 per month over the most recent 12-month period, the President shall suspend the entry of covered aliens until the monthly average number of apprehensions of illegal aliens is less than 30,000.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6891A8218B75466A8E60876172505688" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of this paragraph, the number of apprehensions and findings of inadmissible aliens shall be the total number of U.S. Customs and Border Protection enforcement actions taken under this Act and section 362 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD90040A149434A18AE56671879A027B6" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <quote>covered alien</quote> means an alien seeking entry to the United States who is inadmissible under subsection (a)(6) or subsection (a)(7).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

