<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB27DF4AFED52421F8E7A0EC615FE01F1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 443 IH: Enhancing Detection of Human Trafficking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 443</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230120">January 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Labor to train certain employees of Department of Labor how to effectively detect and assist law enforcement in preventing human trafficking during the course of their official duties, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H427EE8F9358940819F7CCA9AF29B7E9A" style="OLC"><section id="H98CDDBBF40DD4BBFACAB4182832BE6D9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Enhancing Detection of Human Trafficking Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCF7FE0D6315343C4B085819A6F895093"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition of human trafficking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act the term <term>human trafficking</term> means any act or practice described in paragraph (11) of section 103 of the Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7102">22 U.S.C. 7102</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="HE090ED0A48134389B7F36D8A9F9AD85E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Training for Department personnel to identify human trafficking</header><subsection id="H1A81FEC22B0547F893390938A0747B00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall implement a program to provide training and periodic continuing education to employees of the Department of Labor who the Secretary considers appropriate, on how to effectively, during the course of the official duties of such employees, detect and assist criminal law enforcement in detecting human trafficking.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEBF666406EA344CA9706A5A8E991FFAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Training and continuing education described</header><text>The training and continuing education provided under the program referred to in subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="H83D75210A4A042449E89A4C9592938B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may be conducted through in-class or virtual learning capabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA98E217E90CC48CCA64F2C14ECBEA758"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H536AB0FA5E3849A3A4737F062C754CD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>training or continuing education that— </text><clause id="HF4F5F1BBD9D0487597993B5275C031BD" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is most appropriate for a particular location or professional environment in which the employees receiving such training or continuing education perform their official duties;</text></clause><clause id="H31B44873327B44BEA9A95FB0C9D0C96F" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>covers topics determined by the Secretary of Labor to appropriately reflect current trends and best practices for such location or environment; and</text></clause><clause id="HB6DB47EA7FA4471EBF04FD7971337E13" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes—</text><subclause id="H3CB7E7BDCA684D3B8CF40804264BFADD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the provision of current information on matters related to the detection of human trafficking to the extent relevant to the official duties of such employees, and consistent with privacy laws;</text></subclause><subclause id="H44503EEEECA2494180E76262AAF36091"><enum>(II)</enum><text>methods for identifying suspected victims of human trafficking and parties who may be suspected of the trafficking activity; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HFFB3DF3F60B94B1D84083753204A9731"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a clear course of action for referring potential cases of human trafficking to the Department of Justice and other appropriate authorities; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBC6658B3C1A48A1BB58DBF01E889F62"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an evaluation of the training or continuing education by such employees after the completion of such training or education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF814B6C828BC40D28A344FB45BF7174E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the Secretary of Labor first implements the program under section 3(a), and each year thereafter, the Secretary of Labor shall report to the Committee on Education and Labor of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate on—</text><paragraph id="HCD99D2D7E56D40F9A618B0A380883A18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the training and continuing education provided under the program for the preceding year, including—</text><subparagraph id="H516FF3CA27974512A3DD88A92241A591"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an evaluation (including the overall effectiveness) of such training and continuing education; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78CFE08265B64075B9CBD0C2B0355DEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of individuals who have completed such training or continuing education; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FBB2BA555D94830804DAE3E06B53485"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of cases referred during the preceding year to the Department of Justice and other appropriate authorities by employees of the Department of Labor in which human trafficking was suspected, and the metrics used by such employees to accurately measure and track the response of the Department of Labor to such cases.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

