<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59D8F031177E4427BDDC26DD4CF690C7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5530 IH: VA Emergency Transportation Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5530</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230918">September 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for certain limitations to the authority of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to make changes to the Department of Veterans Affairs rate of payment or reimbursement provided for transportation of veterans and other eligible individuals on special modes of transportation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAE42A1FEF1CB4E8FB3CB51842E6A21A5" style="OLC"><section id="H6C7D6D3DF11B4030AD37E72B96868117" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Emergency Transportation Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5BA5168518014567818D6868A7BD7E6C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority for changes to Department of Veterans Affairs rate of payment or reimbursement provided for transportation of veterans and other eligible individuals on special modes of transportation</header><subsection id="H66F4AB6DFB834E088FFDF18B93C55F5C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may not change the rate of payment or reimbursement provided for the transportation of a veteran or other eligible individual on a special mode of transportation, as in effect on January 1, 2023, unless—</text><paragraph id="H29FDD8066BF94ABEA6CD7647B28F14F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such change would increase the rate of such payment or reimbursement; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CEF58FD542742F98955DD9E807F971E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>before the effective date of such change, the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="HBA3C97667A5C4A46ACAE089088326247"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducts a thorough review and analysis of—</text><clause id="H126B5951F8004373A8B85C1128F73E7D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the economic effect of the change on the Department of Veterans Affairs;</text></clause><clause id="H71746E57E19C4BA5A5F0169885D7B27F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the economic effect of the change on the industry associated with the special mode of transportation that would be affected by the change; and</text></clause><clause id="HD116E79997B248FBB4678F4079240745"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the effect of the change on access to care for veterans;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CD5F4A2FA8C4289B278A65A9033BA5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develops a formal process to ensure that any change made to such rate does not reduce the access to care for veterans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E7CB663E1394584BB032D310FD61717"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensures that the new rate reflects, at a minimum, the actual cost of such transportation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3256FF008CD6478DAE4CA44F445DCD75"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out any review under subsection (a)(2)(A) and develop any process under subsection (a)(2)(B) in consultation with a committee made up of each of the following, who shall be appointed by the Secretary:</text><paragraph id="H347F74325C2941C7BECA44C7C5CA02F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Relevant industry experts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4861670F16EB45D9B06A370764785A9C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Representatives of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DFB81D3ABA24828B59CDC6FC6344C9C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Department employees with subject matter expertise in transportation, access to care, integrated veteran care, rural veterans, Native American veterans, and other matters determine appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8F7F661A3B04CEE8637377098375228"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Representatives of veteran service organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD4FC7A23FFD94C18B857F8BB94B9E432"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Template and process for affected contracts</header><text>Not later than two years before the effective date of any change made to the rate of payment or reimbursement for special modes of transportation pursuant to subsection (a) that affects the rate payable under any contract of the Department, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H1B1E52DB0C5F4AF79EDBC01253460317"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a template and a standardized process for entering into and making changes to rates in effect under such contract;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8140FBF71ACC41EFB8FFFF2DB2E327D5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue guidance about the use of such template and process within the Department and across the industry associated with special modes of transportation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H747D8DA9BBFB4307B935068F14C6B58F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report that includes a description of the template and process.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD3C0FDA314A4801A9365C990F31CDFE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special mode of transportation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>special mode of transportation</quote>—</text><paragraph id="H596849D800194D5792F52C01942B864E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means an ambulance, ambulette, air ambulance, wheelchair van, or other mode of transportation specially designed to transport disabled persons; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39B63BDD45C6448CAD9F713791C6E7DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not include—</text><subparagraph id="H130326AAC8184E8DB821FD336715078F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a mode of transportation not specifically designed to transport disabled persons, such as a bus, subway, taxi, train, or airplane; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93FD25C571884AF9BAD0CE594216F642"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a modified, privately owned vehicle, with special adaptive equipment or that is capable of transporting disabled persons.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

