<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC09CC05BA5DC4932952E7838122DC952" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6232 IH: Coordination for Soil Carbon Research and Monitoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6232</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an interagency committee on soil carbon sequestration research, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H95F4EA688FDB4D979A86CEC3F11937BB" style="OLC"><section id="HE279F76D386843BBA499DDA48D1864E3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Coordination for Soil Carbon Research and Monitoring Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H52670E2F7A7F4CC1AF3C9BD883B785C9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Soil carbon research and monitoring</header><subsection id="H39447FBC34E048F88755C336EB73156D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Interagency committee</header><paragraph id="H1F37F022FBE14AE099EBF6F386081DBB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established an interagency committee to be known as the <quote>Interagency Committee on Soil Carbon Research</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Interagency Committee</quote>), to be led by the Office of Science and Technology Policy and composed of representatives from the following:</text><subparagraph id="H73CF6C63CDD2462C958F5E140A7CCE94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Department of Agriculture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8680EDD8EAC4D138999934E7CF4365E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7170BBBAD0F40C0B74ED5A3478A4606"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of the Interior.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03E832CEBF28418BA55F3347E0AD9CE2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Environmental Protection Agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73063873E1FE40C2972A6D6A9FC42B03"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The United States Geological Survey.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27859AA244B14AC18C8ACC59343AE1F5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC8A7E6A26146BBB0FB929F68291441"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The National Science Foundation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94CB30343EB144C8B34D08AAE3AD63F8"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H748338DE6B7C439BA18EFF1412DFA053"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The White House Environmental Justice Advisory Council.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4AB6D47F7A24F5E9C1B53E01E17955D"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0EBB9F3F8D14757890B988D2B20B79D" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other Federal agencies as the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E8082498A734FACB5FFF042F6CB9F50"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Interagency Committee shall—</text><subparagraph id="H8152BEB5FE6C436292546E92C4D636FA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a cross-agency strategic plan for Federal research, development, and deployment regarding soil carbon sequestration sampling and measurement methodologies, measurement and monitoring technologies, and community needs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H153C51AA612E422AAB021FC4AD7261D3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">propose roles and responsibilities to each Federal agency to advance soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75A99E0DB57047F0B3F2AFAB6E1FEDB8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>oversee working groups established under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF81F1E0791014F1982C6B1FD8324FDD8" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as appropriate, seek to consult with Federal agencies and with the Office of Management and Budget regarding planning and budget review, respectively, concerning matters relating to Federal soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AE1B906B89047B18DF53FE29521BB65" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress a baseline report on existing soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H739AA8E0225140D6896A08634C26DB73" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress progress reports on soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring activities at one-, three-, and five-year intervals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70A9091224B84EC88771A0F58556DAA7" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>encourage coordination between Federal agencies and evaluate soil carbon sequestration monitoring activities, data collection on soil carbon and greenhouse gas (GHG) fluxes, and long-term storage protocols for soil carbon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78AE8D3CDF694C4B96154AA7ED62AD26" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>support comprehensive reporting on soil carbon sequestration related activities based on a standardized integration of existing and new relevant data collection efforts across Federal agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF76C1075278C47B3A5F829BF15B39147"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">share recommendations for review and input with soil science experts from academia, private industry, and nonprofit organizations that represent the geographic, operational, and demographic diversity of United States agriculture; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB71CB887D5243D6A3DB4C8500F3996C" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>designate a member of the Interagency Committee to collaborate with Federal agency heads on soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H14284323978F43B4870B13DA322B4A30"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Working groups</header><subparagraph id="HE08D74535A204100B7E4C5E6A29DF1D5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Interagency Committee may, as appropriate and necessary, establish working groups to coordinate on cross-cutting priorities on soil carbon research as determined by the Interagency Committee, including relating to the following:</text><clause id="H37D3CCF69EA948FA8969000A7481F65A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Monitoring, Reporting, and Verification (MRV).</text></clause><clause id="HF43BC99124994B238E67337D92E1EBB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data collection and management, with a focus on measurement standards, standards for use of new technologies, and data architecture for accessibility across agencies.</text></clause><clause id="HBC71B231FD074FC0A65A74A2BC462921"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Fundamental research, including regarding soil carbon dynamics, plant breeding, and soil amendments.</text></clause><clause id="H375064E0479E451D8F438E469D53F537"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Community engagement in research development and dissemination of results, particularly with historically underserved and disadvantaged groups.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35141A540F9548069F2AC7DEB18A32D7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>Working groups established pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="HBF88B3ADF1EE445BBD13E3394B7A03C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify ongoing research and monitoring efforts on soil carbon at each Federal agency represented in each such working group;</text></clause><clause id="H36F1C2D388CB4421A997ACA15DFD5AAF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify gaps in current efforts on soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring;</text></clause><clause id="HD24F7D62F9B14A678373D3363CD1DFCA" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">outline current collaboration across agencies on soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring;</text></clause><clause id="HA7A0CF7BB51F41CDBB30DFD5D555CC8E" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">propose coordinated projects and budget requests to advance the field of soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring;</text></clause><clause id="HA7BE0DB9403B411AAE81968DDCE0975E" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage with and conduct outreach to agricultural communities and producers, particularly those historically underserved, to ensure soil carbon sequestration research and monitoring is rooted in stakeholder engagement and on-the-ground perspectives;</text></clause><clause id="H5A8DA6E2B6A7424A94CBDB4CFC745DA7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage with research and extension soil scientists, private industry, nonprofit organizations, and other interdisciplinary soil science expert groups to ensure that recommendations are informed by the best available science; and</text></clause><clause id="H7B61336F41444E3C8BB64012931A5EA0"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>collaborate on the development of standardized monitoring of the long-term carbon and environmental impacts of soil carbon sequestration research.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85F6B67A255C43E5881BAFCBEDB46623" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

