<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3D909AFB13DD4841B2B0C7176751F946" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4141 IH: To provide that certain communications projects are not subject to requirements to prepare certain environmental or historical preservation reviews, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4141</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000469">Mr. Fulcher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that certain communications projects are not subject to requirements to prepare certain environmental or historical preservation reviews, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B552610EDDC4A08A1AF27B996B6F9EF" style="OLC"><section id="H5E4408340B1D49E79A767596C584AA74" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Application of NEPA and NHPA to certain communications projects</header><subsection id="HEC291841A66C4AE88123C565EEB8B7D1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H3E17E81283234FAD8503074817738936"><enum>(1)</enum><header>NEPA exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal authorization with respect to a covered project may not be considered a major Federal action under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A75CAAE82CB43888F2C39D24983D745"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National Historic Preservation Act exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered project may not be considered an undertaking under section 300320 of title 54, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F7726F00D75401E93EE41692E1D2AB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant of easement on Federal property</header><paragraph id="H62B351AB4E2043D9A203C37CE8F4382A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>NEPA exemption</header><text>A Federal authorization with respect to a covered easement for a communications facility may not be considered a major Federal action under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>), if—</text><subparagraph id="HD8ADDAAF292F4FCDB779CD7B082207AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a covered easement has previously been granted for another communications facility or a utility facility with respect to the same building or other property owned by the Federal Government; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89F173380550429A8BCF53EE9D5958B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the covered easement is for a communications facility in a public right-of-way.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D427C53AEBE4643AE1CAE7A1475D0D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National Historic Preservation Act exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered easement for a communications facility may not be considered an undertaking under section 300320 of title 54, United States Code, if—</text><subparagraph id="H3369921703BF46ED891813B43820E287"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a covered easement has previously been granted for another communications facility or a utility facility with respect to the same building or other property owned by the Federal Government; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C953E35A9474D9299C4D5044B1A2234"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the covered easement is for a communications facility in a public right-of-way.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBA9DC5FD306D456E83F44E61A90FA7D3" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requests for modification of certain existing wireless facilities</header><text>Section 6409(a)(3) of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block id="HA28CE452D6DE43CDB10AA087B4AD2765" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H9F228986497E4742B4EDD580701BD5D5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application of NEPA; NHPA</header><subparagraph id="HD9FDF0DBA64B4A33BA1EB046D8BDBE6D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>NEPA exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal authorization with respect to an eligible facilities request may not be considered a major Federal action under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AA160FCFED2425BB6904ECD85A16734" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>National Historic Preservation Act exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible facilities request may not be considered an undertaking under section 300320 of title 54, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C6DC61993C9492FBC0A30202AD04EC9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Federal authorization defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>Federal authorization</term>—</text><clause id="H341493AA15EF4EB7ACD0AE746B09BFEA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any authorization required under Federal law with respect to an eligible facilities request; and</text></clause><clause id="H9AFDC262EC514E5787A29DFED3A894C3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any permits, special use authorizations, certifications, opinions, or other approvals as may be required under Federal law with respect to an eligible facilities request.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HB1CE5481B02B423B8C2C3C285D8D586C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Presumption with respect to certain complete FCC forms</header><subsection id="HEBDB39F6353A4BAA870E458E21827471"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presumption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an Indian Tribe is shown to have received a complete FCC Form 620 or FCC Form 621 (or any successor form), or can be reasonably expected to have received a complete FCC Form 620 or FCC Form 621 (or any successor form), and has not acted on a request contained in such complete form by the date that is 45 days after the date of such receipt or reasonably expected receipt—</text><paragraph id="HFC8DA8D5FFB0445E94473CD7628CA415"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Commission and a court of competent jurisdiction (as the case may be) shall presume the applicant with respect to such complete form has made a good faith effort to provide the information reasonably necessary for such Indian Tribe to ascertain whether historic properties of religious or cultural significance to such Indian Tribe may be affected by the undertaking related to such complete form; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H082231B8C67C410F9317BB35A11D2BBF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such Indian Tribe shall be presumed to have disclaimed interest in such undertaking.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H254981EBDDB04FC3A4755544DAE61A38"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Overcoming presumption</header><paragraph id="H5B185C18AC634199A43DE6ADBD6B8698"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An Indian Tribe may overcome a presumption under subsection (a) upon making, to the Commission or a court of competent jurisdiction, a favorable demonstration with respect to 1 or more of the factors described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6CF328555F7467282AE322EBED066A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors considered</header><text>In making a determination regarding a presumption under subsection (a), the Commission or court of competent jurisdiction shall give substantial weight to—</text><subparagraph id="HAB2E3022DE2E411A948A10BC3B17405A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the applicant with respect to the relevant complete form failed to make a reasonable attempt to follow up with the applicable Indian Tribe not earlier than 30 days, and not later than 50 days, after the applicant submitted a complete FCC Form 620 or FCC Form 621 (as the case may be) to such Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2744BC0A8A4D48A38465AA075BFC5900"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the rules of the Commission, or FCC Form 620 or FCC Form 621, are found to be in violation of a Nationwide Programmatic Agreement of the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3743B9B8C4BC49A4931D5090FFECB071"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or any amendment made by this Act may be construed to affect the obligation of the Commission to evaluate radiofrequency exposure under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="H38D2B18BFFB64117BB2E8CBF13C3865D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H3A3A10D3A23F4CF99CE9620E387EFDC6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chief Executive</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Chief Executive</term> means the person who is the Chief, Chairman, Governor, President, or similar executive official of an Indian tribal government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H525BFF11097F46BEA2F0D9E039EA9F3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82D54EFCCED6470CBE7285EFD36B5E42"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <term>communications facility</term> has the meaning given the term <term>communications facility installation</term> in section 6409(d) of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EEDAC1F21F24029BAFFB2A25C37DB0E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered easement</header><text>The term <term>covered easement</term> means an easement, right-of-way, or lease with respect to a building or other property owned by the Federal Government, excluding Tribal land held in trust by the Federal Government (unless the Indian tribal government with respect to such land requests that the Commission not exclude the land for purposes of this definition), for the right to install, construct, modify, or maintain a communications facility or a utility facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H131824F02FAA49D581A8CA0FD909BD32" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered project</term> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H6BAA6711EA3E4E348E04D07AD305AAD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A project—</text><clause id="H26CD04C0C3774FCB815FD7890F472337" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for—</text><subclause id="H72056DC3798044DCB2D443EDB1FEE302"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the mounting or installation of a personal wireless service facility with another personal wireless service facility that exists at the time at which a request for authorization of such mounting or installation is submitted to a State or local government or instrumentality thereof or to an Indian tribal government; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H1715BA82E74842D1B6EF5FD78B6F1853" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the modification of a personal wireless service facility; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H7500BA56BFB14110B2AD8F573F945F8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a permit, license, or approval from the Commission is required or that is otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C1445BDDCA540FD814819DB8D32C85A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project—</text><clause id="H90B7F729536D40FBB2207AD9DA5AB073" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the placement, construction, or modification of a telecommunications service facility in or on eligible support infrastructure; and</text></clause><clause id="H449946C2C423468EB628698509B4838B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a permit, license, or approval from the Commission is required or that is otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5C3998023F544D5894C02D129A155AA"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project to deploy a small personal wireless service facility.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE71564365EB4DF1815055F7ACE38807"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project—</text><clause id="H40AC35FBD5E64FC580269A1738DEC080"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the deployment or modification of a communications facility that is to be carried out entirely within a floodplain (as defined in section 9.4 of title 44, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act); and</text></clause><clause id="H0CA7E113E45C4DBEB09FD1664DA88A5C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a permit, license, or approval from the Commission is required or that is otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA129F6F9EC94AD9A6B966FF47045151"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project—</text><clause id="HB20C5F5203C249F693F66C94E5AD2A81"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the deployment or modification of a communications facility that is to be carried out entirely within a brownfield site (as defined in section 101 of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9601">42 U.S.C. 9601</external-xref>)); and</text></clause><clause id="H48BF6DB18CFE4CB58A2EE5D922DD8237"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a permit, license, or approval from the Commission is required or that is otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7578DD1EBF7842DA9FB6D2FDD1BF1B9A"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project to permanently remove covered communications equipment or services (as defined in section 9 of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1608">47 U.S.C. 1608</external-xref>)) and to replace such covered communications equipment or services with communications equipment or services (as defined in such section) that are not covered communications equipment or services (as so defined).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB789A452D2214BCBA5C089A4B6EB7ECA" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A project that—</text><clause id="H22644B9A675940BA880B1976962EC66B" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is to be carried out entirely within an area for which the President, the Governor of a State, or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government has declared a major disaster or an emergency;</text></clause><clause id="HDA76D26C389148E2A2D6AD30A4308A04" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is to be carried out not later than 5 years after the date on which the President, Governor, or Chief Executive made such declaration; and</text></clause><clause id="HF4209D48965A4EC1BAA413092A43DA50" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>replaces a communications facility damaged by such disaster or emergency or makes improvements to a communications facility in such area that could reasonably be considered as necessary for recovery from such disaster or emergency or to prevent or mitigate any future disaster or emergency.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1E5BE72E1BA4FDE81D5F7DA395724C4" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project for the placement and installation of a new communications facility if—</text><clause id="H4208FADA6ED847CD9137C45F4E8E2189" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such new facility—</text><subclause id="HB31E1DA69F42485899DBDE502194E0B4" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>will be located within a public right-of-way; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H69C6D368C229424B9B61895CF66B3DB6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is not more than 50 feet tall or 10 feet taller than any existing structure in the public right-of-way, whichever is higher;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H3B4239D411114C92A95340B5AF89154C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such new facility is—</text><subclause id="H1E0086C0290F4BF69154AE2CD241A943" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a replacement for an existing communications facility; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1A071CC8C7D84E309E38F92E841057DC" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the same as, or substantially similar to (as such term is defined by the Commission), the existing communications facility that such new communications facility is replacing;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H14A6833B5818492D8997B08C353A8C87" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such new facility is a type of communications facility that—</text><subclause id="H1D1ECB5F0A444D3B95E6FEA0AE2C9163" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is described in section 6409(d)(1)(B) of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455(d)(1)(B)</external-xref>); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H02C56B053001479483CC15D68AC9D3B7" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meets the size limitation of a small antenna established by the Commission; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H457716BD4A634B29AD00192C44ED9A5F" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the placement and installation of such new facility involves the expansion of the site of an existing communications facility not more than 30 feet in any direction.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H939DFE48381F49399BB7C03A75643F7C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible support infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible support infrastructure</term> means infrastructure that supports or houses a facility for communication by wire (or that is designed for or capable of supporting or housing such a facility) at the time when a request to a State or local government or instrumentality thereof, or to an Indian tribal government, for authorization to place, construct, or modify a telecommunications service facility in or on the infrastructure is submitted to the government or instrumentality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77638AD261C8493B90DAB02FA4D63586"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Emergency</header><text>The term <term>emergency</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HD7DAEE9B65FD42C299E3CA69D8FD0E68"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an emergency declared by the President, an emergency declared by the President under section 501 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5191">42 U.S.C. 5191</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7355E8D762E74FE5B104F9FF17F79773" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an emergency declared by the Governor of a State or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government, any occasion or instance with respect to which the Governor or Chief Executive declares that an emergency exists (or makes a similar declaration) under State or Tribal law (as the case may be).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC7F3B851710416E8363495C03AA4530"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Federal authorization</header><text>The term <term>Federal authorization</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H2470267F4369471796894D3D7B21A60C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any authorization required under Federal law with respect to a covered project or a covered easement; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5ED27B3C20714874AF21D36DAC4E02A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any permits, special use authorizations, certifications, opinions, or other approvals as may be required under Federal law with respect to a covered project or a covered easement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H478B181218444F959B6B5566C17108EF"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Governor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Governor</term> means the chief executive of any State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7C8060CCE4B4428904846499D73EBC1" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Indian tribal government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian tribal government</term> means the governing body of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F4CECDCFDFD4B708BF05759EC885752" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> under section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDA7CA8827A94228B55DD914558C657F"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Major disaster</header><text>The term <term>major disaster</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H19079DA6896B477AA68F3C90FAC67119"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a major disaster declared by the President, a major disaster declared by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E5923B18B3B4A5C8760CC132F34C0F4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a major disaster declared by the Governor of a State or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government, any occasion or instance with respect to which the Governor or Chief Executive declares that a disaster exists (or makes a similar declaration) under State or Tribal law (as the case may be).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20DCC6C432DD43E5ABFB45AB35CD6041" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Personal wireless service</header><text>The term <term>personal wireless service</term> means any fixed or mobile service (other than a broadcasting (as defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>)) service) provided via licensed or unlicensed frequencies, including—</text><subparagraph id="H745286A02F4F4F1CB7F699C281C721AD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>commercial mobile service (as defined in section 332(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/332">47 U.S.C. 332(d)</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFCB8E614BD64953B0415211500F948F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>commercial mobile data service (as defined in section 6001 of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1401">47 U.S.C. 1401</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H134E466656B34D50AF03047884A7774E" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>unlicensed wireless service; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54CF33AE29FA447CADEEC682A92275F5" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>common carrier wireless exchange access service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2252F88FF5446F19073254827F830C3" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Personal wireless service facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>personal wireless service facility</term> means a facility used to provide or support the provision of personal wireless service. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68F480079E8D41E58E96D6CA4177B7D5"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Public right-of-way</header><text>The term <term>public right-of-way</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H4A6704B87C414ECABDC26332B949832E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text><clause id="H310A0A35EC8C4ED9838640EF744496BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the area on, below, or above a public roadway, highway, street, sidewalk, alley, or similar property (whether currently or previously used in such manner); and</text></clause><clause id="HB10441839B334D459F072BA342943030"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any land immediately adjacent to and contiguous with property described in clause (i) that is within the right-of-way grant; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DB6A2258CEC4C7AB84CA6A039009AD2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include a portion of the Interstate System (as such term is defined in section 101(a) of title 23, United States Code).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H868B302EE0604FD498812457C864FF16" commented="no"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Small personal wireless service facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>small personal wireless service facility</term> means a personal wireless service facility in which each antenna is not more than 3 cubic feet in volume (excluding a wireline backhaul facility connected to such personal wireless service facility).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0546595AB0541D49D88C414E70FBB25" commented="no"><enum>(17)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, and each territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83CB95162F89424FB32ABD994DEE66FA"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Telecommunications service</header><text>The term <term>telecommunications service</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B498CE3240A45BEAF5160C676DB44CD"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Telecommunications service facility</header><text>The term <term>telecommunications service facility</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H40331F22BFB647CAB4FFF5F05B5858E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a facility that is designed or used to provide or facilitate the provision of any interstate or intrastate telecommunications service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC68F388CBC04E7E8E2D4576AF755D29"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a facility described in subparagraph (A) that is used to provide other services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HACDDCD9C82E04C5DA233F922080473DF" commented="no"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Unlicensed wireless service</header><text>The term <term>unlicensed wireless service</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H2AE76627C95B4C2BB771A2BB4679A976" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the offering of telecommunications service or information service (as defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>)) using a duly authorized device that does not require an individual license; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF51927FF66A44EC3B2BF57BC78649B66" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include the provision of direct-to-home satellite services (as defined in section 303(v) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/303">47 U.S.C. 303(v)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7FD408E27274B4E8A1F8833BC2B5BF0"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Utility facility</header><text>The term <term>utility facility</term> means any privately, publicly, or cooperatively owned line, facility, or system for producing, transmitting, or distributing power, electricity, light, heat, gas, oil, crude products, water, steam, waste, storm water not connected with highway drainage, or any other similar commodity, including any fire or police signal system or street lighting system, that directly or indirectly serves the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA264CB585749E1861BDB4B82C9F4A9" commented="no"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Wireline backhaul facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>wireline backhaul facility</term> means an above-ground or underground wireline facility used to transport communications service or other electronic communications from a small personal wireless service facility or its adjacent network interface device to a communications network.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

