<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB583DA6108254C5AA278F9719C79F0E0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6405 IH: Lori Jackson-Nicolette Elias Domestic Violence Survivor Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6405</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231114">November 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to protect more victims of domestic violence by preventing their abusers from possessing or receiving firearms and to amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to establish a grant program relating to the removal of firearms from adjudicated domestic violence offenders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H57D45C1E14644633A854DC458637E174" style="OLC"><section id="HB220220883DC44DE92EE3C76F9878602" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Lori Jackson-Nicolette Elias Domestic Violence Survivor Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8E270ADCE7794EF4B62CF3AC2E15F12A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H4C77372D7D094E8991930354516B6B77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Congress has the responsibility to keep the populace of the United States safe, and domestic gun violence is a significant threat to the well-being of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD06149C36BD9491C848DFDB490C4AD9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each year in the United States, more than 800 women are shot and killed by an intimate partner. More women are killed in the United States by domestic partners than by any other type of assailant, and most of these homicides are committed with firearms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3A263F8B4724054ACB7B961DD46B70A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Approximately 4,500,000 women alive in the United States today report having been threatened with a gun by a domestic partner. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9FB660EFE5C41DF96676782B641B7EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Almost two-thirds of intimate partner homicides in the United States are committed with a firearm. If a woman has an abusive male partner who has access to a firearm, the woman is 5 times more likely to be killed than she would be if the abusive male partner did not have access to a firearm, and domestic violence assaults involving a gun are 12 times more likely to result in death than domestic violence assaults involving other weapons or bodily force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE30C42D8C499468E9A436B73F9EFD8B9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Perpetrators of intimate partner violence are far more likely to commit additional acts of gun violence. Nearly half of all mass shooters have committed acts of domestic violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39CCC92E9291474FA36DE5A0C4FAB64F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Victims of intimate partner violence often pursue restraining orders as a means of protection in the immediate aftermath of, or in conjunction with, leaving dangerous partners and situations. This time period is especially dangerous for victims.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H564EC2F2AA6241208D3D79E162EA57BC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Although individuals against whom there is a domestic violence restraining order are barred from purchasing a firearm under section 922(g)(8) of title 18, United States Code, various loopholes in that section allow perpetrators to purchase and maintain possession of firearms. For example, Federal law only protects domestic violence victims against spouses, former spouses, cohabitants, former cohabitants, and individuals with whom those victims have a child. Furthermore, under Federal law, protective orders issued against domestic violence abusers on an emergency or ex parte basis do not prohibit those abusers from possessing or purchasing firearms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55FB3593C3EC4ADD9C7ED8E9AC4C3280"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Some States and local governments have passed laws that go beyond the Federal baseline by expanding the range of abusive partners included in firearm restrictions to encompass abusive dating partners. Numerous studies conducted between 2000 and 2017 have shown that States that pass these laws experience a significant reduction in intimate partner homicides.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5471F0AAFCF446CBA98750E35CF1D0B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>States that restrict access to guns to individuals subject to active domestic violence restraining orders have experienced a 13-percent reduction in intimate partner homicides involving firearms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF85D92829CA4299B27F88A0E88ECF33"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Congress has the power to set a national standard to protect domestic violence victims who seek restraining orders against abusive partners by preventing those abusive partners from possessing or purchasing firearms and ammunition while the restraining order is in effect.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H130CD6D4520E479FB6132358D7031C84" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Expanded definitions of <quote>covered domestic violence court order</quote> and <quote>intimate partner</quote></header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF7A67A510D46404BA44A49B8E3F0F7BC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting before paragraph (32) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D61A4CF7BB6411AADDF537716D6DA77"><paragraph id="H4EC43E6D3E344A69BC58C8A1DE8B3C24" commented="no"><enum>(31)</enum><text>The term <term>covered domestic violence court order</term> means a court order, with respect to a person—</text><subparagraph id="H5C9664E5127241CB93AFB3B72D7C2F0F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4B9BE6A56CB44A5D97CC98F9A148E261"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that was issued after a hearing of which the person received actual notice, and at which the person had an opportunity to participate; or</text></clause><clause id="H66900647CC394A72BF9129950BC91CED" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of an ex parte order, relative to which notice and opportunity to be heard are provided—</text><subclause id="H7C6488BC90924604BF4B33F976B4D17F" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>within the time required by State, Tribal, or territorial law; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3ECDEFB66FEC494B8532C172609E29C1" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in any event within a reasonable time after the order is issued, sufficient to protect the due process rights of the person;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8E4B30670494DA483790FD1BDDB11C2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that restrains the person from—</text><clause id="H85E57FAE77364B06964E8700DBC9FE97" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>harassing, stalking, or threatening an intimate partner of the person or child of the intimate partner or person, or engaging in other conduct that would place an intimate partner in reasonable fear of bodily injury to the partner or child; or</text></clause><clause id="H54DBA04BE51849A08DE11B2004832366" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>intimidating or dissuading a witness from testifying in court; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD085CBEF5EA44C4D91AB9FFE8D8FDCE8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that—</text><clause id="HE0621D01B9814D659F6D7B3B813218BB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>includes a finding that the person represents a credible threat to the physical safety of an individual described in subparagraph (B); or</text></clause><clause id="H08A0EFD5083342CD9D44B541946000E6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by its terms explicitly prohibits the use, attempted use, or threatened use of physical force against an individual described in subparagraph (B) that would reasonably be expected to cause bodily injury.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F4ED7C7C6E94C83B85E0CD756E2BA3B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (32), by striking all that follows after <quote>The term <term>intimate partner</term></quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H55DEB5BDC1064F4BB5BB82FAC68C49A2"><text>—</text><subparagraph id="H4EA0D37F62F445858DD930BF92CAF283" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means, with respect to a person, the spouse of the person, a former spouse of the person, an individual who is a parent of a child of the person, and an individual who cohabitates or has cohabited with the person; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C6148997CA94CBF859FCB4C37B63CF3" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="HB1F4197485554DFD8792E1A475737436" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a dating partner (as defined in section 2266) or former dating partner; and</text></clause><clause id="HBB35C6924A194BE9B11FEC4289905553" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other individual similarly situated to a spouse who is protected by the domestic or family violence laws of the State, local, or Tribal jurisdiction in which the injury occurred or where the victim resides.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6E9AE9A3B2A4A1FA4BF55F0CB839744" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (33)(A)—</text><subparagraph id="HFE94F803AABE4A3EB97A76CB1F95CFBB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (i), by inserting after <quote>Federal, State,</quote> the following: <quote>municipal,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C5693FA1A80487D9D2043B2D710A71E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HD58E4BA0D1B9447EBDC75B277E86C867" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H65A19E408E7B495B8E68A58AD81D646E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has, as an element, the use or attempted use of physical force, or the threatened use of a deadly weapon, or that is classified as stalking, committed by—</text><subclause id="H3A1BAC3548C84182A1CFF760333E353A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC5A846A2EC114EB8B061FE6105D12D08"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a person with whom the victim shares a child in common;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCECCF8D101D34B4C955C71514CAA13C9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a person who is cohabiting with or has cohabited with the victim as a spouse, parent, or guardin;</text></subclause><subclause id="H088C11CEEFB24E38BE07F900F9642D65"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a person similarly situated to a spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim;</text></subclause><subclause id="H607C32EAE2D943CDBB615DFF757687A1"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person who is or was a dating partner of the victim; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC2D73CEDBDB24135BE925C5C9E7F1F9C"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person who is or was a dating partner of the victim’s parent or guardian. </text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H9AC6B67D5A5B4A40A31FF8CD3B64E352" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Unlawful sale of firearm to a person subject to court order</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922(d)(8) of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD31A7E03C83245C79FB8B6E9A490BABF"><paragraph id="H879D78BAE77749D18286C2BEF72E6891" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>is subject to a covered domestic violence court order; </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H7F579FE825DE421DA41B72563B18E473" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>List of persons subject to a restraining or similar order prohibited from possessing or receiving a firearm expanded</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922(g)(8) of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC853C655C54246F5B3482CCDC40D22C8"><paragraph id="HA3537BFEB06444A5BA2C1F3DA74D064E" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>who is subject to a covered domestic violence court order; or</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HEB63F99B81894FCDAA1FE10C09F70977" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>6.</enum><header>Grant Program Regarding the Removal of Firearms From Adjudicated Domestic Violence Parties</header><subsection id="H4D4A7B685E154825949EF9B913996A9C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text>Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA02474C05E614B3192D2967F9A4A618B"><part id="HBE0F2B728F114B0399E13AD71F1F4643" style="OLC"><enum>PP</enum><header>Grant program regarding removal of firearms from adjudicated domestic violence parties</header><section id="HFBFEB27FB40043128D0145A523998419"><enum>3061.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text><paragraph id="HE00341FDC26F451DB6EF690C1CFF1662"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ammunition; firearm</header><text>The terms <term>ammunition</term> and <term>firearm</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 921 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC23E31F831AF468E9D483B41EB24AC92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H325ECF8C6E57450C9225835389BB6808"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A055364461E4551865FE5D0B61C743D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92EBB4132AC64446B276EFD121034264"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a unit of local government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H083ED62AD100469099A8F61B420270FE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Domestic violence protection order</header><text>The term <term>domestic violence protection order</term> has the meaning given the term <term>covered domestic violence court order</term> in section 921 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE60A0535C01C4DBC8B7FBC48ED13DC77"><enum>3062.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="H41E785A0596444558CA58FC1C5C6DEC3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To make grants</header><text>The Attorney General may make grants to covered entities to assist the covered entities in carrying out the policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations described in section 3063.</text></subsection><subsection id="H838135B3CAB04777B4C4609C84A91F61"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible covered entity</header><paragraph id="H75B98343E7F24018AFB8A97FC615EFBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered entity shall be eligible to receive a grant under this section on and after the date on which the Attorney General determines that the covered entity has in effect policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations that are substantially similar to the policies, procedures, laws, court rules, or regulations described in section 3063.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H168FF4B943E5469DB1F7FFE6BB185CB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>In making a determination under paragraph (1), the Attorney General may consider policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations of a covered entity to be substantially similar to the policies, procedures, laws, courts rules, or regulations described in section 3063 even if the policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations of the covered entity—</text><subparagraph id="HDCA392FF382F40D4B59A5CB1C3D1E35B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>vary in scope;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C96286288454681A3D08F72109F6686"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prescribe different types of protective orders or firearm surrender orders; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1390E36D0ABD4B9E9CBDE55F772A8CC1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide different timing requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2EFF4ECFD6FA4D62A1D1E9153A18A2EE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Grant funds awarded under this section may be used by a covered entity—</text><paragraph id="HE461155A375C4707B8EA69A2DA9AFCCB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to assist law enforcement agencies or courts of the covered entity in carrying out the policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations described in section 3063; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFC4DDD3E89140189A50CEF6F29A3458"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in order to ensure the safety of domestic violence victims after a domestic violence protection order is issued in accordance with the policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations described in section 3063, to partner with and provide support to not less than 1 domestic violence victim service provider, which may include an organization that is a culturally specific organization.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F15D98A08CB4998AE0C0C612C3F3948"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H91DD1640326B43079C9B68DF215C6D5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing or accompanied by such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC587D5088A7F443CBF5975D92FDC470A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>An application submitted under this subsection shall include a description of an action plan of the covered entity to establish a partnership described in subsection (c)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H38E131AC055341858831C51BAF94BD5F"><enum>3063.</enum><header>State and Tribal policies and procedures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations described in this section are policies, procedures, protocols, laws, court rules, or regulations relating to the possession of a firearm or ammunition that—</text><paragraph id="H1B39C41D237D469CA776CA184030E580"><enum>(1)</enum><text>direct a court, upon the issuance of a domestic violence protection order, to issue an additional order (referred to in this section as a <quote>firearm surrender order</quote>) that—</text><subparagraph id="H284C313DE4274401919B053313C471D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is in effect for the duration of the domestic violence protection order;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E68E1295F9A4CB7876C7144F0DBCDCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>automatically terminates upon the expiration of the domestic violence protection order;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A4ADAF5DB1E40718717FBAF46F3CE08"><enum>(C)</enum><text>requires—</text><clause id="HF2FD3AE64EFB4642A40497CA6DBD17DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the individual subject to the firearm surrender order to, not later than 24 hours after the firearm surrender order is served, surrender physical possession of all firearms and ammunition in the possession, care, custody, or control of the individual, including any firearm that the individual has entrusted or lent to a third party, by either—</text><subclause id="H53631F4DA3F5444097C170C56CEF9AD9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>surrendering the firearms and ammunition to the chief law enforcement officer of the district in which the individual resides or a law enforcement agency designated by the State or Indian Tribe to receive and store firearms and ammunition; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H140603AB6808493DBCCB06F73287C2EC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>selling the firearms and ammunition to a licensed dealer (as defined in section 921 of title 18, United States Code); or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H68295E14A0DF45158EE47C4105187909"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the chief law enforcement officer of the district in which the individual resides or a law enforcement agency designated by the State or Indian Tribe to receive and store firearms and ammunition to, not later than 24 hours after the firearm surrender order is served, request the surrender of and remove and store any firearm or ammunition in the possession, care, custody, or control of the individual, including firearms and ammunition that the individual has entrusted or lent to a third party;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB57D37DD6DDF45828BDAB1CA1FF87EB2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>prohibits the individual from purchasing, possessing, or receiving, or attempting to purchase or receive, a firearm or ammunition for the period of time during which the firearm surrender order is in effect;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA60D80075DF542529ABB3421B4C54BF3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>revokes any permit or license of the individual to purchase, possess or carry a firearm or ammunition for the period of time during which the firearm surrender order is in effect; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D1EC2BCB944459BB43DA57CC2EEB8A7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>requires the individual subject to the firearm surrender order to, not later than 48 hours after the firearm surrender order is served by a court, file with the court—</text><clause id="HD1427BE4D9FC43E1A1510AAA7A392AA3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a declaration under penalty of perjury that—</text><subclause id="H2496A0B5E5754A15821857D61F495691"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the individual has made the surrender described in subparagraph (C)(i);</text></subclause><subclause id="HBAFDD008A32141CA8067C6728C8AD813"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the chief law enforcement officer of the district in which the individual resides has conducted the removal described in subparagraph (C)(ii); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H8FCCF7341BA2497B82B3D13ACF718B47"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the individual did not possess any firearm or ammunition at the time of the issuance and service of the firearm surrender order and continues to not possess any firearms or ammunition; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC17F9E6D3D7E4729A399809A8FF54A82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an itemized receipt of any firearms or ammunition surrendered by the individual subject to the firearm surrender order under subparagraph (C)(i), or removed by a chief law enforcement officer from that individual under subparagraph (C)(ii), that is signed by the individual who took possession of those firearms or ammunition;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C9AFB086D3C41218DC52383A6295AD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who does not comply with paragraph (1)(C)(i), and where there are reasonable grounds to believe that the individual possesses or has purchased a firearm, require the chief law enforcement officer or designated law enforcement agency described in paragraph (1)(C)(ii) to remove any firearm or ammunition from the individual;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F562CFC85A74AC390814EE3D3C9A23E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>requires a chief law enforcement officer or designated law enforcement agency that conducts a removal under paragraph (1)(C)(ii) or (2) or receives a firearm or ammunition surrendered by an individual under paragraph (1)(C)(i)(I) to, not later than 48 hours after conducting the removal or receiving the surrendered firearm or ammunition, notify the court of the removal or surrender;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3621492848C34A9BB27E8C21390308EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>with respect to a firearm or ammunition that is surrendered under paragraph (1)(C)(i) or any firearm or ammunition removed under paragraph (1)(C)(ii) or (2), require the law enforcement agency to which the firearm or ammunition is surrendered or that removes any firearm or ammunition to—</text><subparagraph id="HA49105D2219943E69468715A98577A10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>safely store the firearm or ammunition; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2797BAEE64124D4BB9706B3828FC8228"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at the request of the individual subject to the firearm surrender order, not later than 7 days after the date on which the domestic violence protection order described in paragraph (1) expires or is removed—</text><clause id="H5C37565D23BC48CDB21378F807638A98"><enum>(i)</enum><text>perform a background check on the individual subject to the firearm surrender order to determine whether the individual is prohibited from possessing or receiving a firearm under Federal or State law; and</text></clause><clause id="H162F8CC09A5C464DA6FBAB26060D2E8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>return the firearm or ammunition to the individual subject to the firearm surrender order if the individual is not prohibited from possessing or receiving a firearm under Federal, State, or Tribal law; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3296B399C0149C6A1041EFC4E3610DF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>require the courts and relevant law enforcement agencies to partner with and provide support for local domestic violence programs in order to ensure the safety of victims of domestic violence after the issuance of a firearm surrender order.</text></paragraph></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7B5CAB01804F49B4B5DD25299B84FC7F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>Section 1001(a) of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10261">34 U.S.C. 10261</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H56D0301927154F3E8459CEC109093C05"><paragraph id="H71138413430B437B9746E0F6B9EFE4D7" indent="up1"><enum>(29)</enum><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out part PP.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H15A3FD90B249419593B8C89D36B08410"><enum>7.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The NICS Improvement Amendments Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40902">34 U.S.C. 40902 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE3625C50F1BB4A96BBE3D01C41D3605D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 3(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40903">34 U.S.C. 40903(1)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>court order (as described in section 922(g)(8)</quote> and inserting <quote>covered domestic violence court order (as defined in section 921(a)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE11CE268BD4A4E5AB939B5B89E987919" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 102(b)(1)(C)(v) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40912">34 U.S.C. 40912(b)(1)(C)(v)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>court order described in section 922(g)(8)</quote> and inserting <quote>covered domestic violence court order, as defined in section 921(a)</quote>. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

