<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD5BA4AB955D4264A865D24D41BBEB19" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3530 IH: Cut Red Tape For Online Sales Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3530</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to increase the de minimis exception for third party settlement organizations to $5,000, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HADB5667CDB2C426E9A1D50D0B5F5FA67" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H171D39695DAD414788783EE36268C5B7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cut Red Tape For Online Sales Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H4FC79F1A06694A838BD1B3D46A61917B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of exception for reporting of third party network transactions</header> <subsection id="H876905AE58BD40658C9AD7D94EF9D39C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6050W">Section 6050W(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>exceed $600</quote> and inserting <quote>equal or exceed $5,000</quote>. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0E247F8F9EEC46CC8F15D1296C36DAF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to returns for calendar years beginning after December 31, 2021.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HFA2CE1098EFD4424928A8305F3C85FD5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Plain language notice to payees regarding form 1099–K</header> <subsection id="H6EB21FDC28EC440A9EE1997B5B0A4144"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6050W">Section 6050W</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h) and by inserting after subsection (f) the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H89ADA92519454FFA9C1799F0D4D44C8E" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H880CE40394FC421AAFECEB73237F14F7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Plain language description required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every person required to furnish a written statement under subsection (f) shall simultaneously issue to the recipient of such statement a plain language notice explaining the contents of such statement, either through using a Form or notice issued by the Internal Revenue Service or by providing a written explanation that is substantially similar in content to plain language on the Form or notice issued by the Internal Revenue Service. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HA45ABDC27A804706889B43FAD244008C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to statements issued in taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDAD89FB345734C15BF497D320EDAC2B8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment of notice to taxpayers with respect to form 1099–K</header>
<paragraph id="H652F982531F24C15945953A4715894FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary’s delegate) shall amend Form 1099–K to include, in plain language, a notice with respect to such Form which—</text> <subparagraph id="HF999E3E6A1DE4B10BA521EE34F4B90FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>directs payees to refer to the instructions for such Form to determine if a tax return must be filed, </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC9DBF2B0F8A04F3FA6C612A7DED859BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>summarizes rules for taxability of income reported on such Form, including as to under what circumstances—</text> <clause id="H46C6E0631D5E4D5E9F6F742297861D20"><enum>(i)</enum><text>income reported on such Form may be subject to tax, and</text></clause>
<clause id="H1B245681FA1543A9A6C18DE79416854F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>income from personal items sold at a loss or for no gain may not be subject to tax, and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD180501FCE3842FEB232F3D841B5A644"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides a reminder to participating payees that they may qualify for relevant small business deductions. </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such notice shall be similar in form to the Notice to Employee included in Form W–2 (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act) and shall also be issued as a stand-alone flier. </continuation-text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H55D378DDEBD342F08654EA1F000CF9FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury may prescribe such regulations or other guidance as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HAE700D026EB2469CB457ED74DBF3E4CB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Application of backup witholding with respect to third party network transactions</header> <subsection id="H3664C59699C04FD782DC6293AADA9F18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/3406">Section 3406(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF0DC4806FD244750B34AC92086ED6527" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H96AAA6D7008D4444849AD551034FB8B4"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Other reportable payments include payments in settlement of third party network transactions only where aggregate for calendar year is $5,000 or more</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any payment in settlement of a third party network transaction required to be shown on a return required under section 6050W which is made during any calendar year shall be treated as a reportable payment only if—</text> <subparagraph id="HAE2B7BB192804F1B809E741315EC5669"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the aggregate amount of such payment and all previous such payments made by the third party settlement organization to the participating payee during such calendar year equals or exceeds $5,000, or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H205244F086434ACCA15BBACF55BA3D2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the third party settlement organization was required under section 6050W to file a return for the preceding calendar year with respect to payments to the participating payee. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H9CE44304F34E4A13B1179E3577DF3D42"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to calendar years beginning after December 31, 2021.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HEEDE892051D14FC89AF62471A2E1AF52"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transitional rule for 2022</header><text>In the case of payments made during calendar year 2022, <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/3406">section 3406(b)(8)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by this section) shall be applied by inserting <quote>and the aggregate number of third party network transactions settled by the third party settlement organization with respect to the participating payee during such calendar year exceeds 200</quote> before the comma at the end. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

