<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7B399728E01942DE977E1FCB50F5CFDF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3284 IH: Providers and Payers COMPETE Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3284</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to submit an annual report on the impact of certain Medicare regulations on provider and payer consolidation.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4BEEDC8718ED487FACA89EF325A77AA1" style="OLC"><section id="H96C4E48DAA2B4F2B8DD0F7ED68D1447C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providers and Payers COMPETE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H095FBA1CE69647489A6BCBD21C76469A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual report on the impact of certain Medicare regulations on provider and payer consolidation; public comment on provider and payer consolidation for certain proposed rules</header><subsection id="H79411EE18C374CD88239CB20AA5A0985"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 30, 2026, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall submit to Congress a report on the impact in the aggregate on provider and payer consolidation with respect to regulations for parts B, C, and D of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j et seq.</external-xref>) implemented in the calendar year immediately prior to such report. Such report shall include regulations that—</text><paragraph id="H7667064FC857414691F8F68E0764C6D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implement a change to an applicable payment system, a rate schedule, or another payment system under part B, C, or D of such title; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8080BC861EE489F8A09318BCDE65307"><enum>(2)</enum><text>result in a significant rule effecting provider or payer consolidation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E1F3FF66BFB4D36BD516AC93E423DE1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public comment on impact to provider and payer consolidation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning for 2025, as part of any notice and comment rulemaking process that will result in a significant rule effecting provider or payer consolidation with respect to a proposed rule for parts B, C, and D of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j et seq.</external-xref>), the Secretary shall seek public comment on the projected impact of such proposed rule on provider and payer consolidation in the aggregate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H167952BCF28B42FC9E5272334D13B17C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB06B5A9D9F78496FAF88B947C7753481"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Provider and payer consolidation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>provider and payer consolidation</term> includes the vertical or horizontal integration among providers of services (as defined in subsection (u) of section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>)), suppliers (as defined in subsection (d) of such section), accountable care organizations under section 1899 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395jjj">42 U.S.C. 1395jjj</external-xref>), Medicare Advantage organizations, PDP sponsors, pharmacy benefit managers, pharmacies, and integrated delivery systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3109E718159E44668BB4DA4077AF0622"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable payment system</header><text>The term <quote>applicable payment system</quote> includes—</text><subparagraph id="H5059C4A994A54DDAAA92055B72C162DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to outpatient hospital services, the prospective payment system for covered OPD services established under section 1833(t) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395(l)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H249D096D27E341B6A350F863FF9A07AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to physicians’ services, the physician fee schedules established under section 1848 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H046139CE57BC4E83BD12B3E5B7F5B6B3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Consideration of effects on provider and payer consolidation with respect to CMI models</header><subsection id="H451152963E254E359F3AC0F552FA2BC1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1115A(b)(4)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a(b)(4)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1E3558E7B8994A849D15F0ED8645CFF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking at the end <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2818BAA0E90041E6AE7BEDE08EFAF3DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD4289D256584A3886546D8FAB979E76"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H134138B49EF3453DB491790331408E9A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H8D95406782DF4CDC83C92A9B02749D7A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which, and how, the model has effected and could effect provider and payer consolidation, which includes the vertical or horizontal integration among providers of services (as defined in subsection (u) of section 1861), suppliers (as defined in subsection (d) of such section), and accountable care organizations under section 1899. </text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1CA88F527BFA47EFA698151D7F5C6449"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to models tested on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

