<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H29782169515F46D5B206A1D6437A2398" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3179 IH: Supporting Apprenticeship Colleges Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3179</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize funding to expand and support enrollment at institutions of higher education that sponsor construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H20F8AA8CBCDE4B219BDC63761F91A191" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6C44361EA3064233A921530E1F681F4A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Apprenticeship Colleges Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB184BC57FABA477F9A54E7A8A707FF48"><enum>2.</enum><header>Community outreach grant program</header> <subsection id="H849F3FC28BE64FC48A7DD56302CA53C7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under subsection (f), the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, shall provide grants to eligible entities for the purposes of expanding or supporting potential student and employer outreach carried out by such entities with respect to the construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship programs offered by such entities. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HD6F9E88188BD47D0BC9A9A16D104D06C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amounts</header><text>The total grant amount made to an eligible entity under this section may not exceed $500,000.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H24FE79C3E5874C6B8D48622CEC4606E2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use such grant for the outreach described in subsection (a), which shall include the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H232EC3DAAEB249DCB98CF76C8D39CF66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Outreach to high schools, for the purpose of educating students, parents, guardians, and faculty on the benefits of enrolling students in the construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship program offered by the eligible entity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D1258C47BE1441ABA82A15EBFFF776C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Outreach to local businesses and other potential employers for the purpose of educating such employers on the benefits of supporting and hiring graduates of such program, which shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC10700B929DB4FB6BDEC9F6958E3B837"><enum>(A)</enum><text>primarily target relationship building with potential employers in rural, exurban, and suburban areas; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB13DDBF09EFE4B2C9D72526050E9D25B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seek to maximize the number of students who work in such areas after completing such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1953D4CA45A041818F451868F4CD0D15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Outreach to local workforce development boards and apprenticeship intermediaries for the purpose of reaching nontraditional student populations and prioritizing local needs. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H421948940C54455D8FDB2C7BB34BFA70"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H632A0202FB7A455986FAFF830FAC61FD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that demonstrate outreach efforts targeted at increasing program enrollment for rural students, first generation college students, minority students, and nontraditional students, or other students from underrepresented population.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1BE969217FAA40C98BF645FD5A8B5A5A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 to carry out this section for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H59D819E232A64B0B99578A662E28049F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Student support grant program for expanded academic advising</header>
<subsection id="H03523A5174DD4D56BDB4F69F9F594B69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under subsection (g), the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, shall provide grants to eligible entities for the activities described in subsection (d).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4590BEC7257C48EFB18364CCA56DDAD3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amounts</header><text>The total grant amount made to an eligible entity under this section may not exceed $500,000.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HCFC2A34FE4124063A8F217FFF338435A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Multiple grants permitted</header><text>An eligible entity may receive a grant under sections 2 and 3.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCC542CCA1F80434AB3C06BA768129EEF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of grants</header> <paragraph id="H5B8BC57341784B6398EC083AB6E9EE4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use such grant for advising and support services to enrollees of construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship programs offered by such entity to increase retention, persistence, and completion for students. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7B0DAFC29C174FC59C4AB3E5C1181DDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Such advising and support services shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H54A2CED15F5E43C29BAE0F3C67D6DBD6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Expanding academic advising programs that provide services to students, including—</text>
<clause id="H3EE812DB440E4B4C8B8A35D178FBCB75"><enum>(i)</enum><text>career advising and professional development;</text></clause> <clause id="H93CCA5673E2441B48353AC0054F5B0EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support for English as a second language students;</text></clause>
<clause id="HADFB3363CB5F466FB170589C79954DE0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>information and resource systems;</text></clause> <clause id="H6DF76E527A1F4270A86B980DE44519F2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>mentoring systems; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HE054DC06CFFA44A88CDB57D21BFDC10F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>other similar advising activities that support enrollment, retention, persistence, and completion. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8BF8CFEE67E8426F8217D4B895CD627A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Expanding student support programs that provide services to students, including— </text>
<clause id="H53177DDAEFD34C41BF3B9006E89884F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>health and family-related services, including substance abuse disorder and mental health counseling;</text></clause> <clause id="HDC17351B84EA407184CDEE7C6E779983"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support for first generation college students;</text></clause>
<clause id="H33E06980BEE2483D87881D85E31BED4A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>childcare support; or</text></clause> <clause id="HAA4BEA5F447346E6B319159ED74ADDFA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other similar support activities. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0E4E1FBC8E044695ACF8C3AD64BFB51E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7E48094DD63A4188AFB8821B8F334024"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="HEC2E8D0611704682B1EC0014264B850F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary a report on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H45A6D7720DBF49E78304069F086A149D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the activities supported by the grant;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA0C170CE06894261BE8BBD0F7D31EC4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of students participating in the activities supported by the grant;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E5D182AB98C4F4B9A024C1B6095249E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the percentage of students participating in the activities supported by the grant who are high school students; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A27627469B34333914A08900953AA6D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the progress made in achieving the goals of the program supported by the grant, in general, and measuring in particular—</text>
<clause id="HC9263B1167EE493B891223929846C6FC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the grant in expanding overall enrollment and program and apprenticeship completion rates and certification; </text></clause> <clause id="H06C3D7E82C164C72A300A6ABFEAF4B7A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the grant in expanding enrollment and program completion rates for underrepresented populations; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5DEC31BB5E59426CB263C31C2E74BEC7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any progress made towards the type of indicators of performance as described in section 116(b)(2)(A) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HACB9A8E9553C4269B97B0EAC53037C39"><enum>(E)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4A17F20EF73F43F18611D7EB17B5169A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timeline for submission of report</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall be submitted to the Secretary not later than 180 days after the date on which the eligible entity concludes the activities supported by the grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE11B164733E24F3F906DFEEA7EAAACAD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H6B9B2E0A94384504AA2764610510CF5F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H85A26EAEF4AB4A8294743C2A23471DDC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Construction and manufacturing-oriented apprenticeship college</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>construction and manufacturing-oriented apprenticeship college</term> means an institution of higher education that is a sponsor of a construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship program. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H95C464E277EA4725A7B1488BF10D8711"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship program</header><text>The term <term>construction and manufacturing-oriented registered apprenticeship program</term> means a registered apprenticeship program that—</text> <subparagraph id="HF10A95A2E47749DFA709DE80882C15D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides coursework and training in preparation for employment in the construction or manufactory industry (such as employment as a painter, drywall finisher, glazier, or glassworker); </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H059C1CE153994CE68D63F7433E484351"><enum>(B)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC6B8AEFC6A3C481C94CC449473FA9DD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>leads to a recognized postsecondary credential other than a certificate of completion of an apprenticeship; or</text></clause> <clause id="H54ED792B21BD48D6ACE02AFABB1800B4" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>awards credits that can be applied toward a recognized postsecondary credential at least at the institution that sponsors the program; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0E05F948B1EA479486B823D45DDD877B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is accredited by a nationally recognized accrediting agency or association recognized by the Secretary pursuant to part H of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1099a">20 U.S.C. 1099a et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2D2C433DC4548EB8328EA2E3B088060"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a construction and manufacturing-oriented apprenticeship college.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2568D606920342D89ABD39E188D9AC3D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>First generation college student</header><text>The term <term>first generation college student</term> has the meaning given the term in section 402A(h) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070a-11">20 U.S.C. 1070a–11(h)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE12918BC33646BA97C543C52581B274"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High school</header><text>The term <term>high school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H58382646885B402A858C25269F392107"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAC858EEB7AB4867B1BFF4183A212285"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The term <term>outreach</term> means communications and relationship-building opportunities undertaken by an eligible entity.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1C1DDD4EC3A44F2AB41F21FF08163560"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Recognized postsecondary credential</header><text>The term <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0884C7BF859494790DBB87FDB533F47"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Registered apprenticeship program</header><text>The term <term>registered apprenticeship program</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H96A52D5F95744353BDBF001EF1524B76"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Second language</header><text>The term <term>second language</term> means any language other than English, including Braille and American Sign Language.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CDAB9F220E448208683378A5CC3D027"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFEDD68B2FC5E4302B67A297EE741893F"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Underrepresented population</header><text>The term <term>underrepresented population</term> means an individual who is from a group whose gender, ethnic background, or national origin is not traditionally represented in registered apprenticeship programs.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

