<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCCBA80A5CA034898A6923AE17F932A99" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3959 IH: COVID–19 Commuter Benefits Distribution Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3959</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To allow for one-time distributions from certain transportation fringe benefit accounts.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8DDAE109730A4884BD54599AEC2EDEDD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H40CB27CE74C24910A34A0AFE252357B4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>COVID–19 Commuter Benefits Distribution Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HDF1BE355E3C54102884EFC45E5BD309C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of certain distributions from transportation fringe benefit accounts</header> <subsection id="HDF084F3DB2B741FCA5D97298CCAD0626"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any qualified payment from a specified transportation fringe benefit account—</text> 
<paragraph id="H973B6C8683494EC88D7F541CC4F380BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such qualified payment shall be includible in the gross income of the employee for the taxable year in which such qualified payment is made, and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39B888E87B8B44A197019E8456DA1537"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the determination of whether any other payment from such account is a qualified transportation fringe for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/132">section 132</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall be determined without regard to such qualified payment.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0148ADC6256241CFA2EE15DD2F2F11C8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified payment</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>qualified payment</quote> means a one-time payment made during the 6-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act from a specified transportation fringe benefit account to the employee for whose benefit such account is maintained but only to the extent that such payment does not exceed the lesser of—</text> <paragraph id="H8B3A5DA8275F4578BF941772CB10233C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the highest balance of such account during the period beginning on March 13, 2020, and ending on the date of the enactment of this Act, or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDCC92E9372DE46E6B5F36480B76F3A24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the balance of such account on the date of such one-time payment.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0D3830179D864C03B7F8A020287A3CF4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Specified transportation fringe benefit account</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>specified transportation fringe benefit account</quote> means, with respect to any employee, amounts set aside by such employee’s employer under a compensation reduction agreement which—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1D0469F745BD4E5889E45CC9B4AFE166"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides for payments to such employee of amounts which are excludible under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/132">section 132</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 as a qualified transportation fringe (determined after the application of subsection (a)), and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B7526AFD4D941BB8844261D04C05C19"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides that unused amounts at the end of a month may be carried forward to the succeeding month (subject to such requirements or limitations as such agreement, the Secretary of the Treasury, or the Secretary’s delegate, may provide).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

