<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC758DC5779484E1E80339519E4A19A10" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 814 IH: Protect Social Security and Medicare Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 814</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Committee on Rules</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To protect benefits provided under Social Security, Medicare, and any other program of benefits administered by the Social Security Administration or the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H81C6B8602162498799CB5C501C92836F" style="OLC">
<section id="HDA5C871759394F33BD4F34C00B45C7EC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Social Security and Medicare Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAEE5C0663FC045D59982CA1EA857CE95"><enum>2.</enum><header>Supermajority vote required to cut benefits administered by Social Security Administration or Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</header> <subsection id="H3DCC36AE21094ECFBB8AD8C6CA00B1E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Supermajority vote requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A bill or joint resolution, or any amendment offered to a bill or joint resolution, which contains any provision which, if enacted, would result in the reduction of any existing benefit provided or administered by the Social Security Administration or the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services may not be considered in the House of Representatives or the Senate unless two-thirds of the Members present and voting agree to a motion to consider the bill, joint resolution, or amendment with the provision included. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDC5FFC2B77944947BBF43E3D57DDC53C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception for payments to Medicare advantage plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) does not apply to any provision which, if enacted, would result in the reduction of any payment made to a Medicare Advantage plan under part C of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-21">42 U.S.C. 1395w–21 et seq.</external-xref>), but only if the provision would, if enacted, result in an increase in the amount of payments made for other purposes under title XVIII of the Social Security Act in an amount equal to or greater than the amount of the reduction in payment made to the Medicare Advantage plan.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H22DF04D7030D4C9987D4E6F363AA6EE2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determination of reduction of benefits</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">During the consideration of a bill, joint resolution, or amendment in the House of Representatives or Senate, any determination regarding whether a provision in the bill, joint resolution, or amendment would, if enacted, result in a reduction described in section 2(a) or a reduction or increase described in section 2(b) shall be made solely on the basis of a determination made by the Office of the Chief Actuary of the Social Security Administration.</text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


