<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFAA07D33A1EA4D0CA0E16EA8369D3A5F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2633 IH: Terrorist Organization Classification Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2633</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230417">April 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to submit to Congress a report on the designation of MS–13, Queen Nation, Sinaloa, Cartel Jalisco Nueva Generación, and Beltrán Leyva Organization as foreign terrorist organizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF171FE4B7345424C8732C967C441CF75" style="OLC"><section id="H014CBBF6E8414F8BAD8C56BCE1330E63" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Terrorist Organization Classification Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0CC17AD31D57427AB90A11D864B1E731"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on designation of certain drug cartels as foreign terrorist organizations</header><subsection id="HAA5E632D91F44513B20719F21780D20D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that each of the drug cartels set forth in subsection (b) meets the criteria for designation as a foreign terrorist organization as set forth in section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF9FE0E6419D43C6A47F62F2B8A0CFC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The Secretary of State shall designate each of the following Mexican drug cartels as a foreign terrorist organization under such section 219:</text><paragraph id="H8934B4C90FDA49DE8D639BDDB27BAB1D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>MS–13.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FEA1CA959714A4E933F5A0B176BF172"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Queen Nation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C736936C7534FCBADABB3E7883F730F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Sinaloa.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H733F59E00D3F40D18388F6A1943549B5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cartel Jalisco Nueva Generación.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C060453D77A47E89798A0E915E52183"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beltrán Leyva Organization. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEF7A99AE969042938F093721849CA089"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H51AA1B2321F648A3849FEC1E38B9A44E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress—</text><subparagraph id="H2852B9BBFDDA44B1993839A5A9AB4025"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a detailed report on each of the drug cartels listed in subsection (b) and any other cartels the Secretary may identify, including the criteria met for designation as a foreign terrorist organization as set forth in section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D080FF825694DD4B6CADEBD38755233"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each of the cartels designated under subsection (b), if the Secretary determines that the drug cartel does not meet the criteria set forth under such section 219, a detailed justification as to which criteria have not been met.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H62303D2D6AF3443D8354A07646EF953B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designation of additional cartels</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the submission of the report the Secretary shall designate any cartel or any faction thereof as a foreign terrorist organization listed in the report that met the criteria for designation as a foreign terrorist organization as set forth in section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H517B8EC04C53457B8F8F693427DA0137"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD7102165A8BB41E0816CE44C9ABA668B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H149EAC3447924CDFA4399FC66C12B8BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be made available only in electronic form and shall not be printed, except if a printed copy is requested by an office of the legislative branch.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07C60D37EF5349BB860DED160DDB23A0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H0B8CFBE76E7B42B5BC1D8C8F219BCDC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE8500F10B5A47CD91904D11E72C33C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H281B455E422247C69621D531697A11E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed to expand the eligibility for asylum of any alien by reason of the designation of a drug cartel as a foreign terrorist organization. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

