<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD35B95E5AF0E47C6A5C9BFA0B306D5F7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 660 IH: Ethan's Law</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 660</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, to require the safe storage of firearms, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDB59706BF1CE42B4BAECC1028FB2500F" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H345FAF8A8D2045B4840CD2A9C6BCA906"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Ethan's Law</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H639472085DA14B10AC965AA0A5FE8F0D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress find the following:</text><paragraph id="H057336D4EDBF48AE8CDA055A6634E915"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An estimated 4,600,000 minors in the United States live in homes with at least 1 unsecured firearm.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8B933F085464C089617C8724D276440"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Seventy-three percent of children under the age of 10 living in homes with firearms reported knowing the location of their parents’ firearms. Thirty-six percent of those children reported handling their parents’ unsecured firearms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD678FEA3B4764C128708AD1257A28004"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The presence of unsecured firearms in the home increases the risk of unintentional and intentional shootings. Over 75 percent of firearms used in youth suicide attempts and unintentional firearm injuries were stored in the residence of the victim, a relative, or a friend.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H410C77C7982846FDAD67C7D33E91FD83"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United States Secret Service and the Department of Education report that in 65 percent of deadly school shootings, the attacker obtained the firearm from his or her own home or that of a relative.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EAACC10BE134229A15D5E73484D8F25"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In the last decade, nearly 2,000,000 firearms have been reported stolen. In 2016 alone, 238,000 firearms were reported stolen in the United States. Between 2010 and 2016, police recovered more than 23,000 stolen firearms across jurisdictions that were used to commit kidnappings, armed robberies, sexual assaults, murders, and other violent crimes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H891F141AB6FB4F72BD3C4AB75AE0F189"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Higher levels of neighborhood gun violence drive depopulation, discourage commercial activity, and decrease property values, resulting in fewer business establishments, fewer jobs, lower home values, and lower home ownership rates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6D77EC335344CDB8458175FD915AE9B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The negative economic impact of gun violence in communities is tied directly to the national economy and interstate commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F3D1BCEC3A74695AB96EA68A81556AC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Congress has the power under the interstate commerce clause and other provisions of the Constitution of the United States to enact measures ensuring firearms are securely stored.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="HBF1CE2A5B6494483B27C19BA0B2070C8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Secure gun storage or safety device</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922(z) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC44982D7CD7E4A549CE0049A1CFE988D"><paragraph id="H21D1B881414C4445B8DD39D12F688085"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secure gun storage by owners</header><subparagraph id="H1641CA8A68BF45A2B4816AF8EC5EE777"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Offense</header><clause id="HD8064B98E02F4186A5565AF81207210A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), it shall be unlawful for a person to store or keep any firearm that has moved in, or that has otherwise affected, interstate or foreign commerce on the premises of a residence under the control of the person if the person knows, or reasonably should know, that—</text><subclause id="HD741EDE37E6641B690F1E2D4182D6190"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a minor is likely to gain access to the firearm without the permission of the parent or guardian of the minor; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC8B2B77322A44435BE5DD94994DE792E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a resident of the residence is ineligible to possess a firearm under Federal, State, or local law.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H27B1E45C9A9C433AA3FDA0C926F1AC98"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply to a person if the person—</text><subclause id="HA04C9E2950F744E9BA2C44FA69C4924C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>keeps the firearm—</text><item id="HBD1E353F49FF4458A760E5241D9066FC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>secure using a secure gun storage or safety device; or</text></item><item id="H18CBDA6212C547B0939ECEA60A2159E1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in a location that a reasonable person would believe to be secure; or</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H789C66EE4E6C491AAE25A1826044E828"><enum>(II)</enum><text>carries the firearm on his or her person or within such close proximity thereto that the person can readily retrieve and use the firearm as if the person carried the firearm on his or her person.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AFDCEFC9F6A407E9B8454E9BCBB5222"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Penalty</header><clause id="H76C4CB099882450BBB10B7809C16265B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person who violates subparagraph (A) shall be fined $500 per violation.</text></clause><clause id="HAF5C839DCAAC404C94F8432DCD2EA106"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Enhanced penalty</header><text>If a person violates subparagraph (A) and a minor or a resident who is ineligible to possess a firearm under Federal, State, or local law obtains the firearm and causes injury or death to such minor or resident, or to any other individual, the person shall be fined under this title, imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both.</text></clause><clause id="HB03B4B2CBB2D4AC2A8F70C47251D9CF5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Forfeiture of improperly stored firearm</header><text>Any firearm stored in violation of subparagraph (A) shall be subject to seizure and forfeiture in accordance with the procedures described in section 924(d).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H447A954AD0DA4F0D9B08BBF99CE363CB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Minor defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>minor</term> means an individual who is less than 18 years of age.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HB68AD295C12749DAB47090239F4D89DE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Firearm Safe Storage Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H561D831CDB2141C1A67158E4381CAAD6"><part id="HE0144ACF4C4644339C67F5AAD592848C" style="OLC"><enum>PP</enum><header>Firearm Safe Storage Program</header><section id="H1E450BA175A8476B9A8319E6F0F052E8"><enum>3061.</enum><header>Firearm Safe Storage Program</header><subsection id="HE4EEBADCF06941CD941EC0316B8B9CA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Attorney General shall make grants to an eligible State or Indian Tribe to assist the State or Indian Tribe in carrying out the provisions of any State or Tribal law that is functionally identical to section 922(z)(4) of title 18, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1FB525612F1342B6B251E771028040B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible State or Indian Tribe</header><paragraph id="H3A928FD8DB824710B378C1428CA6DC1A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), a State or Indian Tribe shall be eligible to receive grants under this section on and after the earliest date as of which—</text><subparagraph id="HABD06ED3280543C38B8EA1AE603B475A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State or Indian Tribe has enacted a law that is functionally identical to section 922(z)(4) of title 18, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE95595E1CCF44518D4E5EE153DF599C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the attorney general of the State (or comparable Tribal official) has submitted a written certification to the Assistant Attorney General stating that the law of the State or Indian Tribe reflects the sense of Congress in section 922(z)(4)(D) of such title 18.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB01D673F16844E4BCBD1077007A87C4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>First year eligibility exception</header><subparagraph id="H5C98CB9A23454FC98AD0665FAFAF5B57"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered State or Indian Tribe shall be eligible to receive a grant under this section during the 1-year period beginning on the date of enactment of this part.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57A2FD4A39734E34A2A503936A52893E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered State or Indian Tribe</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>covered State or Indian Tribe</term> means a State or Indian Tribe that, before the date of enactment of this part, enacted a law—</text><clause id="H9AC9777C1128494380921FBFC26CD71E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is functionally identical to section 922(z)(4) of title 18, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H37A3782FFEC243B293B8887C2098E974"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for which the attorney general of the State (or comparable Tribal official) submits a written certification to the Assistant Attorney General stating that the law of the State or Indian Tribe reflects the sense of Congress in section 922(z)(4)(D) of such title 18.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H40ABD90569C44C6C843088D03F189B6F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Funds awarded under this section may be used by a State or Indian Tribe to assist law enforcement agencies or the courts of the State or Indian Tribe in enforcing and otherwise facilitating compliance with any State or Tribal law functionally identical to section 922(z)(4) of title 18, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA075B2B96E214CF8B2D4C57652600CBC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible State or Indian Tribe desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Assistant Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing or accompanied by such information, as the Assistant Attorney General may reasonably require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H75276B5676CD4525B8B26B4E7E2C703F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Incentives</header><text>For each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027, the Attorney General shall give affirmative preference to all Bureau of Justice Assistance discretionary grant applications of a State or Indian Tribe that has enacted a law—</text><paragraph id="H23998A4AA53F49C890577940DA0EF336"><enum>(1)</enum><text>functionally identical to section 922(z)(4) of title 18, United States Code; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC15D77009604322B5FE892191923915"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for which the attorney general of the State (or comparable Tribal official) submits a written certification to the Assistant Attorney General stating that the law of the State or Indian Tribe reflects the sense of Congress in section 922(z)(4)(D) of such title 18.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H7D6097EBF1C54A5485BB4AB596F79C81"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of section 922(z) of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 3, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15EE76F92E764C7DB213EACDBC8FD61C"><subparagraph id="H1690C965B53344B090DE78FA7ACADA06"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Sense of Congress relating to liability</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><clause id="H7AC9A7CF841D4A6982F9E3EE165CA9DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>failure to comply with subparagraph (A) constitutes negligence under any relevant statute or common law rule; and</text></clause><clause id="H656A2F559EFD4FAEBE74A544726DD969"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>when a violation of subparagraph (A) is the but-for cause of a harm caused by the discharge of a firearm, such violation should be deemed to be the legal or proximate cause of such harm, regardless of whether such harm was also the result of an intentional tort.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H4ECBCD018EF44F6195308690FD6380E3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance, is held to be invalid, the remainder of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

