<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9496493E1E8B4D2EB237BC9AD8AF354E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1693 IH: Reporting Efficiently to Proper Officials in Response to Terrorism Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1693</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for joint reports by relevant Federal agencies to Congress regarding incidents of terrorism, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H684F50DE25774F6BB4773A39ED1E7202" style="OLC">
<section id="H1BA58C1EFD174F9EB82FD660643628EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reporting Efficiently to Proper Officials in Response to Terrorism Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the<quote><short-title>REPORT Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H594FB1B0594E44D7AEA751427D478BE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Duty to report</header> <subsection id="H31EE7B2F755B4ECAB283761E297308C3" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whenever an act of terrorism occurs in the United States, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Attorney General, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and, as appropriate, the head of the National Counterterrorism Center, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees, by not later than one year after the completion of the investigation concerning such act by the primary Government agency conducting such investigation, an unclassified report (which may be accompanied by a classified annex) concerning such act. Such unclassified report shall be posted on a publicly available website of such primary Government agency.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1F82A931977349A3B3B4573FFEBD4D46"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content of reports</header><text>A report under this section shall—</text> <paragraph id="HC21CB9AC588C46948B648F233E78CD11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include a statement of the facts of the act of terrorism referred to in subsection (a), as known at the time of the report;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC3BC2030CF53400EA9BC54FF5E662D82"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify any gaps in homeland or national security that could be addressed to prevent future acts of terrorism; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H877209AEBD714CE8AB1FDB21933D2521"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include any recommendations for additional measures that could be taken to improve homeland or national security, including recommendations relating to potential changes in law enforcement practices or changes in law, with particular attention to changes that could help prevent future acts of terrorism.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H40FF91BDBA6048C48F71124CC100768C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception</header>
<paragraph id="H3AB2F47AE14142CEA167D5BBE7F1CF95"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Attorney General, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, or, as appropriate, the head of the National Counterterrorism Center determines any information described in subsection (b) required to be reported in accordance with subsection (a) could jeopardize an ongoing investigation or prosecution, the Secretary, Attorney General, Director, or head, as the case may be—</text> <subparagraph id="H64E36F0E483E4A658A4A36E965E966C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may withhold from reporting such information; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD04A2FE1D3AD4424B11C28F8F3D8896A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall notify the appropriate congressional committees of such determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5E03724A6ABC4E1897B049CB2783F76A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Saving provision</header><text>Withholding of information pursuant to a determination under paragraph (1) shall not affect in any manner the responsibility to submit a report required under subsection (a) containing other information described in subsection (b) not subject to such determination.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9AE7ED8D952347B5947658F9F03466C9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HBF8254C471E547AD99717A89CD0A0898" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Act of terrorism</header><text>The term <quote>act of terrorism</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3077 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC72B3BA818564E24B1B101C16B2FBB05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HD07ADC2375694422B64C1EE8E5A7E70E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the House of Representatives—</text>
<clause id="H516B0AFBCAAF4C14BB8F1FA428E5F309"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security;</text></clause> <clause id="H78C3007C72E74B7083D50FE6E76E4673"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HDE86AD3F9F1B4FB6AC56A251B5669BAC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE86A884D5E3E493884E39EE193539DA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the Senate—</text>
<clause id="H6279AC342AF2429EB2B2EBDC0B6A4631"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs;</text></clause> <clause id="H4B1108CA37DE43ECA47CE2E2B99A4B50"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HA33DD9488C05483BB55BF4390356E215"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Select Committee on Intelligence.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7261890EB93C4BA9AFAD6446F82FCEFC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


