<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2A08E9E2C1E544D5914064B69FC24DBE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5108 IH: To abolish the United States Agency for International Development, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5108</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To abolish the United States Agency for International Development, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4D37DFB2F26E4C4D910B9D7A2F5CF0CD" style="OLC"><section id="H9E9344CF54254A84BF3C5735B88361D5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows: </text><paragraph id="H6AB00A274C5D4BB4B6914A1210E950F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States, in dealings with allies and adversaries, should engage in diplomacy and international relations that do not undermine the culture or tradition of other nations and peoples, but instead seek to develop working and friendly relationships relative to the interests of both parties with United States citizens chiefly in mind.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7245B9715FAE4A20A56F68C06650A38C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States Agency for International Development (USAID) operates several <quote>capacity building</quote> programs abroad and uses these programs to spread perverse ideology, that is antithetical to functioning, well-ordered society, across the globe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61F44394EA29466A89D2DBB7A1130D4C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>USAID uses United States tax dollars to push radical, leftist ideology abroad, going so far as to undermine foreign governments who do not adhere to the perverse ideology it espouses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H852DC6BCC2FC42C9B353F7753D77085C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>USAID does not act in the best interest of the United States or its people, nor the foreign nations it purposes to support.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6961A9FDD9CB4A81B55399D7505C30A0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>USAID aims to identify and address <quote>restrictive gender norms and inequalities … to foster the sustainability of results</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAD9FEA30D8C4C9085B30A3F018688B0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>USAID meddles in local elections, promoting the interests of <quote>women, youth, and other traditionally marginalized groups</quote> ahead of the interests of the other nations’ citizenry.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72E4863147924E4E9204EB1150FE7475"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The international affairs budget for the fiscal year 2022, passed by the House of Representatives in July 2021, for the United States Department of State and USAID, undid historical precedent by repealing the Helms Amendment that previously restricted United States foreign aid from paying for abortions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1532E48A796942C8B64DE72A79FA7485"><enum>(8)</enum><text>USAID has provided grants totaling $850,000 to the Bandhu Social Welfare Society for <quote>the rights of gender diverse people</quote> in Bangladesh.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA88F56DB2AEE4485BE820B2812FDB85E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>USAID has provided a $3.7 million grant to Aurat Publication and Information Service Foundation to <quote>provide support for gender equity programs</quote> in Pakistan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9CE167BC9EF44E59E285FBDB659F67B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Eighty-five grants totaling $138.1 million have been provided through USAID to the International Organization for Migration for <quote>humanitarian assistance</quote> to support open borders policy around the globe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36A701C712454554A50715EE0C102054"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Eight grants totaling $21.7 million have been provided through USAID to the Soros-backed Tides Center for various <quote>civil society innovation initiatives</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD55B44A155648B7BF83F4F9602BB9B6"><enum>(12)</enum><text>USAID has provided a $1 million grant to the United Nations Development Programme for supporting <quote>LGBTI human rights advocacy in Asia</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C08B306691441B19B8376FC95D3B670"><enum>(13)</enum><text>USAID has provided a $370,000 grant to Public Information and Need of Knowledge for promoting <quote>the human rights of LGBTI people in Armenian society</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8FA82919E1645A399AA288A0C1B83FF"><enum>(14)</enum><text>USAID has provided $1.1 million grant to the Pink Human Rights Defender for <quote>empowering the LGBTI community and their allies to advance human rights</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32751607A6FB4450A34F6E707217FEC0"><enum>(15)</enum><text>USAID has provided a $323,871 grant to Ryan Thomas Kaminski to serve as the United States personal service contractor LGBTI Advisor.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0AD8D586D03546C5ACD995F39C437D8F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Abolish the United States Agency for International Development</header><subsection id="HCA1405FBAEFF4BFFB6469250FC85DA15"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, no Federal funds may be made available to carry out any of the functions, duties, or responsibilities assigned or delegated to the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development pursuant to the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151">22 U.S.C. 2151 et seq.</external-xref>) or any other provision of law.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF8D2105B08B24E48861269DC67093A45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rescission of funds</header><text>The unobligated balance of each amount made available to the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act is rescinded. Any other assets or liabilities of the Agency as of such day shall be transferred to the Secretary of State.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

