<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H798C8673FAFD4FB3B4C3BFDD26D4294C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3464 IH: Affordable Homeownership Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3464</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To exempt small seller financers from certain licensing requirements.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAEDDF310EE124D9C9D879BA7F09F1BED" style="OLC"><section id="H1716912E5576455CB8EFEADDEE2CADC0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Affordable Homeownership Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8AEC5E9CCCD040A3BB7C79E9AD2D8D6B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD67265B0919F4CECBA1C297B91982D05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Real-estate owner financing is a transaction in which the owner of a real estate property provides financing for the buyer of that property and the buyer makes some form of a down payment to the owner, receives the deed or title to the home and then makes installment payments to the owner over a defined period of time.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10C30894021F44E19527F07F51BB3BB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Owner financers provide financing in lieu of the buyer choosing to obtain a loan from a bank.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC6FACD61537473E886EF5EFC3A7555F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The owner finance industry consists of small business owners who own real estate and provide financing on those properties to underserved buyers who cannot or would prefer not to obtain traditional bank or loan based financing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H581676A29DA84FE0B90F42443365C397"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Owner financers are governed by real estate and consumer protection laws (including, but not limited to, ability to repay, deceptive trade practices, and usury laws) of each State, as well as State and Federal fair housing and equal opportunity laws.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEC4FD48B1334F0A9532D3B323A62FDE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Using owner financing will benefit home values, increase neighborhood stabilization, and assist with family wealth creation through increased homeownership as more homes are sold with owner financing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H533327309955453EA7E95D62EA32A328"><enum>(6)</enum><text>None of the amendments made by this Act, are applicable to transactions known as Contracts for Deed or Land Installment Contracts that are not lawfully recorded, Lease Options, Lease with Option to buy and Rent to Own.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H931052396976475E9163B0C33C9E0DAE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Exception for owner financers with respect to loan originator license or registration requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1504 of the S.A.F.E. Mortgage Licensing Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5103">12 U.S.C. 5103</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HDFFA734C800C47BCBA277166C703FCFB" style="OLC"><subsection id="H105277193B8C4D4089C122BE935DCC2E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception for owner financers</header><text>The requirements of this title shall not apply to any person (other than a depository institution) who—</text><paragraph id="H5F14CDEF952A47CEBA16CF7919A4DE95"><enum>(1)</enum><text>extend credit with respect to not more than 24 residential mortgage loans in a 12-month period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H870644BA637045679A145A14D9DFA806"><enum>(2)</enum><text>only extend credit with respect to residential mortgage loans that are with respect to property that is owned by such person.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HA3532DA725AD4687B2E098BCCC1F4011"><enum>4.</enum><header>Exception for owner financers in the definition of mortgage originator</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subparagraph (E) of section 103(dd)(2) of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1602">15 U.S.C. 1602(dd)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H545A2081A52848718C039A3C736B3DA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (F) and (G) as subparagraphs (G) and (H), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F9E2F8E70454207AF013D3564C642BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (E) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H59C15D7652F54953B97AD92A42B45227" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H135C26661CB647DDA644338C6CC4DAD0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>does not include, with respect to a residential mortgage sale, a person or entity (including a corporation, partnership, proprietorship, association, cooperative, estate, or trust) if—</text><clause id="H6685A33659B84D1E860B86D97675BEEA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such a person or entity provides owner financing, in a 12-month period, for the sale of 24 properties; and</text></clause><clause id="H4CDADAFDE7FE4FCEB542455DD242D75E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each piece of real property described under clause (i) is owned by such a person or entity and serves as security for the loan or extension of credit, provided that such loan or extension of credit—</text><subclause id="HFD20C813D81F47A69343E21DB8CA22FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not made by a person or entity that has constructed, or acted as a general contractor for the construction of, a residence on the property in the ordinary course of business of such person, corporation, association, estate, or trust;</text></subclause><subclause id="H18BD058B27BF47359A3670CE4F320DC9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is fully amortizing;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB8E4B6C50F5F47F68EEC01B5768C0472"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is with respect to a sale for which the owner determines in good faith and documents that the buyer has a reasonable ability to pay the owner;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCDF79080B8B04A238C3FB9C0B629F340"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>has a fixed rate or an adjustable rate that is adjustable after 5 or more years, subject to reasonable annual and lifetime limitations on interest rate increases; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H31545B4213A948CAAC08F196279B6E22"><enum>(V)</enum><text>meets any other criteria the Bureau may prescribe by rule;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F489C903C0441C895C61B18361BA1D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (E) the following:</text><quoted-block id="HF0F6CAFBB7514922A78D725472A6B0A1" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H0C7070DFD9FC42E1B896A3F81087C993"><enum>(F)</enum><text>does not include, with respect to a residential mortgage loan or extension of credit, a person or entity (including a corporation, partnership, proprietorship, association, cooperative, estate, or trust) if—</text><clause id="H60C580F063DA43AEBD4D8E083A1DD37C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the loan or extension of credit is owner financed and is a consumer loan or extension of credit secured by a security interest on a manufactured home (as defined under section 603 of the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974); and</text></clause><clause id="HAED5BF6F99D347B8A2F100DC0C7A4A26"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each home described under clause (i) is owned by such a person or entity and serves as security for the loan or extension of credit, provided that such loan or extension of credit—</text><subclause id="H957CBF3775C54EE295F2BCC26696B0A6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not made by a person or entity that has manufactured the manufactured home;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF9DF1B26CC4D4321B5C395633A0A40CC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is fully amortizing;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF51B2F88B897454E8B84CC80B0FAB990"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is with respect to a sale for which the owner determines in good faith and documents that the buyer has a reasonable ability to pay the owner;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE6D0A00295734178A4D208E92C19FC09"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>has a fixed rate or an adjustable rate that is adjustable after 5 or more years, subject to reasonable annual and lifetime limitations on interest rate increases; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD76483B62E5D4D55AE856D0BA17E68D6"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets any other criteria the Bureau may prescribe by rule;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H5FD21B340B404A70B79056FBC8AC94D3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report on owner financing</header><subsection id="H3FC0A03B06B941B39DFDDE61EE201B22"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development and the Secretary of the Treasury shall jointly carry out a study on—</text><paragraph id="H6F39DBF7E7494521BA936EBB632C9885"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of homes bought for under $150,000 or 60 percent of the median home value in a given community, whichever is lower, in the United States by utilizing owner financing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5DE6DC1CCBD47D1B80AA82862ADA7E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of homes described under paragraph (1) financed by licensed mortgage brokers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF87AE4EE0DF34755A9CEC9EDAF12377F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the potential number of homes described under paragraph (1) which could be sold but aren’t, because owner financiers are unwilling, or from a practical standpoint unable, to comply with mortgage broker rules; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC20C7AAB2459480AA154EADAA46763D8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the potential benefit to home values and wealth creation if more homes were to be sold utilizing owner finance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4DBC3F8140A94086B2523B870B5560CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development and the Secretary of the Treasury shall jointly issue a report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate containing—</text><paragraph id="HA00AF859EFAF4C9C8319C1E5D027D44A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all findings and determinations made in carrying out the study required under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D4C333897F5461E9C716194BD7598D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>data on the number of transactions utilizing owner financing 20 years, 15 years, 10 years, and 5 years prior to the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

