<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD10EF717CD0D4B789A7151C709F7DF37" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>114 HR 6054 IH: Represent America Abroad Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6054</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that the United States diplomatic workforce at all levels reflects the diverse composition of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE906AA17EDBA4CC9B3416B116F2A3A49" style="OLC"><section id="H12B242157ACB459F870BC520A7E56C75" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Represent America Abroad Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HCC3EB8E0A7D241698DFCAD0529DBA18C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HE033C12ADB16489D9EBAE0C4838B48C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Department of State and the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) must continue to invest in policies to recruit, retain, and develop the best and brightest from the full spectrum of American society in order to be better positioned to advance United States interests abroad. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD513A200F0AB4ADBB1533FFE40019DCC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Foreign Service officers are America’s face to the world and in order to effectively advance American values on the world stage should represent the United States commitment to inclusion and diversity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3361990F43BF4F0A85785FA586B98B0A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Department of State and USAID must embrace policies that recruit professionals from the broadest possible pool of talent and retain them in order to have a Foreign Service that is the most effective and truly reflects the diversity of the United States. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4E4242E639642549328DF24D854EB3D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">February and June 2020 reports by the Government Accountability Office found barriers to a diverse and inclusive workforce within the ranks of the Foreign Service, especially at the mid-career and senior levels. Individuals who are racial or ethnic minorities comprise only 24 percent at the Department of State and 27 percent at USAID. At the executive level, individuals who are racial or ethnic minorities comprise only 13 percent at the Department of State and 17 percent at USAID. This means that the leadership is the least diverse level within the Foreign Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21C0483BF7284680A53837F49996072B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In the past, Secretaries of State have acknowledged the lack of workforce diversity and pledged to take concrete steps to address the problem. In 2017, then-Secretary of State Rex Tillerson recognized a great diversity gap in the Department of State and former Secretary of State John Kerry noted that in order to represent the United States, the Department of State must have a workforce that reflects the rich composition of its citizenry. Yet there has been no concrete plan to address the lack of diversity at the mid-career and senior levels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54F806D144344613B86AF51532AB9621"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">USAID has previously identified under-representation of specific groups in its workforce, but staffing gaps, partly due to a lack of senior leadership attention, prevent the agency from adequately addressing the issue.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4C3B619CA7FB45F9B017C5E3F000E74F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Declaration of national interest; statement of policy</header><subsection id="H1A95CD790C01465293DBC69AAF39C60B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Declaration of national interest</header><text>Congress declares that it is in the national interest of the United States to ensure that the members of the United States Foreign Service workforce be representative of the American people.</text></subsection><subsection id="H338FD0E8F8D444EABE1319803CB6392E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>It shall be the policy of the Department of State and of the United States Agency for International Development—</text><paragraph id="HCEC119D55593450DB8E1D5FC19199C09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to strengthen the Foreign Service workforce by bolstering the diversity of those who represent Americans abroad;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF99DBEAC96429C993B6A1A3314576A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to treat the people of the Foreign Service as its primary asset, and as such, hold as a central tenet making strides in increasing representation at all levels of the Foreign Service workforce to secure the country’s national interests; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD62E64445D04245BAC581BAF9F9BF36"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in accordance with the Foreign Service Act of 1980, to attract highly qualified, mid-career professionals who belong to historically excluded groups, through a pathway program for entry into the Foreign Service.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD2C89B948D6047669364084A38328B21"><enum>4.</enum><header>Modification of lateral entry foreign service program</header><subsection id="H0E1CDF6967674673A0D7F85A02DCF7FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Modification of lateral entry foreign service program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 404 of the Department of State Authorities Act, Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/323">Public Law 114–323</external-xref>; 130 Stat. 1928) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H69B4CE2EA9B64687AC2EABAB768B7430" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H4158414D35DF459780DF811B6379A73F"><enum>404.</enum><header>Lateral entry into the foreign service</header><subsection id="HB1DA0568052640A9BD87B0ED3A251645"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HCDBF5E587D6543CEAD13E4234D274A1C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Foreign Service should permit mid-career entry into the Foreign Service for qualified individuals who are willing to bring their talents and experiences to the work of the Foreign Service; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC5FB5C025554BD7B387092515ACD229"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the lateral entry program authorized under this section should be used to address disparities in retention and promotion as identified by barrier analysis and 2020 Government Accountability Office reports, by identifying, attracting, and welcoming into the Foreign Service highly qualified mid-career professionals who belong to historically excluded groups in terms of racial, ethnic, geographic, and gender diversity, and disability status.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H873E9B864E2A47CF9DD2C398C140CDF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a pilot program for lateral entry into the Foreign Service by mid-career professionals who belong to historically excluded groups in terms of racial, ethnic, geographic, and gender diversity, and disability status that—</text><paragraph id="H8B25591DBE70410E91713480B71A2E3D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is in full comportment with current Foreign Service intake procedures, including the requirement to pass the Foreign Service exam;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0C37DB120DB4482BFA70623570B34D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>requires only one directed assignment in a position appropriate to the grade level of the participant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64B7884E7977447CAD0710EDFEEC70C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>includes, as part of the required initial training, a class or module that specifically prepares participants in the pilot program for life in the Foreign Service, including conveying to such participants essential elements of the practical knowledge that is normally acquired during a Foreign Service officer’s initial assignments; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7928CBBA0A83423B9812F08F2C8FC8B4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>includes an annual assessment of the progress of the pilot program by a review board consisting of Department officials with appropriate expertise, including employees of the Foreign Service, in order to evaluate the success of the pilot program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3CAA54A175C4261ADFE2AA80D2A420D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes recruitment outreach for pilot program participation to—</text><subparagraph id="H7198E29FE78F41C7A705E9E295F8A193"><enum>(A)</enum><text>diversity officers in the private sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FAF492682D245B78CD4EAB24F02EC60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all members of the civil service of the Department and recognized Department affinity groups;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H665153EF3F89411C95BE644DA8A95AB4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the civil service of other national security related Federal agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07DA77675F2F4CC7AF7E41258F6C01B2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>professional associations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H435F631A09EF4FDBB71EF9F09B7848B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pilot program under subsection (b) shall be administered jointly by the Director General of the Foreign Service, the Director of Global Talent Management of the Department of State, and the Chief Human Capital Officer of the Office of Human Capital and Talent Management of the United States Agency for International Development.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF05641B8193E4AA7BEF0936DBF6EACCC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Elements</header><paragraph id="HB4F5EA5B5F294973AA808EFB47DB8570"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the following with respect to the pilot program under subsection (b):</text><subparagraph id="HE295187737E54BB2A8FDBF80881A5AE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Establish and publish eligibility criteria for candidates to participate in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0D5B6F836484971AE53101E7B385537"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Carry out countrywide recruitment efforts to attract highly qualified, mid-career professionals from among historically excluded groups, such as at and through the following:</text><clause id="HC9BFB1767EEC4F5C885A6B8649E0C26C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Community agencies and organizations.</text></clause><clause id="H9C34940095FB40088C8563340377EF83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Faith-based organizations.</text></clause><clause id="H82BA1E2EC7734108B8E5A13ADB97022D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Community events.</text></clause><clause id="HD01E0FB4A2234E78AF29433ADC2C440A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Professional associations.</text></clause><clause id="HEBAB99A246F543678C20825490EB60CB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Colleges and universities, including historically Black colleges and universities and other minority-serving institutions such as Hispanic-serving institutions, Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institutions, American Indian Tribally controlled colleges and universities, Alaska Native and Native Hawaiian-serving institutions, Tribal colleges and universities, Predominantly Black Institutions, and Native American-serving, Nontribal institutions.</text></clause><clause id="H4322BBDB11D241B0A0BC4C9DEAD21E9C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Diplomats in residence.</text></clause><clause id="H399A52FE01D145AFB4CA3A8F088BBA41"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Job fairs.</text></clause><clause id="H66534710A504430D92BD2848AF353568"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Newspaper/magazines/journals.</text></clause><clause id="HED4669CEF9E54189A8F57463646E9955"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Radio stations and programs.</text></clause><clause id="HA0638D8AF9154B40BE7457CBF9CCEBD0"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Websites, webcasts, podcasts, and other online channels.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H049D71AA9DC04609948C81FAEFA4EBDC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Include appropriate mentorship and other career development opportunities, such as leadership training, for participants in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8C187EB5EE74AB2BBF82ABAC467756C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Overall qualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing eligibility criteria under paragraph (1)(A), the Secretary shall seek highly qualified individuals who are mid-career professionals from the civil service and private sector belonging to historically excluded groups—</text><subparagraph id="H48255F70D4084E97B295401577481AED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with diverse work experience, who have capabilities, insights, techniques, and experiences that would serve to enrich the Foreign Service workforce and empower it to perform more effectively;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4D6FE6CD68B48E99BB690932B70EF51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with demonstrated knowledge of, experience with, and interest in United States foreign policy and national security and international affairs, including knowledge of the affairs, cultures, and languages of other countries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2442A60A733C4C37AEE73086DC8CC9C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with demonstrable leadership skills and the potential for further growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EB38039880F459686275061B347920C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that demonstrate a track record of collaboration, team-building, and stakeholder management skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB20E10EB57304AB68ABFBA7A4256404A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>with demonstrated capacity for critical thinking and analytical skills, including the ability to synthesize information into clear and concise recommendations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H237313147F07407F9533E286CF17C992"><enum>(F)</enum><text>with strategic thinking, and ability to solve complex problems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57E7E0EC5F82404ABBE1045FBC476E48"><enum>(G)</enum><text>with flexibility, adaptability, and determination; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FA6348E1AE64205B1FBEDC9B7543938"><enum>(H)</enum><text>who are United States citizens with worldwide service availability and who are able to obtain appropriate security and medical clearances.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE939CBC82AF84313A75EFCA359344504" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advancement from program</header><text>Candidates who are accepted into the pilot program under subsection (b) in accordance with the qualifications and requirements of this section shall have the opportunity to advance to the Foreign Service oral assessment for potential entry as the appropriate class of mid-level Foreign Service officer in accordance with the candidate’s professional qualifications with a goal of not less than 50 percent of such participants per year being so placed. </text></subsection><subsection id="H57900C708A294FEAAD4874721B6A06DD" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Represent America Abroad Act of 2023</short-title>, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the status of the pilot program under subsection (b). Each such report shall include the following information with respect to the previous year:</text><paragraph id="H7399E51A18214A4EACBBDE72CDBB5F8B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of accepted and unaccepted applicants to the pilot program, and the number of accepted applicants who began participating in the pilot program, and the number of accepted applicants who began participating in the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B35F9B0EBF94AE0B5B4166C4D89EB3D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Anonymized information on the backgrounds of accepted pilot program applicants and participants with respect to education and prior work experience, ethnicity, and sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3C2860796224B4C8CA4CF6A87C09C8B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The number of pilot program participants who have advanced from the pilot program to a placement in the Foreign Service, disaggregated by education, prior work experience, ethnicity and sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72303873474C4D30B6E6D6906EA15801" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A disaggregation by Foreign Service assignment, cone and post or mission (including identifying whether the post is hard-to-fill) assigned to each pilot program participant who has advanced to a placement in the Foreign Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8582547155764BC6AF71438E8A2B2B65" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The grade level at which each pilot program participant who has advanced to a placement in the Foreign Service entered the Foreign Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD236A77A35142CCB55A511B9263B583" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The structure and operation of the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB576EA1FD17645A0A48F6BD605B8D2FF" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Attrition rates and retention data with respect to the pilot program, including information on how such data compares to the data reported in the most recent prior submission of such report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D0E1CE3517D4A0E86E19C80F046E18E" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Information on recruiting efforts for the pilot program, including the resources allocated to outreach, as well as where, how, and when outreach will be carried out.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB532C28B53F84D5CAA6C89B5C303586E" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Information on efforts to improve the efficacy of the pilot program and promote retention of program participants.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E1105BCDE6C411484E5A0FCEC1AD640"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Longitudinal data</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H0812FA6047DB4DB3B220F084FEABED14"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collect and maintain data on the career progression of each program participant for the length of each participant’s Foreign Service career; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7882E807785F45E7AABE0CA946034359"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make the data described in paragraph (1) available to the appropriate congressional committees upon request.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H376B65A7C1194C27A6F6999524018B95"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The pilot program under subsection (b) shall be for an initial duration of 3 years, but may be renewed for an additional 5-year period following the end of such initial duration.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDB609759A6144E54A2CF3E92CF793E87" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Mid-Career professional defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>mid-career professional</term> means an individual who has the skills and experience to serve as a mid-level Foreign Service officer (class 3, 2, or 1) and who meets any of the following criteria, consistent with the merit-based principles and core precepts set forth in the Foreign Affairs Manual and Handbook and in accordance with applicable requirements of the Foreign Service Act of 1980:</text><paragraph id="H28530BE68DA3441FBC19D0344357615B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An individual with at least 8 years of professional experience and a bachelor’s degree from an accredited college or university in selected fields of study representing the needs of the Department of State, including public policy, public administration, international law, international relations, political science, foreign languages, business administration, economics, history, sociology, geography, social or cultural anthropology, statistics, or the humanities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2823828EE11A4821BA5009ED0D064831" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An individual with at least 7 years of professional experience and a master’s degree from an accredited college or university in selected fields of study representing the needs of the Department of State, including any field specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H975D7318B17049378FAD6944DA96C68C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An individual with at least 5 years of professional experience and doctoral degree from an accredited college or university in selected fields of study representing the needs of the Department of State, including any field specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF79D6F8E076246789282930FA5BD0EF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall commence the implementation of the pilot program under section 404(b) of the Department of State Authorities Act, Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/323">Public Law 114–323</external-xref>; 130 Stat. 1928), as amended by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

