<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4487C60BF82E42BDB8D00ACBD4FDB74D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3508 IH: Comprehensive Southern Border Strategy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3508</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a comprehensive southern border strategy, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H192CA4B0B40A4719AD20C9177F02E199" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBB91A2E3A09D4ADD8F06B5E854130102" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Southern Border Strategy Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H6BA60D9FD3D2443B9BF4B9539B914B30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Comprehensive southern border strategy</header> <subsection id="H13A0812117614DE8A0901154F63B4540"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Comprehensive strategy</header> <paragraph id="H6CB0DD2962634A55966974E1FBF9C946"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a comprehensive southern border strategy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2963EC022554CED810B1298103AAF34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The strategy submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H09BF9358BC0D45A885A262FC136A53F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive overview of the current security risks present along the southern border, including relating to deficiencies along the physical border, aerial and maritime vulnerabilities, and the presence of illegal tunneling.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4F822CB524AE436CACA09BC51A4C5463"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A substantive review of the Department of Homeland Security’s technology, tools, or other devices used to combat the trafficking of drugs across the southern border, with an emphasis on fentanyl and related substances.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA684361594F8456C95017D8690512CBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A thorough outline of the Department’s technology, tools, or other devices used to combat human trafficking across the southern border by international criminal organizations.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2FC3512F9C1B468299E0B59D01511BBB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A list of known physical barriers, technologies, tools, and other devices that can be used to achieve and maintain situational awareness and operational control along the southern border.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC644F76E42EA45A3B981AEC5A3D62ED7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A projected per mile cost estimate for each physical barrier, technology, tool, and other device included on the list required under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H536B383C00854903B440E4DDEE1929E9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A detailed account of which type of physical barrier, technology, tool, or other device the Department of Homeland Security believes is necessary to achieve and maintain situational awareness and operational control for each linear mile of the southern border.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H625047BB284F4C51859CA990B3E68395"><enum>(G)</enum><text>An explanation for why such physical barrier, technology, tool, or other device was chosen to achieve and maintain situational awareness and operational control for each linear mile of the southern border, including the following:</text> 
<clause id="H71FAB8D8E1814CD6A63F6F6BF4C68A48"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The methodology used to determine which type of physical barrier, technology, tool, or other device was chosen for such linear mile.</text></clause> <clause id="HD6CE8F23FBCC4FDDBD0E08F3DAE62E27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An examination of existing manmade and natural barriers for each linear mile of the southern border.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H99EC8438472D46ABA1D68F26DF3A3C9B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The information collected and evaluated from the following:</text> <subclause id="HF667DB95B8CF4D84839CA528C362ECFB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The appropriate U.S. Customs and Border Protection Sector Chief.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF9B5A31733F14538A0D0875A919CE050"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The appropriate State Governor.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6E969330DAE247BEB3C0C0E788578549"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Local law enforcement officials.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9E21A8B4F270484B8D9542D46A3EE18E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Private property owners.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF31BA421554E497F920E4250A512A556"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Other affected stakeholders.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA5BDD4182C0A4176AC97D40AA1D78073"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A per mile cost calculation for each linear mile of the southern border given the type of physical barrier, technology, tool, or other device chosen to achieve and maintain operational control for each linear mile.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC4AEFAD45D9B468B881A871A25F5B70F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>A cost justification for each time a more expensive physical barrier, technology, tool, or other device is chosen over a less expensive option, as established by the per mile cost estimates required in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5BCAA285BCA244E0AA0A4E8575B76BB8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HD515A1C976604AF9934F8BFD9C3379EA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Operational control</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>operational control</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2(b) of the Secure Fence Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1701">8 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/367">Public Law 109–367</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD71DBB5FEC7434F9DB938EF78C6051D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Situational awareness</header><text>The term <quote>situational awareness</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 1092(a)(7) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

