<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-type="olc" bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-SIL23B02-J5Y-K4-RYL"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5896 IH: United Negro College Fund, Inc. Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5896</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill </action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc display="yes"> Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To award a congressional gold medal to the United Negro College Fund, Inc. and the institutions that make up its membership on the occasion of its 80th year of existence. </official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body style="OLC" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H4839C9FE1A1C4775A19F907ABEEBD631"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="idd87a41c93aaa4e698a5868621e86269c"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United Negro College Fund, Inc. Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAF3465B729414A84A25A428EA17D0643"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9EF2F65B20C84C248D08752AAD381FDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Historically Black Colleges and Universities (referred to in this Act as <quote>HBCUs</quote>) were established during a time when African Americans seeking to further their education was a dangerous undertaking and illegal in many areas of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HECCBB679D8BE4929A4649E22B4442E2C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>HBCUs initially educated the progeny of slaves, and the graduates of those institutions have been impactful as 80 percent of all African-American judges, 80 percent of all African-American doctors and dentists, 50 percent of all African-American lawyers, 50 percent of all African-American professors, 50 percent of all African-American public school teachers, 40 percent of all African-American Members of Congress, and 40 percent of all African-American engineers, while educating only 10 percent of all African-American students in higher education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H126A182804A9464099A04754EF3A5A16"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a United Negro College Fund, Inc. (referred to in this Act as the <quote>UNCF</quote>) study, the annual economic impact of HBCUs is over $14,800,000,000 a year, the institutions generate 134,090 jobs for their local and regional economies, and 1 annual class of HBCU graduates constitutes over 50,000 graduates with a lifetime earnings of $130,000,000,000, 56 percent higher than what they could have expected to earn without their HBCU college credentials.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8A014806674D4B4F81730155DE58803F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The UNCF, established in 1944, is the premiere fundraising and scholarship organization in assistance of HBCUs and African-American students.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD25802506D864A578B60C19B87DCF79D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In its 80 years of existence, the UNCF has raised over 7,000,000,000 in private donations for HBCUs and African-American students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80B1588BD84F434CB8D6B93CCBD08F38"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On an annual basis, the UNCF awards $100,000,000 in scholarships to 10,000 students at hundreds of colleges and universities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30FE8E8857324A3D9D83AA8FB8A99EC5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>UNCF also provides grants to its members, which include: Miles College, Oakwood University, Stillman College, Talladega College, Tuskegee University, Philander Smith College, Bethune-Cookman University, Edward Waters University, Florida Memorial University, Clark Atlanta University, Interdominational Theological Center, Morehouse College, Paine College, Spelman College, Dillard University, Xavier University of Louisiana, Rust College, Tougaloo College, Bennett College, Johnson C. Smith University, Livingstone College, Saint Augustine University, Shaw University, Wilberforce University, Allen University, Benedict College, Claflin University, Morris College, Voorhees College, Fisk University, Lane College, Huston-Tillotson University, Jarvis Christian College, Texas College, Wiley College, and Virginia Union University. The fundraising efforts of the UNCF also positively impact each HBCU and African-American student at many non-HBCU institutions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E06233D2C9C4AC4BC86975D63033318"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The iconic motto of the UNCF, <quote>A Mind Is a Terrible Thing To Waste</quote>, is commonly known throughout the lexicon in the United States and reminds us as a nation to strive for our individual fullest ability and the highest national ideals through philanthropy and achievement.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H46B0B77715F744A18B80592288FC53E4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header> 
<subsection id="H67919F304E7041B794D17404AF1810B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the presentation, on behalf of Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design to the UNCF and the institutions that make up its membership.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDA7B9BCA6F4F44D7BF8B854F785CE08A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the presentation described in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike the gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H42872F76898F45A8B050A2FECC07E2EA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the costs of the medals, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section> <section id="HC9257E37B648472D87D3D3C83D7C7F42"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> It is the sense of the Congress that the United States Mint should expedite production of the gold medal and duplicate medals under this Act, so that the UNCF and its member institutions can be recognized in a timely manner for its 80th anniversary.</text></section> 
<section id="HCDD9B43642C940888AAA69E3313C045F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Status of medals</header> 
<subsection id="HD8A1E6F2DF1A444EB2E187B7DA3B843E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The medals struck under this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0EABCF60E5134256B54649FE15B802E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4C883AAECCF47F9809AACE7751CCCE8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header> 
<subsection id="H869943AD59714FFBA21B6DC5E7B885E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7C4407E14D49495A9F76106431B68150"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


