<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H71B102A54D144FDBA1B6EF8D983824F4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 4567 IH: Strengthening the Uyghur Forced Labor Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4567</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref> to strengthen the requirements under that Act.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC412FF89618E40D9AFF1D4A4E55057F6" style="OLC"><section id="H9AE88D49C11A4EC1AAD38E3D755C91BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening the Uyghur Forced Labor Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1C173445AB0C4BE5AC2E9E3B0553AB44"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments to <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref></header><subsection id="HE867C8E1A5384037BC60E499D61C0C30"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref> (135 Stat. 1526) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3FE235085017406E98F30890DEFFBAFA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(2)—</text><subparagraph id="H336DC96365264A85904B977DC8E20EFE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>of <quote>pairing assistance</quote> and <quote>poverty alleviation</quote> or any other government labor scheme that includes the forced labor of</quote> and inserting <quote>of all state-sponsored labor programs, including programs associated with <quote>surplus labor transfer</quote>, <quote>poverty alleviation</quote>, <quote>mutual aid</quote>, <quote>Xinjiang Aid</quote>, and <quote>re-education</quote> programs targeting</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC72F99C782B84DF79769D5F8F571CE64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause id="HE6344C55D99F49E6AA20813E9267367F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by adding at the end before the semicolon the following: <quote>or receive labor under any of the programs described in subparagraph (A)</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HF3A79B509411450B91FD8FE52C871BF2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H767B69AF5C9742E7AE57AA7FE52CEC15" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H1510F22461FE4BBDB6AEC37C712B574F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of entities working with the regional, prefectural, county, or local government agencies of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region or the Xinjiang Production and Construction Corps to recruit, transport, transfer, harbor, or receive forced labor under any of the programs described in subparagraph (A) outside of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region; </text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H02BD60029C57482DBF7027E086A765C9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking <quote>described in clause (iii)</quote> and inserting <quote>mined or manufactured by entities listed in clause (i) or (ii)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H083D4C0540844617A8F5089A38D424DA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by amending clause (v) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB84514324D934997817C968C4C11DA45" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H00E2ED7BE7FD47D5969CA6493AF31A52"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of facilities and entities outside of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region that source material from the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region or from persons or entities working with regional, prefectural, county, or local government agencies of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region or the Xinjiang Production and Construction Corps or receive labor under any of the programs described in subparagraph (A); </text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD429F3C3AA92453FB0FAAA1CC7871C8F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2), by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCCC5135EBD844D2B9D59CADB2B4E439C" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>Each such update—</text><subparagraph id="H530AAE5595514562BEA520B0017D6A1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall give effect to all determinations made by U.S. Customs and Border Protection regarding whether the statutory prerequisites for the rebuttable presumption under section 3 have been met, whether any such presumption has been rebutted, and which companies have exported goods found to be made in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H409B9D60E37442B7A2BF2FB3E9BF513D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include additional entities, facilities, and products to, or removal of entities, facilities, and products from, the lists required by clauses (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), and (v) of subsection (d)(2)(B), and may include revisions to the processes and standards for doing so, provided that such processes and standards are explained fully in the revised strategy and that they do not impede giving effect to determinations made by U.S. Customs and Border Protection as required by subsection (d)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85C3C9C61DDB4BE6BC3B1BE2BA9F103C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 7(2) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref> (135 Stat. 1532) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HEEC6524476EA41B1A74640EB3D01F5E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59965E2C747B4D5EB00F546B01B9EC51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53D3953B14B54887919D8610D1B72ED8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA4F9E977ECA3427DBAFC0AA62182EE83" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H6A020AA64F8246358F8829B1189808FE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes all state-imposed labor programs, including programs associated with <quote>surplus labor transfer</quote>, <quote>poverty alleviation</quote>, <quote>mutual aid</quote>, <quote>Xinjiang Aid</quote>, and <quote>re-education</quote> programs targeting Uyghurs, Kazakhs, Kyrgyz, Tibetans, or members of other persecuted groups inside or outside of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region or similar programs of the People’s Republic of China in which work or services are extracted from Uyghurs, Kazakhs, Kyrgyz, Tibetans, or members of other persecuted groups through the threat of penalty or for which the Uyghurs, Kazakhs, Kyrgyz, Tibetans, or members of other persecuted groups have not offered themselves voluntarily.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

