<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4CD3631866454B7B91E24532C6A59870" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 634 IH: Fixing Announcements for Intermittent Remapping and Notification Expectations to Stop Surprises in Flood Insurance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 634</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230130">January 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator to provide certain notices to property owners when undertaking remapping in geographic areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H02470C077B864842A8B19C948AEC405F" style="OLC"><section id="H588C371CF1694C78B9A340EF01D716DB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fixing Announcements for Intermittent Remapping and Notification Expectations to Stop Surprises in Flood Insurance Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAIRNESS in Flood Insurance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1E6363F8B1A741C0BE683FD70D5EFEFE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mapping notice requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1360 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4101">42 U.S.C. 4101</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H49D52AAA8F8248648F14C2C6FE56154D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HC1950900F09B422680A094682536EA29"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Additional mapping notice requirements</header><paragraph id="HD32F6049B3634AB4B63F9C3B776BCE7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice of remapping</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator seeks to revise or update any floodplain areas and flood risk zones identified, delineated, or established under this section, the Administrator shall provide notice of such intended remapping, not less than 15 days before such remapping process is to begin, to each owner of a property in the geographic area being remapped, including each owner of a property located in an area within the geographic area being remapped that previously was not designated as having special flood hazards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02D204EE2DB940929E3C9B55CBBF9820"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice of remapping appeals process</header><subparagraph id="HDA67744A7FC342209E77DBBA2A2596F5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>At the start of the appeals process</header><clause id="HF4B9A9F1454045D29F5DD2631F7B8BFA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After completing a revision or update of any floodplain areas and flood risk zones identified, delineated, or established under this section, and prior to the implementation of such revision or update, the Administrator shall, not later than 30 days before the date on which the appeals process begins, provide notice to each owner of a property in the geographic area being remapped, including each owner of a property located in an area within the geographic area being remapped that will be included in a special flood hazard area.</text></clause><clause id="HFB3073CF98964458A00A2955B27EA98A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The notice required under this subparagraph shall—</text><subclause id="H6B3F5E82CBAD41B2916575BE20A0136A"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notify the property owner that the remapping process has been completed;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5884A224349C4E8DA5D04808DD5382C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a property owner whose property is within a special flood hazard area, notify the property owner that flood insurance may be required and notify the property owner of the approximate cost of such flood insurance;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBEEF55A6A01745B2A60BCE13A29290E4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>notify the property owner that the remapping appeals process has begun; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H67F692F38D4E49E2B6CFCF9899B1F81A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>provide information to the property owner about the appeals process.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE69B68545D20405598C781EEDA209F74"><enum>(B)</enum><header>At the end of the appeals process</header><clause id="H38A0167EF7B44DCEA1CB556FCE9FBCA4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After completing a revision or update of any floodplain areas and flood risk zones identified, delineated, or established under this section, the Administrator shall, not later than 15 days after the conclusion of the appeals period, provide notice to each owner of a property in the geographic area being remapped, including each owner of a property located in an area within the geographic area being remapped that will be included in a special flood hazard area, that the remapping process has been completed and that the appeals process has concluded.</text></clause><clause id="H48E00EB8C106458B9CD03AF820F05353"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The notice required under this subparagraph shall—</text><subclause id="HB918949A38B74B7EA9B28897E457BB23" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a property owner whose property is within a special flood hazard area, notify the property owner that flood insurance may be required and notify the property owner of the approximate cost of such flood insurance;</text></subclause><subclause id="H238C0294D33B408C831CD5E48CA2E66E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>notify the property owner of the date on which the appeals process for the remapping concluded; and </text></subclause><subclause id="H97F077A1D1524DE7BB1E168449913368"><enum>(III)</enum><text>inform the property owner about additional avenues for recourse, including letters of map amendment and letters of map revision. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFB77E9FAE944A898565B86ED2EF758A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice requirements</header><subparagraph id="HB7424DDD6CE04532AD4C99169471FEDA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to any notice requirement under this subsection, the Administrator shall—</text><clause id="H0F1129ED18DB456F843B728D4DB3541A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide notice by mail in the form of a letter; and</text></clause><clause id="H2A3AF667A2B245C6941532FCF1060840"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>where possible, ensure that a reasonable attempt is made to send the letter to the mailing address of the owner of the property to which the notice relates if such address is different than the address of the property to which the notice relates.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32E7E0E0BC6C4B8C894D45395F38DA04"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contracting limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may not contract with a State, Tribe, or any political subdivision thereof, including a State department, agency, or local government, to provide notices required under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

