<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2A21BC9C00374B8DB71D386D053D8C1B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6144 IH: Combatting Fentanyl Poisonings Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6144</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to authorize grant programs to combat fentanyl poisonings.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2E1B0155C9FF4DD7851477F71B5D8FE3" style="OLC"><section id="HBDC4703847F64972805451CA376D193D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combatting Fentanyl Poisonings Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1206210A9DAC4C84A66A3087DF513919"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant programs to combat fentanyl poisonings</header><subsection id="H66B365891C96452DAB0C27E730A77B6E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant programs authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (34 U.S.C 10151 et seq.) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HADC549D3AB1F42949682093229E3E4F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 509 as section 510; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82C2BA92CED1449A9550072EAC2BEF03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 508 the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1AFA84724F5247139B6D21EA175E9EA5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFF8E886E0CC74358A1EF8D242B2DE6BA"><enum>509.</enum><header>Grant programs to combat fentanyl poisonings</header><subsection id="HCBA758EEDBF94EB190C01B42B5C43BA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants To prevent the sale of controlled substances on social media platforms</header><paragraph id="HF28E33FD15A34D708ABA886C87E403C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>The Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance, and in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, is authorized to award grants to State and local law enforcement agencies to assist such agencies in planning, designing, establishing, or operating locally based, proactive programs to combat the sale, marketing, or distribution of controlled substances (as such term is defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>)) using social media platforms, including programs that—</text><subparagraph id="H05B56B87A515487CA34B80971F8F227C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prioritize the arrest of individuals who use social media platforms as a primary source of marketing or distributing controlled substances;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2AEA74698F94A63A1C92881252F8BF1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide education and training, including online training resources, to school personnel, clinicians, and the public in order to—</text><clause id="H650D569DCED54CA69D718458BA41253B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educate such persons on the dangers of ingesting controlled substances purchased using a social media platform, especially the risk of fentanyl poisoning from a counterfeit substance (as such term is defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="H97F5EA2AA36346D6BDDD4222ED846906"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>educate parents or personnel who are charged with the well-being and safety of children on commonly used methods of communication between online drug dealers and potential victims.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60553552954D41F291DAF3A3C1B1162F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The head of a State or local law enforcement agency seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General an application, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4EEDBDB33B0D4D7EB1A77B51B1AD78ED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants To increase public awareness about the dangers of fentanyl</header><paragraph id="H751E4248628545DCB378F895A953DD9E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>The Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance, and in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, is authorized to award grants to non-profit organizations to assist such organizations in designing, establishing, and operating public education and awareness campaigns that teach individuals about the dangers of fentanyl.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5C84144F0EF4C1FAE0B282F253BF28F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants awarded under this section may be used for the following purposes: </text><subparagraph id="HDE6CE3AA7CCF41B489602D3B5F690A2D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Providing transportation for parents or immediate family members of individuals who died from fentanyl poisoning to speak at public events or awareness campaigns. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AE77CD6F40B4D238EA2C893479A5E80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Creating, producing, and disseminating educational materials related to the dangers of fentanyl, such as documentaries, pamphlets, books, and infographics. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFB1CB0318CA4D51B2A30B482CED1E78"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Providing counseling or mentorship services to individuals who have had a friend or a family member die from fentanyl poisoning. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF539ADF84A254A52951ED80293C811E0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Providing naloxone or overdose reversal education and training services to parents and school employees. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0562E1ABF18144D49DF716BD60104E01"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants awarded under this section may not be used to purchase harm reduction services or supplies, such as substance abuse test kits, sharps or medication disposal kits, medication lockboxes, supplies to promote sterile injection (including syringes and drug paraphernalia), safer smoking kits (including pipes, pipettes, and drug paraphernalia), and written educational materials on safer injection practices, except that such funds may be used to purchase naloxone, naloxone administration supplies, or naloxone administration training. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8F469EAC6CB46F3935B77EF2400D858"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The maximum amount of a grant under this subsection is $50,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9F7E1AC67E34CFBB8779E906CC8B557"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization that is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF055FC8B62F47E2BE44E00DA85070D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reserved funds</header><text>Section 506(a) of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10157">34 U.S.C. 10157(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HB24F5F694E664CA4AE5CBF223263A56B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H830814F1D6ED44C3B367A3C71E0D2188"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9071744F579A4DB29BF4862142BD3583"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7917444CB8194B35B0D3BFF30F5C6FEB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H8D520FD45F6E47FC981F3367C775E671"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$10,000,000 for grants under section 509(a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04DBBE6022F14C349DFCA00436C40A18"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$2,000,000 for grants under section 509(b). </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

