<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5AEEF1223EF14E3EB3F2AB6F1FCCF802" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6139 IH: To direct the Postal Service to establish a post office at 73 West Stewart Road in Lathrop, California, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6139</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Postal Service to establish a post office at 73 West Stewart Road in Lathrop, California, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5CE853B794E94FB196F09805EFE36B8F" style="OLC"><section id="HFF49C3C282CD41FD9405491AABEE9A5C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establish post office at 73 West Stewart Road in Lathrop, California</header><subsection id="H7BF2CFA429B5458D9C987AFA13F877FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service, using the authority under section 401 of title 39, United States Code, shall seek to establish a post office at 73 West Steward Road in Lathrop, California, not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H034715DB047948A7B64505B04BC57721"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Good faith negotiations</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Postal Service shall seek to enter into good faith negotiations with all owners of the location described in such subsection to acquire or lease such location for the purpose of establishing a post office at such location.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAA2A90419EFA4CD6945C0795C4B7F04C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Borrowing limit exception</header><text>To the extent necessary to establish a post office at the location described in subsection (a) pursuant to this Act, obligations issued for the costs of establishing such post office shall be disregarded with respect to limitations under section 2005(a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

