<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H213E3CE5761347B1AB2EF9F7339DA295" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4354 IH: Accountability of Leaders in Education to Report Title IX Investigations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4354</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that certain incidents involving a covered employee that are reported to the title IX coordinator at an eligible institution of higher education have been reviewed by the president of the institution and not less than 1 additional member of the institution’s board of trustees, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5A105E9FF3144234B55D914A804860BC" style="OLC"><section id="H605286B285BF4A6FBC30B5CCF56AF4C2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accountability of Leaders in Education to Report Title IX Investigations Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ALERT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H31362E958AFE472BAAD8FDA939C6516F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Review of title IX investigations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 487(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E9C2DE4F83A43B4B7052CB365225037" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H207476C672E649CAA7B51CE19C288635"><enum>(30)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0BC72B2A88F3490B97291B512D072D7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The institution will submit an annual certification to the Secretary affirming that—</text><clause id="H127E2269093C4AEEAF568866B26A013F" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the president of the institution (or the equivalent officer) and not less than 1 additional member of the institution’s board of trustees (or a designee of the board) have completed a comprehensive review of any incident involving a covered employee that was reported to the title IX coordinator at that institution in the previous 12 months involving an offense described in section 485(f)(8)(A)(i); and</text></clause><clause id="H134EAD92B75943C9B0B41CF67C2598E5" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the individuals described in clause (i) who completed the comprehensive review did not interfere with or influence any investigation or disposition relating to the reported incident.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04BABA4DFB084EAEAF74724B55FFF22E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In this paragraph—</text><clause id="H9AB9B8CED7BA4B9E9B229168D83FB6E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the term <term>comprehensive review</term> means a review that includes, at a minimum—</text><subclause id="H59F584BCB90D4B189310B8A0257F00B4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a review of—</text><item id="H50DF350D879E4E84AE12968CCEEB6B5B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>material findings of fact relating to the incident that was reported to the title IX coordinator;</text></item><item id="H31F5BF18628C4A2F844277DDD9B9ABAF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the basis for any conclusions about whether a covered employee violated a policy of the institution; and</text></item><item id="HC72B202ECC584636BD087DEB1149395F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the disposition of any complaints arising from the reported incident, including any sanctions imposed on a covered employee; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H5C2D4A1973A041C1928B88C32DA77499"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the redaction of the identity of the individual reporting such incident from such review, and a prohibition against sharing the identity of the individual without the consent of such individual;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H480665F9AD78427AA49660491BAE6460"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the term <term>covered employee</term>—</text><subclause id="HB8E9674B36C24016B957D96D163CF35F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>means—</text><item id="H85CBF2CE62B34FC1B02875417681EB87"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a full-time employee of the institution; or</text></item><item id="H4F44F0B69FC24DA48B0911E5DE8446E2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an individual who was acting as an employee of the institution, or who was paid by an entity contracting with the institution and acting on behalf of the institution, at the time of the incident that was reported to the title IX coordinator; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4A748EAF84664D6585CD83B92D344E15"><enum>(II)</enum><text>does not include an undergraduate student; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H71FB56D79F6A4EA5984DD2FAB8BF064B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the term <term>title IX coordinator</term> means a responsible employee, as described in section 106.8(a) of title 34, Code of Federal Regulations, designated to coordinate efforts under title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

