<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1EF33D45C85740D18A25DC8462C6E4E2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1775 IH: Assessing Unintended Drivers of Illegal Trafficking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1775</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230324">March 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require certain bureaus of the Department of State and the United States Agency for International Development to release quarterly reviews of certain grants, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9C32B3E331D74624AB6D842CD80A7858" style="OLC"><section id="HD7E944578826473F9157590DA8F16AC7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Assessing Unintended Drivers of Illegal Trafficking Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AUDIT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFEE69C0F32E040208AC73C277A1F9BD8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Latin America migrant services grant transparency</header><subsection id="H2C31B1163582427482BC2B693DE92C81"><enum>(a)</enum><text>The Department of State’s Bureau of Population, Refugees, and Migration shall:</text><paragraph id="H8F959CAC47C444DD9FDFAB7C9F981D32"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Issue a quarterly report documenting all the Bureau of Population, Refugees, and Migration grant money spent on migrant and asylum-seeker programs in Central and South America. The report shall explain why each implementing partner was chosen, the amount of money it received, the availability of asylum claim processing in the countries in which those partners operate, and the number of claims processed in those countries. The report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H262E88A590A4482F85F606C9EB426339"><enum>(A)</enum><text>grants given to non-governmental organization implementing partners which are building asylum shelters or creating asylum processing capacity in Central and South America;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA01B05C975E340D28C376E508704D98C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grants given to implementing partners conducting casework, counseling, or legal representation for asylum seekers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD28EBAD58B2E4EBB9F64A2AA9D10ED40"><enum>(C)</enum><text>grants given to implementing partners providing other services to asylum seekers, including transportation, monetary assistance, and housing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE3F74EB4ED348C7A1E43E0A3E7AF02E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Be prohibited from giving grants to implementing partners which provide abortion services to asylum seekers. This includes implementing partners—</text><subparagraph id="H319BD2018A5F4EB7B1D95130621110F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing sexual and reproductive health services that include referrals to receive abortions; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H725A0F29A8534EC4A7465D76C9ED740A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing assistance in obtaining abortions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3D36A7CD69640C7B889451163D4AD95"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing the abortion procedure itself; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7073C669285D464C8C49181CB6B0BF49"><enum>(D)</enum><text>which directly or indirectly fund abortions or services for obtaining abortions in any manner for asylum seekers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E1A6A489ACD4F7B9433BD50740689D1"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The Department of State’s Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor shall:</text><paragraph id="H1BE281575F154D1D819159568B3CD224"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Issue a quarterly report documenting all the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor grants given to migrant and asylum seeker rights programs in Central and South America. The report shall explain why each implementing partner was chosen, the amount of money it received, the availability of asylum claim processing in the countries in which those partners operate, and the number of claims processed in those countries. The report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H9A7B41E4A16046808905ADBD2AE106E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">direct grants from the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor to migrant shelters;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4BA8C05B88C442E4937584CB327BC0A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">grants to non-governmental organization implementing partners that provide grants or programming to other non-governmental organizations or migrants rights organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BA5FF01DCAD4E87BEE324280E63925F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor programming for building local asylum processing capacity or improving institutional transparency or efficiency; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B9A831BA0B94D7EA6D8206878D5E7A5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>grants given to implementing partners conducting casework, counseling, or legal representation for asylum seekers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BD7493A8069421EBF64EE57CE6240A6"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other programs the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor funds for the purpose of promoting migrant or asylum seeker rights.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H75A85CF2B47540B497A61CE7FA900DDF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Be prohibited from giving grants to implementing partners who provide abortion services to asylum seekers. This includes implementing partners—</text><subparagraph id="H94EA426282CE49E1905926EC12B5C211"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing sexual and reproductive health services that include referrals to receive abortions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA418C9A3680C4CFFB7CC0AA0837E6545"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing assistance in obtaining abortions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85D5B293A9794FA09444F12E64B565E7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing the abortion procedure itself;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FB626F9CE314FC8BDA2CD0578C99812"><enum>(D)</enum><text>who directly or indirectly fund abortions or services for obtaining abortions in any manner for asylum seekers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81E9F3E2AA8744AA9B7827FB7F45BA74"><enum>(E)</enum><text>which directly or indirectly fund abortions in any manner for asylum seekers, provisions, or assistance in obtaining an abortion.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35775B0AD6594C6BBDA07DD3CC8AA75E"><enum>(c)</enum><text>The United States Agency for International Development shall:</text><paragraph id="HD1E4F5839A8548BC820DAB1CA188F8DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Issue a quarterly report documenting all the United States Agency for International Development grants given to migrant, asylum seeker, and internally displaced persons programs in Central and South America. The report shall explain why each implementing partner was chosen, the amount of money it received, the availability of asylum claim processing in the countries in which those partners operate, and the number of claims processed in those countries. The report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HD13E117FE014462C8A93F63AD12F459C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">direct grants from the United States Agency for International Development to migrant shelters;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADB8D810B16448DBAD27270D1AB3CEEA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grants from the Bureau for Humanitarian Assistance to implementing partners in the region working with migrants and asylum seekers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AAE1C8FB242427E9061CD2BE83CD508"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prosperity, security, and governance grants given to El Salvador, Guatemala, and Honduras;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BC6305E81FD4F48B71F0F25EF69855E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>integration grants to Belize, Costa Rica, and Panama;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D128A4B2124440789872400A81A9314"><enum>(E)</enum><text>grants given to resettle and integrate Venezuelans outside their country and grants to implementing partners operating within Venezuela;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H651591BC13504B77B52A12C6AB1EF22A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>grants or programs related to messaging to citizens of Central and South America; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39715E5A39FB4CC8B5895429A332BF6E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>grants given for governmental institutional capacity building.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA16E1530F744E0EA9E7A9898353A720"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Be prohibited from giving grants to implementing partners which provide abortion services to asylum seekers. This includes implementing partners—</text><subparagraph id="H5C029ED97DE54CA9AF9B4E74D7F4D882"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing sexual and reproductive health services that include referrals to receive abortions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CD662D275AA4D4CAAC150813F094409"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing assistance in obtaining abortions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB982289591B84508B06812929C61C057"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing the abortion procedure itself;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79DC0296564948ADB6A05D6E5DA62163"><enum>(D)</enum><text>who directly or indirectly fund abortions or services for obtaining abortions in any manner for asylum seekers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H225E80549CD54E6F9D3907BBD8C035BA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>which directly or indirectly fund abortions in any manner for asylum seekers, provisions, or assistance in obtaining an abortion.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E232D61AC4243D9A047CD74AB183E61"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reports by the Bureau of Population, Refugees, and Migration, the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor, and the United States Agency for International Development shall begin the quarter after this legislation is enacted.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

