<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0B32ACF5C2B34AA395D0910D6922C1C9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6621 IH: Rural Uplift and Revitalization Assistance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6621</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide technical assistance for geographically underserved and distressed areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEBAB46309F9340009C5AF621F66012E4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3E9D1A2C4FA846A292C49B3D867F984E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Uplift and Revitalization Assistance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0DAFF62789134E17A5FEA25CAA20A10F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technical assistance for geographically underserved and distressed areas</header> <subsection id="H582C0932493448ABBC17AC6FE1FC6AD8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall directly, or through cooperative agreements, provide technical assistance and strengthen local capacity to improve access to rural development programs administered by the Secretary for local partners (including local governments, cooperatives, businesses, healthcare facilities and networks, community anchor institutions (as defined in section 60302(6) of the Digital Equity Act of 2021), and nonprofit organizations) in geographically underserved and distressed areas.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF1879F814F244373A1EAFD0B8392EEA0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall annually publish, make available to the public, and submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report on how the provision of technical assistance under subsection (a) has affected geographically underserved and distressed areas in the year covered by the report.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H277680199A1C4E5586D83A414DFB6766"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of geographically underserved and distressed area</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>geographically underserved and distressed area</quote> means a rural area (as determined by the Secretary)—</text> 
<paragraph id="H93635A612535461687FB2E78A4F0FEBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in a socially vulnerable community (as determined by the Secretary);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36E3D9C51E654562A7242F27BF68A9B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a persistent poverty county (as determined by the Secretary);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC0EA316FD1534B26857E6AD70B35F7AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a economically distressed area (as determined by the Secretary); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H219113E04A7A4096BE872EC41616D465"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that lacks adequate water services, sewer services, or decent housing in any region near the border between the United States and Mexico.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

