<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H88B55311A7A24FF3B2980E4F152DB781" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3093 IH: Affordable Pricing for Taxpayer-Funded Prescription Drugs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3093</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require persons who undertake federally funded research and development of a biomedical product or service to enter into reasonable pricing agreements with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7C044F9123C44FEE9C09548935A75F1D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H96F633266CFB4C5F8F803426DAA69DBE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Affordable Pricing for Taxpayer-Funded Prescription Drugs Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4C39752C82374D208638EDDB65D63EFD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reasonable price agreement</header> <subsection id="HF616A2A44F4C4D26B8C3527070D8E5FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All Federal agencies providing or receiving research funding, through a grant, contract, cooperative agreement, or other agreement, shall require in such agreement, and in any license of the rights to a patent or regulatory test data for a biomedical product or service, that the price of any biomedical product or service developed with the benefit of such research be reasonable (as determined by the Secretary) unless the Secretary waives such reasonable price obligation under subsection (d).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F2426A13D5441A68B387CF57F4D5F6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition against charging prices higher than in other large economies with high incomes</header> 
<paragraph id="H16B8645F3F1D42B0A1335AF33835E982"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), any reasonable pricing formula shall ensure, without prejudice to any other standards or negotiated provisions for reasonable pricing, that residents of the United States are not charged more for the biomedical product or service involved than the reference price for countries with large economies and high incomes.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFC5B101D6074092AA7A8B7279F23509"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reference price</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the phrase <quote>reference price for countries with large economies and high incomes</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H043513A3218448FE8836F4B99FE6EEC3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the median price charged for the biomedical product or service involved in Canada and the additional six reference countries; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4D6D681CA3C74236A1830AA6EE525691"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a modification to such price that is adopted by regulation after providing notice and the opportunity for the public to comment, if the Secretary determines such modification to be an appropriate and reasonable measure to protect United States residents from paying prices that are higher than prices in other countries with large economies and high incomes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9576077C38594F3097A9ED2444C1EB63"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H51CCDA72A5694A09B92FFA40FE12FB30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary may promulgate by regulation additional requirements to ensure that the price for the biomedical product or service described in subsection (a) be reasonable.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1D40DBB31BE46D8B2112183C7EA019A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The additional requirements under paragraph (1) shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE6D9187F9E504C578A3AEA694671E49B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>address the public interest in ensuring that publicly supported innovations for biomedical products and services have reasonable prices; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58C562C052A941B2BF0D69249FBF7EC9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>take into account—</text> 
<clause id="H9D675B826B6543D7B226FCEDEC070E10"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the importance of providing robust incentives to invest in biomedical research and development; and</text></clause> <clause id="HAFCCEECD03DE4343A84533CB3B4B9554"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the challenges of administering agreements described in subsection (a), including in cases where third parties control relevant intellectual property, know-how, or other assets.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC65CB01C05B94C62A53793E9ECA0E904"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Possible mechanisms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The additional requirements for reasonable pricing authorized by paragraph (1) may include—</text> <subparagraph id="H39ADA5E675014B97BC46AE575BFE7CAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">mechanisms to—</text> 
<clause id="HC3B3D4D624F04E48B322531E0A3A9771"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lower prices or shorten exclusivity periods when revenues exceed targets;</text></clause> <clause id="HD2B36FB08E1740848BD11C3F315A9929"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lower prices that exceed a standard of cost per health benefit achieved; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7C5AFFA3EDA94E77852B6B65ABACA1CA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>lower prices that constitute significant barriers to access or fiscal burdens on patients; or</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D2195A42541453884D2474509F8E249"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a combination of mechanisms listed in subparagraph (A) or other mechanisms.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA10F60E2C4DA4B7585A984386DF1AA95"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver</header> 
<paragraph id="HE6C2B8EC41794ECCA44209F486D4E81B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may waive part or all of a reasonable pricing obligation under this section upon a demonstration that such a waiver is in the public interest. A decision to grant such a waiver shall set out the Secretary’s finding that the waiver is in the public interest.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBD577E7E3B24760A05E0407ED2A2F77"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required process</header><text>No waiver under paragraph (1) shall take effect before—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6CBBFEF397A44F0784B87113DC7FF546"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the public is given notice of the proposed waiver and provided a reasonable opportunity to comment in writing and at a public hearing on the proposed waiver; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4B9C941F553B403AAED703C02E0A6386"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary publishes an economic analysis to justify the waiver.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2EBC15FE834F4A6DBA9022C1906B3DF2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Transparency</header> 
<paragraph id="HDBE1CFF4ABF34BB6BEEA7B06C29CE34C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to evaluate additional requirements promulgated under subsection (c), agreements subject to subsection (a) shall include a requirement that the manufacturer or other companies commercializing the biomedical product or service involved report to the Secretary in formats determined by the Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="H95BE795AD78448E995BA2C5422BD1F9E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the costs of each clinical trial undertaken to support the Federal regulatory approval of the biomedical product or service involved;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H993158968B034243AD024E8DC6878AD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subsidies of those costs by the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0E1EEA1E7F2046C392B6A4855C494E16"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the annual revenues generated by the biomedical product or service involved, by county of sale. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE85FF84DDE740B1B6A4A3EB996AFF55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make all reports under paragraph (1) publicly available.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4BFB46AA369D40BF82827E2151F232C9" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>No effect on other requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reasonable pricing requirements imposed under this section are in addition to any other requirements to limit the price of biomedical products or services, including such requirements imposed—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCE6DDDF2483640288ECD28AA4A6AE5EB" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>through standards or negotiated provisions on pricing in contracts; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCB628C3E3634B43B955DE78ACB0AD63" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/35/18">chapter 18</external-xref> of title 35, United States Code, to make the benefits of inventions funded by the Federal Government available to the public on reasonable terms.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFD0B7FA42DAF4A6B8482FF9AB0ED040D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H5F02A03517CB4D4D87C1B7F95564F2AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>biomedical product or service</term> means a drug, vaccine, medical device, diagnostic test, assistive technology, cell- or gene-based therapy, or other technology used to provide health care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74CF8D23429E4FB78C7FA98B3877D65B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>medical device</term> has the meaning given to the term <term>device</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4146FA7110A9494AB21DBB700670FD3A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7C401B8713949DFA0F2C26DE61CCD49"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>six reference countries</term> means the six countries, excluding Canada, that over the previous three calendar years—</text> <subparagraph id="HFAE8FD4EDB264AC5B77AE98458C12499"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are member countries of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB5BE383EED14406EA22C47BDC90AABCD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have the largest gross domestic products; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6B52D1E59149464180684BA6D2CFB862"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have a per capita income that is at least 50 percent of the average per capita income of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

