<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB42EC70D4BB41608D4EE35C5C8C9C2D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6036 IH: To require GAO to conduct annual assessments to determine the extent to which TSA’s passenger security screening practices comply with TSA non-discrimination policies to identify any needed actions to improve compliance, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6036</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231024">October 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require GAO to conduct annual assessments to determine the extent to which TSA&#8217;s passenger security screening practices comply with TSA non-discrimination policies to identify any needed actions to improve compliance, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0EDB3AF9DDA6462BA3542CC33FCB2AE3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC883DBDC2C8245D3B7C12332A67BBC7B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>GAO assessments of TSA compliance with non-discrimination policies during passenger security screenings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation an assessment of the extent to which passenger security screening practices of the Transportation Security Administration comply with non-discrimination policies of the Administration in order to identify any needed actions to improve such compliance.</text> </section> </legis-body></bill>

