<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H625AA4C085934FA7BF0DA1256D6A78EE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3722 IH: Daniel J. Harvey, Jr. and Adam Lambert Improving Servicemember Transition to Reduce Veteran Suicide Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3722</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require a pilot program on activities under the pre-separation transition process of members of the Armed Forces for a reduction in suicide among veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H9F61556DDDE34B30A06B854ED8B98AEB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H45ECB1DD0D5A4315B2A0652EF2CD991D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Daniel J. Harvey, Jr. and Adam Lambert Improving Servicemember Transition to Reduce Veteran Suicide Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H71701D4607C44E529E917D73B308CC13"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on activities under the pre-separation transition process of members of the Armed Forces for a reduction in suicide among veterans</header> <subsection id="H2760AEE458A34C7489C4097F88A3067F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program required</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall jointly carry out a pilot program to assess the feasibility and advisability of providing the module described in subsection (b) and services under subsection (c) as part of the pre-separation transition process for members of the Armed Forces as a means of reducing the incidence of suicide among veterans.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDF3318D6E8114067AFA4E0E1375211C5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Module</header> 
<paragraph id="H849650FF31334D01B329961C4A3A8D29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The module described in this subsection shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HE7D7F2EDAA75418DA9D6C9817C3A1A58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An in-person meeting between a cohort of members of the Armed Forces participating in the pilot program and a social worker or nurse in which the social worker or nurse—</text> 
<clause id="H275BF3D1F643422984F76D99295CE89D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>educates the cohort on resources for and specific potential risks confronting such members after discharge or release from the Armed Forces, including—</text> <subclause id="HEB6870E3D85F41E792B8F1B706A21B4E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>loss of community or a support system;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HC2EDB2E9DD2144779B8B76D4B1637B1F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>isolation from family, friends, or society;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB81772BB7A8C458DB908A9381DA966EE"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identity crisis in the transition from military to civilian life;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8965E4D19AC0433FB5EA216D4D0656B5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>vulnerability viewed as a weakness;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA24CD269136E4A959F6D6F494B06142E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>need for empathy;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HECE2931D0AEA40818B4ECED3A9C05E3A"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>self-medication and addiction;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6EECD261E2E24897B675D11F03783C49"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>importance of sleep and exercise;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H408EF0DD040147C59C92F6B2068E5B17"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>homelessness; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2B1AF595C40C41D093A819C2F58E73B2"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>risk factors contributing to attempts of suicide and deaths by suicide; </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H91DEEDC3BE824E50A4219BE94D051583"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>educates the cohort on—</text> <subclause id="HF0103731035249C9A15D09E30CB29118"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the signs and symptoms of suicide risk and physical, psychological, or neurological issues, such as post-traumatic stress disorder, traumatic brain injury, chronic pain, sleep disorders, substance use disorders, adverse childhood experiences, depression, bipolar disorder, and socio-ecological concerns, such as homelessness, unemployment, and relationship strain;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H60D4D9CD0E764EF69E7824BC9E9ADEB9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the potential risks for members of the Armed Forces from such issues after discharge or release from the Armed Forces; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H145EB9D569FB4B12984447545188C0C9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the resources and treatment options available to such members for such issues through the Department of Veterans Affairs, the Department of Defense, and non-profit organizations;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H945D591DA36642F786F4281C05AB87D1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>educates the cohort about the resources available to victims of military sexual trauma through the Department of Veterans Affairs; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBC65CBD7768A41DFB57E29D8F3E3F1E6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>educates the cohort about the manner in which members might experience challenges during the transition from military to civilian life, and the resources available to them through the Department of Veterans Affairs, the Department of Defense, and other organizations.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAB5A380410A94B62A9B656286D09C492"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The provision to each member of the cohort of contact information for a counseling or other appropriate facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs in the locality in which such member intends to reside after discharge or release.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H61E9B5676C1F4F7D9E85C19814517B11"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The submittal by each member of the cohort to the Department of Veterans Affairs (including both the Veterans Health Administration and the Veterans Benefits Administration) of their medical records in connection with service in the Armed Forces, whether or not such members intend to file a claim with the Department for benefits with respect to any service-connected disability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31759B4B46FF41A5BCBB5FDEAEA4F104"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition of cohort</header><text>Each cohort participating in the module described in this subsection shall be comprised of not fewer than 50 individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCF56F25382D04ABF9BA2D724162A586C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Services</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall provide to each individual participating in the pilot program the following services:</text> 
<paragraph id="H75B2700816EF49F7A3BA20D5BDDAA46F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>During the transition process and prior to discharge or release from the Armed Forces, a one-on-one meeting with a social worker or nurse of the Department of Veterans Affairs who will—</text> <subparagraph id="H329DBCE4EA5E4E0FA43947D8F84EB888"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct an assessment of the individual regarding eligibility to receive health care or counseling services from the Department of Veterans Affairs; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA98AF36096C34B31BB5ABFB60F3C29DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for those eligible, or likely to be eligible, to receive health care or counseling services from the Department of Veterans Affairs—</text> <clause id="HED43A6C39E7B4307B6237D6FA4DDDE45"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify and provide contact information for an appropriate facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs in the locality in which such individual intends to reside after discharge or release;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE21C4FFA7F0A4BE3A0FD024AA9FA5A4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>facilitate registration or enrollment in the system of patient enrollment of the Department of Veterans Affairs under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code, if applicable;</text></clause> <clause id="HBAA8B72EF87342DB95C8E6DCB86DEAA5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>educate the individual about care, benefits, and services available to the individual through the Veterans Health Administration; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFDE97C83DA5348F7BEDF2A993A709555"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>coordinate health care based on the health care needs of the individual, if applicable, to include establishing an initial appointment, at the election of the individual, to occur not later than 90 days after the date of discharge or release of the member from the Armed Forces.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H809F99D9EC9A4893BAB21175167153F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For each individual determined ineligible for care and services from the Department of Veterans Affairs during the transition process, the Secretary of Defense shall conduct an assessment of the individual to determine the needs of the individual and appropriate follow-up, which shall be identified and documented in the appropriate records of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D57F7196B764C85B5E2CFF465E43866"><enum>(3)</enum><text>During the appointment scheduled pursuant to paragraph (1)(B)(iv), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct an assessment of the individual to determine the needs of the individual and appropriate follow-up, which shall be identified and documented in the appropriate records of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H33542A969D584D91AC4C884BFF608607"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Locations</header> <paragraph id="HFCF97BE41DA84226AE16BA1C38AE4ED4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Module and meeting</header><text>The module under subsection (b) and the one-on-one meeting under subsection (c)(1) shall be carried out at not fewer than 10 locations of the Department of Defense that serve not fewer than 300 members of the Armed Forces annually that are jointly selected by the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for purposes of the pilot program.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79A8CFCA68874BE8BE6DE2F8EB10EB83"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment and appointment</header><text>The assessment under subsection (c)(2) and the appointment under subsection (c)(3) may occur at any location determined appropriate by the Secretary of Defense or the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, as the case may be.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA36486C1F75640CFA38F29938EF81F75"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Members served</header><text>The locations selected under paragraph (1) shall, to the extent practicable, be locations that, whether individually or in aggregate, serve all the Armed Forces and both the regular and reserve components of the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5FD11B5B9E434C169016995C172DAB4E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection and commencement</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall jointly select the locations of the pilot program under subsection (d)(1) and commence carrying out activities under the pilot program by not later than September 30, 2024.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9FA4301A522C44919A5C4E3A04569936"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The duration of the pilot program shall be five years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H63C9098F46C54906A7BB75412B231418"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<paragraph id="H5104BD26E62D4E2C8E5A15525C8B04A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the commencement of the pilot program, and annually thereafter during the duration of the pilot program, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall jointly submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the activities under the pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB4E69808ED904CA5AAAE5C02A9798002"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H06B83999CE0E46289BA2A93C24630F53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The demographic information of the members and former members of the Armed Forces who participated in the pilot program during the one-year period ending on the date of such report.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H99CB240D7E864849BBBF501015D0AF3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the activities under the pilot program during such period.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H82A853F74CAC42B1A6A694B386C28AD8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An assessment of the benefits of the activities under the pilot program during such period to members and former members of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H670C38A3A0BB42D7AA6D44C3870F3310"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An assessment of whether the activities under the pilot program as of the date of such report have met the targeted outcomes of the pilot program among members and former members who participated in the pilot program within one year of discharge or release from the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DE09AB405C54BD19AD4CD2594992BD4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Such recommendations as the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs jointly consider appropriate regarding the feasibility and advisability of expansion of the pilot program, extension of the pilot program, or both.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H286AE6499B714EA2BE3CD27F9D5CA15E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of congress defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H59F3417D3F0C4BDB9F7A5A1703F47E70"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAFCDE0E6EB1425D89D55DAE79BE1905"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


