<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H768C9C430E1B44ECB44C86C5DD57DAC9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5256 IH: Medicare Access to Rural Anesthesiology Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5256</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230822">August 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide payment under part A of the Medicare Program on a reasonable cost basis for anesthesia services furnished by an anesthesiologist in certain rural hospitals in the same manner as payments are provided for anesthesia services furnished by anesthesiologist assistants and certified registered nurse anesthetists in such hospitals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2F1E4B68D2384516B100401D115811AD" style="OLC"><section id="HE055914015C04AFDB0F0A17AB8BD6021" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicare Access to Rural Anesthesiology Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H27EBBF14D00C4A4895F87A3F52304FD8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medicare part A payment for anesthesiologist services in certain rural hospitals based on CRNA pass-through rules</header><subsection id="HD87BAAE45F154D248B8401B3645FE3FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Section 1814 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395f">42 U.S.C. 1395f</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="HD107363D3926434EB1E49DD3E29856B7" other-style="archaic" style="other"><subsection id="H67CAC32094D14241A07976D67F703B2B"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Anesthesiologist Services Provided in Certain Rural Hospitals</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H217195D53A5B4C3C9192C9A5864E50BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, coverage and payment shall be provided under this part for physicians’ services that are anesthesia services furnished by a physician who is an anesthesiologist in a rural hospital described in paragraph (3) in the same manner as payment is made under the exception provided in section 9320(k) of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1986, as amended by section 6132 of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1989 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395k">42 U.S.C. 1395k</external-xref> note) (relating to payment on a reasonable cost, pass-through basis), for certified registered nurse anesthetist services furnished by a certified registered nurse anesthetist in a hospital described in such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2616BD4AC371420183211D9759516235" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>No payment shall be made under any other provision of this title for physicians’ services for which payment is made under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C54C0F913284CCC978651F879C9A33C" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A rural hospital described in this paragraph is a hospital described in section 9320(k) of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1986, as so amended (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395k">42 U.S.C. 1395k</external-xref> note), except that—</text><subparagraph id="H81A28660A5BF4ADC8C2D415D1C520F89"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any reference in such section to a <term>certified registered nurse anesthetist</term> or <term>anesthetist</term> is deemed a reference to a <term>physician who is an anesthesiologist</term> or <term>anesthesiologist</term>, respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7810ED1BA8E842DAA1E2023B2D41DBF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any reference to <term>January 1, 1988</term> or <term>1987</term> is deemed a reference to such date and year as the Secretary shall specify.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HB6685C479597481AAABBA6D09A9F8626"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply to services furnished during cost reporting periods beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

