<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3F0CB985D4A943EB8D00FE44A1109D80" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5603 IH: World Language Education Assistance Program Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5603</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to award grants to local educational agencies to establish or improve world language or dual language programs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HA75CC12F313B4560BB574605A9D4E292" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6F6CFD1C67C94603961151A9EA05B33B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>World Language Education Assistance Program Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>World LEAP Act</short-title></quote>. </text> </section> <section id="H77DEAE82D7B143029E234DB88B59462A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to establish and make assistance available to the World Language Education Assistance Program in order to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA722CDDD51C441CCA0BD70E93A6533E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish or improve and carry out World Language Education Assistance Program grant programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D42075424E04F518835B48BBE898971"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support and uplift dual language and world language programs; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30562DDF191D4AB2B3837C3455A83E0B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide students with the language skills necessary for an interconnected and global world.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HCE83CAD7CBE842F6A9EB72173D43B8C2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFDFDEDF45840496D949C772E3EF25661"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recent academic studies demonstrate that America’s language capacity has reached a crisis point, with only one fifth of United States residents speaking a language other than English at home, 90 percent of United States-based employers reporting a reliance on employees with language skills other than English, and one third of foreign language-dependent employers reporting a language skills gap. This language crisis has real world implications for business, government, the military, and diplomatic and intelligence services.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H338A0F5A8D72419CA0369B4779FEE788"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Department of Education does not have an innovative world languages program for elementary and secondary students.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF0C9431D8DB40F9B614D6E1C5AB02CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Nation’s education system is suffering from severe shortages of world language, English learner, and bilingual and dual language immersion educators that have been exacerbated by the COVID–19 pandemic. Currently, foreign language is the second highest teacher shortage subject area in the Nation, with 6% of English as Second Language or bilingual education positions vacant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48A8D650A8FB4463973C2FD025200E05"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The lack of a Federal elementary and secondary school world language and dual language program, coupled with the continuing shortage of world language and bilingual teachers, creates significant obstacles to providing equitable opportunities for all students to develop multilingualism. English learners, a population which has grown by 2,100,000 between 2000 and 2019, have been disproportionately impacted.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1683622FF52848718C655847137243B4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Federal Government has a strong interest in better preparing American students to compete in the global economy.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HACBD4ACB9CB740B4AAC77514117B807A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5B654AFF9FD74A5F9C16B80FCD1E163A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community-based heritage language school</header><text>The term <term>community-based heritage language school</term> means a nonprofit, community-based school that offers classes for students in pre-kindergarten through grade 12, for the purpose of maintaining and teaching the language and culture of non-English speaking communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H921E9925B7DB4C5A92B5EB870239F340" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dual language program</header><text>The term <term>dual language program</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7D91B560FB8145BF98AF458CFCA6BCD1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to pre-kindergarten and elementary school, a bilingual education program in which students receive instruction in English and a language other than English for at least half of the instructional school day for each year of pre-kindergarten and elementary school, with the goal of achieving proficiency in both languages; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9D03D7A67406491C9474C21121EBC1A6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to grades 6 through 8, a bilingual education program in which students who participated in a program described in subparagraph (A) continue to receive instruction in English and a language other than English for at least half of the instructional school day for each year of such grades 6 through 8. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H81AC0372458D4577A2DAC46A74775138"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESEA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>English learner</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>professional development</term>, <term>Secretary</term>, and <term>State</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EE6E51CA7CE4B53AE685C7B2538DADD" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Heritage learner</header><text>The term <term>heritage learner</term> means an individual—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB78D328BDA8A4FADB212E96527341AFD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with proficiency in, or a cultural connection to (through family, community, or country of origin), a language other than English; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFE3446541E47461180D305BE3C4EB722" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is studying such language in pre-kindergarten, elementary school, or secondary school.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H008DBB4EB69D426BBA6CBC3A45EB8F63" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>World language program</header><text>The term <term>world language program</term> means a program that educates and prepares pre-kindergarten, elementary, or secondary school students to communicate, in a proficient and culturally competent manner, with individuals who speak a language other than English.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H34194B040A6544F19EE831A52F156D1C"><enum>5.</enum><header>World language education assistance program</header> <subsection id="H78450CC6564E41B8A759D9EC3D6EFBEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="H1C205FECCA6044968FCE696738D58358"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award, on a competitive basis, grants to local educational agencies to establish and carry out new, or improve existing world language or dual language programs. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H046F3D8A50E04986A591E92571524865"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A grant awarded under this section shall be for a period of 3 years and may be renewed at the discretion of the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9829AF5D95C54BBC8FD019E1FD7486D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A local educational agency desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information and assurances as the Secretary may require.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HB8CEFA797E79407FB4C564B49A8C6580"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria for selection</header> 
<paragraph id="H46E1DF9FDE3D493B9F311F2C1549A240"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In awarding a grant to a local educational agency under this section, the Secretary shall select applications describing programs that—</text> <subparagraph id="HE844FC93F601450280A3DB20BBA0306E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide approaches to instruction that lead to demonstrated growth in language proficiency from kindergarten through grade 12;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H528B35955F664095957155EAA9128672"><enum>(B)</enum><text>can be disseminated and duplicated in other local educational agencies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H59F8358E80534C658081F4491D136B44" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have a plan for how the program will continue after the conclusion of the grant period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H55EF56BB9853488D990FFBC275D7FF25"><enum>(D)</enum><text>include a professional development component.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8355A2F15F6843AFABFB4D5F6165B5CC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to applications describing programs that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE87E081683D84A0E9589DC9A199A03EF" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include intensive summer professional development for world language program and dual language program teachers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2FEA23BCC314D6B88873D03BD1482CE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enter into partnerships with community-based heritage language schools and communities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H349DFB32FAA54D0CA2917A1DDAD27B8A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide world language and dual language immersion programs across all socioeconomic and demographic groups, including English learners and heritage learners;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62771DA067304E9EBC935A94326E1B72" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>are carried out through a consortium that shall include the agency receiving the grant and an elementary school or secondary school served by such agency, with a preference for consortia that include an institution of higher education; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H30A571215A764F68810538C8141455C2" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>collaborate with the appropriate State licensure office to broaden pathways for language or dual language teacher certification; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5FB142E6205841E2A7E914CA5A110D13" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>conduct outreach and recruit secondary and post-secondary students of diverse socioeconomic backgrounds, including former English learners and heritage learners, into programs that prepare such students to become dual language or world language program teachers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H58AF19881834414B87B9C618F007AE30"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A local educational agency that receives a grant under this section shall—</text> <paragraph id="H94EF55AC60774CDCA9A3E71E2D205730"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reserve not less than 20 percent of such grant funds to provide—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEB445EDDEF4E47478E888FEE5E57C0C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>accessible pathways for paraprofessionals to gain certification and licensure as world language or dual language teachers; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1B6D6C975F746ADA5062763B90517FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>professional development for certified and licensed world language or dual language teachers; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC700DD75F90C41BCA938B00A361C2565"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reserve not more than 5 percent of such grant funds to evaluate the efficacy of programs carried out with funds awarded under this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2326A56F5627440FB9C8430DCAF18C5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>after making the reservations required under paragraphs (1) and (2), use the remainder of such grant funds to establish and carry out new, and improve existing, world language or dual language programs (including any associated administrative expenses).</text> </paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HEC29EC24010D4B48BB1FA730CF59C2F0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="HFB3AAB2BEFCF4591BAA301A6665EEB31"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after receiving a grant under this section, each local educational agency shall submit to the Secretary a report that—</text> <subparagraph id="HAEFB35FE0A244C069D2EA9F0D5E2AC58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes the implementation of the program for which the local educational agency received the grant; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3EDD19A424E243F3ACEFBC2F7F8C808D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes data that identifies—</text> <clause id="H8D4A3E3E4D16421B88B34F22E38D8F9C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of students enrolled in language education at the elementary and secondary schools served by the local educational agency prior to receiving a grant under this section;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H43B67E30290A47B892B011112F8BF35F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of students enrolled in such language instruction as of the date of submission of the report;</text></clause> <clause id="H89071FC20F924BE18BA5308D22A058BC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of certified bilingual educators working for the local educational agency prior to receiving a grant under this section;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5B18ACF2BA314B08A06678E6EDE0C4BB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of certified bilingual educators working for the local educational agency as of the date of submission of the report; and</text></clause> <clause id="H910C80F85A244AC7955BCA11902A18EC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>levels of community support for language education—</text> 
<subclause id="H0F1C3A5A5E4C42D581AE93B3C90BF32A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>prior to receiving a grant under this section; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDD4AFB0E2278417A88F2FD99D602A18E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>as of the date of submission of the report.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1FA586B19CE74FC4A6D28CB234647511"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Student privacy</header><text>A local educational agency shall prepare the report required under paragraph (1) in a manner that protects the privacy rights of each student in accordance with section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>; commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCECA81519F9447DC85B1781B6C0A72B6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and for each subsequent fiscal year.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


