<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H18920FE98D0E4A5A836434EF8B3ADC87" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 136 IH: Help Ensure Legal Detainers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 136</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To deny Federal funding to any State or political subdivision of a State that has in effect any law, policy, or procedure that prevents or impedes a State or local law enforcement official from maintaining custody of an alien pursuant to an immigration detainer issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3FDF063CB0F64D7D946780F543198A76" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7A74DF81F1984E1E9ADB2EA6EE856E88" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the—</text> <paragraph id="H5B20A4A1B7044933B4FB9BE64C5496A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote><short-title>Help Ensure Legal Detainers Act</short-title></quote>; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6881B57E0E2B481482FBC139B76B4E2F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote><short-title>HELD Act</short-title></quote>.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H69508585E8D848728C50AA46FB1C541D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Denial of Federal funding to States and units of local government that fail to respond to immigration detainers</header> <subsection id="H1DC0A759E7EA418AB473CE229CCB4CDA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to fiscal years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act, no Federal funds may be used to assist any project or activity carried out by a State, or a political subdivision of a State, described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB253D3488B5D414A93AE895989DEC399"><enum>(b)</enum><header>States and political subdivisions described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State, or political subdivision of a State, described in this subsection is any State, or political subdivision of a State, that has in effect any law, policy, or procedure that prevents or impedes State or local law enforcement officials from—</text> <paragraph id="H33E83C215C9747F495143878FDE02CF4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">timely responding to an immigration notice issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security that requests information about an alien in State or local custody, including the alien’s estimated release date, in order that the Secretary may arrange to assume custody of the alien upon such release; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8E60747E93944F4D845B2158B3AA0D80"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintaining custody of an alien for a period of up to 48 hours (excluding Saturdays, Sundays and holidays) pursuant to an immigration detainer issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security in order that the alien can be transferred to the custody of such Secretary to determine whether the alien should be detained, placed in removal proceedings, released, or removed.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6C39F7D073DE45A4B997F5E11D320CF3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>A political subdivision of a State that is not ineligible under subsection (a) to receive Federal funds, but is part of a State or another unit of government that is so ineligible, may submit, notwithstanding any other provision of law, an application for direct receipt of any funds that the political subdivision otherwise only would receive through subgrant, allocation, or allotment made by the ineligible State or government unit.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

