<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7C6FB953B7BA43BEA5D6302305B68B51" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4764 IH: HIVE Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4764</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000377">Mr. Armstrong</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a standard of identity for honey, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC9E779663A79400DB4E47C67BED1E61B" style="OLC"><section id="HF1C9B010781544FF865A03B47FF7664D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Honey Identification Verification and Enforcement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>HIVE Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="H815F0B9D8E09497CA84C50842906DDDC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Standard of identity for honey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall establish a standard of identity for honey in accordance with applicable United States Pharmacopeia standards under section 401 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/341">21 U.S.C. 341</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="H283BE52C288C4EC182B14F44DB10B81E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report to Congress on enforcement actions with respect to misbranded honey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall submit a report to the Congress on enforcement actions taken under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to honey that is adulterated under section 402 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/342">21 U.S.C. 342</external-xref>) and honey that is misbranded under section 403 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/343">21 U.S.C. 343</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="H928C6C60DD434274B036F60F8CE31AA0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Countries of origin listed in descending order of predominance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(h)(6) of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1622">7 U.S.C. 1622(h)(6)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H28889BE9C6B74253A053BFABDD8BDD12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>a comparable size,</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEEC018A1806547BAB9F5210F6E60EC3C" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>a comparable size—</text><clause id="H06C6591EA41342D8A17A1CFB014E4936"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 1 or more names of the 1 or more countries of origin of the lot or container of honey, listed in descending order of predominance and preceded by the words <quote>Product of</quote> or other words of similar meaning; </text></clause><clause id="H06CC7A4770E9432BB437DC07298A9900"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the country of origin is listed as the United States, a statement clarifying the de minimis allowance specified in subparagraph (C); and</text></clause><clause id="HBA4F50B23D124550A823CE4089779E9A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a certificate, mark, or statement indicating that the honey meets the standard of identity established under section 2 of the HIVE Act. </text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2AB27AFDD9C489FA4FD5222A462B6E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5630C15792BE40C690EF8983D10E0055" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H3CBC63804F6B4737AD41B130487EB63A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>De minimis allowance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of honey that lists, pursuant to subparagraph (A)(ii), the United States as the country of origin of such honey, the producer of such honey shall not be in violation of the requirements of such subparagraph if 95 percent of such honey has a United States country of origin and contains not more than a de minimis amount (not to exceed 5 percent) of honey from any other country (or countries) of origin. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

