<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9C2425A46DED40B58FB6B62CF923B66A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2426 IH: Find and Protect Foster Youth Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2426</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001093">Mrs. Houchin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend part E of title IV of the Social Security Act to require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to identify obstacles to identifying and responding to reports of children missing from foster care and other vulnerable foster youth, to provide technical assistance relating to the removal of such obstacles, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H824CB42EE4214C6A968EB7487B969731" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2924A661AA9C4962A912083A9F06BAE9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Find and Protect Foster Youth Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF6507B5CAD5D45DDBF4E7F118C917C26"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eliminating obstacles to identifying and responding to reports of children missing from foster care and other vulnerable foster youth</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 476 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/676">42 U.S.C. 676</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA82A7D8EB0554494B70AF31BDF50FFB3" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H4697BEAC8C714A2698B4820EF30E0791"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation of protocols relating to children missing from foster care and other vulnerable youth; technical assistance</header> 
<paragraph id="HE8341523E5A44EE99B6CCD0B9C1EE210"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an evaluation of the protocols established by States in accordance with the requirements of section 471(a)(35) and, to the extent applicable, by Indian tribes or tribal organizations (as defined in section 479B(a)) or tribal consortia with a plan approved under section 471 in accordance with section 479B.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8651851C2892466B96743E1F0BE0213E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The evaluation shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7A1252F492484632BC1A14EAFF0D327E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A review of relevant aspects of reports submitted by States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia under this part and part B, and data and other information reported pursuant to the system established under section 479.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC813D34ECBE84BF38791407E4702C48A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Analysis of the extent to which States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia comply with, and enforce, the protocols required by section 471(a)(35).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC36E773E906745D29DB9B6A0BB5506FE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Analysis of the effectiveness of such protocols.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40A56E30C6B749E7B61FEE39FD40CB38"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Identification of obstacles for States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia to identifying and responding to reports of children missing from foster care and other vulnerable foster youth.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32E8FAFD20924037A1AD49E52C2DA402"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Identification of best practices for identifying such children and youth and intervening with effective services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95D73AF047E945FAA1D2677C981181E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia with information, advice, educational materials, and technical assistance relating to eliminating identified obstacles to identifying and responding to reports of children missing from foster care and other vulnerable foster youth and providing such children and youth with effective services. Such assistance may include dissemination of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7AFAF8A31EBD4D279D913E3A89C82D3D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>processes and tools to identify and examine risk factors and potential trends related to children who go missing from foster care and other vulnerable youth;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1126C4571F14AA1810C7A6103F0A5BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>best practices for runaway tracking and recovery; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDEEF4D8ABC2E43C3BECC2A8ADA2A4C66"><enum>(C)</enum><text>guidelines for intervention, including with respect to services, types of providers, and placement settings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04A6357B770845CC8750BADB422E217A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress on the results of the evaluation conducted under this subsection and the technical assistance provided in accordance with paragraph (3).</text></paragraph> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H1373AA56DD5649DF8A2EE359515AB9F1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Improving screening and assessment of children returned to foster care after going missing to determine whether they were, or are at risk of becoming, victims of sex trafficking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 476 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/676">42 U.S.C. 676</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H24C7EBB6C8C546BC8AFCE333C910B576" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H64E62A07A9464E0EBD231C1D3A6D3A18"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Improving identification of, and services for, children who return to foster care after running away or otherwise being absent from foster care and who are, or are at risk of being, victims of sex trafficking</header> <paragraph id="HAFB9013D54FA4F79B68B4D51D9BFB37C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistance</header> <subparagraph id="HE232CF4D59F9422091224DD99209C41E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Screening after a return to foster care</header><text>The Secretary shall provide States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia, with information, advice, educational materials, and technical assistance to improve compliance with section 471(a)(35)(A)(iii).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2C516A975F224177ADDDE24661C09BAB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Improving other requirements</header><text>The information, advice, educational materials, and technical assistance provided may include information, advice, educational materials, and technical assistance to improve or modify policies and procedures (including relevant training for caseworkers) developed by States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia under section 471(a)(9)(C), including the following:</text> <clause id="HA3F5086E81744DD6A54C50E1CF3CF399"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Identifying, through screening, whether the State has reasonable cause to believe the child or youth is, or is at risk of being, a victim of sex trafficking.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD93B83CF93DC41ADB38F205DDCF34000"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Documenting the results of such screening in agency records.</text></clause> <clause id="H8D9988E018634A359571E24409597E02"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Determining appropriate services for a child or youth for whom the State determines there is reasonable cause to identify the child or youth as a victim of sex trafficking, or as at risk of being a victim of sex trafficking.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4B8DF673C1F5441DB1D3E41F1FAF920D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Documenting in agency records the determination of appropriate services for a child or youth described in clause (iii).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14E2540632444F41BA9E1E18862DCBF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forms of assistance</header><text>The assistance provided under this subsection shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF6502B90FCD04E66AB9A9F9A84123762"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Assisting States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia, with developing oversight mechanisms to assess their compliance with section 471(a)(35)(A)(iii).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06110CE1591644EDABFB531639D8268D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Assisting States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia in developing—</text> 
<clause id="H090BEE1C82704F6385728F358A09A73A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assessments for screening children who return to foster care after running away or otherwise being absent from foster care for risk of becoming victims of sex trafficking; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCEEB76A722E145C2A54011DC6D8BCBCA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>effective and robust policies relating to the use of the assessments.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF8AF2541E29A4E4FADBC317267256B30"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Working with States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia to improve or modify policies and procedures developed under section 471(a)(9)(C).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H708F9BB2F33E4AEE9EDBEEC967AC0A6F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Providing technical assistance on how States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia may best use data collected pursuant to section 479 for oversight of, and to ensure compliance with, the requirements of paragraphs (9)(C) and (35)(A)(iii) of section 471(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9C9685CFC634444781EFAA4F27A31391"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, consult with internal and external offices with expertise on sex trafficking, including the Office on Trafficking in Persons of the Administration for Children and Families, on the development and dissemination to States, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and tribal consortia of the assistance required under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H3BF84A9800E741DBAF01A80675B6B278"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary such sums as are necessary to carry out this Act for fiscal year 2023, which shall remain available through fiscal year 2027.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

