<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEC1366727F5C487B97FCE45CBA6BD779" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 653 IH: Transition-to-Success Mentoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 653</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to award grants to eligible entities to establish, expand, or support school-based mentoring programs to assist at-risk middle school students with the transition from middle school to high school.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA47ABD6BB60442CF80C02724D73AD385" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H83D8EFDF0C2E4D249DBB561AA9F87E36"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transition-to-Success Mentoring Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1A50B1AE4F204A59AA06AC9B49081961"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transition-to-Success Mentoring Program</header><subsection id="H560D021327A748069105385267F48D5D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transition-to-Success Mentoring Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part D of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6421">20 U.S.C. 6421 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF0D695D48B348E99ADE58FC5FB811C9"><subpart id="HA6A3376CA23E4D9EADF4B9CA059AA92E"><enum>4</enum><header>Transition-to-Success Mentoring Program</header><section id="HC88FF57EEE91404EA756DE9E08CD49A3"><enum>1441.</enum><header>Transition-to-Success Mentoring Program</header><subsection id="H6528FB80A3F54E45ABDB390E99FBE2D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to establish, expand, or support school-based mentoring programs to assist eligible students with the transition from middle school to high school.</text></subsection><subsection id="H84E47213383347D8958B21BFAF08FF8A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H380ED76D78324B19AFC0968AD9791D55"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC884E492A25D488F9863BE5C89AA19B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting grant recipients, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text><subparagraph id="H945ACD51BA0B43688395AAACC61AF6B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serve children and youth with the greatest need living in high-poverty, high-crime areas, or rural areas, or who attend schools with high rates of community violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD6C4831473A4B88B50B32D56A299B01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide eligible students with opportunities for postsecondary education preparation and career development, including—</text><clause id="H1D72EC96CBDB43DE9AD5A256C342915A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>job training, professional development, work shadowing, internships, networking, résumé writing and review, interview preparation, transition services for students with disabilities, application assistance and visits to institutions of higher education, and leadership development through community service; and</text></clause><clause id="H9604398D1FE349DE82C823C3CD20A334"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>partnerships with the private sector and local businesses to provide internship and career exploration activities and resources; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB40625301424945937FEABEE1C2A8FB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>seek to provide match lengths between eligible students and success coaches for at least 1 academic year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H719258148CCF406E8B6758F388C6B11F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>indicate how, and the degree to which, children were consulted and engaged in the development, design, and implementation of the school-based mentoring program. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFFB06CC2F2F4B328433CD4AD556A709"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><paragraph id="H5ABBE4C83D16422E81297711EB5C8869"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Required uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to establish a school-based mentoring program, or to expand or provide technical support to an existing school-based mentoring program, in all middle schools served by the entity, under which each eligible student is assigned to a success coach who—</text><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC42DC44A4634E66AEF37D1548765748"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">creates a plan for success for the student that—</text><clause id="HAFE7C743BE1C4DA0ABD5F155074BD550"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is created with the student, mentor, relevant school staff (such as a teacher or school counselor), and parents of the student;</text></clause><clause id="H1892D37941E743B9944A1D062BC7B2A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes, for each academic year, the student’s academic, personal, college, and career exploration goals, and a strategy on how to accomplish such goals;</text></clause><clause id="HFD4EAE6966184DB6ADB5518334AE5F5E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies the student’s strengths, areas for improvement, and academic progress; and</text></clause><clause id="H343E410D732F4FC2A6DCAF301485CCCC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a plan to educate and support the student’s college or career exploration goals;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DCD958E0F0749FDAB18854AD06395B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enters into a signed, written agreement with the parents of the student that describes how the parents should assist the student in carrying out the plan for success;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CCA2C99145840C8A81508B39229F0EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>meets with the student at least once per month to—</text><clause id="HB869345AB4764066A6DF0A9A024F76E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assist the student in achieving the goals under the plan for success;</text></clause><clause id="HFD6970FA9E3A4160BD34CA8F44E5B2B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify the student’s academic areas for improvement;</text></clause><clause id="HF27851CA690D4A9F82A51E0A7E38CB75"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>connect the student with the tools and resources necessary to help improve the student’s potential for academic success;</text></clause><clause id="HEEF4D32B9E574AD593942A7BB2039267"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure the student’s successful transition from middle school to high school by identifying opportunities to help the student develop a positive attitude toward school, improve classroom behavior, complete coursework, and socialize with peers; and</text></clause><clause id="H90257ACCC11A473B9A9D416B36E12142"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in the case of a student with behavioral issues, assist the student in behavior management techniques;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2809576C744F40568425FE2E97BDB7CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>at least quarterly, meets with the student and the parents, teachers, or counselors of the student to—</text><clause id="H1C078DF7CED04B5DA7FF3A890336D6EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evaluate the student’s progress in achieving the goals under the plan for the current academic year; and</text></clause><clause id="H9642A023EA014D12AF46ACB7924A1110"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>revise or establish new goals for the next academic year; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC80A0B1DB0D744108259FEBF26019980"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assists the student in exploring higher education and career exposure opportunities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD8F5EC1EDDD438BA04CA251CE17CDCE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorized uses of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may use such funds to—</text><subparagraph id="H7D60E4E554B64DA6ADAC091A52D41D06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and carry out regular training for success coaches, including on—</text><clause id="H997DF8CC533548ECB3DDDBDBD6C84845"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the impact of adverse childhood experiences;</text></clause><clause id="HA8DD8EFC91AA4519BA5DAD4292D1257A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>trauma-informed practices and interventions;</text></clause><clause id="HBE68568631114C858264146A4CB4AD36"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>supporting homeless children and youths;</text></clause><clause id="H134FBEBB60874F998891D4AD2840C29E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>supporting children and youth in foster care;</text></clause><clause id="HACD53FD4BE274EC8970C14F04EDB0A24"><enum>(v)</enum><text>cultural competency;</text></clause><clause id="H18CE9B16184F46CB848CA7792BA28383"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>meeting all appropriate privacy and confidentiality requirements for students, including students in foster care;</text></clause><clause id="H5F6BA01764274FB5A7849B9483BDA1AE"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>working in coordination with a public school system;</text></clause><clause id="HECFB836C77A340B0BB0ACBE4984A401F"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>positive youth development and engagement practices; and</text></clause><clause id="H993BF62655A94CDBACB8DF7889041323"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>disability inclusion practices to ensure access and participation by students with disabilities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C1B0903E00946D391FB420CD69526C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recruit, screen, match, compensate, and train success coaches, and pay for costs related to success coach and mentee participation in the program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FA1162ECE624499B317214832BC9813"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hire staff to perform or support the objectives of the school-based mentoring program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4CAE450A6A24634AFD1514072CC67F2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide inclusive and accessible youth engagement activities, such as—</text><clause id="HA842C72EFD8F4788A8337413F9F2D966"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enrichment field trips to cultural destinations; </text></clause><clause id="H2C9ED51A824944B8A3E5EEC4B0EEC724"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>career awareness activities, including job site visits, informational interviews, résumé writing, interview preparation, and networking; and</text></clause><clause id="H2DAE8B4C0CD6411C9B8CDA19AF5BABE1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>academic or postsecondary education preparation activities, including trade or vocational school visits, visits to institutions of higher education, and assistance in applying to institutions of higher education; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82418E2C9A2D41C7AD3DDEF11660B202"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide activities or programming with the purpose of engaging and connecting the student to the school community; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H294BC508924041BF95DB389E1769C8D5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>conduct program evaluation, including by acquiring and analyzing the data described under subsection (e). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD15497F839DE49A0BA1C8C7180E35DF7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant Duration</header><text>A grant under this section shall be awarded for a period of not more than 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H68AD3BCFDE8E45E4B2DC62D7F7D5E882"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="H1A2ABFC8CDFD4071ACCBB90969B3DCA3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary, at the end of each academic year during the grant period, a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H370640CBE3B74F10A1013E1FD04DBE23"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of students who participated in the school-based mentoring program that was funded in whole or in part with the grant funds under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF69DF9E5DD54FC6BDFC98DAA2A70086"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demographic data on such students;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1A468BEA6B74817B03562CA53D586FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>data on the academic achievement, dropout rates, truancy, absenteeism, outcomes of arrests for violent crime, summer employment, and postsecondary education enrollment of such students; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC833854A8F564E4383F8C61F7F6DF5FB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of contact hours between such students and their success coaches; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7013E653858F4163B0EAEEB4A912F327"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the number of students with disabilities connected to transition services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86FB0F6BE2364007A9B7213B95CD9EB8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>data on social-emotional development of students as assessed with a validated social-emotional assessment tool; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA12BD2364B1C4F79824773704563FF84"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require to evaluate the success of the school-based mentoring program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9B8834FE21744994B997DB90B253D78B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H50C4321096DA4326BA50C3D27ED3E819"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the end of the third fiscal year for which funds are made available to carry out this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress an interim report on the success of the school-based mentoring programs funded under this section that includes the information received under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H415872A69A9D420FB414BF8ACF438620"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the end of the fifth fiscal year for which funds are made available to carry out this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a final report on the success of the school-based mentoring programs funded under this section that includes the information received under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H81175563B33C4D82B2A4B8A80E18EAEE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Mentoring resources and community service coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall work with the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention to—</text><paragraph id="HC10C1A28F9564899AB148968FAAFCF83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>refer grantees under this section to the National Mentoring Resource Center to obtain resources on best practices and research related to mentoring and to request no-cost training and technical assistance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6AABEDCB18F46EE89B136E699C3778E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide grantees under this section with information regarding transitional services for eligible students returning from correctional facilities and transition services for students with disabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5CF3AE70EB234855A861A0B76C9A3157"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HAA952E48E50D4F4CABDCD6F13B68B340"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HD14376A5C8E34C6D8AF918482CE6DE7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a local educational agency that—</text><clause id="HB11A6A016F054C1D97A211BC966386E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receives, or is eligible to receive, funds under part A of this title; or</text></clause><clause id="HECA3CAC1BD144EE484263FB62BB3A5EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a high-need local educational agency; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D183580950F4489964BFD9E27BCD52D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a partnership between a local educational agency described in subparagraph (A) and a nonprofit, community-based organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB30E0F51DD6842B7A6BC09256887B93F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible student</header><text>The term <term>eligible student</term> means a student who—</text><subparagraph id="HF909E4EBFB224245828C499A88D0CA72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is enrolled in a middle school served by an eligible entity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8B6B262271C4C6F90A840CECC1BFCB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is an at-risk student.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4ABB46E6FB2246B38D1F680516B49334"><enum>(3)</enum><header>High-need local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>high-need local educational agency</term> means a local educational agency that serves at least one high-need school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29795F896A494E98871191118421AC98"><enum>(4)</enum><header>High-need school</header><text>The term <term>high-need school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2211(b)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE686048570FD439683088B76E3517B6A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Middle school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>middle school</term> means a nonprofit institutional day or residential school, including a public charter school, that provides middle school education, as determined under State law, except that the term does not include any education below grade 6 or beyond grade 9.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H38D55E4AF73C4822A6B9F69E68BF18D6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>School-based mentoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>school-based mentoring</term> means mentoring activities that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5F1F9774BC02466CBF07CB6475CDF1ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are closely coordinated with a school by involving teachers, counselors, and other school staff who may identify and refer students for mentoring services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H82D4663D8F644386B14A7AC74AD2291F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assist at-risk students in improving academic achievement and attitudes toward school and reducing disciplinary referrals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87C4E175AD0A457B823A2CAEBBA9138A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Success coach</header><text>The term <term>success coach</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HCD4D8DA096F64C9697D102F63E8C894E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="H2C5A2294DC184644BAC228EAAB3F6579"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an employee or volunteer of a local educational agency in which a mentoring program receiving support under this section is being carried out; or</text></clause><clause id="HF616F7740E1B4875BA785B832577B23C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a volunteer or employee from a nonprofit, community-based organization that provides volunteers for mentoring programs in secondary schools; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1E68B3EAA4D043F183F711E52947C222"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prior to becoming a success coach—</text><clause commented="no" id="H05AEDB2B8C6E4784926A643B477F4C9E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>received training from an eligible entity, which, at a minimum, was 2 hours in length and covered the roles and responsibilities of a success coach; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF374C708180245E19F8357F860F6D1B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>underwent a screening by an eligible entity that included—</text><subclause commented="no" id="HA6D29EC6A12D4FAB8E36D1021375420A"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appropriate job reference checks;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HECFFDA7055774F39A3A6307D94938167"><enum>(II)</enum><text>child and domestic abuse record checks; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA36400A6A0264F87B9B5A8C7F05C68E2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>criminal background checks.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBE7C569C9FBF4E8488B166B0F88F5A20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents in section 2 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6301">20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1432 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB72C6A53265B40B082F1A96AB8E22DC9"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="subpart">Subpart 4—Transition-to-Success Mentoring Program </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 1441. Transition-to-success mentoring program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

