<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC7C0D1AF6C374725ABD3EA0ECBDE5A84" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5607 IH: COUPLES HSA Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5607</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to allow both spouses to make catch-up contributions to the same health savings account.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H179209FFC0D34A5698F58B1C8841DB80" style="OLC"><section id="HD69C6F2B1FFA4EA789C9CFB5F38A1C96" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Contribution Opportunities for United Partners with Limit Expansions in a Single HSA</short-title></quote> or the <quote>COUPLES HSA Act</quote>. </text></section><section id="HF7519970433C4711ADBD199DFD940689" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Allow both spouses to make catch-up contributions to the same health savings account</header><subsection id="H1F539659918845DB83856FE3EF8B8470"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">Section 223(b)(5)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E2D6699712040F6A4AEE0E95A0439E5"><paragraph id="H8E194CDDD4D64F7F9470636CB8A89670" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Special rule for married individuals with family coverage</header><subparagraph id="H5F4B9FFCF4E644538B2EF2222748D55C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of individuals who are married to each other, if both spouses are eligible individuals and either spouse has family coverage under a high deductible health plan as of the first day of any month—</text><clause id="H61A2558A772E473A99544D2D868FE85E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the limitation under paragraph (1) shall be applied by not taking into account any other high deductible health plan coverage of either spouse (and if such spouses both have family coverage under separate high deductible health plans, only one such coverage shall be taken into account),</text></clause><clause id="HB11B5AAEF62C460081739C4000D4DA9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such limitation (after application of clause (i)) shall be reduced by the aggregate amount paid to Archer MSAs of such spouses for the taxable year, and</text></clause><clause id="HDF2F84C2626D47668018C86FD883A511"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such limitation (after application of clauses (i) and (ii)) shall be divided equally between such spouses unless they agree on a different division.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1D6BE4E55E64A16BF788D7B082C816C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of additional contribution amounts</header><text>If both spouses referred to in subparagraph (A) have attained age 55 before the close of the taxable year, the limitation referred to in subparagraph (A)(iii) which is subject to division between the spouses shall include the additional contribution amounts determined under paragraph (3) for both spouses. In any other case, any additional contribution amount determined under paragraph (3) shall not be taken into account under subparagraph (A)(iii) and shall not be subject to division between the spouses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBA31F979F3F94350B5A738FE6B0031F2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

