<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H15237ECA21AC43B2B810A73E86DEFF5F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3996 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to impose a tax on the acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3996</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001126">Mr. Carey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to impose a tax on the acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H79B198EE86B546EA9BAA4D194E78973B" style="OLC"><section id="H1395C501D10B40CD8EE3D1E5AD8125A7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Imposition of tax on the acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="HE06EE8A8F4C24A1CB36DDA482660BA37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle D of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after chapter 50A the following new chapter:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF9FE167A20864A7AB5426761BFF45D20" display-inline="no-display-inline"><chapter id="H7FFF00728F434319B5FED845B354F04E"><enum>50B</enum><header>Acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><toc container-level="chapter-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H7FFF00728F434319B5FED845B354F04E" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HC6C830E6BB45442C95EB7B3A8B1A1A11" level="section">Sec. 5000E. Imposition of tax on acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><section id="HC6C830E6BB45442C95EB7B3A8B1A1A11"><enum>5000E.</enum><header>Imposition of tax on acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="H6325D6FC0FA844EA93CBBE2D7B7E387C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest by any disqualified person, there is hereby imposed on such person a tax equal to 60 percent of the amount paid for such interest.</text></subsection><subsection id="H212004337F624C10A45F7AEF0494F5BA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disqualified person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HE4A363E62FFD42DFABF5E97C4EB25DD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>disqualified person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2F4AFCE1F1FB48C0BF166D6E548D3F5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any citizen of a country of concern (other than a citizen, or lawful permanent resident, of the United States and other than an individual domiciled in Taiwan possessing a valid identification card or number issued by the government of Taiwan),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H340FE2EA6FEF4D23B8B5F973A7284415"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any entity domiciled in a country of concern (other than an entity domiciled in Taiwan),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13F2C437579C48F2AAB1A0B9FBC21010"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any country of concern and any political subdivision, agency, or instrumentality thereof, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76436BEE4EAB46649EFA328F1D56A2C2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>except as provided in paragraph (3), any entity if persons described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) (in the aggregate) 10-percent control such entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77A7CFAF3C20475C8038C681125E62B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>country of concern</quote> means any country the government of which is engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or the security and safety of United States persons, including the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, Iran, North Korea, Cuba, and the regime of Nicolas Maduro in Venezuela.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6097631C9DB4C4AB48188C4B57DC9FC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception for certain publicly traded corporations</header><subparagraph id="H4D34FA43B6384ADC804F1AF80FB1EF7F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity shall not be treated as described in paragraph (1)(D) if—</text><clause id="HE244759EBA48449092DCC0958FCDE1FB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such entity is a specified publicly traded corporation, or</text></clause><clause id="HAB1BFBF09B4049D7835EE2F3399C69B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specified publicly traded corporations (in the aggregate) control such entity.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89CD681E5D50447A8645C7D1E5D51A16"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Specified publicly traded corporation</header><clause id="H8DDB54BD9816485F9D618BC122B321A8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>specified publicly traded corporation</quote> means any corporation if—</text><subclause id="H81109C2BEEF24E98866063F063CA79B6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the stock of such corporation is regularly traded on an established securities market located in the United States, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2E0F6375601A447D8EA1DE4FD615FCFE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>specified disqualified persons do not (in the aggregate) control such corporation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE2E9FD761B34440CB25189EB68DACC8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Specified disqualified persons</header><text>The term <quote>specified disqualified persons</quote> means, with respect to any corporation referred to in clause (i), any person which—</text><subclause id="HFD3BDFD0D95F42389B6B65439CD68C97"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of paragraph (1), and</text></subclause><subclause id="H14585F4C50C1472CB0647F3D3B2B6700"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has 10-percent control such entity.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60E85C46A9B747A9B9062D51493EBF33"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prorated tax on acquisitions by entities not more than 50 percent controlled by disqualified persons</header><paragraph id="H2CB50532FD344817BF455F1812C32A45"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any disqualified person described in subsection (b)(1)(D) with respect to which persons described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) do not (in the aggregate) control such disqualified person, subsection (a) shall be applied by substituting <quote>the applicable percentage of the amount</quote> for <quote>the amount</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8FA836BF4F74ED79BDCF1951490732D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>applicable percentage</quote> means, with respect to any disqualified person to which paragraph (1) applies, the highest percentage which could be substituted for <quote>50 percent</quote> both places it appears in section 954(d)(3) without causing persons described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) (in the aggregate) to control (determined by taking into account such substitution) such disqualified person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B89CC0016874F0CAF1FD4C7890B79E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Control</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H7ADCBBF9EDB94CB7BFA34304E5E6681B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>control</quote> has the meaning given such term under section 954(d)(3), determined by treating the rules of section 958(a)(2) as applying to both foreign and domestic corporations, partnerships, trusts, and estates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFE142C0D2CF4DE3816CBB45E6D7849E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>10-percent control</header><text>The term <quote>10-percent control</quote> means control (as defined in paragraph (1)), determined by substituting <quote>10 percent</quote> for <quote>50 percent</quote> both places it appears in section 954(d)(3). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H671393FD8F424981AD26E39FDF1EA892"><enum>(e)</enum><header>United States agricultural interest</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H7C3575FFCEAB47EFBF282B47EBE532AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>United States agricultural interest</quote> has the meaning which would be given the term <quote>United States real property interest</quote> by section 897(c) if—</text><subparagraph id="HA6C01C47C52242518E159C23C8FEF767"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paragraph (1)(A)(i) were applied by substituting <quote>an interest in agricultural land</quote> for <quote>an interest in real property</quote> and all that follows, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6781CC51385487BB68167DC2A68B0A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>paragraph (1)(A)(ii) were applied by substituting <quote>such corporation was not a United States real property holding corporation at the time of acquisition</quote> for <quote>such corporation</quote> and all that follows,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08AAD4701B6F4C38BC2468B5C1E758B8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">paragraph (1)(B) did not apply, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7A7C5F5DF1445259B71ECC5A5A2210C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>paragraph (3) were applied by substituting <quote>at the time of acquisition</quote> for <quote>at some time during the shorter of the periods described in paragraph (1)(A)(ii)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H27A9CEC048404EC9A12FEBA16951F39F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agricultural land</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <quote>agricultural land</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HBCA95951834742698ADDEA80C05D1BD2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">agricultural land as defined in section 9 of the Agricultural Foreign Investment Disclosure Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3508">7 U.S.C. 3508</external-xref>), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13975037016D496B8EE187D0BC18E915"><enum>(B)</enum><text>land located in one or more States and used for livestock production purposes (determined under rules similar to the rules that apply under such section 9).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4B210C29B98145E4A04FF7D443531CF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="H3A050EC49ADD4A6783D4693FC54DE509"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subpart B of part III of subchapter A of chapter 61 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0BA995C2214F428F8756049D30C5E029" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H14E9EC277AB94B65BBC85EF6ADD8BA51"><enum>6050AA.</enum><header>Returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="H17A5C873CF1E4C4297E24C45039B5A95"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The required reporting person, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest by a presumptively disqualified person to which section 5000E(a) applies, shall make a return at such time as the Secretary may provide setting forth—</text><paragraph id="H4589439E6CB94660BFB8244DC7BE8F2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, address, and TIN of such presumptively disqualified person,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1FA45BF2C3142CE8AFCD8BB3B90041B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of such United States agricultural interest (including the street address, if applicable), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4B84C547A28414AAB8D9C750017020E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the amount paid for such United States agricultural interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDBC83177FB88419FA417E5AC157641E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement To be furnished to presumptively disqualified person</header><text>Every person required to make a return under subsection (a) shall furnish, at such time as the Secretary may provide, to each presumptively disqualified person whose name is required to be set forth in such return a written statement showing—</text><paragraph id="H6FE884FBF8F140D2861A7B08DE9EEDB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name and address of the information contact of the required reporting person, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DF7A6466FEA4D549FC32DD8913614D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the information described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a) which relates to such disqualified person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC52BB213CB7B4EE0A4489D03E0C07AD9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required reporting person</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>required reporting person</quote> means, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest—</text><paragraph id="HBF58F28805A04F6F90050AAE29D9E675"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person (including any attorney or title company) responsible for closing the transaction in which such United States agricultural interest is acquired, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DBD1D012520488AAFC681B132B44BC3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if no one is responsible for closing such transaction (or in such other cases as the Secretary may provide), the transferor of such United States agricultural interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4847194E22947CE8E087C4685F36891"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Presumptively disqualified person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>presumptively disqualified person</quote> means any person unless such person furnishes to the required reporting person an affidavit by the such person stating, under penalty of perjury, that such person is not a disqualified person (as defined in section 5000E(b)).</text></subsection><subsection id="H61F6EEC1D13543479DA48E93AD6F5945"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirement To request affidavit</header><text>If the required reporting person, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest, has not, as of the time of such acquisition, been furnished the affidavit described in subsection (d) by the acquirer of such interest, such required reporting person shall furnish to such acquirer, at such time, a written statement informing such acquirer of the required reporting person’s obligation to make the return described in subsection (a) with respect to such acquisition and including such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H92AD07F3E7864E8491B266F314706E13"><enum>(f)</enum><header>United States agricultural interest</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>United States agricultural interest</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 5000E.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BB33AB7B6314C8796A7542061736689"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6724(d) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H77CECCA75D3B4A00949C18B781276647"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of clause (xxvii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (xxviii) and inserting <quote>or</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4EC9A994B9154216BA6B294F1A8D8495" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H016CCAEFC04D40C79678C697E1553F34"><enum>(xxix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 6050AA(a) (relating to returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons), and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H470D84E2853D4FB9965223D9140DA6A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (KK), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (LL) and inserting <quote>, or</quote>, and by inserting after subparagraph (LL) the following new subparagraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H60418049BE884617B5ABB9433BB6C315" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H5E424441291644479521CFDF80F024CF"><enum>(MM)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subsection (b) or (e) of section 6055AA (relating to statements relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAAA3772EFBD149B08BE9CFB1A1C0A523"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><paragraph id="H717D3C33FAEC4E2EA3497A2FBA415D58"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of chapters for subtitle D of such Code is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 50A the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6B26B7B342D84D28B1BC78F40D66044F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HF9FE167A20864A7AB5426761BFF45D20" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H7FFF00728F434319B5FED845B354F04E" level="chapter">Chapter 50B. Acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D7223A9D64B4624B0D2F2B1F0E40AA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart B of part III of subchapter A of chapter 61 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H481FA8B2F8DA48488776642C26FBE6BB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H0BA995C2214F428F8756049D30C5E029" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H14E9EC277AB94B65BBC85EF6ADD8BA51" level="section">Sec. 6050AA. Returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HACAFD45D78A846A2994F54DAB59B2DB9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to acquisitions after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

