<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5AA91ECE44724E57A180ABBE265C3992" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1081 IH: Averting the National Threat of Internet Surveillance, Oppressive Censorship and Influence, and Algorithmic Learning by the Chinese Communist Party Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1081</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To protect Americans from the threat posed by certain foreign adversaries using current or potential future social media companies that those foreign adversaries control to surveil Americans, gather sensitive data about Americans, or spread influence campaigns, propaganda, and censorship.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE5062719DA244347967CD0EB3C2928BB" style="OLC">
<section id="HDB21DF8EBD0244F5998BE3CC8CE2E548" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Averting the National Threat of Internet Surveillance, Oppressive Censorship and Influence, and Algorithmic Learning by the Chinese Communist Party Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ANTI-SOCIAL CCP Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA1620DCA97334DBB84DD53B131B229B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protecting Americans from social media companies controlled by countries of concern</header> <subsection id="HBC288F127ABD4BBF99EC0F68C33EFCB9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibited commercial transactions</header> <paragraph id="H1C210AA972DA42F7950B5BB74F6B2DA2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On and after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall exercise all the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of a social media company described in subsection (b) if such property and interests in property—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC54BD963F0544EB29F313F455C1AC66A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are in the United States or come within the United States; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF5559B4A9F8E4F6CB8BF704D7759EDEA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent necessary to prevent commercial operation of the social media company in the United States, are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6E0117325A70480C8F90B6B1A8479053"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability of certain provisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of section 202 and the limitations under section 203(b) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1701 and 1702(b)) shall not apply for purposes of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6B66D5CBB89C494C8D3673B3947F2410"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Social media company described</header> <paragraph id="HD84CCF54360E46508C4106E2076D7BBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A social media company described in this subsection is a social media company that meets one or more of the following conditions: </text>
<subparagraph id="HC0411C9A0A5D4BC2A8EF48C3E2CD0179"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The company is domiciled in, has its principal place of business in, has its headquarters in, or is organized under the laws of a country of concern.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H55F4A89CB96B471F82FB2347CAD86429"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A country of concern, entity of concern, or some combination thereof, directly or indirectly owns, controls with the ability to decide important matters, or holds with power to vote, 20 percent or more of the outstanding voting stock or shares of the company.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC30235C44DE049969425EAD09371E64D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The company employs software or algorithms controlled or whose export is restricted by a country of concern or entity of concern.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB11D009F90145C987F8A29439296A2B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The company is subject to substantial influence, directly or indirectly, from a country of concern or entity of concern owing to which—</text>
<clause id="H45DC637B597041CDA5A20993FF7BBD4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the company shares or could be compelled to share data on United States citizens with a country of concern or entity of concern; or</text></clause> <clause id="H3D9E3FB869A149189FBDD970DE94182F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the content moderation practices of the company are subject to substantial influence from a country of concern or entity of concern.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4EA577017BA446F39EE2ADF2F9EEB82A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deemed companies</header><text>The following companies shall be deemed to be social media companies described in this subsection as of the date of the enactment of this Act unless and until the date on which the President certifies to Congress that the company no longer meets any of the conditions described in paragraph (1):</text> <subparagraph id="HF28009CDB9F7475896C5E0405594112F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Bytedance, Ltd.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE7633B7A112C4855B7AA8CA99A88C64E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>TikTok.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42CB89B682D9405FB2A3DC610F46C3B8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A subsidiary of or a successor company to a company listed in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF2C83542738E4EFAB97D26BA8D1B0758"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A company owned or controlled directly or indirectly by a company listed in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0ABA17A35D294D19AAAA16640C5053C8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <paragraph id="H47F7250076E84CE994FC5F436CA33AC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Intelligence activities</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any authorized intelligence activities of the United States. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H763375F7FC934825B296F39A7E1BFBCE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Importation of goods</header>
<subparagraph id="HD4C732BC47EE4A7AA75A3C87EA5D3D9A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The authorities and requirements to impose sanctions authorized under this section shall not include the authority or requirement to impose sanctions on the importation of goods. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3AAB23A8FD4B4C2594E04AE0B161FE88"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Good defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>good</term> means any article, natural or manmade substance, material, supply or manufactured product, including inspection and test equipment, and excluding technical data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF538097922584CD3803300E5E3F08821"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header>
<paragraph id="HF91D5B438E90443DA50809E627BD5E8E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise the authorities provided to the President under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to the extent necessary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A9F6C3F620A481589FC29D81C4CE3E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, or causes a violation of subsection (a) or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out that subsection shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of the section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H575C206F9F85461DB947F1EA16DEC9C4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Severability</header><text>If any provision of this section or its application to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity does not affect other provisions or applications of this section that can be given effect without the invalid provision or application, and to this end the provisions of this section are severable. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HF2DFC3D56B5C43AB8AD49FCF24B1EA7C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H8541E95BA16F4DA5B204B3CA14446501"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text>The term <term>country of concern</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H1C9E14D37EE6403AB37B7617E606FBEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term <term>foreign adversary</term> in section 8(c)(2) of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1607">47 U.S.C. 1607(c)(2)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD7CECDB01A654CD2A886DC9D61C04FF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes the People’s Republic of China (including the Special Administrative Regions of China, including Hong Kong and Macau), Russia, Iran, North Korea, Cuba, and Venezuela. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB96B760DDC64BF08ADC5B23B8CCC92D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Entity of concern</header><text>The term <term>entity of concern</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="HAC849CBFC0C1498D82CDF75B05CCCCE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a governmental body at any level in a country of concern;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H45199A96A58548749107588E126492B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the armed forces of a country of concern;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3FEBFDA1B4D84F9AA36C254A06DB993F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the leading political party of a country of concern;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF505192D263E46BD82DF3D91237CF58A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a natural person who is a national of a country of concern, is domiciled and living in such country, and is subject to substantial influence, directly or indirectly, from an entity described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3271CCBDAD1945AB9BD36061C1EF0CAE"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a private business or a state-owned enterprise that is domiciled in a country of concern, or owned or controlled by a private business or state-owned enterprise domiciled in a country of concern, and that is subject to substantial influence, directly or indirectly, from an entity described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE0A4CF33BDD4EB58F0E337254879CE9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Social media company</header><text>The term <term>social media company</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="HAD1331D24E1C4BE0B6752AE16E7802F2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any entity that operates, directly or indirectly, including through its parent company, subsidiaries, or affiliates, a website, desktop application, or mobile application that—</text> <clause id="H9D1974A4AB8C42E2929E63578239AED0" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>permits an individual or entity to create an account or profile for the purpose of generating, sharing, and viewing user-generated content through such account or profile;</text></clause>
<clause id="HBBFE930257884C85B66BA5DCEC859B54" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sells digital advertising space; </text></clause> <clause id="H9B11EEBDA9D4453684FA09396FEAD4A8" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has more than 1,000,000 monthly active users for a majority of months during the preceding 12 months;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6B71F90F799B4D279E7562896C4A663D" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>enables one or more users to generate content that can be viewed by other users of the website, desktop application, or mobile application; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6B6CDA244DAE449F924F82F71E6B94AB" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>enables users to view content generated by other users of the website, desktop application, or mobile application; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H49289E9C05E747E9832FCB5271F15C2D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an entity if the entity does not operate a website, desktop application, or mobile application except for a website, desktop application, or mobile application the primary purpose of which is—</text> <clause id="H1BEFC0FA98F74DEFBAF6A694E5DE0C12" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to allow users to post product reviews, business reviews, or travel information and reviews; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H01D339A70E08481BB5150E9165FDBCF8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to provide emergency alert services.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

