<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H06BCEEF5A83A47D1B19334C05DBDE3CA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5699 IH: Charles Rochester Blood Clot Prevention and Treatment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5699</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide programs to assist diagnosis, awareness, and education of blood clot conditions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0B8AD1F830134103801754DAD3A32343" style="OLC"><section id="HFF767099DCF94F4C8FFE60CA1486BB6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Charles Rochester Blood Clot Prevention and Treatment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF085136917884FE1B6CACE98BF33EFCE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H7E8AFC6E3D8F44BCA98B9032BC00FAA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Deep venous thrombosis (in this Act referred to as <quote>DVT</quote>) occurs when blood clots form in the legs, pelvis, or arms, and the most serious complications occur when a part of the clot breaks off and travels to the lungs, causing a blockage called pulmonary embolism (in this Act referred to as <quote>PE</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F2A4849673F4D149562EE96F24D62D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1 American dies every 6 minutes as a result of a blood clot, and 1 in 4 people who have a PE die without warning.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBF908CF9D734CB6BE7668B8523FFC5C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has estimated that about 900,000 people suffer from DVT/PE per year and 100,000 people die each year from blood clots, but also recognizes that the precise number of people affected by DVT/PE is unknown.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F0B50252FBF4E8CA2B639613946D593"><enum>(4)</enum><text>These numbers are estimated because currently there is no systematic collection of DVT/PE-related morbidity or mortality data in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDC9F49F106F4DC5B409F734373391B2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Blood clots can affect anyone, but certain risk factors make certain individuals more susceptible, including pregnancy, cancer, hospitalizations, obesity, older age, and African American race.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H878152D03A4F491D8A55BFAF24C3F682"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The overall incidence of DVT and PE is 30 to 60 percent higher in Black Americans, who also have a higher rate of 30-day mortality compared with White Americans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B2AB6D8B414C6CAB5622A426ED0D47"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The direct and indirect cost of blood clots is more than $10,000,000,000 annually.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C1665C1FE774527AC84E269A10E462B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Early diagnosis of a DVT is one of the most important factors in preventing a PE.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC2F557F03E9B4CF1B00FFAC3BC92E2B4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Public education, awareness, and diagnosis of DVT/PE</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part J of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280b">42 U.S.C. 280b et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 393D the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF438210A0B524F24AC68CEDC3A4267FC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H123346A673574AA4857C8AD47A1088FF"><enum>393E.</enum><header>Prevention of morbidity and mortality as a result of deep venous thromboembolism</header><subsection id="H186DD064990048BDB3C11BC6824372EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out projects to increase education, awareness, or diagnosis of deep venous thrombosis (in this section referred to as <quote>DVT</quote>) or pulmonary embolism (in this section referred to as <quote>PE</quote>) and to reduce the incidence of morbidity and mortality caused by blood clots. Such projects may be carried out by the Secretary directly or through awards of grants or contracts to public or nonprofit private entities. The Secretary may directly (or through such awards) provide technical assistance with respect to the planning, development, and operation of such projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF2C310E1D71143F1ABC90E77E4FB1E48"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Projects</header><text>A project under this section may include—</text><paragraph id="H0122681C31914A02A1196DDECD0520E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the implementation of public information and education programs for—</text><subparagraph id="HD9994566B70343508B5C25DC1695B051"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the prevention of death from DVT/PE;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA57172855D84F81BDDAD710390BD7D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">broadening the awareness of the public concerning—</text><clause id="HC60965F6071A428F8948875061014D24"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the risk factors for and the symptoms of DVT/PE;</text></clause><clause id="H2BB4560F60AF457DA06102020035E58B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>target populations with greater risk for DVT/PE, including women, seniors, cancer patients, hospitalized patients, pregnant and postpartum women, Black Americans, and those in rural areas; and</text></clause><clause id="H81A9AB1EEAC94E55BF5CFFE6B53F2AA1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the public health consequences of DVT/PE; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26F0EA298D324117BFB2B35A8F7BB129"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increasing screening, detection, and diagnosis of DVT/PE; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H358A0D65EEE64758B06917C883B58796"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">surveillance of the prevalence and incidence of DVT/PE to improve patient outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26B64C0661A945F4B9EA1C5E14B6A416"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant and contract prioritization</header><text>The Secretary may, in awarding grants or entering into contracts under this section, give priority to entities seeking to carry out projects that target the populations referred to in subsection (b)(1)(B)(ii).</text></subsection><subsection id="HA257A2E3AAE54C98971C426D6673A72C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination of activities</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that projects carried out under this section are coordinated, as appropriate, with other agencies of the Public Health Service that carry out activities regarding DVT/PE.</text></subsection><subsection id="H115599C265894993B47199940EC9A327"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HFF7F6677CEEA4EAA97B6CD4AFAEEC14C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collect and analyze the findings of research conducted with respect to DVT/PE; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FF0148A3C484697ADF167F04903EFD5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>taking into account such findings, publish on the website of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention best practices for physicians and other health care providers who provide care to individuals with DVT/PE.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H6059B391B0294087B193449A62F795AF"><enum>4.</enum><header>Advisory Committee for DVT/PE Prevention</header><subsection id="H7E4E83A38112452488A1B127DF413E57"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish an advisory committee to be known as the <quote>Advisory Committee for DVT/PE Prevention</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H333FB644DD87461681AC906A055EBD71"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall—</text><paragraph id="H0A2A647FD759491A8B438B511323F70B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify the aggregate number of individuals in the United States who experience DVT/PE annually;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFA06D5FBEF340849F1AC0906A533B82"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify how data are collected regarding DVT/PE and the adverse outcomes associated with such conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79762336A61347C7AD979F31520ADD79"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify how DVT/PE impacts the lives of individuals in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF5659ECC2F945A68D32831323555158"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify the standard of care for DVT/PE surveillance, detection, and treatment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB34B95A3AE1C47B5A9E9C91ED43DEF33"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify emerging treatments, therapies, and research relating to DVT/PE;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF36C7AE907B54BE3BABFB6332A2450EA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>develop recommendations to help health care providers identify patients who may be at a higher risk of forming DVT/PE in health care facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8F9A47A292942E68DDB5052BB380FC1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>develop recommendations to help improve patient awareness of DVT/PE;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4E66DF0757E477B8437AADCA3492E7A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>develop recommendations with respect to the standard of care for patients at risk of forming DVT/PE;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50E75D20EECB46BF97CE4BA5E80F6163"><enum>(9)</enum><text>develop recommendations relating to providing patients and their families with written notice of increased risks of forming DVT/PE; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB07865E16DF44FA9B611C22C3FCBB8C4"><enum>(10)</enum><text>identify the estimated level of Federal funding needed for DVT/PE services to meet the needs of high-risk populations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB9B9A3903FC41CF9C36157D7B44D6E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Committee shall be composed of members appointed by the Secretary as follows:</text><paragraph id="HE9FC83DD091A4E4BA199FD51F99BA464"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 1 individual who has experienced blood clots.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A0FF02A9F254454A73A53798638011D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At least 1 family member of an individual who died from DVT/PE.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1216E858A267426B914ED314DCAA66D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>At least 1 health services researcher.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6A129C417D94D05B823A3BB49A41F90"><enum>(4)</enum><text>At least 1 health care provider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F17712F42A64A68AC72D2BE7A888885"><enum>(5)</enum><text>At least 1 representative of a health plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0CFEE6A35E54866B61BC5FA280C6F72"><enum>(6)</enum><text>At least 1 representative of a hospital or health system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A46311B5983414D9818EE5D8C17D1EF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>At least 1 epidemiologist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD856D8090FEC48558B664EF69059ECAB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>At least 1 public health expert.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H219D43D578624497A57011524D484550"><enum>(9)</enum><text>At least 1 patient representative or representative of a patient group.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC7E1E87308547DFAE392EFC5FA6B7D0"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Such individuals representing other interested parties or associations, as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D5BCF4540E44DA89C06429A9A621715"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the first meeting of the Advisory Committee, the Secretary shall submit to Congress (and make publicly available) a report—</text><paragraph id="HF72677B3C41C4E7B9AACAC74038718C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>summarizing the meetings and findings of the Advisory Committee; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A0EC825500F473F9B36ABF759E58134"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describing the recommendations of the Advisory Committee for legislative or administrative action to improve DVT/PE prevention, treatment, and diagnosis, including the recommendations described in paragraphs (6) through (9) of subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3790393B9721425C8731DA07B4A5F833"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H343C34D82D8C4EF49D37214F2BB35862"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the Secretary submits the report under subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA9ACB173D284537ABBE99304C16AAED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date that is 18 months after the first meeting of the Advisory Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEF55CA8ADA8C4EF2B2CF980D77978DAA"><enum>5.</enum><header>DVT/PE surveillance study and report</header><subsection id="HC5664947AEEC4EEA8177330839733297"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall conduct or support a study on model systems of DVT/PE surveillance, including the use of electronic medical record-based methods of detecting DVT and PE International Classification of Diseases codes (commonly known as <quote>ICD codes</quote>) or other population-based surveillance.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB54B89376D8D41918C2C413CF59C5D16"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress and the Advisory Committee for DVT/PE Prevention established under section 4(a) a report detailing the results of the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H289E20B6D6974F5287E93CA9DCC7BAC5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2029.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

