<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2788C748B17C4FF39BBEFCEA1DA33E24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3468 IH: Electric Vehicles for All Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3468</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Energy to establish a grant program to facilitate electric vehicle sharing services operated at public housing projects, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H17E60B687C364C20903ABAC05874C384" style="OLC"><section display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="section-one" id="HCB43F5A64B4845DEA3A52A4D81A6F1ED"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Electric Vehicles for All Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EVs for All Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1ADDA746B3124C709CC0B2ADB110DE4E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Energy electric vehicle sharing service grant program</header><subsection id="H619E4BF40DE147D481CC62EABBD43F74"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDFDED13B92FF44EB975664147C6D2F9C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Charger</header><text>The term <term>charger</term> means a device with 1 or more charging ports and connectors for charging electric vehicles.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB3C3067413D8415C8BA180583509FD7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Electric vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>electric vehicle</term> means a vehicle that derives all of the power of the vehicle from electricity.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H25838AA527674548B574DE6946D26F98"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Electric vehicle sharing service</header><text>The term <term>electric vehicle sharing service</term> means a service that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB5E318E3A6D94C5094A851F292D61E4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allows an individual to apply for a membership that preapproves the individual to rent electric vehicles from the service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC94F621CFAB743E3AA52A0A8133BBA26" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>permits preapproved individuals to rent electric vehicles for short periods of time. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F3B31493BAB44FF87620C5EBD7FCD9D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Electric vehicle supply equipment</header><subparagraph id="HAC0D21AF57FC45208EB1B938A7B9E07D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>electric vehicle supply equipment</term> means any property, other than a building or a structural component of a building, that is—</text><clause id="H34EDAAAA0AB04573A5B84C8B9228523D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a charger;</text></clause><clause id="HE3B121F29F874FA6B9EF67906E071D91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>present at the location where electric vehicles are charged; and</text></clause><clause id="H749B37361C7B4C7382B16B435E7C19AF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>available for use by members of the general public.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54BB0DB67AA4467997827FD09CB71FC8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>electric vehicle supply equipment</term> includes any utility service connection, or utility panel upgrade, that is required for the charging of electric vehicles.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F5CF037D173435EBAA78799FB8031D7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H3EAC0483C9F4484494F7926090E36B12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a public housing agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BB9C796565C48639398E74DC90A5082"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a unit of local government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B14C41DDF7C404C96915B9CD130840F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization that has entered into an agreement with a public housing agency or unit of local government under which the public housing agency or unit of local government agrees to host an electric vehicle sharing service on the property of the public housing agency or unit of local government. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H456D8416EDC945C2BC3405B2466D3EE2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Fair labor practices</header><text>The term <term>fair labor practices</term> means practices that comply with applicable labor laws and regulations and provide workers with fair wages, safe working conditions, and protections against discrimination, harassment, and exploitation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63E1DFA381404EE19F70EB47F074333C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Final assembly</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>final assembly</term> means the process by which a manufacturer produces a new electric vehicle at, or through the use of, a plant, factory, or other place from which the electric vehicle is delivered to a dealer or importer with all component parts necessary for the mechanical operation of the electric vehicle included with the electric vehicle, regardless of whether the component parts are permanently installed in or on the electric vehicle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D674E8E5C9B46F7B51B23634592FA67"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Major urban area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>major urban area</term> means a metropolitan statistical area within the United States with an estimated population of not less than 1,500,000 residents.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE2CBBE1C5EAA4304A69A43CAA748E4FA"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Networked direct current fast charging equipment</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H425600F54F694F18AAB7E43D6776BBAA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>networked direct current fast charging equipment</term> means electric vehicle charging equipment that—</text><clause commented="no" id="H868F8F62139D441895D2D209565D799D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provides a direct current power source at a minimum of 50 kilowatts; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H896AABA7F0A44019BF00501F4289CBCB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is enabled to connect to a network to facilitate data collection and access.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H90D3034928A54F55B5B3B7A566870972"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>networked direct current fast charging equipment</term> includes a Direct Current Fast Charger.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AE4F319D85D409BA1471B0942C285FE"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Registered apprentice</header><text>The term <term>registered apprentice</term> means a person participating in a program registered pursuant to the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>) (50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B6DCE3E5F074682B3D4D95268A19341" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H055894E126BB48169F78B1B0D79DFD11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Transportation and the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, shall carry out a program to award grants, on a competitive basis, to facilitate electric vehicle sharing services operated at public housing projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="H185C1BFE4BA644D8AE856B2D080777D0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application in such form, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC0A2D1537F2E4C528A1537EEBA142C8D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Criteria for grant awards</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall consider the following criteria:</text><paragraph id="H65CAD2D0C5654412BF503F47C71B619D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The capacity of an eligible entity to operate a proposed electric vehicle sharing service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63F7A77ABC3B43539184B4228AB2DA81"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether a proposed electric vehicle sharing service would address—</text><subparagraph id="HB3004D6317ED43BCAEA742C93112C0BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the infrastructure needs of the public housing project where that electric vehicle sharing service will be operated; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF32311710CC44E1881CF3FADC0ED7EE3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the transportation needs of the community surrounding the public housing project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2F18487495C4B5E9A07DFF6DC33DDD7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether the eligible entity has developed a culturally competent community engagement and education plan for outreach regarding the proposed electric vehicle sharing service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE19B1E2C9C5E42B4B97E23D84C3E2209"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The economic and operational sustainability of the proposed electric vehicle sharing service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2744BB5D7A9843479BE8159CD4E1CC06"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether the eligible entity proposes to install networked direct current fast charging equipment in connection with the proposed electric vehicle sharing service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2DC2FDF9A5D40C2A35D69CA6694F2D2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Whether the eligible entity proposes to purchase electric vehicles with respect to which final assembly occurred at a location operating under a collective bargaining agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1596FE1E123464DB6078DFD9458828C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Whether the eligible entity proposes to purchase electric vehicles that—</text><subparagraph id="HC63F496E72CD4CB0957382CECEE700B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to final assembly, are assembled using component parts that are at least 50 percent domestic content; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEE5E467D91C480CB9A80D65C2E196D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are powered by battery cells manufactured in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D2DCC0E55D34F2CB05F42DD2A65EB4C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Whether the eligible entity proposes to purchase electric vehicles from manufacturers that prioritize fair labor practices and worker protections, as demonstrated through certification programs or publicly available reports on the supply chain practices of the manufacturer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC922973B72EB4D9280F7A18396348B3D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Other criteria as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H474C5CCEFBFB4C5E83920C4E2D53FAA2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prioritization of grant awards to marginalized communities</header><paragraph id="H2B8B814351C44E2386A5DD97C1D8DD57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that serve communities that have been historically marginalized or disproportionately impacted by environmental injustice.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA0DE3E5E7984646A1E3A24607905446"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for prioritization</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider the extent to which the proposed public housing project—</text><subparagraph id="H6B79CACCD18B48DDB7B1157D819986FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is located in a community that has—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFA53D8A01914E479383A44218D65541"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disproportionately high rates of pollution and poor air quality; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA6A460F6685F4E7F86F3EDAFE209B696"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">limited access to affordable transportation options; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E9C8565091545539C0F0CEA4348D779"><enum>(B)</enum><text>will benefit from an electric vehicle sharing service, especially with respect to addressing transportation needs and reducing greenhouse gas emissions and criteria air pollutants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H260C11ECC00748B987D5F4F5B679193D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Permitted grant uses</header><paragraph id="HCE514D738FF645DD93E47562FEC4AF5C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity awarded a grant under this section may only use grant funds for the following activities to facilitate an electric vehicle sharing service operated at a public housing project:</text><subparagraph id="HA9B611277D3F4FABA9B119B99AD63694"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The purchase of light-duty electric vehicles that are not more than 5 years old.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1B3A27B11814A4B9D8792EA774A6A38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The purchase, installation, and maintenance of electric vehicle supply equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB314C8CFD95E4CE98D8E898049974777"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Conducting community education and outreach with respect to the electric vehicle sharing service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEABA72493BCB48DBB4F3100A211C12CC"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing incentives for residents of the public housing project to use the electric vehicle sharing service, including subsidized fares.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD770F69A05D64EA3879E5DE190120A79"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Maintenance, repairs, and other costs associated with operating the electric vehicle sharing service, including towing, impound, and driving infraction fines.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22AD5FCA770447BCBB3E337650D8281E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Monitoring, data collection, and evaluation with respect to the electric vehicle sharing service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82A0851FB46F48DBB2B6FF64C57BBB04"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Obtaining technical assistance relating to the establishment, operation, and evaluation of the electric vehicle sharing service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H570FF95265B245B2AF67298D52CD26B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum standards for purchased electric vehicles</header><text>The Secretary shall establish minimum standards relating to functionality and range for electric vehicles eligible to be purchased under paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8752A4E46FD84A09A7EFB9C59E44993D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Grant limitations</header><paragraph id="H9AB383ED681F41A1B835B48FF867D20B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grant funds awarded under this section to an eligible entity shall be available for obligation or expenditure during the 5-year period beginning on the date on which the grant funds are awarded.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1CD5437C82B4BA5AB40FF50CC06E80E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E2A41678A254984859B11C1E9CC672E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), the amount of a grant under this section shall not be more than $1,000,000 for each public housing project at which the eligible entity receiving the grant will operate an electric vehicle sharing service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E708F99049041FCBA7885CB171AF1BC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Networked direct current fast charging equipment</header><text>In the case of a public housing project that includes the installation of networked direct current fast charging equipment, the maximum amount of a grant under subparagraph (A) may be increased by $50,000 per unit of networked direct current fast charging equipment, for not more than 2 units of networked direct current fast charging equipment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H630B9EEB411D4FE7843474F415A559E3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary, before the end of each year during which the eligible entity receives grant amounts, a report that—</text><paragraph id="H05E04AEAA798489BAAE56AE718E28785"><enum>(1)</enum><text>describes the activities carried out with the grant amounts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E635BD526D046E78C602FAA8E22C53A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes data on—</text><subparagraph id="H50A4DCF093FF409D98DC21404200A3E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the operating and capital costs for the electric vehicle sharing service facilitated with those grant amounts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E7CBDEE55A44C0DA3C26CC7262E9A3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the revenue generated by the electric vehicle sharing service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FC557E5AAAA42F28BE3B4B892E5866E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the daily averages of individual bookings and hours of electric vehicle use for the electric vehicle sharing service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13F361E30FD14449979BE9C5150C5E0B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of active users of the electric vehicle sharing service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB078D579F117410D97201040683AD40A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the distance traveled by the electric vehicles of the electric vehicle sharing service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9AC0039C1324C3D819FBE67D21ECF9E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the estimated reduction in greenhouse gas emissions and criteria air pollutants associated with the electric vehicle sharing service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A44331E67BB469282F069098E2A7555"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the results of a survey of customers of the electric vehicle sharing service that provides information on customer preferences, destinations, and other information the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9371AF5126FC48CBA8EA78E8450FAE8F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Labor</header><paragraph id="HE2C4FF4BD41C424A92EB879EDDA96D2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Contracts for installation of electric vehicle supply equipment</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall ensure, to the maximum extent practicable, that—</text><subparagraph id="H6BF06AA5E0504F85813AF38BC1B6700D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not less than 40 percent of the employees of any nongovernmental entity that enters into a contract with the eligible entity, or a subcontract thereof, for the installation of electric vehicle supply equipment are—</text><clause id="H8AA92D0FA3B54B4391B68CBC8AF47281"><enum>(i)</enum><text>domiciled—</text><subclause id="HDB88CB3014604DB2A7ECCE9872A0426B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the installation is carried out at a location in a major urban area, not farther than 15 miles from the location of the installation; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H02E24642D0D149DEAB51EE12172CF22F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the installation is not carried out at a location in a major urban area, not farther than 50 miles from the location of the installation;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4EA6B223196E4E43B5244D6A4B350029"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>members or veterans of the Armed Forces;</text></clause><clause id="H285AFA4B262B428C9D9EC08A8366E0E5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">displaced and unemployed energy workers;</text></clause><clause id="H4AC1528AF8514E9691A735E2956B0E9D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>registered apprentices who have completed less than 15 percent of the required hours for the apprenticeship program in which the registered apprentices are enrolled; or</text></clause><clause id="H00C4CBCC47224478A588A26482B4C525"><enum>(v)</enum><text>persons who—</text><subclause id="HC93CE4071AD140DFAEFBF01F98CE7403"><enum>(I)</enum><text>were formerly—</text><item id="HF07D590D91F74C1DB9EF0704DDDD3A48"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>incarcerated in a juvenile or adult detention or correctional facility; or</text></item><item id="HF16F27C9961E487692A9C8853C8427EB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>placed on probation, community supervision, or in a diversion program;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HF98BE0AED68A435A80E852A4820DB3DB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>are emancipated from the foster care system;</text></subclause><subclause id="H8A170FEA7BC840568A8CCE96D4162E7A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>have a disability;</text></subclause><subclause id="H55C2D13C5CA14439A5A29555317D9895"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>are experiencing homelessness;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1161E85A53F941A290BE37499D6DF08E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>receive public assistance; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H0CCF34ACE829456281CD4C58C87DC7BC"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>lack a general education or high school diploma; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H247749EC40944F7D9B52F62BF68ADC2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all electricians installing, maintaining, and operating electric vehicle supply equipment (including chargers) shall be—</text><clause id="HA8909DD33FF34F3F933C02F47E812423"><enum>(i)</enum><text>certified through the Electric Vehicle Infrastructure Training Program (as defined in section 680.104 of title 23, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations)); or</text></clause><clause id="H33B9515641794FC8B66486697EBB5E87"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>graduates of or in possession of a continuing education certificate from a registered apprenticeship program for electricians that—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC24B1CB203E44FEA1081DB1BC8A4ADB"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes charger-specific training; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HAC03D0E0ACAE406C9A725338F89C2F8A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>complies with the standards and requirements of the National Electric Vehicle Infrastructure Formula Program.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7FA620C3BF0E4560B6104D3B8F4D2C0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Wages</header><subparagraph id="HFEFE8DC79AE14E5E8F1FC6C525E81544"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall ensure that all laborers and mechanics employed by a nongovernmental entity that enters into a contract for the performance of construction, alteration, or repair work that is facilitated, in whole or in part, by the grant, or a subcontract thereof, are paid wages at rates not less than those prevailing on similar construction, alteration, or repair work in the locality as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Davis-Bacon Act</quote>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CBF84F35FF942C082A349AE6CF26EA5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Labor standards</header><text>With respect to the labor standards described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary of Labor shall have the authority and functions set forth in Reorganization Plan Numbered 14 of 1950 (64 Stat. 1267; 5 U.S.C. App.) and section 3145 of title 40, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66A85D8366824D17B2070A49D57D407B"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Limits on charging fees</header><paragraph id="HC55609C2044142E89BEA3B3641146CEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that installs an electric vehicle charging station using a grant received under this section—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3548F23AA2994492B0B8F40B586DAC53"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall implement pricing policies for that electric vehicle charging station that are affordable and equitable for all users; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB9022467FD047F891890588C806E115"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not impose fees for that electric vehicle charging station that are excessive, in accordance with paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2B87AE3B2FE4EE4A5A573E4E8BF5004"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Excessive fees</header><text>A fee shall be considered excessive for purposes of paragraph (1)(B) if the fee is—</text><subparagraph id="H2D1A7A4529BB4FDA8B0578A2851A7F26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>higher than the average market rate for charging services in the same geographic area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4645BE60E004280B4C9E2DBF59DF005"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not proportional to the cost of providing the charging service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H219146ADBD55452188696831282C5128"><enum>(C)</enum><text>designed to discourage or prevent use of the charging station; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3313C4435DA481F96DD00EC99821FB3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>designed to generate revenue for the entity operating the charging station beyond the reasonable costs of providing the charging service. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F4908797FFC478B80EB0AFBBE1A7158"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2033.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

