<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H11363681ED4745BA92F99560E6A45ED3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3707 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide a tax credit for expenses for household and elder care services necessary for gainful employment.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3707</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide a tax credit for expenses for household and elder care services necessary for gainful employment.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB54F6C7C888243A4888F2E7B590F5E89" style="OLC"><section id="HB0DD5CBBEA8946C7822DA1C2985C87B0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Expenses for household and elder care services necessary for gainful employment</header><subsection id="H8350A693F75D452597CBAA1DD3CCF719"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart A of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C7D22D55132466B9A0ED354517E0380" style="OLC"><section id="H858F0A2828D04CDCAE9281C3D994F9C3"><enum>25F.</enum><header>Expenses for household and elder care services necessary for gainful employment</header><subsection id="H3923C9DA55954CD9B7DA59A2546DF8C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><paragraph id="H1EC3B6C5FD1E4B6E8CCB976A721CB9C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of an individual for which there are one or more qualifying individuals (as defined in subsection (b)(1)) with respect to such individual, there shall be allowed as a credit against the tax imposed by this chapter for the taxable year an amount equal to the applicable percentage of the employment-related expenses (as defined in subsection (b)(2)) paid by such individual during the taxable year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A2A489D92CF4CB09657269376CB43B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable percentage defined</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <term>applicable percentage</term> means 35 percent reduced (but not below 20 percent) by 1 percentage point for each $2,000 (or fraction thereof) by which the taxpayer’s adjusted gross income for the taxable year exceeds $15,000.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59BE8252EEDB4AA298B73A9AC8AF2612"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions of qualifying individual and employment-Related expenses</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H35400425E269484A83820DD0E02F3F28"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Qualifying individual</header><text>The term <term>qualifying individual</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HBFBC767D992640F5B1A90E86E1310587"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has attained age 50, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD093315A1164E548F65F79A18518329"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is one of the following:</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8E6E4271CD1E4858A998FD441AA1984A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An individual who bears a relationship to the taxpayer described in subparagraph (C) or (D) of section 152(d)(2) (relating to fathers, mothers, and ancestors).</text></clause><clause id="H181D4C72CB394E5BAB07BAB865276BF3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual would be a dependent of the taxpayer (as defined in section 152, determined without regard to subsections (b)(1) and (b)(2)) as a qualifying relative described in section 152(d)(1) if—</text><subclause id="H8509DF4D7E984B8C9822621383943E7E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in lieu of subparagraphs (B) and (C) thereof the following applied with respect to the individual:</text><item id="H4E45EE9494F0415498EC602DB5FF5DCD"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the taxpayer has provided over one-half of the individual’s support for the calendar year in which such taxable year begins and each of the preceding 4 taxable years, and</text></item><item id="H954CBF72DBA94848B6966629AAE759C1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the individual’s modified adjusted gross income for the calendar year in which such taxable year begins is less than the exemption amount (as defined in section 151(d)),</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H69FA81076887471E9C79940B30FB8AE5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the individual is physically or mentally incapable of caring for himself or herself, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0004E59340A44F72A89FC8CB9C8AFF1C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the individual who has the same principal place of abode as the taxpayer for more than one-half of such taxable year.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC2171D6164184E678359998D941ABDC5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The spouse of the taxpayer who is physically or mentally incapable of caring for himself or herself.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F0035EE2DFB49C681DEC53FA2C84B75"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Modified adjusted gross income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>modified adjusted gross income</term> means adjusted gross income determined without regard to section 86.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF51E34BB19B943FB89DE369FBFCDE084"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Employment-related expenses</header><subparagraph id="H3B9D23CFF7964E42ACDE31989C566EAD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>employment-related expenses</term> means amounts paid for the following expenses, but only if such expenses are incurred to enable the taxpayer to be gainfully employed for any period for which there are one or more qualifying individuals with respect to the taxpayer:</text><clause id="HA06D252C3E954AF9B22B461F3290ACA4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>expenses for household services, and</text></clause><clause id="H3D7CE74221E6487380A855428EA90C4B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expenses for the care of a qualifying individual, including expenses for respite care and hospice care.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E5685EA970B468FB87ADAB82DCED766"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Employment-related expenses described in subparagraph (A) which are incurred for services outside the taxpayer’s household shall be taken into account only if incurred for the care of—</text><clause id="H5C0B8F3C7C2947D6AA9C47A1543C3A0E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a qualifying individual described in paragraph (1)(A), or</text></clause><clause id="H917C86E2B6D4489F89EA65EE27A8B530"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a qualifying individual (not described in paragraph (1)(A)) who regularly spends at least 8 hours each day in the taxpayer’s household.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD84BD24044CD4248A652D6D4C9A2C862"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Dependent care centers</header><text>Employment-related expenses described in subparagraph (A) which are incurred for services provided outside the taxpayer’s household by a dependent care center (as defined in subparagraph (D)) shall be taken into account only if—</text><clause id="H59B877EEE7224140B95CADB9806A7371"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such center complies with all applicable laws and regulations of a State or unit of local government, and</text></clause><clause id="HFF043C92FEE54F50A97907F3B3446BA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the requirements of subparagraph (B) are met.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H661C4DDBA5044657A51B81158CC30A0B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Dependent care center defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>dependent care center</term> means any facility which—</text><clause id="H70555D8E71A4448983F7ED15BC6667CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provides care for more than six individuals (other than individuals who reside at the facility), and</text></clause><clause id="H340B1A04DDA949D584F1AC07B9574ADF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>receives a fee, payment, or grant for providing services for any of the individuals (regardless of whether such facility is operated for profit).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H48D5971C70EB44E7ACCC71C6BA4A827F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Dollar limit on amount creditable</header><text>The amount of the employment-related expenses incurred during any taxable year which may be taken into account under subsection (a) shall not exceed—</text><paragraph id="H0D6FB6B6C2264395A3154127229C88EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$3,000 if there is 1 qualifying individual with respect to the taxpayer for such taxable year, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1592EC80EABE47E687E2C6E5AECBECF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$6,000 if there are two or more qualifying individuals with respect to the taxpayer for such taxable year.</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">The amount determined under paragraph (1) or (2) (whichever is applicable) shall be reduced by the aggregate amount excludable from gross income under section 129 for the taxable year. </continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="H58ECA768EDF34AB4B1C2DBCDEF7A88EC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Earned income limitation</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the amount of the employment-related expenses incurred during any taxable year which may be taken into account under subsection (a) shall not exceed—</text><paragraph id="H4B2471D1C6374966B54155DFE9E3146E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who is not married at the close of such year, such individual’s earned income for such year, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C18A6C0C7834EE2A11C400A793CE66F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who is married at the close of such year, the lesser of such individual’s earned income or the earned income of his spouse for such year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1232EFF7489441D18CDD98B44FFA79CE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special rules</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H1F58AE1EF810437FB960BFB3BEAC31D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Place of abode</header><text>An individual shall not be treated as having the same principal place of abode of the taxpayer if at any time during the taxable year of the taxpayer the relationship between the individual and the taxpayer is in violation of local law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D5E576277014808AE9C43C37C0A90A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Married couples must file joint return</header><text>If the taxpayer is married at the close of the taxable year, the credit shall be allowed under subsection (a) only if the taxpayer and his spouse file a joint return for the taxable year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D5761E3BF904EC8A2CE7BBF8208F17B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Marital status</header><text>An individual legally separated from his spouse under a decree of divorce or of separate maintenance shall not be considered as married.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C2030A0BEBE4D9DA299850F5DF13674"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certain married individuals living apart</header><text>If—</text><subparagraph id="H5C82F84A925A4571932760418CAA345F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is married and who files a separate return—</text><clause id="H49F245C21A444A7CAB00AE883F5EE063"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maintains as his home a household which constitutes for more than one-half of the taxable year the principal place of abode of a qualifying individual, and</text></clause><clause id="H6BFA933CEE8244179E120682AA2B1553"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>furnishes over half of the cost of maintaining such household during the taxable year, and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D43081AD3AE4524AA5AB9C2A14FECED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the last 6 months of such taxable year such individual’s spouse is not a member of such household, such individual shall not be considered as married.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BE8C03295F24348B622CA00E26A7219"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Payments to related individuals</header><text>No credit shall be allowed under subsection (a) for any amount paid by the taxpayer to an individual—</text><subparagraph id="H6D18E152EB4142F595AD70F20F6BAF48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to whom, for the taxable year, a deduction under section 151(c) (relating to deduction for personal exemptions for dependents) is allowable either to the taxpayer or his spouse, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EAB213D89CC4CDDBFD095B687304689"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is a child of the taxpayer (within the meaning of section 152(f)(1)) who has not attained the age of 19 at the close of the taxable year.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>taxable year</term> means the taxable year of the taxpayer in which the service is performed. </continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95EAB7D4B4D647BA802C3EA7D246C2E1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Identifying information required with respect to service provider</header><text>No credit shall be allowed under subsection (a) for any amount paid to any person unless—</text><subparagraph id="H6AD84C8AFC1049788456C6CDECA6E9CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name, address, and taxpayer identification number of such person are included on the return claiming the credit, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9AD0BC42534423794258843EA66F0C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if such person is an organization described in section 501(c)(3) and exempt from tax under section 501(a), the name and address of such person are included on the return claiming the credit.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">In the case of a failure to provide the information required under the preceding sentence, the preceding sentence shall not apply if it is shown that the taxpayer exercised due diligence in attempting to provide the information so required. </continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC428BD3C63A04ACDB02B4F6946F5A64D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Identifying information required with respect to qualifying individuals</header><text>No credit shall be allowed under this section with respect to any qualifying individual unless the TIN of such individual is included on the return claiming the credit.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A341CB3291946889DE258F118DA7CF5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to carry out the purposes of this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBEB4C943BE6D42FFB39C4F04D0ACA8B5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart A of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAED56C43237A4C9188DE7EAA20A9D6AD" style="OLC"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" idref="H8C7D22D55132466B9A0ED354517E0380" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"><toc-entry idref="H858F0A2828D04CDCAE9281C3D994F9C3" level="section">Sec. 25F. Expenses for household and elder care services necessary for gainful employment.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HB3868BF117854509BD38F9BB229F8DF3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

