<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2037B7E5393241849007242DD3DC91BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2546 IH: To provide for the development and implementation of economic defense response teams.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2546</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230410">April 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the development and implementation of economic defense response teams.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4524DD2F05B64D6D932758E46F2FEE11" style="OLC"><section id="H594C155EA48F42E7B91538EB05940F53" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Economic defense response teams</header><subsection id="HA23484ED2FDD428EB996E129C11200FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President, acting through the Secretary of State, shall develop and implement a pilot program for the creation of deployable economic defense response teams to help provide emergency technical assistance and support to a country subjected to the threat or use of coercive economic measures and to play a liaison role between the legitimate government of that country and the United States Government. Such assistance and support may include the following activities:</text><paragraph id="HAA2E0F9932DA499CB03C42606F88A33F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Reducing the partner country’s vulnerability to coercive economic measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E87B1CFC37F4B6FA1E621646B7FDA68"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Minimizing the damage that such measures by an adversary could cause to that country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08774405592C4AD5825D358C081E947F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Implementing any bilateral or multilateral contingency plans that may exist for responding to the threat or use of such measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAB48C957F38464585158F1990982DA1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In coordination with the partner country, developing or improving plans and strategies by the country for reducing vulnerabilities and improving responses to such measures in the future.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA73C3F5B4DD241AA9B4F3F520E520D29"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Assisting the partner country in dealing with foreign sovereign investment in infrastructure or related projects that may undermine the partner country’s sovereignty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CCCA2D62D84E478D8791016C7FF42E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Assisting the partner country in responding to specific efforts from an adversary attempting to employ economic coercion that undermines the partner country’s sovereignty, including efforts in the cyber domain, such as efforts that undermine cybersecurity or digital security of the partner country or initiatives that introduce digital technologies in a manner that undermines freedom, security, and sovereignty of the partner country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69C6F060957647C894B837897F535939"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Otherwise providing direct and relevant short-to-medium term economic or other assistance from the United States and marshalling other resources in support of effective responses to such measures.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H901C85C8C5774E9691815E7D13C673BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Institutional support</header><text>The pilot program required by subsection (a) should include the following elements:</text><paragraph id="H7073490B6F1B48FCACDE0050285936C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Identification and designation of relevant personnel within the United States Government with expertise relevant to the objectives specified in subsection (a), including personnel in—</text><subparagraph id="H64AEDBBE1358476A93EDE0A50299874D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of State, for overseeing the economic defense response team’s activities, engaging with the partner country government and other stakeholders, and other purposes relevant to advancing the success of the mission of the economic defense response team;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FF1AA2EF45543FEB7BA127857BFA66B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the United States Agency for International Development, for the purposes of providing technical, humanitarian, and other assistance, generally;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6051F2F870041889177BFCF8C0C7927"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of the Treasury, for the purposes of providing advisory support and assistance on all financial matters and fiscal implications of the crisis at hand;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E3609ACF6374C3A87AB3E781C48AE80"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Commerce, for the purposes of providing economic analysis and assistance in market development relevant to the partner country’s response to the crisis at hand, technology security as appropriate, and other matters that may be relevant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H611326D2ABAE4C7785CB5F6B807AE466"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Department of Energy, for the purposes of providing advisory services and technical assistance with respect to energy needs as affected by the crisis at hand;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H373FF3BCB9D14735B4C3C26E1304BCDE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security, for the purposes of providing assistance with respect to digital and cybersecurity matters, and assisting in the development of any contingency plans referred to in paragraphs (3) and (6) of subsection (a) as appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC854F79ADD40407C8A82595CA43C2F0D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Department of Agriculture, for providing advisory and other assistance with respect to responding to coercive measures such as arbitrary market closures that affect the partner country’s agricultural sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H953873069FFF4F24A99228939840446B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Office of the United States Trade Representative with respect to providing support and guidance on trade and investment matters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89AE298B34684AFB9C7155B378A06757"><enum>(I)</enum><text>other Federal departments and agencies as determined by the President.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAAC0CA949FD471FB7A0FDF2C7AB4509"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Negotiation of memoranda of understanding, where appropriate, with other United States Government components for the provision of any relevant participating or detailed non-Department of State personnel identified under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85019726D830461DA6130D92B0F1D566"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Negotiation of contracts, as appropriate, with private sector representatives or other individuals with relevant expertise to advance the objectives specified in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50EED453FB974B9EBDD0BE77010EC261"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Development within the United States Government of—</text><subparagraph id="H4D759AC3FC7B45438E78EED5C0E52CEB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appropriate training curricula for relevant experts identified under paragraph (1) and for United States diplomatic personnel in a country actually or potentially threatened by coercive economic measures;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4086183F5E4D49C4A38D8174D099FC15"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operational procedures and appropriate protocols for the rapid assembly of such experts into one or more teams for deployment to a country actually or potentially threatened by coercive economic measures; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD95D6D0CC087438894E51E0F54D7E7AF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>procedures for ensuring appropriate support for such teams when serving in a country actually or potentially threatened by coercive economic measures, including, as applicable, logistical assistance, office space, information support, and communications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7403134B5EC24954B31078EE5F129D5C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Negotiation with relevant potential host countries of procedures and methods for ensuring the rapid and effective deployment of such teams, and the establishment of appropriate liaison relationships with local public and private sector officials and entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF241EDBC9E3B44649D43630CB3D54043"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports required</header><paragraph id="H904423BC2C244D21AABD74E1398A7681"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report on establishment</header><text>Upon establishment of the pilot program required by subsection (a), the Secretary of State shall provide the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives with a detailed report and briefing describing the pilot program, the major elements of the program, the personnel and institutions involved, and the degree to which the program incorporates the elements described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4309AFBBB18443779B0D98792220ACED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Follow-up report</header><text>Not later than one year after the report required by paragraph (1), the Secretary of State shall provide the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives with a detailed report and briefing describing the operations over the previous year of the pilot program established pursuant to subsection (a), as well as the Secretary’s assessment of its performance and suitability for becoming a permanent program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H837C652C98844CBBBC285553EC3833EA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required under this subsection shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF82990179730428BBA560EBA66F615F2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Declaration of an economic crisis required</header><paragraph id="HED10CB45558B4A9FB8321EA06755459F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>The President may activate an economic defense response team for a period of 180 days under the authorities of this section to assist a partner country in responding to an unusual and extraordinary economic coercive threat by an adversary of the United States upon the declaration of a coercive economic emergency, together with notification to the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1F58B275AC404B86C2C55F4B417C53"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extension authority</header><text>The President may activate the response team for an additional 180 days upon the submission of a detailed analysis to the committees described in paragraph (1) justifying why the continued deployment of the economic defense response team in response to the economic emergency is in the national security interest of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9F141B5646C2413EBD3666153E8CD019"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authorities provided under this section shall expire on December 31, 2026. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

