<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAB3E71BC26434EB4927858A05083B21E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2556 IH: Simplify, Don’t Amplify the IRS Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2556</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230410">April 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to improve and promote transparency, efficiency and operational integrity of the Internal Revenue Service, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8D33E0873B73451EBF8299C32F2CBCEC" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HDA78CEABB101463D8ECA96114EDD7916"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Simplify, Don’t Amplify the IRS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><title style="OLC" id="H1C4099DEB1314059BA33DDB9EA9A19F9"><enum>I</enum><header>Provisions relating to tax administration and taxpayer protection</header><section id="H9E5E1FBB9DA84BCF8FC8BB9ADE20FF5A"><enum>101.</enum><header>Preventing weaponization of the Internal Revenue Service</header><subsection id="HAF37EC232859402FB7AE509085E334A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Organizations exempt from reporting</header><paragraph id="H0BAAB74084AD4BCCAE71901D6E9B9685"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gross receipts threshold</header><text>Clause (ii) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">section 6033(a)(3)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>$5,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$50,000</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C3A227BB638406897C2579BBF4A89FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Organizations described</header><text>Subparagraph (C) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">section 6033(a)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H4620BDB0786B476DBD2EDFC3C9DA2C59"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (v),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5590AE9B5DB64CD1921EF35594BAC8FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of clause (vi) and inserting a semicolon, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32E390B01EE64CE8B763D48AA947E924"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clauses:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07872667490746D5A66FDAD42D0207C3"><clause id="HF2C81199AE6B434BB2ABA0812A33EEA9"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any other organization described in section 501(c) (other than a private foundation or a supporting organization described in section 509(a)(3)); and</text></clause><clause id="HA7D227E970F149C989BD5784CC51EAA4"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>any organization (other than a private foundation or a supporting organization described in section 509(a)(3)) which is not described in section 170(c)(2)(A), or which is created or organized in a possession of the United States, which has no significant activity (including lobbying and political activity and the operation of a trade or business) other than investment activity in the United States.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9457D565CA694AB09C268F612BF8174A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95F9E616F78A4A67AB9AA272EF4EB49C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification of application to section <enum-in-header>527</enum-in-header> organizations</header><paragraph id="H8210DE33206B4666920AEDBCF8D81B03"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">section 6033(g)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HE65752CCB731402CB1A0637B6123ECB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>This section</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as otherwise provided by this subsection, this section</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H282AA12F0D88449EA90457448E47B369"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>for the taxable year.</quote> and inserting <quote>for the taxable year in the same manner as to an organization exempt from taxation under section 501(a).</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C17A8C8908D46C9BAC362C27E9A552D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1886E7FBB0B1469EA9B966F1DBCD7B61"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting of names and addresses of contributors</header><paragraph id="HDE6C60E2A6B3441CB341049322005DD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">section 6033(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Except as provided in subsections (b)(5) and (g)(2)(B), such annual return shall not be required to include the names and addresses of contributors to the organization.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F8E3DA8DB7A4725AEBC6371657D0C81"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application to section 527 organizations</header><text>Paragraph (2) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">section 6033(g)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H52CE71E942C64469A42A9395776ADA27"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (A),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86B4D6DE1A1B42E58125BA642457F6CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (B) as subparagraph (C), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEE40407E0A24E8090079ED37BF3223A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H320C7D6932AD40838D397AD571B279B8"><subparagraph id="H5A7FF99960E946E6B2BE2E0506A9FF02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>containing the names and addresses of all substantial contributors, and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H09B2A3825B9B4584B3C7B61A74570735"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB433FBFEAA1542FD8790DB553AC35A3F"><enum>102.</enum><header>Limitation on taxpayer funded union official time for Internal Revenue Service employees</header><subsection id="HB937D480D8004F7ABB3F8B7AF6C81E16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 7131 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF48E4522E7E4B68A21D3312D9E60E8B"><subsection id="H716D80532C984665A654CD78FA662C65"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority provided under subsection (d) shall not apply with respect to the Internal Revenue Service, or an employee of the Internal Revenue Service, during the period each year beginning on February 12 and ending on April 15.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H79ADA3F574EA4B468444405FA7C1CC16"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 7131(d) of title 5, United States Code, is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>preceding</quote> and inserting <quote>other</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7834460E964147F49ECD3EBD9FBB620D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall apply to any collective bargaining agreement entered into after the date of enactment of this section. </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D0BA22430264EA180C2465193EF79DA"><enum>103.</enum><header>Protecting taxpayer privacy</header><subsection id="HBB5769DA515D46E89A391A958A783E05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increase of penalty for unauthorized disclosure of taxpayer information</header><paragraph id="H9A2D0DA6C4284CB295E9CC89D592AA8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7213">section 7213(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>$5,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$250,000</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE84B3193DB074590B3C5F3B7803D2695"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosures by tax return preparers</header><text>Subsection (a) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7216">section 7216</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>$1,000 ($100,000 in the case of a disclosure or use to which section 6713(b) applies)</quote> and inserting <quote>$250,000</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60A7920D34E54B2A85E1D859E145E366"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to disclosures made on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H922235E39E8C4D5FB69643FC7928E337"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Removal</header><paragraph id="H5B4EDC62BAE84A74AEF2052C2621A635"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 7701(c)(1)(A) of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>or in the case of an action involving a removal from the service for an alleged violation of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7213">section 7213(a)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986,</quote> after <quote>described in section 4303,</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16BAE6C1562C4064A5D09D3A43D62675"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The amendments made by paragraph (1) may not be construed to permit an officer or employee of the United States to submit an appeal to the Merit Systems Protection Board if that individual is dismissed from office or discharged from employment upon conviction for a violation of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7213">section 7213(a)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H2D11F7C2BD6147379F893437139346FE" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Restraints on IRS enforcement</header><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H8450CF978F7D445AAEA97102E913EAB0"><enum>201.</enum><header>Tax gap projection</header><subsection id="H45C3E8A31E0D4DC1AD762B90B6202DE0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, and no later than July 31 annually thereafter, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit to Congress a projection detailing the tax gap estimate for the most recent taxable year as is practicable using the most recently available data, and including identification and detailed descriptions of the data used for such projection and clear identification of the amount of the projected tax gap associated with nonfiling, underreporting, and underpayment (including identifying the amount subject to collection actions).</text></subsection><subsection id="H19C8970287854D079CC241FDD114D08F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, for purposes of reducing the burden on taxpayers subject to National Research Program audits, the Commissioner shall use artificial intelligence, including neural machine learning, and other available data analysis tools, including commercial analytic data providers, to calculate a projection described in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2ED4E87230DE435190B863317482AF06"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National research program audits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In calculating a projection described in subsection (a), the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall not undertake more National Research Program audits in any one fiscal year than are undertaken in fiscal year 2022.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3F034B479C3349E18AE2A4F4D4F8FA25"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Tax gap</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>tax gap</term> means the difference between tax liabilities owed to the United States under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and those liabilities actually collected by the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subsection></section><section id="H83B6C231FF3643E69947702520FFD480"><enum>202.</enum><header><enum-in-header>JCT</enum-in-header> Report</header><subsection id="H0FBDF2C1E1B8493EA77397BDE7A14728"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the submission of the first tax gap projection to Congress under section 201, and not later than 90 days after the submission of each successive submission, the Chief of Staff of the Joint Committee on Taxation shall submit to the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Finance of the Senate a report analyzing such projection, including—</text><paragraph id="HFEEC023EC2954C2E857BD981E040D8E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identification of methodologies used, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7244140EF607412E88DC530E2633032D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any statistical or methodological uncertainties, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEA434BAB0CE4E4099A845D5F81EB6AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the effect of outdated data, if any, on the accuracy of such projection, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8614862C1CD4CEEB53739C57BFC1C2D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such additional information as the Joint Committee on Taxation determines is useful for Congress to use to assess and analyze the tax gap projections provided by the Commissioner of Internal Revenue. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64CAF5DF88E343258677E0D1615F9BB4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Release of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of facilitating the report described in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury shall, in a timely manner, provide to the Joint Committee on Taxation such information as such committee requests.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC5D3E843833C4CDEA9FE17035983301D"><enum>203.</enum><header>Restriction on increased enforcement funds</header><subsection id="HCE7C71FC60BB4E6782D19D49446FA82C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no funds appropriated to the Department of the Treasury for audit and enforcement purposes in excess of the levels appropriated for such purposes in fiscal year 2022 may be expended for such purposes, including for salaries, expenses, and enforcement activities, until 180 days after the Internal Revenue Service publishes an updated tax gap projection pursuant to, and compliant with, section 201. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4557A0859E1F485284198E29424F26CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of subsection (a) shall not apply after the date which is one year after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC5A0CEBCC0BD48B08EE20AFB84E0B58E"><enum>204.</enum><header>Restriction on increased funding for other specified purposes</header><subsection id="HA9F46D208FCC43B6952269A48528CDD1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no funds appropriated to the Department of the Treasury in excess of the levels appropriated for specified purposes in fiscal year 2022 may be expended for specified purposes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H871313D321CA4C158232A3679A7952E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Specified purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the term <term>specified purposes</term> means—</text><paragraph id="HBBC36909E8C143E291D8BFFACFF01716"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the implementation of new information reporting requirements on flows of deposits and withdrawals in individual and small-business banking accounts and other financial accounts,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EE4FE1622EA41B9A794C9D230F60114"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the targeting of United States citizens in response to the exercise by such citizens of any legally protected or recognized right guaranteed under the First Amendment to the United States Constitution, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71450E894DDE4E248AA3F4767663554B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the targeting of a group for regulatory scrutiny based on the ideological beliefs of such group, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1069D250AF4E4A02B7122D30964DDBDF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the auditing of individual taxpayers with an adjusted gross income of less than $400,000, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14E0B7E33CE9401E8E89E5A05E85B61F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the hiring under an agreement pursuant to the Intragovernmental Personnel Act of 1970 (sections 3371 et seq. of title 5, United States Code) or any other authority of an authorized researcher who is not a full time Federal employee to access data subject to privacy protections afforded by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCD704956E5524911A9B71080F347DA0F"><enum>205.</enum><header>Efficient use of existing <enum-in-header>IRS</enum-in-header> resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of increasing enforcement actions in areas of high noncompliance and reducing the corporate audit no-change rate of the Internal Revenue Service to below 20 percent by 2024—</text><paragraph id="H0390819A0EEA46049F60B76FD0558CF4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary (or the Secretary’s delegate) shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section—</text><subparagraph id="H0F4259C43CD447739B2B7387497FB5B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">update the methodology that is used for the selection of corporate returns for audit, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42BE705B3CF54A70A6922D8380E6FA31"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reassign resources of the Internal Revenue Service such that the majority of high-income nonfilers are subject to enforcement actions, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H46C795B223594392BA2C8FB61E1A5BDE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Comptroller General of the United States shall, within one year after the date of the enactment of this section, issue a comprehensive report to Congress on information returns and data collected by the Internal Revenue Service that could be deployed for compliance activities but that are not currently used for such activities. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H934175A073A84F7BB172B0139F8BCF2D"><enum>206.</enum><header><enum-in-header>IRS</enum-in-header> Fellowship Program</header><subsection id="H447FD3B332F34411874580AB011ECB9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than September 30, 2024, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue (hereinafter known as the <quote>Commissioner</quote>) after consultation with the Chief Counsel of the Internal Revenue Service (hereinafter known as the <quote>Chief Counsel</quote>), shall establish within the Internal Revenue Service a fellowship program (hereinafter known as the <quote>program</quote>) to recruit private sector tax experts to join the Internal Revenue Service to create and participate in the audit task force established under subsection (e). </text></subsection><subsection id="HA33A267B8AC14172B794D774FA56B943"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Objective</header><text>The Commissioner, after consultation with the Chief Counsel, shall design the program in a manner such that the program—</text><paragraph id="H6A6655B539B343E8982C3A0877D55BE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>addresses such tax cases handled by the Internal Revenue Service as the Commissioner determines—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8DD73CB41C7A45F281F5E46289D9E199"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are the most complex, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE34242FCD2B8424AAFFD252A9B3D3E67"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include new and emerging issues, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4DFDDDA808C47FD8F53E45F98EF8038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recruits and retains outstanding and qualified tax experts. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H929A9F202CCF4E7685BD3A191286DA11"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advertisement of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner shall advertise the program in such a way as to attract mid-career tax professionals, including certified public accountants, tax attorneys, and such other tax professionals as the Commissioner determines are appropriately qualified to handle the most complex tax cases. </text></subsection><subsection id="H736E7402185A4C8EB214FB98AD08A99A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Structure</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H07685187140247A18E14A3E4D28F2B9C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The program shall be staffed by not fewer than 30 fellows at the discretion of the Commissioner based on needs of the Internal Revenue Service and the availability of qualified candidates. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D52FCDE741E4ACC9A641922E615C45D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Term of service</header><subparagraph id="H3896C02C5C264D86AE02790957D05799"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each fellow shall be hired for a 2-, 3-, or 4-year term of service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2417FE2D01240B1ADEF1BBAF7C647E5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extensions</header><clause commented="no" id="HC6A7E786184A40DC8D62B305424A6703"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A fellow may apply for, and the Commissioner may grant, a 1-year extension of the fellowship. </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H4463E777434A479F8DC7608DD84FB0F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>No limit on number of extensions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be no limit on the number of extensions under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0080C07F3CA5499690F8DDB1F06ADC69"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fellowship vacancies</header><text>The Commissioner, after consultation with the Chief Counsel, shall fill vacant fellowships—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6161127D35B14938906EEAEE051D015F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in such a manner as to ensure that the program is staffed with no fewer than 15 fellows, and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HAA2B57066731482FAEDF5994C9301703"><enum>(B)</enum><text>as soon as practicable after the vacancy arises.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H245A6436D0814973A9E0593CAC66F496"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Hiring authority</header><text>The Commissioner shall have authority to permanently hire a fellow at the end of the term of service for such fellow. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB3FDC5F276C84FAC9AC4DFAFBA414EEA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Task force</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date on which the first fellowship is awarded under this section, the Commissioner shall establish a task force within the Internal Revenue Service and the office of the Chief Counsel in both national and regional office placements that includes the fellows hired pursuant to subsection (d), the purpose of which is to—</text><paragraph id="H8DD445D90A8B4B9CBF802FB429102A82"><enum>(1)</enum><text>perform audit case selection,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B573451126E432AA57BEC61167BFFD3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>educate Internal Revenue Service employees on emerging issues, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7800F03AA8A404BA158E50E366C4AC2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>audit selected taxpayers,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CD67B38CEAD4D63A57A5A01F3F53097"><enum>(4)</enum><text>address offshore tax evasion and issues implicating the Foreign Account Tax Compliance Act, and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00EF7BE987E442BEAC5A31D21AF31F90"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify, mentor, and train junior employees from the Internal Revenue Service with respect to audits. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HF361C6CEDBCF49FC9D80FA3355998D57"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The task force established under subsection (e) may be composed of both—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H3FD6D8EBE2EC4BA48B6F4EF01C21D14A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>fellows, and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9FA21F62C2754200892E7F48E6DACA93"><enum>(2)</enum><text>permanent employees of the Internal Revenue Service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD9152C40B80F4A70866A583CB8E95A42"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Pay of fellows</header><paragraph id="H1D0BBC2E827A441BAF38489CB52FB153"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary’s delegate) shall determine, subject to the provisions of this subsection, the pay of fellows recruited under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9B9D2D61CD64E59A4137BCAAC119A01"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pay scale</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the pay of a fellow shall not be less than the minimum rate payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule and shall not exceed the amount of annual compensation (excluding expenses) specified in section 102 of title 3, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BFE8FD353104CEA8F22DEE9C75FCC9E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Administration of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may appoint a lead program officer to administer and advertise the program.</text></subsection><subsection id="H22D566EBF8324AFFB0A2700994ECB8D1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Annual review and report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the first fellowship is awarded under this section, and annually thereafter, the Commissioner shall submit to Congress a report containing—</text><paragraph id="H6A30274777964E149E976E993AF5B67A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of the effects of the program,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4D800AFBC084ECD9086942C1B13CE60"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of the return on investment of the program, including calculations of all costs incurred and all tax revenue and penalties collected due to the work of the task force, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89817FC78FC543E0AE55BBBD00D33D52"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the total number of fellows who apply each year, and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F41E3E4C2574C39892D7FBA8056F5A7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations for changes to the program, if any. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8BB337628764D20832E58BF9E1E7BB6"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Rules and regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner, with the approval of the Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary’s delegate, other than the Commissioner), shall promulgate such rules and regulations as may be necessary for the efficient administration of the program.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HF4AF7F5FA8DB4C70A7E960E5F113D91D" style="OLC"><enum>III</enum><header>Provisions to reduce improper tax payments</header><section id="H9EA9CFF4206945ADACE233D471552E25"><enum>301.</enum><header>Findings and purpose</header><subsection id="H961D3E6619DE4AEC9336C2066491C33B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds that when the Internal Revenue Service makes payments to taxpayers, the Internal Revenue Services must make every effort to confirm that the right recipient is receiving the right payment for the right reason at the right time.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9AA6D3F25542491BBA3F308C4649643E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this title is to—</text><paragraph id="HFE2FCE3556024DB6B09C22E72941E439"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reduce improper tax payments by the Internal Revenue Service—</text><subparagraph id="H7A20DACAE36242BABF8B743F4D375AE7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by intensifying efforts to eliminate payment error, waste, fraud, and abuse; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H411AE0DF2813492D912A2F042F9A5CB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by continuing to ensure that the Internal Revenue Service provides accessible taxpayer services; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4F55DD532C9487C9BAF52907A4E79A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>adopt a comprehensive set of policies, including—</text><subparagraph id="H0A6F62634E914096BC1960034A85A7AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transparency of significant improper tax payments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD0869D532B44803B1238F64394C263F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>accountability for reducing improper tax payments; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBE22B88918A45F48DF0C961A61D40F7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>protect taxpayer services. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H290EEC500B4042059420B4621D8995BC"><enum>302.</enum><header>Improper tax payment defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this title, the term <term>improper tax payment</term> means any credit or refund of an overpayment of a tax imposed under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that should not have been made or that was made in an incorrect amount. </text></section><section id="HC4B68305494A4C178A5FDB9B371563C5"><enum>303.</enum><header>Transparency</header><subsection id="H2A01E250D4CC4AEE987E1C9289560BCC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of the Treasury shall establish, in coordination with the Commissioner of Internal Revenue, annual targets for reducing improper tax payments made by the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA0E8B3F3C0C4C00B657B9CA14415CB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Published information</header><paragraph id="HA82DFD1F1B1246A8B7BAB3368BA4C8F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury shall publish on the internet information about improper tax payments made by the Internal Revenue Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FBAF74B3EE44EE090906C3670193B4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The information published under paragraph (1) shall include, subject to Federal privacy policies and to the extent permitted by law—</text><subparagraph id="H44345DBC49974D76B5BC6ECCEB54D483"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name of the accountable official designated under section 304(a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9BC7B40E75A42F09CDC21D6C13F1E41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rates and amounts as of the date of enactment of this section, and historical rates and amounts, of improper tax payments made by the Internal Revenue Service, including, if known and appropriate, the causes of the improper tax payments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE645E2B00280458BBEE883F401DB6908"><enum>(C)</enum><text>rates and amounts as of the date of enactment of this section, and historical rates and amounts, of the recovery of improper tax payments (estimated on the basis of applicable samples where appropriate); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB217D9C21FD48E58F6DEFC5F93CFD51"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the annual targets for reducing improper tax payments.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H7F340E10110C489FBDCF8377AAAE326A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Methodology</header><text>The methodology used for identifying and measuring improper tax payments under this section shall meet the requirement of section 3352(c)(1)(A) of title 31, United States Code. </text></subsection><subsection id="H839AF47952914642B134F62D5D41055F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Links</header><text>The Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall prominently display on the homepage of the website of the Internal Revenue Service a link to internet-based resources for addressing improper tax payments, including the information published under subsection (b)(1).</text></subsection></section><section id="HF7E7B296B3EC4F86A2B7516A1816B391"><enum>304.</enum><header>Accountability and coordination</header><subsection id="HF3B0A76E1DF144C592FE01638E23346C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Accountable officials</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall designate an official to be accountable for meeting the reduction targets under section 303(a) without unduly burdening taxpayer services.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC7BDE74DE1C8455C8974B621E82A772E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H72A20F12117B413CACACECC4C512405D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the official who is designated under subsection (a) shall provide the Director of the Office of Management and Budget and the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H8314120C78A64B3ABB7E3047B668056C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the methodology used for identifying and measuring improper tax payments under section 303(c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D829A418F5C42688259515CC200F511"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the plans for meeting the reduction targets under section 303(a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H810BB27642444531818329613B8996E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the plans and supporting analysis for ensuring that initiatives undertaken in accordance with this title do not unduly burden taxpayer services. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H873F84E99D3B40D99D42EE6FF8E9880D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Finance of the Senate and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H68A2344BA21343999E2DC7151A4E28BD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties of inspector general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which the annual report required under subsection (b) is submitted, the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration shall—</text><paragraph id="HC28E6473F7A94917825BC8FA75A7EE50"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assess the level of risk for improper tax payments by the Internal Revenue Service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8CC388934C944C2B9349291E2A42DDF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determine the extent of oversight warranted (in addition to oversight requirements under section 3353 of title 31, United States Code); and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02EE82B0B3B24DE9BA7C5FB5797F9D5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide the Commissioner of Internal Revenue with recommendations, if any, for modifying the methodology, improper tax payment reduction plans, or taxpayer services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52840C4663D44D3985229154DC6CAB43"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agency failure</header><paragraph id="H7E0151D336B1459FB4568A092B191F0F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Internal Revenue Service does not demonstrate an improvement in reducing improper tax payments, fails to develop a plan to meet reduction targets under subsection (b)(1)(B), or fails to implement the plans described in subsection (b)(1)(C) for not less than 2 consecutive years, the official designated under subsection (a) shall submit to the Commissioner of Internal Revenue, the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration, and the Chief Financial Officer of the Internal Revenue Service a report that— </text><subparagraph id="HD6CA89AEE39D40A891AE10F8A27EBF15"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describe the likely causes of the lack or improvement or failure; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H896DBBDAA2254E27BBAC4DBCB9D9CD41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>proposes a remedial plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5AD4F31CD3426482AE6600BF10F7A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Annually, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall, with respect to a remedial plan proposed under paragraph (1)(B)—</text><subparagraph id="H4B10A0BAB55D45A5B10D79437C1A8F63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the remedial plan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H72DDC3AC7CC34533B9F5552AF68E985A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in consultation with the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration and Chief Financial Officer of the Internal Revenue Service, forward the remedial plan and any additional comments and analysis to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB4A4A915EE9B45F2B092F244E82E51ED"><enum>305.</enum><header>Policy proposals</header><subsection id="H98012EA94D6C4C2CBD0B03FFBF4DCB4B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Commissioner of Internal Revenue and the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration, shall develop policy recommendations, including potential legislative proposals, designed to reduce improper tax payments, including improper tax payments caused by error, waste, fraud, and abuse, made by the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subsection><subsection id="H68D4B0297C6C439587FCD7981ECCB5F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recommendations developed under subsection (a) shall be included, as appropriate, in the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter. </text></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

