<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D8F2E50BAFB44B68B8BD2A5EC6BFAB8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3189 IH: Mental Health Workforce and Language Access Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3189</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To increase language access to behavioral health services at eligible health centers, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H294901CB4C854C0FBC3FC870B2414187" style="OLC">
<section id="H784D1AD060A742769C9ADC57B49FBBED" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mental Health Workforce and Language Access Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H478710CFC5A7408A9417A881A215730D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Demonstration program to increase language access at eligible health centers</header> <subsection id="HA2D6FE490707491D90FAE32CA61E96A3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a demonstration program consisting of awarding supplemental grants under section 330 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b</external-xref>) to eligible health centers to recruit, hire, employ, and supervise qualified behavioral health professionals who—</text>
<paragraph id="H7E00AEECC08241CD910336ECF8B7FD89"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are proficient in speaking and understanding both spoken English and at least one other spoken language, including any necessary specialized vocabulary, terminology, and phraseology;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A03959798D348AE817253751B7703FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are able to effectively, accurately, and impartially communicate directly with limited English proficient individuals in their primary language; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7423D89C6BC9494B975CC73C09CA69E4" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are, or will be, employed—</text> <subparagraph id="HB69B3DE4E3404CA2A75C4460441E44B6" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>directly by the eligible health center; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5467E236FDA64EC3940EF9D0045CC952" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through a contract between the eligible health center and the qualified behavioral health professional that provides for supervision of the professional by the health center in order to provide behavioral health services in another language.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA2C2C9204D3640908D5F575102F3DFDF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Preference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting grant recipients under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give preference to eligible health centers at which at least 10 percent of the patients are best served in a language other than English, as indicated by data in the Uniform Data System (or any successor database).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H24EA75ADF61F4B2DB5BAC835B553E34B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Marketing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible health center receiving a grant under this section shall use a portion of the grant funds to disseminate information about, and otherwise market, the behavioral health services supported through the grant.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFC0A58F4931645D2B4793B4633953A74"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="HE02D987777E640C3B56A1F5BB9C26D66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the first grants are awarded under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations and Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, the Committees on Appropriations and Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and other appropriate congressional committees, a report on the implementation of the program under this section. Such report shall include—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD6B2803584364D7E9013B399A8E2E317"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the languages spoken by the qualified behavioral health professionals recruited pursuant to a grant under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6517FD316378495F8BDDF1AB302B3257"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the eligible health center at which each such professional was placed;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBCDA1CAFB8DD48178B39CF37460D34F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how many eligible health centers received grants under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA80EED0EE8824DDABBDE95CF62325011"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis, conducted in consultation with the eligible health centers receiving grants under subsection (a), of the effectiveness of such grants at increasing language access to behavioral health services; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFFCE774D0B3C4AEDB0A6F2277644785E"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">best practices, developed in consultation with eligible health centers receiving grants under subsection (a), for the recruitment and retention of qualified behavioral health professionals at such health centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H707DA1B1F53142FF9A0A127A8CFDFF5C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of fiscal year 2026, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations and Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, the Committees on Appropriations and Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and other appropriate congressional committees, a final report on the implementation of the program under this section, including the information, analysis, and best practices described in subparagraphs (A) through (E) of paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H58BF6A53C910481996BE25B63CD3D550"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6E162D0859DC4B29B9407041CFE1C2EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible health center</term> means a health center (as defined in section 330 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b</external-xref>)) that is already receiving assistance pursuant to one or more grants under such section 330 at the time of the award to such health center of a supplemental grant under subsection (a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC2E62878956A4D53B77BACFA06CA70EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>qualified behavioral health professional</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H096566BB4DFA40559420E9196EAF6770"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a behavioral and mental health professional (as defined in section 331(a)(3)(E)(i) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254d">42 U.S.C. 254d(a)(3)(E)(i)</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2C5101C1A64246D794FCE1F5F2303817"><enum>(B)</enum><text>substance use disorder counselor;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5DAA2ED8F98C488E840700BA862E2ADC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an occupational therapist; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8171871ADB0D4242A398E428432CAA6F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an individual who—</text> <clause id="H1EF5EC4B5D134D24B579D5D09F591083"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has not yet been licensed or certified to serve as a professional listed in any of subparagraphs (A) through (C); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H28A295EF1BDE471FA5D705F79C838A44"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will serve at the eligible health center under the supervision of a licensed individual or certified professional so listed.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC3AD89FA6CA49A9B28233F2BC5E7538"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1FD5BF5ACBCD4F9580E6B530AF2BDB79"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header>
<paragraph id="H3518D354BF004272AF96B0AECD551096"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAB0DFC1450C4E049984009F071541B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts made available to carry out this section shall be in addition to amounts otherwise available to carry out section 330 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


