<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFD26B21C3F8C409AA3103A1CDD03ADBF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5216 IH: Connecticut River Watershed Partnership Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5216</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230815">August 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct restoration and protection efforts of the 5-State Connecticut River Watershed region, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9931F99650234E1CB192F377B075529B" style="OLC"><section id="H4CC02F64E0B04381BF713711E7D993D5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecticut River Watershed Partnership Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H607C676D3CCF4EADB1C765EDE12D104E" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H047694DEBFC841658F720EB41FDB948E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Environmental justice community</header><text>The term <term>environmental justice community</term> means a community with significant representation of communities of color, low-income communities, or Tribal and Indigenous communities, that experiences, or is at risk of experiencing, higher or more adverse human health or environmental effects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AB1421FEBBE4BF79B33121AB0D74598" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foundation</header><text>The term <term>Foundation</term> means the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D43A8C16D524C24A91871119F0A0011" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text>The term <term>grant program</term> means the voluntary Connecticut River Watershed Partnership grant program established under section 4(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3138284856B47E9A80514A48AA611F8" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>program</term> means the nonregulatory Connecticut River Watershed Partnership program established under section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC39561F3FA1A4D7C927DD225ACEC1F88" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Restoration and protection</header><text>The term <term>restoration and protection</term> means the conservation, stewardship, and enhancement of land and water for fish, wildlife, and people—</text><subparagraph id="H821B932DF9AB44BD84719C316CD9A6FB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to preserve and improve ecosystems and ecological processes on which fish, wildlife, and people depend; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BB28C1E5DAA4686B53E16DB0344B732" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for use and enjoyment by the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D6461B3D841445EAA802FFE7C1C940A" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD670CC94C1CB4A3E804D580F7092C084"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Tribes</header><text>The term <term>Tribes</term> means Native American groups that descend from peoples indigenous to the Watershed, without regard to whether the groups are—</text><subparagraph id="HD23F25915AD048D1A46C93BD6D99E634"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recognized by the Federal Government or a Watershed State; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CB8E8201810475EAA5B3295A3DB285F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>non-enfranchised.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AAE922A679345F2B0691A17BDC5B0F9" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Watershed</header><text>The term <term>Watershed</term> means the 5-State watershed region, including the Connecticut River and its tributaries and all of the land area in portions of the Watershed States whose surface water drains into the Connecticut River.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EE71353BCD3490E97FD5D5B3104731D" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Watershed State</header><text>The term <term>Watershed State</term> means each of the States of Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, and Vermont.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBDAEF18475F243DD8AC92E55AB22CA31"><enum>3.</enum><header>Connecticut River Watershed Partnership program</header><subsection id="H91A2644E9F95404B908B527C0F8EDBD6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a nonregulatory program, to be known as the <quote>Connecticut River Watershed Partnership program</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD213CBE07D5542B6BD36A50A943ED75E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall draw on existing and new approved plans for the Watershed, or portions of the Watershed, and work in consultation with applicable management entities, including representatives of the Friends of the Silvio O. Conte National Fish and Wildlife Refuge, the Connecticut River Joint Commissions, the Connecticut River Atlantic Salmon Commission and its successor organization the Connecticut River Migratory Fish Restoration Cooperative, the Federal Government, and other State and local governments, Tribal governments or organizations, and regional and nonprofit organizations, as appropriate, to identify, prioritize, and implement restoration and protection activities within the Watershed through the adoption of an inclusive Watershed-wide strategy and framework.</text></subsection><subsection id="H734504EDF9E940B9BF2C8883E4E1D33D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In establishing the program, the Secretary shall consult, as appropriate, with— </text><paragraph id="H0C03BD74D4C843EC93D6A7EC946534D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the heads of Federal agencies, including—</text><subparagraph id="HC070AEAA8DD54F86953943153B26D6DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H505220B33490458A992FA6856E1963BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DBFE7D580D943079C5A9693C0D5FAEB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Chief of the Natural Resources Conservation Service; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59C69A9EA38943E19D100E5ADEC2EB40"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Director of the National Park Service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7034DC5FA38B44EDB081E14E5215FA24"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Chief of Engineers of the Corps of Engineers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CC32485529D41F2B0A6FFA8400056D8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Secretary of Transportation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C807D1C8C514B309CCFF786403F6582"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0B8AC70038F4874B7029226A1EAEA8F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the head of any other applicable Federal agency, as determined by the Secretary;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B79A62EA2484F95B66159E27801D05C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Governors of the Watershed States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75BC2D01C6284E1087B61E4CA96D8395"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Tribal governments or organizations, including Tribes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8B34DE2D5114A11A08F2AAF2A66789A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Friends of the Silvio O. Conte National Fish and Wildlife Refuge;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H030CEEEA550E48D68797FFFAEAD378DE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Connecticut River Joint Commissions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H225502D5E392487597655A8B4A07BE54"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Connecticut River Atlantic Salmon Commission and its successor organization the Connecticut River Migratory Fish Restoration Cooperative; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18C75547FFD841D6B5FFB983796C19EC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>other public and quasi-public agencies and organizations with authority for the planning and implementation of conservation strategies in or affecting the Watershed; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF40CD43E1ADE44A098B1F95AEB282C19"><enum>(8)</enum><text>stakeholders from impacted environmental justice communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2807946132184A199DF05D2F496CC224" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the program are—</text><paragraph id="H76144FD856FC4306A9071BAF33929833"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to coordinate and collaborate on restoration and protection activities among Federal, Tribal, State, local, and regional entities and conservation partners throughout the Watershed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DA68B4F69FA4C9B83ACEED36B67D3E7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to carry out coordinated restoration and protection activities in, and provide technical assistance throughout, the Watershed— </text><subparagraph id="HF41A1C371EBD479494F71883E6D64165" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to restore, recover, and manage for sustainable fish, wildlife, and plant populations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC8004E0DC6F46788C59DEF60595BB79" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to sustain and enhance fish and wildlife habitat restoration, stewardship, and protection activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDE66E4B0BF74FD4BF59B60F96DE849F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to improve and maintain water quality to support fish, wildlife, and fish and wildlife habitat, including to improve opportunities for public access and recreation in the Watershed consistent with the ecological needs of fish and wildlife habitat;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6E97713739145E1AB6BFF24E4679B7F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to advance the use of nature-based solutions to maximize the resilience of communities, natural systems, and habitats under changing sea levels, storm risks, and watershed conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22D5C0243F114A538C94109778A018B4" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to support farmland conservation and food equity, including habitat protection, climate resilience, and carbon sequestration on working farms and forests;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FB2DBA93CFD4215B0B21BC830996ED8" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to engage the public, particularly environmental justice communities, through outreach, education, and community involvement to increase capacity and support for coordinated restoration and protection activities in the Watershed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE56137A2ECBC400992345BD7FB0E4EDC" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to identify, affirm, and promote the practice and awareness of traditional Tribal river and Watershed-related cultural practices and traditional ecological knowledge;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H904675267A5A48B181B2D2B44376CBE7" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>to improve access to open space and trails by enhancing trails in the Watershed and on-street active transportation, such as bike lanes, sidewalks, public transportation, and bike share;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97F3BA34AEF8422B91736A68779907B2" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to sustain and enhance water management for volume and flood damage mitigation improvements to benefit fish and wildlife habitat;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A7A4F1F8C7D4F1F9DC10612F69310F3" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>to support land and water conservation and management activities necessary to fulfill the Watershed-wide strategy adopted under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AA26350554242C7A66E9EDE743706E4" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text>to monitor environmental quality to assess progress towards the purposes of the program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F9CC066D5204167B8B36948E3318ED5" commented="no"><enum>(L)</enum><text>to facilitate strategic planning to maximize the resilience of natural systems and habitats under changing watershed conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H525C969BBAE04F9F8367B18366BFD8D4" commented="no"><enum>(M)</enum><text>to improve fish and wildlife habitats, including opportunities for personal recreation, hunting, fishing, and wildlife viewing along rivers, particularly in environmental justice communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H884E5DFE36944EB0A78EEC628FF831BD" commented="no"><enum>(N)</enum><text>to increase scientific capacity to support the planning, monitoring, and research activities necessary to carry out coordinated restoration and protection activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H685520E1469E4A4E8125946AB6A54DEF" commented="no"><enum>(O)</enum><text>to provide technical assistance to carry out restoration and protection activities in the Watershed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H914607066FEA4CF6B62C9FE42ED537E4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Connecticut River Watershed Partnership grant program</header><subsection id="HAD9399AB1EB04292BE289E03E100C41A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83601C090F434F91A787432819669F91"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a State, Tribal, or local government;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15C355F803724C1B9CA219A96B92DC7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA7C99AB1CF44A569D23E9B64D76C7E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F2E1A1D331D414390B0B46FBEC0EE0E"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a voluntary grant and technical assistance program, to be known as the <quote>Connecticut River Watershed Partnership grant program</quote>, to provide competitive matching grants to eligible entities to carry out restoration and protection activities for the Watershed.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC1848203B25F46C49A868B0C962BE9E3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the agencies, organizations, and other individuals and entities referred to in section 3(c), shall develop criteria for the grant program to ensure—</text><paragraph id="HADB1D911884745EA832EA02D0AA59C0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the equitable distribution of funds; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25EE2A187CDD43B89EB675C63C7EA45F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that projects funded under the grant program accomplish 1 or more of the purposes described in section 3(d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H757BD4455CA0426ABD31EAA5E31800ED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cost sharing</header><paragraph id="H3963B6A80E104503958344DE2AA87270"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal share</header><subparagraph id="H8D3466DD534F460EB6187D6D2458A349"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the Federal share of the cost of a project funded under the grant program shall not exceed 75 percent of the total cost of the project, as determined by the Secretary. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80E6085F58894B89B8ED040265A30493"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Environmental Justice communities</header><clause id="HD81409BF31544A67A8831D5AC3C72236"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), the Federal share of the cost of a project funded under the grant program that serves an environmental justice community shall be 90 percent of the total cost of the project, as determined by the Secretary.</text></clause><clause id="HB41BB2FD7E3A494498B9A05E85109E4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may increase the Federal share under clause (i) to 100 percent of the total cost of the project if the Secretary determines that the grant recipient is unable to pay, or would experience significant financial hardship if required to pay, the non-Federal share.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC8D79901FCB44ECBF3BFE6E4E754CDA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-Federal share</header><text>The non-Federal share of the cost of a project funded under the grant program may be provided in cash or in the form of an in-kind contribution of services, materials, or land value. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCF5BB6B83B794A4F894AED18E6FA7CFF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="HBA85F8535A4749608B96C611D8319E2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may enter into an agreement to manage the grant program with the Foundation or a similar organization that offers grant management services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA089B3DA7B043F4B9869F82FD10905E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>If the Secretary enters into an agreement under paragraph (1), the Foundation or similar organization selected shall— </text><subparagraph id="H3D6A18FDFBE54C3290F90F014C070AB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for each fiscal year in which the grant program is carried out, receive amounts made available to carry out this section for that fiscal year in an advance payment of the entire amounts on October 1 of that fiscal year, or as soon as practicable thereafter; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63B1A5F080744629878E8D0889AF7B9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>invest and reinvest those amounts for the benefit of the grant program; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C30DEC5D70A4900AA86BAEB69C65061"><enum>(C)</enum><text>otherwise administer the grant program to support partnerships between the public and private sectors in accordance with this Act. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C09540C545345C5B6025C8C44FA8132"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>If the Secretary enters into an agreement with the Foundation under paragraph (1), any amounts received by the Foundation under this section shall be subject to the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation Establishment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3701">16 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>), excluding section 10(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3709">16 U.S.C. 3709(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H639DACF305D6403AA88E351807746C6C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the implementation of this Act, including a description of each project that has received funding under the grant program in the preceding fiscal year.</text></section><section id="H2A858E9834FD4F83B7CFE7A6D7C77D86"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="HD51A71BCA50E4F1BBDA34675A899E8C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this Act such sums as are necessary for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE5478D1A7E3A482EBE424066159A27D5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use for grant program</header><text>Of the amounts made available to carry out this Act for each fiscal year, the Secretary shall use not less than 75 percent to carry out the grant program and to provide, or provide for, technical assistance under that grant program. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7A66CC7042494BCE8FCF451394510592"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Amounts made available to carry out this Act shall supplement, and not supplant, funding for other activities carried out by the Secretary in the Watershed.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

