<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB293E05D3B9D4E1EA3A0F79384EFB004" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6754 IH: School Violence Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6754</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the establishment of a comprehensive school-based violence prevention program to assist youth at highest risk for involvement in gun violence in local communities and schools, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H186746DA863F46AA8D5F9280F107E4B4" style="OLC"><section id="H057575DE993F422F9FD5090BBC0A40AF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>School Violence Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H856C2C94A7024C4E9F53EBA474B0BE18"><enum>2.</enum><header>Comprehensive school-based violence prevention program</header><subsection id="H422C58328B05411A9BCCE56708E6D782"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text>The second part G (relating to services provided through religious organizations) of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290kk">42 U.S.C. 290kk et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H63FA7CB99BE54D7197644614DA0FE7C7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating such part as part J; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1DDBF8840449AE8E23D6AA41084300"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 581 through 584 as sections 596 through 596C, respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A5182EAEA6347BBA05C8681DA8DA407"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>Section 581 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290hh">42 U.S.C. 290hh</external-xref>) (relating to children and violence) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H1CDFFDBF81D84515BDA5FBF11800F039" style="OLC"><section id="H6C29356AFCF142A796C219E58E3B5B60"><enum>581.</enum><header>Comprehensive school-based violence prevention program</header><subsection id="H892526D3FFC944B9AA5007D0C6F28535"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall award grants to eligible entities to establish or expand a comprehensive school-based violence prevention program to assist youth at highest risk for involvement in gun violence in local communities and schools (including schools funded by the Bureau of Indian Education).</text></subsection><subsection id="HAAFBBA4BE5F14AD7A4A5D3E9335EC9D6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Grants awarded under subsection (a), shall, as appropriate, be used for—</text><paragraph id="H0BF53F8250074BCA95428BCE69B97876"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the implementation of school-based violence prevention programs that—</text><subparagraph id="H54D62D0038E24BA1911EC5A880417149"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are primarily focused on providing services to students enrolled in kindergarten through 12th grade or youth younger than 19; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4C613BA581F489CAF58744F278D95C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use strategies that are evidence-based, culturally competent, trauma-informed, and linguistically and developmentally inclusive, and have demonstrated effectiveness at preventing or reducing violence among youth at highest risk for involvement in gun violence, including strategies that—</text><clause id="HAB6BA2D013D54F7FB8DCCBCF4EC58C88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>promote community engagement that supports healthy development, including emphasizing self-esteem and cultural or ethnic pride;</text></clause><clause id="HC73C2C98BBA34D129EC97B8664A85DD7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>promote healing from trauma and other adverse childhood experiences that increase a young person’s risk for involvement in gun violence;</text></clause><clause id="HF5419C1B26D84B848B47ECE40BEACD7B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>strengthen the interpersonal and emotional skills of youth, such as communication, problem-solving, empathy, and conflict management;</text></clause><clause id="H8E5A0BA1EC5D4EFBA033E473C60DCAB4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">connect youth to mental health professionals, counselors, mentors, community leaders, crisis intervention professionals, community violence interrupters, or educators trained in trauma-informed care and activities;</text></clause><clause id="H70AAB938293A442586E8E632AFE2908A"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">foster community engagement and safe community environments; or</text></clause><clause id="H60156DCD996B41F8A15A67E296408B5F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">lessen harms of escalating violence and prevent future risk of violence, including gun violence;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CE3C027F42942589F9BEB07285CC31A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technical assistance to local educational agencies and community-based nonprofit organizations with respect to the development of programs described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C4DD94EC1C84A0C8337494ED93109E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitating community partnerships among youth, families, schools, local businesses, and agencies with respect to such programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1DE4420DF054C42A8D4827426CCCD50"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing teacher, school leader, and other school personnel access to evidence-based trauma support services, social and emotional learning, and mental health services through professional development; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAA664CEB03540989FDB970041AA5D34"><enum>(5)</enum><text>collecting data in accordance with subsection (g).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5A67D33FF038473A89618996B7BC4CE3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under subsection (a), an entity shall be a partnership that includes—</text><paragraph id="H410C375299334FADB6A6026DDC0839A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a State educational agency, in coordination with 1 or more local educational agencies located in a municipality or other local government—</text><subparagraph id="H7EFC2632EE8E4F4895D38D44C4D1A2EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that, for not fewer than 2 of the 3 years preceding the grant application—</text><clause id="HA82E116400014B7FBE11463307367F3C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>experienced 35 or more homicides per year;</text></clause><clause id="H70358F7A2780412E8930E06C4C1FDE31" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>experienced 20 or more homicides per year and had a homicide rate that was not less than double the national average;</text></clause><clause id="H5AD5288696354BB58EA3445C59548101"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">had high rates of violent injury or injury recidivism among youth as determined by the State; or</text></clause><clause id="H60BC1750804D463E9D4456D25EE21B68"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">had a juvenile arrest rate for violent crime that was not less than double the national average; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A883ECD4EEB48DFBB57384720658003"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that demonstrates a unique and compelling need for additional resources to address youth gun violence; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE734519CDB1847B8AA8B7003B806E52E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 1 community-based nonprofit organization that serves the youth or families of the youth of the 1 or more local educational agencies referred to in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BD8FD25950F43489B9E9ED2D96E7B1E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Geographical distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that grants under subsection (a) are distributed equitably among the regions of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1989706CE5C54237A1198501B8309F11"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duration of awards</header><text>A grant under subsection (a) shall be for a period of 5 years, and may be renewed by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC69CF16690F547BC9150192C225ABB53"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation and measures of outcomes</header><paragraph id="HB6104E7C949E4B75B633D197C6A94A42"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="H11FF64646E7D41C88FF7A90E628E082F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Development of evaluation process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Education, shall develop a process for evaluating activities carried out through a grant under this section. Such process shall include—</text><clause id="HCFAADF4D808D412CA42AF4EBDF1160F9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the development of guidelines for the submission of program data by grantees;</text></clause><clause id="H282C55374B544B07AA190693819E66DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the development of measures of outcomes (in accordance with subparagraph (B)) to be applied by grantees in evaluating programs carried out through a grant under this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HC54D8EA653B14229B8CFC502206AF364"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the submission of regular reports by grantees concerning the impacts of programs carried out through a grant under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61017CC39D3D4F87BC0338DFE39B5223"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Measures of outcomes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall develop measures of outcomes to be applied by grantees under this section—</text><clause id="H56570115E4A647899B92BDF8DBF2070B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to evaluate the impacts of programs carried out through a grant under this section, including outcomes related to the students, families, and local educational systems supported under this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HB6DB81C935614CDBA4A5403CDB621544"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to disaggregate data on such outcomes by the subgroups of students listed in section 1111(c)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H377BAADC558D47AA9C7197B6E94272D9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Submission of data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of each of the second and last academic years covered by the period of a grant under this section, the grantee shall submit to the Secretary and the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences a report that—</text><clause id="H3A7E5A86EC184B0BAD14C8EA9A4C7E42"><enum>(i)</enum><text>includes data to evaluate the success of the program carried out by the grantee based on whether such program is achieving the purposes of the program; and</text></clause><clause id="H61C9073649124D5E879E0C5A15DFCB78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilizes the measures of outcomes developed under subparagraph (B), including high school graduation rates, employment rates, and rates of enrollment in postsecondary education and trade schools, in a reasonable manner to demonstrate the progress of the program in achieving such purposes.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46357FFBEB8D4AA4B9FFA788D412D150"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Evaluation by Secretary and the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based on the data submitted under subparagraph (C), the Secretary and the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences shall submit to Congress a report at least once every three years concerning the results and impacts of the programs carried out with assistance received under this section, including recommendations on how to conduct gun violence prevention activities with limited resources following a co-occurring emergency (such as a national public health emergency or a natural disaster).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2CC79C8E8A74BDDA8F9A1F726DF9230"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Independent researcher</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall contract with independent researchers, including researchers with expertise in violence prevention programs, to evaluate the performance and impacts of selected programs funded through grants under this section. Such evaluations shall be made publicly available on the internet website of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CFECE18C6314C0D811672F9E8D4140E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Information and education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall disseminate best practices to the public based on the findings resulting from programs funded through grants under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D4CF0099BD34DB6A36F696E1ADA15F1"><enum>(h)</enum><header>ESEA terms defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <term>local educational agency</term> and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given such terms, respectively, in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3D704DBED3C5422988F90FC69116A3C6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph id="H6007349356694E45AA8283C65A150954"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2031.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA683242711EA4C8EB37340F61F554793"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluation activities</header><subparagraph id="H3CCEE333556A4B8F983621FB3ADB77C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>By grantees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out evaluation activities under subsection (f)(1), an eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use not more than 20 percent of the total amount received through the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H949B946587F3407BA99F791D64400A71"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Independent researcher</header><text>To carry out subsection (f)(2) for a fiscal year, the Secretary may reserve not more than 5 percent of the funds made available to carry out this section for such fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H07F7961E167345AB9C3CD759184BD8B8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Part G of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290hh">42 U.S.C. 290hh et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (b), is further amended by striking the part designation and heading and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="H9A94759C97A04127AFAE4F3CFFDA3981" style="OLC"><part id="HA2CAD141F4B349149576E5BBAC02C70F"><enum>G</enum><header>Comprehensive school-based violence prevention program</header></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

