<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6BDE830BF1514CE0A3AD3AC9359D925C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4704 IH: Artificial Intelligence and Biosecurity Risk Assessment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4704</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response shall conduct risk assessments and implement strategic initiatives or activities to address threats to public health and national security due to technical advancements in artificial intelligence or other emerging technology fields.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2F0161E2A625412182EABA74AAEA91F1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0F2297EE63914A72B5DCAA60806600E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence and Biosecurity Risk Assessment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8EC649F98B284F1DBEE9501B3F5CD07D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Regular assessment of emerging risks</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2811 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300hh-10">42 U.S.C. 300hh–10</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD26E63E76EB4125A37618A33FC35C60">
<subsection id="HC3AE8AEEC4D84DC8A42778AD2DAD7B00"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Assessment of emerging risks</header><text>In carrying out subsection (b)(4)(I), the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response shall conduct risk assessments and implement strategic initiatives or activities to address whether technical advancements in artificial intelligence, such as open-source artificial intelligence models and large language models, can be used intentionally or unintentionally to develop novel pathogens, viruses, bioweapons, or chemical weapons. Such initiatives and activities may include—</text> <paragraph id="HCF606E71227B4E52AF35C4B264AE7565"><enum>(1)</enum><text>regularly monitoring and researching potential global biological catastrophic risks in which biological agents could lead to sudden, extraordinary loss of life and sustained damage to national governments, international relationships, economies, societal stability, or global security; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H76F0F034BD63470183491AB6F6CDD9E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>including in the National Health Security Strategy under section 2802 a summary of the risk assessment conducted under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

