<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4F706538FD9B45A1A7812AE52B9ACEB7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4004 IH: United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade First Agreement Implementation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4004</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000470">Mrs. Fischbach</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To approve and implement the Agreement between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States regarding Trade between the United States of America and Taiwan, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB80A63C75DBD442FBB32EB6732D2944F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0CBF4304580543C4A053E5175E15F09A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade First Agreement Implementation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBC6E49F987654B3EAA6F3C70F2E57CE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9C2A9E2F8DA247D385574473F4BA3638"><enum>(1)</enum><text>As a leading democracy, Taiwan is a key partner of the United States in the Indo-Pacific region.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2298B34D1744AEC8ACC55C842521137"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States and Taiwan share democratic values, deep commercial and economic ties, and strong people-to-people connections. Those links serve as the impetus for expanding engagement by the United States with Taiwan.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6612582E2CC4693A76F7866959340E3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Taiwan is the eighth-largest trading partner of the United States and the United States is the second-largest trading partner of Taiwan.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD145E92B7F224D01BD306F33D1E73269"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Since 2020, the United States and Taiwan, under the auspices of the American Institute in Taiwan (AIT) and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States (TECRO), have held an economic prosperity partnership dialogue to enhance economic and commercial ties between the United States and Taiwan, including with respect to supply chain security and resiliency, investment screening, health, science, and technology, and the digital economy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA97FC169F054CDAB24FA1E3E4247130"><enum>(5)</enum><text>On June 1, 2022, the United States and Taiwan launched the United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade to deepen our economic and trade relationship, advance mutual trade priorities based on shared values, promote innovation, and support inclusive economic growth for workers and businesses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3ECB75AD84064DD19D05A9787E65FEAE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On August 17, 2022, the United States and Taiwan announced the negotiating mandate for formal trade negotiations under the United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade and agreed to seek high-standard commitments.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8110864612784ACDB55CB38CB76EB9E5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Article I, section 8, clause 3 of the Constitution of the United States grants Congress authority over international trade. The President lacks the authority to enter into binding trade agreements absent approval from Congress.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65F52AD47D684E05AF5E86409841750A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Congressional approval of the United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade First Agreement will ensure that the agreement, and the trade relationship between the United States and Taiwan more broadly, will be durable. A durable trade agreement will foster sustained economic growth and give workers, consumers, businesses, farmers, ranchers, and other stakeholders assurance that commercial ties between the United States and Taiwan will be long-lasting and reliable.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H6F367E22089B427085151975C024AD03"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is—</text> <paragraph id="H9C28AD1222724B508F5ECD6DE9EB57D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to approve and implement the Agreement between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States regarding Trade between the United States of America and Taiwan, done on June 1, 2023;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H691FD21569854E7E9366EB694A35B3BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to strengthen and develop economic relations between the United States and Taiwan for our mutual benefit;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C9DF313A30A4DE8994A0406B532BB57"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to lay the foundation for further cooperation to expand and enhance the benefits of the Agreement; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBDB6E0DC216442DAA7BDB15B7B6C509E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to establish transparency and consultation requirements with respect to Further Agreements. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H1E18E05BFB4B429DAE5AEB5CBC0228B3"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD47857B5A2EB4FE79DE8BF035BFBDB6A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text>The term <term>Agreement</term> means the Agreement between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States regarding Trade between the United States of America and Taiwan approved by Congress under section 5. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F86F70911C64240B3DD80A1A15C6705"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H91D0D27E5F414C628014ED2D38CD7D90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Finance of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCA93DC712AC849CFB8122305055DDA2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB343D8A5C45C40A5A0CF365EBE362931"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Further Agreement</header><text>The term <term>Further Agreement</term> means—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC79CDEA94074E14B670388E2A54DB56"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any trade agreement, other than the Agreement approved by Congress under section 5, arising from or relating to the August 17, 2022, negotiating mandate relating to the United States-Taiwan Initiative on 21st-Century Trade; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8D26781E8D5D47AEB2868BAF6DFA2C84"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any nonministerial modification or nonministerial amendment to the Agreement. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39C3B6E32D2E48C0854425CF7E28217F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Negotiating text</header><text>The term <term>negotiating text</term> means any document that proposes the consideration, examination, or adoption of a particular element or language in an international instrument. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H362544B42DBC4889A87187B6DD7D606C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State law</header><text>The term <term>State law</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H4811FC8843A64118B54F4A338C0A88CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any law of a political subdivision of a State; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86837C5F2B1A45ABB4F599827C7034D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any State law regulating or taxing the business of insurance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB76D00437EC14EE6AC5F1F67E7B1BAA6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Trade Representative</header><text>The term <term>Trade Representative</term> means the United States Trade Representative.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HE06BC3AED2804ED49C963FDD1D86FBDA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Approval of agreement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress approves the Agreement between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States regarding Trade between the United States of America and Taiwan, done on June 1, 2023.</text></section> <section id="H019654A0ED30457B9F28CEECC95952C6"><enum>6.</enum><header>Entry into force of agreement</header> <subsection id="HF10A5DDBDB3B4B5F96F57E3EB4F2EBD0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Conditions for entry into force of agreement</header><text>The President may provide for the Agreement to enter into force not earlier than 30 days after the date on which the President submits to Congress a certification under section (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H728A7A57B6214283ABB5C778D8C393FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation and report</header><text>The President, not later than 30 days before submitting a certification under subsection (c), shall—</text> <paragraph id="H539C6090CDD645E9BF80C10A12B30ABB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consult with the appropriate congressional committees;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2202863F2584D83A9A91BBAB0BD9282"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text> <subparagraph id="HD77FE957C2074ED180D294E3B5FA83D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explains the basis of the determination of the President contained in that certification, including by providing specific reference to the measures the parties to the Agreement intend to use to comply with the obligations in the Agreement; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7DC03B86B0944DB6BDD1A7A49019BB63"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describes, including through the use of economic estimates and analyses, how entry into force of the Agreement will further trade relations between the United States and Taiwan and advance the interests of workers, consumers, businesses, farmers, ranchers, and other stakeholders in the United States; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDD1B3EFA14DF4BF4901D6696DFF4FFE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>answer in writing any questions that relate to potential compliance and implementation of the Agreement that are submitted by the appropriate congressional committees during the 15-day period beginning on the date of the submission of the report under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7E0A2A4DDC344444BE53CEB0F07D886F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>A certification under this subsection is a certification in writing that—</text> <paragraph id="H2F5D8DD1E448442DB9504C7A8F39CC97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>indicates the President has determined Taiwan has taken measures necessary to comply with the provisions of the Agreement that are to take effect not later than the date on which the Agreement enters into force; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE9251E2465D94E7EBD26F72819309302"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifies the anticipated date the President intends to exchange notes or take any other action to notify Taiwan that the United States has completed all procedures necessary to bring the Agreement into force.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H887E3765F38849C19EBD7CD7714E1277"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report on implementation</header> <paragraph id="H2BC76ECFA2954C27929212D0B2FF50EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after entry into force of the Agreement, the Trade Representative shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report providing an assessment of the implementation of the Agreement, including by identifying any provisions for which further progress is necessary to secure compliance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82E7DAC21144441B9A8340AFDC14B1CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted with any confidential business information clearly identified or contained in a separate annex.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9EA8018F1C394407A7954FC42ED920CA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 5 days after the report required by paragraph (1) is submitted to the appropriate congressional committees, the Trade Representative shall publish the report, with any confidential business information redacted, on a publicly available website of the Office of the United States Trade Representative.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H62DAB6D7158949318562319306382665"><enum>7.</enum><header>Transparency and consultation with respect to Further Agreements</header> 
<subsection id="H0A134D9E2DBD4C3EA1849B159A1CEAC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress on deepening relationship with Taiwan</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the United States should continue to deepen its relationship with Taiwan. Any Further Agreements should be high-standard, enforceable, and meaningful to both the United States and Taiwan, as well as subject to robust requirements on public transparency and congressional consultation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H92979C0A2312463A83092771DB7177BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Access to texts of further agreements</header><text>The Trade Representative shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees the following with respect to a Further Agreement:</text> 
<paragraph id="HA07BED937CEA4326A2EE99ED9B083C0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Negotiating text drafted by the United States prior to sharing the negotiating text with Taiwan or otherwise sharing the text outside the executive branch.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD348A338F13C4B70992D92823F01C5B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Negotiating text drafted by Taiwan not later than 3 days after receiving the text from Taiwan.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H965C5CDD9D5547329D4061B8DA693593"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any consolidated negotiating texts that the United States and Taiwan are considering, which shall include an attribution of the source of each provision contained in those texts to either the United States or Taiwan.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07661A263CC5431E80639A46DAA11C96"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The final text not later than 45 days before the Trade Representative makes the text public or otherwise shares the text outside the executive branch.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEF4F162DC4DF4C8F98D655E7273D1043"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review of texts</header> 
<paragraph id="HA434E5613BB347EAAA2C04981DA19E8A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>The Trade Representative shall schedule a briefing with the appropriate congressional committees to discuss the texts provided under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB76292B7C9544D83B5EEBF4CCBDACBAB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The appropriate congressional committees shall have not less than—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H782A2AA209254B9981C74844D0A2E8FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>2 business days prior to the briefing under paragraph (1) to review the texts provided under subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F8C09E0B1074C32A960397B83262006"><enum>(B)</enum><text>4 business days after the briefing to provide comments with respect to the texts before the Trade Representative transmits any such texts to Taiwan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE8A197B4ADFE432F97C4E1DC1577BE0F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional time to review United States negotiating text</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, during the period specified in paragraph (2)(B), 2 members who are not of the same political party and each of whom is the Chair or Ranking Member of 1 of the appropriate congressional committees jointly request additional time to review the negotiating text provided under subsection (b)(1), the Trade Representative shall not transmit the text to Taiwan for a period of 15 business days following the request, unless the request indicates less time is necessary or the Chair and Ranking Member issue a subsequent joint notification to the Trade Representative that they have concluded their review sooner.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA3EA0FAF0CE54DF0B0E56927B420127A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notification and briefing during negotiations</header><text>The Trade Representative shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1C38962BD7564571BD4D0DBBABB126D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than one business day after scheduling any negotiating round with respect to a Further Agreement, promptly notify the appropriate congressional committees and provide those committees with the dates and locations for the negotiating round;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EF7CBCECC9F415594759E7ACEEF36AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that any individual described in section 104(c)(2)(C) of the Bipartisan Congressional Trade Priorities and Accountability Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/4203">19 U.S.C. 4203(c)(2)(C)</external-xref>) that attends a negotiating round is accredited as a member of the United States delegation during any such negotiating round; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA93D2E4C15A44FA825B9A6A4480D032"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide daily briefings to the individuals described in paragraph (2) during any such negotiating round regarding the status of those negotiations, including any tentative agreement to accept any aspect of negotiating text.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB85AD4FBDFE54595B203B64B6CE16989"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Approval</header><text>A Further Agreement shall not take effect unless—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBF2C9A1203E041B29FECB3B87AF6DC55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President, at least 60 days before the day on which the President enters into the Further Agreement, publishes the text of the Further Agreement on a publicly available website of the Office of the United States Trade Representative; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E3698AC5F1B496389C733499D900775"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a bill is enacted into law expressly approving the Further Agreement and, if necessary, making any required changes to United States law.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H570DD8454C794E13B1C46808F3035FDE"><enum>8.</enum><header>Relationship of the agreement to United States and State law</header> 
<subsection id="H649F44476CE842D1A3DFF26F8CF772F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relationship of the agreement to United States law</header> 
<paragraph id="HE7F2A923407C4915B31D810847F056F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>United States law to prevail in conflict</header><text>No provision of the Agreement, nor the application of any such provision to any person or circumstance, which is inconsistent with any law of the United States, shall have effect.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB8DD1967DF81412F8724A90BD1D1B729"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Internal revenue code</header><text>The Agreement does not constitute a free trade agreement for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">section 30D(e)(1)(A)(i)(II)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4171FC75ECFE4C94BE6D8ECCFF59E429"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Unless specifically provided for in this Act, nothing in this Act shall be construed—</text> <subparagraph id="HB350B5FAA3604A03831BE04436600CBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to amend or modify any law of the United States; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C50070D1BA644B694FAF88CAE8B84D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to limit any authority conferred under any law of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4312EE7F21D6415BBDA7011D7403D33B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Relationship of the agreement to State law</header><text>No State law, or the application thereof, may be declared invalid as to any person or circumstance on the ground that the provision or application is inconsistent with the Agreement, except in an action brought by the United States for the purpose of declaring such law or application invalid.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA38998893740494DBE946061A94222EB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect of the agreement with respect to private remedies</header><text>No person other than the United States—</text> <paragraph id="HA18946774B304353A76CEA761E409C37"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall have any cause of action or defense under the Agreement or by virtue of congressional approval thereof; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0256BD34F38B4B65BC3398846E4F2CC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may challenge, in any action brought under any provision of law, any action or inaction by any department, agency, or other instrumentality of the United States, any State, or any political subdivision of a State, on the ground that such action or inaction is inconsistent with the Agreement. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

