<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2746501DA7E843EBB47F515F26B3ECC4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1266 IH: Building Credit Access for Veterans Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1266</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230228">February 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out a pilot program on using alternative credit scoring information for veterans and members of the Armed Forces, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5DBD96853FE54F59838EE43E922935E5" style="OLC"><section id="H36CAE6675DE94CE2AC9470C8DD56D59A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Credit Access for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8CE79FB7727245D68DD6E703003DC012"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs pilot program on use of alternative credit scoring information or credit scoring models</header><subsection id="HD80B3FFBCDE44B358E8083B6CC9A43F0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program required</header><paragraph id="H87CC342DDE2C4223A09C1A7AE2D31EFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall commence carrying out a pilot program that will assess the feasibility and advisability of—</text><subparagraph id="HD74D64FB06AB486B9835F7404C1F7B45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>using alternative credit scoring information or credit scoring models using alternative credit scoring methodology for an individual described in paragraph (2)— </text><clause id="H9704F7851E8A4268B4B370134C9547AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to improve the determination of creditworthiness of such an individual; and </text></clause><clause id="H27769E4BA7EB4DC4BC08AF393E806D8F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to increase the number of such individuals who are able to obtain a loan guaranteed or insured under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43E8B9F98F4D4D1BBDFA5B2F73E5D95B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in consultation with such entities as the Secretary considers appropriate, establishing criteria for acceptable commercially available credit scoring models to be used by lenders for the purpose of guaranteeing or insuring a loan under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H54F2A2EC448144FFB767CEFE8A9CA960"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individual described</header><text>An individual described in this paragraph is a veteran or a member of the Armed Forces who—</text><subparagraph id="HA929FD98683E4D209F28A029CEDB7C53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is eligible for a loan under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8620F22686CE405D80202F54B8859A45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has an insufficient credit history for a lender or the Secretary to determine the creditworthiness of the individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H54ACB248A43743968CA7B25C5537F9C0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alternative credit scoring information</header><text>Alternative credit scoring information described in paragraph (1)(A) may include proof of rent, utility, and insurance payment histories, and such other information as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69B6C3D03FA740359555B030CE42A785"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Voluntary participation</header><paragraph id="HAADA756005334F69AA92ACCDEEE2E200"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any participation in the pilot program is voluntary on an opt-in basis for a lender, a borrower, and an individual described in subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E15F41DB3B24D2882B2D66E8372B357"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice of participation</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), any lender who participates in the pilot program shall—</text><subparagraph id="HC02F6BD1AF274DF097ECC171270F3ED3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notify each individual described in subsection (a)(2) who, during the pilot program, applies for a loan under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, from such lender, of the lender’s participation in the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22555A5474E340E3B9C6BF1328D559C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offer such individual the opportunity to participate in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10AA32079C884325AB67AD8ABE1F4DE2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><subparagraph id="HA444AF9A66944993A2EFCEF9AF151847"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may establish a limitation on the number of individuals and lenders that may participate in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F711E0D207F472E837FD3B5461AFB69"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text>If the Secretary limits participation in the pilot program under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall, not later than 15 days after establishing such limitation, submit to Congress a report setting forth the reasons for establishing such limitation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0533C1C6C9F04129B3F9CFE0AB6B5C28"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Approval of credit scoring models</header><paragraph id="H798F216FE7E348E4B292554E9DE9B339"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A lender participating in the pilot program may not use a credit scoring model under subsection (a)(1)(A) until the Secretary has reviewed and approved such credit scoring model for purposes of the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H243CDAD074A640B2A25B66744F7013B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication of criteria</header><text>The Secretary shall publish in the Federal Register any criteria established under subsection (a)(1)(B) for acceptable commercially available credit scoring models that use alternative credit scoring information described in subsection (a)(1)(A) to be used for purposes of the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10698373DD004709B5BA676484D1890D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations; approval of certain models</header><text>In selecting credit scoring models to approve under this section, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB46A3FDE17F04460B022A056D7834A5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consider the criteria for credit score assessments under section 1254.7 of title 12, Code of Federal Regulations; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H735D2D25D3FD42CA807A06AED27673AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>approve any commercially available credit scoring model that has been approved pursuant to section 302(b)(7) of the Federal National Mortgage Association Charter Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1717">12 U.S.C. 1717(b)(7)</external-xref>) or section 305(d) of the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1454">12 U.S.C. 1454(d)</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6CDFD697916C48C880A8C3C308B09CA9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>To the extent practicable, the Secretary shall conduct outreach to lenders and individuals described in subsection (a)(2) to inform such persons of the pilot program.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6DDBF51C9E0341578E08C36BD0256820"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H1F4383E1E3B54C43838B89C950682D36"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F937CCA8C734FC9A37587C972025151"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA7ABCBA1DBFF4A9A801693D7E593B428"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The findings of the Secretary with respect to the feasibility and advisability of using alternative credit scoring information or credit scoring models using alternative credit scoring methodology for individuals described in subsection (a)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA22EEE91D80480EB36A72165FC92658"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the efforts of the Secretary to assess the feasibility and advisability of using alternative credit scoring information or credit scoring models as described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H374FF7AEE50445038D68945A8B2057C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To the extent practicable, the following:</text><clause id="H762A0BAE816F46878003092FC2D5E7F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The rate of participation in the pilot program.</text></clause><clause id="HD4FC4E70C8AF406887D6F5BB55806776"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An assessment of whether participants in the pilot program benefitted from such participation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5649B2D0607140F988EB5385AB5403BC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An assessment of the effect of the pilot program on the subsidy rate for loans guaranteed or insured by the Secretary under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AC8B8686F944446910E56517DEE26C6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC050D07D6652487A8484CF417D24AFD9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H1B0EA70865B6468FBC25815462B95411"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall complete the pilot program required by subsection (a)(1) not later than September 30, 2026.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H927921822F594679B37F44A13286431D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect on loans and applications</header><text>The termination of the pilot program under paragraph (1) shall not affect a loan guaranteed, or for which loan applications have been received by a participating lender, on or before the date of the completion of the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2F701B16B374A0C8D8357D7BCDD81A0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Insufficient credit history defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>insufficient credit history</term>, with respect to an individual described in subsection (a)(2), means that the individual does not have a credit record with one of the national credit reporting agencies or such credit record contains insufficient credit information to assess creditworthiness. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

