<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA50CB6229862493FB0C5C21A3F22FA7F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3499 IH: Direct Hire To Fight Fires</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3499</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to provide direct hire authority to appoint individuals to Federal wildland firefighting and firefighting support positions in the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE9FC37E71967432481367897F5D2D2D8" style="OLC"><section id="H19BC19FFC7C144869AB3EABC110C4693" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Direct Hire To Fight Fires</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA6DFA2121FD84498B4FE5AA176C1B9DE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HED3F9CA90B694E209DDA98BD4EC610C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Veterans are an appreciated and sought after population for positions within the Forest Service and in the positions contained in this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73E531E1717A41F8982F0008D2B022D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Veterans deserve expedited hiring and employment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA270E549A94541DAAAC9366DC4500017"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In fiscal year 2020, the use of the Fire Direct Hire Authority (<quote>DHA</quote>) was on average 31 days compared to non-use of the Fire DHA at 51 days and overall Forest Service (<quote>FS</quote>) hiring at 65 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB0ABDB0C123499EA5E816A7A64B81F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In fiscal year 2021, the use of the Fire DHA was on average 40 days compared to non-use of Fire DHA at 94 days and overall FS hiring at 73 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6B5F0B3B42B4B4F8994E85E52D63BD2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fiscal year 2022, the use of the Fire DHA was on average 58 days compared to non-use of Fire DHA at 96 days and overall FS hiring at 104 days. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25C58E789CA94D4AAEA19C70A56ED7C5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In fiscal year 2020, the number of days from authorization to employee entry on duty averaged 55 days with the use of the Fire DHA compared to non-use of the Fire DHA at 103 days and overall FS hiring at 92 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCC1A9AC72784993B2DBA9002BA5A7E4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In fiscal year 2021, the number of days from authorization to employee entry on duty averaged 57 days with the use of the Fire DHA compared to non-use of the Fire DHA at 105 days and overall FS hiring at 94 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32035030F3B142CE84DD59327E51A222"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fiscal year 2022, the number of days from authorization to employee entry on duty averaged 101 days with the use of the Fire DHA compared to non-use of the Fire DHA at 139 days and overall FS hiring at 146 days.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H858513840EB149E3A5DBCB37DD9F8A88"><enum>3.</enum><header>Direct hire authority to appoint individuals to Federal wildland firefighting and firefighting support positions in the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior</header><subsection id="HC65D1D6345DC475A8591D0D82EFBABF2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/96">Chapter 96</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H6A46331BB3D14005A1660124DFE9B821" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HEF00026BDA7A4182B12F714EDA4EDD03"><enum>9603.</enum><header>Direct hire authority to appoint individuals to Federal wildland firefighting and firefighting support positions in Forest Service and Department of the Interior </header><subsection id="HA47B4A4158A24CB085941D049B2D26A4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior may appoint, without regard to the provisions of sections 3309 through 3318 of title 5, United States Code (other than sections 3303 and 3328 of such chapter), and part 211 and part 337 of subpart A of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations, qualified candidates to any position described in subsection (b) in the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior, respectively.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD07159D846944FC84DFF0C08780148C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Positions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A position described in this subsection is any Federal wildland firefighting position, or any position in support of such firefighting position, within any of the following occupational series (or any successor series):</text><paragraph id="HD2CDA8B23C02492EB9147F8C92BBD0BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Forestry Technician Series, GS–0462.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B9B36617ED44BDC8A16E8F2E0507473"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Aircraft Operation Series, GS–2181.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H800D32FFCA564670A5D1C4D6EE9138E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Miscellaneous Administration and Program Series, GS–0301, that supports firefighting and is eligible for primary or secondary firefighter retirement coverage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01204E86F4F741689827DE67A21A94EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">General Natural Resources Management and Biological Sciences Series, GS–0401, that supports firefighting and is eligible for primary or secondary firefighter retirement coverage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F05F3E532714DF48B325BD18E57D05E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aviation Management Specialist Series, GS–2101.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEB9D0C45F4C4627BB7B4B164D86AEFA"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Engineering Equipment Operator, WG, WL, or WS–5716, that supports firefighting and is eligible for primary or secondary firefighter retirement coverage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7611519F78E43EB807237A754FD2D5B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Dispatching Series, GS–2151, that supports firefighting and is eligible for primary or secondary firefighter retirement coverage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F1171C40A2C4E1CBC9E129037AE2162"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Equipment Specialist, GS–1670.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A4E56E5E4CA48F193432D2CBE78E9C7"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any additional occupational series developed specifically for wildland firefighting.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD3330B05C7AD48189EBBA1341AEC237E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for such chapter is amended by adding after the item relating to section 9602 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HF90012E641874BA385C650FC283E5E52" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">9603. Direct hire authority to appoint individuals to Federal wildland firefighting and firefighting support positions in Forest Service and Department of the Interior.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HE69C866854E541F2AB47C7A440F8D1B4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Streamlining and transparency in Federal Wildland Firefighting Hiring At the Forest Service and the Department of the Interior</header><subsection id="H59E18282814C4573B9E7513AC0997729"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Streamlined hiring</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretaries, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, shall implement policies to recruit and retain wildland firefighters that—</text><paragraph id="H53FFAC9A01BC499B9136F369D0764B15"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reduce the amount of time required to hire wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9479E76993D4AFEBF8EC9FF3005BAD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>address and eliminate redundancies in the Federal hiring process for wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0169EA9DB0A4FEDBD7D54BC15B7DDFC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>streamline the process for hiring wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel who were employed by the agencies in prior years; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EED212430D844DF940BC757DC7FD9B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>reduce barriers for wildland firefighters transferring between agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB68E3988C3D14B4FB18EB6C0F2B0AE4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transparency</header><paragraph id="H654402BF2C6641B1AD1A577C4A4E1359"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Secretaries shall each submit a report to the relevant Congressional Committees that includes the information described in paragraph (2) no later than February 1st of each calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09B8D9854B9A475FBC65FD0483595887"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>As part of the report submitted under paragraph (1), the Secretaries shall include information regarding—</text><subparagraph id="HCFC6513A052448D592CE54BA0687EA4B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel the agency anticipates it will need for that calendar year, delineated by position;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H560D57964B344A30B42844329BD71AE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of hiring events the agency is planning to hold that calendar year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA06ED6929F5D446D8B6A48B540513E31"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel currently employed by the agency, delineated by position;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2A116F6C86A4973963F9EEC6A6C6791"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of wildland firefighting vacancies by State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B1E2F4A240247FAA84982C6069ABBCF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any barriers the agency is facing to meet the hiring goal outlined in subsection (a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48A0C0DBA2174B28AF7BB2AB1741434E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the implementation of the direct hiring authority provided in section 3 of this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E9E5C88C13C4C1EB0F3E5BB5AD3F433"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the implementation of the streamlined hiring policies developed under subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2266EBFFCC79448E9BF840F8A00B9CAA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>recommendations to Congress to further improve the recruitment and retention of wildland firefighters and wildland firefighting support personnel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5137A3AAB5F4459CA0E9D1B3D6091CCB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretaries shall each annually publish the report submitted under paragraph (1) on a publicly available website.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA40D2B30B74E40EAA4B3476857C170E1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><subparagraph id="H12987E246DF6472DAF99F0A7B30BF61B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> means—</text><clause id="HB9722617DC90484F9CDADDF05BABD29E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Forest Service, with respect to National Forest System lands; and</text></clause><clause id="HCC64D54E5AA146D8BD4C33979204FE4F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Department of the Interior, with respect to lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB940D834146545E1AB39C6369C6BC9E4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>relevant Congressional Committees</term> means—</text><clause id="H2D2974614C0E455A9C435A740526AC8B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committees on Agriculture and Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause><clause id="H051214A802E34F31B1E39EE6B8336F39"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committees on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry and Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA59A957057340F195692D9B43B335EB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <term>Secretaries</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

