<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB5DCA30C0DB7410DB8F08955204ADF26" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2374 IH: New Way Forward Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2374</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reform the process for enforcing the immigration laws of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H68D26519BEC64F03BA778F48DC686AD5" style="OLC"><section id="H4C9861F1E8914EFAA073A6E3091BFDE0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>New Way Forward Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><title id="HDCD63CA37B764A4E806032662FCF8B86"><enum>I</enum><header>End Mandatory Detention and Require Probable Cause for Arrest</header><section id="H503B98390B264EB8A09F453DB77217F4"><enum>101.</enum><header>Phase-out of private for-profit detention facilities and use of jails</header><subsection id="H6A801CBE0F7A47F193B918930EF46823"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Secure detention facilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security may not enter into, or extend, any contract with any public or private for-profit entity that owns or operates a detention facility for use of that facility to detain aliens in the custody of the Department of Homeland Security, and shall terminate any such contract not later than the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act. Beginning on the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, any facility at which aliens in the custody of the Department of Homeland Security are detained shall be owned and operated by the Department of Homeland Security.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9BDFE70F902B4D878316477F1D339B14"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Non-Secure detention programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security may not enter into, or extend, any contract with any public or private for-profit entity that owns or operates a program or facility that provides for non-residential detention-related activities for aliens who are subject to monitoring by the Department of Homeland Security, and shall terminate any such contract not later than the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act. Beginning on the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, any such program or facility shall be owned and operated by a nonprofit organization or by the Department of Homeland Security.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7ED32DFEAD9340729385E4E8F66A03F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication of plan</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall develop, and make publicly available, a plan and timeline for the implementation of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H183BC81767AD4D239EA6A9F52000AE42"><enum>102.</enum><header>Procedures for detaining aliens</header><subsection id="H5376CDED641D48928F1EE12F07F8F307"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Custody and bond determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 236 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H61BD6E3CFFBD4590862D2E216517096D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsections (a) through (c) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H638A1CDE3C3B4B1E9BE0ED65C7167EB0" style="OLC"><subsection id="H37171BF0D00E4C51981B91805B96BA87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Arrest, detention, and release</header><paragraph id="H6C142ECC487A408B84CCD475A7C572A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On a warrant issued by an immigration judge, or pursuant to section 287(a)(2), the Secretary of Homeland Security may arrest an alien and, in accordance with this section, may, pending a decision on whether the alien is to be removed from the United States—</text><subparagraph id="H59D32681373C44AFA5623FE28FC77AB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>detain the alien; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EA71865F1994CA696B385C3FF9B9353"><enum>(B)</enum><text>release the alien—</text><clause id="H96ECD955B7D34DE5B37FD4800F684F63"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on bond;</text></clause><clause id="H5AE0C0E00C314307BAC1864E3DD9E8B3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>subject to conditions; or</text></clause><clause id="H5852E8F021104980AA725B29E1827AC4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>on the alien’s own recognizance.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07E97FED08B748AFA04249D7586A7762"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall not apply to an unaccompanied alien child (as defined in section 462(g)(2) of the <short-title>Homeland Security Act of 2002</short-title> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/279">6 U.S.C. 279(g)(2)</external-xref>)). Such an alien shall be transferred to the custody of the Secretary of Health and Human Services pursuant to section 235(b)(3) of the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1232">8 U.S.C. 1232(b)(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF9B2B75278024ABABEA1F1CBF31B11D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Custody and bond determinations</header><paragraph id="H84B8C2E6D831495081577FA4689CF11B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 48 hours after taking an alien into custody, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall make an initial custody determination with regard to that alien, and provide that determination in writing to the alien. If the Secretary determines that the release without conditions of an alien will not reasonably assure the appearance of the alien as required or will endanger the safety of any other person or the community, the custody determination under this paragraph will impose the least restrictive conditions, as described in paragraph (4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BC446A466B64FAA8AD44688E3DF22F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an alien seeks to challenge the initial custody determination under paragraph (1), the alien shall be provided with the opportunity for a hearing before an immigration judge to determine whether the alien should be detained, which hearing shall occur not later than 72 hours after the initial custody determination, except that an immigration judge may grant a reasonable continuance upon the alien’s request for additional time to prepare for the hearing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03B7D8A3F48B4F6F8DCD7B3FCEC0314B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Presumption of release</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a hearing under this subsection, there shall be a rebuttable presumption that the alien should be released. The Government shall have the duty of rebutting this presumption by clear and convincing evidence based on credible and individualized information that establishes that the use of alternatives to detention will not reasonably assure the appearance of the alien at removal proceedings, or that the alien is a threat to another person or the community. The fact that an alien has a prior conviction or a criminal charge pending against the alien may not be the sole factor to justify the continued detention of the alien.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6BCF4B8C6734116BC610BE6BDE1AD1E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Least restrictive conditions required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an immigration judge determines pursuant to a hearing under this section that the release without conditions of an alien will not reasonably assure the appearance of the alien as required or will endanger the safety of any other person or the community, the immigration judge shall order the least restrictive conditions, or combination of conditions, that the judge determines will reasonably assure the appearance of the alien as required and the safety of any other person and the community, which may include secured or unsecured release on bond, or participation in a program described in subsection (i). Any conditions assigned to an alien pursuant to this paragraph shall be reviewed by the immigration judge on a monthly basis.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H98B3DE1B853648249325947C1B79461F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Bond determination</header><text>In the case that an immigration judge makes a determination to release an alien on bond under subsection (a)(1)(B)(i), the immigration judge shall consider, for purposes of setting the amount of the bond, the alien’s financial resources and ability to pay the bond without imposing financial hardship on the alien.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD89E2EF5F3247368299A6E1DC33BB1F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Special rule for vulnerable persons and primary caregivers</header><text>In a case in which an alien who is the subject of a custody determination under this subsection is a vulnerable person or a primary caregiver, the alien may not be detained unless the Government shows, in addition to the requirements under paragraph (3), that it is unreasonable or not practicable to place the individual in a community-based supervision program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F0B12FA0B0E4ADCAFBAFA7F8F3A5542"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>vulnerable person</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H27EF478F81DF4EDA9579A81550F2215F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is under 21 years of age or over 60 years of age;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H487F6DBA506644B58AA73780CBD8899E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is pregnant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15716E1953A94B9CB21F48ACD35080AF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identifies as lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, or intersex;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F7E889F59024F5280AA51FD4C40E067"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is victim or witness of a crime;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE50289A46DB348159B129C7BA22C48DC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>has filed a nonfrivolous civil rights claim in Federal or State court;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2500312E2F2A4B37905A5883207BDEE4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>has a serious mental or physical illness or disability;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D1113187AC144F5AF4DB774983E6C55"><enum>(G)</enum><text>has been determined by an asylum officer in an interview conducted under section 235(b)(1)(B) to have a credible fear of persecution or a reasonable fear of persecution under section 208.31 or 241.8(e) of title 8, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of the New Way Forward Act);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D83EC073D3E478C94B18297E8FD6752"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has limited English language proficiency and is not provided access to appropriate and meaningful language services in a timely fashion; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD750D89E26740C3A0BC4A7321D78C38"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has been determined by an immigration judge or the Secretary of Homeland Security to be experiencing severe trauma or to be a survivor of torture or gender-based violence, based on information obtained during intake, from the alien’s attorney or legal service provider, or through credible self-reporting.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5F4DF83885846BBBDBDB402BC6367A1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Subsequent determinations</header><text>An alien who is detained under this section shall be provided with a de novo custody determination hearing under this subsection every 60 days, as well as upon showing of a change in circumstances or good cause for a de novo custody determination hearing.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5030392A9174EF38ED1707C9324D30F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (e) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36D061E6E6144C08AAC0219F3E5111DC" style="OLC"><subsection id="HB128C077B7D846CCA01353DFF679B379"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Release upon an order granting relief from removal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an alien with respect to whom an immigration judge has entered an order terminating removal proceedings or an order providing for relief from removal, including an order granting asylum, or providing for withholding, deferral, or cancellation of removal, which order is pending appeal, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall immediately release the alien upon entry of the order, and may impose only reasonable conditions on the alien’s release from custody.</text></subsection><subsection id="H767AAA2550BF4EFF852F94C0DDF9707F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Community-Based case management program</header><paragraph id="H9376F10EEB4A424BAAEA46E8CDABCF3B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish, outside of the purview of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement, a community-based case management program that—</text><subparagraph id="HB7D6FD190AF942A2B467EA70A0FC90CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides alternatives to detaining aliens;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07651546740644A69442AED1FBEA0A77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offers a continuum of community-based support options and services, including—</text><clause id="H2278591496D047D79A091D74474514CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>case management; and</text></clause><clause id="H5123D20BFE43438B85E8C457CFF602D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access to—</text><subclause id="HEFEA3FC518D440AAA8E932F4F84064A3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>social services;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB66001F1DB60429194F5AA5BF7BC6687"><enum>(II)</enum><text>medical and mental health services;</text></subclause><subclause id="H527137CE4CF349AAACE178ED29AEB2C4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>housing;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5B209BB7C0D740AA871B041E98122369"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>transportation; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9845C65D84914B85867548E5EBAD06C8"><enum>(V)</enum><text>legal services; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE407AB1FEDF140849B557C67F8386225"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides services in the appropriate language.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC95CE929ACF4131B24B98FB10E58F0A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on electronic surveillance</header><text>The program under paragraph (1) may not include, as an alternative to detention, the provision of ankle monitors or other forms of electronic surveillance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6E52F8676C64367B1B10E44B092E1F2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Within 180 days, the Secretary shall undertake a study to examine best practices of government-funded case management and related services, including exploring the possibility of funding case management services out of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF45DAF1478749B8A270B95286B95185"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Contracts</header><subparagraph id="HA2AFD67A74DB451C90238C06845ADE84"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may enter into 1 or more contracts to operate the case management program described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59230DAC3782491E8221192D83C0643D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>In entering into a contract under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall give priority to direct contracts with qualified nongovernmental community-based organizations that have experience providing services to immigrant, refugee, and asylum-seeking populations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9125D2D830F54A7EADC386E1AAF06071"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Individualized determination required</header><subparagraph id="HABD755E86EF74F0E8FFA1A05ABDBD869"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In determining whether to order an alien to participate in a program under this subsection, the Secretary or the immigration judge, as appropriate, shall make an individualized determination to determine the appropriate level of supervision for the alien.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB45D5172C0CB46AF9396CF64164C863D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>Participation in a program under this subsection may not be ordered for an alien for whom it is determined that release on reasonable bond or recognizance will reasonably ensure the appearance of the alien as required and the safety of any other person and the community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E1BB36E72045988F5FB5391007CA67"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees for alternatives to detention</header><text>An alien who is required to participate in a specific alternatives to detention program or service may not be charged a fee for such participation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD425501FAD8743B0B5F43E828284AE0F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Case management review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the New Way Forward Act, the Secretary shall conduct a review of—</text><subparagraph id="HD504748ABD4545A29C0A759BFB181393"><enum>(A)</enum><text>best practices in federally funded case management programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0C966F0E9434026A03A7B94B4A0854D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the feasibility of transferring alternatives to detention case management programs out of the purview of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H765A0FC44E8646629E2BF51CC1C8BB39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Probable cause hearing</header><text>Section 287(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking the matter preceding paragraph (3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EFAE8FCA4A340D08908F50569E11515" style="traditional"><subsection id="HA96A1FFF88654A8FA590B5D815B283C5"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any officer or employee of the Department of Homeland Security authorized under regulations prescribed by the Secretary of Homeland Security shall have power without warrant—</text><paragraph id="HE03E071B14D94E8282595720C2B16ACE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to interrogate any alien or person believed to be an alien as to the person’s right to be or to remain in the United States, provided that such interrogation is not based on the person’s race, ethnicity, national origin, religion, sexual orientation, color, spoken language, or English language proficiency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FF9391285534256A8E9397A709DF3F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to arrest any alien who in the officer or employee’s presence or view is entering or attempting to enter the United States in violation of any law or regulation made in pursuance of law regulating the admission, exclusion, expulsion, or removal of aliens, or to arrest any alien in the United States, if—</text><subparagraph id="HED6C0DB863EB4AD2B4927D979A13B39F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the officer or employee has probable cause to believe that the alien so arrested is in the United States in violation of any such law or regulation and is likely to escape before a warrant can be obtained for his arrest;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF9BD076CE5643679659C28622DD8FF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the officer or employee has reason to believe that the person would knowingly and willfully fail to appear in immigration court in response to a properly served notice to appear; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35A794AC78FF4A4980931D6571B42805"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 48 hours after being taken into custody, the arrested alien is provided with a hearing before an immigration judge to determine whether there is probable cause as required by this section, including probable cause to believe that the person would have knowingly and willfully failed to appear as required under subparagraph (B), which burden to establish probable cause shall be on the Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H00EBC7D862CD47169FAC70B7576B7399"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mandatory detention repealed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HA1DBBE9E169449728B906AE424845056"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 235(b)(1)(B)(ii)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0BBCF27AF00F4F83BF8E5A7A2CDF9AA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shall</quote> and inserting <quote>may</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3FB97C40C4F0474F95E64E3C769DDF0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>pursuant to the custody review procedures set forth in section 236</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B86A55EC77F48CF8FC6FBF951534234"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking section 235(b)(1)(B)(iii)(IV);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2437E1FEC68748568095230592AA0948"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 235(b)(2)(A)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDB5C88A289AC4CEC9207F0E02AD60A5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shall</quote> and inserting <quote>may</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFD36CA4BB3C745DF876E49BB9A25C08D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>pursuant to the custody review procedures set forth in section 236</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC4CC6911ABD49E3ABCD389A6E590CBD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking section 236A;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BBDEBD5691943FBB68322B6787DFB2A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 238(a)(2), by striking <quote>pursuant to section 236(c)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4572845A58874C5F8D37E2517CDF1EB9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 506(a)(2)—</text><subparagraph id="H74A3DD0A39AB4DADB26C6C1FAB790021"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking the paragraph heading and inserting the following: <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Release hearing for aliens detained</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C0DF296A71E411598FAEB62C9917608"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HA252DBA7E8814821B2D77D5C1D95CCC9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>lawfully admitted for permanent residence</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HFD9E0F5617AB4187BE33FB522D13D621"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking clause (i); and</text></clause><clause id="H3AF42F8FA6C949D99F93044CC0DE63A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (ii) and (iii) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB11F3BC2DB874A2EAE3F01CB40ABF0E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Aliens ordered removed</header><text>Section 241(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H79A36F4872D748A285EFFD07F3A1E6E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>90 days</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>60 days</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5374D6A87894286A68964895253B8B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B3E87EA54BC4B44844C1D811148BB8C" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H12DE9852F5564853BB71A45C320B7C67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial custody redetermination hearing</header><subparagraph id="HA43FFF5BB013454AB1A1E38652652A37"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 72 hours after the entry of a final administrative order of removal, the alien ordered removed shall be provided with a custody redetermination hearing before an immigration judge.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA94D4D18B4884922BF5A1EE0BCD219AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Presumption of detention</header><text>For purposes of the hearing under subparagraph (A), the alien shall be detained during the removal period unless the alien can show, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the alien’s removal is not reasonably foreseeable and that the alien does not pose a risk to the safety of any individual or to the community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H99FF0E625B1C43B694C19D26E821ACC5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><subparagraph id="HBC73330357E740C2BDCC6A7284492C63"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">90-day</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">60-day</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3E2EC5E5E4C4EDFA06C7762F2F7F8C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>the alien, pending removal, shall be subject to supervision under</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>except as provided in paragraph (7), any alien who has been detained during the removal period shall be released from custody, pending removal, subject to individualized supervision requirements in accordance with</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1DCAD1BA289495191F60F8E113869D1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (6); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC95192AAAF1A4E3990A1D9B5637A8166"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (7) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF4CD4CEAF26544E7A3DB008BC2E0B404" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HF03D7CA01E474D53B19B33D5727E8DF9"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Subsequent custody redetermination hearings</header><subparagraph id="H88AC18A7C25844168610F2F329EB6744"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Government may request a subsequent redetermination hearing before an immigration judge seeking continued detention for an alien ordered to be detained pursuant to paragraph (2) who has not been removed within the removal period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02B764DB3FD94C9B89499C459EA0DB18"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Standard</header><text>An alien may only be detained after the removal period upon a showing by the Government that—</text><clause id="H4F9C8ABD61214D70926CDD435640368A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the alien’s removal is reasonably foreseeable; and</text></clause><clause id="HC9DE52AFCCFB49D985C4237774F106CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien poses a risk to the safety of an individual or the community, which may only be established based on credible and individualized information that establishes objective risk factors, and may not be established based only on the fact that the alien has been charged with or is suspected of a crime.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AC4958485194995B5C9EFCF12CF907A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Period of detention</header><text>An alien may not be detained pursuant to an order under this paragraph for longer than a 60-day period. The Government may seek subsequent redetermination hearings under this paragraph in order to continue detaining an alien beyond each such 60-day period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HAA633E85CCEA407FA5C4C7A46603D9DB"><enum>II</enum><header>Statute of Limitations</header><section id="H9DE86FF0C96949CDA599F5B04A3AC21E"><enum>201.</enum><header>Time for commencing removal proceedings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 239(d) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229">8 U.S.C. 1229(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B0771DD6E6241909DAE90B1641C6430" style="traditional"><paragraph id="H8EA13143767749A8AD094F6CBFE5AA6E" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9DAB642A8A424CBC858BDC277DDD79A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (2), any removal proceeding against an alien previously admitted to the United States for being within a class of deportable aliens described in section 237(a)(2), or within a class of inadmissible aliens described in section 212(a)(2), shall not be entertained unless commenced not later than the date that is five years after the date on which the alien became deportable or inadmissible.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BFAD8E4891D4A2FA14F5F65AFD8C7BA" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>This paragraph shall apply to any removal proceeding resulting in an order of removal before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>New Way Forward Act</short-title> as if in effect on the date on which the removal proceeding was commenced.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title id="HEADC2CF0C024457BA912F09B30ABF3AB"><enum>III</enum><header>Limit Criminal-System-to-Removal Pipeline</header><section id="H3F53A14CB72449548E6D2BFFC1FE9962"><enum>301.</enum><header>Criminal offenses and immigration laws</header><subsection commented="no" id="H5C870EE849ED4C94820A4E9B66AA0488"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Inadmissibility based on criminal and related grounds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 212(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H6D054583E0154BDDB6D4103766A57AEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A); and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1378D322A23549879F9F04ADB487173B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (I) as subparagraphs (A) through (H), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF65BBB31E5A944B3BFD00FD3D17B9A59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deportability based on criminal offenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 237(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4AF435715125483A897F9689B75790E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subparagraph id="H74EBBF0D12CD4B95B904DC132C4A3138"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking clauses (i) and (ii);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H432AA93041B142F9A22A7141614285BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (iii) through (vi) as clauses (i) through (iv), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B90350217804307A8F0288FF4022B11"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in clause (iv), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>Clauses (i), (ii), and (iii)</quote> and inserting <quote>Clauses (i) and (ii)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H364CEB0943804416B8AC0815EAF3C8B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H075680976F3746F5B3601CAE1D318858"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (C) through (F) as subparagraphs (B) through (E), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9A23D5AF17034E9F9EAF5AF4642C6C0D"><enum>302.</enum><header>Definitions</header><subsection id="H2603C2409CF849A28FB8DE6A10EF3263"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Aggravated felony</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 101(a)(43) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(43)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H491142F04BC34E698E55B7DAD41C2F1A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>means—</quote> and inserting <quote>means a felony, for which a term of imprisonment of not less than 5 years was imposed, that is—</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H813237E04ACB4BB8A0324FB57032F3B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>for which the term of imprisonment at least one year</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H952BDA847F054DC5883CB7E51A7F0F8D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>for which</quote> and all that follows through <quote>year</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE4152494CAE47E89A2F376409E94071"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>, for which a sentence of one year imprisonment or more may be imposed</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BC244FF6FBF41F5B60AB106765A4D9E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subparagraph (P)—</text><subparagraph id="HD9EA42D7CABE4C97A518C38591C7E646"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(i)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A4F3F4F33B84494AF5F1711F7FA6AE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and (ii) for which the term of imprisonment imposed (regardless of any suspension of such imprisonment) is at least 12 months</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8732F09B88A54C0D96F1CDBD58EB9122"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subparagraph (R), by striking <quote>for which the term of imprisonment is at least one year</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25576A4E39E24AEEBA1877DF59EBC7F0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in subparagraph (S), by striking <quote>, for which the term of imprisonment is at least one year</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD11204688F2540078068660C6412F4D8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>by striking the last sentence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF84E365D56B9467EBE4E7B4E3893DE37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conviction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 101(a)(48) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(48)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1AFCAB03F25943B4A0DC990F38F1B877"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>court</quote> and all that follows through <quote>to be imposed.</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>court. However, any such adjudication or judgment of guilt that has been dismissed, expunged, sealed, deferred, annulled, invalidated, withheld, or vacated by any court or entity shall not be considered a conviction for purposes of this Act. Any such adjudication or judgment of guilt where a court has issued a judicial recommendation against removal shall not be considered a conviction for purposes of this Act. Any disposition that is an order of probation without entry of judgment or any similar disposition, or where the President of the United States, the governor of a State or territory, or any body authorized by a state legislature or governor has issued a pardon, shall not be considered a conviction for purposes of this Act. Any such adjudication or judgment on direct appeal or within the time to file direct appeal shall not be considered a <quote>conviction</quote> for the purposes of this Act.</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70B816FDCE5D4A6DB6831FD5D00A05BE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subparagraph id="H9157E61B1C724D3EB8FD8EA21FEEEF7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>only</quote> after <quote>deemed to include</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63E0B2779F92429097EDCFC6C51AC251"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or confinement</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>ordered by a court of law. Any such reference shall not include any term of imprisonment or any sentence that has been subject to any suspension of imposition or execution in whole or in part, or that has been commuted or in any way modified or changed by the President of the United States, the governor of a State or territory, or any body authorized by a State legislature or governor to commute, modify, or in any way change a sentence.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA83EBE9645964AB3BB283CCE886233C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Particularly serious crime</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(b)(2)(B)(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(2)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8BB00E7903C34753A405922EEE1CBBD1" style="OLC"><clause id="HCA03D036E6764FDDACE2D2B353895401"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Conviction of aggravated felony</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of clause (ii) of subparagraph (A), section 241(b)(3)(B), or any other provision of this Act, only an alien who has been convicted of an aggravated felony for which a term of imprisonment of not less than five years was imposed shall be considered to have been convicted of a particularly serious crime.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H41B0A3D8D19D4128AD4B7702B4E29DDC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to—</text><paragraph id="HA47AF63566EF4A54A3F2A7F865BF34E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">admissions and conduct occurring before, on, or after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E2667FDC0B84C74B6216E5A9FEE8727"><enum>(2)</enum><text>convictions and sentences entered before, on, or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H6422BF879359451D9A2066912BA10982"><enum>IV</enum><header>Restore Judicial Discretion and End Removal Without Due Process</header><section id="HB873F9AF845746C09FF54920624094FA"><enum>401.</enum><header>Immigration procedural changes</header><subsection commented="no" id="H58DCDE967A1B469FA9396660F4092F9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Decision and burden of proof</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 240(c)(1)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229">8 U.S.C. 1229(c)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the period at the end the following: <quote>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an immigration judge may grant any relief or deferral from removal, including withholding of removal, to any individual who is otherwise eligible for such relief but for a prior criminal conviction, or the commission of or a finding of the commission of other conduct described in section 212(a)(2), 237(a)(2), or 237(a)(3), if the immigration judge finds such an exercise of discretion appropriate in pursuit of humanitarian purposes, to assure family unity, or when it is otherwise in the public interest.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H230A9DC9AC3544FF991CE34BB90F7470"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Removal of aliens who are not permanent residents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 238 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1228">8 U.S.C. 1228</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HFD416978C3B6485BB5925A50D04A55F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H077D30A9A3604E3EAB2CE375997BFBDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating the first subsection (c) as subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H364AD67EF8C94A9EB40DA3B90407D4B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reinstatement of removal orders against aliens illegally reentering</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 241(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7AAA8C840E6E4E2C807F77A68AD9AEBF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (5); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83C2834EA2E9433ABE61B58505383D03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (6) and (7) as paragraphs (5) and (6), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H074DC0BD02844770B753D8DA441D6671"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rules relating to continuous residence or physical presence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 240A(d) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229b">8 U.S.C. 1229b(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H88B6A8DE782D4E27B05B6C347D4CD74C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54C2665CF9C64BDABB969ED65C81498F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2) and (3) as paragraphs (1) and (2), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1CABBC855AE64ED7BE037B20DFEB6667"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Judicial review of orders of removal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 242 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1252">8 U.S.C. 1252</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (a)(2)(C).</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HC24397421CEB47E39504E1B1984B8029"><enum>V</enum><header>Prohibition against Performance of Immigration Officer Functions by State and Local Officers and Employees</header><section id="H0F1013E02C754EAD99FB327145F48A43"><enum>501.</enum><header>Local enforcement</header><subsection id="HC209D5916E5D46B6B03AA8E11F2AE150"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 287(g) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357(g)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2B1F4C439BC448AA0B68C5994D9C94B" style="OLC"><subsection id="H37CF7625BB7E43BDB78472AF3F266CBA"><enum>(g)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0DDF21A1468449F5BFBB9BABEDB43950"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The officers and employees of any State, or any political subdivision of a State, are prohibited from performing the function of an immigration officer in relation to the investigation, apprehension, transport, or detention of aliens in the United States or otherwise assist in the performance of such functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6D61320B6A94C1C8EA1592EEF3103B2" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Civil immigration warrants shall not be made available to the officers or employees of any State, or any political subdivision of a State, through the National Crime Information Center database or its incorporated criminal history databases. Federal, State, and local law enforcement officials are prohibited from entering into the National Crime Information Center database or its incorporated criminal history databases information that relates to an alien’s immigration status, the existence of a prior removal, deportation, or voluntary departure order entered against an alien, or any allegations of civil violations of the immigration laws. Any information described in this paragraph that is in the National Crime Information Center database shall be removed from such database not later than 90 days after the enactment of the <short-title>New Way Forward Act</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H8476C2B44BE94F409DEB9030E3227C19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibiting coordination for enforcement of immigration laws</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H7C8D42AB7DC042F48AD116914885B7D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header> Prohibiting State and local law enforcement arrest and detention of aliens</header><text>Section 439 of the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1252c">8 U.S.C. 1252c</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H212936C2631C4E03AB06D4CC21C462BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 434 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1644">8 U.S.C. 1644</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0499E70673094A3E8436F7A29D20E49F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Communication and enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 642 of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1373">8 U.S.C. 1373</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></subsection></section><section id="H55E4A21F48C240258B79551319F16D2D"><enum>502.</enum><header>National Crime Information Center</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 534(f) of title 28, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD5BB4D2FFD2649C3862B97BBC7523CD5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFE12D08AD3D4FF7A26BE6D80AD49547"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H857D528D18C047A7AA0F9EC9F6DC3004" style="USC"><paragraph id="HA842D3B3C33648B4951FC18050D98C46"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Civil immigration warrants shall not be made available to the officers or employees of any State, or any political subdivision of a State, through the National Crime Information Center database or its incorporated criminal history databases. Federal, State, and local law enforcement officials are prohibited from entering into the National Crime Information Center database or its incorporated criminal history databases information that relates to an alien’s immigration status, the existence of a prior removal, deportation, or voluntary departure order entered against an alien, or any allegations of civil violations of the immigration laws. Any information described in this paragraph that is in the National Crime Information Center database shall be removed from such database not later than 90 days after the enactment of the <short-title>New Way Forward Act</short-title>.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title><title id="HC439E2E0F0ED4352952718A4C639E1A2"><enum>VI</enum><header>Decriminalize Migration</header><section id="HDA1177373BDD4732BD25AF2D21E7D396"><enum>601.</enum><header>Repealing migration criminal laws</header><subsection id="HFAD3A80E1D3C499D87D9176E0BAEACE7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Criminal penalties for entry at improper time or place</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 275 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1325">8 U.S.C. 1325</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF47538D25014E54854C793EC26FC7F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criminal penalties for reentry</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 276 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1326">8 U.S.C. 1326</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H9F0198FD881B4994A218C294B34DA846"><enum>VII</enum><header>Right To Come Home</header><section commented="no" id="H31815A8F726C40BDA6B2190E4A27525F"><enum>701.</enum><header>Reconsidering and reopening immigration cases</header><subsection commented="no" id="H353E8D57ED244B8CA7A36BBCD81CD52F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Attorney General—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HE572EEADEAFB46C694F0A2245ED57FA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall grant a motion to reconsider or reopen proceedings pursuant to paragraph (6) or (7) of section 240(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a(c)</external-xref>) with respect to any alien who—</text><subparagraph id="HFECC18E12D634B868520041517BDB85E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on or after April 24, 1996—</text><clause id="H4061FFD13C684F06819AA90B4CA7AF4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>was ordered removed, deported, or excluded; or</text></clause><clause id="HCA08D65A5BB44624B3E8851F1B3C2778"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>departed the United States pursuant to a grant of voluntary departure under section 240B of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229c">8 U.S.C. 1229c</external-xref>) (regardless of whether or not the alien was ordered removed, deported, or excluded); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC57460AFF2AD4D79947A769AB9FE9C8E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstrates that the alien—</text><clause id="H577C58AF639A4BB5BD3C455108EAF571"><enum>(i)</enum><text>would not have been considered inadmissible, excludable, or deportable under the immigration laws (as defined in section 101(a)(17) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(17)</external-xref>)) if this Act, and the amendments made by this Act, had been in effect on the date on which such order was issued or the voluntary departure took place; or</text></clause><clause id="H2879B4CA5F894077934CDEBCD51D9ED3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">would have been eligible to apply for relief from removal, deportation, or exclusion under such laws if this Act, and the amendments made by this Act, had been in effect on the date on which such order was issued or the voluntary departure took place; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCD64ABE253704E57BA9F9B4F4A83EFC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall deem an alien who makes the demonstration under paragraph (1)(B) as not having been removed, deported, excluded, or departed, and as not having failed to depart under a voluntary departure order, for all purposes under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H96F68EA4D6C84263858A49763F771AF9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Previously filed application; previous motions To reopen or reconsider</header><text>The Attorney General may not reject or deny a motion to reconsider or reopen under subsection (a) because—</text><paragraph id="H55E74AB9CBF941D18C5A47D90A891C19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the alien did not include a copy of any previously filed application for relief; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H102CFBFA8A284A169DA4C384AFE5B0B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien had previously filed a motion to reopen or reconsider.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E7A954E5D6644619450AA0088C12E11"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The deadline described in paragraphs (6)(B) and (7)(C)(i) of section 240(c) of the Immigrations and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a(c)</external-xref>) shall not apply to a motion to reopen or reconsider under this section.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB433CE78554B40C79276CF7BBA12E218"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transportation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide transportation for aliens eligible for reopening or reconsideration of their proceedings under this section, at Government expense, to return to the United States for further immigration proceedings and shall admit or parole the alien into the United States.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H56BA19E03E51499186176B06D87D3CE1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Physical presence requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of applications filed subsequent to reopening under this section pursuant to section 240A of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229b">8 U.S.C. 1229b</external-xref>), or any other application for relief under the immigration laws (as defined in section 101(a)(17) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(17)</external-xref>)), removal, deportation, exclusion, or voluntary departure shall not be considered to toll any physical presence requirement.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE8FA7E3FB3BD4914A69F58E1AB84142C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>), any denial of a motion to reopen or reconsider submitted pursuant to this section is subject to de novo judicial review in a Federal district court having jurisdiction over the applicant’s residence or, in the case of an applicant who was removed from the United States, the last known residential address of the applicant in the United States.</text></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

