<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC5D7586378141AD929EC7592B3064B1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1724 IH: Securing Maritime Data from Communist China Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1724</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To counter the spread of the LOGINK logistics information platform, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H24F385EF56444EC3A99D43C56F22499B" style="OLC"><section id="H7B65E03373834136BE835C66AAB1D8B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Maritime Data from Communist China Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB3BA4DE67D6F4A8C8217827A3525406C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H45D2E16206A440FCAC455E419EF635E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H03F4985983E84BBF9422FFC5E5C7714B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Committee on Finance of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1703117CA9D43A49160A31F55F37649" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DCBFF8D9F5849DA8793048DBE71C9CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given the term in section 721(a) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4565">50 U.S.C. 4565(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8364B12187744D6A0BF6F129DCA785B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>LOGINK</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>LOGINK</term> means public, open, shared logistics information network known as the National Public Information Platform for Transportation &amp; Logistics by the Ministry of Transport of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H57AF5296CF62493593CFFBF42C45E4C9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Countering the spread of LOGINK</header><subsection id="H696860F4BD614633BA799DA3896DD9A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><paragraph id="H67B6851167534717BDFBDE2A8C2A6478"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Contracting prohibition</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1048ACC069D436BA337747E25D935D7"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The Department of Defense may not enter into or renew any contract with any entity that uses—</text><clause id="HE43927B3F31940C98CAE3171EAEA399F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>LOGINK;</text></clause><clause id="HE2BC941434494F50B74DE31B551EBDD5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any logistics platform controlled by, affiliated with, or subject to the jurisdiction of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></clause><clause id="H0FE381099A364FCC947BCDB3BC4325E7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any logistics platform that shares data with a system described in clause (i) or (ii).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9876C7653574D3798A351BC8F221EC6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>Subparagraph (A) applies with respect to any contract entered into or renewed on or after the date that is 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9990EA419ABA43BBB733DB7147F39209"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ports and critical infrastructure ban</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B5E62A4399B42C98D3914DAD2B62797"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Beginning on the date that is 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall—</text><clause id="HD579C2464BD94736A0E4192F759C322C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prohibit any entity which owns or operates a port in the United States from using or sharing data with a system described in clauses (i) and (ii) of paragraph (1)(A); and</text></clause><clause id="HADAB6FC1B9F846CA9D457A5B68CB3380"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prohibit any entity which owns or operates other critical infrastructure in the United States, as the President considers appropriate, from using or sharing data with a system described in such clauses.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H078CE4355EAF4F0EBD764EF7ECC8D1CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header><clause id="HAE19CA76F35A44E189503F5AD035EAA0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise the authorities provided to the President under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to the extent necessary to carry out this paragraph.</text></clause><clause id="H9BF60A3CA6B942B78B04F41BF77C4E79"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of a prohibition described in subparagraph (A) or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out that subparagraph shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H639FA4B7CF7447A79596BBA635DC7C49"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Negotiations with allies and partners</header><paragraph id="H84D6B58DE9124132822498DE4907264E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Negotiations required</header><text>The President shall enter into negotiations with United States allies and partners, including those described in paragraph (3), if the President determines that ports or other entities operating within the jurisdiction of such allies and partners are using an entity described in subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00910E29B4A34CFA94EB2B94536CBA6A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>As part of the negotiations described in paragraph (1), the President shall—</text><subparagraph id="H62526913C53E46E99C39D57DF56CE884"><enum>(A)</enum><text>urge governments to require entities within their jurisdiction to terminate use of LOGINK and other platforms described in subsection (a)(1)(A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF91E15104C6E4B9A83548299BCDA3D60"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe the threats posed by LOGINK and other platforms described in subsection (a)(1)(A) to United States military and strategic interests and the implications this threat may have for the presence of United States military forces in such ally or partner;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F22E4124E5D428D94563001E71F3608"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">urge governments to cooperate with the United States to counter attempts by the People's Republic of China at international standards-setting bodies to spread LOGINK and other platforms described in subsection (a)(1)(A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7667CBBF52E04538A5AC38CBAA7DDA9B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>attempt to establish through multilateral entities, bilateral or multilateral trade negotiations, military cooperation, and other relevant engagements or agreements a prohibition on the use of LOGINK and other platforms described in subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75542DF78174D078CE5BC3875147A46"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Allies and partners</header><text>The allies and partners with which the President shall conduct the negotiations described in this subsection include—</text><subparagraph id="H123BB746368342A29B3A6A608583ADA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Japan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECAE6781F27349B784984A1ADA680D6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Republic of Korea;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75EB3876EFB3457CB90DE53D640D0D1D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Philippines;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCED4DD9A5A64A83B33D32E8D88EDC11"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Australia; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC9EFE419F614E74BD3332A89F8A6B48"><enum>(E)</enum><text>North Atlantic Treaty Organization members; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D8D978E6ED44075A8DF046FAA09B432"><enum>(F)</enum><text>European Union members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1A1537DC930442B3B51E65BC19AEA085"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees describing—</text><paragraph id="H9E724EEFE2494575BEE7B4F561A334BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the efforts made by the United States Government thus far in the negotiations described in section 3(b), including whether the United States Government has raised such negotiations in multilateral trade and technology discussions and negotiations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCEEF08F809A4D9085232174F7FBB1AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the actions taken by the governments of allies and partners pursuant to the negotiation priorities described in section 3(b);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E604FF088BA4DDC81440E7E69592FE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the possible effects that the contracting prohibition under section 3(a)(1) and the port and other critical infrastructure prohibition under section 3(a)(2) may have on United States military operations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5784B69E966E402F92E9FF3DFD113942"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the possible effects that the port and other critical infrastructure prohibition under section 3(a)(2) may have on the commercial operations of United States ports and other critical infrastructure.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

