<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H694695B701EC4DB68D8616C571F208EB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 687 IH: United Nations Human Rights Council Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 687</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require certain actions relating to the United Nations Human Rights Council, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8E1106323B8F459B8BD45E46EF86CC04" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5B961A89524940348B99DFD6FB78EBDA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United Nations Human Rights Council Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD390407A9C94488487EBA3B1260C5F68"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on voluntary and assessed contributions to United Nations Commissions of Inquiries that relate to Israel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The United States may not make any voluntary or assessed contributions to United Nations Commissions of Inquiries that relate to Israel as mandated by the United Nations Human Rights Council.</text></section>
<section id="H79AE217ABB504164918EA902B333DC54"><enum>3.</enum><header>Actions relating to United Nations Human Rights Council</header>
<subsection id="H4699B0DC3BDD4D0997BF0949159BCACA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall take such actions as may be necessary to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States in the United Nations Human Rights Council and the United Nations General Assembly to seek to—</text> <paragraph id="H64B18ED7E5DC4202ADCBAB4707426F02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>eliminate Agenda Item 7 of the Human Rights Council;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9AAF27363EBE4AB191F293216E37A056"><enum>(2)</enum><text>eliminate secret-ballot elections for membership to the Human Rights Council; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5439F3D8E5FF479690C778F465A539CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>institute baseline criteria for membership in the Human Rights Council.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HCBF291C439444F16A5AED80BF22299DA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the implementation of the actions described in subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H958B3858C9FF466FAA91E271C452B702"><enum>4.</enum><header>Congressional briefing relating to United Nations Human Rights Council</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 30 days before the start of each session of the United Nations Human Rights Council, the Secretary of State shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on—</text>
<paragraph id="H9E92DC66D2204E3E94E10E86352D6D1D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the session agenda of the Human Rights Council; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D3FA7BC80F44457B361F4F6058A088A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reports, appointments of mandate holders of special procedures and expert mechanisms, and accreditation requests relating to the Human Rights Council. </text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H6AB871E584D2477CBD8F8B0DE83CF198"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees, on an annual basis, a report on—</text> <paragraph id="HC4679740BB874C4BAF231AC5202722B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>each vote related to Israel and Palestinian territories taken by the United Nations Human Rights Council in the preceding calendar year, indicating—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0A62F53DB36E4F678A4792FDA2C7C194"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the agenda item under which the vote was taken; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9FA0C937558944B99A11CAE06208E0F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how each member state of the Human Rights Council voted; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEDC363780E35463381CB803733DBD205"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount of bilateral United States foreign assistance, by account and program area, provided under the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 to each member state of the United Nations Human Rights Council in the preceding calendar year.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HE672156578134D4BBED3A3020D3E8EB2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<paragraph id="HADB9E9A1AE4543CCAC2C24B25BB8F18A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H712AC44F5F834A34BE0AE68F97933B46"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

