<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H98F66243230742749FD883F1EFA46357" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 165 IH: New Source Review Permitting Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 165</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend sections 111, 169, and 171 of the Clean Air Act to clarify when a physical change in, or change in the method of operation of, a stationary source constitutes a modification or construction, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDB348E45A0144AF9ACC358D0C211314E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2FA6D26C54054FD8823AE516A6B73F15" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>New Source Review Permitting Improvement Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HD075825D084B48A09D10C00D5C79CDD9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarification of definition of a modification: emission rate increases, pollution control, efficiency, safety, and reliability projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of section 111(a) of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7411">42 U.S.C. 7411(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9FC09AADCBC34C7985A756ED237E6E80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(A)</enum-in-header></header-in-text></quote> before <quote>The term</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAFA954F1F8624C8496AD7BBB38305C5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>. For purposes of the preceding sentence, a change increases the amount of any air pollutant emitted by such source only if the maximum hourly emission rate of an air pollutant that is achievable by such source after the change is higher than the maximum hourly emission rate of such air pollutant that was achievable by such source during any hour in the 10-year period immediately preceding the change</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H21D33D59F9774D6D96FCE05D449B27A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H84FFB618EAA7447B8AAD8C2597A0B5C8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HC161EFE7867B4286BD4553D4F7E3BB32" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subparagraph (A), the term <term>modification</term> does not include a change at a stationary source that is designed—</text> 
<clause id="H045318498ACB463DAD413829D5CF3E4C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to reduce the amount of any air pollutant emitted by the source per unit of production; or</text></clause> <clause id="H17C0A99A5FD44C6B98F07781BC6E4590"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to restore, maintain, or improve the reliability of operations at, or the safety of, the source,</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">except, with respect to either clause (i) or (ii), when the change would be a modification as defined in subparagraph (A) and the Administrator determines that the increase in the maximum achievable hourly emission rate of a pollutant from such change would cause an adverse effect on human health or the environment.</continuation-text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HED20F28A2A5E4C9DA3B81ADC5E8C5349"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification of definition of construction for prevention of significant deterioration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subparagraph (C) of section 169(2) of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7479">42 U.S.C. 7479(2)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2E8C90DD887C47E08D95740144E3E852" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H78EC129D08184A0A99DCA85195F8ADF7" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>construction</term>, when used in connection with a major emitting facility, includes a modification (as defined in section 111(a)) at such facility, except that for purposes of this subparagraph a modification does not include a change at a major emitting facility that does not result in a significant emissions increase, or a significant net emissions increase, in annual actual emissions at such facility.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HB18A3D5519144BE5B5B9F2D97389F14D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Clarification of definition of modifications and modified for nonattainment areas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of section 171 of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7501">42 U.S.C. 7501</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H46BF0029318743B497FE4D6A3E7EC103" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HAC715F2F370B4B5BB13E9A2521A237F5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>modifications</term> and <term>modified</term> mean a modification as defined in section 111(a)(4), except that such terms do not include a change at a major emitting facility that does not result in a significant emissions increase, or a significant net emissions increase, in annual actual emissions at such facility.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H0A2880B8CB764AC8A33AD63F21675CE9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Nothing in this Act or the amendments made by this Act shall be construed to treat any change as a modification for purposes of any provision of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7401">42 U.S.C. 7401 et seq.</external-xref>) if such change would not have been so treated as of the day before the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

