<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9E62F238692642B6B5002E1C5EE77F8E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 299 IH: Care Packages for Our Heroes Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 299</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 39, United States Code, to direct the United States Postal Service to establish rates of postage for packages shipped by priority mail from the United States to a foreign Army Post Office, Fleet Post Office, or Diplomatic Post Office, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC45F37BB3C264D5199D2AA7CFAACA5BB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H26A52D07F693492FB774A5A4C5028BAD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Care Packages for Our Heroes Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3621676F74F242209478ACD1C5E05F06"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of rates of postage for packages shipped by priority mail from the United States to a foreign Army Post Office, Fleet Post Office, or Diplomatic Post Office</header> <subsection id="H6010D50063194B57BBD4146D5B74BBBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3632 of title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98A819A6E358499FBE94F02C0756C269" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H2F7FAB8879FC450D9122971AADC67140"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (a), not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Postal Service shall establish rates of postage for packages shipped by priority mail from the United States to a foreign Army Post Office, Fleet Post Office, or Diplomatic Post Office address whereby such packages may not be charged a zoned rate greater than the zone 2 rate (as that term is defined in section 608.9 of the Domestic Mail Manual, or any successor manual).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HFFBD9F777AD647A5A15A7EFD37A95DE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2401 of title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HC01E9693D1C04B0896E59484C3FBB2CF" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HF397742753D54E0984EE40A6265CA6A1"><enum>(h)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As reimbursement to the Postal Service for the costs of carrying out subsection (d) of section 3632, there are authorized to be appropriated to the Postal Service for any fiscal year an amount equal to the revenue difference between the estimated revenue the Postal Service would have received during such fiscal year if such subsection had not been enacted and the estimated revenue the Postal Service would receive during such fiscal year as a result of carrying out such subsection.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

