<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1165DB895C384C7791D9994D034EC602" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" star-print="first-star-print"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3545 IH: Ritchie Boys Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3545</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to the military intelligence professionals at Camp Ritchie, commonly known as the <quote>Ritchie Boys</quote>, in recognition of their groundbreaking contributions to the field of human intelligence and their outstanding service during World War II.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H29F0B03A83484ED9BD6C22FB4472D03F" style="OLC"><section id="HD0FD0E121B624D54B9E4F78D3CC875A7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ritchie Boys Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H821D76A66AFA4CAF996131B552D38B90"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB0145CF05BD44CB09924F11EF2C674B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Ritchie Boys were a group of approximately 15,200 servicemembers who trained in United States Army Intelligence methods at Camp Ritchie, Maryland, during World War II.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84F95A7DAE9C49EBA2A3B5EA57FD2704"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Most of the men and women assigned to Camp Ritchie possessed critical language skills in German, Polish, Italian, French, and other languages that became an asset to allied forces during the war.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B5CFC7F3C4F48E2B6F1AAF9C1C07DE7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Approximately 14 percent of the Ritchie Boys were Jewish refugees from Germany and Austria who had detailed knowledge of German cultural attitudes and communication.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H588DB1E4E9744AF1AB059534F5DD91B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Ritchie Boys were trained in methods of human intelligence, including groundbreaking techniques in interrogation, counterintelligence, and psychological warfare that leveraged cultural knowledge as a tool for building rapport with prisoners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC871D3D7B5FC4182B7204AC2C543A4C0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Consequently, the Ritchie Boys were able to gather vital intelligence regarding the hierarchy, strategies, motivations, and attitudes of the German military.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A00A5B9787D475289FBE89D0A9736AD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Ritchie Boys who completed training at Camp Ritchie went on to serve in units on the front lines in Europe, conducting human intelligence operations and analyzing German military plans to provide strategic intelligence to commanders in the field.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36A29C16EA6A449FA7D03970F25EE395"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Ritchie Boys also conducted counterintelligence operations aimed at demoralizing the enemy and convincing German soldiers to abandon their units.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81045311497743B4BF34BBD7BAB154E0"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the war, many of the Ritchie Boys helped shape American culture and society through their continued work in the intelligence community as well as governance, academia, and other fields.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66EDFF18DBFC49FD8067A1F8E74C6614"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A United States Army report found that approximately 60 percent of the actionable intelligence gathered in Europe during the war came from the Ritchie Boys.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H1776C99ED5B7431FB8AABF7714BF137E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="HEEF5499D9182471A996C3D19A3EC46E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Award authorized</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the award, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design to the military intelligence professionals at Camp Ritchie, commonly known as the <quote>Ritchie Boys</quote>, in recognition of their groundbreaking contributions to the field of human intelligence and their outstanding service during World War II.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA81B7265E6CC46BFA6610E1FBACBA89E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury shall strike the gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0824CA822F004995A38C734AA049F888"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian Institution</header><paragraph id="H195DCD05D193439185BD49F7471F0411"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Following the award of the gold medal in honor of the military intelligence professionals, the <quote>Ritchie Boys</quote>, the gold medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where it shall be available for display as appropriate and made available for research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2478BC1BF5BA4D00ADAB9162BDAC6809"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Smithsonian Institution should make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available for display elsewhere, particularly at other locations associated with the Ritchie Boys.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H50D99993B440423E9019F8137B51A62A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck under section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the costs of the bronze medals, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section><section id="H85AFB817BC574C3E819CC5ADE6C32E44"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The gold medal struck pursuant to this Act is a national medal for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></section><section id="H4F539D91507748169380075B32D1C554"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="H24F09A29C91C474DBA83102BEF48CF00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H332A0EBE03574702B3DBA3F72E20ACC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

