<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4C776B6AB93043368054BCF76329AB17" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5468 IH: Children’s Savings Accounts Offer Parents Plenty Of Reasons To Understand and Invest in Tuition Yearly Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5468</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Social Security Act, the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008, and the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981 to require that the value of children&#8217;s savings accounts be disregarded for the purpose of determining eligibility to receive certain benefits under such Acts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA35805EFA9474B0AB53FED4BE1C8008B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H920AD6700ECF4AA092FF506040FB76D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Children’s Savings Accounts Offer Parents Plenty Of Reasons To Understand and Invest in Tuition Yearly Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CSA OPPORTUNITY Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1E4EA84438D143C9AB742CCCD2D093C9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H564EB857B4E847EC9E98ABBADE572A5C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Children’s savings account program</header><text>The term <term>children’s savings account program</term> refers to a program created or organized by a State, local, or Federal Government, a 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization, a school district, or a college or university for the purpose of creating children’s savings accounts.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2DD1B12920AC496CA105ECFDC3F3E321"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Children’s savings account</header><text>The term <term>children’s savings account</term> means a savings or investment account or trust created as part of a children’s savings account program exclusively for the purpose of paying the qualified expenses of only individuals, who, when the account is created, have not attained 18 years of age, provided that it has the following requirements:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF95D980CE09949D38FD0D013CF61F823"><enum>(A)</enum><text>If a savings or investment account is created—</text> <clause id="H44DBC95FEB894F9C9BCBBD270B8BE65E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the account is held in a federally insured financial institution, or a State-insured financial institution if a federally insured financial institution is not available, or in an investment account by a custodian or third-party owner on behalf of the individuals, if the custodian or third-party owner is a State, local, or Federal Government, a 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization, a school district, or a college or university,</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBD6B8B3E9BE944F4A2D9BD18A9622D6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the assets of the account will not be commingled with other property except in a common children’s savings account, trust fund, or other common investment fund, and</text></clause> <clause id="HD483A9CA28C44A7EB93EDEC3B4B78441"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any amount in the account that is attributable to a seed deposit, matched deposit, or other incentive provided by the children’s savings account program may be paid or distributed from the account only for the purpose of paying qualified expenses of the individual.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8D9CD413BCE546E79E9E80FAA24844E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If a trust is created or organized, the written governing instrument creating the trust contains the following requirements:</text> <clause id="H17D3E6F43D5940B29BC1CE1B729E66EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The trust is created on behalf of the individuals, and the trustee is a State, local, or Federal Government, a 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization, a school district, or a college or university.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6E7B2E674C5C435AB1DD0A1A9F5E0D12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The assets of the trust will be invested in accordance with the direction of the trustee.</text></clause> <clause id="H171EAC31345E41668984C9FF1A286E05"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The assets of the trust will not be commingled with other property except in a common trust fund or common investment fund.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H28F06446AC544ED7945C74BCCA487F74"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Any amount in the trust that is attributable to a seed deposit, matched deposit, or other children’s savings account program incentive may be paid or distributed from the trust only for the purpose of paying qualified expenses of the individual.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07CED07805F6439C8046D90F632F4E14"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified expenses</header><text>The term <term>qualified expenses</term> means, with respect to an individual, expenses that are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H73F72D2EA7FC413699CCF2DC579168D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>incurred after the individual receives a secondary school diploma or its recognized equivalent, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2319AA2BCAC44E098D502245440A3D08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for—</text> 
<clause id="HBE93A7152E5442D8BE803C67A4E26F46"><enum>(i)</enum><text>postsecondary educational expenses (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529">section 529</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) of the individual,</text></clause> <clause id="H9EE65537026A455492BB4A57B73FB462"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the purchase of a first home by the individual, or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF86751490F3C4E6CA91C6166E234E6D2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the capitalization of a business owned by the individual.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <title id="H6B2BB2ADAD634E92BD072140A836D198"><enum>I</enum><header>Amendments to the Social Security Act</header> <section id="H0C9CEAA7CEB449B5A4492CC040EC95E7" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>101.</enum><header>Interest in, and distribution from children’s savings accounts required to be disregarded under the TANF program</header> <subsection id="H2A8FCC36C6C74353AB29098566A92DDF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 408(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FDE027D3B7F4E369258710BE9C324E7"> 
<paragraph id="HB8CB347898CF47D8A4E5710953B62941"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Requirement to disregard value of children’s savings accounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State to which a grant is made under section 403 shall disregard the value of funds in any children’s savings account (as defined in section 2 of the CSA OPPORTUNITY Act), including accrued interest or other earnings thereon, in determining the eligibility of, and the amount or type of assistance to be provided to an individual or family under the State program funded under this part.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H2B9271BB21D24C71906A0F8AF4ED564B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalty for noncompliance</header> <paragraph id="HD4ECC7B228B24CDDBAFD7A6B4D217B60"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 409(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0DAA8921D432419BB3FEE03C68EFD6F9"> 
<paragraph id="HCD3195D35DC544BAAEDFDF897175770F"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to disregard value of children’s savings accounts</header> 
<subparagraph id="HDA25A265288F4959902795BCF41AB9DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary finds that a State to which a grant is made under section 403 for a fiscal year has failed to comply with section 408(a)(13) during the fiscal year, the Secretary shall reduce the grant otherwise payable to the State under section 403(a)(1) for the succeeding fiscal year by the percentage specified in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4639C58A97774BD38DA04D400C5E0D64"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount of reduction</header><text>The reduction required under subparagraph (A) shall be—</text> 
<clause id="H24F903F3B50A458CAD68D29F465FF32B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not less than 1 nor more than 2 percent;</text></clause> <clause id="H53C363EBAE214D53A4D7329A4DC3529F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not less than 2 nor more than 3 percent, if the finding is the second consecutive finding made pursuant to subparagraph (A); or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDC87A67403C742328065B2BB352C1526"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>not less than 3 nor more than 5 percent, if the finding is the third or a subsequent consecutive such finding.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBCD1B432A154690A632BAEAD621F780"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No exception for reasonable cause</header><text>Section 409(b)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>or (13)</quote> and inserting <quote>(13), or (17)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4FB5AA1C73D04629AE5AD533ED602C1B"><enum>102.</enum><header>Exclusion of children’s savings accounts from resources under the SSI program</header> 
<subsection id="HFA98E79FB47C4F71AB583801D8687B92"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1613(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1382b">42 U.S.C. 1382b(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8CDC3560E63D494585C067FC6BDE49A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (16);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B7AD3D53CC641F8B877FA94505B7D9B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (17) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65C383F0439B485881E0D7B9E5BEF091"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (17) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB50DE18AF6C44EFAAD84D89C62A7AF7" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H5DF1CA4CDF7A423E9FBE1B8B6038A6A5"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the value of funds in any children’s savings account (as defined in section 2 of the CSA OPPORTUNITY Act), including accrued interest or other earnings thereon.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2B67AF3C2E91494390040376180AD5B6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1613(e)(5) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1382b">42 U.S.C. 1382b(e)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>of this Act or section 2 of the CSA OPPORTUNITY Act</quote> before the period.</text></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="HFCE922EED3A349F98591630F2DEDD7F4"><enum>II</enum><header>Amendment to the Food and Nutrition Act of <enum-in-header>2008</enum-in-header></header> 
<section id="HA135369B68984D9C83E3C2D1EB17E087"><enum>201.</enum><header>Exclusion of children’s savings accounts from resources under the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(g) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2014">7 U.S.C. 2014(g)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0BBEA07B73334AAD85E53C4A0AD6D508" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HE1C7EE6CC42F4E4BBBE0BC9A7AF41F38"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Exclusion of Children’s Savings Accounts From Allowable Financial Resources</header> <subparagraph id="H5A1466AABD854816AD82A2204EBCFCCF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall exclude from financial resources under this subsection the value of funds in any children’s savings account, including accrued interest or other earnings thereon.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H674A5BCC9E534587AC28E74107843DFC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Children’s savings account</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>children’s savings account</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the <short-title>CSA OPPORTUNITY Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title> <title id="HDE9FB07D997A42C283FEF1828EC6915B"><enum>III</enum><header>Amendment to Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of <enum-in-header>1981</enum-in-header></header> <section id="H2C7D08ADF88C4CF9A4A01AFCBE0965DF"><enum>301.</enum><header>Exclusion of certain accounts from calculation under the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2605(f) of the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8624">42 U.S.C. 8624(f)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9AAADFC60B7E4B72BA9EB458F8B7708A" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H23515414A1C347AEB13F66952F1CBB5F" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusion of certain accounts from calculation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H508B5320142A4304BEE570BF5ABB463F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The determination of the income or assets of a household for purposes of eligibility under this section shall be made without regard to the value of funds in any children’s savings account, including accrued interest or other earnings thereon.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE93CD61A68194C8E906C56A05560D0FE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Children’s savings account</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>children’s savings account</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the <short-title>CSA OPPORTUNITY Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title> 
</legis-body></bill>

