<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H2E73485A29F1445F8AFFA7564D589FA5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5961 RH: No Funds for Iranian Terrorism Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 218</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5961</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–270, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231016">October 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001176">Mr. Scalise</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001309">Mr. Burchett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000307">Mr. James</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001093">Mrs. Houchin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment and referred to the Committee on<committee-name committee-id="HBA00"> Financial Services</committee-name> for a period ending not later than November 9, 2023, for consideration of such provisions of the bill and amendment as fall within the jurisdiction of that committee pursuant to clause 1(h) of rule X</action-desc><action-instruction>Insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To freeze certain Iranian funds involved in the 2023 hostage deal between the United States and Iran, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="H3C72E98C7C5F4AD9AEA143A8E1C59A73" style="OLC" changed="not-changed"><section id="H1EF3BF0F17D84E97B8A32387AD244AFE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Funds for Iranian Terrorism Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H87034C3B40B74762A24F8AEE0C052601"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H55CC1C575D5746D1BF918F53D16B6639"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On October 7, 2023, Iran-backed Hamas terrorists launched a massive, unprovoked war on Israel by air, land, and sea, in which they engaged in the brutal murder of over 1,300 people and kidnapped 130 people who are now being held hostage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H072A242952434AF7A9004800805FE1D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Hamas, Palestinian Islamic Jihad, and Hezbollah have all been designated by the United States as Foreign Terrorist Organizations pursuant to section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4899B45DDE55400EA8D9F9BD1F773DA9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to an unclassified United States government assessment, <quote>Iran has historically provided up to $100 million annually in combined support to Palestinian terrorist groups, including Hamas, Palestinian Islamic Jihad (PIJ), and the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98E0A7D197FA4E359DEA24818352C6DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>As National Security Advisor Jake Sullivan stated on October 10, 2023, <quote>Iran is complicit in this attack in a broad sense because they have provided the lion’s share of the funding for the military wing of Hamas, they have provided training, they have provided capabilities, they have provided support, and they have provided engagement and contact with Hamas over years and years.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26B8005654C34B51929FE5B0D29D32B9" reported-display-style="italic" changed="added" committee-id="HFA00"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">President Biden reached an agreement with the Iranian regime to bring home Siamak Namazi, Morad Tahbaz, Emad Shargi, and two additional American hostages all of whom were wrongfully detained in Iran.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFBE3D39F1697473BB19B49C28FE2CA2F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to covered Iranian assets</header><subsection id="HF3EF2F901F8745FE9CA1F7FFED401F7A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On and after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall impose the sanction described in subsection (c) with respect to each foreign financial institution and each international financial institution that the President determines engages in an activity described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD4CF13D74EC141EC87CFEBD3FB8568E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities described</header><text>A foreign financial institution or international financial institution engages in an activity described in this subsection if the institution processes, participates in, or facilitates a transaction using or involving covered Iranian funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E7A55B4ABF048E891FEE27F4890248D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>The sanction described in this subsection is the exercise of all of the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of a foreign financial institution or international financial institution described in subsection (a) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFDAEE37795114AF1AD6A35BBAE6746A9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to a person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this section or any regulations promulgated to carry out this section to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of that Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBD61FD6457564CD1911A67D1FE71E997"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination of sanctions</header><text>The President shall not be required to impose sanctions under this section with respect to a foreign financial institution or international financial institution described in subsection (a) if the President certifies in writing to the appropriate congressional committees that the Government of Iran—</text><paragraph id="HEA8F5B72AFD24D57AD9DD58999849806"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no longer repeatedly provides support for international terrorism as determined by the Secretary of State pursuant to—</text><subparagraph id="HF8A424B90BCA4932A9644674B20A8999"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 1754(c)(1)(A) of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4318">50 U.S.C. 4318(c)(1)(A)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1F87C2FB3C146C9BCB04A69A5635673"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H172E8A37225740AC9E0BA662ED17403C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AEF8CC9070B416487433246E410FADF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other provision of law; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2F655C8DA1A46388C5D8BFF413C7577"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has ceased the pursuit, acquisition, and development of, and verifiably dismantled its, nuclear, biological, and chemical weapons and ballistic missiles and ballistic missile launch technology.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD0B3E6D0E15646509E4F1DDEEE1951D0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HA8C9502D9D7E4E2D85A6369F1087BB50"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H95DF3D239FC74B0FB72CC97D8837B92C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD466E518B1214F81984959C517EECA6A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9454517B57EE4810BBD3F379D8D6D34F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered Iranian funds</header><text>The term <term>covered Iranian funds</term> means any funds transferred from accounts in the Republic of Korea to Qatar pursuant to or under the authority or guaranty of a waiver, license, assurance letter, or other guidance issued pursuant to or in furtherance of the waiver determination made pursuant to sections 1244(i) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8803">22 U.S.C. 8803(i)</external-xref>) and 1247(f) of the Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8806">22 U.S.C. 8806(f)</external-xref>) and section 1245(d)(5) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a(d)(5)</external-xref>) that is the subject of the document entitled <quote>Waiver of Sanctions with Respect to the Transfer of Funds from the Republic of Korea to Qatar</quote> and was transmitted to Congress in September 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E3ED8B72EA74428A2BDBFCADD48FD2D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign financial institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign financial institution</term> has the meaning given such term under section 561.308 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D5BAEBA1D5C41E3B9A5A847C1F27D14"><enum>(4)</enum><header>International financial institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>international financial institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1701(c) of the International Financial Institutions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/262r">22 U.S.C. 262r(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment and referred to the Committee on<committee-name committee-id="HBA00"> Financial Services</committee-name> for a period ending not later than November 9, 2023, for consideration of such provisions of the bill and amendment as fall within the jurisdiction of that committee pursuant to clause 1(h) of rule X</action-desc><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

