<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6F025CBAB8CC40C4A4EFFDBBDCBDEF45" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3094 IH: To terminate the requirement imposed by the Secretary of Homeland Security for proof of COVID–19 vaccination for foreign travelers, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3094</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To terminate the requirement imposed by the Secretary of Homeland Security for proof of COVID&#8211;19 vaccination for foreign travelers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDCFCDE0458CA43A29FD2C621D4AB6DF0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0A86332C028D4D3C9EE1328F369E7607" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Terminating DHS requirement for proof of COVID–19 vaccination for foreign travelers</header> 
<subsection id="HFB42E24142804D749BDEE0502B8336B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, a travel vaccination requirement for foreign travelers referred to in subsection (c) shall have no force or effect, unless otherwise specified in a provision of law enacted after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6D71EA6F5F9149CD9F3C657E3C906B22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, no Federal funds may be used to administer, implement, or enforce a travel vaccination requirement for foreign travelers referred to in subsection (c), unless otherwise specified in a provision of law enacted after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H03413EB98399465C805333E045925DE4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Travel vaccination requirement for foreign travelers</header><text>In this Act, a travel vaccination requirement for foreign travelers referred to in this subsection is a requirement specified in—</text> <paragraph id="HB723727022664385A770B7FF754B9526"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the decision issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection entitled <quote>Notification of Temporary Travel Restrictions Applicable to Land Ports of Entry and Ferries Service Between the United States and Canada</quote> and published in the Federal Register on April 22, 2022 (87 Fed. Reg. 24048 et seq.) for proof of COVID–19 vaccination for travelers who are covered individuals (as defined in such order);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7D214EFD47924FC59DA7FED0552543D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the decision of the Secretary of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Notification of Temporary Travel Restrictions Applicable to Land Ports of Entry and Ferries Service Between the United States and Mexico</quote> published in the Federal Register on April 22, 2022 (87 Fed. Reg. 24041) to continue to temporarily restrict travel by certain noncitizens into the United States at land ports of entry, including ferry terminals, along the United States-Mexico border; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H886828DCF9274100B331C6F317B8FA7F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any successor or subsequent decision of the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection for the processing for entry into the United States foreign persons to show proof of COVID–19 vaccination as a condition on entering the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

