<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA5E974A4E9CE497190A82FB70849CA58" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6261 IH: Impact of Crime on Public Building Usage Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6261</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General to conduct a review on the impact of crime on public building usage, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H61C672CE214D45DAA28D811DCCF07940" style="OLC"><section id="H6482ABCBAC0240B68768CF851B4C21E1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Impact of Crime on Public Building Usage Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H13E2063B374B426DA6363958B5B2D416" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on impact of crime on public building usage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a review and submit to Congress a report outlining—</text><paragraph id="H63236B27862B4D0E9293AB77D9F3F538"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the effects of increased crime rates and safety concerns, including use of fentanyl and other drugs and homelessness, in urban areas on building usage for in-person work at Federal buildings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB17520021FF4D1B9DA95FB2EFF95EA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how usage of different commuting modes of transportation to Federal buildings are affected by increased crime rates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB494E70C168A486EADEC0BD6BF624D25"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the effects of low office utilization rates on safety around Federal buildings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5ED928CFDDF4CA8BE8AC0254140B9B3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any agency exceptions given to the policy set forth in the memorandum of the Office of Management and Budget titled <quote>Measuring, Monitoring, and Improving Organizational Health and Organizational Performance in the Context of Evolving Agency Work Environments</quote> and issued on April 13, 2023, due to unsafe commuting conditions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EA4CAEADA8C4D589D45503FAADAA894"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any costs associated with safety issues impacting Federal building.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H40A85DB2605F463DB3F5C449CBA2E44D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on costs of crime around public buildings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the inspector general of the General Services Administration shall submit to Congress a report on the impacts on and costs associated with building operations related to crime and public safety in and around Federal buildings. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

