<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCC2ACEA8E6204930B31B50208FD9CD94" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1180 IH: Billion Dollar Boondoggle Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1180</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Director of the Office of Management and Budget to submit to Congress an annual report on projects that are over budget and behind schedule, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE371984C5C1745D4B30C98F265D4DD44" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA3662AE1240442D7ABB4A834B80A8B6E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Billion Dollar Boondoggle Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF5B28622BD884D7AA9470A13075D6F13"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual report</header> <subsection id="HB8E24BACA1274F8D96BECAAEF6A08602"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text>
<paragraph id="H7E19847D24E1447BB4D4421BEC017862"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>covered agency</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H00616EFC74594E18B334BCF0F868A781"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an Executive agency, as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H03C316C579264A4EBF5BEAF9430B09EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an independent regulatory agency, as defined in section 3502 of title 44, United States Code;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11085991B5274786A2CCF0C3D40487DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>covered project</term> means a project funded by a covered agency—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE5402F789482411080F41A114FDB3D0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is more than 5 years behind schedule; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H31A5A9BD7A32462791CA6FABAE654BEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which the amount spent on the project is not less than $1,000,000,000 more than the original cost estimate for the project; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0B160C8ACF164F13B72D0B2532213355"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>project</term> means a major acquisition, a major defense acquisition program (as defined in section 2430 of title 10, United States Code), a procurement, a construction project, a remediation or clean-up effort, or any other time-limited endeavor, that is not funded through direct spending (as defined in section 250(c) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/900">2 U.S.C. 900(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H20B86DAE694B4D20A1BC4A67C073ECA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall issue guidance requiring covered agencies to include, on an annual basis in a report described in paragraph (2) of section 3516(a) of title 31, United States Code, or a consolidated report described in paragraph (1) of such section, information relating to each covered project of the covered agency, which shall include—</text>
<paragraph id="H490543B2C64F4D07A6C16FD262D7429B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a brief description of the covered project, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H28B69ED1B6EE41CF826DA538AA8788BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the purpose of the covered project;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1352ABB389C04B5A9B217B0B0D846511"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each location in which the covered project is carried out;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85F8B12FA81544F4BA231A7D81CD5C22"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the contract or award number of the covered project, where applicable;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7A12F35386484237B1B64CF5973FFF04"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the year in which the covered project was initiated;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC27DBAFD89CA48029A55C5511B8B4972"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Federal share of the total cost of the covered project; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD3CBBE12D7AD4D47821365F879370809"><enum>(F)</enum><text>each primary contractor, subcontractor, grant recipient, and subgrantee recipient of the covered project;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H954554E56FF24E91A65553495221CC7F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an explanation of any change to the original scope of the covered project, including by the addition or narrowing of the initial requirements of the covered project;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB15757C4170848CF8215863D89578D51"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the original expected date for completion of the covered project;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9C8C01E8641D46069D9E037F372D4C5D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the current expected date for completion of the covered project;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3F5C0EE225E34C20A264E4BC514FB1D9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the original cost estimate for the covered project, as adjusted to reflect increases in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers, as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H509C3A86EA4840A49CAC2DCE55FD0199"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the current cost estimate for the covered project, as adjusted to reflect increases in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers, as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7D54EB96C2DD44199B99684199C59BC5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an explanation for a delay in completion or an increase in the original cost estimate for the covered project, including, where applicable, any impact of insufficient or delayed appropriations; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H911D23B5C2914ACA8E1C82ACE356B779"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the amount of and rationale for any award, incentive fee, or other type of bonus, if any, awarded for the covered project.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


