<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3E9DCFFF2AA94749BF073536502A484D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4363 IH: Comprehensive Cancer Survivorship Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4363</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To address the health of cancer survivors and unmet needs that survivors face through the entire continuum of care from diagnosis through active treatment and posttreatment, in order to improve survivorship, treatment, transition to recovery and beyond, quality of life and palliative care, and long-term health outcomes, including by developing a minimum standard of care for cancer survivorship, irrespective of the type of cancer, a survivor’s background, or forthcoming survivorship needs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6E3F1D29EF2C44538BD3ACF7FD7A9779" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB130380DF9C44F3391E75DF158F71D64" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="HA49FBFFA4B894ACC80575598E2136E1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Cancer Survivorship Act</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HC0AD349AB2FA471E80053657782066E1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="HB130380DF9C44F3391E75DF158F71D64" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9666373ADB1E443995C88791CF48C3CA" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HDA414219BA464E3DB6025EB1BFB5C08A" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H5B2D8C391D104CD5B43FF2A6E3AE038F" level="section">Sec. 4. Coverage of cancer care planning and coordination services.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HDE27504711C5414B98A2F6F2DC78634C" level="section">Sec. 5. Survivorship transition tools.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HAF35B2CCB62E4784AE49926428CEC9E1" level="section">Sec. 6. Alternative payment model.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HB4DCFC03F13746A48C6C74073191D354" level="section">Sec. 7. Survivorship navigation.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFBB43B9EF9144DADBBB084FCEFF68895" level="section">Sec. 8. Survivorship care demonstration program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H879733BF2FCB4E5CB98BCE7D977B8BE0" level="section">Sec. 9. Cancer survivor employment assistance program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HCAB9C73B2F9E4F8A98807C55502BA2F3" level="section">Sec. 10. Comprehensive cancer survivorship program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0BBCDC0BC45E455395FCF21F13B55594" level="section">Sec. 11. Adult cancer survivorship study.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9825AA2D821843279352207E29CB22A0" level="section">Sec. 12. Survivorship progress report.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H2DAE013E08E744DF92607F112B0AD3D7" level="section">Sec. 13. Promoting State innovations to ease transitions to the primary care setting for children with cancer.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H7FA28DACA8E24991880C3A8C7204C0E7" level="section">Sec. 14. Childhood cancer demonstration model and standard of care.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0F57FA21B0084C258AB83F6D729BC709" level="section">Sec. 15. Medicaid coverage of cancer fertility services for cancer survivors.</toc-entry> </toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9666373ADB1E443995C88791CF48C3CA" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="HC1B1A49673824D55941495E7A79F9187" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A cancer survivor is any individual with a history of cancer, from the time of diagnosis through the rest of their life, across the continuum of care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB7A06B0280245C298A6FA4F1D1F45B9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Today, there are approximately 18,000,000 Americans who are cancer survivors, and the number of survivors is projected to reach 26,000,000 by 2040. Therefore, there is a great need to be able to provide ways to sustain the care needed and to offer those living with, through, and beyond cancer a safe, supportive, and accommodating environment where such individuals can engage in physical and social support activities to sustain optimal quality of life.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5091045D94C54ECABF350B62562573C8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cancer survivors face difficult emotional, psychological, neurological, financial, legal, and other physical challenges that persist beyond diagnosis and treatment, often arising months and years after active cancer treatment ends.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5CD5C26C8F0045A786905749301CBA3C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Cancer survivors have unique needs and must manage short- and long-term effects of their treatment, as well as regular screenings for cancer recurrence or new cancers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H188B467668AC48518B67D83B3B1D1CA1" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Cancer survivors of racial and ethnic diversity, as well as lower socioeconomic status, have disproportionately lower health-related, quality-of-life scores compared to non-Hispanic White cancer survivors.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H242C3F3D9E2D4649A83F1E17B55D944B" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Cancer survivors living in rural areas have less access to services and have poorer outcomes than survivors in metropolitan areas.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA69509E41BF42118955176D46A31CDE" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Children, adolescent, and young adult cancer survivors are particularly susceptible to long-term consequences from treatment, and up to 80 percent have a severe, disabling, life-threatening, or fatal health condition by the age of 50. Best practices in this area would improve treatment, quality of life, and long-term health outcomes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H17EA786BB3D74B04A9BB6C4D49EAACD5" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Clinical trials have shown that cancer survivorship programs help cancer survivors meet or exceed the recommended amount of physical activity, significantly increasing their cardiovascular health and overall quality of life and decreasing their cancer-related fatigue.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE0F0317818F14183A38D810A462D8028" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Despite the National Cancer Institute and other professional organizations’ definition of a cancer survivor beginning on the day of a cancer diagnosis, there is little agreement among clinicians, researchers, and insurance companies on what services are included in <quote>survivorship care</quote> and the point at which <quote>survivorship care</quote> begins.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE0DF4005029409F8FBABD5F38D58014" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cancer survivors, their families, their caregivers, and their providers face many difficulties understanding and coordinating the transition from specialty to primary care, and for this reason communication and treatment are often fragmented and inconsistent.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB23AFDDD1F54446B94E4C59446BE65BD" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>To avoid additional health-related or financial hardships to cancer survivors and their families, comprehensive and forward-thinking cancer survivorship studies and programs across Federal agencies, in collaboration with States, localities, and medical and professional organizations, are required to engage in a coordinated effort to improve health outcomes and quality of life of survivors.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HDA414219BA464E3DB6025EB1BFB5C08A" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HC7C8230990B74BEE8F2B1D4CAB46B1B9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cancer survivor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cancer survivor</term> means an individual from the time of cancer diagnosis through the balance of his or her life. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44A514066DD64C45B9EC1FE091ABD994" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Caregiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>caregiver</term> means a family member, friend, or other person who cares for an individual with a chronic or disabling condition, including cancer. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D38504597404E15921DC1B8278B2E7D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Patient experience data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>patient experience data</term> means patient experiences, perspectives, needs, and priorities related to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6238A8BC045541D6860F267465438553"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the symptoms of the patient’s conditions and the natural history of such conditions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H26A17D68921643EBB39ADC3058107F7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the impact of the conditions on the patient’s functioning and quality of life;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H209467C3B9EB49A4A09B525AA54F8684"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the patient’s experience with treatments;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC73C91C6B164098A9D33F032B9EBAFE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">input on which outcomes are important to the patient;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H28B45F9CA46547C0A0232E00B3807A60"><enum>(E)</enum><text>patient preferences for outcomes and treatments; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H38A5437839AA421381604A8A688180CF"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the relative importance of any issues as defined by patients.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A4E2F421369497B8444496F642A9DAE" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Psychosocial effects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>psychosocial effects</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="HD35E6FDC74704C688A3AA179F32BEB2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the psychological, behavioral, emotional, and social effects of a disease, such as cancer, and its treatment; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE50DE78A36474872ACB79F904D4E3223"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of such effects of cancer, includes changes in how a patient thinks, their feelings, moods, beliefs, ways of coping, and relationships with family, friends, and coworkers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0A0888F0F3334B5DB297E11775A86A2C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Psychosocial care</header><text>The term <term>psychosocial care</term> means psychological and social services and interventions that enable survivors, patients, their families, and health care providers to optimize health care and to manage the psychological, behavioral, physical, emotional, and social aspects of illness and its consequences so as to promote better health and well-being.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4BB13B4CB9884DE493C3544F7F21EEAB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Except as otherwise specified, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE82F9290FDF4B0EA4029758AAF8D46A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Survivorship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>survivorship</term> means the period from the time of cancer diagnosis until the end of life, including any portions of such period during which interventions are necessary to address—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBE280FA3DEA5440FA5D98DC78BEFB789" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the physical, mental, emotional, social, and financial effects of cancer that begin at diagnosis and continue through treatment and beyond; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H679DD086457D408C9361AF3D4AD067C5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issues related to follow-up care (including regular health and wellness checkups), late and long-term effects of treatment, screening for cancer recurrence and new cancers, and quality of life.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD02F6C3B5FCE4E29ABBB3839255D09FB" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Survivorship care plan</header><text>The term <term>survivorship care plan</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="HDB40094E689D42BE822B8C21005436FE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an individualized care plan for patients who have been diagnosed with cancer; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3BC48A00A379410091EE93173EBE3AA2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a treatment summary and any follow-up care guidelines in such plan that—</text> <clause id="H36F23DDC87004F78998DA8F972AC2A9B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are for monitoring and maintaining the patient’s medical and psychosocial health and well-being; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H99B6BBC56B94468FB4A1E878802F2341"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are meant to be a transition and communication tool for the survivor, their family, their caregiver, and all their health care providers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7743D0D6BA141EF80A66F5CAA1E04ED" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Survivorship navigation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>survivorship navigation</term> means a service that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8A3CEC6C032C4945A1B6F00198E4277E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>helps patients overcome health care system and other barriers; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA884C74046ED4618AF5D86267C441181"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides patients with timely access to high-quality medical, physical, and psychosocial care from their cancer diagnosis through all phases of their cancer experience.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H42EB1771ACF9485FB15AD947617C559E" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Treatment summary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>treatment summary</term> means a detailed summary of a patient’s disease, the types of treatment the patient received, members of the patient’s care team, and any side effects or other problems, including psychosocial effects, caused by treatment.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H5B2D8C391D104CD5B43FF2A6E3AE038F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Coverage of cancer care planning and coordination services</header> <subsection id="H36BA4C93EB0246F1B7883EE8D7D19834"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA3E00A913D3E4AF2905B464EA6C9FCCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (s)(2)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEC9DA8FB21714CF9956559977BD753CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (II);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAEF27FB4272E43C1AE6AB1B8E3FE6C45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (JJ); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB778FCD7287E40E09869FAD4CC1490EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H746CAB32CCCE4C0DA4E2E74945B3DD19" style="traditional"> 
<subparagraph id="H88699C6F007C4E1185E47DFD9CBFD701" indent="up1"><enum>(KK)</enum><text>cancer care planning and coordination services (as defined in subsection (nnn));</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2C14A51633E49CCA202E5CBCA3850DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD2E7119F7C94CC29C497246196A05F4" other-style="archaic" style="other"> 
<subsection id="H5D50285CFE114566802EDBC42F82FE35"><enum>(nnn)</enum><header>Cancer Care Planning and Coordination Services</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE5CC2186184E4C6AB084616FDF6D192D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cancer care planning and coordination services</term> means, with respect to an individual who is diagnosed with cancer, the development of a treatment plan by a physician, physician assistant, or nurse practitioner that—</text> <subparagraph id="H5ACE2CB2491C495EB5CB98EB976E9C76" indent="up1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes each component of the Institute of Medicine Care Management Plan (as described in the article entitled <quote>Delivering High-Quality Cancer Care: Charting a New Course for a System in Crisis</quote> published by the Institute of Medicine);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2502AFC3540A4CC288763F93F8E69080" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is furnished in written form or electronically, at the visit of such individual with such physician, physician assistant, or nurse practitioner, or as soon after the date of the visit as practicable; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA30FF6208C85407684CE9CD51E265E2C" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is furnished, to the greatest extent practicable, in a form that appropriately takes into account cultural and linguistic needs of the individual in order to make the plan accessible to such individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF25A5D740F27428C8953C3D1D8E52F42" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish frequencies at which services described in paragraph (1) may be furnished, provided that such services may be furnished with respect to an individual—</text> <subparagraph id="HFBF5F045370E4DAAAEC33FAE77C95C2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at the time such individual is diagnosed with cancer for purposes of planning treatment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD724F9B52F9F4AC19808B4A99BC0751F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if there is a change in the condition of such individual or such individual’s treatment preferences;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H986A94891FE44C43B60D28EC03F58536"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at the end of active treatment and beginning of survivorship care; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H003D27ECDEC44B2589A8DE07DFD86C08"><enum>(D)</enum><text>if there is a recurrence of such cancer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEF250083C8484143BDFB27032DD07B8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment under physician fee schedule</header> <paragraph id="HD91FEBD585C34055A6E33A66DC47706A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1848(j)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(j)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(2)(KK),</quote> after <quote>health risk assessment),</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC478C7D13764DED93DCDDAC0AE484F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial rates</header><text>Unless the Secretary otherwise provides, the payment rate specified under the physician fee schedule under the amendment made by paragraph (1) for cancer care planning and coordination services shall be the same payment rate as provided for transitional care management services (as defined in CPT code 99496).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBDB1BE9683D345B0A57506CD389A3D68"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to services furnished on or after the first day of the first calendar year that begins after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HDE27504711C5414B98A2F6F2DC78634C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Survivorship transition tools</header> 
<subsection id="HF02355D857F04ECE8897123F084302EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of the Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology, in collaboration with Director of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, shall—</text> <paragraph id="HFB356E9F0428437885D1613618026588"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluate existing models for survivorship care plans, as they relate to both adults and children, through engagement with professional societies, payors, patient advocacy organizations, community-based organizations, electronic health record vendors, and other stakeholders;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F3EE3D3755C4CC597AFA9D1F19A0ACF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluate other existing tools for developing survivorship care plans, such as—</text> <subparagraph id="H8FA9861A8E1C4F1D8EF06DA15B30FE82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>survivorship guidelines of the National Comprehensive Cancer Network and the American Society of Clinical Oncology; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H520EB0FEB48D43BE9B02DE3C6575AF80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>tools such as Passport for Care;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7891AE35DCC04D128C390D5CF987378D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>collaborate with the Office for Civil Rights of the Department of Health and Human Services to evaluate the privacy and security implications of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4364362E3F734EF3BDAA374E6AB9891C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consolidating treatment history and survivorship guidelines into a personalized survivorship care plan, as described in paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D19BB6505134C3FB1B84BE3635B5888"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">patient use of computer or mobile phone-based application programs described in paragraph (4)(B); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E79D78E7C06464EB896100BC7537955"><enum>(4)</enum><text>taking into consideration the results of evaluation under paragraphs (1) and (2)—</text> <subparagraph id="H86CCC6EAEF844FB0BF320FEB770B307F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 36 months after the date of enactment of this Act, publish information resources for cancer patients and providers on strategies for consolidating treatment history and survivorship guidelines into a personalized survivorship care plan to guide survivorship monitoring and follow-up care; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB6C77880410F4E859405308128B8DF12"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include in such information resources recommendations about possible patient use of application programs (<quote>apps</quote>) to develop personalized survivorship care plans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5E97C69BD2004385B2B702F78CCD5408"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>electronic health record</term> means an electronic record of health-related information on an individual that is created, gathered, managed, and consulted by authorized health care clinicians and staff.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HAF35B2CCB62E4784AE49926428CEC9E1" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Alternative payment model</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall develop an alternative payment model for payment under title XVIII and XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>, 1396 et seq.) for items and services relating to cancer survivorship care (as defined by the Secretary). Following such testing, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report containing a description of such model that includes the following information:</text> <paragraph id="H77A80F32FC60433293350F5F33E879D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of what event would trigger an individual’s entry into such a model (such as the end of the individual’s active cancer treatment, the beginning of the individual’s need for supportive care during active treatment, or another event).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H391D64BAB2D74F00A2600B5407AB92FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The length of the individual’s participation under such model, including a description of any ability to extend such participation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4960DB128AF346E1AEC33EE229FC0A4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that such model is based on an episode of care, the appropriate length of the survivorship episode of care and whether additional episodes may be triggered, if necessary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAFEE198A45DF422499CE351D626FD0D5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strategies to ensure that any episode of care under such a model begins with the development and dissemination of a survivorship care plan for the transition from active cancer treatment to follow-up care to the individual and all relevant health care providers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HECE011D531244E0EAF7679CE96107C2C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of any bundled payment packages that will be used under such model.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE0E68C95CBA42B3B7BCB0C683AB82CC"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A specification of any follow-up or new screening under such model for unmet needs of individuals participating in such model.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D72B87C9CB74F83AF54B462C4B38468"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How consistent, shared decision making will be promoted under such model so that individuals are given the knowledge needed for self-management between episodes of care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19415D9FBECA45EDA3AD6DC7F3D050F0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A specification of which types of health care providers may furnish items and services under such model, including genetic counselors and mental health professionals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56ACED41FF814AE69E9CA966124549DA"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strategies for applying evidence-based risk stratification principles to direct survivors to personalized care pathways that match the level of care needed to the relative risks and needs of the survivor.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2ACACD0135E472D894BC66BDF141346"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strategies for coordination of care between such providers, such as between specialists and primary care providers, and how principal responsibility will be assigned for an episode of care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED8C3837E1704C4C8242326B6C526316"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strategies for addressing social determinants of health through such model.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB483163B84D42F09325A7B2749F9EDD"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how such model will promote—</text> <subparagraph id="H7A884C47D4214E4FAE4A77B7F63F2799"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevention, early detection surveillance, and treatment for individuals continuing to receive systemic therapy after the end of active cancer treatment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73DB5F3AC39349628028B43B90E29257"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such individuals’ understanding of, and access to, treatment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA48FBF3005DB4DE4B964D5D35D3EB4F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>survivorship research; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H121AA04D567542EE80310A110154F113"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the continuing health of cancer survivors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4092C76319AF4DE280FEE118BBD52B12"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of how different forms and stages of cancer may require the development of different survivorship plans and alternative payment models based on varying episodes of care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2FA4A4FE31E40F4BD090704BA4442EE"><enum>(14)</enum><text>A plan for testing any alternative payment model described in the report, including the timing of such testing, an analysis of the impact of such testing, any barriers to implementing such testing, and any other recommendations determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HB4DCFC03F13746A48C6C74073191D354"><enum>7.</enum><header>Survivorship navigation</header> <subsection id="H84EAD040532B4528858498AC6424C534"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review of programs and navigation study</header> <paragraph id="H52EDF924445C45C29A04806263844B3B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2D50F40A00FD4DA2829C04F5774450BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complete a review of previous and current cancer survivorship navigation programs, including any applicable standards of care such as those of the Professional Oncology Navigation Task Force, and the Academy of Oncology Nurse &amp; Patient Navigators, the Oncology Nursing Society; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H770313A6179C4CA2B8B4F16739FFD014" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a report to the Congress on the results of such review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H17E7FF4F3A3B4E038C57F6FA3E87369F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall take into consideration each of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H58A834854BAE46819587D21B8536F91C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How cancer survivorship navigation program services might be provided from diagnosis across the continuum of care through survivorship, taking into consideration—</text> 
<clause id="H2431002DA43D41A5A92029B6FE5282D9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the type of navigation services that are most effective for survivors at the time of diagnosis; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4CB878505F7B43EB96FF2FE50DE56CBB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the type of navigation services that are most useful for survivors who are managing the late and long-term effects of cancer and cancer treatment.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5D65DEDF2EEC414C8A5A3761539F9331"><enum>(B)</enum><text>How navigation services might evolve over the continuum of care and how to encourage a dynamic navigation system.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD33B089BC5A400299BE98BABB27DE76"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Training needs for navigators.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B1154C4E5FD4C228620FF18E8E53390"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Comparison and delineation of navigation services provided by lay and professional navigators.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB600715ECD034EDD95DB2B05C170E109"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Evaluation of optimal strategies for offering survivors navigation services and encouraging their utilization of such services.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD507C1C42B564AD291D3057FE7E4BEBB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Defining—</text> <clause id="H44845C97D7FB4C05AB64613021BC3E57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the continuum of care during which services are provided; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFA2D4ABCF9314929A078DEEE7849BC53"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the nature of services for a long-term survivor.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9877387A861E4A46B2499D7C4413A43B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The location of navigation services (such as whether such services should be provided as part of oncology practices or outside of oncology practices).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H70825882D63E4324BF4741AC3337CE5A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Federal financing for navigation services (such as whether to finance such services through a grant program funded through annual discretionary appropriations).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA31679522A33423D896A7C7FC541E259"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Alternative delivery and payment models for cancer survivorship navigation services, including consideration of—</text> 
<clause id="HA48BB9FF1DFF4A9EA87207464D717816"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an episode-of-care model for providing cancer survivorship navigation services, or a patient-focused navigation benefit that survivors could utilize in different settings, with the navigation services meeting standards set by the Secretary; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD944A54AD11E4D7997F52E0971B0A1F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>services funded through the Medicare and Medicaid programs.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFF9DF82C91644EC7BCC176F93F176C9D" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Resources and the role of patient advocacy organizations and peer support networks in cancer survivorship navigation services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAC71C390070147FDB2D87A860F84B737"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Demonstration program for navigation services for cancer survivors</header> <paragraph id="HF3221664EECF44CDBD11746FD532C115"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a demonstration program consisting of awarding grants to eligible entities to provide navigation services to cancer survivors.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3511834134B9450387C9C5F492FF098F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall initiate the demonstration program under this subsection not later than 12 months after completing the review as required under subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7548A90BB4C1404488E13982E5933C4F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA4931CD4ED214432BA5D779251A96335"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have staff and expertise to provide navigation services; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF1D7E57D427647B2B96E4D0E259FA2C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be—</text> 
<clause id="HA84A5D53A1CA4D42A31C68CB36B5B2AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a community-based organization;</text></clause> <clause id="H15D70D77D9D04F37B229875EBFAA618A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a patient-centered education and service organization;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF066AF9516F440809A284BB3B5770875"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nonprofit patient or cancer advocacy organization;</text></clause> <clause id="H8E40546BF7B449E1BE9E46B6D7E0D040"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a community cancer provider;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3F1D1C988E494EECB4F64FD87690E1C4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a cancer center;</text></clause> <clause id="H09077A6B18474AF492C317F25285BE06"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a hospital; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H5F457C18C9C4463C9A5FECE279D076D6"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>a community health center;</text></clause> <clause id="H9EB86D6362044CBB903BB4FF2B9F191B"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>a rural health clinic; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3EBF4EFCDE4B49EAB8DEC686C86B27D5"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">another type of entity as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3059341C874744DB89FF32C5C21F84C8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under this section shall use the grant to provide navigation services to cancer survivors, including by—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H10BB02985C0C4839A999ECDB851DF7E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>offering navigation services from diagnosis through the continuum of care, including long-term survivorship, or offering navigation services from the end of active treatment with an emphasis on facilitating the transition from active treatment to long-term survivorship care and throughout survivorship;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCD28973F47F14CA18D97E8551A29E832"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a timely manner, assisting cancer survivors to navigate cancer treatment and follow-up services, such as screenings, risk assessment, mitigation, health promotion activities, providing health information and education, coaching, and support;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB59C16386C8F40579733EF9916DDFA16"><enum>(C)</enum><text>addressing cancer care disparities in the design and delivery of services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H19FA6DF82C414EDBBCA0D597BA9733E1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensuring coordination with the survivor’s health care providers;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC281281E70D243848FF1F99CC7F91756"><enum>(E)</enum><text>following evidence-based survivorship care guidelines in the design and delivery of survivorship services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H08A1137B67974180A6B6D394F71BACAE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>ensuring the delivery of culturally appropriate services and materials; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H56983E7DDBDD4125B842DC061FE1653D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>assisting cancer survivors to meet and overcome barriers to treatment and follow-up services, such as any such barriers relating to food insecurity, housing, transportation, labor, access to broadband connectivity, the availability of telehealth, or child care, with emphasis placed on high-risk populations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HFBB43B9EF9144DADBBB084FCEFF68895"><enum>8.</enum><header>Survivorship care demonstration program</header> <subsection id="H491C45624C7247D0875BEA103BE93823"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a demonstration program for a period of 5 years consisting of awarding grants to improve the quality of cancer survivorship care.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H110078D1445B4D6297D5FAE062022C90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall initiate the demonstration program under this section not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB5E5A749F5CE4FB3904A4F9F4B4DCA2B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Demonstration sites</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that grants are awarded under this section to improve the quality of cancer survivorship care at a wide diversity of sites, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H856A2A5735DD46918BB255EB014D3B2B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in urban, suburban, rural, and Tribal areas;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC347BF1A09C4441BB3DE384B1D79A4F9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in one or more territories of the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE13C8C73E9AA46A1BD4F839388EE7CBA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at cancer care sites including cancer centers, academic health centers, Federally qualified health centers, rural health clinics, physician offices, Tribal organizations, community-based health care providers, and health care providers serving medically underserved communities.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE397198FCB664838BF56850A4652F404"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Areas of focus under the demonstration program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The demonstration program under this section shall be designed to ensure the development of a variety of models for survivorship care that will permit evaluation of a variety of care strategies, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB6C8EB03AAAC47BF8B3467E872441530"><enum>(1)</enum><text>utilization of navigators to assist survivors in obtaining survivorship care;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEE811195357B459CBC4C494EF25B93DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>employment of risk-stratification to better determine the nature and intensity of services that survivors require;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD29323D7A49A405FA8C5797131544D47"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">transitions of care from cancer care providers to primary care providers, through transition-of-care models that involve collaboration between cancer care specialists and primary care providers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3AEFF9106C544AC68150645259754229"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the training needs of primary care providers to be better equipped to work with survivors in primary care settings;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE21B4081174A4027BBA6F28A98CFAAC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>utilization of survivorship care plans to facilitate coordination of survivorship care;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE02AEFA9A8AE47948B00687891090E5C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>experimentation with providing cancer survivorship care at home;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8B6614E5A564F3FA1F195FF594798C2"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use of information technology to plan and coordinate care to improve the consistent identification, collection, and measurement of all forms of patient experience data, including patient-reported outcomes of patient-reported symptoms and quality-of-life measures; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21576326A2FF46B4A47A87E7A7B62627"><enum>(8)</enum><text>expansion of existing successful models of survivorship care.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8057533E2EE24DCEA68FD1FB6367EFD4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation of demonstration program</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H6C43352B25014031B78223936FFBE480"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop a plan for evaluating the projects that are conducted as part of the demonstration program under this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6F162913C2F445FA9BA9281643EFFA1B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 18 months after the end of the 5-year demonstration program, complete such evaluation and submit a report to the Congress on the results of such evaluation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2EE9C67D807B4CF7915A780E87ED6881"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H879733BF2FCB4E5CB98BCE7D977B8BE0"><enum>9.</enum><header>Cancer survivor employment assistance program</header> 
<subsection id="H21208816B1344B688377C07A499FE589" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall carry out a program to award grants to nonprofit organizations and other entities to provide education and targeted assistance—</text> <paragraph id="H47041E4FFB3940D6AE2E1462AD2357C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to eligible cancer survivors facing barriers to employment, including those who remain in the workforce during treatment, those who reduce working hours while in treatment, and those who reenter the workforce after a treatment-related departure; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD5B345654D404518AB781AA9C6B77739"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the families and caregivers of such eligible cancer survivors.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5126F57D3AC446BCBF39447DBD4DA43A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program under this section shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6CEAF78A15924AAEBF553F1B003E5DFA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistance, career and training services, and supportive services for eligible cancer survivors who stay in the workforce during treatment, and for their families and caregivers, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HCCC8DE559ACB4449A376923F7C35684E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transportation assistance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFA6B256B835B46FCAA810A9B0930A9AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>childcare assistance;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFF237AD8DD3D4F15960A3E4C5D01FC9F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>nutritional assistance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00A95DFA04124FA2A87057B8C3DEEC0D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">physical activity assistance;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9286019BA2764C6F8A4B08BD69044C7C"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">psychosocial assistance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD95DDB2DB674DCA8ED4A2E3CBFA26C0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>financial assistance during a period of medical leave; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2660D35C84114A559AC5605406A1F039"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other similar assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE5A43A60E9E42B9B5DBA339D3AC0BD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistance and education for eligible cancer survivors who leave the workforce during treatment, and for their families and caregivers, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H53F799264F764BDEA89F96519CA54AF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">financial assistance during a period of medical leave;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9203A913CAEC40F5819B47285182B6AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assistance with premiums for continuation coverage provided pursuant to part 6 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1161">29 U.S.C. 1161 et seq.</external-xref>), title XXII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300bb-1">42 U.S.C. 300bb–1 et seq.</external-xref>), or <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4980B">section 4980B</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4980B">26 U.S.C. 4980B</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H84AD0C7191D044ECBCC2CFD7B35D64F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">career and training services, including upskilling and reskilling, for eligible cancer survivors who are not able to return to work after treatment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H978DEE2DBD74400EA97D06B16B76FA74"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistance, career and training services, and supportive services for eligible cancer survivors who are unable to work after a cancer diagnosis, and their families and caregivers, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H63F8E491F78F4B37AAF0E57D5D4EF284"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assistance in applying for—</text> 
<clause id="H7ACEED4EB25345FF92226EE8AE242993" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supplemental security income benefits under title XVI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1381">42 U.S.C. 1381 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause> <clause id="H66E14712C7D14158BC04D044EC2A2809"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disability insurance benefits under section 223 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/423">42 U.S.C. 423</external-xref>);</text></clause> 
<clause id="HED3457416CD943F88FE4EACE949AA5F0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">benefits under a State plan, or waiver of such plan, under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause> <clause id="H5ACC5E11FAC6477BA18E2B372771B752"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to minimizing delays in eligibility before a cancer survivor becomes eligible for Medicare coverage, benefits under the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1801">42 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), including with respect to enrolling in plans under part C or D of such title and supplemental plans under section 1882 of such title;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H85345BBA54384DF0BF04CFDCCF63B385"><enum>(v)</enum><text>State and private sector assistance programs for such cancer survivors; and</text></clause> <clause id="H69DFB1E5EC3D4B10BC2E2056B98570E7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">career and training services available under title I, II, or IV of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD39F19CC42E346FF8AF1AC8E4F492CE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the eligibility of a cancer survivor, and their families and caregivers, for benefits or services described in any of clauses (i) through (vi) of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H918F7811E6B5499A8C9AF2F791998FE4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Evidence-Based resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall use evidence-based resources, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2031932D849C47DD81D369BD3C446360"><enum>(1)</enum><text>nationally recognized evidence-based guidelines; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FFFA209DCF54D709301B39356DA51E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>other resources as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H893EC1C92ED242E3952124A3A390B5F4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HC2FB492078BF414BA8C445424BA02466"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible cancer survivor</term> means a cancer survivor (as defined in section 3) who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H562F15312A46413090996550FEEE7180"><enum>(A)</enum><text>remains in the workforce during cancer treatment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54B15506028E452E8A7B120B29AAC4BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduces working hours during cancer treatment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H59E284A48710417FA85A6B4B222EF308"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reenters the workforce after a cancer treatment-related departure; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34A9AB67D2EB45E5B875D7EEC534CFAD"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">leaves the workforce as the result of a cancer diagnosis or related complications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7A598D8F651247DC995FCEDDEBF1E989"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>supportive services</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HCAB9C73B2F9E4F8A98807C55502BA2F3"><enum>10.</enum><header>Comprehensive cancer survivorship program</header> <subsection id="H6B4CE07C51A5475FB66A07B9BEA8DD84"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a comprehensive cancer survivorship program that includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDEFF09A6716C46FF8DFF95B9155AB099"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a cancer survivorship resource center in accordance with subsection (b) to provide evidence-based resources to cancer survivors, their families, and their caregivers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B5CB43F8A9541E5A4249415907DD06D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a health care professional resource center in accordance with subsection (c) to assist and educate health care professionals in the delivery of high-quality survivorship care;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA75A33EB29894653BA3CB99B6DB51B2B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an educational campaign in accordance with subsection (d) to provide health care professionals with resources to improve cancer survivorship care; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BFC3B914B6F4750AE4CB6AAFBA0C4C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a program of supportive care services in accordance with subsection (e) to improve the quality of life and long-term survivorship of cancer survivors.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC7E576DC311D4C85811B3F382666E4BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cancer survivorship resource center</header> 
<paragraph id="HF565E51A3A7C4987A09DEC27FBA23935"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and operate a survivorship resource center (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Center</quote>) that serves as a comprehensive source of information and resources related to survivorship.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1DA13AB90A84D71A0CD643A087B80AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish and begin operation of the Center.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D095CCD25AC497DA447B4E54B0D9C78"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing and operating the Center, the Secretary shall consult with cancer survivors, patient organizations, health professionals, researchers, health education organizations, oncology professional societies and other medical societies, community-based organizations, and science education organizations regarding—</text> <subparagraph id="HD5AB77DE1F82429B9D9C7CEF07C7C2F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the information and resources that would assist cancer survivors in managing the survivorship experience and obtaining high-quality care across the continuum of care;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H10C8D8C7FFA3456ABEFAA71F2FCF1852"><enum>(B)</enum><text>gaps in such information and resources that need to be addressed to respond to the needs of cancer survivors; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA0394F4634B64C77B02327A80A7DA86B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">optimal strategies for ensuring that cancer survivors have access to the Center, including strategies that provide virtual options, online resources, and marketing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B852871F9E94813920D2D7888C480FD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of available evidence-based resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing and operating the Center, the Secretary shall, with permission and attribution, rely on and utilize the evidence-based materials and resources developed, collected, and distributed by cancer organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6485B2E1CB2E4BB0BB2664DDF386BFB2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Health care professional resource center</header> <paragraph id="H8E99D8D3521F4FE0BF1DE2231F884598"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish and operate a health care professional resource center (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Center</quote>) that serves as a comprehensive source of information and resources to assist health care professionals in the delivery of high-quality survivorship care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A2A4C611175458CAE2D909C23E82D96"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reference cancer survivorship guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing and operating the Center, the Secretary shall reference cancer survivorship guidelines developed by cancer care professional societies, patient organizations, research foundations, and other health care professional societies in the development of materials related to survivorship care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA697346A0BE14051B45C2161F0FEF596"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Support partnerships between cancer specialty societies and primary care provider organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing and operating the Center, the Secretary shall facilitate collaboration between cancer care specialty societies and primary care provider organizations in the development of standards for survivorship care, including standards for coordination of care and transitions of care from active treatment to long-term survivorship care.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB9CF17DA87614EA79EF86994C6DF6D83"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Campaign To educate survivors and health care professionals in survivorship care</header> 
<paragraph id="H6B6BD4D7D6F9459BB04301447AF7795B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H5D2804DA92814CFEBFC5C1EF51DB463B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expand educational programs and services to—</text> 
<clause id="HA443D32E6DA440FCB27154FC0917481B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>health care professionals; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD29A8C8255F94F71BE52494593986312"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>cancer survivors, their families, and caregivers; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C94AEB4284C40A98FDFB9867CF9506F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enhance the continuing medical education resources on cancer survivorship that are available to health care professionals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC79A1D5D5C9A40D5A1B4B224A5B9C65C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expand collaboration with Comprehensive Cancer Control National Partnership and other organizations for survivorship education and support</header> <subparagraph id="HD5F3FD1A6A834C8FA1F97573CD16B72D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall expand collaborations with organizations that are part of the Comprehensive Cancer Control National Partnership and other organizations to focus on increasing education and awareness related to cancer survivorship through materials, resources, and other methods as necessary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F6E637485FC490491CFCB5A335D2EB9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Collaborate with the organizations in the National Partnership and other organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall collaborate with the organizations that are part of the Comprehensive Cancer Control National Partnership and other organizations to inform cancer survivors of survivorship monitoring and follow-up standards, availability of survivorship care services, and how to access these services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDA41406CE3A546EE9CC82D34F07B8208"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reference the survivorship standards of care developed and published by cancer organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In collaboration with organizations that support the National Comprehensive Cancer Control Program, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<clause id="HF1B53D99E81A40FE8F653B8CBA144FFE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and implement a plan to distribute survivorship educational materials to ensure that such materials are accessible to all cancer survivors, their families and caregivers, and health care professionals; and</text></clause> <clause id="H003B0CBFF77740C08F1C20A41F42DEF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reference in such plan the survivorship standards of care developed and published by such organizations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H972C6A8BFAC84CB6B6178F47236AA17C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Continuing medical education</header> 
<subparagraph id="H717370BB0D0D46AAA53AB730629215E0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Development of programs</header> 
<clause id="H5C41E131CFF64A1A9136813D7623F235"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Grants and contracts</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a program of awarding grants and contracts to eligible entities to support the development of continuing medical education programs for survivorship care that utilize and rely on the guidelines for survivorship care developed and published by national organizations.</text></clause> <clause id="HAF97ED8B031F4937BE2EAE50AF562328"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall initiate the program required by clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H82CC7B5BA83C412E80F9E6F0F184C950"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grants for development of curriculum for survivorship continuing medical education</header> 
<clause id="H4E593D057CA24792A14B58D1713B3A66"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities for development of diverse, equitable, and culturally appropriate curricula for survivorship care curriculum for medical care.</text></clause> <clause id="HBF8E5A9DB07E4E32B1FFE20196C196D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Scope of curriculum</header><text>To receive a grant under this section, an applicant shall demonstrate its ability to develop survivorship care curriculum for medical care, taking into consideration services from the legal, social work, public health, behavioral sciences, genetic, epidemiology, and nursing fields.</text></clause> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H202D40EAE1C2490895BB453E22AA2600"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>eligible entity</term> includes a medical professional society, a patient organization, an academic institution, a cancer center, and any other entity with experience in continuing medical education for cancer professionals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F1CD214E4634ADEB47A8CE21D1A06F6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public awareness campaign</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, at an appropriate time after the availability of patient survivorship materials, professional survivorship materials, and continuing medical education programs under this subsection, shall initiate a linguistically and culturally appropriate public awareness campaign that targets the organization's catchment area to ensure that cancer survivors, their families and caregivers, health care professionals, and the public are aware of the scope of survivorship educational and informational resources available from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H573002A39F1743118FFBC31F426A208A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Cancer survivorship quality-of-Life program</header> 
<paragraph id="H5131CF9B6E9D485495ED59699AA7B816"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program of awarding grants to eligible entities to provide services to cancer survivors to enhance their quality of life and improve their long-term survival rates. Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall commence operating such program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29C7347E5926479AACE0BA047CB22275"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>eligible entity</term> includes an entity that is—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H434685DB1BC447378562CA0848C6AAD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State comprehensive cancer program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H51D4AB548A55474DBB384A5E0CCE682F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a National Cancer Institute-designated cancer center or centers; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF87613536C644F4CBBF940D9B231AE5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a community-based organization, including a patient advocacy organization, that—</text> <clause id="HD8B8F362DB2B4A88B543BBDE0DE4E0A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the capacity to reach cancer survivors through local, State, or national organizations; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H859BE969D81046378DCDFC6505974DB7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is focused on cancer survivors and strategies for meeting their needs related to their health and well-being.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63B6632FF379478FACC4333F828C5E5B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A grant received under this subsection shall be used to provide services to cancer survivors to enhance their quality of life and improve their long-term survival rates, such as by assisting survivors to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDE40425B9745400E9F66F25AF151308A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>engage in moderate physical activity and other health-promoting activities, including ceasing tobacco use and increasing consumption of healthy foods;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H834D3D6233364A8EB863B4A0F778C5DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increase access to services to mitigate anxiety, depression, and uncertainty;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7BC52D0480404FBF9411A1AD0DFEE5F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>utilize community support services to fully implement survivorship care plans;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H550CE96770344D0B9BAC5360CB872F91"><enum>(D)</enum><text>access nutrition education and counseling; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5CE70B9DF86D4EB6BED44BE5B94DBD68"><enum>(E)</enum><text>adhere to a schedule for, and access, screening for recurrence of cancer or the occurrence of other primary cancers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBAC25B351BB547BC99D20840F69FEE95"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Standards for application from eligible entities</header><text>To seek a grant under this subsection, an eligible entity shall submit an application, at such time as may be required by the Secretary, that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3DA3B88FDE474BD3888A2AAF559A37D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an explanation of how the entity will—</text> <clause id="H01082AD006A74C69B4D1B735C0B27F9C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide cancer survivors access to cancer patient navigator services;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB0B4A83ACBA34E899319F5EA3B5F1EE6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>overcome barriers to care for communities of color and multilingual communities;</text></clause> <clause id="H4B4E40AA179A4B2BBC3B1B4AF9A9F745"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provide culturally competent care; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9C4E19DCA9944836B10A12BE07BA4E44"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>work with and support caregivers of cancer survivors;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE9E2611C87CE4D5191AB965E2AF2D821"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of how the entity receives referrals of cancer survivors from health care professionals, including health care professionals serving historically disadvantaged and underserved communities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7BD2B82839E8492A9972C5F252365F14"><enum>(C)</enum><text>documentation of the curriculum that will be used for providers in the program, including mechanisms to update the staff on curriculum changes; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6538CF10BA8D4BEBA856DC53AD9B3FE1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an agreement to provide the Secretary semiannual reports on—</text> 
<clause id="HC0417B003522430EB1333F39C2CFEBD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of participants served;</text></clause> <clause id="H71259B879B2B467989A5A6EAA899AB3C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>quality-of-life measures for participants; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H01E953E4BEDC45589C5820F68F3C5C43"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>plans for fostering communication between oncology and non-oncology providers serving participants.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BB1A4A9BF934C33A68CAA7AE745B348"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Responsibilities of the Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9AF5213D2F28457F9447CD71685F755B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct outreach to inform health care professionals of the availability of programs and activities funded under this subsection;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2B17BA87D5D14F66A5DCF3EEB71C0AB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>analyze the data submitted by grantees under this subsection to determine the number of cancer survivors served and the impact of the program under this subsection on their quality of life; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC7266FE2112B48299D9D54787CE1C136"><enum>(C)</enum><text>share best practices among all grantees under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H0BBCDC0BC45E455395FCF21F13B55594"><enum>11.</enum><header>Adult cancer survivorship study</header> <subsection id="HE25941BE6E67454CA56D19FAAA35238A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall complete a landscape analysis that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD9BDD002D7CD40BBBACE74D5E196084A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assesses the potential benefits of an adult version of the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81DB4DB8BC4A46C49CC6B79CDF24AF48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assesses the financial costs and other burdens associated with an adult cancer survivor study;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEFBAA11460CF457DA8ABA2BD1E32A887"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identifies sources of data on adult cancer survivors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC53135FFAC44A6CB54A9A5D76C1FDB7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identifies gaps in data on adult cancer survivors, compared to data collected in the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06B7D93EE8474E81AF06C6F089D62136"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identifies strategies to publish data on adult cancer survivors derived from research that is conducted or supported by the National Cancer Institute, in a manner that is accessible to cancer survivors, health care professionals, researchers, and the public.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8D91F60281724C738A8A1A9D299DEC31"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of completion of the landscape analysis under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a report on the results of such landscape analysis.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9825AA2D821843279352207E29CB22A0"><enum>12.</enum><header>Survivorship progress report</header> 
<subsection id="HCB10D68FA17E4CAF99F615701862FB0B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Government Accountability Office to conduct a study of the progress made in cancer survivorship over the period beginning on the date of enactment of the National Cancer Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/92/216">Public Law 92–216</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4E8B9C8F79C04B7D86606A519524A4EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope of the study</header><text>The study under subsection (a) shall investigate developments over the period described in subsection (a) in—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8CA4F17F6AC842819B4C11E58F08A721"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the nature and quality of survivorship care;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9DCDD68CC35041A6AC4A2E913FD5AF95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>transitions from active treatment to survivorship care;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H00651BE3E44945E289A8BD562B2C097D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the quality of life of cancer survivors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDE7D7DE9DB84120983C2149BF148640"><enum>(4)</enum><text>outcomes for cancer survivors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF12E879AFB4240D0A256AD7776C586FE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>disparities in access to care and survivorship outcomes;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F19509EDFEF4416B5989DEBD99ED331"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the health care systems for providing survivorship care;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H180717E1D8D740D987D123932248DDEA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the contribution of community-based services to the survivorship care system; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBEE873EE14484CBD9AB7F9D8CE7B29A7"><enum>(8)</enum><text>payment for survivorship care by public and private third-party payors.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF751E9E035434E90B247AE95E29E10E9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Role of Office of Cancer Survivorship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H98DD7E01C1DC42F0B9145E3696DD9369"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider the contribution of the Office of Cancer Survivorship to the evolution of cancer survivorship care over the last 25 years; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE72F9E0E26794FDBBE1C709B77AF25CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assess the impact of the mission of the Office and the resources provided to the Office on its leadership in cancer survivorship care.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC2CB64E7E804406695971E7242F05119"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public meeting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Comptroller General of the United States shall hold a public meeting with a broad cross section of stakeholders to inform the study’s findings and conclusions. Such stakeholders shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC0F55112231248418D056173E2BF81DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cancer survivors and their caregivers and families;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H15154A1835224D4890B0EFC1709E01A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>patient organizations representing cancer survivors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD133B78215B448F692B8B1F812549513"><enum>(3)</enum><text>oncologists involved in survivorship care and the professional societies representing them;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDDBF0AB7D5CA4527A8FB6310D13B55CB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>primary care providers involved in survivorship care and the professional societies representing them;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64784E3517A545C4BBF5CBA9946032F6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>other health professionals providing survivorship care and the professional societies representing them;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D20DCC7B2044EE0BC93E207E2AD2A9A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>community-based organizations involved in survivorship care;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD4E66659E9844199AE1D666B9071D8D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>representatives of the National Cancer Institute;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C30837D2D4648DAA77CEC34951D354E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>third-party payors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H76537F1863364A618D8D56DB27555A7F"><enum>(9)</enum><text>researchers engaged in survivorship research;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H54AFEFC7392645A98E66552BF1F91794"><enum>(10)</enum><text>epidemiologists with knowledge of trends in cancer survivorship; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB36C403D873E4F9CA7CADC83F38F90B8"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other stakeholders as the Comptroller General deems important to participate in the public meeting.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2B9BB3F4AB2443D483C1AC44F0FF7311"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF0C3848D7C384F468883D9D2DFD5CB4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>release a report on the results of the study under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3FAE13B24534EA99D71E2432A9AEE14"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in addition to the public meeting convened under subsection (d)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H83EF2EB38972460B8926457BB92CE31A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>convene another public meeting to be held on the day of the release of the report; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA243F10C51547D2BF802471E9E7D179"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include in such meeting all categories of stakeholders listed in subsection (d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2DAE013E08E744DF92607F112B0AD3D7"><enum>13.</enum><header>Promoting State innovations to ease transitions to the primary care setting for children with cancer</header> 
<subsection id="H3B0676E0945C4A6DA121068EA05BF059"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Stakeholder group development of best practices; State Medicaid and CHIP program innovation</header> 
<paragraph id="H8FEF11AF7DB143C395977E6657CFF7F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Stakeholder group best practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall convene a stakeholder group of representatives of childhood cancer advocacy organizations, Medicaid and CHIP beneficiaries, providers with childhood cancer pediatric expertise, the National Association of Medicaid Directors, and other relevant representatives to develop best practices (and submit to the Secretary and Congress a report on such best practices) for States to ease the transition from active oncological care to primary care of children or adolescents with cancer, including best practices for ensuring development of and delivery of summary of care and survivorship care plans to patients, families, and primary care providers, and best practices for such transitions occurring under the State Medicaid plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) or State child health plan under title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>), as applicable. Such best practices shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H11B0E266B8544275AA98F3C981BF3DDD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">design of models of follow-up care, monitoring, and other survivorship programs (including peer support and mentoring programs);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H57823EFE417F485BB67172DCC14D4181"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">development of models for providing multidisciplinary care;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2E5BE6249AEB45FEB6388363048030A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">dissemination of information to health care providers about culturally and linguistically appropriate follow-up care for cancer survivors and their families, as appropriate and practicable; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73962357B41B41C98B0843C748D23D83"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">dissemination of the information and programs described in clauses (i) through (iii) to other health care providers (including primary care physicians and internists) and to cancer survivors and their families, where appropriate and in accordance with Federal and State law.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H1B6A825BC5D8462B82D7CDDCB8FC0913"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State Medicaid and CHIP program innovation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall work with States on innovative strategies, based on the best practices identified under the process described in subsection (a)(1), to ease the transition from active oncological care to primary care of child or adolescent with cancer ensuring development of and delivery of survivorship care plans to patients, families, and primary care providers and transition coverage under the State Medicaid plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) or State child health plan under title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>), as applicable.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34957961068D41909E7F606123C46C76"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nonapplication of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the stakeholder group convened under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H648FF8CCD0B94EBB858EA63105716FF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance on innovative service delivery systems demonstration project opportunities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date the stakeholder group is convened under subsection (a), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue guidance to State health officials, based on best practices developed under subsection (a)(1), regarding opportunities to improve care transitions for children and adolescents with cancer who transition from oncological care to primary care and who are otherwise eligible to receive medical assistance under title XIX of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) or title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7FA28DACA8E24991880C3A8C7204C0E7"><enum>14.</enum><header>Childhood cancer demonstration model and standard of care</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1115A(b)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H886A70B02DC646059118DBD4DA8075CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, and shall include the model described in clause (xxviii) of such subparagraph.</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD49361E78EC64B93B8E283298B9F7342"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0C6F284AA27C401B98E50195E90444DB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H2C8CD90CB1C24F61BF889A207032650E"><enum>(xxviii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local service delivery and State payment model for individuals up to age 21 enrolled under a State plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XIX or a State child health plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>) who have been diagnosed with cancer and who are in the survivorship phase of their treatment. Such model shall—</text> 
<subclause id="HEA05E5240092445EB63A76BE3F048914"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for the creation of a survivorship plan, that can be integrated into an electronic health record, for such individuals and disseminate the plan to such individuals, families of such individuals, and the health providers of such individuals;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4AA08914355F4125A38B470B699195C2"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer States and local providers technical assistance to develop and implement different survivorship care planning services;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4BAD22D9AA064DDC9046271AC4699CAC"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a standard of care based on the Children’s Oncology Group (COG) Long-Term Follow-Up Guidelines for Survivors of Childhood, Adolescent, and Young Adult Cancers to manage the transition of such individuals from active treatment to general care with the informed knowledge of such individuals; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HCCF8AE0D133846BDAF42557547BF7B94"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide incentives to health care providers for treating such individuals through such model that includes at least two survivorship care planning visits.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H0F57FA21B0084C258AB83F6D729BC709"><enum>15.</enum><header>Medicaid coverage of cancer fertility services for cancer survivors</header> 
<subsection id="H9AA90A4CDB39439BBE5747C270C658E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicaid</header> 
<paragraph id="H7B7F8DCA0893434BBFC8214093AECCA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mandatory coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(a)(10) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HA8AC41FA5998415884EB9852C4CB0E01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD2370500B52485984B0436F6B6DD465"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagrah (G), by adding at the end <quote>and</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEE7797A16254DCEAFD5ACE5C5C1E3D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (G) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDBF84755EB5F4C04AECC4ACE9DAAD3F8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HA9E5DBA802CD42ACA4C26C29C4BBAFD3"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notwithstanding section 1902(a)(10)(B) (relating to comparability), for making medical assistance available for cancer fertility services (as defined in subsection (jj));</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD167544EEDBB4067AB7F18E9DFB6BFCA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H798BC4CFB7F4429E8698E4C2C302AC12" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H31EDFB37AA1A4C06A28596161A78D8C5"><enum>(jj)</enum><header>Cancer fertility services</header> 
<paragraph id="HFFA2EB473EBC4552B32EE0B99F19FE18"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of section 1902(a)(10)(H) and this subsection, the term <quote>cancer fertility services</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="HF9D0B34D2F31492B8266D6A83DEA5919"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means fertility treatment and fertility preservation services for individuals diagnosed with cancer who—</text> 
<clause id="H7254242B193F4C5E91AA72D385D1611C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are undergoing treatment for such cancer where such treatment may lead to iatrogenic infertility;</text></clause> <clause id="H59334D0505454352A34E79E26A4AA28F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>previously underwent such treatment and may be at risk of such infertility due to such treatment; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H622FEEBB2D484C81B131B42B8BAF005C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>are preparing to undergo such treatment where such treatment may lead to such infertility; and</text></clause> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0DC8B95AAC9B4B538F8BDDA9F6FC54BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text> 
<clause id="HB3CA40F3A8AC45C5A8C8920EDFA1C93A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other services, including experimental and non-experimental services to preserve fertility or treat infertility (as determined by the Secretary, consistent with established medical practices and professional guidelines published by the American Society for Reproductive Medicine, the American Society of Clinical Oncology, or other professional medical organizations specified by the Secretary); and</text></clause> <clause id="HF8917069F02A4480B0111375FC33C073"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>long-term storage costs—</text> 
<subclause id="H574AD6296B354F598E90145DA0A6463E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with respect to individuals under the age of 18, for a period of not less than 15 years; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2DDEE874050D4C469C8934ABFFBEC53D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to individuals age 18 or older, for a period of not less than 10 years.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF49AA06E8CB64E02AEF47ED80CEA3306"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception for territories</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, in the case of a State (other than the 50 States and the District of Columbia), the requirement stated in section 1902(a)(10)(H) shall be optional.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E0C0C95C69B40EA83208327F0FC3355"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition on cost-sharing</header> <subparagraph id="H47A90A6E062D415C8C88C3708B42327D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1916 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o">42 U.S.C. 1396o</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H0F500D09799F4EF7911BAC2983B5A9DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)—</text> <subclause id="H9D905C90C8C345C697791F3E743265D7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking at the end <quote>, or</quote> and inserting a semicolon; </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H232559ECAD3A45EABBC5A082F42781A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking at the end <quote>; and</quote> and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9E99C2EC9FB14C958C88E02C3103C051"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA488262535054D808F507DA9753317D5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H3292B2E4BAFA407894C22DF7EAD41319"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cancer fertility services (as defined in section 1905(jj)); and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause> <clause id="HFACCB1AF15774C4C8CA37F689DB0016A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text> 
<subclause id="HAB65346068424D83B9808AD221C80C50"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking at the end <quote>, or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB2AC8DE47990436ABBF7055715E61325"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking at the end <quote>; and</quote> and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1996F5E801354F86959F476A84875F37"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD9D7988A71424BADA52C6330D09D322E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HAE8B0D1DA33C4E77A3F05C94EE1AE4C6"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cancer fertility services (as defined in section 1905(jj)); and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD20776F35AFB4CF4A3BE42566F01C8A3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application to alternative cost-sharing</header><text>Section 1916A(b)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o-1">42 U.S.C. 1396o–1(b)(3)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2B14E61A56F54ED6A3B9CE7599655830" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H0E23F5794B914EF8A5D7B0FADCB071D2"><enum>(xv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cancer fertility services (as defined in section 1905(jj)).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H40BCE57ADC5D41418D67E783EA08490E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>CHIP</header> 
<paragraph id="HC0713D05ED654E7CA8EAE76E8D7B1A73"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2103(c) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397cc">42 U.S.C. 1397cc(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H3A7BF0D9E7D5439E9A2ED00FB195C4A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating the paragraph (12) added by section 11405(b)(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> as paragraph (13); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HABB8CB0E311244D29DFFD17EEFAA758A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (11) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE46052062BFB4646BE652BD245BE43F4" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H343F787A0E8C48C49A71A6C1ACE5DA38"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Required coverage of cancer fertility services for cancer survivors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Regardless of the type of coverage elected by a State under subsection (a), the child health assistance provided for a targeted low-income child, and, in the case of a State that elects to provide pregnancy-related assistance pursuant to section 2112, the pregnancy-related assistance provided for a targeted low-income pregnant woman (as such terms are defined for purposes of such section), shall include coverage of cancer fertility services (as described in section 1905(jj)). </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC206B458EC5744ECB0AEF0E1A5314AA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on cost-sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2103(e)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397cc">42 U.S.C. 1397cc(e)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HED6E034AB3C849AE90B02834E644A1AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">cancer fertility services,</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">covid–19 treatment,</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H991FFE5DBBF54D1BAD143B4BE516318F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>cancer fertility services (as described in section 1905(jj)),</quote> after <quote>testing or treatments described in section 1916(a)(2)(I) furnished during the period described in such section,</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9526969C1B704AA28301367568C9FA9F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by paragraph (1)(A) shall take effect on October 1, 2023.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H39F1335C71D9454190A97D84578D3F0B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section (other than the amendment made by subsection (b)(1)(A)) shall apply with respect to medical assistance, child health assistance, and pregnancy-related assistance furnished on or after the date that is 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

