<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H31A87781A2AB441DAD8AE5FC6E190ABD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4840 IH: Uyghur Forced Labor Disclosure Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4840</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230724">July 24, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000197">Ms. Pelosi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to require issuers to make certain disclosures relating to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HD27085590D494A5BAE021E01F3D9481C" style="OLC">
<section id="H6F1BB080552640ED851AC826A8FCC094" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Uyghur Forced Labor Disclosure Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5736B99CCFFB4D61A837E20631614F5E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certification of certain activities relating to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region as procedure for registration of securities on an exchange</header> <subsection id="H7CBFFEFE487F4E21AB3F090FCF1D35CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 12 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78l">15 U.S.C. 78l</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCAD6537A58694830ADDA4D2BC828E017" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H0C64703E8E0C47FEA23A93F609002FA7"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Reporting of certain activities relating to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region</header>
<paragraph id="HFE3B1E4C70D54BCEAAB91A673A178E14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of the 180-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this subsection, the Commission shall issue rules—</text> <subparagraph id="H005E3CE0C9144A4198C86F8873A1F36C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to require an issuer filing an application to register a security with a national securities exchange to—</text>
<clause id="H0B6FCC6CE01340DD9734A0FB368A80C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include in such application the documentation described under paragraph (2); and</text></clause> <clause id="H9DEF8AECC67245A89580D3D4E3E683ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to file the application and documentation with the Commission;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H103F79DF783548218CE6897D44E3CEA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to require an issuer to file a report with the Commission containing the documentation described under paragraph (2) if the issuer is not listed on an exchange and merges with another issuer that is listed on the exchange; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83C3BF78F1FB4BB08AA36CB4270D355E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to require an issuer filing a registration statement under subsection (g) to include with such statement the documentation described under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAABFD15407B14F0E92D9BABFEACD2E00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Documentation required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to an issuer, the documentation described under this paragraph is documentation showing whether the issuer or any affiliate of the issuer, directly or indirectly, contains within its supply or production chain—</text> <subparagraph id="H8A1BCD91318B4B6989A6ACB4CC3FA60A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">goods, wares, articles, or merchandise sourced from or through the XUAR, or mined, produced, or manufactured wholly or in part by forced labor identified by mandate of section 2(d)(2)(B)(iv) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref>, including—</text>
<clause id="H7A2E3E05A5724C5BBBF241E7FE901348"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the industries contained on the <quote>Illustrative List of Industries in Xinjiang in which Public Reporting has indicated Labor Abuses may be Taking Place</quote> in Annex 2 of the <quote>Xinjiang Supply Chain Business Advisory</quote> (published July 13, 2021) and any successor list; and</text></clause> <clause id="HAB818FAFAF934C818D3716A3A2873FE0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>all products listed within <quote>high-priority sectors for enforcement</quote> by the Forced Labor Enforcement Task Force pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref>; or</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6BE04848ECD844A0A0579B8B870D678A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">goods, wares, articles, or merchandise that are mined, produced, or manufactured by an entity engaged in labor transfers from the XUAR or forced labor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5319C93B7F344068AA84429122830CA1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transparent documentation of supply chain links</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In issuing rules under paragraph (1), the Commission shall require an issuer to list the name (in English and in the most commonly-spoken language of the country in which the issuer is incorporated, if other than English), address, and sourcing quantities from each smelter, refinery, farm, or manufacturing facility (as appropriate) of each person mining, producing, or manufacturing a good, ware, article, or merchandise described under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD809D28CBDA645ECAE706CE53DF151C8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Independent verification of documentation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In issuing rules under paragraph (1), the Commission shall require an issuer—</text> <subparagraph id="HA23C44BAFDEF40A6AE3EF434128A81E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to obtain independent verification of the documentation described under paragraph (2), by a third-party auditor approved by the Commission, before the filing of an application, report, or registration statement containing such documentation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H00D42732E6C14B038B2A0F6AE9A367B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to maintain the confidentiality of the identity of such third-party auditor, unless the auditor proactively waives confidentiality; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42802895C63547A189471B99805F6793"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to establish policies to respond to any reprisals against the third-party auditor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA7C7B19BE31C41B99546799830D455D8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public availability of documentation</header><text>The Commission shall make all documentation received under this subsection available to the public.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97041C90DC2E48C28A0EE2BA548B287D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Additional penalties for certain violations</header><text>In addition to other penalties provided under this Act, with respect to an application described under paragraph (1)(A), if an issuer fails to comply with the requirements of this subsection (including any misrepresentation of the information described under paragraph (3))—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7302CABBDF3C48E0A20B6497D54F9ABF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicable national securities exchange may not approve such application; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3B1F71353A5C409BA644E087DEC58F17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the issuer may not re-file the application for 1 year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7B1976E6505D4149BEFDD6391EB3B1EA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H0A2DBB068FFB4D90AD046B0CF3206673"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Forced labor</header><text>The term <term>forced labor</term> means—</text>
<clause id="H08C1E805BED54711BE8505B117D39713"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any labor carried out by the Uyghur, Kazakh, Kyrgyz, or another oppressed ethnic group in the People’s Republic of China under any State-sponsored labor program, including any program associated with <quote>surplus labor transfer</quote>, <quote>poverty alleviation</quote>, <quote>mutual aid</quote>, <quote>Xinjiang Aid</quote>, and re-education programs targeting minoritized citizens of the XUAR, whether inside or outside;</text></clause> <clause id="HBF855597A22C4C8EADF43FE289B41119" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any labor carried out in the XUAR unless the specific labor has been identified by the United States authorities under existing forced labor and the Uyghur protection laws as not involving the use of forced labor; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H7572E3625CD345AC825DB26ED04FEA82"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any use of convict labor, forced labor, or indentured labor described under section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2821167A001A4FA2BC73C3C7379D32B5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>XUAR</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>XUAR</term> means the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H484C7A0C43284C69B31DD25928441E94"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall be repealed on the earlier of—</text> <paragraph id="HFB3C186238B3441E89C10FF1D66F2C58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 8 years after the date of the enactment of this section; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1EAE4EE4915A4762ABF126188A976C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the President submits to Congress (including the Office of the Law Revision Council) a determination that the Government of the People’s Republic of China has ended mass internment, forced labor, and any other gross violations of human rights experienced by Uyghurs, Kazakhs, Kyrgyz, and members of other persecuted groups in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H711B498CB0B546F79FD629893B9B9D86"><enum>3.</enum><header>Disclosure of certain activities relating to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region</header> <subsection id="H34622BCAE86143209CFB851FD34A3DF2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H56A621290914408CAC7F3F8854E95D22" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H8EE2A17D3D10460A95D777EA66A12F01"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Disclosure of certain activities relating to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region</header>
<paragraph id="HD057731D94CD4A49896637C19B79AB66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the end of the 180-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this subsection, the Commission shall issue rules to require each issuer required to file an annual report under this section or section 15(d) or a proxy statement under section 14 to disclose in each such report or proxy statement whether, during the period covered by the report or proxy statement—</text> <subparagraph id="H2E3F5753A78B4C078E5FAEA7FEC0FC88"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the issuer or any affiliate of the issuer, directly or indirectly, engaged with an entity or the affiliate of an entity to use or source goods, wares, articles, or merchandise sourced from or through the XUAR, or mined, produced, or manufactured wholly or in part by forced labor identified by mandate of section 2(d)(2)(B)(iv) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref>, including—</text>
<clause id="HF5E5CC36E61B4E279C66C67AF8A03C75"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the industries contained on the <quote>Illustrative List of Industries in Xinjiang in which Public Reporting has indicated Labor Abuses may be Taking Place</quote> in Annex 2 of the <quote>Xinjiang Supply Chain Business Advisory</quote> (published July 13, 2021) and any successor list;</text></clause> <clause id="H7744E0AF8F0D42CE9315B7BFC68D3536"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>all products listed as <quote>high-priority sectors for enforcement</quote> by the Forced Labor Enforcement Task Force pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H992AB44A5A2C40E0B7079C41D1A86987"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>all products exported from the People’s Republic of China into the United States that are listed by mandate of section 2(d)(2)(B)(iv) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref> that are sourced from or through the XUAR; or</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6441712960A4B6890B02E76EA92A71C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any goods, wares, articles, or merchandise described under subparagraph (A), whether the goods, wares, articles, or merchandise have supply chain links to facilities that employ forced labor;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4B3876C0895743CEB2EBCF4A1FF120CF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to each good, ware, article, and merchandise described under subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="HC444F1A9088A42C9B7051FBDF4AC9341"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the nature and extent of the commercial activity related to the good, ware, article, or merchandise;</text></clause>
<clause id="HBCC3EAB9551449BC975CFB6662AA2F98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the gross revenue and net profits, if any, attributable to the good, ware, article, or merchandise;</text></clause> <clause id="H54F986A21014471FBF8F7A1AD8C26816"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alternative sourcing options for the good, ware, article, or merchandise, while protecting proprietary information of the issuer and any other cited business;</text></clause>
<clause id="HE3BEDEF010814056BE940E6F0E2C2AB4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the measures taken by the issuer to exercise due diligence on the source and chain of custody of the good, ware, article, or merchandise; and</text></clause> <clause id="H095AFC7E71E249B2A216595B11287583"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other entities and facilities affiliated with the facility employing forced labor, including the physical location of such facilities and of the supplier entity’s headquarters; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFADD97D302DE4780B2B213A602A9CE5B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the issuer or any affiliate of the issuer, directly or indirectly, was involved in the development or provision of surveillance goods, services, or technologies (including telecommunications, information security, and sensors) used to facilitate gross human rights abuses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2968EACEBF4542749809D9107B2671A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of information</header><text>The Commission shall make all information disclosed pursuant to this subsection available to the public on the website of the Commission.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H740AB72D472143069F6B17DFD45F8C15"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <quote>forced labor</quote> and <quote>XUAR</quote> have the meaning given those terms, respectively, under section 12(m)(8).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H8AE1CBB52E4C447396DB4A3E316ACA5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall be repealed on the earlier of—</text>
<paragraph id="HE0E301BF21304FD695D8F9AAE50B3097"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 8 years after the date of the enactment of this section; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1EEEBB50D22349E5AB75178AC4F46257"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the President submits to Congress (including the Office of the Law Revision Council) a determination that the Government of the People’s Republic of China has ended mass internment, forced labor, and any other gross violations of human rights experienced by Uyghurs, Kazakhs, Kyrgyz, and members of other persecuted groups in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HA1B0361B848542EF8158ED01D5276B3D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports</header>
<subsection id="HC5991C6CC72C4891B9A530EDFE642ABA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Securities and Exchange Commission annual report to Congress</header><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission shall—</text> <paragraph id="H75429FFF53B74D86AE12DF4290FC47B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct an annual assessment of the compliance of issuers with the requirements of section 12(m) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H251B914B869046F686B427574AE42107"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issuers described under paragraph (1)(A) of such section 12(m);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H904167F2DA2D456A9F3DB4FD2C4D7BE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issuers described under paragraph (1)(B) of such section 12(m); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H65CBFC2560214F118307BEB35EC03B39"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issuers described under paragraph (1)(C) of such section 12(m);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2353C3FCE8504206A3184A07A596469E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct an annual assessment of the compliance of issuers with the requirements of section 13(t) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC441844DBBB24A7B96C34DCC9DFC6D09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>issue a report to Congress containing the results of the assessments under paragraph (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD94B124EBFAB49DC9D1FFAFBB9F3BFB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall periodically evaluate and report to Congress on the effectiveness of the oversight by the Commission of the certification requirements under section 12(m) and section 13(t) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934.</text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


