<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C06178F04AE471FBDA386A06695CD66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5863 IH: Federal Disaster Tax Relief Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5863</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide tax relief with respect to certain Federal disasters.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H64FC3DAED8444963ACA5946CE7518270" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9DB3EC1A14CB40F890FCA6ABE2C18CAE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Disaster Tax Relief Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H333B1EBB71BD43D1A03EFC1D427DA3D4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension of rules for treatment of certain disaster-related personal casualty losses</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of applying section 304(b) of the Taxpayer Certainty and Disaster Tax Relief Act of 2020, section 301 of such Act shall be applied by substituting <quote>the Federal Disaster Tax Relief Act of 2023</quote> for <quote>this Act</quote> each place it appears. </text></section> 
<section id="HCABAE7CF551F4D66ADDB4D4E5F68FCA0" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Exclusion from gross income for compensation for losses or damages resulting from certain wildfires</header> 
<subsection id="HA0872151F38F4A7D95630C97A60C1E3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, gross income shall not include any amount received by an individual as a qualified wildfire relief payment.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1FFD25D36BDD4288A07F05FF4F0A6731"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified wildfire relief payment</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAE732ECA1569433C9568099E09015530"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified wildfire relief payment</quote> means any amount received by or on behalf of an individual as compensation for expenses or losses incurred as a result of a qualified wildfire disaster, but only to the extent any expense or loss compensated by such payment is not compensated for by insurance or otherwise.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29C54868E4E64F979934E16732BB1213"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified wildfire disaster</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>qualified wildfire disaster</quote> means any federally declared disaster (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/165">section 165(i)(5)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) declared, after December 31, 2014, as a result any forest or range fire.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAC749C5460654A449218EE6561EDACDC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Denial of double benefit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986—</text> <paragraph id="HB63625FC706C4B1082F959CF3365B525"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no deduction or credit shall be allowed (to the person for whose benefit a qualified wildfire relief payment is made) for, or by reason of, any expenditure to the extent of the amount excluded under this section with respect to such expenditure, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5159CB6A7C17409C86A0CB052D3E11F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no increase in the basis or adjusted basis of any property shall result from any amount excluded under this subsection with respect to such property.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3CCB07813E3942E88F39716BE0520236"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on application</header><text>This section shall only apply to qualified wildfire relief payments received by the individual during taxable years beginning after December 31, 2019, and before January 1, 2026.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H894BAAA55F9745FE8B0DD780BABA17A4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>East Palestine disaster relief payments</header> 
<subsection id="H3398D6233E8F441684ED2E28FC50DF3B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Disaster relief payments to victims of East Palestine train derailment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">East Palestine train derailment payments shall be treated as qualified disaster relief payments for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/139">section 139(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE80AA601B3F04FB589320CC9B2E60DD7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>East Palestine trail derailment payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>East Palestine train derailment payment</quote> means any amount received by or on behalf of an individual as compensation for loss, damages, expenses, loss in real property value, closing costs with respect to real property (including realtor commissions), or inconvenience (including access to real property) resulting from the East Palestine train derailment if such amount was provided by—</text> 
<paragraph id="H725930AE99DF4ED8ABAB55D0F33CEA00" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a Federal, State, or local government agency,</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE4382E78E6644241857C09CE2BC4FE53"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Norfolk Southern Railway, or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H065E0CBBA9334BB3A58FB6FD2703A175"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any subsidiary, insurer, or agent of Norfolk Southern Railway or any related person.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8AF8A09D017F4048B0C39188A019C2D5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Train derailment</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>East Palestine train derailment</quote> means the derailment of a train in East Palestine, Ohio, on February 3, 2023.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H68C93E9A25664CD4A576A59CF3A22D81"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This subsection shall apply to amounts received on or after February 3, 2023.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

