<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H88E317D344B84CC288E8FAF133DE153D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5719 IH: Black Panther Party National Historical Park Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5719</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Black Panther Party National Historical Park in the State of California, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H39517E5A77D44A5A8C58AF3F21706578" style="OLC"><section id="H759B9FB6206944D393382BDEB27B253C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Black Panther Party National Historical Park Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H550FCED2E1E14D44A3696AF9C2413751"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H7FFD0C51893942DD8DFB28355293E5F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Black Panther Party was an integral part of the civil rights movement and its history and influence is nationally significant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEBD054767344295A529211D351854C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States government has not provided a publicly accessible space to learn about the history of the Black Panther Party and their contributions to social progress nationwide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35112FAD91D4493288AE1434ACF1CFA4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>National Park Service has the opportunity to engage with a large new audience and tell a more holistic history of the United States by interpreting the histories of people of color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDF484FD185243A5859231D104E574E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Black Panther Party, originally called the Black Panther Party for Self-Defense, was established in Oakland, California in 1966 by Huey P. Newton (Minister of Defense from 1966–1981) and Bobby Seale (Chairman of the Black Panther Party from 1966–1974), who met at Merritt College in Oakland. Oakland, California, was the home of the Black Panther Party, which came to include more than forty chapters around the United States and numerous others elsewhere in the world.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32ED4CDA8BD0448AAF7879E8F799E10C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Black Panther Party was founded in Oakland, California, to address systemic poverty and protect the Black community from police brutality. Although they intended on being a local organization, communities across the country were empowered by their message and services, leading to the establishment of over 40 chapters across the United States and many multi-racial and class coalitions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF80C0001790145DCAC02762D06CCC0F0"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">DeFremery Park is perhaps Oakland’s best known site for many of the Black Panther Party’s free community programs, political demonstrations, rallies, and fundraisers. Panthers and community members continue to hold a myriad of programs and direct services at DeFremery Park to commemorate this legacy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B154ED8DD3245ED9E786DE45358931F"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1973, the Black Panther Party established the Oakland Community School, an elementary school that took a holistic approach to education, centered around Black history, encouraged civic participation, fed students, and performed health screenings. California is now in the process of establishing <quote>community schools</quote> statewide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C8ED8332E6046C888F7CF4457E63072"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Starting in 1968, the Black Panther Party established dozens of free medical clinics across the United States. Then through those clinics, in 1970 the Black Panther Party launched the first nationwide sickle cell anemia testing program, which directly influenced Congress’ decision to pass the National Sickle Cell Anemia Control Act of 1972.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F0015DC41946F89A69E70DD050296B"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In January 1969, the Black Panther Party created the first <quote>Free Breakfast for School Children Program</quote> in the Nation, eventually feeding hundreds of thousands of children across the United States and becoming a model for today’s Federal school breakfast program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H104CEEC826544748BDE61F6C16507DCB"><enum>(10)</enum><text>David Hilliard and Fredrika Newton established the Dr. Huey P. Newton Foundation to educate both the local community and visitors from around the world on the history and principles of the Black Panther Party and its co-founder Dr. Huey P. Newton.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF732E25DB226491B8B6535E887547579"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The cities of Oakland, Berkeley, and Richmond unanimously adopted resolutions urging the National Park Service to conduct a reconnaissance survey to determine the appropriateness of a National Park Service unit to recognize the historical significance and contributions of the Black Panther Party. The resolutions also urge President Biden to use the results of the survey to establish a National Park unit including a Visitors Center and Museum through the Antiquities Act. These are the first 3 cities in the United States to adopt such resolutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFE2B9E26CA84CB0B923F3DBD9414442"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 17, 2021, Ninth Street at the intersection of Mandela Parkway in Oakland, California, was renamed after the Black Panther Party co-founder: Dr. Huey P. Newton Way.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67A68B5C776749C2A2C8273C21CB865F"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On March 4, 2021, Congresswoman Barbara Lee requested the National Park Service launch a reconnaissance survey in regard to the Black Panther Party, especially with regard to the sites in and around Oakland, California, that would be suitable for National Historical Park designation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2804691E6F2C437EB7AE82724176C61B"><enum>(14)</enum><text>On January 10, 2022, the bust of Dr. Huey P. Newton was unveiled at Dr. Huey P. Newton Way and Mandela Parkway, near the spot where Newton was murdered in 1989.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H003B57D6E14445E39AB47FA2FE79E030"><enum>(15)</enum><text>On July 19, 2022, Oakland City Council unanimously approved the Dr. Huey P. Newton Foundation to enter into a lease agreement with the City Administrator to establish the Black Panther Party Museum.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7CE9FD288D544019BA8CDBF4C86F9D31"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of the National Historical Park are—</text><paragraph id="HEC227951B2AC4889A608A0CCFA640FB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to preserve and protect for the benefit of present and future generations the nationally significant historic resources associated with the Black Panther Party;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3824CEEF877A4A718F16E7058BAC7D5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to improve public understanding of the legacy of the Black Panther Party through interpretation of the historic resources associated with the Black Panther Party; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1E948B370244F28836B65F571BE787F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to enhance public access to preserve and protect the historically significant resources associated with the Black Panther Party.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5A04EC2EC2424D51B3CE37734A053FFB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H20820EA0E71A4813AE9130CF05232574"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National historical park</header><text>The term <term>National Historical Park</term> means the Black Panther Party National Historical Park established by section 5(a)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFCC65924E754C72BF91AA258287135C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>Map</term> means the map entitled ____, numbered __, and dated ____.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F4E5D9703D44AF781A66A1CF1DB407E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Director of the National Park Service.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HEF0FCC348876432DBCD471AA07CCC0AB"><enum>5.</enum><header>Establishment of the Black Panther Party National Historical Park</header><subsection id="HA6EC961596BC4E389D2B15A0783CCB8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="HF5B3C8AE9D7441A2B73BB9EE1437C313"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), there is established the Black Panther Party National Historical Park in the State of California, as a unit of the National Park System, to preserve and educate the history and impact of the Black Panther Party and the nationally significant role it played in the history of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA066FF2D5B7A4B4D82524C2FDAD81C0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The National Historical Park shall not be established until the date on which the Secretary acquires sufficient land within the boundaries of the National Historical Park to constitute a manageable unit.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1264DFC7A27546EFBAC52D99B02C5E92"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Boundaries</header><text>The boundaries of the National Historical Park shall be the boundaries generally depicted on the Map.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA42BBC8698D143BDAF27B3CF3E30590E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text>The Map shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service.</text></subsection><subsection id="H488A1C1B3CBD4B29B0922AA7896E9A9E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may include in the National Historical Park boundary any resources that are the subject of an agreement under subsection (g).</text></subsection><subsection id="H429731455BE445B18A154F250785EA45"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Boundary adjustment</header><text>On the acquisition of additional land or interests in land or on entering an agreement under subsection (g), the boundary of the National Historical Park shall be adjusted to reflect the acquisition or agreement by publishing a National Historical Park boundary map in the Federal Register. The map shall be available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCE38BE89CA0C46B3AD04A78227461DCE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Land acquisition</header><text>The Secretary may acquire any land or interest in land located within the boundary of the National Historical Park, by—</text><paragraph id="HBE841C4BEA2648528E13D88AE80F286E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>donation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD860449A72647DE9AADEC3C95E8FEA0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase with donated or appropriated funds; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D04B5FEEC014401948D53B2EE24D83B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exchange.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB7E83B1C9460492DBB88E355E75782D3"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header><paragraph id="HF088A553F16A48A1972509A874C3C4E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may enter into a cooperative agreement with the city of Oakland, the State of California, political subdivisions of the State of California, institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations (such as the Huey P. Newton Foundation), and individuals for the purposes of carrying out this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF45073A59789461FA2A4F725CD6278D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost-sharing requirement</header><subparagraph id="HD9DEBA2329E64BF1AA209DD4F8399DD6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the total cost of any activity carried out under a cooperative agreement entered into under paragraph (1) shall be not more than 50 percent.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8E1F976E00F4E71A70E2FBC7F0C1F8B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form of non-Federal share</header><text>The non-Federal share may be in the form of in-kind contributions or goods or services fairly valued.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H943D2856ACC446D4AB5DD39FF45F32EF"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Related sites</header><text>The Secretary may provide technical assistance, visitor services, interpretive tours, and educational programs to sites and resources associated with the purposes for which the National Historical Park is established.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA7CEA8DAC8243E795BC55728B02AEB2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="H5BABB376C8CA4A9DB22D26CCC10F4EA2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall administer the National Historical Park in accordance with—</text><subparagraph id="H9B270387D90C4F34A19579B878EBB40B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A2341C299F04D86ABBE50D1AF0E1E98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the laws generally applicable to units of the National Park System.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C2940AA578A4EF194C67C3AF3648C19"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management plan</header><subparagraph id="H0EF90D13460B473199FCC013F0CBBDFD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Deadline for completion</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date on which funds are made available to carry out this subsection, the Secretary shall prepare a general management plan for the National Historical Park—</text><clause id="H22BAC330302F4F0E9439414E7DC17B01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in consultation with the States and other interested parties; and</text></clause><clause id="HEDFB2AD27C14481EB940F8B048AEC16A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in accordance with section 100502 of title 54, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE32EC79D680B495F899B793B2095D5AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Submission to congress</header><text>On completion of the general management plan under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall submit that general management plan to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

