<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9E653915F5734BDFBB96C1B60898A76C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2616 IH: Stop the Import of Fentanyl Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2616</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a National Center to Stop the Import of Illicit Synthetic Drugs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE9C9B210E5CC43A8969626112CC5F728" style="OLC"><section id="HC85C8E13BAA64EDD8B4C4EACC863F3FA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop the Import of Fentanyl Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2A977000C4AD4437B5A8B9BD8590A251"><enum/><header>National Center to Stop the Import of Illicit Synthetic Drugs</header><subsection id="H9809159FB70F40B09B2E46C502549B0C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is within the Drug Enforcement Administration a National Center to Stop the Import of Illicit Synthetic Drugs (hereinafter referred to as the <quote>National Center</quote>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H45C8505B6FA64EBCB108AFD6564D8EB5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director of National Center To Stop the Import of Illicit Synthetic Drugs</header><paragraph id="H8A2D01E62A194AC39365CB14432246F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is a Director of the National Center, who shall be the head of the National Center, and who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66D9D98ED9294F9D85D3772F5C1CCD1E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No simultaneous appointment</header><text>The Director of the National Center may not simultaneously serve in any other capacity in the executive branch. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8458DE64B9154AD0815F3772448164C0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report and briefing required</header><paragraph id="H11A38F10D3FB4BA1A65090EB4E261C1C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 90 days after date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Director of the National Center shall submit to the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration a report including—</text><subparagraph id="H3FEA73B0DA564052B3ADB01BF337C256"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an overview of how synthetic drugs come into the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H741C92FA5AD84BC1BFB65142D8E7E470"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a strategic plan of action on each of its primary missions under subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CADC0DBBD47447E937849A17D20CDEA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identification of necessary resources from agencies and Congress to accomplish the primary missions under subsection (d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77C06877B5CB44CA8893B8810FE0C5AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Brief required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Director of the National Center shall provide a brief to Congress on the report required under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D79AFADD60A47C2965440F395719775"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Primary missions</header><text>The primary missions of the National Center shall be as follows:</text><paragraph id="HD3FBAF7C109D4B8D9913363712D1F165"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To serve as the primary organization in the United States Government for analyzing, tracking, and halting the movement of synthetic drugs domestically, particularly as it relates to the trafficking of fentanyl, fentanyl analogues, and precursor chemicals to produce fentanyl. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08A34C687D704490879D713510366705"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To serve as the primary organization in the United States Government for tracking the movements of persons trafficking in the synthetic drug trade in the United States and overseas through intelligence gathering, in cooperation with other agencies, including:</text><subparagraph id="H400C0F385CBE4CE3B344E365B95EBAC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Drug Enforcement Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0F90EB25C114038B90632ED0BF1BE76"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45C7FF7923F347369548910065A9DC7D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB7A6041A3E84127A3776DBFD9A5DF3D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA4075174D894DCB8B7D68E865FB6C92"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Internal Revenue Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04A812D49A7040CC9D6CF7A7039B7325"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H372458A24B314D03ADAF062EF25C063D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The National Security Agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB18C73AD69ED4A07833F458A226A1EC2"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Central Intelligence Agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CEC306A2D3142FD96490B3B34FC1F65"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The United States Postal Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H563A1FAB44DF4A1EA06296A220E2810F"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB195240124D49F5BBEB5F3A9C3FD96A"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The United States Customs and Border Patrol.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05307652279D4AB1B0AAA2C29C4ECF27"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The Office of National Drug Control Policy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F74585769664E6B870AFB9B6A23447F"><enum>(M)</enum><text>The Office of the Director of National Intelligence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A4287A994844A28A727E7A025F23CFF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To collect and share information with the agencies identified under paragraph (2) to identify and disrupt the movement of fentanyl from an original source to a consumer. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE70F65D7A22D4D2CB3943917FAFF407C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To develop a strategic plan to lead agencies, as appropriate, in the execution of efforts to break up the synthetic drug trade, including assigning roles and responsibilities to such agencies. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC60AD1E3FDA43879F72AE8ECA1BDD92"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To ensure that agencies, as appropriate, have access to and receive information from other agencies, needed to execute their efforts to break up the synthetic drug trade or perform independent, alternative analysis of the synthetic drug trade. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2271916D5ADB466CA3F7E20B768D3504"><enum>(6)</enum><text>To ensure that agencies have access to and receive intelligence needed to accomplish any activities assigned to such agency pursuant to this subsection. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E08E9D62B4B49498A35EE9D94AB7A03"><enum>(7)</enum><text>To serve as the central and shared knowledge bank on known and suspected drug trafficking organizations, both foreign and domestic, including such organization’s strategies, capabilities, and networks of contacts and support.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FB9B5F4F2374E038E33C799C953EB39"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To trace the sale proceeds of the synthetic drug trade, to identify the interests of drug trafficking organizations and persons trafficking in the synthetic drug trade and reveal any network that facilities such trade. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFF2AE40CD1D54D69ADB911E221A5B934"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duties and responsibilities of Director</header><text>The Director shall:</text><paragraph id="HACD012BA3D9742529573210CDE7E34D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Serve in the President’s cabinet as the principal advisor to the President on the synthetic drug trade.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H427AA0D88EE84A6DAD30D6AAE0FD8C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Provide strategic operational plans for efforts of the United States Government to effectively break up the synthetic drug trade, both foreign and domestic. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB47B7E997D444C6BA943E4FC16CDD2CD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Advise the Secretary of State on intelligence gathered related to the synthetic drug trade in foreign countries. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67EE9E99547140DF91F4FDA54EFF4C17"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Support relevant agencies in their efforts to break up the synthetic drug trade. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1130E7EB6E114BD4910341AD4A079D39"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Testify before the appropriate Congressional committees annually.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H302B795AC6F741F991F1235814434C7F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to limit the action of any person acting in compliance with State law relating to the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of cannabis.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEA14B482EFDF42ACAB11388F89CB39E6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sunset</header><paragraph id="H2C5B5435A74947F79DB9D5DE0BFA5EB1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The National Center shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05105DBD0A6B4583A45AB3E0830E5138"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional time period</header><text>The President may authorize the National Center to operate for an additional two years after the date of termination under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8CEDE05DD2784AE4B5E1F8C6022F2A8B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H03B458FE08B147709C521EED89268F26"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <quote>agency</quote> shall have the meaning given such term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9F7AC3620D34DD1A5197FD3B7C85591"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate Congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate Congressional committees</quote> means the—</text><subparagraph id="H4A4A131C03AA41B28170D2FD89FDD17F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Financial Services Committee of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H904FC97680F741118D69F48A65F7B01C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8401E713574043829522338A25CC0652"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FA75DFEAD0F4CF589A33D146BDDB578"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2380CD3E158483DB99B11BC23AFBC40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Drug trafficking organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>drug trafficking organization</quote> means a complex organization with highly defined command-and-control structures that produce, transport, or distribute large quantities of one or more synthetic drugs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8CA2CEDBD3B48EEA11D8560D15C2146"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Persons trafficking in the synthetic drug trade</header><text>The term <quote>persons trafficking in the synthetic drug trade</quote> means a person that plays a role in the synthetic drug trade.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B396792FF05428B9D2C9C02B8919286"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Synthetic drug trade</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>synthetic drug trade</quote> means any illicit activity to cultivate, produce, manufacture, distribute, sell, finance, or transport synthetic drugs, or otherwise endeavor or attempt to do so, or to assist, abet, conspire, or collude with others to do so.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

