<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC7221782DD34B96A0CA44C7C9A688FF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 439 IH: Public Land Search and Rescue Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 439</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230120">January 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior to establish a grant program to allocate resources for remote search and rescue activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD7E52485C967447987BC84BA08013452" style="OLC"><section id="H3FF49D864F5642F4B7AC791FF976BA81" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Public Land Search and Rescue Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFE627535922F4DA091061ADF4D8D47D4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program for remote search and rescue activities</header><subsection id="H54C859CD30A742BABFEE1CD0561AF91A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Interior shall establish a program (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to allocate resources to remote search and rescue activities conducted on lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior.</text></subsection><subsection id="H77F84C222B594217A2687603E288537F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Program, the Secretary may award a grant on a competitive basis in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1311B3C9A4FE44AFB80D58594BC4FE9B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible recipients</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award a grant under the Program to a State, political subdivision thereof, or their designee, that conducts search and rescue operations, determined by the Secretary to have the authority and capability to carry out a project described in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D132FDD14F64CBFB4D5230DDC4C96BA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grant funds awarded under the Program may be used—</text><paragraph id="H1E2596FAB9F04FA4905712D72133AF62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by an eligible recipient to purchase equipment and gear necessary for remote search and rescue activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7561BB325DE4B9D8CABA2593DC57521"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to reimburse an eligible recipient for the cost of maintenance and repair of remote search and rescue equipment owned or leased by an eligible recipient; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H889F6150503348889F5F5646A6616DA8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by an eligible recipient to reimburse State and local agencies responsible for remote search and rescue activities. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F2B7E73996748A7BB61C2C588445399"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H2BDAC40C4E8E4176A429CD44574BFAEA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under the Program, an eligible recipient shall submit to the Secretary an application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7083D5C02F52468C8306806B0648D9CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible recipient may submit to the Secretary an additional application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines to be appropriate for additional funding for purposes under subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCDB9F61484F4788878E647C3CB1B342"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary shall prioritize an application from an eligible recipient who serves an area with a high ratio of visitors to residents. </text></subsection><subsection id="H611C8A9A0C4D411A972E5BE3ED4E7677"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal share of assistance under the Program shall be 75 percent of the cost of an eligible project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H755BE292E0A34388AA183B02238567CE"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Remote search and rescue activity defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>remote search and rescue activity</quote> means an activity that utilizes, trains, or supports responders with specialized equipment to locate, provide assistance to, and remove to safety individuals who are lost, injured, stranded, or entrapped in remote areas. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

