<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBB1FAFC238C34C05ACF61F9A391F776F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6837 IH: Stopping Grinch Bots Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6837</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the circumvention of control measures used by internet retailers to ensure equitable consumer access to products, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H30F99126C4D6459FA669BE2FE8E6F8E4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBCBC37BAAADB46D49D9B2A1BA0A56E63" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stopping Grinch Bots Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC10B4276B25C48D0A9D5CF82EF1C3CB4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices relating to circumvention of online access control measures</header> <subsection id="H664CD62A45354A7FB18E1CEDAEBF7DE6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Conduct prohibited</header> <paragraph id="HA3C0FA296F57461C9FA83B3AA2A19355"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), it shall be unlawful for any person—</text>
<subparagraph id="H48800B7FE94044759E639A3D7F9E7087"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to circumvent a security measure, access control system, or other technological control or measure on an internet website or online service to enforce posted purchasing limits or to manage inventory; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2BF087DAF844096A552561A47F47BCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to sell or offer to sell any product or service in interstate commerce obtained in violation of subparagraph (A) if the person selling or offering to sell the product or service—</text>
<clause id="H9AAEE2E605B3426DA8EFF5FE4379A1F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>participated directly in or had the ability to control the conduct in violation of subparagraph (A); or</text></clause> <clause id="HE18528E75F824536A0ABB148DA285E8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>knew or should have known that the product or service was acquired in violation of subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE254056534BD4927BF94CF4149DDE96F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>It shall not be unlawful under this section for a person to create or use any computer software or system—</text> <subparagraph id="H0641498DF3AE4DEDA9A4B8F66F4BD921"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to investigate, or further the enforcement or defense, of any alleged violation of this section or other statute or regulation; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3ED7929649A54D7988A59956E405DA11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to engage in research necessary to identify and analyze flaws and vulnerabilities of measures, systems, or controls described in paragraph (1)(A), if these research activities are conducted—</text> <clause id="HB455A75237BC498781AED3B90074B1F0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to advance the state of knowledge in the field of computer system security; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H8BD8EA59D1BB4120A5F369DD8F841A90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to assist in the development of computer security product.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4F65CA13B8BE4E189B4D9025EDF18EB6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement by the Federal Trade Commission</header> <paragraph id="H8C7809003EBF4906937DB4D43E4D6568"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of subsection (a) shall be treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or a deceptive act or practice under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1B5DABF893A846CA84B5469C3A0E7529"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header>
<subparagraph id="HBEDDE57276434BE6924860E1E8E02ABD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4DC7406AC234245B9A60DFC70BA5E26"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Privileges and immunities</header><text>Any person who violates subsection (a) shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0DE98ACCDD93469BA302B85CEF9DBF98"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Authority preserved</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other provision of law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDE9AF52CD78E4EE8A2C8F4C8BD3DBA2D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement by States</header> <paragraph id="H40652866A425423A967AF26E74F305A8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any case in which the attorney general of a State has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of the State has been or is threatened or adversely affected by the engagement of any person subject to subsection (a) in a practice that violates such subsection, the attorney general of the State may, as parens patriae, bring a civil action on behalf of the residents of the State in an appropriate district court of the United States—</text>
<subparagraph id="H499FF09542A045DCA64565BAD00F161F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to enjoin further violation of such subsection by such person;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HFEEFA99C38D648458D45DACB740EEB10"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to compel compliance with such subsection; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF2FCEE4882A84082878E9DCB5DEE4080"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of such residents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9AA8808C0794B13BF1146D7B9C7E332"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rights of Federal Trade Commission</header> <subparagraph id="HF161A2E0AB104D0C8F75AD1A8130A2B5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice to Federal Trade Commission</header> <clause id="H955D6E488DB74B879B0E87A959739943"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (iii), the attorney general of a State shall notify the Commission in writing that the attorney general intends to bring a civil action under paragraph (1) not later than 10 days before initiating the civil action.</text></clause>
<clause id="H7D502EF8BA8D44ED8D59AE68FB497B9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The notification required by clause (i) with respect to a civil action shall include a copy of the complaint to be filed to initiate the civil action.</text></clause> <clause id="H6FD04608D6E2486A87E1112C4433834A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If it is not feasible for the attorney general of a State to provide the notification required by clause (i) before initiating a civil action under paragraph (1), the attorney general shall notify the Commission immediately upon instituting the civil action.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H73FF68F904244CAD95B445EC5F42D8DA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Intervention by Federal Trade Commission</header><text>The Commission may—</text> <clause id="H60538BAC54BE44DF8EA4EC01DAD4041F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>intervene in any civil action brought by the attorney general of a State under paragraph (1); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H43373A9F12FD465D929D89CB8BB5C372"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>upon intervening—</text> <subclause id="HAC2621CD2F3A4889B36BF4B9147C5517"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be heard on all matters arising in the civil action; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H29BEC2F8B82641D882261377169E8CD2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>file petitions for appeal of a decision in the civil action.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H991AF7A7934B4FB59EB7CD2E4C115A34"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Investigatory powers</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to prevent the attorney general of a State from exercising the powers conferred on the attorney general by the laws of the State to conduct investigations, to administer oaths or affirmations, or to compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary or other evidence.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEA591B35EC4E475DBBD212A8F43DFBDB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Action by Federal Trade Commission</header><text>If the Commission institutes a civil action or an administrative action with respect to a violation of subsection (a), the attorney general of a State may not, during the pendency of such action, bring a civil action under paragraph (1) against any defendant named in the complaint of the Commission for the violation with respect to which the Commission instituted such action.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H83F9DFB4901944A29A03672FC45D71B8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Venue; service of process</header> <subparagraph id="HBB1241E9C56A4812AA63BE1842E15D37"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Venue</header><text>Any action brought under paragraph (1) may be brought in—</text>
<clause id="H3EA398B099DB451B8511148A6D5AE7F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the district court of the United States that meets applicable requirements relating to venue under section 1391 of title 28, United States Code; or</text></clause> <clause id="H1D39118FB7484DB5867A6150AD68A27C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>another court of competent jurisdiction.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3F94F55EBDDE4D06B133787E39E052DA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Service of process</header><text>In an action brought under paragraph (1), process may be served in any district in which the defendant—</text> <clause id="HCC5271B377ED4B54AD0619426F0BFD79"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is an inhabitant; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H89AEE24922934AA8BCC0587982468D44"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may be found.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB67D38FF86D46A082F4A33AB4CC07D5"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Actions by other State officials</header> <subparagraph id="HA8695E83CFB14BCCB0679E4D750C1903"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to civil actions brought by attorneys general under paragraph (1), any other consumer protection officer of a State who is authorized by the State to do so may bring a civil action under paragraph (1), subject to the same requirements and limitations that apply under this subsection to civil actions brought by attorneys general.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H851572D6D95A439EBAAFDE585F851E68"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to prohibit an authorized official of a State from initiating or continuing any proceeding in a court of the State for a violation of any civil or criminal law of the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB79F9D69B56A4C45AC2065403377AF64"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H41EE65582BF8439D987747AB29C86DA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1247A677BEC48E2B81114FE3E0DD4CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Posted</header><text>The term <term>posted</term> means clearly and conspicuously published on an internet website.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

