<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F97A95A9C7744968B720FFF57ED4E6F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2879 IH: National Center for the Advancement of Aviation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2879</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001314">Mr. Bean of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the National Center for the Advancement of Aviation.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HF8B484DE2D0C4407A2A4074C57E0F717" style="OLC">
<section id="H8EFC6C77F10943A09228CC4732CB1B9C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Center for the Advancement of Aviation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3FBEDE34C9AA44E1AE9B9E3318A1EEF6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal charter for the National Center for the Advancement of Aviation</header> <subsection id="H86192F6C4439491AB3226E3511E23C47"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/1">Chapter 1</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H5B94FCD7F4814E48BD29F468D528A751" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="HB9E7A964680A4E08BE3FAF6BA2271DC5"><enum>120.</enum><header>National Center for the Advancement of Aviation</header>
<subsection id="H73001F68831C45F494193A0E0F04A6D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal charter and status</header>
<paragraph id="H520A77DFA88642E5B5B80D1998D23485"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Center for the Advancement of Aviation (in this section referred to as the <quote>Center</quote>) is a federally chartered entity. The Center is a private independent entity, not a department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States Government or a component thereof. Except as provided in subsection (f)(1), an officer or employee of the Center is not an officer or employee of the Federal Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7A8E2BFF9CF4DA9B558519EF67CC03C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Perpetual existence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided, the Center shall have perpetual existence.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H602928600BB5494B91573ADB0C898781"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Governing body</header>
<paragraph id="HBCE15F5641A946F6B589382E80D2A069"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board of Directors (in this section referred to as the <quote>Board</quote>) is the governing body of the Center.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H948D96B6F60D4188B29144EE6B1C6009"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority of powers</header> <subparagraph id="HB98E35922928471CBDE95D6E479D309B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall adopt a constitution, bylaws, regulations, policies, and procedures to carry out the purpose of the Center and may take any other action that it considers necessary (in accordance with the duties and powers of the Center) for the management and operation of the Center. The Board is responsible for the general policies and management of the Center and for the control of all funds of the Center.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7CFF89E1749E413ABA3A5318BCB1B159"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Powers of board</header><text>The Board shall have the power to do the following:</text> <clause id="HDFDA6844778B4D78B6235132426F61E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Adopt and alter a corporate seal.</text></clause>
<clause id="HA119BA9B397B4B66B561E3E382E91234"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish and maintain offices to conduct its activities.</text></clause> <clause id="HDF0E0841C474460F99FC205C997E14A1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Enter into contracts or agreements as a private entity not subject to the requirements of title 41.</text></clause>
<clause id="HDB8BB283EDA04FBDB0D57BD0C5B34A81"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Acquire, own, lease, encumber, and transfer property as necessary and appropriate to carry out the purposes of the Center.</text></clause> <clause id="H5827B35C34B3413693795E41D4129704"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Publish documents and other publications in a publicly accessible manner.</text></clause>
<clause id="H14E5AEB1A9D44D00A2ABCEF79150C5C1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Incur and pay obligations as a private entity not subject to the requirements of title 31.</text></clause> <clause id="H0EDE5CB6828E40A9939A9663FBC9752F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Make or issue grants and include any conditions on such grants in furtherance of the purpose and duties of the Center.</text></clause>
<clause id="HF3E843B6B43B4413BBE082CE0B6AC3E5"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Perform any other act necessary and proper to carry out the purposes of the Center as described in its constitution and bylaws or duties outlined in this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79CB839FE87F4DE4B2B7D1A1D611F69E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Membership of the Board</header> <subparagraph id="HE109471095094C39AC6B57D8EB41E0B7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall have 11 Directors as follows:</text>
<clause id="HC7C251F4E13041A6AD1005644EA4B21C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Ex-officio membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following individuals, or their designees, shall be considered ex-officio members of the Board:</text> <subclause id="HC12B0CD562074CE6AE84AABABA9B1F06"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration. </text></subclause>
<subclause id="H66907DA606D149C98FF78409364E442D"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director, pursuant to paragraph (5)(D).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC34BEF65315C4CA58BF46F493CA2D75F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Appointments</header> <subclause id="H18083B85173F47F691CC4D007F2FA7F4"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From among those members of the public who are highly respected and have knowledge and experience in the fields of aviation, finance, or academia—</text>
<item id="H78E5A2F7E68047449E3ECB7116817A82"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Transportation shall appoint 5 members to the Board;</text></item> <item id="HF615A15D950B42969701F2D1EE773387"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense shall appoint 1 member to the Board;</text></item>
<item id="H972D71BFA17A409DA182E74F5F61865A"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall appoint 1 member to the Board;</text></item> <item id="H3671453F273E412AAD58A677B75CAA27"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>the Secretary of Education shall appoint 1 member to the Board; and</text></item>
<item id="HDA392F072DA447D799951CAFA7D128C3"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall appoint 1 member to the Board.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H7BB03B6F45264E11BDE0441AC8681309"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Terms</header> <item id="H1CD261779C5B43A2B262B2CD6A26C5D0"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The members appointed under subclause (I) shall serve for a term of 3 years and may be reappointed.</text></item>
<item id="HD9D3F9AFB21C4A14AC3167AF8020A80E"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Staggering terms</header><text>To ensure subsequent appointments to the Board are staggered, of the 9 members first appointed under subclause (I), 3 shall be appointed for a term of 1 year, 3 shall be appointed for a term of 2 years, and 3 shall be appointed for a term of 3 years.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H053FD3ECA9214847B84FE8DA19EFAAEB"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In considering whom to appoint to the Board, the Secretaries and Administrator referenced in subclause (I) shall, to the maximum extent practicable, ensure the overall composition of the Board adequately represents the fields of aviation and academia.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H58F19696D22D4A11B2021217303D6287"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vacancy on the Board shall be filled in the same manner as the initial appointment.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0CE06097B6274DDE83DF9592B148D218"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Status</header><text>All Members of the Board shall have equal voting powers, regardless if they are ex-officio members or appointed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H81212B08559F44F59584623F3B1623F2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chair of the Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall choose a Chair of the Board from among the members of the Board that are not ex-officio members under paragraph (3)(A)(i).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49D11EE671964F28B9D996D917F71BE2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Administrative matters</header> <subparagraph id="HA08B135230D0490BAF6D85B4677EDB16"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Meetings</header> <clause id="HF96F81F4639E445C8E037DF512B5A9DB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall meet at the call of the Chair but not less than 2 times each year and may, as appropriate, conduct business by telephone or other electronic means.</text></clause>
<clause id="H03B3D6AC8B764D00B7302E275290449F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Open</header>
<subclause id="H28C5DAF25832418AB3ACB08729608EA7"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subclause (II), a meeting of the Board shall be open to the public.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2B5BC20A0E9646D3897BF98B51102EA0"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A meeting, or any portion of a meeting, may be closed if the Board, in public session, votes to close the meeting because the matters to be discussed—</text>
<item id="H056BB4A9CD9849F4991D5BAA9151D675"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>relate solely to the internal personnel rules and practices of the Center;</text></item> <item id="H0102A683E6254A78BE5359BC68F58EA5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>may result in disclosure of commercial or financial information obtained from a person that is privileged or confidential;</text></item>
<item id="H5EFCE486F6C949A1B515A48F850C829B"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>may disclose information of a personal nature where disclosure would constitute a clearly unwarranted invasion of personal privacy; or</text></item> <item id="H48821D614F45488099DDB55DB08069B7"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>are matters that are specifically exempted from disclosure by Federal or State law.</text></item></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H56D75CFB066E4D63B276AAE13AD2EC1C"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Public announcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 1 week before a meeting of the Board, and as soon as practicable thereafter if there are any changes to the information described in subclauses (I) through (III), the Board shall make a public announcement of the meeting that describes—</text> <subclause id="HCB6B66494EE141758D438E1DFD111099"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the time, place, and subject matter of the meeting;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H30BCBED2D5E74723A5260A9DA06B4D38"><enum>(II)</enum><text>whether the meeting is to be open or closed to the public; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H824A40529FD9484998C2AACD61F232A6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the name and appropriate contact information of a person who can respond to requests for information about the meeting.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H33D4EEB6DF544450B1E2248E4C996097"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Record</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall keep a transcript of minutes from each Board meeting. Such transcript shall be made available to the public in an accessible format, except for portions of the meeting that are closed pursuant to subparagraph (A)(ii)(II).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H93DD800F2EB8411787C5C29B3A1983D2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of members of the Board shall constitute a quorum.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5234C133206740E7910C98C54486E45F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Restriction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No member of the Board shall participate in any proceeding, application, ruling or other determination, contract claim, scholarship award, controversy, or other matter in which the member, the member’s employer or prospective employer, or the member’s spouse, partner, or minor child has a direct financial interest. Any person who violates this subparagraph may be fined not more than $10,000, imprisoned for not more than 2 years, or both.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6FD45380F72D491CA9CB1CBF06D02409"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall appoint and fix the pay of an Executive Director of the Center (in this section referred to as the <quote>Executive Director</quote>) who shall—</text>
<clause id="HF736C5BEF86D48C9BC1D073B11E9EFE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serve as a Member of the Board;</text></clause> <clause id="H1AF44967B59344A4B598F301FBA4040D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>serve at the pleasure of the Board, under such terms and conditions as the Board shall establish;</text></clause>
<clause id="H8AE56918C1A743EEB567064311AA1CB6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is subject to removal by the Board at the discretion of the Board; and </text></clause> <clause id="H3C1A20AC03314F91A75BE5DF0E3D0011"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>be responsible for the daily management and operation of the Center and for carrying out the purposes and duties of the Center.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7752DEF020DD4DB38255359FB8569398"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Appointment of Personnel</header><text>The Board shall designate to the Executive Director the authority to appoint additional personnel as the Board considers appropriate and necessary to carry out the purposes and duties of the Center.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF7009ED0A484720B5D3A28FD0001D6A" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Public information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to withhold disclosure of information or records that are subject to disclosure under section 552 of title 5.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H340BCB69C06E4DDB80813A7FFF333BCA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purpose of the Center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of the Center is to—</text> <paragraph id="H19D3EE9FC6E04F7F8AE5D168FCAE9C5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a skilled and robust U.S. aviation and aerospace workforce;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1F4702AF789A479B8C280B1841214C6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide a forum to support collaboration and cooperation between governmental, non-governmental, and private aviation and aerospace sector stakeholders regarding the advancement of the U.S. aviation and aerospace workforce, including general, business, and commercial aviation, education, labor, manufacturing and international organizations; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H37879F5A626F4CFDBA1D0828F70E284C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>serve as a repository for research conducted by institutions of higher education, research institutions, or other stakeholders regarding the aviation and aerospace workforce, or related technical and skill development. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3D044AE89B044DC0BA4E6D4082CC1E0F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties of the Center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to accomplish the purpose described in subsection (c), the Center shall perform the following duties:</text> <paragraph id="HACAA0B6999314A2BADF8E9027DD3F0B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improve access to aviation and aerospace education and related skills training to help grow the U.S. aviation and aerospace workforce, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBE4C1DDA20264BA2803B3F03FE77CE8F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assessing the current U.S. aviation and aerospace workforce challenges and identifying actions to address these challenges, including by developing a comprehensive workforce strategy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H13AF22FD202048B49096180FC6BA693C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing scholarship, apprenticeship, internship or mentorship programs for individuals who wish to pursue a career in an aviation- or aerospace-related field, including individuals in economically disadvantaged areas or individuals who are members of underrepresented groups in the aviation and aerospace sector;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1127C0F512F54482A99CE9B3CC2AEA2C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>supporting the development of aviation and aerospace education curricula, including syllabi, training materials, and lesson plans, for use by middle schools and high schools, institutions of higher education, secondary education institutions, or technical training and vocational schools; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95B3C731DB024A61BBC960C6EC417871"><enum>(D)</enum><text>building awareness of youth-oriented aviation and aerospace programs and other outreach programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H08AFEFD73E884A07B31EB613D0338905"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Support the personnel or veterans of the Armed Forces seeking to transition to a career in civil aviation or aerospace through outreach, training, apprenticeships, or other means.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H528A24F31C3C4CEBBD061710AF4F607D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amplify and support the research and development efforts conducted as part of the National Aviation Research Plan, as required under section 44501(c), and work done at the Centers of Excellence and Technical Centers of the Federal Aviation Administration regarding the aviation and aerospace workforce, or related technical and skills development, including organizing and hosting symposiums, conferences, and other forums as appropriate, between the Federal Aviation Administration, aviation and aerospace stakeholders, and other interested parties, to discuss current and future research efforts and technical work.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5064544598294260845EC80185F9A7F1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants</header>
<paragraph id="HA77C51001C664A899A24640E806AA41E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to accomplish the purpose under subsection (c) and duties under subsection (d), the Center may issue grants to eligible entities to—</text> <subparagraph id="HE1C393259B2343C4A41FD4A6B45ACF19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>create, develop, deliver, or update—</text>
<clause id="H8D67D1788D68452CB5341F2A7401161D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">middle and high school aviation curricula, including syllabi, training materials, equipment and lesson plans, that are designed to prepare individuals to become aircraft pilots, aerospace engineers, unmanned aircraft system operators, aviation maintenance technicians, or other aviation maintenance professionals, or to support the continuing education of any of the aforementioned individuals; or</text></clause> <clause id="H862343E49A8449A2B91EADEB93AA4ED2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aviation curricula, including syllabi, training materials, equipment and lesson plans, used at institutions of higher education, secondary education institutions, or by technical training and vocational schools, that are designed to prepare individuals to become aircraft pilots, aerospace engineers, unmanned aircraft system operators, aviation maintenance technicians, or other aviation maintenance professionals, or to refresh the knowledge of any of the aforementioned individuals; or</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0A6947B9583046D78C594339A7FCDBAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the professional development of educators using the curriculum in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7EFAD0E6583745F1B2C1EBAD544102E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establish new education programs that teach technical skills used in aviation maintenance, including purchasing equipment, or to improve existing programs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9888CA1C06CD47E082274CD07A6BB222"><enum>(D)</enum><text>establish scholarships, internships or apprenticeships for individuals pursuing employment in the aviation maintenance industry;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1E120EB219D3477F920F37F2AA700C86"><enum>(E)</enum><text>support outreach about educational opportunities and careers in the aviation maintenance industry, including in economically disadvantaged areas; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2586B4CB61F741299E9AEFF02539E459"><enum>(F)</enum><text>support the transition to careers in aviation maintenance, including for members of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09E1418C8A6E4A54BB84AF5ACCD33260"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>An eligible entity under this subsection includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF99A4F5F48CE496BB105BFDB32BF7DDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an air carrier, as defined in section 40102, an air carrier engaged in intrastate or intra-U.S. territorial operations, an air carrier engaged in commercial operations covered by part 135 or part 91 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, operations, or a labor organization representing aircraft pilots;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H11F17FAB3D7C4E4CBA04B2D89A89B043"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an accredited institution of higher education or a high school or secondary school (as defined in section 8101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2A88EBACFE424FA886029C0F1D6135A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a flight school that provides flight training, as defined in part 61 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, or that holds a pilot school certificate under part 141 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H030A8A5B378745E6B53E6E202F20C03D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a State or local governmental entity;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H54D55A2B7447445BB7111C0BAE601E98"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an organization representing aircraft users, aircraft owners, or aircraft pilots;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5BBED8D873A4C7288284232B3C027B1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a holder of a certificate issued under part 21, 121, 135, or 145 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations or a labor organization representing aviation maintenance workers; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7E2E2681922B4F71B916E03C36C2F013"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other organizations at the discretion of the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H15B34CEDDF22431AAF8A096F52060BAD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No organization that receives a grant under this section may sell or make a profit from the creation, development, delivery, or updating of high school aviation curricula.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0EFA9BB81A474C9BA8DB99B03090B0F5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Administrative matters of the Center</header>
<paragraph id="H317699FF4F6A4E70A94FD0EFB8B5E1FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Detailees</header>
<subparagraph id="H0DF1FBCF2F854A8198A6738FC0955C2A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request of the Center, the head of any Federal agency or department may, at the discretion of such agency or department, detail to the Center, on a reimbursable basis, any employee of the agency or department.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB1B701D002214DC3991AB27D8BB09E3B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Civil servant status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The detail of an employee under subparagraph (A) shall be without interruption or loss of civil service status or privilege.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H48AF85FD7F73464D89EB6D05FDA59D2C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Names and symbols</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center may accept, retain, and use proceeds derived from the Center’s use of the exclusive right to use its name and seal, emblems, and badges incorporating such name as lawfully adopted by the Board in furtherance of the purpose and duties of the Center.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66FF557782044650B030EBE4B68267E0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gifts, grants, bequests, and devises</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center may accept, retain, use, and dispose of gifts, grants, bequests, or devises of money, services, or property from any public or private source for the purpose of covering the costs incurred by the Center in furtherance of the purpose and duties of the Center.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3F8DDAD204AE4A7E8A957A8B8A596ACB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Voluntary services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center may accept from any person voluntary services to be provided in furtherance of the purpose and duties of the Center.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE773E1723C0A4854A4450F25A9BBED3D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Restrictions of the Center</header> <paragraph id="H8FF52BAF83A74F788A57B2990BB4CD21"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Profit</header><text>The Center may not engage in business activity for profit.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC29D906DD465416AA2AC89BBF0A9B4EC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Stocks and dividends</header><text>The Center may not issue any shares of stock or declare or pay any dividends.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA89E0F52E6A24C4589DF1BB622DBD2FB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Political activities</header><text>The Center shall be nonpolitical and may not provide financial aid or assistance to, or otherwise contribute to or promote the candidacy of, any individual seeking elective public office or political party. The Center may not engage in activities that are, directly, or indirectly, intended to be or likely to be perceived as advocating or influencing the legislative process.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3742EBC308BC45FA9ADCCE7DD07ED1A4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Distribution of income or assets</header><text>The assets of the Center may not inure to the benefit of any member of the Board, or any officer or employee of the Center or be distributed to any person. This subsection does not prevent the payment of reasonable compensation to any officer, employee, or other person or reimbursement for actual and necessary expenses in amounts approved by the Board.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE10D3A7940E741F2B4EA3CCB7DD4A8A1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Loans</header><text>The Center may not make a loan to any member of the Board or any officer or employee of the Center.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCBE6CDCB70614BE699E5A03F67952DEC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>No claim of governmental approval or authority</header><text>The Center may not claim approval of Congress or of the authority of the United States for any of its activities.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H94CE5C8FF3654B35B39D0FE8569BB3FD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Advisory committee</header> <paragraph id="H6EFD5DEDAD9246EC9A63D8AAD175A2EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Executive Director shall appoint members to an advisory committee subject to approval by the Board. Members of the Board may not sit on the advisory committee.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE91BBDB6C6404FBCB9A3FF9CCFB6D2A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The advisory committee shall consist of 15 members who represent various aviation industry and labor stakeholders, stakeholder associations, and others as determined appropriate by the Board. The advisory committee shall select a Chair and Vice Chair from among its members by majority vote. Members of the advisory committee shall be appointed for a term of 5 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H844E39D5C1FB4DC0B63664F46B4766BC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The advisory committee shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBC9A1D5737F84EA98B5F1D7F279D7666"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide recommendations to the Board on an annual basis regarding the priorities for the activities of the Center;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA01347B8FDA945A98D4E8DAB22ED9E8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consult with the Board on an ongoing basis regarding the appropriate powers of the Board to accomplish the purposes and duties of the Center;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H98DF84E63A3B446FBF4F3F524C4ACD44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide relevant data and information to the Center in order to carry out the duties set forth in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H48DD088B26D142F2B3D97319F180E9FC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>nominate United States citizens for consideration by the Board to be honored annually by the Center for such citizens’ efforts in promoting U.S. aviation or aviation education and enhancing the aviation workforce in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E67986C6CBA4F85B6EE67FE50266D0E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The provisions for meetings of the Board under subsection (b)(5) shall apply as similarly as is practicable to meetings of the advisory committee.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H705102B3EF8049FEAE8CC05BF3EDFA66"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Working groups</header> <paragraph id="HC61478CEDE284748B3C7D33A233B3EE5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board may establish and appoint the membership of the working groups as determined necessary and appropriate to achieve the purpose of the Center under subsection (c).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H53051BBBE56E455288BA56417277439F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>Any working group established by the Board shall have members representing various aviation industry and labor stakeholders, stakeholder associations, and others, as determined appropriate by the Board. Once established, the membership of such working group shall choose a Chair from among the members of the working group by majority vote.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB25A6D8B686B4165A3126147808CB093"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Unless determined otherwise by the Board, any working group established by the Board under this subsection shall be constituted for a time period of not more than 3 years.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H727F4C8E8A2B49E7B044FF9AFA24C807"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Records of accounts</header><text>The Center shall keep correct and complete records of accounts.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H02AFE362C7524D06A84A647B6EFEB93C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Duty To maintain tax-Exempt status</header><text>The Center shall be operated in a manner and for purposes that qualify the Center for exemption from taxation under the Internal Revenue Code as an organization described in section 501(c)(3) of such Code.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H37F5720AE6B040398D7EFCD2035ECE52"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall submit an annual report to the appropriate committees of Congress that, at minimum,—</text> <paragraph id="HDCC06D189EE94AB6A6019E6BA2CB898F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>includes a review and examination of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H36AC69D6381641138A16483A1F85420E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the activities performed as set forth in subsections (d) and (e) during the prior fiscal year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE22140EE4F6A4AE6B7E1A7304B46F118"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the advisory committee as described under subsection (h); and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAFCB619B9F804DE580A1C260B6C0A0D4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the working groups as described under subsection (i); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BAC6977972B4CE98613DC6615E56508"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides recommendations to improve the role, responsibilities, and functions of the Center to achieve the purpose set forth in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1193A302126B4A789C4ED1AD4C561D8B"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Audit by the Department of Transportation Inspector General</header>
<paragraph id="HB68C6CC18A944FC5935DBF5FAAA9F504"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Center is established under subsection (a), the inspector general of the Department of Transportation shall conduct a review of the Center.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FE818CDC2724126B406818E732A2B46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The review shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H86AA216EB2A84A0F8BAA9A93BE36235A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include, at a minimum—</text> <clause id="H9067CCD699F94F2190E7A07A2DD53F6C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an evaluation of the efforts taken at the Center to achieve the purpose set forth in subsection (c); and </text></clause>
<clause id="H9C80680247F04958AFEB1B2BC9AD0E66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the recommendations provided by the Board in subsection (l)(2); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H36A468FBC8554003A913B74EE82C52AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide any other information that the inspector general determines is appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6C529D45A3CE4B22A612EC3D1B0BE04A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report on audit</header>
<subparagraph id="H14A56DF6769540DA9027626C275EFBE9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report to Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of completion of the audit, the inspector general shall submit to the Secretary a report on the results of the audit.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A2CE17960D84036B8559D5D038D1A6A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of receipt of the report under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a copy of the report, together with, if appropriate, a description of any actions taken or to be taken to address the results of the audit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD5FC3A41497D4A32B1465F561E1E3090" commented="no"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter an amount equal to 3 percent of the interest from investment credited to the Airport and Airway Trust Fund.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5AF61B415C044E39BBD54052AE6E1090"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HD3C9899F07094FF194B4AA815116ACAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48CAC8018B9D43B88F4E2A7A7BC34D63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD665E701926F4E758AC72318CD4ADB37"><enum>(3)</enum><header>STEM</header><text>The term <quote>STEM</quote> means science, technology, engineering, and mathematics.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H39EAC864F0B84EA09C717C9D086F391A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/119">section 119</external-xref> the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H08BEB47C57354CBC9B297A4B0ACF03EB" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">120. National Center for the Advancement of Aviation. </toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="H2BBBCDA16CD84F3F831DFB2BB2330837"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prevention of duplicative programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Board of Directors of the National Center for the Advancement of Aviation established under section 120 of title 49, United States Code (as added by this Act), shall coordinate with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to prevent any programs of the Center from duplicating programs established under section 625 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note).</text></section> <section id="HBA6330FA0C5549C8BBEBB7DF05F50F98"><enum>4.</enum><header>Determination of budgetary effects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the House Budget Committee, provided that such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage.</text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


