<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC80FBAADD1104DD5A6CC66C93F09FB3A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6524 IH: Federal Cybersecurity Workforce Expansion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6524</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231130">November 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency to establish an apprenticeship program and to establish a pilot program on cybersecurity training for veterans and members of the Armed Forces transitioning to civilian life, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H876F138D0BF2456F9F1DEC0FC1E7999D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE802854199FE42A581F690E4E9DC3E62" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Cybersecurity Workforce Expansion Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB679EE560F09431AB1F7AA7549D86A86"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAAEF83B758824ED0A0D90A8295615397"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the need for qualified cybersecurity personnel is greater than ever, as demonstrated by the recent SolarWinds breach and the growing spate of ransomware attacks on critical infrastructure entities and State and local governments;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7177E4FCA9C5462AA4E8E3C81F710B43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Federal Government is facing a shortage of qualified cybersecurity personnel, as noted in a March 2019 Government Accountability Office report on critical staffing needs in the Federal cybersecurity workforce;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H97F7536EA61B4E828E9EDFAF40172105"><enum>(3)</enum><text>there is a national shortage of qualified cybersecurity personnel, and according to CyberSeek, a project supported by the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education within the National Institute of Standards and Technology, there are approximately 500,000 cybersecurity job openings around the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA07DAE69E7714222BA9ADAF742917521"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in May 2021, the Department of Homeland Security announced that the Department was initiating a 60-day sprint to hire 200 cybersecurity personnel across the Department, with 100 of those hires for the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, to address a cybersecurity workforce shortage; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEEFC81D7ECEC4A02B3AB5B8548E074AE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Federal Government needs to—</text> <subparagraph id="H94ADA2A714CB4AD1A0819F866A111345"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expand the cybersecurity workforce pipeline of the Federal Government to sustainably close a Federal cybersecurity workforce shortage; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAFB752E84D0149888D4F9E48CF7D5F5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>work cooperatively with the private sector and State and local government authorities to expand opportunities for new cybersecurity professionals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HCAAE76872B554E03925578C7BBB00E34"><enum>3.</enum><header>Cybersecurity and infrastructure security apprenticeship program</header> <subsection id="HF1A8F47C32044115976E3162E22D7352"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle A of title XXII of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/651">6 U.S.C. 651 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA18BD19979141B28AE22E25A9205648"> 
<section id="HFB7BF88E63334DC887B130439ED4E8A0"><enum>2220F.</enum><header>Apprenticeship program</header> 
<subsection id="H625AA2EC762741BFAD26EECEAD9A161A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HF9B08CA30C5542E0A3303B7BD853ADC5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Area career and technical education school</header><text>The term <term>area career and technical education school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FF7FF0A5AB54414AB9E1383A0FFF671"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community college</header><text>The term <term>community college</term> means a public institution of higher education at which the highest degree that is predominantly awarded to students is an associate’s degree, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H3C938B59AF794521A88342956257A62F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a 2-year Tribal College or University, as defined in section 316 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c</external-xref>); and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4A3F54283B1648CAB214EB35ADC80DCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a public 2-year State institution of higher education. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H729A541CE40945928EA5AFBCC4BDF6FD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cybersecurity work roles</header><text>The term <term>cybersecurity work roles</term> means the work roles outlined in the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education Cybersecurity Workforce Framework (NIST Special Publication 800–181), or any successor framework. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9386E59A866B4C96AB7324E5F9EF7128"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Education and training provider</header><text>The term <term>education and training provider</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HCB23C3E105F34A52999E9853FB920B45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an area career and technical education school;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8CEDC2BE8B7B4F2D8420B7529F264E0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early college high school;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8E25809981C84DBB92D528838A2173EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an educational service agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7ADD16EDFBA148D29ABAF0CAC94DDA67"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a high school;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5A60DA9E42874CE58917D795BCD55E1F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a local educational agency or State educational agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H436926FEE2EF4525BC7362BA30F69900"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a Tribal educational agency, Tribally controlled college or university, or Tribally controlled postsecondary career and technical institution;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4055E646452741C4AF38295E97EE2B10"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a postsecondary educational institution;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDDF4EF99DF254004A33193E190AD9973"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a minority-serving institution;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBBF83DABBCB04515801EBCAAFB95EA3A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a provider of adult education and literacy activities under the Adult Education and Family Literacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3271">29 U.S.C. 3271 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF072AF6DFAF44716AD04DD59733DE1BD"><enum>(J)</enum><text>a local agency administering plans under title I of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/720">29 U.S.C. 720 et seq.</external-xref>), other than section 112 or part C of that title (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/732">29 U.S.C. 732</external-xref>, 741);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC4B4E3F1EE9F481090DDA3E4072A76C4"><enum>(K)</enum><text>a related instruction provider, including a qualified intermediary acting as a related instruction provider as approved by a registration agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCC5541DA54A049CA9A68312BF4781F30"><enum>(L)</enum><text>a Job Corps center, as defined in section 142 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3192">29 U.S.C. 3192</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H692D17549AF9422FB16350E288A0A633"><enum>(M)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (L).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H340994000B7442F9B9F0D9CD30CA2D43"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header> 
<subparagraph id="H47BD28B073B245E39FB2BB3AA8B8940B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> <clause id="H7CE636086DAF43DD963A662F39DA902C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a program sponsor;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6898F01038844F2E8F33A43F50391B35"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State workforce development board or State workforce agency, or a local workforce development board or local workforce development agency;</text></clause> <clause id="H7A3D8963BA8F4699994666D0C96D234F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an education and training provider;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H936EFA50DD4848CEA968CF2BEFB5494E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>if the applicant is in a State with a State apprenticeship agency, such State apprenticeship agency;</text></clause> <clause id="H038DB935F4FD4F319564DD85D95BDEE6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe or Tribal organization;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H224D3FBE626B43CB974E6E6ABCF37C99"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>an industry or sector partnership, a group of employers, a trade association, or a professional association that sponsors or participates in a program under the national apprenticeship system;</text></clause> <clause id="HD96BD45462AC4B3BA63BB423EFC9A266"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>a Governor of a State;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5AD3A19E66324EF3B6B273B0D8E6C520"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>a labor organization or joint labor-management organization; or</text></clause> <clause id="H0BC358CC844E424B84B68794D4C61335"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>a qualified intermediary.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD38016CD9F1445F7A98A37789DA7405E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sponsor requirement</header><text>Not fewer than 1 entity described in subparagraph (A) shall be the sponsor of a program under the national apprenticeship system. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H265A84F8C17C4A65B2E222B1464BB2BF"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0EF78BB075524F5BB3CB4C245D76B15A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Local educational agency; secondary school</header><text>The terms <term>local educational agency</term> and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H06FC8331ED3E46859D4DBCCD7D72A726"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Local workforce development board</header><text>The term <term>local workforce development board</term> has the meaning given the term <term>local board</term> in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA89CC506E5742258BE774477066941D"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization that is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85E3ADC0F7C84B3387803645A021646D"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Provider of adult education</header><text>The term <term>provider of adult education</term> has the meaning given the term <term>eligible provider</term> in section 203 of the Adult Education and Family Literacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3272">29 U.S.C. 3272</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB83DCD78404141CE91BA31367E29FC75"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Related instruction</header><text>The term <term>related instruction</term> means an organized and systematic form of instruction designed to provide an individual in an apprenticeship program with the knowledge of the technical subjects related to the intended occupation of the individual after completion of the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23506583B7764CD5A08A36EBED2FF3F2"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Sponsor</header><text>The term <term>sponsor</term> means any person, association, committee, or organization operating an apprenticeship program and in whose name the program is, or is to be, registered or approved.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H599047091CD24F6F8BFF42194F1DCD19"><enum>(13)</enum><header>State apprenticeship agency</header><text>The term <term>State apprenticeship agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 29.2 of title 29, Code of Federal Regulations, or any corresponding similar regulation or ruling.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H590E8B8524D54908A7533D1A07220DBC"><enum>(14)</enum><header>State workforce development board</header><text>The term <term>State workforce development board</term> has the meaning given the term <term>State board</term> in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B33A10C6EF74353B3F3DB305EE85E98"><enum>(15)</enum><header>WIOA terms</header><text>The terms <term>career planning</term>, <term>community-based organization</term>, <term>economic development agency</term>, <term>industry or sector partnership</term>, <term>on-the-job training</term>, <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term>, and <term>workplace learning advisor</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6752154F019F40A68C5D1C8A9258499A"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Qualified intermediary</header> <subparagraph id="H64FB6D78602D442581CD5102E01DDD85"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified intermediary</term> means an entity that demonstrates expertise in building, connecting, sustaining, and measuring the performance of partnerships described in subparagraph (B) and serves program participants and employers by—</text> 
<clause id="HBA8E43C1D2F84389A915D38964DB9AD2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>connecting employers to programs under the national apprenticeship system;</text></clause> <clause id="H47A63D0E51994289AE228AB9515C357B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assisting in the design and implementation of such programs, including curriculum development and delivery for related instruction;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A6276AFF1FC485BA5811396F64E6176"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>supporting entities, sponsors, or program administrators in meeting the registration and reporting requirements of this Act;</text></clause> <clause id="HEEA5D30F6DB143CABF09640F5E3B30DF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>providing professional development activities such as training to mentors;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC958A1124909419F8FC7953AC50532BC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>supporting the recruitment, retention, and completion of potential program participants, including nontraditional apprenticeship populations and individuals with barriers to employment;</text></clause> <clause id="H9CC34DC008394F89ADD8548447E77FD5"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>developing and providing personalized program participant supports, including by partnering with organizations to provide access to or referrals for supportive services and financial advising;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A22D38A59A14DB5A3B9157ED47F7E7E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>providing services, resources, and supports for development, delivery, expansion, or improvement of programs under the national apprenticeship system; or</text></clause> <clause id="H4C18BAE2008E44D8B7B6251EB697CBD0"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>serving as a program sponsor.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4B515D201EA1486E94C31DC2774A76C5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>The term <term>partnerships described in subparagraph (B)</term> means partnerships among entities involved in, or applying to participate in, programs under the national apprenticeship system, including—</text> <clause id="HA3C90FEED097460CBD016C083119EE0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>industry or sector partnerships;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCF4E3A064DCD4C91980781194DA92272"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>partnerships among employers, joint labor-management organizations, labor organizations, community-based organizations, industry associations, State or local workforce development boards, education and training providers, social service organizations, economic development organizations, Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations, one-stop operators, one-stop partners, or veterans service organizations in the State workforce development system; or</text></clause> <clause id="H78A68F02F3DF467584640CFA78BF709D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>partnerships among 1 or more of the entities described in clauses (i) and (ii). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC5D78EFC69BF458E9495D7A57C451B10"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of apprenticeship programs</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Director may establish 1 or more apprenticeship programs as described in subsection (c).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H33668D727C604390BC3907D490D3D737"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Apprenticeship programs described</header><text>An apprenticeship program described in this subsection is an apprenticeship program that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H77A40E00C11C4738A962E4B78002794D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>leads directly to employment in—</text> <subparagraph id="H9766B6A3FCD94570A4B82B6C159CEDC3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a cybersecurity work role with the Agency; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1E3C9816A68D448FAEA32BB25D0A9CF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a position with a company or other entity provided that the position is—</text> <clause id="H810CFA2D715F49DE8B017AB6B4AC4A5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>certified by the Director as contributing to the national cybersecurity of the United States; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC1B4477BD6934BFBB3E555F0D0F85E78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>funded at least in majority part through a contract, grant, or cooperative agreement with the Agency;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF7E4EEF5E8B42B682909C119004D618"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is focused on competencies and related learning necessary, as determined by the Director, to meet the immediate and ongoing needs of cybersecurity work roles at the Agency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF4700A2F5D947BA98A9B8F085A859A5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is registered with and approved by the Office of Apprenticeship of the Department of Labor or a State apprenticeship agency pursuant to the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H21B9C9F3851D414085FD3946B87B85C4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In the development of an apprenticeships program under this section, the Director shall consult with the Secretary of Labor, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Secretary of Defense, the Director of the National Science Foundation, and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management to leverage existing resources, research, communities of practice, and frameworks for developing cybersecurity apprenticeship programs.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB5B2C3A3B93C4602AB42BE5DA049F947"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Optional use of grants or cooperative agreements</header><text>An apprenticeship program under this section may include entering into a contract or cooperative agreement with or making a grant to an eligible entity if determined appropriate by the Director based on the eligible entity—</text> <paragraph id="H0FCE3F76182543DEA3B036C214386526"><enum>(1)</enum><text>demonstrating experience in implementing and providing career planning and career pathways toward apprenticeship programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49CB2CC378B74A76A1A37C52592780BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>having knowledge of cybersecurity workforce development;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBCA3F96A04B4324A5EA9DE870A8060C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>being eligible to enter into a contract or cooperative agreement with or receive grant funds from the Agency as described in this section;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2836AFCD85E842CFAE6A175E8506FEAF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing students who complete the apprenticeship program with a recognized postsecondary credential;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA10DA7F0A9D7439691F9AF1F37C60F9C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>using related instruction that is specifically aligned with the needs of the Agency and utilizes workplace learning advisors and on-the-job training to the greatest extent possible; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7F1452008A214F0BA936B89754E3454F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>demonstrating successful outcomes connecting graduates of the apprenticeship program to careers relevant to the program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC82E37672DAC4BE09372795CE32329F2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>If the Director enters into an arrangement as described in subsection (e), an eligible entity seeking a contract, cooperative agreement, or grant under the program shall submit to the Director an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Director may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5018AA1B77F94FF3A00C5C5509B0E4FE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to receive a contract, grant, or cooperative agreement under this section, the Director may prioritize an eligible entity that—</text> <paragraph id="HBDDB7B2BC5834C3E8AC1D6E65201FD38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is a member of an industry or sector partnership;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H60FF62CC406146F7922D258DC0E59D2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides related instruction for an apprenticeship program through—</text> <subparagraph id="H45194D78D6D6474E98EBC78218A212EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency, a secondary school, a provider of adult education, an area career and technical education school, or an institution of higher education; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3CCB30D706A44A13AFADFFFC25881333"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an apprenticeship program that was registered with the Department of Labor or a State apprenticeship agency before the date on which the eligible entity applies for the grant under subsection (g);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H19B40A7162E241B1A262EF8CAA146CCB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>works with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, or veterans organizations to transition members of the Armed Forces and veterans to apprenticeship programs in a relevant sector; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9D41BF4B05C7489E967296CA97650C86"><enum>(4)</enum><text>plans to use the grant to carry out the apprenticeship program with an entity that receives State funding or is operated by a State agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1B70049BE2F64A90A9C6BD3A9169452A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Director shall provide technical assistance to eligible entities to leverage the existing job training and education programs of the Agency and other relevant programs at appropriate Federal agencies.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H31AEB827E32342B7ABF27186391BF94D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Excepted service</header><text>Participants in the program may be entered into cybersecurity-specific excepted service positions as determined appropriate by the Director and authorized by section 2208.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD0268A69680B459482FD2878427ED05E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="H4D6645DD03DB4C58BB16CEB1C5C32758"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less than once every 2 years after the establishment of an apprenticeship program under this section, the Director shall submit to Congress a report on the program, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H457D85A661EE4B8491DCEA653B4401E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of—</text> <clause id="H6A7414EBB4504BB9A554C8C3CE0DDD47"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any activity carried out by the Agency under this section; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HA8774FCAF4B44CBA93BD7788AF5DC79E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any entity that enters into a contract or agreement with or receives a grant from the Agency under subsection (e);</text></clause> <clause id="H399C54B0A9094D7BA00BE43C27A27D76"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any activity carried out using a contract, agreement, or grant under this section as described in subsection (e); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB3EF0D4D64A4D62B47D74FEDFDF75CF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>best practices used to leverage the investment of the Federal Government under this section; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD8ABF3A1863C474CA656DB90958ECE65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of the results achieved by the program, including the rate of continued employment at the Agency for participants after completing an apprenticeship program carried out under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0072281A09DE4E6B807B69D636163523"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Performance reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the establishment of an apprenticeship program under this section, and annually thereafter, the Director shall submit to Congress and the Secretary of Labor a report on the effectiveness of the program based on the accountability measures described in clauses (i) and (ii) of section 116(b)(2)(A) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAFDFB162ED0147F987DA484435078D7B"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Agency such sums as necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H07F89A0340F94884848AD48710CD8F24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 2220E the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5B707EB9268545469F571377B773B1AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 2220F. Apprenticeship program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HEBC3B8A4ECC6425BA949E5FE9C3BE809"><enum>4.</enum><header>Pilot program on cyber training for veterans and members of the armed forces transitioning to civilian life</header> <subsection id="HB14F9A0F902E42E7BA2474956E791CE0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H011F71BE633C4512A8AC5FB94F245F47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>The term <term>eligible individual</term> means an individual who is—</text> <subparagraph id="HD8C9904229C644E9A9E22934DE5D64A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a member of the Armed Forces transitioning from service in the Armed Forces to civilian life; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H04229F81B1D946A9AD5754AD041B2E0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a veteran.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE19225D923A4C7F8ED7DAF4279708F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Portable credential</header><text>The term <term>portable credential</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5B3E20C080214BBEA1339721A180CEB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a documented award by a responsible and authorized entity that has determined that an individual has achieved specific learning outcomes relative to a given standard; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF1C16E7FE74947F0BD4DB3CF894E3C77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a degree, diploma, license, certificate, badge, and professional or industry certification that—</text> 
<clause id="H387D2AA8876F415B99D11E0FFF51724D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has value locally and nationally in labor markets, educational systems, or other contexts;</text></clause> <clause id="HB272389673A4463BA6B7C7CAD583BA9F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is defined publicly in such a way that allows educators, employers, and other individuals and entities to understand and verify the full set of skills represented by the credential; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H07329FFD1A234E6B94BD4E305E7C8A7C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>enables a holder of the credential to move vertically and horizontally within and across training and education systems for the attainment of other credentials.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE4D9A23F49BA48F8B3F8D2FAAD122431"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Veteran</header><text>The term <term>veteran</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95BEF4FC76054BE5A7CA0C45B0FFEF66"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Work-based learning</header><text>The term <term>work-based learning</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4F66815C1FF24C74AD8A3DF3C7ABA32A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a pilot program under which the Secretary shall provide cyber-specific training for eligible individuals.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9A170A3A791C4895BAC93CEFC5FC8AF0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The pilot program established under subsection (b) shall incorporate—</text> <paragraph id="H4F492ED5C3D2421F8B2005F1BA237821"><enum>(1)</enum><text>virtual platforms for coursework and training;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32D7F0091F5D485AB134FFE0E4186E7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>hands-on skills labs and assessments;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5048574B568A47168E8F9346766F1E50"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal work-based learning opportunities and programs; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30AE38CD66324E6DAE217945D7B946CB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the provision of portable credentials to eligible individuals who graduate from the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H67739DD865304B2C8935209623FE52BC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Alignment with NICE workforce framework for cybersecurity</header><text>The pilot program established under subsection (b) shall align with the taxonomy, including work roles and associated tasks, knowledge, and skills, from the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education Workforce Framework for Cybersecurity (NIST Special Publication 800–181), or any successor framework.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H15F2C6E8DD224683BC9D7A0EAFAA873F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header> 
<paragraph id="H214C65D6E6E6438F80A7BCC30FCF9E33"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Training, platforms, and frameworks</header><text>In developing the pilot program under subsection (b), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall coordinate with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Labor, and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management to evaluate and, where possible, leverage existing training, platforms, and frameworks of the Federal Government for providing cyber education and training to prevent duplication of efforts.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC68356AA1B0D48A0944B6ABF3426493F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal work-based learning opportunities and programs</header><text>In developing the Federal work-based learning opportunities and programs required under subsection (c)(3), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall coordinate with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Labor, the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, and the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies to identify or create interagency opportunities that will enable the pilot program established under subsection (b) to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4B85FE881725459AAB2C909D2975D0F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>bridge the gap between knowledge acquisition and skills application for participants; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54F47E85AA3049928B5EBD03CA32B9F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>give participants the experience necessary to pursue Federal employment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4DD57148D9E242C79DE3B7F3FDA9615C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Resources</header> 
<paragraph id="H3A3A60F056E24F6F987682FE22E9DECE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any case in which the pilot program established under subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCAEF7B9A597B4867976EBD95B68673B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>uses a program of the Department of Veterans Affairs or platforms and frameworks described in subsection (e)(1), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall take such actions as may be necessary to ensure that those programs, platforms, and frameworks are expanded and resourced to accommodate usage by eligible individuals participating in the pilot program; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6FF0031D5D6142D0B49F3E46642E2BE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not use a program of the Department of Veterans Affairs or platforms and frameworks described in subsection (e)(1), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall take such actions as may be necessary to develop or procure programs, platforms, and frameworks necessary to carry out the requirements of subsection (c) and accommodate the usage by eligible individuals participating in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC084CD177AEA46C1A992C5CB912CEA8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Actions</header><text>Actions described in paragraph (1) may include providing additional funding, staff, or other resources to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3E5F27C9D4DF4B4684BB4B56DBFC58FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide administrative support for basic functions of the pilot program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H763FC3EC098044C0A189A6C4B3ABC82F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure the success and ongoing engagement of eligible individuals participating in the pilot program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA78BF4650F4D4FBF88D7AF3286323BEF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>connect graduates of the pilot program to job opportunities within the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0DFB7421E2FC4EDE8FD9922BF4AAF201"><enum>(D)</enum><text>allocate dedicated positions for term employment to enable Federal work-based learning opportunities and programs for participants to gain the experience necessary to pursue permanent Federal employment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H515A84F3F27A402BACF929D914841549" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal workforce assessment extension</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 304(a) of the Federal Cybersecurity Workforce Assessment Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/301">5 U.S.C. 301</external-xref> note) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>2022</quote> and inserting <quote>2025</quote>.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

