<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEA888E1133E1431B9BA894BC49711D51" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 5008 IH: Health Equity and Access under the Law for Immigrant Families Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5008</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand access to health care services for immigrants by removing legal and policy barriers to health insurance coverage, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDF4616E5F2C84092A512BA3A5E89353A" style="OLC"><section id="H20AECF601F5D4A0B8A6FC98C22CC69BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Health Equity and Access under the Law for Immigrant Families Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HEAL for Immigrant Families Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA0469D80B4F24788A5C1AE3B11EF4884"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><subsection id="H02A6F9469DA0401F97E5279AF99BB84E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H60F81C5ED0F14433B010B5F13D63E1DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Health insurance coverage reduces harmful racial, economic, gender, and health inequities by alleviating cost barriers to, and increasing utilization of, necessary health care services, especially among low-income and underserved populations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H000DEE2EF78F440E8998BA5505907885"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Based solely on their immigration status, many immigrants and their families face legal and policy restrictions on their ability to obtain affordable health insurance coverage through Medicaid, the Children’s Health Insurance Program (CHIP), and the health insurance exchanges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3393F3D8CCA4745AC01640BFF2322C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Lack of health insurance coverage contributes to persistent inequities in the prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of health conditions. This leads to negative health outcomes for immigrants and their families, especially Black, Indigenous, Latinx, Asian, Pacific Islander, and other Immigrants of Color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A266A1C2D7749AC8B671BF8DB261FF9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Black immigrant women often cite cost as a major barrier to health care. Many who are undocumented forgo doctor visits altogether due to the financial burden in addition to consistent racial bias by medical practitioners and racism in health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8318391C2FB5480B988F0366DA0685CD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Nearly half of immigrant women are of reproductive age. Immigrant women, lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ) immigrants, and immigrants with disabilities disproportionately live in households with low incomes and lack health insurance coverage. Legal and policy barriers to affordable health insurance coverage significantly exacerbate their risk of negative pregnancy-related and other reproductive and sexual health outcomes, with lasting health and economic consequences for immigrant women, LGBTQ immigrants, immigrants with disabilities, and their families and society as a whole.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3906B1EF0BFE4319868CF0C72BE7EB1F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Denying health insurance coverage or imposing waiting periods for health insurance coverage on the basis of immigration status unfairly hinders immigrants’ ability to reach and maintain their optimal levels of health and undermines the economic well-being of their families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C093D70C1D54C5FBAFD22952925412B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Like the Hyde amendment’s prohibition on public insurance coverage for abortion care, immigration-related health care eligibility barriers have long curtailed access to abortion. In June 2022, in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization, the Supreme Court of the United States overturned the constitutional right to abortion, exacerbating pre-existing barriers. In the year since the Dobbs decision was issued, 19 States have banned or restricted abortion—disproportionately impacting 15 million women of color and millions of transgender and nonbinary people. Notably, in 2022, 39 percent of all Latinas living in States that were likely to ban abortion following the Dobbs decision were born outside of the United States—this group includes people with varying citizenship statuses, among whom fear of surveillance may be particularly prevalent, due to disproportionate investigation and surveillance that many immigrant communities already face. Bans and restrictions on abortion exacerbate the fear of criminalization in immigrant communities, and contribute to a chilling effect that leads many immigrants to forego reproductive health care and coverage of any kind as they navigate these intersecting risks of criminalization. Polling conducted in 2018 found one in four Latina/o voters (24 percent) had a close family member or friend delay or avoid health care because of fear related to discriminatory immigration policies, and one in five (19 percent) said the same about reproductive health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D2F74938AAA45E48280D5F857E269DF"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensuring access to crucial coverage of reproductive and sexual health services such as contraception and pregnancy-related care through Medicaid and the Affordable Care Act is imperative, with only half (52 percent) of immigrants at risk of unintended pregnancy receiving contraceptive care in the previous year. Many immigrants are being denied the basic human right to make the health care decisions they believe are best for them and their families, including abortion care, simply because of their immigration status. In States along the Southern Border, immigrant communities are subject to interior checkpoints that increase the threat of family separation, deportation, and detention, and compound the harm of abortion restrictions that force people to travel to obtain care. Immigrants living without documentation, in particular, may have no way of obtaining an abortion when immigration enforcement and abortion restrictions combine to prevent them from traveling to a provider. Further, due to the high cost of travel associated with the onslaught of abortion bans, practical support organizations that assist with procedure and travel costs have been experiencing high demand, and struggle with inadequate resources. Accessing support services can be out of reach for those without reliable technology to research and maintain contact with support services, or who encounter linguistic barriers when support services are not able to provide translators. For many, abortion care will be entirely inaccessible due to these compounding barriers, thus exacerbating the need for accessible reproductive and sexual health services such as contraception and pregnancy-related and post-pregnancy care. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB95ED2D974C24BE9951555946107ADC5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>International human rights standards hold that governments have an affirmative obligation to ensure that everyone, including immigrants, can access safe, respectful, culturally and linguistically appropriate, and high-quality pregnancy-related care, including postpartum care, free from discrimination or violence. Medicaid is the Nation’s single largest payer for pregnancy-related care. Nevertheless, barriers to health coverage persist for pregnant and postpartum people, particularly immigrants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDA1A4A727574792BAC4A10D343A1C6D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Immigrants—especially Black, Indigenous, Latinx, Asian, and Pacific Islander immigrants—are among those most harmed by the United States pregnancy-related morbidity and mortality epidemic, which is the worst among high-income nations. Black people are nearly four times more likely than White people to suffer pregnancy-related death, and twice as likely to suffer maternal morbidity. Indigenous people are two and a half times more likely than White people to die from a pregnancy-related death. The majority of United States pregnancy-related deaths are preventable. Lack of access to health care, immigration status, poverty, and exposure to racism, sexism, and xenophobia in and beyond the health care system contribute to the disproportionately high number of pregnancy-related deaths among BIPOC birthing and postpartum people. Unnecessary barriers that limit pregnant and postpartum immigrants’ access to health care undermine their health, safety, and human rights.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26FCDE309A4948F188BBFB6353DD890F"><enum>(11)</enum><text>One in seven United States residents is foreign-born, approximately one in four children in the United States has at least one immigrant parent, and the population of immigrant families in the United States is expected to continue to grow in the coming years. It is therefore in our collective public health and economic interest to remove legal and policy barriers to affordable health insurance coverage that are based on immigration status.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16425B08E1BB4049BE9DEFCEBC360A7E"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Delaying or denying health insurance coverage because of immigration status can impede mental health and substance use prevention and early intervention interventions. Not acknowledging the impacts of trauma can impact mental health and substance use, and conditions may increase in severity without appropriate and consistent support and treatment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D28A5824165445DBD7B243FFCED57ED"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Although individuals granted relief under the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals (DACA) program are authorized to live and work in the United States, they have been unfairly excluded from the definitions of lawfully present and lawfully residing for purposes of health insurance coverage provided through the Department of Health and Human Services, including Medicaid, CHIP, and the health insurance exchanges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FF83412AD1A4827A3381A01BD325870"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On April 26, 2023, the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS) published a proposed rule that would modify the definition of <quote>lawfully present</quote> used to determine eligibility for Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (ACA) health plans and certain other health care programs. Codifying these protections in legislation is crucial to ensure individuals granted relief under the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals (DACA) program and those who gain new forms of administrative relief are not similarly excluded in future administrative action. This is even more imperative as more than a quarter of DACA recipients are currently uninsured as they await the finalization of the proposed rule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H683F82042EF549BAB63C50175ED67DC9"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Since immigration law evolves constantly, new immigration categories for individuals with federally authorized presence in the United States may be created.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEE34934790B46CBA00419C8869719B3"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Some States continue to unwisely restrict Medicaid access for immigrants who have long resided in the United States, fueling significant health inequities and increasing health care costs for individuals and the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF421B64B9B7B4F50AD758909A0B57B5B"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Congress restored Medicaid eligibility for individuals living in the United States under the Compacts of Free Association as part of bipartisan legislation in December 2020 and should build on that success by ensuring all immigrants can access care.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94121E2ADAEC4366BBAE2E643B47FEF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this Act to—</text><paragraph id="H3C9C0CB0E48042AF80BE6AB96F835E2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that all individuals who are lawfully present in the United States are eligible for all federally funded health care programs; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CF4A361389744F9BB10EE8506EF3A5F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>advance the ability of undocumented individuals to obtain health insurance coverage through the health insurance exchanges established under part II of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BF0CFB43272439D984A193983D6654F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>eliminate the authority for States to restrict Medicaid eligibility for lawful permanent residents; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED411AE88C604564914A321144C3A7FB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>eliminate other barriers to accessing Medicaid, CHIP, and other medical assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H64920C5248534C5384DF323194C0E336"><enum>3.</enum><header>Removing barriers to health coverage for lawfully residing individuals</header><subsection id="H187BC33679524C84B777FBDC1A3E54E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>Section 1903(v)(4) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(v)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H994B7DEEC2D34109803CB6626FCD9B0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HF48E504F77034B8394A6CC1419F4CCDC" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H99F0731812EE403C845CFE9C756E8CDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding sections 401(a), 402(b), 403, and 421 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996, a State shall provide medical assistance under this title, to individuals who are lawfully residing in the United States (including individuals described in paragraph (1), battered individuals described in section 431(c) of such Act, and individuals with an approved or pending application for deferred action or other federally authorized presence), if they otherwise meet the eligibility requirements for medical assistance under the State plan approved under this title (other than the requirement of the receipt of aid or assistance under title IV, supplemental security income benefits under title XVI, or a State supplementary payment).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7997A3A4D59647F9AE03A977A13203D9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (B) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HDE7B6812483B4CB18473BD7E38E05B36" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HDBC16CB29A114FC2B9341796F2A571C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>No debt shall accrue under an affidavit of support against any sponsor of an individual provided medical assistance under subparagraph (A) on the basis of provision of assistance to such individual and the cost of such assistance shall not be considered as an unreimbursed cost.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE966804A1FE542718F0219F154307514"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><subparagraph id="H403B3200686940EFA4B315C30FA30DD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an election by the State under subparagraph (A)</quote> and inserting <quote>the application of subparagraph (A)</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H133F4E29338348B891127307E70BB33B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or be lawfully present</quote> after <quote>lawfully reside</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE598EFBD5764EB39A6D44FDD180BAD7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or present</quote> after <quote>lawfully residing</quote> each place it appears.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H909509D6420A4FC09A6F4B6B887D14C6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>Subparagraph (N) of section 2107(e)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397gg">42 U.S.C. 1397gg(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H40EE11A660AE48278A1C85DF4F87EBD5" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H878CC4757F6540FE9883C1B303BA80E1"><enum>(N)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of section 1903(v) (relating to lawfully present individuals and undocumented immigrants).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H8BBB3DEDA3A04CBB9F3AA252D0AA6B3A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H7AAFA19F3B014FBDA4488D0A6F547E1B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act and shall apply to services furnished on or after the date that is 90 days after such date of enactment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H932D5BF675B34FD7856D952921AB97A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception if State legislation required</header><text>In the case of a State plan for medical assistance under title XIX, or a State child health plan under title XXI, of the Social Security Act which the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines requires State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) in order for the plan to meet the additional requirements imposed by the amendments made by this section, the respective State plan shall not be regarded as failing to comply with the requirements of such title solely on the basis of its failure to meet these additional requirements before the first day of the first calendar quarter beginning after the close of the first regular session of the State legislature that begins after the date of enactment of this Act. For purposes of the previous sentence, in the case of a State that has a 2-year legislative session, each year of such session shall be deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB085F26B617C4391BFD86344E89DFEB5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Consistency in health insurance coverage for individuals with federally authorized presence, including deferred action</header><subsection id="H9126E38BE7C74183961C62ECB1AE0F6A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of eligibility under any of the provisions described in subsection (b), all individuals granted federally authorized presence in the United States shall be considered to be lawfully present in the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H297E9AD81B224D10A46A8992C80FA0A9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provisions described</header><text>The provisions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H2E2B5F46D6B048DEAAB46AB5433B8529"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exchange eligibility</header><text>Section 1411 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFD455C8462A4B789ACCC96CFFD0A91B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reduced cost-sharing eligibility</header><text>Section 1402 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18071">42 U.S.C. 18071</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H864CAC8F614B4101878E5F6A8DE0282B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Premium subsidy eligibility</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">Section 36B</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">26 U.S.C. 36B</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FDD0217C9A141F9BA6340951DEBD4C0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Medicaid and chip eligibility</header><text>Titles XIX and XXI of the Social Security Act, including under section 1903(v) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(v)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E2B4F2DFF8645258AAB4F6557D86F10"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="HADD4C60BA94946A482E92855587CBA7F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42DF1861B4F3426BBA2408EFC7423833"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transition through special enrollment period</header><text>In the case of an individual described in subsection (a) who, before the first day of the first annual open enrollment period under subparagraph (B) of section 1311(c)(6) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031(c)(6)</external-xref>) beginning after the date of enactment of this Act, is granted federally authorized presence in the United States and who, as a result of such subsection, qualifies for a subsidy under a provision described in paragraph (2) or (3) of subsection (b), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish a special enrollment period under subparagraph (C) of such section 1311(c)(6) during which such individual may enroll in qualified health plans through Exchanges under title I of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act and qualify for such a subsidy. For such an individual who has been granted federally authorized presence in the United States as of the date of enactment of this Act, such special enrollment period shall begin not later than 90 days after such date of enactment. Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed as affecting the authority of the Secretary to establish additional special enrollment periods under such subparagraph (C).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7CDC5481E4524F3C9E7638F2778B2951"><enum>5.</enum><header>Removing citizenship and immigration barriers to access to affordable health care under the ACA</header><subsection id="H0292EF0885544B08A6B718B74F88EEB7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H2D465C312FFB4E0A805BB29DBB921276"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Premium tax credits</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">Section 36B</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HEA7B303A89504B51B23B1E4C75812ADF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)(B)—</text><clause id="H69D63BACDCCF49FD9389F847B1A73CC1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by amending the heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Special rule for certain individuals ineligible for medicaid due to status</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H58E8B14750754B86A066B04D503DE45E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF9F4A07B3E4B4EDEA5763323BBF8DC66" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H44EFEEABC184420B9F2A994D4744A819" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the taxpayer is a noncitizen who is not eligible for the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act by reason of the individual’s immigration status,</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAABA2A5DEB1444180638CB1533548D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5257D5B470FD4A3EAADA588A53363071"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost-sharing reductions</header><text>Section 1402 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18071">42 U.S.C. 18071</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (e) and redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89572552673F4184987A588F8CA56697"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Basic health program eligibility</header><text>Section 1331(e)(1)(B) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18051">42 U.S.C. 18051(e)(1)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>lawfully present in the United States,</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07E15B247C0C4C169635FAA455606762"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Restrictions on federal payments</header><text>Section 1412 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18082">42 U.S.C. 18082</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (d) and redesignating subsection (e) as subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5770C16FD354461FA1AEAA934D1BC405"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Requirement to maintain minimum essential coverage</header><text>Subsection (d) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5000A">section 5000A</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking paragraph (3) and by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H335D770A85F34EF2AB809A97EF8312EB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="HEBC706D351E7438D9712AAB069BBD46E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text>Section 1411(a) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18081">42 U.S.C. 18081(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (1) and redesignating paragraphs (2), (3), and (4) as paragraphs (1), (2), and (3), respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65AF24EE9BFC41789612F4A84F16CA0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified individuals</header><text>Section 1312(f) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18032">42 U.S.C. 18032(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H17D99131FEF14620B6B1B3ECA950C496"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">; access limited to citizens and lawful residents</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H600490D1A16048D99973AF3218F526AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5048B9E7AC824DB6AA4DCB667DBBE40E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to years, plan years, and taxable years, as applicable, beginning after December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6DCFE60075154A4C802DBDDA9432D337"><enum>6.</enum><header>State option to expand Medicaid and CHIP to individuals without lawful presence</header><subsection id="H06CB99C7225040EFA4569EDB1D6F18D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><paragraph id="H2E0375CC831245F590C02F70B90853B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(a)(10)(A)(ii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H56C76E039AEA4741838A199DA73DB4AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (XXII), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3315336FFE6046F782B92268BD48F1DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subclause (XXIII), by striking the semicolon and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB8F4D05C5224F3EA2BD9FBB09E7830A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB217207F13F5418DAC8652A97062D121" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="H2E056E93195743349E17F9D8BA8A35BA"><enum>(XXIV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who would be eligible under the State plan (or waiver of such plan) under this title if they were citizens of the United States;</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5C51C507F0A4CA9A841ED827356C3AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1905(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(a)</external-xref>) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H26C9E1FC6AC0437CA8002A82F29F5854"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter designated as clause (xxvi), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0A8656AFCA44F8AAE855E3FD7E8F7FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter designated as clause (xxvii), by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFD5C70C7C784A17BED65BC64A379587"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after the matter designated as clause (xxvii) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC287CA8E997D4F9AA604CAE03988007D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HF6921E395F8C4F8098A2609FE0E93F32" indent="up2"><enum>(xxviii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">individuals described in section 1902(a)(10)(A)(ii)(XXIV),</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3994DB0E283A4C5197E7CFE2999D9A50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>Title XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 2112 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4E5D59D1A2EA44F5A99E9C2FE190FA25" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H08577250DF4F4742BAB2A0CA6E2F4D97"><enum>2112A.</enum><header>State option to provide coverage for individuals without lawful presence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State may elect through an amendment to its State child health plan under section 2102 to treat an individual as a targeted low-income child or a targeted low-income pregnant woman for purposes of this title if such individual would otherwise be included as such a child or such a pregnant woman (as applicable) under such plan if the individual were a citizen of the United States.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4A21DF2A9EE3415FA67B69F2814FE952"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Nonapplication of eligibility prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401(a) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1611">42 U.S.C. 1611(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>The preceding sentence shall not apply with respect to a noncitizen’s eligibility under a State plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XIX of the Social Security Act or under a State child health plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XXI of such Act to the extent that such State has elected to make such individual so eligible pursuant to section 1902(a)(10)(A)(ii)(XXIV) or 2112A of such Act, respectively.</quote>. </text></subsection></section><section id="HC26EFD92107944C6A0305EC2B6213CD9"><enum>7.</enum><header>Preserving access to coverage</header><subsection id="HC9E1F89A981F4622973A044817A2B57A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, including the amendments made by this Act, shall prevent lawfully present noncitizens who are ineligible for full benefits under the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act from securing a credit for which such lawfully present noncitizens would be eligible under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">section 36B(c)(1)(B)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and under the Medicaid provisions for lawfully present noncitizens, as in effect on the date prior to the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA793DE056944BEDA33B75797E18A2BF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the term <term>full benefits</term> means, with respect to an individual and State, medical assistance for all services covered under the State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act that is not less in amount, duration, or scope, or is determined by the Secretary of Health and Human Services to be substantially equivalent to the medical assistance available for an individual described in section 1902(a)(10)(A)(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)(A)(i)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="H2436EC082798451381A3740C33B9589E"><enum>8.</enum><header>Removing barriers to health coverage for lawfully present individuals in Medicare</header><subsection id="H6CE8DB0E208745169D1B2FBEE085A9F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Part A</header><text>Section 1818(a)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395i-2">42 U.S.C. 1395i–2(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>an alien</quote> and all that follows through <quote>under this section</quote> and inserting <quote>an individual who is lawfully present in the United States, including individuals with an approved or pending application for deferred action or other federally authorized presence</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H12120D3405934466B702EAC5F5C3B691"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Part B</header><text>Section 1836(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395o">42 U.S.C. 1395o(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>an alien</quote> and all that follows through <quote>under this part</quote> and inserting <quote>an individual who is lawfully present in the United States, including individuals with an approved or pending application for deferred action or other federally authorized presence</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4A92E2011A8F49E2B83D8004FB21D0F5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Lawfully present defined</header><text>The term <quote>lawfully present</quote> shall include, at a minimum, all immigration categories that are treated as lawfully present for purposes of the title XIX program as amended by section 3.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

