<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H49D233C4741B4959B02621ED1B69A27B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6803 IH: Grandfamilies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6803</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide greater support for grandfamilies and older caregiver relatives.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1E795265C92A46A0A26F4416422F4071" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HF1448419DFD0417EACA10A1DB7388ECC"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grandfamilies Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H116497657B0B483CB9AFD256347C5D66"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increasing access to Social Security benefits for children who live with grandparents or other family members</header><subsection id="HD322E2599E744686B7D7BA32089F3BB5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/401">42 U.S.C. 401 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7058617BB49743069EA4361793843EA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 202(d)—</text><subparagraph id="H24DE9F5C0D5F45B1AEE4311BA52113ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(C), by inserting <quote>except as provided in paragraph (9),</quote> before <quote>was dependent</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41C0159D4EC048AF87B1B4106BAA41CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (9) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="other" act-name="" id="HFD4B2C8EA6394CF2BB3E18172A904951" other-style="archaic"><paragraph id="H8C713554DA8942B0B87DB7CB2AD0FECB" indent="up1"><enum>(9)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5A9E703A4D3D43E7AAB602667BA4181C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a child who is the child of an individual under clause (3) of the first sentence of section 216(e) and is not a child of such individual under clause (1) or (2) of such first sentence, the criteria specified in subparagraph (B) shall apply instead of the criteria specified in subparagraph (C) of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B3EBCE2C1424FE197315EE64C5705D0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The criteria of this subparagraph are that—</text><clause id="H55699B7480FE44C2988F544CF9F79B35"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the child has been living with such individual in the United States for a period of not less than 12 months;</text></clause><clause id="HCD309EAACF0D4467A0CAD36082F73499"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the child has been receiving not less than ½ of the child's support from such individual for a period of not less than 12 months; and</text></clause><clause id="HAA09BB9816AD4E4F968CDC805A198B36"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the period during which the child was living with such individual began before the child attained age 18.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A3D97A0F9294B309EA98FEF9327A5E3" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>In the case of a child who is less than 12 months old, such child shall be deemed to meet the requirements of subparagraph (B) if, on the date the child attains 1 year of age, such child has lived with such individual in the United States and received at least ½ of the child's support from such individual for substantially all of the period which began on the date of such child's birth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H28404C8E99F2422CAC315250AF11FB95"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 216(e), in the first sentence—</text><subparagraph id="H8962225E3C9A47D39196241D934A6373"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>grandchild or stepgrandchild of an individual or his spouse</quote> and inserting <quote>grandchild, stepgrandchild, or other first-degree, second-degree, third-degree, fourth-degree, or fifth-degree relative of an individual or the individual's spouse</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C6BA152D7184F7987B609A1BCABCCD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>was no natural or adoptive parent</quote> and inserting <quote>is no living natural or adoptive parent</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAFDC7D8BB0A4DA38E5673799AB20075"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>was under a disability</quote> and inserting <quote>is under a disability</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B9185E40BCF42A2B5B4B9E2BFDD7584"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking <quote>living at the time</quote> and all that follows through <quote>, or (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (B)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63E3930CD8A44BE4A94D0AC18FE4EFE4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or (C) the person has been in the custody of such individual pursuant to a court order for a period of not less than 12 months</quote> before the first period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5A2117A7F6184AD2AA814BBE40C9D290"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 202(d)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/402">42 U.S.C. 402(d)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H088A7DCFF30D4D5799B4CCA3B003E385"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraphs (A) and (B) and subparagraph (C) or paragraph (9) (as applicable)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98F4AEEB33C046B592F1D677DD0A4E3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subparagraphs (B) and (C)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (B) and subparagraph (C) or paragraph (9) (as applicable)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H728E649B031D462CB9E9EEEE16849FB1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H96210CFB14D2405C93E082047B435581"><enum>3.</enum><header>Eliminating barriers to TANF for children, older caregiver relatives, and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><subsection id="HF151DE69923E47E9B01FEAE7EA50C53D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Broadening good cause exception to requirement To provide information on noncustodial parents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 454(29)(A)(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/654">42 U.S.C. 654(29)(A)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>best interests of the child</quote> and inserting <quote>best interests of the child, including, if enforcement procedures against a non-custodial parent of the child are initiated, whether such procedures will impede the parent's ability to reunify with the child in the future</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H783F37008673406F80F4AC586BC5CDD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disregard of nonparent caregiver relative income, assets, and resources in child-Only cases</header><paragraph id="H621E9655355E4D5B9BA0766774B461C8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="HAA639366B3DF4B7EB4A03C0A8B6F7248"><paragraph id="HA448C8E049C34EA289B113EADDF7D56F"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Disregard of income, assets, and resources for nonparent caregiver relatives in child-only cases</header><subparagraph id="HE7003DCB264C4901B26E1CB77F6B897F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to a minor child who does not reside in the same household as a parent of the child, a State to which a grant is made under section 403 shall not take into account the income, assets, or resources of such child's nonparent caregiver relative who is not seeking assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) on their own behalf in determining whether the child is eligible for assistance under any such program, or in determining the amount or types of such assistance to be provided to the child.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E10C0912C244006903CD1FF4637259F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply in the case of a State program—</text><clause id="HD909F349A7D44B3B8562521BA4F9772D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is operated specifically for children living with nonparent caregiver relatives;</text></clause><clause id="H4396BF452A094CB781C02C9C9ECD2013"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that provides monthly financial assistance to a child living with a nonparent caregiver relative in an amount that is greater than the amount of assistance that the child would receive on the child's own behalf under the State program funded under this part;</text></clause><clause id="H93472BDFD68B45CFAA92536E91AF86C8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that is separate from the State program funded under this part; and</text></clause><clause id="H697121A855E542648C648331BF6645E4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>that is described in the State plan submitted under section 402.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DEACEC7D66B4F528D288E128E5972F6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H93E6D64A01314C8FA32FCDD151313E6E"><paragraph id="H807E0B4EFD0A4EAA906A9407FC24F96B"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to disregard income, assets, and resources of nonparent caregiver relative in child-only cases</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a State to which a grant is made under section 403 in a fiscal year has violated section 408(a)(13) during the fiscal year, the Secretary shall reduce the grant payable to the State under section 403(a)(1) for the immediately succeeding fiscal year by an amount equal to 3 percent of the State family assistance grant.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29AA3068422749828939F4025CC533AC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eliminating 5-Year cap on assistance in child-Only cases</header><paragraph id="H4EF18193D7754B0C93AA23F07429097B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408(a)(7) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(a)(7)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H45DB4A0E0A884C34B71A16933F2A7C0A"><subparagraph id="H7C763887D7E84197BF401FA1D7E9CDF8"><enum>(H)</enum><header>No limit for child-only cases</header><text>A State shall not limit the number of months of assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) for a family in which all adults in the family—</text><clause id="HFF2F4D552715492BAED42A7BBD4E1CD4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are nonparent caregiver relatives of a child who does not reside in the same household of the parent of the child; and</text></clause><clause id="H669E4AA826714439A92E263F5280F3E0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>do not receive assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) on their own behalf.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8503B27B28D64FB3B54DA45FC620B64A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>), as previously amended by this section, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H864A4FE94B214EC4B25B02F7661F78EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by inserting <quote>(other than subparagraph (H))</quote> after <quote>section 408(a)(7)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2882F6E18C3B47E8AA121B7CD4437D0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H1E96586A4B9D4B0A8FB62C4E22758192"><paragraph id="H1B56E1C44B694428A6BCCB43E07ABAA0"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to comply with 5-year cap exemptions</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a State to which a grant is made under section 403 in a fiscal year has violated subparagraph (H) of section 408(a)(7) during the fiscal year, the Secretary shall reduce the grant payable to the State under section 403(a)(1) for the immediately succeeding fiscal year by an amount equal to 3 percent of the State family assistance grant</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC67CEEFA13F84A51ACD79241204590A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemption from work requirements for nonparent caregiver relatives in child-Only cases</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H20409E497DC14536A41C31DEB56D1DD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H96B5979C61B149A69921BA75E201C2DC"><subsection commented="no" id="HF2F773BF0B7742F6961D0C0764C634F2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>State required To exempt nonparent caregiver relatives from work participation in child-Only cases</header><text>A State shall not require an individual to engage in work if the individual—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H89B65999F4DD4B2D8CAB891E39D67A21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is the nonparent caregiver relative of a child who does not reside in the same household as a parent of the child; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HED945FBD162E41299E321BA252D957C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>resides in a household in which no adult receives assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) on their own behalf.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HC33309D5C2D143B985DF020035153159"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>), as previously amended by this section, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" act-name="" id="H563326DB00FB4052A9D40544AA338537"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E913F2DC36E479FB30D472C11B3880C"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to comply with work participation exemptions</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a State to which a grant is made under section 403 in a fiscal year has violated subsection (h) of section 408 during the fiscal year, the Secretary shall reduce the grant payable to the State under section 403(a)(1) for the immediately succeeding fiscal year by an amount equal to 3 percent of the State family assistance grant.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDFA7D803AF674A23A65D79AAF9AF2F45"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eliminating 5-Year cap on assistance for older caregiver relatives and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8794D0C80D94BDAB37E4A66889A1EF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408(a)(7) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(a)(7)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (c)(1), is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H26C17B0825734E909B6E8E71BFD8CE42"><subparagraph id="HB7703EABF2BA4377B444E062F9B805A6"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Non-application of limit to older caregiver relatives and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><clause id="H37C9982551004EF4B6E96B453F215937"><enum>(i)</enum><header>No limit for older caregiver relatives and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply and a State shall not limit the number of months of assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) based on receipt of such assistance by an individual who is an older caregiver relative or a caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability (as such terms are defined for purposes of paragraph (14)).</text></clause><clause id="HBAF4F486644942E3B330AA610140B9BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Disregard of months of assistance</header><text>In determining the number of months for which a family that includes an adult who has received assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)), the State shall disregard any month for which such assistance was provided with respect to the family during which such adult was an older caregiver relative or a caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability (as such terms are defined for purposes of paragraph (14)).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F07AB952E5A41C9B9407B127F938CD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>), as previously amended by this section, is amended—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF7F75346CC84AFA9AD4C43CA0FA4B39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by inserting <quote>or (I)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (H)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4573DD67CDF44DBB6D336F6DB5E7684"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (18), by inserting <quote>or (I)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (H)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0DFF652FC07640C7903521CF22E748CE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exemption from work requirements for older caregiver relatives and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><paragraph id="H4CC09B0165294EC6B98BAB8E229CEA5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608</external-xref>), by subsection (d)(1), is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HB7953077271E4385AA18BC074B984C37"><subsection id="HDE449B3431AC4575862BB09CB04BBFE8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>State required To exempt caregiver relatives from work participation where caregiver receives assistance</header><text>A State shall not require an individual to engage in work, and, at the option of the State and on a case-by-case basis, may disregard such individual in determining the participation rates under section 407(a), if the individual—</text><paragraph id="HEC19B24DF2734FAEAFDDBD7A9A088ECE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is an older caregiver relative or a caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability (as such terms are defined for purposes of subsection (a)(14)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5D221ABBEF847E39D6AD37CA945C304"><enum>(2)</enum><text>directly receives assistance on the individual’s own behalf under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE322AC7F065D4C1E81A8064D02DF130D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Paragraph (18) of section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (d)(2), is amended by inserting <quote>or (i)</quote> after <quote>subsection (h)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC27E072BE016412EA312D1C0AE9B8D0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>402(a)(1)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/602">42 U.S.C. 602(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HBF92018FC0704CAF92A02C783E62AFFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by inserting <quote>and subject to subsections (h) and (i) of section 408</quote> before the period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE992936FD8A144269F03E004C4C9EA87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>and subject to subsections (h) and (i) of section 408</quote> before the period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9437E6DBFCFC44DEA0820300A3538C7A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Disregard of income, assets, and resources for older caregiver relatives</header><paragraph id="HC18452E0452A4EDD8D757EBE4B4AD949"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 408(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(a)</external-xref>), as previously amended by this section, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="H2CBE7E2A50744B5A8FD6CE1E0407BF34"><paragraph id="H7479102B53A24B1D897218280B1212A5"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Disregard of income, assets, and resources for older caregiver relatives and caregiver relatives caring for a child with a disability</header><subparagraph id="H7CEFB4C6411346428A42A2CC0AA2F1DC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In determining the eligibility for, and amount of, assistance under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)) for a family that includes an individual who is an older caregiver relative (as defined in subparagraph (B)) or a caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability (as defined in subparagraph (C)), a State to which a grant is made under section 403 shall not take into account the income, assets, or resources of that individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13D8FCD1488042DCBEE494612F0892AE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition of older caregiver relative</header><clause id="H340C4C0D27CE47CEB5D15FBACDBF283B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>older caregiver relative</term> means an individual who—</text><subclause id="HDC0BBC3DD9B4418FBB274AC363594695"><enum>(I)</enum><text>subject to clause (ii), has attained age 55; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D01CDA933674DE9882E039FE3692573"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is the primary caregiver for a minor child who—</text><item id="HC00ADDCCA98E4F6A91C180B8A035252A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is living with the individual;</text></item><item id="H1DC1113A4F774516A56AA480E0A2004D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>does not have a parent living in the home; and</text></item><item id="H072B38D7194D4FE9A5163FFFB2647463"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>is a grandchild, stepgrandchild, or other first-degree, second-degree, third-degree, fourth-degree, or fifth-degree relative of the individual or the individual's spouse.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HF033474CAB6C4B1895A6197BEB7F6965"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>State option to modify age criterion</header><text>At the option of a State, such term shall include an individual who has not attained age 55.</text></clause><clause id="H02867242E91F406CB48397A0DEF2380A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Determination to be made by State</header><text>The determination of whether an individual meets the criteria described in clause (i)(II) shall be made by the State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H412DD3C1D9654E0BB8EF62D4C8F2BB35"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Definition of caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD83FD09C773242B2B2D1F2E36C6F6CFD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>caregiver relative caring for a child with a disability</term> means an individual, regardless of age, who is the primary caregiver for a minor child who—</text><subclause id="H9D82BC5DC70046F4A3B41A28E6345C9A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is living with the individual;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA1220E42068E418BADD05438936694F7"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a child, grandchild, stepgrandchild, or other first-degree, second-degree, third-degree, fourth-degree, or fifth-degree relative of the individual or the individual's spouse; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HACC7D62D61584DC09E3FD0ADCC7588B7"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a disability, as defined in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>)).</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6C9EDB7119743C3928A4D797C5964C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determination to be made by State</header><text>The determination of whether an individual meets the criteria described in clause (i) shall be made by the State.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H39F3A14B8B4E45CEA27AD9C50AB89D1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Section 409(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)</external-xref>), as previously amended by this section, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" act-name="" id="H2968D13F87494146B522EF697C739019"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95CCD3A5BD804F328CB40842BFE78B44"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to disregard income, assets, and resources for older caregiver relatives</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a State to which a grant is made under section 403 in a fiscal year has violated section 408(a)(14) during the fiscal year, the Secretary shall reduce the grant payable to the State under section 403(a)(1) for the immediately succeeding fiscal year by an amount equal to 3 percent of the State family assistance grant.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D209D4C3F2E45058B1983A496B167F7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H346A3FEC3E374E1F9E12087AC21A1A2F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCACA871A79894F75BB8DA09E3474A063"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delay permitted</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAAAC5429DDA0453DB49113E2ED297DB1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before the date described in subparagraph (B), a State plan under title IV of the Social Security Act shall not be regarded as failing to comply with an additional requirement imposed on the plan by this section if the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines that such additional requirement—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE7C621D7C64843EC8D3D1EA9BECEDDDE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>requires State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) in order for the plan to meet such additional requirement; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32C7FC30AAC047EB8FBC2BF2A8F792E8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>could not practicably be met by the plan before such date.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CCF24F77DFE4C2EA4355DBFF6F945D2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Date described</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the date described in this subparagraph is, with respect to a State, the first day of the first calendar quarter beginning after the close of the first regular session of the State legislature that begins after the date of enactment of this section. For purposes of the previous sentence, in the case of a State that has a 2-year legislative session, each year of such session shall be deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD453E1F7AF484A21902DE3DC6EE9B702"><enum>4.</enum><header>Improving the collection of child support for families receiving TANF assistance</header><subsection id="H40865F204A94408F96FF03FB40D83527"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 454 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/654">42 U.S.C. 654</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4742BD0C44F44BFBACB21CE085095276"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (30) through (34) as paragraphs (31) through (35), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H561FD81B42844321B33A7972401E69BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (29) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H545B3D7F9E604CD3B0EF9B9E0EA79C26"><paragraph id="HFFF1C60C90F248FFAB652C1AEB2CC833"><enum>(30)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a description of—</text><subparagraph id="H69A3DD61CC6446D6B6C20BD94A0A36E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the methods used by the State to determine whether an individual who has applied for or is receiving assistance under the State program funded under part A, the State program under part E, the State program under title XIX, or the supplemental nutrition assistance program, as defined under section 3(h) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2012">7 U.S.C. 2012(h)</external-xref>), is cooperating in good faith with the State in establishing paternity or in establishing, modifying, or enforcing a support order, as provided in paragraph (29);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H339B83DD2A8441C9833150953809E2CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State’s process for determining in a timely manner whether such an individual satisfies the cooperation requirement described in subparagraph (A) due to the individual’s participation in another State or Federal assistance program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D8EA576A9DA4085B3B5BBB005D55BE1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the good cause or other exceptions to the cooperation requirement that the State recognizes, including an explanation of any special requirements or considerations for a relative caregiver seeking to apply for such an exception; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B947B34835C48BCBA4FD50FC2FB951B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how the State makes clear to an individual who has applied for or is receiving assistance under a program referred to in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H22ED0A6939E14B3FA58D3D85039A091D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>what, if anything, the individual needs to do in order to satisfy the cooperation requirement, including explaining to the individual how the individual might satisfy the requirement through participation in another State or Federal assistance program;</text></clause><clause id="H3BD32D90EE834DB69F8D40AD6C3E3CA0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effect on the individual’s eligibility to receive assistance under a program referred to in subparagraph (A), and under other State or Federal assistance programs, if the individual fails to satisfy the cooperation requirement; and</text></clause><clause id="HB248B29153BB47CCB917F0CC27B4F95E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the good cause or other exceptions to the cooperation requirement for which the individual may be eligible, including if a standard of proof is required to qualify for each exception and an explanation of any special requirements or considerations for caregiver relatives;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3CFD93DF573340BF8750C60FED0CFB2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H594D00B1920B4ABCBE852D959B57E870"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 452(k)(1), by striking <quote>section 454(31)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 454(32)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF710738AC64A4C5FBA8D2AF40FF73BFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 454, in the matter following paragraph (35) (as redesignated by subsection (a)) by striking <quote>paragraph (33)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (34)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB4EB635FC88D4FD49BCCE54808FDC1B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA73B94C4AA254544AAF4EDCEA47311C2"><enum>5.</enum><header>Encouraging States to adopt temporary guardianship laws</header><subsection id="H869446ACCD8543979A55F6FFF2EC08E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 474(a)(7) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/674">42 U.S.C. 674(a)(7)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(or, in the case of a State that has in effect for the quarter a temporary guardianship law (as defined in section 475(14)), 75 percent)</quote> after <quote>50 percent</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD5E0D4FD05204D1FA4BE1310E1EA5AF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 475 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/675">42 U.S.C. 675</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HA914080711594FF695B0F944D384F6D6"><paragraph id="H24685F6FB7434CB5B1312BBBB3C3059F" indent="up1"><enum>(14)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H189FB30BBC0A44F49AF94DE2119040A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>temporary guardianship law</term> means a State law that allows for the establishment, by operation of such law and through an easily navigable simple civil process, of a relationship between a child and a nonparent caregiver who has taken responsibility for caring for the child in the absence of the child's parents in which some of the parental rights with respect to the child are transferred to the caregiver for a specified period of time which may be extended or renewed, except that the total period of time for which such rights are transferred to the caregiver (including any extensions or renewals) shall not exceed a maximum period of time (as established by the State).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA232F0D299F4478491F77A3F61B26DA4" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the process established under a law described in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H99C00EE266344F138C19905A7B71A7D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">court fees shall be waived or reduced; and</text></clause><clause id="H303EB130C0544CA3A4249E9AF0CCB513"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any court forms or filings related to the process are easy enough to understand that a nonparent caregiver who has taken responsibility for caring for the child in the absence of the child's parents could reasonably complete such forms or filings without legal assistance.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD0D2C97E834141A892BE22969935D6D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9A7F04404FC54137B3E8692F7AFAA14D"><enum>6.</enum><header>Guidance</header><subsection id="H5329BB02C5D74E29B3FA628583DA7813"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Guidance to States on ensuring awareness of child welfare system among kinship caregivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue guidance to States on ways to ensure that kinship caregivers who receive assistance under a State program funded under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/609">42 U.S.C. 609(a)(7)(B)(i)</external-xref>)) are—</text><paragraph id="H820B8E089B0D49B9BC55B707815EF57A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provided with information about any appropriate assistance and services available to them through the child welfare system of the State, including eligibility for foster care licensure and pathways to guardianship assistance programs or adoption subsidies, and how to access such assistance and services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA69F955D99340AA8799EFBC81C886C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>referred to any kinship navigator program operated by the State.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7599285CC7CB4B34A1561FC331F042CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance on coordinating assistance for caregivers</header><text>Not later than the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue guidance for States identifying options for State programs, including programs funded under title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>), programs funded under the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3001">42 U.S.C. 3001 et seq.</external-xref>), and other relevant programs that are jointly funded or administered by States and the Federal Government, to collaborate, coordinate, and streamline outreach to, and processing of applications of assistance, for grandparents and older relative caregivers or kinship caregivers caring for grandchildren and other relative children residing with them. The options identified in such guidance shall include best practices for State programs to coordinate with the National Technical Assistance Center on Grandfamilies and Kinship Families established under section 2922 of the American Rescue Plan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3020g">42 U.S.C. 3020g</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HBD4FAD51293E4A4C8ADBE9C3B2BF1D77"><enum>7.</enum><header>State support plans for grandparents caring for grandchildren</header><subsection id="H435F7A5E3C6440F38736ED2F8D97D334"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the first day of the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act, from amounts appropriated to carry out this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall award grants to States for purposes of developing State support plans for grandparents caring for grandchildren and other relatives caring for relative children.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1BF7FCB7EA184D1C9D2566C5E8202C43"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A State support plan for grandparents caring for grandchildren and other relatives caring for relative children that is funded by a grant under this section shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H9D15AFE2EE514ED2A2696E81EFC0130E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An initial assessment of the state of grandparents caring for grandchildren and other relatives caring for relative children in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE528D3382DE442F9891F85A0DE8BD94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A plan for how appropriate State agencies can collaborate in their efforts to provide financial support, housing services, and other services and supports to grandparents caring for grandchildren and other relatives caring for relative children.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAF2AF82A7E24C1CA1C6180EDD756B54"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Steps that the State proposes to take over the next 5 years to ensure that grandparents caring for grandchildren and other relatives caring for relative children have necessary resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1A90013E0394629A55A74D6484A2E6F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A plan to simplify or combine application requirements for State public assistance programs to reduce administrative burdens on recipients, with a focus on families consisting of grandparents or other older caregiver relatives raising relative children.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97AD302F40504ACEB74E039F9132803E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A plan to incorporate in the State support plan—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67B659A2ED1B4962AD71769CA183F14D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 1 recommendation from the most recent report to Congress of the Advisory Council to Support Grandparents Raising Grandchildren (provided that such report was released not more than 5 years before the date on which the State is awarded a grant under this section); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6C75F0EC36243C1AA75A31BC8EE3CEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">least 1 recommendation from the Administration for Community Living.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3E21808CBE949CFA06C69893DEF743A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination with National Technical Assistance Center on Grandfamilies and Kinship Families</header><text>The National Technical Assistance Center on Grandfamilies and Kinship Families established under section 2922 of the American Rescue Plan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3020g">42 U.S.C. 3020g</external-xref>) is encouraged to coordinate with States on the development of State support plans funded by grants under this section.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA7095D75B83409EA1A18DB0B618C6DC"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2ED034FE4F09449AA1197397870B783D"><enum>8.</enum><header>Grandfamilies and kinship families alliance grants</header><subsection id="H900B34C5C8BC464C936A1C248892182C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purposes of this section are—</text><paragraph id="HCDD0E9F6299C46F08B00160D835F7B2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide funds, through the Administration for Community Living, to strengthen and support grassroots efforts that address the unique needs of grandfamilies or kinship families, including those supporting children with disabilities or those navigating through mental health concerns or trauma; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H189F29BD9D0D4896B7F488D711766BEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to establish cross-sector partnerships, in order to establish interagency collaborations and foster the integration of new or existing activities, designed to increase the health, well-being, financial security, or legal standing of members of grandfamilies or kinship families.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1DFBDFE9AB9470696F3D5DE127F4D83"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE25B0FB969EA432F99B3A07B51D3D11C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Administration for Community Living.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B25A122382A4AFE99F547125D76422F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cross-sector</header><text>The term <term>cross-sector</term>, used with respect to an entity, means that members of the entity represent different service-related sectors, such as aging, child welfare, income support, food and nutrition, legal, health and mental health, education, housing, or disability services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF4DCE1A1BD44AABAD69CC239265C048"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cross-sector partnership</header><text>The term <term>cross-sector partnership</term> means an alliance, or other partnership, that—</text><subparagraph id="H47F0B72D065C4F56BA6C65777654FC71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is cross-sector in nature; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96ECCAA37A95446A90BDA0029CD9CEA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>serves a local (which may be regional) area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6376A86348544C08424FCEA9D99C781"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Educational provider</header><text>The term <term>educational provider</term> includes an institution of higher education, including such an institution that is a junior or community college (as defined in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>)), and a secondary school (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36577B22950341618FBCF88B58C3BCBF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Grandfamily or kinship family</header><text>The term <term>grandfamily or kinship family</term> means a family in which a child resides with and is being raised by a grandparent, another extended family member, or an adult with whom the child has a close family-like relationship, such as a godparent or a close family friend. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H554B5A49B1544E7882B448B18950379D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H150A46037BBE4E8F9531056A1C722C7A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H386AF41C2E9144A5A041C6A9CF13216B"><enum>(8)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means any of the 50 States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Marianas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H18D5D40A308749D6BC97C0799B28045E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant program</header><paragraph id="H425A56C695CB49DD8864D0BBA6AEB698"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator, acting directly, or by contract with another entity, shall carry out a grant program. In carrying out the program, the Administrator shall make grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities. The Administrator shall make the grants for periods of 5 years and in amounts of not less than $200,000 per year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11150B5FD33B41389B3113EC6074E291"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="H9D4B261148EB47D7B8A1635F4BD27F80"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be a nonprofit organization, State or local agency (including an area agency on aging as defined in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>)), an Indian Tribe, or an educational provider in 1 or more States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A9C6B26D291449C8921A70099217D5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a proven record of supporting members of grandfamilies or kinship families and convening key stakeholders to address an issue related to grandfamilies or kinship families. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H14BCEB9F1FF04AFCB057DB3CCAF19F78"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall submit an application with respect to a cross-sector partnership to the Administrator, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Administrator may require, including—</text><subparagraph id="H6B859DD8FB2F45E290925B97F698C548"><enum>(A)</enum><text>information that demonstrates the entity's capacity for establishing and sustaining cross-system partnerships aimed at improving the health, well-being, financial security, or legal standing of grandfamily or kinship family members;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69DD0D4249C6469BAB98F6DB8E374B1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information that demonstrates the entity sought and included, or an assurance that the entity will seek and include, input from key stakeholders, including members of grandfamilies or kinship families, when establishing the partnership and identifying relevant activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF72BCB634B194F63ADAC8D54AA727620"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a plan from the entity to incorporate in the activities carried out under the grant— </text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1FE3E2730CC94484A1CCA3F9D27D9DF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 1 recommendation from the most recent report to Congress of the Advisory Council to Support Grandparents Raising Grandchildren (provided that such report was released not more than 5 years before the date on which the entity submits its application for a grant under this section); or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB92BB1824122442EAE1D89723D5A681A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at least 1 recommendation from the Administration for Community Living;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA3C490DBE6B420099BD417CD6ECB00D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>information that demonstrates that the cross-sector partnership involved has developed or adopted, or an assurance that the partnership will develop or adopt, well-defined activities that are evidence-informed or trauma specific or trauma informed, to enhance the health, well-being, financial security, or legal standing of grandfamilies or kinship families;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0286ED03AFCC42C7A6A4156B4B50921E"><enum>(E)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6D3E04BA892647649DF94F2E2745D8DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>memoranda from at least 3 organizations that are cross-sector stakeholders that indicate the organizations will participate in the cross-sector partnership; </text></clause><clause id="HFE369BEEEC6E40E68B9572DD2CB39A95" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an assurance that at least 1 participating stakeholder organization, or the lead entity itself, will be an institution of higher education that provides not less than a 2-year program that is acceptable for full credit toward a degree; and</text></clause><clause id="H09274B48662A400888A332E0BD844F3C" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an assurance that the contributions of the participating stakeholder organizations will be reflected in the programmatic budget of the partnership; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5C3E68843B44BC493FA154FBD61E903"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information that demonstrates how the eligible entity will work with the cross-sector partnership to align existing (as of the date of submission of the application) activities to support members of grandfamilies or kinship families;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07C6077D0ABF4886B131A364BA339D2F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>information that demonstrates how the eligible entity will identify, support, and provide stipends to volunteers to support the goals of the cross-sector partnership, which volunteers may include—</text><clause id="H83F8685A13C246E0B4D1CE08297BD18D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>volunteers or participants of AmeriCorps programs under the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12501">42 U.S.C. 12501 et seq.</external-xref>) or the Domestic Volunteer Service Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4950">42 U.S.C. 4950 et seq.</external-xref>), the National Community Care Corps program supported by the Administration for Community Living, or any other federally-funded program supporting volunteers in community service; </text></clause><clause id="HE6A8766F94AD4E29BAD8C8A4A6259D3E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>community members; or</text></clause><clause id="H5361703502D9430E92BB3FF3CB04F4BC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>students at an institution of higher education who are seeking internships or direct volunteer experiences; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H103BD5B95FFA4F51B25C4B1A4F20FA9F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>information that identifies potential members of a cross-sector advisory council that—</text><clause id="HA75C11A6E4B8499B9E1A8084F0BCF43F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will be comprised of at least 7 members, and on which a majority of members are or have in the past been members of grandfamilies or kinship families; and</text></clause><clause id="HB1493559D1674599A3C07AE65F6AB0F9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will advise the partnership on activities to be carried out under the grant; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7816BE4D528C41479C49D03081BF5E08"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a plan developed by the eligible entity to work in partnership with technical resource centers supported by the Administration for Community Living, including the National Technical Assistance Center on Grandfamilies and Kinship Families established under section 2922 of the American Rescue Plan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3020g">42 U.S.C. 3020g</external-xref>), on activities related to the objectives for the grant. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA4E93D0B1204EB596A571F1A8CBDDF0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In determining which entities shall receive grants under this section, the Administrator shall give preference to entities that—</text><subparagraph id="H253863EF011E4550A01C7D16ABAC001A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide geographic diversity, including entities that serve rural localities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE52DE1B85FDC4C5B8DA73F73FB21B0D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support children who have been orphaned by the COVID–19 pandemic or opioid crisis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H627F1789F0A14B46AD1CA41F4BA67FFE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have capacity to provide culturally appropriate activities; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A0D52BBA8FE48FCBDC00E08B70BE33D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>demonstrate capacity to work with educational systems, including systems for early childhood education or elementary education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H917B0A9D2F70409EA5213FBBE7FF30A6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>support children with disabilities living with a grandfamily or kinship family; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D19E11878B5443A87737FA68A51CAF9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>identify as a lived experience entity, which are organizations, groups, or collaborations whose primary mission is to put people with lived experience in grandfamilies or kinship families in a position to support other individuals going through similar experiences. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE9D3AC49C9A440CB17E9B1EF88D9AB2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><subparagraph id="HC1B431F678DE4A43B4A867300707DB07"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Required uses</header><text>An entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds—</text><clause id="H27B032BB87DF4D53A02F2AC9BD71DBD3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to establish or sustain a cross-sector partnership to strengthen and support grassroots efforts that address the unique needs of grandfamilies or kinship families, including those supporting children with disabilities or those navigating through mental health concerns or trauma; </text></clause><clause id="H6C233AC4271F4D46BEDD2F1C113E7033"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to foster the integration of new or existing activities designed to increase the health, well-being, financial security, or legal standing of members of grandfamilies or kinship families; and</text></clause><clause id="H7345117B80EE482DB9FEDDA338F2AABA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to promote peer-to-peer support efforts, including such efforts through support groups, social activities, or educational training.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5ABD870638B943E1AC6B8128CDE387D7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Allowable uses</header><text>An entity that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds—</text><clause id="H3700A49977604430B44860D5870A79A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to support volunteer efforts related to objectives of the partnership, including conducting outreach to and providing stipends for members of grandfamilies or kinship families participating in advisory councils described in paragraph (3)(H), or providing peer-to-peer supports described in subparagraph (A)(iii), who are not otherwise being paid for such participation or supports;</text></clause><clause id="HBC19B5CBAE6F405EA6B7A2B6B813BA19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for staff positions for the partnership;</text></clause><clause id="HCDEC715267A94A7F8FEA4507CF64C96E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to conduct a gap and asset analysis and to raise awareness of the needs of grandfamilies or kinship families within the local area served;</text></clause><clause id="H68F3BCF3709046DC9680557AC4134583"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to support technology and software needs related to the partnership;</text></clause><clause id="H50AE4158966F4E5AAE5B8BF337CC095C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>to reimburse project-related mileage for staff and volunteers; </text></clause><clause id="HB8002DC2E29D4DFCA64A5404A02F0827"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>to attend grant recipient trainings or other meetings with technical resource centers supported by the Administration for Community Living; or</text></clause><clause id="H12AB1127A08548DCA983C24E2347E1CA"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>to help grandfamilies or kinship families coordinate benefits or assistance under any Federal program or any State or local program financed in whole or in part with Federal funds.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7CD109564540CC839BB3599AB77A3E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Amounts made available under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, and local public funds expended to provide services for grandfamilies or kinship families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4E4E426190F482ABA398296D84D41A3"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Annual report</header><subparagraph id="H10D0DEB615C1475F816BAE90C131DF15"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Information from grant recipients</header><text>Each recipient of a grant under this section shall annually submit to the Administrator information consisting of— </text><clause id="H059A1D6B25564547AFB3E0AF31B0509B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of individuals and organizations supported by the partnership funded by the grant, including the number of people who received direct services or training from the local activities carried out under this section and the estimated number of people who were impacted by the activities;</text></clause><clause id="H2C32C9B9D8E54621AB6367B86B2F1A75"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>demographic data, including the age, sex, ethnicity, disability status, and race of those supported by the partnership;</text></clause><clause id="H87C5E82763094E46A181F04029B43460"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of and demographic data for volunteers involved in supporting the objectives of the activities and the number of people who benefited from the contributions of volunteers; </text></clause><clause id="H68E0B3ED23E54095BA0166AA4C8747BA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>recommendations to align and coordinate activities across service-related sectors, such as aging, child welfare, income support, food and nutrition, legal, health and mental health, or education services, for members of grandfamilies or kinship families, and lessons learned and promising practices developed during the year; and</text></clause><clause id="H7804BC91E3144D97B1BE84EE74B1F4EC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>ways in which the project supported by the grant has engaged individuals with experience related to being a member of a grandfamily or kinship family in the design, implementation, and feedback related to the project. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC99C7A491DFE48EF989B3465680DEB41"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report by administrator</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act and every year thereafter, the Administrator shall—</text><clause id="H4ED51E5FBD0C48528D53DF41F8C38F0D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prepare, based on the information submitted under subparagraph (A), a report on the impact of the program carried out under this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HB0E530E1164747ADA0B1E6C1DE7A53B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>submit the report to—</text><subclause id="H950D43A59F7B4007A84C04011839E885"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, the Special Committee on Aging, and the Committee on Finance of the Senate; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA517E97E114546A0BFDB174C537BF5BC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Committee on Education and the Workforce and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9460B6DF9D2F4B6A9F078FCAC6651D90"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><subparagraph id="HC09D5700DD8E474BB91330B540901969"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall reserve not more than 10 percent of the funds made available under this section for administrative purposes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H187723A0A4CC462A8B8F476BD37CA2F9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The Administrator shall use funds reserved under subparagraph (A) for evaluation in the aggregate of the local activities supported by the grants. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E533B38A5C4480482110E010A92571F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Permissible uses of funds</header><text>The Administrator shall use the reserved funds for administrative purposes that may include—</text><clause id="HE08CD471AA594DAAB636A9C004C9EB89"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the establishment of an interagency task force to evaluate the recommendations provided by grant recipients under paragraph (7)(A)(iv), to foster Federal coordination related to activities for grandfamilies or kinship families;</text></clause><clause id="HDA3DE138D55649C99FACDE493592DEEC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support for the Administration for Community Living’s Research, Demonstration, and Evaluation Center for the Aging Network, established under section 201(g) of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3011">42 U.S.C. 3011(g)</external-xref>); </text></clause><clause id="H0CDEA79DC490498B8AEC2993523D0951"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>evaluation described in subparagraph (B) by an independent evaluator, separate from any of the grant recipients, hired by the Administrator; and</text></clause><clause id="H075A52D971B04F95A1EDBFB6A1112E1B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>hosting, not less than annually, learning collaboratives with the grant recipients.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C30EB3B935B4453B700C2933080D422"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Funds</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $8,750,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

