<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB60B64EEA9104488B859B33E2174793C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3372 IH: To amend title 23, United States Code, to establish a safety data collection program for certain 6-axle vehicles, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3372</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, to establish a safety data collection program for certain 6-axle vehicles, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H47ED8DFA3B3C4D3A98865CC4342108C0" style="OLC"><section id="HF7DCE0DBD53844909D8BF01E26E8FC58" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Safety data collection program for certain 6-axle vehicles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127 of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HD133C92016D7488D81541099EDAF7430" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H0DB5F8BC774347708B502D1192268F20"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Pilot program for safety data collection on certain 6-Axle vehicles</header><paragraph id="H7B45B9BB54E14F728ED1E2D22C7D3AE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall establish a pilot program (referred to in this subsection as the ‘pilot program’) under which States admitted by the Secretary under paragraph (2) may allow covered 6-axle vehicles to be operated on the Interstate System in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F8EDEF584C84D54B44728CACBA7BF75"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Admission to pilot program</header><subparagraph id="HE0C7FA37D57B497DB2CE1E3C78FDFEB5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 30 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, a State seeking to participate in the pilot program shall submit an application to the Secretary in electronic form, containing such administrative information as the Secretary may require, including a certification that the State has or will have the authority pursuant to State law to implement the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13C63F72B76C40E5832D9A452B692ED8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Admission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall admit to the pilot program, on a rolling basis, States that submit a completed application under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CEC77E38BB14AABA9B470A459A6FCDE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Election to no longer participate</header><text>If a State elects to no longer participate in the pilot program, the State shall notify the Secretary of such election.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3DF04D081404A4FB728DEEE3EE06F8D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Means of implementation</header><subparagraph id="HF3F9160E7D14488493C3F0AE22455B3D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to participate in the pilot program, a State shall agree to implement the pilot program through the issuance of permits per vehicle or group of vehicles with respect to covered 6-axle vehicles.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEACEF48B03147EA9DD97BD27D9EB0EA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Permit</header><text>A permit described in subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="HB2C26D723A7F4D0790CABA163A35B33C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe the Interstate System routes that may be used while operating at greater than 80,000 pounds gross vehicle weight in a covered 6-axle vehicle; and</text></clause><clause id="H896D624063E2407C80408430D7A277ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require the permit holder to report to the State, with respect to each covered 6-axle vehicle for which such permit was issued—</text><subclause id="H3866F1A236F74D12B059382AD3EF80AC"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each accident (as such term is defined in section 390.5 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection) that occurred in the State involving the covered 6-axle vehicle on the Interstate System in the State;</text></subclause><subclause id="H285B9E233E024D00A3BA0A6809DBE50E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the estimated gross vehicle weight of each covered 6-axle vehicle at the time of an accident described in subclause (I); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2CAC7846BAE54D6DAFC38BF70470847F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the estimated miles traveled by the covered 6-axle vehicle on the Interstate System in the State annually.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF12C5BF667294C15AC7893C59D2B42D7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Safety equipment incentive</header><clause id="H0EC0CDEDD91449559AE80B6D85740F6B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Fee reduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any fee associated with a permit under this paragraph, the State may reduce the fee otherwise applicable to a vehicle by 67 percent if the vehicle is equipped with an automatic emergency braking system, including such systems in use on the date of enactment of this subsection. </text></clause><clause id="H6DF3AA8B7DD4475F8B2FF133D06E1ACF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Group of vehicles</header><text>As applied to a permit for a group of vehicles, the reduction under clause (i) shall only apply with respect to individual vehicles in the group that are equipped with an automatic emergency breaking system, including such systems in use on the date of enactment of this subsection. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10D141231EA745F38115C16CF4CDDD7C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other authorizations not affected</header><text>This subsection shall not restrict—</text><subparagraph id="HC716EBA2CADB45BB9E1CFBA966553D69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a vehicle that may operate under any other provision of this section or another Federal law; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5DCA0ADB2E045119B014F3E7166D69C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State’s authority with respect to a vehicle that may operate under any other provision of this section or another Federal law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE794B85E3CC46F0A304F2A35617A0A5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No highway funding reduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (a), funds apportioned to a State under section 104 for any period may not be reduced because the State authorizes the operation of covered 6-axle vehicles within such State in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74206EAE3CD14EBDBDE3265E729D8067"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the first March 1 after the date of enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, a State participating in the pilot program shall submit to the Secretary with respect to the previous calendar year, a report on—</text><subparagraph id="HBA5D53A3D5B6405CB8F97053297067DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of accidents (as such term is defined in section 390.5 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection)) that occurred on the Interstate System in the State involving a covered 6-axle vehicle for which a permit was issued under the pilot program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7CCA733A13E4D518B672BA47C7CE980"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the estimated gross vehicle weight of each such vehicle at the time of the accident in the State described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDADB0CFC3FB443D3BE5341271CD571BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the estimated miles traveled by such vehicle on the Interstate System in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBF92331CF784728827EA4F342255BEC"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Termination of pilot program</header><subparagraph id="H772F52E247F1447AA05BD2EC87BBB78E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the pilot program shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of enactment of this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CA7F3E809C24B70B7185D38B5CBD899"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional application; continuation of authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a period of 10 years beginning on the date described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary may continue the pilot program with respect to each State in the program, upon the application of a State and after consideration of—</text><clause id="H38B098D0A954401FA713D74C6747BEE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the actual experience of the State under the pilot program; and</text></clause><clause id="H10598EA1773A4CABBD2F5C9C9A9C3FA6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any documents or other material submitted by the State in support of such an application.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC285A4C0C9442CB8D27F51FE0A173EA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Covered 6-axle vehicle defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>covered 6-axle vehicle</quote> means a vehicle—</text><subparagraph id="H3A86C909007B46D480C2BF2F31DC4B57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>equipped with 6 or more axles;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D3326120D75463291BF7F4600004AD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which the weight—</text><clause id="H104B2CD1C15B4494B720C80CFD332C98"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any single axle of the vehicle does not exceed 20,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances;</text></clause><clause id="HE50F3E5DB850415AA2CE5FEBB6842B44"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any tandem axle of the vehicle does not exceed 34,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances; and</text></clause><clause id="HB5B56E221AE644DDA15E3D1E1313BEBC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any group of three or more axles of the vehicle does not exceed 45,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92D5F28432404B6E976A0F9C69FFB27F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for which the gross weight does not exceed the lesser of—</text><clause id="H7724CA46B0BD41AB879F42CA5726C225"><enum>(i)</enum><text>91,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances; and</text></clause><clause id="HA46CFE0CE3E44CBDAA4A35CAF8C85FAD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maximum permitted by the bridge formula under subsection (a); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4415DE4D5FA4C01A8F294E27A018683"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that is not a longer combination vehicle, as such term is defined in subsection (d)(4). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

