<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H73BD938BEF134A81BC292B55469BDA1D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4699 IH: The People’s Response Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4699</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish within the Department of Health and Human Services a Division on Community Safety, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE700591ADA3428E985D6144F36B7BCA" style="OLC"><section id="HE7375AD59EB14067916130DA1C903BEB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; purposes</header><subsection id="H09BA8D0237EE4AD69C5677FB8883B45F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>The People’s Response Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDC9E0D27ADDE4BADA79308B9F9BAC74B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this Act to—</text><paragraph id="HC986E412CADA476FB47596D36AC736CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">catalyze, coordinate, and disseminate research on approaches to community safety that reduce criminal legal contact while expanding opportunity, including a particular focus on groups that have been disproportionately harmed by the criminal legal system; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C21FCE2144246DBAC9E7FD69F43F15A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support State governments, local governments, and community-based organizations in implementing qualified approaches to community safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1990B4E581664128818B68C2B614B070"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">mobilize and coordinate Federal resources to advance qualified approaches to community safety; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BD2BAAAAF8E409A85DF1D87976CB501"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand resources to holistically support survivors of mass incarceration, police violence, rape and other forms of sexual assault, harm resulting from detention or deportation, and other forms of violence and abuse; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96028F226A614EBAB1DD2F468A28C70A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand resources to holistically support marginalized communities, particularly Black and Indigenous communities, to implement qualified approaches to community safety.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB5ED8FD8A67E44F989A84262DD103FF7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4D1BEE4DF6E84BFB9687430131D2E86B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>community health worker</quote> means a frontline public health worker who—</text><subparagraph id="HFA0B9F6E04744CDA98B6DD1C71D9FBB1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a trusted member of, or has a close understanding of, the community served, enabling the worker to serve as a link between health and social services and the community, so as to facilitate access to services and improve the quality and cultural competence of service delivery; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3D5B6AEAEF9478E8D4A0454696721A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>builds individual and community capacity by increasing health knowledge and self-sufficiency through a range of activities such as outreach, community education, informal counseling, social support, and advocacy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6046714AD6414DE2A3A62ADDCF672932"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community land trust</header><text>The term <term>community land trust</term> means a community-based organization that is designed to ensure community stewardship of land and—</text><subparagraph id="H41F69FAD3E4F420B9491B5B00A99BFCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not sponsored by a for-profit organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF49E7B01FD9548D49A187D5208C6CC7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has a membership open to any adult who resides in the particular geographic area in which the organization operates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA43EEFFDD464671A952CEA36378E583"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides low-cost land and housing while maintaining community control over neighborhood resources, including by acquiring land that will be held in perpetuity so as to provide permanently affordable homeownership to those who might not otherwise be able to afford a home.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BFC987A7B104D74B6B5878914FBE206"><enum>(3)</enum><header>First responder</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>first responder</term> means an individual with relevant experience who responds to crises in a way that meets the definition of qualified approaches to community safety. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1000E02E707644F4A6AA4DD802C51217"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified approach to community safety</header><subparagraph id="H10C7C01C00204E30B56C36A6A9CDD26C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified approach to community safety</term> means, with respect to a program or service, that the program or service is established or provided in a manner that is disconnected from carceral institutions, including law enforcement, criminal courts, prosecution, probation, child welfare services, or immigration enforcement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB9B684CEA9B4DA58F75D87E144752C5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disconnected from carceral institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>disconnected from carceral institutions</term> means having no relationship with respect to administration, staffing, or funding, or otherwise cooperating with, collaborating with, or reporting to, any carceral institution in any situation, except where the program or service involved is bound to engage in such cooperation or reporting by existing Federal, State, or local law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60A60DED674E40409B596F21252A6C9D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Participatory budgeting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>participatory budgeting</term> means a democratic engagement process in which community members deliberate and decide directly how to allocate a portion of a public budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E627FEF87D14079A489541685234684"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Safety needs assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>safety needs assessment</term> means a systematic, participatory process for identifying the safety needs in the local community. Such process shall include— </text><subparagraph id="H8231FB2B52344E8AB15007F690BE4690"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">soliciting input from persons who represent the broad interests of the local community, including those who have been directly impacted by arrest, incarceration, criminal supervision, immigration detention, or other criminal legal system involvement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0B493FF1DDC4C5D890BB6947C21737E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying the structural, systemic factors that may lead community members to feel unsafe or may increase the risk that community members may become involved with the criminal legal system; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A35EE04BD474DE9B740FB1232A87643"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying existing resources that are potentially available to address those safety needs as well as any other gaps in necessary resources; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H902CAD4116F84A10B7869632ECA0DBC0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing opportunities that allow people meaningful opportunities to review, comment on, and provide suggested modifications to the draft assessment, such as through public hearings, online publication, and a comment period that allows sufficient time for community feedback.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB2B030C9DD740FF876567B0D416C450"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means any State of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, American Samoa, Guam, and the Northern Mariana Islands. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF46C83FF38740C1AFCBFE69D8376188"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Unit of local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>unit of local government</term> means any city, county, township, town, borough, parish, village, or other general purpose political subdivision of a State.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HD3F8C7EFBCDD4D75B629B09107784941"><enum>I</enum><header>Division on Community Safety</header><section id="H922F7D8CDD3B4697912D5671E4E69DAF"><enum>101.</enum><header>Division on Community Safety</header><subsection id="HE265EDFB187F42E8A85834D8DB4A848B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Department of Health and Human Services a Division on Community Safety (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Division</quote>). The Division shall be headed by an Assistant Secretary for Community Safety (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote>) who shall be designated by and report directly to the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89C9D5E663874048822136367B072F5C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Division shall have responsibility for overseeing activities that promote qualified approaches to community safety, including—</text><paragraph id="H392C964CFF694012A77DE0D8B6202FDB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinating and carrying out other oversight activities with respect to the grant programs established under title II;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA61F524917D948BF87FFEAB6CA2DC5AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>funding, conducting, coordinating, and publicly disseminating the findings of, research into policies, programs, infrastructure, and other investments that serve to increase qualified approaches to community safety, including through interdisciplinary collaborations involving scholars, nonprofits, and other nongovernmental actors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA60021D33B7A4AF4952093EA0524FEEA"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing and funding technical assistance to State and local governments to implement qualified approaches to community safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB422103B6BC74E25BAE5DFD398EF3E7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establishing—</text><subparagraph id="HF1D3E46401E8445791A00AB110188769"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Community Advisory Board under section 102; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A8AC41107B44DF791E77CD0FA5F936B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Federal Health Response Unit under section 103;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9B541CF48B74DD687059BC3E9D60842"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Interagency Task Force under section 104; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H947F93A1068A43C2BF9ADC6C1D75C216"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Community Safety Grant for community-led organizations under section 201;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5185B54D6D543399224CDF47F9575AC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Community Safety Grant for Local Governments under section 202;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D3ECC533B2B45F0A4523EA52B037BC0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Community Safety Grant for States under section 203; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3EE1EE8321148F6A431BC173C69AEDE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the First Responder Hiring Grants under section 204; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H590BA266F57546F9B8AD8FCE2829F243" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating, streamlining, and implementing qualified approaches to community safety in collaboration with the Assistant Secretary for the Administration for Children and Families, Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, Director of the Indian Health Service, the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substances Use, and other relevant agencies within the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAEEE072FB77457D88F64634374F03AC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>supporting and helping to coordinate interagency initiatives that advance, streamline, and otherwise implement qualified approaches to community safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF19017B1F242D898A8C51692AC697F"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administering grant programs that support State governments, local governments, and community-based organizations in implementing qualified approaches to increasing community safety; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E9F4921B1554F59886FBE28FB6A0CA0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>providing to the public updates, findings, and recommendations on qualified approaches to community safety collected from the reports made by recipients of grants under title II; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2B4E0958E1B4E218359DE392A2015A4"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing and maintaining a complaint system responsible for the resolution of complaints from members of the general public regarding grant funding for programs not compliant with the qualified approaches to community safety standard.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF156A1F7EE7B486DB53E086846954A0C"><enum>102.</enum><header>Community Advisory Board</header><subsection id="H90831F4531CE43228DDB6F60301511ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Division shall establish an advisory board to oversee the activities of the Division established under section 101 and grant programs under title II, to be known as the Community Advisory Board (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Advisory Board</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H8349CF5B97AF48CC998899AB7701B022"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><paragraph id="H96F3F94DA3E740D8A3B68AE04DCE78E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Board shall be composed of individuals, to be selected by the Secretary. Such members shall reflect the racial, religious, ethnic, gender, sexual orientation, disability status, immigration status, and other diversities of the United States, including representation for Black people, Asian-American people, Latinx people, Indigenous people, lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer people, women, youth, disabled people, undocumented and formerly undocumented immigrants, and other groups that have been disproportionately disadvantaged by the criminal legal system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H736BB2F801C24FEC9A51BD39B0CB54AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Representation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary shall ensure that a certain number of individuals selected to serve as members of the Advisory Board— </text><subparagraph id="H839A616A52A14670B6F46739743FEDAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have personal experience with the criminal legal system, including—</text><clause id="H3B999EE4B87743E5A4DB5FBBF46EC8EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">individuals who have been detained or incarcerated;</text></clause><clause id="H81FD184E0950490BAC4F33DDC160B8E5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>individuals who are currently on community supervision (such as probation or parole) or who have been on community supervision;</text></clause><clause id="HEC600C2E0C8F41BA9DA2244ADE38BB07"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>individuals who have been arrested or cited by law enforcement;</text></clause><clause id="H8EDB789A3F8A40DEABBA723FC8BE4534"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">individuals who have been directly impacted by police violence or other forms of violence, including domestic violence, sexual assault, rape, and other forms of sexual or intimate partner violence; and</text></clause><clause id="H82B707BCC4CB407EAA413DEEFDECD7E0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>immediate family members of individuals who have been directly impacted by police violence; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB648788699E24DC5B9443EA132074BDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are advocates or grassroots practitioners working to advance educational equity, health equity, housing equity, environmental justice, racial justice, gender justice, disability justice, or Indigenous justice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H029E22D67026429F885ACC3C989A6B85"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Advisory Board shall serve at a rate of pay to be determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H693E3FE47C744BA18BD8E94B5C7F9BA3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The duties of the Advisory Board are as follows: </text><subparagraph id="H4A7F2BBAE13E4C04908503A00CB7DCE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Approving annual priorities and funding for research and technical assistance and evaluating, on an annual basis, research conducted or supported by the Division and technical assistance provided by the Division.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC643CE66D7C84CADAF65A68D1F46E2E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Based on the evaluations conducted under paragraph (5), producing, and submitting to the Administrator, annual recommendations on the following: </text><clause id="H18DFC9F3C8E04B72884EBAED1AB9CF5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether activities conducted by the Division adequately reflect the specific needs and interests of all individuals, including Black individuals, Asian-American individuals, Latinx individuals, Indigenous individuals, lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals, disabled individuals, and other individuals who are members of communities that have been disproportionately impacted by the immigration and criminal legal system. </text></clause><clause id="H22DA0F795A4C4737B2966ABFFF49EA04"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Whether funding made available to the Division is sufficiently flowing to organizations that are led by individuals referred to in clause (i). </text></clause><clause id="H716B898364AC446FBBDD2BC640538AED"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Changes that the Division could make to address any issues uncovered during such evaluations, including ways to ensure that grants awarded under this title are serving to enhance racial equity and benefit community-based organizations that have diverse leadership and composition.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC15ABBD26F414DFD9A43A8BF4B1B26EC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date on which the Division receives the recommendations under paragraph (4)(B), the Division shall submit a report to Congress, which details—</text><subparagraph id="H0EA0315A8A17461EABC911D720E9E62D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>steps the Division has taken or will take to implement the Advisory Board’s recommendations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA0E3CB8E4A3449C9998010EA6BE961D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for any recommendations not implemented or planned to be implemented, an explanation as to why such recommendation was infeasible or conflicted with the Division’s statutory obligations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC4ED28D0AF104050AA525970DBA077CC"><enum>103.</enum><header>Federal Health Response Unit</header><subsection id="H2A6FD7C31DA343E39E4932C69A449FF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish a Federal health response unit, to be known as the <quote>Federal Health Response Unit</quote>, which shall—</text><paragraph id="H6B3A8E4FB6F64225BAD8BC407E2A784A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>respond, through a response unit trained in accordance with training developed under paragraph (2), to any public health emergency—</text><subparagraph id="H15BA7A75E81645AEB006A2FE582E9755"><enum>(A)</enum><text>declared by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93A75B1EE74142308A7B6A2D4DBFEB5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to which the head of a State public health agency makes a request to the Secretary for assistance;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84E4CD56BC5C4501A5864539C2C5ED40"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop, provide for the training of, and hire, not fewer than 5,000 personnel to respond to such an emergency; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H143AE7AB62BB4E68ADDC34961FF1CFAB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop, and provide to States and units of local government, guidelines for implementing qualified approaches to community safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9653B74644F4729A8D46BCCFDFC7C06"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and implement a plan to minimize barriers to community health worker program participation, such as by providing guidance and ensuring the availability of local sources of community health worker-led technical assistance on requirements for participation, including plans to prioritize and build the capacity of community-based organizations and community health worker-led organizations and associations within the State or region as eligible and preferred providers of community health worker technical assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEC11ED4B60C4AC3B8E223FB325632D1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support local educational agencies as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>) with resources, personnel and services that create truly safe and inclusive schools;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H469D4F4F0770432EA279DBF6198DF692"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide States and units of local government with community health workers, including individuals who are trained in first response or violence prevention, or both, and other personnel to improve access to health services and address the public health emergency described in paragraph (1) within their respective jurisdiction; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18098EA9D63C469594DBD6D378E921B5" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate with the commissioned Regular Corps and Ready Reserve Corps under section 203 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/204">42 U.S.C. 204</external-xref>), the Medical Reserve Corps under section 2813 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300hh-15">42 U.S.C. 300hh–15</external-xref>), and State-level agencies and crisis response teams.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H39CDFD0733524D84AAE6120DC66B1E45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that each individual hired pursuant to this section shall be paid a wage, which shall at least be the highest of the following:</text><paragraph id="H64D31B78AA27491E8EA011C8F67BBB31"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$17 an hour.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F7BD8B4A2B14E5C83D0877507C2F2A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The minimum wage under the applicable State or local minimum wage law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1C77B45BFEA4A42BEC859BD5B80F275"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The prevailing rates of pay for individuals employed in similar occupations by the same employer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2E8B71442FA4DF9A6AD3EF1C031FA06"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Federal minimum wage in effect under section 6(a)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD7FC24D3D43141A7BE3AFE89C69F7006"><enum>104.</enum><header>Interagency task force</header><subsection id="H90CE68ED86354C078B78FDD3DF6DFE41"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish an interagency task force (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) to coordinate and promote holistic, qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3A0CC8CB5BD14664B9B9950B5BF1C6AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Members</header><text>The Task Force shall be composed of the following members:</text><paragraph id="HF325C420AD894BD59B4BFB3B2F02231B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, or the designee of the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6E93ECEC0FE436FB0D5D3707F2DCC08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Attorney General, or the designee of the Attorney General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0D7E7E88BEC4C9FA2EB6F8D2CCD13EB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, or the designee of the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04A4065CBCD74897975FC36D18B5AA10"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Secretary of Education, or the designee of the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E23844297F74121B485A873F1F6951B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Secretary of Labor, or the designee of the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87D9CDA3BDF5432A97F984F34755E624"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, or the designee of the Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98D486F03FA34D72B831A16FA7EA1AFD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Other agencies, as determined necessary by the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H51261E6325174924B1C45130A781D01D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Task Force shall:</text><paragraph id="H0F4718842AE24E31B0E2B8785A345DE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Conduct a comprehensive audit of all funds allocated and programs supported by the Department of Justice and other Federal agencies that fund law enforcement, jails, prisons, and other detention facilities, and other coercive or carceral approaches to public safety.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71A5FF08E4624AC38DD235E31493D986"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Conduct a comprehensive audit that assesses all Federal funds allocated to, as well as Federal programs supporting, initiatives that are intended to enhance qualified approaches to community safety, disaggregated by jurisdiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3880181EBCC4A24B329A3A217C84FCB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Facilitate ongoing efforts to streamline the application, monitoring, and reporting processes to make Federal funds provided pursuant to any grant made under this Act maximally accessible to small, grassroots organizations that work to develop, implement, or evaluate qualified approaches to community safety.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65DA5C31A1284821BBE2D41B51961919"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, the Task Force may hold such meetings, and sit and act at such times and places, as the Task Force considers appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC98EA55683854DD6BA2EFD32D18074C4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force may secure directly from any Federal agency such information as may be necessary to enable the Task Force to carry out this section. Upon request of the Chairperson of the Task Force, the head of such agency shall furnish such information to the Task Force. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8F69DFFC867B46429198EA2D8218F9AE" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Agency reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of enabling the Task Force to carry out the audits required under subsection (c), not less than once every six months—</text><paragraph id="H9B6E0A0CF48642709246A855331CFFA9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Education shall submit to the Assistant Secretary a report that contains with respect to each recipient of a grant awarded by the Secretary a profile of such recipient and in the case of any such recipient that is a State or unit of local government—</text><subparagraph id="H77F38FACCC4E462ABF4894D06E279747" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the needs of school health providers in the relevant jurisdiction; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12E5ED622FED43A4A0BB35B48EFCCE1C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information on the applicable local school population, including the largest barriers to the safety of the school population (including when school is not in session); </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H62E698DFD58A47AFAB44A24E9AFFB9FF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Attorney General shall submit to the Assistant Secretary a report that contains with respect to each recipient of a grant awarded by the Secretary a profile of such recipient and in the case of any such recipient that is a State or unit of local government—</text><subparagraph id="H425C7B222853458A9617D987DCDB168C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of grant funds awarded to the jurisdiction under a grant administered by the Attorney General; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA678843FC20548BB8F8BBF6134A63CF4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the recipients’ progress in meeting the purposes specified in section 1, including—</text><clause id="H3816D3D150FF452EAF29DBC8C8B247F7" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of residents who are being incarcerated, criminally supervised, or otherwise confined in any coercive institutional structure and how these numbers have changed over time; </text></clause><clause id="HE71B2A81D9004151A6F62784C83A71AE" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount and type of any fines, fees, or other financial obligations owed by residents to any component of the criminal legal system;</text></clause><clause id="H83E5A75E53E34795B5698BE41C4AEC84" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount and type of contact that residents have with the criminal legal system; and</text></clause><clause id="HA9BAB0F4C2D3466FA46107470880A52C" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">racial disparities in arrest, incarceration, criminal supervision, school discipline, and other areas that people may contact the criminal legal system.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7898A49200F94EEAAC9A3D246CE3EC1D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date on which the Task Force completes the audits described in subsection (c), the Task Force shall submit a report to Congress, which summarizes—</text><paragraph id="HAEADBF0C83C94C1786C3792F09C8864E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the contents of such audits; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9E03609835F47728BBAF1171E306530"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any recommendations, based on such audits, with respect to additional investments or policy changes that would improve the implementation of qualified community safety approaches and maximize community safety outcomes in all jurisdictions served.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H14E0D98931BF43F8BF4881E44CC757D3"><enum>105.</enum><header>Non-discrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No person in the United States shall, on the basis of actual or perceived race, color, religion, national origin, sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), or disability, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under—</text><paragraph id="H455A0F8A9993432892B9106EF2349487"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any program or activity funded, in whole or in part, with funds made available under this title; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89294B66CDE54764BBB166FD6283B283"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other program or activity funded, in whole or in part, with funds appropriated for grants, cooperative agreements, and other assistance administered by the Assistant Secretary.</text></paragraph></section></title><title id="HD709DBA795C740FC88D608220BE90022"><enum>II</enum><header>Grants in support of community safety</header><section id="HE36E8E8F301348CB9854D1C65A7FCF2F"><enum>201.</enum><header>Establishment of Community Safety Grant for Community-led Organizations</header><subsection id="H8E0DEA01054C4603A7148AF4D1D87871"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program established</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), shall award grants, on a rolling basis, to community-based organizations that are designing, implementing, monitoring, or otherwise supporting qualified approaches to community safety, including as intermediaries making subgrants to other local organizations and community leaders who are leading qualified community safety programming.</text></subsection><subsection id="H91C14DDABBED43D7BD47684B1C467EA8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A community-based organization seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA5842CBBAC64BDC8E29BED4DA02EAA7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to community-based organizations that—</text><paragraph id="HCE233A0E54B4456A849D044AD322B16D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve, are located in, and directly employ people who live in, communities that have been disproportionately impacted by the immigration or criminal legal system, as evidenced by high rates of individuals who have been cited, arrested, or incarcerated in the year preceding the year for which the application for such grant is submitted; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56BF025E088344A59110E1B41E811450"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are led by, or employ, individuals who have been directly impacted by the criminal legal system, including via arrests, incarceration, witnessing or being victims of police violence, or having a family member who was arrested, incarcerated, or a victim of police violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1FEF5FEBEB84659A782447CD733BC72"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are led by individuals who have proven ties to the community in which the organization operates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE86CB8BBC7894607B9F41801B6D84F01"><enum>(4)</enum><text>are located in, or primarily serve, Native American communities on and off of reservations, including Urban Indian (as defined in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>)) communities; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7614A379033548089711309855EE1F3C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>have a leadership that reflects the racial diversity of the community in which the organization operates.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1EBAA5021AAF47EE84A4B37C140C0625"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A community-based organization receiving funds under this section shall use such grant funds for any purpose that has demonstrable connection to improving community safety through the use of qualified approaches to community safety, including grant writing or funding that furthers one or more of the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H8119BAA3210D42CB899A0AF771175802"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Crisis intervention, including unarmed first responder agencies and 9–1–1 dispatchers for diverting calls to first responders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H994273DFF9A14B0A8AA99E07959548E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Programs that interrupt or prevent violence, including violence and abuse interruption and prevention programs, neighborhood mediation programs, and safe passage to school programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6ADF4733EC7A4545A90B5CDB44FBDED0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Participatory investments into the built environment, including park redevelopment, streetlights, and public transportation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3C1E6DD1B1A48C8A7673195FBF8F47B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public health activities and voluntary health services, including harm reduction-based treatment for mental health and substance use, hiring of community health workers, long-term supportive housing, lead abatement, pollution reduction, and nutrition access, such as through establishing farmers markets, nonprofit and employee-owned grocery stores, and school-based nutrition programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66AE409610A349CF9D27D850C6971D79"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Housing security programs and initiatives, including outreach programs, permanent supportive housing, community land trusts and housing for individuals experiencing temporary or chronic homelessness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H859AD705EBA74D279F7647DEAB9213FD"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Support for youth and families, including school-based counselors, trauma-informed practices, youth and mentorship programs, after school and enrichment programs, credible messenger in schools programs, social-emotional learning programs, wraparound services, and two-generational programming.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H965F4C46D931451FA6D23816BF6FFC59"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Support for victims, including survivors of domestic violence, sexual violence, and rape, and targeted services to help victims, witnesses, and survivors process trauma, achieve financial and housing independence, make individualized, needs-based safety plans, and otherwise access the help that they need.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A8747B52E8D47ECBA156EE5C174F418"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Reentry support for people who are exiting incarceration or criminal supervision, including educational and workforce programs, stipends, housing programs, and support for worker coops.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95D2BE9C28594943BE75422D613BD531"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Capacity building support to local advocates and community-based organizations, including legal assistance, and startup assistance for coops, community land trusts, and nonprofit organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3858ED5E9B20496AA9D5196D69622057"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant amounts</header><text>In determining the amount of a grant awarded to a single community-based organization under this section, the Secretary shall base such determination on—</text><paragraph id="H626B05A21F764448BAC973392CF224DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of people who will be served by the program or intervention; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7EF225DC9884B8AAAF54CDE0EA5E0CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the depth of need demonstrated, including attention to specific activities planned, the socioeconomic characteristics of the community served by the organization, and current patterns of criminal legal involvement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E10668EFA924E139885508200E62147"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other factors as the Secretary determines are relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H535027614B564B269F4B6CE52978E333"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Funds made available under this section may be used only to carry out programs, services, or activities that use qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCA067BE4D52B4369956C3F31C01188E3"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting</header><paragraph id="H6EF7A7BB37274833919155360EB15B89"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not late<italic></italic>r than one year after the date on which a community-based organization receives a grant under this section, and annually thereafter, the organization shall prepare and submit a report to the Secretary and Assistant Secretary containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text><subparagraph id="H240FB09376A64D1AA7B9FFD9CFCE69A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the use of grant funds; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF0856B3D0B74949ACD97BE4E560DC5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an estimation of the number of people served through activities carried out using grant funds, including demographic information disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, gender, disability status sexuality, immigration status, ZIP Code, and socioeconomic status (where such information is reasonably available and voluntarily provided); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEFFC5878FF4425A968F771DC2F0FF84"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any relevant feedback received by such organization from the populations served by such organization regarding—</text><clause id="H736637AF272F48FA966AD3026E5015E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the efficacy of support from sources other than programs and services provided by such organization using grant funds; and</text></clause><clause id="HD8A416F1B8ED42918F12346C1C6EF7C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>additional resources and services needed by such populations with respect to improving community safety.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB83FC24A61DE44EEB2C03BFCF685A5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted to the Secretary and Division of Community Safety pursuant to this section must protect the privacy of the individuals served. All of the information gathered as part of the reporting process shall be aggregated, anonymized, and used only for the purposes listed in this section and shall not be used to initiate or contribute to any criminal, legal, immigration, or Child Protective Services actions of proceedings, except where such reporting is required by law. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2FEB2E2921854DC6BADC364210BB915F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $4,000,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC1576D0158DC475BB8F121E425C3762E"><enum>202.</enum><header>Establishment of Community Safety Grant for Local Governments</header><subsection id="H2955018666534881B678FE9560C05525"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program established</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants, on a rolling basis, to units of local government to assess safety needs, conduct research on, fund programming on, and otherwise support the development of qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF58515A619A84C609AED5A1936728F8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A unit of local government seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including an assurance that the unit of local government shall develop, and submit to the Secretary, during the grant period, a safety needs assessment to guide local investments in qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="H921EDA4A3D87453D8B5994656593E9B0" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give a preference to a unit of local government that—</text><paragraph id="H1EDA0381035A4A059D1F7A680D07FF96" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has taken steps toward, or is submitting proposals within the application for such a grant for purposes of—</text><subparagraph id="H31D295C2125A40AB9F21046E1A353F04" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing human liberty, including through measures that reduce incarceration, pretrial detention, arrests, criminal supervision, immigration detention, and other forms of criminal justice involvement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5AA33FC4D6A4D97ABEB966FC6F07551" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ending the criminalization of poverty, mental illness, homelessness, substance use, and related issues by addressing root causes of those issues rather than imposing criminal punishment and other punitive responses; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H426A71FE68B04D4A9C0BC4B7C97B97EE" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ending racial, economic, gender, and other disparities in criminal punishment, including discipline in schools;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCC93C90143147D5869B4FBFEC46A0CE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a high rate of poverty, as well as disproportionately high shares of residents who have been impacted by violence and the criminal legal system (as determined by the Secretary); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59EB83D107BE4E5981C71EEA854C40B7" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has prepared and developed the application submitted under this section in consultation with the community the unit of local government serves, especially individuals in such community who have been directly impacted by the criminal legal system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H639FE1B992D6489DA369E3DD8E0052E6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A unit of local government receiving funds under this section shall use such grant funds to: </text><paragraph id="H70B74F212DD640FFB8FBD97A8A5C4D8F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish or designate a community-led entity that—</text><subparagraph id="HE3A7E65E7BE14CEAA41408771E133902"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employs qualified approaches to community safety; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA7DDB73A1EC4E6DBB71D481097320DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>can coordinate and make investments in community safety, including by using participatory budgeting or other community-led processes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBF78EB75B0148A8B62DFB1717D44A4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop a safety needs assessment and create an action plan targeted to address such safety needs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC52CE3F0E02E4217AED1894D04BBC6E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Invest in programs, interventions, or policy initiatives that have a demonstrable connection to improving community safety, including programs interventions, or policy initiatives that are designed to address needs related to economic stability, survivor safety, physical and behavioral health, environmental safety, housing stability, and educational equity and opportunity such as those listed in section 201(d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1013A2FF54D439CA940E04F68454D1F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Train and hire community health workers, including individuals who are trained in first response and violence prevention, who can help to address such identified safety needs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BEB2162BAEA4CFC83892F6BC9185986"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Administer programming, including via grants to community-based organizations and the direct deployment of community health workers, to implement the action plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE584D9A56B6646BF9649A7831CC04FEF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant amounts</header><text>In determining the amount of a grant awarded to a State or unit of local government under this section, the Secretary shall base such determination on—</text><paragraph id="HC44204E0B41D475B8D8F5C95FEA4FD8C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of people who live in the jurisdiction of the local government; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D42BE0BA52B4CF981B3DFC0AB2C7C40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the depth of need demonstrated, including attention to activities planned, the socioeconomic characteristics of the community and residents within that jurisdiction, and current patterns of spending in systems of incarceration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FED569879B944D1BE3FE8BB112144C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other factors as the Secretary determines are relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F3EF3CDA36141C1B035F89C5A7E054E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitations</header><paragraph id="HA680656DD6194AF2AE74040EEFB268CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Funds made available under this section may be used only to carry out programs, services, or activities that use qualified approaches to community safety.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8ED7ADEA46E04F86861738BCDE722E77"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State or unit of local government receiving a grant under this section shall certify to the Secretary that any individual hired using funds received through such grant will be paid a wage, which shall be at least the highest of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7FEB47EEF8044040B8E8F5B9B34D1E93"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$17 an hour.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09BC9E2AED8B495B8A4271BD8F3175DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The minimum wage under the applicable State or local minimum wage law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AC4BC8202924863942DED673F74C4DB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The prevailing rates of pay for individuals employed in similar occupations by the same employer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB01C0744DB5409F9029231EF3AA4F08"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Federal minimum wage in effect under section 6(a)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H259B804C16B7412D86B465B66650BF4A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not late<italic></italic>r than one year after the date on which a local government receives a grant under this section, and annually thereafter, the unit of local government shall prepare and submit to the Secretary, and make publicly available, a report containing information about—</text><paragraph id="H26C66E31AC95430B9253FE9F6ECA6D0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how the grant funds were used;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B9C304FF42341E3AB245E53CF138133"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of people who were cited, arrested, or jailed by any State or local law enforcement officers in the previous year in the jurisdiction of the local government, as compared to the number cited, arrest, or jailed during the term of the grant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H858CC657A1E84E28A3FA699AD2E8C7E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reasons for such citing, arresting, or detained or imprisoned;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B28F8BD3E3E4A828D5B88077E30B67F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demographic data of individuals cited, arrested, or jailed or referred by local law enforcement officers, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, gender, disability status, and socioeconomic status; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H095F7D0FDB10413193079B144B8B692B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the percentage of grant funds that ultimately benefited community-based organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E427627E65341A785F517B59399EFE2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>An unit of local government receiving a grant under this section may use Federal funds received through the grant only to supplement the funds that would, without such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources, and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4E370CA3D27E4831BD345B940F0A0756"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to implement this section $3,500,000,000 <italic></italic>for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB46A8875EF2B4C43872423BDB4DD197A"><enum>203.</enum><header>Establishment of Community Safety Grant for States</header><subsection id="HC15AFFE760DE476EA4805BECE9144877"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program established</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants, on a rolling basis, to States to conduct research on, fund, and otherwise support the development of qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="H350737A62E204D77988888C98758ECB6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A State seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including an assurance that the State shall—</text><paragraph id="HDDD84873431E4F219A9DEEFF2FE7FFEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish or designate a State agency, department, or office equivalent to the Division on Community Safety established under section 101, to oversee and support the use of qualified approaches to community safety statewide; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4083CA874159499F9D221E15F9CFFA3E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide matching funds equal to the amount of Federal funds received under the grant—</text><subparagraph id="HBC4A63B6C5794972997065D79657AA8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to fund qualified approaches to community safety; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6AD2287352C43CB95322D88B3C28969"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to provide an ongoing framework for continued funding of such qualified approaches.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H964BCB640DCB475D95BEEF3B77937C8C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to a State that meets one or more of the same criteria specified in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of section 202(c).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB7CD791842D24EE889362BF2F7E66A10"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A State receiving funds under this section shall use such grant funds to—</text><paragraph id="H73E56F4A67DE499F87B1104937EEA2E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make grants to community-based organizations implementing one or more qualified approaches to community safety, including as intermediaries making subgrants to other local organizations and community leaders who are leading qualified community safety programming on these issues;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95AAE8F81E8B4D7DA18CBF5BE41A6EFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fund local governments to undertake the activities described in section 202(d); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B42095CCACE4130AB8A1BBFBA7CC214"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fund education training for individuals who are taking jobs that advance qualified approaches to community safety. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2BB9EC1BD1C4740B315457199790A99"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant amounts</header><text>In determining the amount of a grant awarded to a single recipient under this section, the Secretary shall base such determination on—</text><paragraph id="HF7EB5001C03747F393B91EF8D77D01B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of people who live in the State; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA33753B5B97A4C7E94E5009DFB8D2A54"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the depth of need demonstrated, including attention to activities planned, the socioeconomic characteristics of the community, and current patterns of involvement in the criminal legal system; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78EFF8B39F914FFB8DBF07F46183063E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other factors as the Secretary determines are relevant; and</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD4C149CB7534BD39326DD6E87697602"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available under this section may be used only to carry out programs, services, or activities that use qualified approaches to community safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9CF437F2FB784297BDEA99193B51BFA6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not late<italic></italic>r than one year after the date on which a State receives a grant under this section, and annually thereafter, such State shall prepare and submit a report to the Secretary containing information about—</text><paragraph id="HFFA53B8937164BD7AF7A8A201A12EC48"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how the grant funds were used;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDED0952C9AD948DFA314EF16C0F3DB8D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of people who were cited, arrested, or jailed by State or local law enforcement officers in the previous year, as compared to the number cited, arrest, or jailed during the term of the grant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB11854AA48DC4C03BAD8618919B0A6B4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the reasons for such citing, arresting, or jailing; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32A6E795CB394733B089F913F2873783"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demographic data of individuals cited, arrested, or jailed or referred by State or local law enforcement officers, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, gender, disability status, and socioeconomic status.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H97C634D9B4E442D2A5D8A595D0F825B0"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>A State shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, without such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources, and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0332BB2CBB3C4734ADEB05D0B943EC1F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to implement this section $3,500,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCB31C4B5DB974B95A93FC8CC77F00CEF"><enum>204.</enum><header>First responder hiring grants</header><subsection id="HC8970E2336EF4D97B777BE491ADD7E8B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a grant program under which the Secretary makes grants to community-based organizations, health departments, States, units of local government, Indian tribal governments, other public and private entities, and multi-jurisdictional or regional consortia for the purposes described under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDAE6867630F148428C17219C28C64661"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grant amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant awarded under subsection (a) may be used to—</text><paragraph id="H77807690AB8F4129BEDEF55A3ECBFB60"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hire and train first responders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF266BA1D17FA48C0914F31D1610B7713"><enum>(2)</enum><text>procure equipment, technology, support systems, or pay overtime, to increase the number of first responders available to a community;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA693735563F4F66804C91F489ADC43F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>increase the number of first responders involved in activities that are focused on interaction with members of the community on crisis response and community violence and trauma prevention;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D913B59271646E5AE91227185C4F38A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide education and training to first responders to enhance their conflict resolution, mediation, problem solving, service, and other skills needed to work in partnership with members of the community, including by programs that incentivize individuals to complete such education and training;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC481FD0B2C074F3AA82310E08C86E936"><enum>(5)</enum><text>develop and implement innovative programs that support members of the community to work with community-based organizations, emergency first responders, and State, Tribal, and local officials in community violence and trauma prevention efforts; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC21155FA4964F0AAD6285CF138EBC6D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>establish school-based partnerships by employing and retaining first responders in pre-Kindergarten, elementary, and secondary schools to support trauma-informed care and behavioral and mental health services, and to operate school-based health centers in local schools. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21D7B7222E4547DBB6F0556A0E0C5D20"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><paragraph id="HEE580D7F740C4DCD8853BA7EE8B3F54E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Funds made available under this section may be used only to carry out programs, services, or activities that use qualified approaches to community safety.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A8597F9D4524BA281231D3C2B1124D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each entity that receives a grant under this section shall certify to the Secretary that any individual hired using funds received through such grant will be paid a wage, which shall be at least the highest of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H75843F8BFC644DEFA75A982C11A4873C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$17 an hour.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1F013E2157645E9A96DB121625D8398"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The minimum wage under the applicable State or local minimum wage law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H532E033295004C608FFC6B948AF11AFB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The prevailing rates of pay for individuals employed in similar occupations by the same employer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82FF65C0F24D46A080C87A274394F7F8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Federal minimum wage in effect under section 6(a)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E5F1CA4603C4A12AE395D0B7B7D1765"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $2,500,000,000 <italic></italic>for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028. </text></subsection></section><section id="H888BA7059E3B4DC3A263AC98413C2DB8"><enum>205.</enum><header>Non-discrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No person in the United States shall, on the basis of actual or perceived race, color, religion, national origin, sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), or disability, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under—</text><paragraph id="H877F3EDB6FB94B8FAAF3937052528908"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any program or activity funded, in whole or in part, with funds made available under this title; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA72DA76A21B43DCAF00D9289912B5BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other program or activity funded, in whole or in part, with funds appropriated for grants, cooperative agreements, and other assistance administered by the Assistant Secretary.</text></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

