<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4A8B1F26C4614D4F83D728708EF7330C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4313 IH: Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Reauthorization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4313</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001051">Mr. Carter of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reauthorize the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2D689E872B41461BA983FAB82665D882" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA0E3B7A8291E4D8187DB8543B02335E8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Reauthorization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H89CA7B5D7B194917A1C29D078EE52019"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1402 of the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8001">15 U.S.C. 8001</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3DC727CC689C42B484811978D73A12AB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H7210617BB5CF4348BD0DC86C6012F155"><enum>1402.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H78E664810F0346F0B42FA1C691EF2A75"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Drowning is a public health crisis. Drowning can happen in seconds, is often silent, and can happen to anyone, anytime there is access to water.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0CA7448E5D64477F80531707802CFE22"><enum>(2)</enum><text>About 11 people die each day from drowning in the United States, and drowning kills nearly 4,000 people each year in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C30B1C22DE54B47854CC6798CF10F72"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of injury-related deaths, drowning is the leading cause of accidental death in children aged 1 to 4 in the United States, and the second most likely cause of accidental death in children aged 1 to 14 in the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H174D815190854F4093ECCDD4E29A7FC1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Drowning death rates for Black people are 1.5 times higher than the rates for White people, and drowning death rates for American Indian people ages 29 and younger are 2 times higher than the rates for White people in the same age range.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H184C2074B95049DA9CBA749508A58678"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">People in rural areas of the United States are 26 percent more likely to die by drowning than people in urban areas of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H75A35F2B08824B6FB468F7D4D7079724"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Research shows that the installation and proper use of barriers or fencing, as well as additional layers of protection, such as swimming lessons, could substantially reduce the number of childhood fatal and nonfatal drownings in residential swimming pools.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H5FBBF9FE14514E4D82D934AC1CB96FBE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Covered entity defined</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1403 of the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8002">15 U.S.C. 8002</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA6435A35C4C14EDBADE2E14DD5462F83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (4) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H522308E1855A4EA8A95A6EF2F1C0031B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H0E964D073FDA4ED4B1B677F74AEB4744"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H31D225C334B6457E87DEFDD5499DA740"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D8E22F66EB648D2A2CE1562D806576A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE2832CB0AA6E43ADA69C32C2444323AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD50EA221F7C145B1A4BFA88D0E8E46FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (7) through (10) as paragraphs (8) through (11), respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H227C40571C684C5AB82F64B39741100C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (6) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEC5F4122DBD946E99B23FF973210A528" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H32F345FEDBA5469E8B0B7E116093F1DE"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>nonprofit organization</quote> means an organization that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9E076D4577ED4ABAA5E41664A0234286"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9812A172D73F4230A7DE265926095303"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has proven experience (as determined by the Commission) addressing swimming pool or spa safety and drowning prevention.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H67E7AC091E274A75B5C80ADBF8A4BBEB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Swimming pool safety grant program</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1405 of the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8004">15 U.S.C. 8004</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H04F07E474665451CB94F811AF21C4C53" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H9A53FC3A0A8141869624C7F6E08648C8"><enum>1405.</enum><header>Swimming pool safety grant program</header> <subsection id="H81B983E6CDD74C5683A648A6EC1C3AB1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations authorized by subsection (i), the Commission shall carry out a grant program to provide assistance to eligible covered entities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB51CEBBC400145BBA1C793202C51CDF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under the program, a covered entity shall—</text> <paragraph id="HA11A18D79832453182220A57196E72B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Commission that, as of the date on which the covered entity submits an application to the Commission for a grant under this section, the covered entity (if the covered entity is a State or an Indian Tribe), or the State in which or the Indian Tribe in the jurisdiction of which the covered entity is proposing to carry out activities using grant funds (if the covered entity is a nonprofit organization), has enacted and provides for the enforcement of a statute that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC853DDAFB7484AF2A6946ED968CD5D2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>except as provided in section 1406(a)(1)(A)(i), applies to all swimming pools constructed in the State or in the jurisdiction of the Indian Tribe (as the case may be) on or after such date; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1D3D1DCF0D94D11ACC77BEB3FA96A14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>meets the minimum State law requirements of section 1406; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD07F87DBE418486BB238B070E3CD6D78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit an application to the Commission at such time, in such form, and containing such additional information as the Commission may require.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5D4536EB994B46029CD1E47FC6E3A075"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection of grant recipients</header> <paragraph id="HCD9A6613472F4E91A7C47117175AF830"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting covered entities to receive grants under the program, the Commission shall give priority (in such order as the Commission considers appropriate) based on the following factors:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H472EC3EB230B40D4B71DBD239053FCAC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A covered entity not having previously been awarded a grant under the program.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5CD762F045B495AB0BC46A71ACD8F73"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity proposing to use grant funds to expand educational activities described in paragraph (1)(B)(i) or (2)(A) of subsection (e) that the covered entity is carrying out at the time when the covered entity submits the application for the grant.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC15B9AF6F1CE4AC6881C2537159A0A5D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity proposing to use grant funds to build on prior expertise and activities aimed at preventing drownings.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H774DE3E9206C413EAA877A0E6E4DA265" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity proposing to use grant funds to carry out activities in a geographic area that has a greater number per capita of drowning or entrapment incidents.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD787D0883F7A46D082BE8958AD5647EF"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity proposing to use grant funds in underserved, minority, or rural communities to provide services that address and target racial, ethnic, or rural drowning disparities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FFBD92DA1374D30B4933FEEE3B08AFB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Such other factors as the Commission considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB03C6505A3541B0BA97990C81AC0A20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3096AEB5F9D04470A12B14D839B06755"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting covered entities to receive grants under the program, the Commission shall, to the maximum extent practicable, ensure geographic diversity in the areas where activities will be carried out using grant funds.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6AC266AEDB71418EB57C4E6CA1C5F340" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>If the Commission awards grants to two or more covered entities that will carry out activities using grant funds in the same geographic area, the Commission shall provide technical assistance to such entities regarding how such entities may collaborate in carrying out such activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H196A65455CF941C4AE4DD8F2A00C8DFB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amount of grant</header><text>The Commission shall determine the amount of a grant awarded under this section, and shall consider—</text> <paragraph id="H35C363C3552C4265B93A8E94792F33E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a covered entity that is a State or an Indian Tribe—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB57D760BA3D7403C9D7671F13F3BDA91"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the population of such State or Indian Tribe;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0218F6311E804148BA54166559CF8FDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the enforcement and implementation needs of such State or Indian Tribe; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H61DF6D05072F4E6183B92EA61E742A81" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the education needs of such State or Indian Tribe proposing to use grant funds pursuant to subsection (e)(1)(B)(i);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8A0ACD81575E470DA28F9D328831686B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a covered entity that is a nonprofit organization, the number of individuals to whom such nonprofit organization is proposing to provide education described in subsection (e)(2)(A) using grant funds, taking into consideration any increased costs of providing such education due to the rural or remote nature of the area where such nonprofit organization is proposing to provide such education; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H41A70DE4DEBF44A7A24E0CC1167401A1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allocation of grant funds in a manner designed to provide the maximum benefit from the program in terms of protecting children from drowning or entrapment.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8EF1E25E18354BFABC01EC026FA5C48D" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header> <paragraph id="HAE95A6D5BFDD4FCEBFD95B95D74969C8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>States and Indian Tribes</header><text>A State or an Indian Tribe receiving a grant under this section shall use—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBDA2414203914AE883271E48AB651912"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least 25 percent of amounts made available—</text> <clause id="H57213F84CA754238B71997AF154DD5E6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to hire and train personnel for—</text> 
<subclause id="H57A784B913A24E3294A20C28EF511C91" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>implementation and enforcement of standards under the swimming pool and spa safety law of the State or Indian Tribe; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H66CA8B5105FF4EDEBC76F11BC6AE496F" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>inspecting and repairing or replacing swimming pool and spa drain covers to ensure compliance with applicable Federal, State, and Tribal law; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HDD3F7CA8BF4243C0851975E94D8CB30D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to defray administrative costs associated with the hiring and training programs under clause (i); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58C9439A81324B01910678995A6A574B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the remainder—</text> 
<clause id="H3CA77EDDBB0841A2AB185B05D962E978" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to educate pool owners, pool operators, and other members of the public about the standards under the swimming pool and spa safety law of the State or Indian Tribe and about the prevention of drowning or entrapment of children using swimming pools and spas, which may include the provision of swimming lessons (except that not more than 25 percent of such remainder may be used for the provision of swimming lessons); and</text></clause> <clause id="HE6727120FF0D4881A3589CA204602B7B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to defray administrative costs associated with the education programs under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDAED75BB2DCB4EC698A455F943EC603C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonprofit organizations</header><text>A nonprofit organization receiving a grant under this section shall use the amounts made available—</text> <subparagraph id="HFFFE411D04CD44538A65BDD09E0A26E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to educate pool owners, pool operators, and other members of the public about the prevention of drowning or entrapment of children using swimming pools and spas, which may include the provision of swimming lessons (except that not more than 25 percent of such amounts may be used for the provision of swimming lessons); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H092125E001404B51AE585B5E486E01D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to defray administrative costs associated with the education programs under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4895C539B0A545F3824D33DB25768E5C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Recipient reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the end of the pool and spa grant program project period covered by the grants awarded under this section, each covered entity that received such a grant shall submit to the Commission a report that includes the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB624E7AD9187421A982AB11ABCE8EBD2" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of grant funds received by the covered entity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0927FA4BDD3432687732DB8EB463095"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose or purposes for which the covered entity proposed to use grant funds in the grant application of the covered entity.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE1EDE6E952E44768A1356CDC432BF30E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose or purposes for which the covered entity used grant funds.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFAB8FD0D3D740A5954CA10BD6C56002"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Whether the purposes identified under paragraphs (2) and (3) were achieved.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H22E1978A7B3B472DB92C28AC2FABD8EB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any barriers encountered in carrying out activities using grant funds.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB252FB16814429698B98FF7BF2353C8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any best practices or recommendations for future recipients of grant funds.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6AC190271B74745A0CE578639534111"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other information requested by the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3B97827B197F47229F03011099550508"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Grant awareness campaign</header><text>The Commission shall carry out a campaign to conduct outreach to covered entities to ensure covered entities are aware of the availability and importance of the grants under this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC592B9BAB3D24A51BFC025CD39152391" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Employees</header> 
<paragraph id="H250BC4002D5B4AC1B5A90BC67C0AD8D2" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director of Drowning Prevention</header><text>The Commission shall have a Director of Drowning Prevention to coordinate the swimming pool and spa safety and drowning prevention activities at the Commission, including carrying out duties under this title.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0646A42FA69423C8A9579CFD5F556C5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Full-time equivalent</header> <subparagraph id="HBDD98258BAF3495D8A36E860D664D7C7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall ensure that at least 1 full-time equivalent is dedicated to carrying out the grant program under this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEEE9F0AF93794629BCD0F421D0EB98B6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Calculation</header><text>Any duties performed by the Director of Drowning Prevention may not be considered in determining whether the requirement of subparagraph (A) is met.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H64EB2EC574DD43F99C5DC6053EC24407"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 $5,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HD5ABB901CEF240BFA83B41180FF2B8E7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reauthorization of CPSC education and awareness program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1407 of the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8006">15 U.S.C. 8006</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE71ECD9C71D646B2A461C81FAE4D2054" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H324247F1E2B1455898051A5665347164"><enum>1407.</enum><header>Education and awareness program</header> <subsection id="H13230E9DBEE9450E95C2915ABC1354D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall establish and carry out an education and awareness program to inform the public of methods to prevent drowning and entrapment in swimming pools and spas. In carrying out the program, the Commission shall develop—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBFA5E313914A4873877204EEE0E45276"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educational materials designed for swimming pool and spa manufacturers, service companies, and supply retail outlets, including guidance on barrier and drain cover inspection, maintenance, and replacement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H464B796D0FB94660A6D588F2BFF03D32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>educational materials designed for swimming pool and spa owners and operators, consumers, States, Indian Tribes, and nonprofit organizations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H751DAD68FC3540A6A5824D2168E4E5B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educational materials designed to reach historically disadvantaged communities that have higher rates of drowning than the nationwide average; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H57150C587C86433083CAE4A5D585487C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a national media campaign to promote awareness of swimming pool and spa safety.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD0D985620A924DF0BDFD78E822F0BF73"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 $5,000,000 to carry out the education and awareness program authorized by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H0E6B4A843EB042F5B406216B00B58C45"><enum>6.</enum><header>CPSC report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1408 of the Virginia Graeme Baker Pool and Spa Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8007">15 U.S.C. 8007</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8103B8976F3647EA9152F93A20360DA6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HC70AEBE7F3E546E284D665239B6E5D90"><enum>1408.</enum><header>CPSC report</header> 
<subsection id="H5489A0FA186C431BA6D67AAA32E8346B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the last day of each fiscal year for which grants are made under section 1405, the Commission shall submit to Congress a report evaluating the implementation of the grant program authorized by that section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA185D7558D954459A60FE56E4D51C274"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) shall include, with respect to the fiscal year covered by the report, the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H17D2CCAE0B8B4383BC839D9BCBB46340"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How many applicants applied for grants under the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED94AD9213ED48E6ACACB787AD0E36FC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For each such applicant—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1C0B07DDCDB04C199E5F2641C10A0920" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>name;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H473724AC0A4343F6B9A46F3497E7E98C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>location;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A17BF1A70BB4547BB92D4CF3B67B90B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prior experience in swimming pool or spa safety; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF5EC8365534041188636894F059DD6EE" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other details as the Commission considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6996EC2F328A4935ADDC0D02F51B0D85" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How many applicants received grants under the program and the amount of the grant received by each such applicant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H887928544FF2461688A6FCDD6C39D2E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How recipients of grants under the program were selected and the purposes for which each such recipient proposed to use grant funds in the grant application of the recipient.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0865B27C8913445B84C17A24911EACA8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any purposes, other than making grants under section 1405, for which the Commission used amounts appropriated under subsection (i) of such section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB00D1E3E37FD4546B3456D6B30FDF0F8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An evaluation of the effectiveness of the program, including any barriers or gaps, and recommendations for legislative changes, if required to increase the effectiveness of the program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

