<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H41835EFCC14C49878D7426C8704579AF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5616 IH: Bringing Reliable Investment into Domestic Gulf Energy Production Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5616</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001176">Mr. Scalise</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Interior to conduct certain offshore lease sales.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H600B16C0DFEB47CAA72F34C5164FC1C8" style="OLC"><section id="H328063163B26413F8668C92C7FDA38A4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bringing Reliable Investment into Domestic Gulf Energy Production Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BRIDGE Production Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H87507FD4132B4EC487CE2C971A043848"><enum>2.</enum><header>Offshore oil and gas lease sales</header><subsection id="H395EB222B3A54CA282FA9A62FB9442B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD927B8CE03424EAF82177F9E93354112"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Offshore lease sale</header><text>The term <term>offshore lease sale</term> means an oil and gas lease sale—</text><subparagraph id="H3AFDA7C9A5044071B732C31FCFB9F2BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is held by the Secretary in accordance with the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>), notwithstanding the requirements of section 18 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1344">43 U.S.C. 1344</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18E5FC092A3E47F5810555385FD1A9FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offers the same lease form, lease terms, economic conditions, and stipulations as contained in the final notice of sale entitled <quote>Gulf of Mexico Outer Continental Shelf Oil and Gas Lease Sale 257</quote> (86 Fed. Reg. 54728 (October 4, 2021)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H963409C5EB664085A1A3151E94191C78"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that, if any acceptable bids have been received for any tract offered in the lease sale, results in the issuance of leases within 90 days of the sale to the highest bids on the tracts offered, subject to the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management <quote>Summary of Procedures for Determining Bid Adequacy at Offshore Oil and Gas Lease Sales Effective March 2016, with Central Gulf of Mexico Sale 241 and Eastern Gulf of Mexico Sale 226</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H76DED29BDBF04865A0BFAF2150EC9A53"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H546E55EB8862444B8DD48820CEBE00B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive any other requirements under section 18 of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1344">43 U.S.C. 1344</external-xref>) that would delay final approval of an offshore lease sale under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6C5FC556FFD749CE9E46B745305FE4AD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Notwithstanding section 18 of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1344">43 U.S.C. 1344</external-xref>), the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H9ADD394648E14E1CA414A73164604631"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct not fewer than 4 offshore lease sales during the 2-year period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1498F06BC5403F9845B38E86CB0F12"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the 2017–2022 Outer Continental Shelf Oil and Gas Leasing Program Final Programmatic Environmental Impact Statement and Record of Decision shall apply to lease sales conducted under this subsection and shall be sufficient for purposes of complying with the National Environmental Policy Act for offshore lease sales conducted under this subsection to the extent it does not conflict with this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE9BA9AA40B94E52B88FD6232AF1E8D9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>In conducting the offshore lease sales required under subsection (c), the Secretary shall conduct an offshore lease sale not later than—</text><paragraph id="HC1DCB417B32E4FACABE9DD74AEA0B1CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>March 31, 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32AF007CCC294B588B2C5C06882DB600"><enum>(2)</enum><text>August 31, 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20D4C8B2E8434F14841CAB0F10142968"><enum>(3)</enum><text>March 31, 2025; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0543CA364F104129A6D32C5475C0EDFF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>August 31, 2025.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35E968F6C7B04BE4B05B7FD5269327B6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Area offered for lease</header><paragraph id="H9D98993624E6440699A4DE655C5D6325"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Acreage</header><text>The Secretary shall offer not fewer than 80,000,000 acres for each offshore lease sale conducted under subsection (c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68908958AB2648D28ADC61EF7F229015"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Location</header><text>An offshore lease sale conducted under subsection (c) shall be in the Gulf of Mexico Region Program Area as identified in Figure S–1 of the 2017–2022 Outer Continental Shelf Oil and Gas Leasing Proposed Final Program published on November 18, 2016, by the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management (as announced in the notice of availability of the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management entitled <quote>Notice of Availability of the 2017–2022 Outer Continental Shelf Oil and Gas Leasing Proposed Final Program</quote> (81 Fed. Reg. 84612 (November 23, 2016)).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4BC80D2E7AF4483AA6EEAF9E13FC0278"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effect of litigation</header><paragraph id="HBD0DA24E1D6A42929A8607069887CD1A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A civil action challenging an offshore lease sale conducted under this section shall not—</text><subparagraph id="HA6E7AC25D88D4EDCA21CD8450A190883"><enum>(A)</enum><text>affect the validity of any lease issued under such an offshore lease sale; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1D801189A0B4DAD86EE90ED81968CDD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>except as provided in paragraph (3)(B), cause a delay in the timelines for the consideration of any exploration plan, development plan, development operations coordination document, applications for permit to drill, or other application for a Federal agency authorization or approval for activities on a lease issued under such an offshore lease sale.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC292CBADD3E3468CA9C038E7EC844635"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Remand; processing of approvals and applications</header><text>If, in a civil action described in paragraph (1), a court finds that the offshore lease sale was not carried out in compliance with Federal law—</text><subparagraph id="HD660B26E880F4A8E95C6B2723AB4E50F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the court shall not—</text><clause id="HEA9EC52401C449FE8D87A9D059D0C3E3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>set aside, vacate, or enjoin the offshore lease sale;</text></clause><clause id="HE80A5DAE9D854BD99889D713F150DFEB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>set aside, vacate, or enjoin the leases issued pursuant to the offshore lease sale; or</text></clause><clause id="H756E4DB0E1C74E8CBFE4DB6F76310150"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>enjoin the Secretary from issuing leases to the highest bidders in the challenged offshore lease sale;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AEA5D4DE9944C8D9514873C3476F231"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the court shall remand the matter to the Secretary and require the Secretary to correct the noncompliance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H710BCF87B56B415995A18CA150192CF3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary shall continue to process all exploration plans, development plans, development operations coordination documents, applications for a permit to drill, and other applications for a Federal agency authorization or other approval for activities requested under any lease issued under the challenged offshore lease sale in accordance with the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC94E739D4F1441FEBD0B62439812CB16"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice</header><subparagraph id="H89E23E707E744B7D8C9CE37B50984F24"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 10 days after the date on which a civil action described in paragraph (1) is served on the United States, the Secretary shall notify the holder of any lease issued, or apparent high bidder if the lease has not yet been issued, under the offshore lease sale that is the subject of the civil action of the filing of the civil action.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF352612606F84CBA8C1283C4F763ABE2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timeline</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of receipt of a notice under subparagraph (A), the holder of the lease may file with the Secretary, and the Secretary may approve, a request to pause the timeline with respect to the term of the lease during any period in which the civil action is pending.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

