<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9F9163B49C7543298687C2111190CCA9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2565 IH: To direct the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to establish an advisory committee for communities impacted by aviation, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2565</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230410">April 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to establish an advisory committee for communities impacted by aviation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF69291006B734F8BBB4F670BA40C4A2F" style="OLC"><section id="HD8E9ECBD6BE74525AE03B20BABD43902" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Impacted communities advisory committee</header><subsection id="H92213FFC03794BDCA593466BA30DDAC1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall establish an Impacted Communities Advisory Committee (in this section referred to as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H39CFC10FDB64438F828988EA293EE2D5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall provide advice and recommendations to the Administrator regarding community needs, objectives, plans, strategies, content, assessments, and accomplishments with respect to—</text><paragraph id="HB6FEAF44E0914EC7A8832E1D32E2408E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>noise policy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C0DCEA29A840AA92192F71BF4CADFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>community engagement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1F371D0031F47E5851BA7B586E60317"><enum>(3)</enum><text>noise, pollution, and health mitigation for communities close to airports and communities away from airports;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04D2B4B71E3C4F4F9970A2E3AE253F46"><enum>(4)</enum><text>integration of new or emerging technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BF33526FC724406AF9412D316C69268"><enum>(5)</enum><text>tools, policies, and analyses to accurately reflect impacts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7B10115CC014B57817C5304F1FCA57F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>material negative impacts of past Federal Aviation Administration actions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD950C5B6BF94A12A2933A392EFEDEF7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>other topics relevant to the Administrator and communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02C210C79B7540C69E23CDCC6663AB56"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="H3C2946DB9266440D990E430427653F05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Committee shall be composed of at least 30 members appointed by the Administrator from among individuals who are not employees of the Federal Aviation Administration, airports, or the aviation industry.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75E24CF81DA44869A8ED823908685874"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>The Administrator in appointing the members of the committee shall ensure that individuals who are represented are specially qualified to serve on the committee by virtue of their education, training, and direct experience from living in areas with substantial impacts from commercial aviation, general aviation, and currently or potentially impacted communities from advanced mobility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFC22A6956134710ABD4DF6916405206"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not more than 3 members may be a member of a roundtable or individuals currently serving on Federal Aviation Administration advisory committees, such as the NextGen Advisory Committee, Advanced Aviation Advisory Committee, and Research, Engineering, and Development Advisory Committee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB744542E79E04F1C831D3AF18DE61F93"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Member representation</header><text>In appointing members to the Advisory Committee, the Administrator shall ensure that the Advisory Committee is fairly balanced and that multiple perspectives are represented, including by ensuring the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE0A40C95844C400E9EEDF894E4E65B2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">20 members shall be from communities impacted by commercial aviation, of which—</text><clause id="HCCAE61FE1B3447DA868AB294BCBB5324"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 10 shall be from communities away from airports and the remaining from communities close to airports; and</text></clause><clause id="HDDEDA46060D44525B9DCFB172C394F0E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 15 shall be from communities with impact from Core 30 Airports designated by the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0669EFCD89C942449D094ABF70374CCB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>7 members shall be from communities impacted by general aviation, including sightseeing, rotorcraft, training flights, and private and business travel.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B62772ECDF64647995670B08F3F1F03"><enum>(C)</enum><text>3 members shall be from communities currently or potentially impacted by advanced air mobility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA101A6271EF946C3AC4E687A818023A2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public meetings</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall—</text><paragraph id="H7BF33904F3BC49EA8BABAF3FA7C95F8F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide public access through a virtual forum for all public meetings of the Committee; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CB26D4DAE1E4144BEDFDD43EA0B0372"><enum>(2)</enum><text>maintain an archive of recorded Committee public meetings.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5030A41D36724B1A9B680C564822E50C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Frequency of meetings</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall meet 4 times per year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H876BAB773263407280C6ED795AA8BF42"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Pay and expenses</header><text>Members of the Advisory Committee shall serve without pay, except that the Administrator may provide any member, while attending meetings of the Advisory Committee or a subordinate committee, travel or transportation expenses under section 5703 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H73335233F1434C378BB5EC33EC494B1F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Support staff</header><text>The Administrator shall provide from the Federal Aviation Administration support staff for the Advisory Committee.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0B0336CEF16F4519A97CCC77D48B80AB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Subordinate committees</header><text>The Administrator may establish any subordinate committees to the Advisory Committee to provide advice on specific areas of need and interest as determined by the Administrator. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

