<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8E796AA99245497E891834F630194CD2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6553 IH: To require the waiver of costs of activities relating to the evacuation of United States citizens endangered by acts of terrorism or war in Israel instigated by Hamas and other Islamist militant groups.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6553</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231201">December 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the waiver of costs of activities relating to the evacuation of United States citizens endangered by acts of terrorism or war in Israel instigated by Hamas and other Islamist militant groups.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC03BC6A0A73E48F98EB9D8F3C8257152" style="OLC"><section id="HC3A20CD085374F5CB1BF50766C60E0FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Waiver of costs of activities relating to evacuation of United States citizens endangered by acts of terrorism or war in Israel instigated by Hamas and other Islamist militant groups</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4 of the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2671">22 U.S.C. 2671</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAFEABE645EE64B32BE5ED668EACDB5C0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H2B1127C8789A4334ADF4397DB5146F9B"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With regard to the repatriations loan program, the Secretary of State shall waive the costs of activities related to the evacuation of United States citizens endangered by acts of terrorism or war in Israel instigated by Hamas and other Islamist militant groups on October 7, 2023, through November 17, 2023, to include the evacuation of United States citizens on United States Government-coordinated transport, from Israel, the Gaza Strip, the West Bank, and affected countries, including Cyprus.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

