<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H341F005C7C254445A9DE1F93032B2F8C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>92 HR 3656 IH: Wild Horse and Burro Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3656</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230524">May 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Act commonly known as the Wild Free-roaming Horses and Burros Act to prohibit certain uses of aircraft with respect to the management of wild free-roaming horses and burros, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H88ABEE2904314CB68167B84E3A403D02" style="OLC"><section id="HFC06C7A913A0487D96F2C4C71CCD7CEA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wild Horse and Burro Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9AECA4A1EBCC48908214B3423A17D622"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H02376E3952BF4B4990C4CD74F9E53EBB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of efforts to control equine populations under law, the Bureau of Land Management is directed to humanely capture wild free-roaming horses and burros for adoption.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA13DBC869E02400AB4B33EA11B4D442F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The use of helicopters to chase equines over prolonged distances, usually on rough terrain, is particularly dangerous, and can frighten the animals and lead to deadly situations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C790B84CE6E464D8FF8C9EC67F51E9A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In January 2022, during the horse gathering at the Pancake Complex in central Nevada, a young colt was chased for miles by helicopter, ultimately gravely injuring itself, and necessitating the need for the animal to be shot and killed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF629466147A42EDA3032FD0FBC00F9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Scientific research shows that more humane and cost-effective alternatives exist to control equine populations, including fertility controls.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H439FF8D80F274D228E067ADCC4D0A90B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since fiscal year 2006, Bureau of Land Management contractors have collected at least $57.4 million in taxpayer funding for roundups that utilize the use of helicopters, including bait-and-trap methods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H250445CB41824A888D522350DA5676CF"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since fiscal year 2017, the Bureau of Land Management has obligated at least $22.5 million in taxpayer funding for the specific purpose of helicopter roundups, including $6.5 million in fiscal year 2022 alone.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68364B1CFCF94AD7BA6124536A2C1AB0"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Currently, the Bureau of Land Management’s Wild Horse and Burro Program spends less than one percent of its budget on implementing fertility controls.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63317B86B7FC48C3B789F36D6D22A343"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The elimination of helicopters from the Bureau of Land Management’s gatherings would provide a more humane method of capturing equines, and provide significant savings to taxpayers.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H600C5145757E46ECB0D1ADB8C9BF3240"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendments to the Wild Free-roaming Horses and Burros Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 9 of the Act commonly known as the Wild Free-roaming Horses and Burros Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/92/195">Public Law 92–195</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1338a">16 U.S.C. 1338a</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H0F2BA0D66FF447939E01B00C420EEE48"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>In administering this Act</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(a) </enum-in-header>In general</header-in-text>.—In administering this Act</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47043E2427A748399A28A5DD07BCF77E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>helicopters or, for the purpose of transporting captured animals, motor vehicles</quote> and inserting <quote>motor vehicles for the purpose of transporting captured animals</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4E39839D6A44006BEDA502975B60684"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>fixed-wing aircraft, or helicopters, or to</quote> and inserting <quote>or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55950B99C24848B98FA9A0CC997C4D47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H60D0F933909D472AAB504664942249DE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HCDCD895D102C46FC8A94B58C3AEEE121"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on certain uses of aircraft</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In administering this Act, the Secretary may not use or contract for the use of helicopters or fixed-wing aircraft for the purposes of rounding up or gathering wild free-roaming horses and burros. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HF465A06ECBB14B8F8AE38DA72F77C33D"><enum>4.</enum><header>GAO Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit, to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate, a report that describes—</text><paragraph id="H775129333609442DBB235FAE0EC9496E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>humane alternatives to the use of helicopters and fixed-wing aircraft in managing wild free-roaming horse and burro populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD15D91417451414285100287A9C4A8FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>job creation opportunities presented by the use of such humane alternatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCC7E755CC6D48A1899EC90693D05900"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the effects of aircraft, including unmanned aircraft systems, on wild free-roaming horse and burro populations. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

