<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCD60354C774748A29CE67639A059E6EC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3344 IH: Justice for Incarcerated Moms Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3344</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To end the shackling of pregnant individuals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF185882514D8405A8B17688013CD7EDE" style="OLC"><section id="H94CA61B5B0E149A993EF87CD2A5EC3C6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justice for Incarcerated Moms Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HA4A6D1FB2D0E419FA7C59C7845A115DB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ending the shackling of pregnant individuals</header><subsection id="HB5F2202E96814689A290B098B38E42CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, in each State that receives a grant under subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151 et seq.</external-xref>) (commonly referred to as the <quote>Edward Byrne Memorial Justice Grant Program</quote>) and that does not have in effect throughout the State for such fiscal year laws restricting the use of restraints on pregnant individuals in prison that are substantially similar to the rights, procedures, requirements, effects, and penalties set forth in section 4322 of title 18, United States Code, the amount of such grant that would otherwise be allocated to such State under such subpart for the fiscal year shall be decreased by 25 percent.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD37551AB5D0D4AF9B2096DAEDBEDAFCE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>Amounts not allocated to a State for failure to comply with subsection (a) shall be reallocated in accordance with subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151 et seq.</external-xref>) to States that have complied with such subsection.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDB73B76F3B1544CE8D059D36F33BF764"><enum>3.</enum><header>Creating model programs for the care of incarcerated individuals in the prenatal and postpartum periods</header><subsection id="H37CAEA8322244BC6B262F1B503297FE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Prisons, shall establish, in not fewer than 6 Bureau of Prisons facilities, programs to optimize maternal health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum individuals incarcerated in such facilities. The Attorney General shall establish such programs in consultation with stakeholders such as—</text><paragraph id="HE4CF7A3B2D6E45478D2F40722407B8F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant community-based organizations, particularly organizations that represent incarcerated and formerly incarcerated individuals and organizations that seek to improve maternal health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89F9F3E9E1904B7296B998D28CCE9DD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant organizations representing patients, with a particular focus on patients from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31254107F547437694072EAEAEEAA134"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organizations representing maternity care providers and maternal health care education programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D14E0C780E643C58E3B7FE8B4534FCD" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>perinatal health workers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8B73517D91A42C298892B90DC907A1A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>researchers and policy experts in fields related to maternal health care for incarcerated individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A5750C01A9D4422AD573F05095B1CD4" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Start date</header><text>Each selected facility shall begin facility programs not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4721F4ACC32B4BDCAC8F0215E9D9741C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Facility priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Director shall give priority to a facility based on—</text><paragraph id="H53156657F3D2481C9E79F14B71B12C4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of pregnant and postpartum individuals incarcerated in such facility and, among such individuals, the number of pregnant and postpartum individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF9AB707885E427DBD960589D9662B1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which the leaders of such facility have demonstrated a commitment to developing exemplary programs for pregnant and postpartum individuals incarcerated in such facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H082ED96058F74A479652EC8B2C117445"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The programs established under this section shall be for a 5-year period.</text></subsection><subsection id="H303314264C4F43739760A0C076C97E78"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bureau of Prisons facilities selected by the Director shall establish programs for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals, and such programs may—</text><paragraph id="H2A8BE81245344C1991A7FA74A97BE8D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide access to perinatal health workers from pregnancy through the postpartum period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H273DC1FA2DFC42CF9DBDCB68BCEAA8E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide access to healthy foods and counseling on nutrition, recommended activity levels, and safety measures throughout pregnancy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7420368D09C41F793986FFF30B872B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">train correctional officers to ensure that pregnant incarcerated individuals receive safe and respectful treatment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15226BB59AE148C68AB8AF2A04D3B491"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">train medical personnel to ensure that pregnant incarcerated individuals receive trauma-informed, culturally and linguistically congruent care that promotes the health and safety of the pregnant individuals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67509F77C724437EB17D2A8279F41983"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide counseling and treatment for individuals who have suffered from—</text><subparagraph id="H69FE989BF0CE4CE3B858554EE4BE6AE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">diagnosed mental or behavioral health conditions, including trauma and substance use disorders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF25C57B8206C44FD8F3416CA829CCF74"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">trauma or violence, including domestic violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1662116334F4841BFFBE0C53AD651AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>human immunodeficiency virus;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F7BB464D9964BB1B4CC0453784E7810"><enum>(D)</enum><text>sexual abuse;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD6F1953F6694EF7AE2B4B80B973653B"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pregnancy or infant loss; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC8189D93B4F4DDCA9CE13113C5B4992"><enum>(F)</enum><text>chronic conditions; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD06E391E9C3248CEB96E40F6A451BFF3"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide evidence-based pregnancy and childbirth education, parenting support, and other relevant forms of health literacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04619093224C438CBD2EFB1099F015E6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide clinical education opportunities to maternity care providers in training to expand pathways into maternal health care careers serving incarcerated individuals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49A4F43D2A244F8588495BF9CAF9D70A"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer opportunities for postpartum individuals to maintain contact with the individual’s newborn child to promote bonding, including enhanced visitation policies, access to prison nursery programs, or breastfeeding support;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7830EC4ED2E64D6E8D4D3CE42C0F6251" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide reentry assistance, particularly to—</text><subparagraph id="H01EB1812053543EDA7CE243D461472AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure access to health insurance coverage and transfer of health records to community providers if an incarcerated individual exits the criminal justice system during such individual’s pregnancy or in the postpartum period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18C6994CEE3E45D4901538042153039C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">connect individuals exiting the criminal justice system during pregnancy or in the postpartum period to community-based resources, such as referrals to health care providers, substance use disorder treatments, and social services that address social determinants of maternal health; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE86C755E172D4BD19BCEB6A10EA3EC20"><enum>(10)</enum><text>establish partnerships with local public entities, private community entities, community-based organizations, Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations (as such terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>)), and Urban Indian organizations (as such term is defined in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>)) to establish or expand pretrial diversion programs as an alternative to incarceration for pregnant and postpartum individuals. Such programs may include—</text><subparagraph id="H2E021449C64A4C4E930427F0ED11D026"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based childbirth education or parenting classes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4782D9482D6B47FB852E1731C156CD71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prenatal health coordination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46781FA2EE5046AE9CA987864F1B5DA0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family and individual counseling;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFA4C7B4A5D546258D4ABF469AE000A1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evidence-based screenings, education, and, as needed, treatment for mental and behavioral health conditions, including drug and alcohol treatments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6888188F9C3848E3A9E32E733F7F357B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>family case management services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9A9330CC09C4B6680BC3A0B01D2D660"><enum>(F)</enum><text>domestic violence education and prevention;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44BEC7DE94EA498FB4BFF3ED1135F53D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>physical and sexual abuse counseling; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC049054E00E747689C406E0781F5779C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>programs to address social determinants of health such as employment, housing, education, transportation, and nutrition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF0620605D2A4BB1BE84C8D818717908" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Implementation and reporting</header><text>A selected facility shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="HB42C3BB8E59C4609A75F3F54B169C4EC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implementing programs, which may include the programs described in subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D4F5036BE65477E9790D31A0F008200" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and 6 years after the date of enactment of this Act, reporting results of the programs to the Director, including information describing—</text><subparagraph id="H9382799F15BD4A2E98B3A7C235BBE040" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant quantitative indicators of success in improving the standard of care and health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals in the facility, including data stratified by race, ethnicity, sex, gender, primary language, age, geography, disability status, the category of the criminal charge against such individual, rates of pregnancy-related deaths, pregnancy-associated deaths, cases of infant mortality and morbidity, rates of preterm births and low-birthweight births, cases of severe maternal morbidity, cases of violence against pregnant or postpartum individuals, diagnoses of maternal mental or behavioral health conditions, and other such information as appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE33F4C2B5EAC4303A2E99ED8C4F07AC2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant qualitative and quantitative evaluations from pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals who participated in such programs, including measures of patient-reported experience of care; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H273B01A21A0C4E18B8D90A815C9F8102" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strategies to sustain such programs after fiscal year 2028 and expand such programs to other facilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96C7A4ADCCFA41FDBB8D0F8990C6611B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director shall submit to the Attorney General and to the Congress a report describing the results of the programs funded under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA5FDEBF5EACC4054A4CA8A15E6436802"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Oversight</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall award a contract to an independent organization or independent organizations to conduct oversight of the programs described in subsection (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC6CD01CEAECF47EF902BF3183BD562E2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1FC3DD23B4BE4AA7BCD4CDEF15A0B9D1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grant program to improve maternal health outcomes for individuals in State and local prisons and jails</header><subsection id="H5F5B57A87E1F4FEE8B5D9A1A24AD59B1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance, shall award Justice for Incarcerated Moms grants to States to establish or expand programs in State and local prisons and jails for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals. The Attorney General shall award such grants in consultation with stakeholders such as—</text><paragraph id="HBC97E86FC65D4D8BA8F4F56F59100807"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant community-based organizations, particularly organizations that represent incarcerated and formerly incarcerated individuals and organizations that seek to improve maternal health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0FE2878FCCB49DBB46AD7ECDCB110E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant organizations representing patients, with a particular focus on patients from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC16FB0D1CA8740F69531DF4A469D6CBD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organizations representing maternity care providers and maternal health care education programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H741EC549677F49788E27D479ADFDD420" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>perinatal health workers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC8896099DFB4ABD8E5AEC04C69C9594"><enum>(5)</enum><text>researchers and policy experts in fields related to maternal health care for incarcerated individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D81D759180D4ABD9B5F0C3DAA2C7641"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>Each applicant for a grant under this section shall submit to the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Director may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB79B8B8CCA4945E8A2E0A7B89FD8B27D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State that is awarded a grant under this section shall use such grant to establish or expand programs for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals, and such programs may—</text><paragraph id="H17BD43398CFF4B038EA67B891B602297"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide access to perinatal health workers from pregnancy through the postpartum period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A9E2130A30C4541B45F9A6B399CE1E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide access to healthy foods and counseling on nutrition, recommended activity levels, and safety measures throughout pregnancy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDFEAD97D1B14EC9A0F779A18ED4F922"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">train correctional officers to ensure that pregnant incarcerated individuals receive safe and respectful treatment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA779623438D4490FA282DDC7493745E2"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">train medical personnel to ensure that pregnant incarcerated individuals receive trauma-informed, culturally and linguistically congruent care that promotes the health and safety of the pregnant individuals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9610819EF01D45E0B7FF7C1D6CD9AD98"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide counseling and treatment for individuals who have suffered from—</text><subparagraph id="H493F1D0BD829457D9F2D6D629961AF56"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">diagnosed mental or behavioral health conditions, including trauma and substance use disorders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6568A1A13A6749E0BD04F28B39162237"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">trauma or violence, including domestic violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1440A2B95C75454A8988ED0DA5909E56"><enum>(C)</enum><text>human immunodeficiency virus;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07DF2E982BE540948417E0BEBC73E6FB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>sexual abuse;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5875FFBB96184FEAA83C35CD6796886F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>pregnancy or infant loss; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F5500450BB24AE2964683C0EF8B8B7E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>chronic conditions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4677C007D9064580BFC516E2255B6B5B"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide evidence-based pregnancy and childbirth education, parenting support, and other relevant forms of health literacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA1C97D9966943B18C1B35ECBD03A9D0"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide clinical education opportunities to maternity care providers in training to expand pathways into maternal health care careers serving incarcerated individuals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H061E742F47EF46CB92B1D0FB5CC48FAB"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer opportunities for postpartum individuals to maintain contact with the individual’s newborn child to promote bonding, including enhanced visitation policies, access to prison nursery programs, or breastfeeding support;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B7C375479B4487FA892E55A16610116"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide reentry assistance, particularly to—</text><subparagraph id="H3D25179DD28D4DE8A0D7D1B3703129DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure access to health insurance coverage and transfer of health records to community providers if an incarcerated individual exits the criminal justice system during such individual’s pregnancy or in the postpartum period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H952722A4570D49E58C52731DF376F153"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">connect individuals exiting the criminal justice system during pregnancy or in the postpartum period to community-based resources, such as referrals to health care providers, substance use disorder treatments, and social services that address social determinants of maternal health; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A99655D95904510B8CB877A8E7C2B0C"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish partnerships with local public entities, private community entities, community-based organizations, Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations (as such terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>)), and Urban Indian organizations (as such term is defined in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>)) to establish or expand pretrial diversion programs as an alternative to incarceration for pregnant and postpartum individuals. Such programs may include—</text><subparagraph id="H97C99D3CE57940B1AE6790BB1A9AB506"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based childbirth education or parenting classes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A79D9075F9F44DE98D7B06316497F8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prenatal health coordination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE359D875AAC34F84B9C616A9BFD84A9F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family and individual counseling;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B645515BC29460B8E1C98314415C094"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evidence-based screenings, education, and, as needed, treatment for mental and behavioral health conditions, including drug and alcohol treatments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB93F50231D3148FC9A6DA1FD048C842E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>family case management services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4BCA0909F3F4F9B916D566622FB5F8B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>domestic violence education and prevention;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD4A26D47D984C0FBDE5E98CE2D78221"><enum>(G)</enum><text>physical and sexual abuse counseling; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H306587140F6B464C9D0DAD2C07CA12CE"><enum>(H)</enum><text>programs to address social determinants of health such as employment, housing, education, transportation, and nutrition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9DF157F3DFF8482E9F7F6F8709D9FE28"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Director of the Bureau of Justice Assistance shall give priority to applicants based on—</text><paragraph id="H349D149627F44FCF92B4024C3B92357C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of pregnant and postpartum individuals incarcerated in the State and, among such individuals, the number of pregnant and postpartum individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23C8CEA0C7664205BCF01E4B813F10A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which the State has demonstrated a commitment to developing exemplary programs for pregnant and postpartum individuals incarcerated in the prisons and jails in the State.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10B24999560943F8B1090E55BE3C7BCB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant awarded under this section shall be for a 5-year period.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1BFDEB616D58435FAD73CB84AE405DA8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Implementing and reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State that receives a grant under this section shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="HA378128C5CD9424A953814AE0CA8205F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implementing the program funded by the grant; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C61E0369B534CF38EB3ACF127FC4708"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and 6 years after the date of enactment of this Act, reporting results of such program to the Attorney General, including information describing—</text><subparagraph id="H5EAD44F1A9D34F8E9FDEEEF883782BE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant quantitative indicators of the program’s success in improving the standard of care and health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals in the facility, including data stratified by race, ethnicity, sex, gender, primary language, age, geography, disability status, category of the criminal charge against such individual, incidence rates of pregnancy-related deaths, pregnancy-associated deaths, cases of infant mortality and morbidity, rates of preterm births and low-birthweight births, cases of severe maternal morbidity, cases of violence against pregnant or postpartum individuals, diagnoses of maternal mental or behavioral health conditions, and other such information as appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC1E5EA597854BC6B84D68945C1A6BBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant qualitative and quantitative evaluations from pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals who participated in such programs, including measures of patient-reported experience of care; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0226438AACE4893B149F72B740D9AF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strategies to sustain such programs beyond the duration of the grant and expand such programs to other facilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDFCECEDA743B45CCA67696D2D6CB1B6B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall submit to the Congress a report describing the results of such grant programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB69494C3439141BBAD65DA785EA47F87"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Oversight</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall award a contract to an independent organization or independent organizations to conduct oversight of the programs described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H46D3EDA0539B460485DBAAB87D09594F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H98358832F40646FCBB7EB01FCAD7BCFE"><enum>5.</enum><header>GAO report</header><subsection id="HA8A60571484E42C68B955500912DD005"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on adverse maternal and infant health outcomes among incarcerated individuals and infants born to such individuals, with a particular focus on racial and ethnic disparities in maternal and infant health outcomes for incarcerated individuals. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA4B6DE4E96AC4749852E56C26129D927"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report described in this section shall include—</text><paragraph id="H89D6FDA937E04331AFC1A33E2992D1CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable—</text><subparagraph id="H642CAC72F289440DAC2FE947381D5EF3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of pregnant individuals who are incarcerated in Bureau of Prisons facilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4DA58EDBD6648A7AC7B2E426288FF88"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local correctional facilities, who have experienced a pregnancy-related death, pregnancy-associated death, or the death of an infant in the most recent 10 years of available data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C3BD4F7FEAB416182AC0A7118B845E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of cases of severe maternal morbidity among incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local detention facilities, in the most recent 10 years of available data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E4B4F7E955442B19C6C15816539B075"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of preterm and low-birthweight births of infants born to incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local correctional facilities, in the most recent 10 years of available data; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC181D993590746199DD1E8F5E906E66D"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">statistics on the racial and ethnic disparities in maternal and infant health outcomes and severe maternal morbidity rates among incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local detention facilities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H623C55FD451B42C1A0EFC455FB546CE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case that the Comptroller General of the United States is unable determine the information required in subparagraphs (A) through (C) of paragraph (1), an assessment of the barriers to determining such information and recommendations for improvements in tracking maternal health outcomes among incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local detention facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE8FE7512F0343D1B3FFC40AECA8976B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the implications of pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals being ineligible for medical assistance under a State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) including information about—</text><subparagraph id="H6C2AF01B38BB475C926FF32911505A80"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of such ineligibility on maternal health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum incarcerated individuals, with emphasis given to such effects for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEA1EE218A2548289BDABCCA3C024D82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>potential implications on maternal health outcomes resulting from temporarily suspending, rather than permanently terminating, such eligibility when a pregnant or postpartum individual is incarcerated;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2F5D20AEB38476A80EC3992F7DD0936"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the extent to which Federal, State, and local correctional facilities are holding pregnant and postpartum individuals who test positive for illicit drug use in detention with special conditions, such as additional bond requirements, due to the individual’s drug use, and the effect of such detention policies on maternal and infant health outcomes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85D05118430E4E8291B21F3D34C3422A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">causes of adverse maternal health outcomes that are unique to incarcerated individuals, including those incarcerated in Federal, State, and local detention facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H141774B807B8440397B284AC1E1F0C8C"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">causes of adverse maternal health outcomes and severe maternal morbidity that are unique to incarcerated individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1765DCFA2E76458CB30429AE0F7E8D58"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations to reduce maternal mortality and severe maternal morbidity among incarcerated individuals and to address racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes for incarcerated individuals in Bureau of Prisons facilities and State and local prisons and jails; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91FBF34F2241441AA8221A7AFB675000"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other information as may be appropriate to reduce the occurrence of adverse maternal health outcomes among incarcerated individuals and to address racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes for such individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA5FF5822CDDB45AB8B6C5C8ABF99448C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HE3C194A779694491A55AAAC0E849ACC9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Culturally and linguistically congruent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>culturally and linguistically congruent</term>, with respect to care or maternity care, means care that is in agreement with the preferred cultural values, beliefs, worldview, language, and practices of the health care consumer and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82E6732C13E64F1D8173F274E3D1B7C7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> means a death occurring during or within a 1-year period after pregnancy, caused by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications, including a suicide, overdose, or other death resulting from a mental health or substance use disorder attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA610DC73611C46B3B4CBEB3A8926E90D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maternity care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternity care provider</term> means a health care provider who—</text><subparagraph id="HB6D628C6122D4939BF8524D929320FFF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a physician, a physician assistant, a midwife who meets, at a minimum, the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives, an advanced practice registered nurse, or a lactation consultant certified by the International Board of Lactation Consultant Examiners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3F372DDB8054AE9A29D49D7400CB70C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has a focus on maternal or perinatal health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B10A54C7F5E4789B0757EEC41DED8A5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Perinatal health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal health worker</term> means a nonclinical health worker focused on maternal or perinatal health, such as a doula, community health worker, peer supporter, lactation educator or counselor, nutritionist or dietitian, childbirth educator, social worker, home visitor, patient navigator or coordinator, or language interpreter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23D72074C35C434E86157C3D0CEE87A6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Postpartum and postpartum period</header><text>The terms <term>postpartum</term> and <term>postpartum period</term> refer to the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy of an individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA06535015FEE45979BEBEC81EB15D3D3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Pregnancy-associated death</header><text>The term <term>pregnancy-associated death</term> means a death of a pregnant or postpartum individual, by any cause, that occurs during, or within 1 year following, the individual’s pregnancy, regardless of the outcome, duration, or site of the pregnancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCABD47E5C3164BCB99740A80A629BD24"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Pregnancy-related death</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pregnancy-related death</term> means a death of a pregnant or postpartum individual that occurs during, or within 1 year following, the individual’s pregnancy, from a pregnancy complication, a chain of events initiated by pregnancy, or the aggravation of an unrelated condition by the physiologic effects of pregnancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF336949221041D7883E0FEDFBA19E28"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Racial and ethnic minority group</header><text>The term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAC8118AF6C148AC9B8C6423AAD0410F"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Severe maternal morbidity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>severe maternal morbidity</term> means a health condition, including mental health conditions and substance use disorders, attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy or childbirth that results in significant short-term or long-term consequences to the health of the individual who was pregnant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39C6CFFA114E453C900462BEF3743AFF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Social determinants of maternal health</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social determinants of maternal health</term> means nonclinical factors that impact maternal health outcomes.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

