<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H9D067499908F4C63ABAEFAF106B215CA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 2980 RH: DOE and NSF Interagency Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 169</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2980</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–209]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on April 27, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for Department of Energy and National Science Foundation research and development coordination, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HSY00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H6B74239BA15647FEAE3EA22441963CA6"><section id="H776ED09EBB1A428A95C0D64E1E6F7AF5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DOE and NSF Interagency Research Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HA9E217094F2C4B02AFC6CDD963DE365E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Energy and National Science Foundation research and development coordination</header><subsection id="H0E05D789F66E4F07BDC2D62DFE8EC538"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Energy (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) and the Director of the National Science Foundation (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>) shall carry out cross-cutting and collaborative research and development activities focused on the joint advancement of Department of Energy and National Science Foundation mission requirements and priorities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA96A6B5A09454B44A62955CD1257EB25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text>The Secretary and the Director shall coordinate the activities under subsection (a) through the establishment of a memorandum of understanding, or other appropriate interagency agreement. Such memorandum or agreement, as the case may be, shall require the use of a competitive, merit-reviewed process, which considers applications from Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, non-profit institutions, and other appropriate entities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF36C1426EDF145EFB1269C4B8F9BC712"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and the Director may—</text><paragraph id="H0F981AC39F2F4113B5509EDC8A65B3F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct collaborative research in a variety of focus areas, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H71E3DDC65BAE4D2FBA72605438134045"><enum>(A)</enum><text>basic plasma science and engineering, including applications in astrophysics, materials science, fusion science, and accelerator science;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC2F5BCC5C8496CA0C0C07ED8A9D553"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fundamental biological and computational science and engineering, including computational neuroscience and neuromorphic computing, including in collaboration with the program authorized under section 306 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18644">42 U.S.C. 18644</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H262256190B924CDC8E293049D281996C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">modeling and simulation, machine learning, artificial intelligence, data assimilation, large-scale data analytics, predictive analysis, and advanced computational, storage, and networking capabilities in order to optimize algorithms for purposes related to energy and climate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54D757BAD9564C09AE05CF18186AF246"><enum>(D)</enum><text>quantum information sciences, including quantum computing and quantum network infrastructure, including in collaboration with the programs authorized under sections 403 and 404 of the National Quantum Initiative Act (15 U.S.C. 8853 and 8854);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4E1CCF65E884E7EB0E6EC5F02A5DE80"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">energy and materials science and engineering, including artificial photosynthesis, plasma, solar fuels, and fusion, including in collaboration with the programs authorized under sections 303 and 307 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (42 U.S.C. 18641 and 18645), and section 973 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16313">42 U.S.C. 16313</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD595A989BD74E6881B64ECCB52E29EB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>advanced manufacturing technologies, including efficient storage systems and alternatives to high-temperature processing, for the purposes of optimizing energy consumption, including in collaboration with the program authorized under section 975 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16315">42 U.S.C. 16315</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90276A285FBD462695949C701A1850A2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>microelectronics, including novel chip architectures, memory systems, and interconnects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACE09F43157E410F8547E94E1754DB01"><enum>(H)</enum><text>advanced physics, including high energy and particle physics, accelerator research and development, and high performance computational tools, including in collaboration with the programs authorized under section 303 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18641">42 U.S.C. 18641</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB46828CDCA94BF692128207EDC72556"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote collaboration, open community-based development, and data and information sharing between Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, nonprofit institutions, and other appropriate entities by providing the necessary access and secure data and information transfer capabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF978F3A56F264F6F8A21905C95781789"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support research infrastructure, including new facilities and equipment, as the Secretary and Director determine necessary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H552867D58FA54A9B88C4DEF3AAB78E4E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>organize education, training, and research initiatives relating to STEM education and workforce development, including—</text><subparagraph id="HF3663B34B1914E04B8246544AC9197CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">internships, fellowships, and other research or work-based learning opportunities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FC208DC29BD48C085F1F86219B36E57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>educational programming for students at all levels, especially experiential and project-based learning opportunities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H972819CAB073416881C5D7E08E124F23"><enum>(C)</enum><text>professional development opportunities for educators and researchers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7AEC3EF62E0F42E987817A274EB53819"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and the Director are authorized to—</text><paragraph id="HF75804DDE2554695915521F029E81299"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out reimbursable agreements between the Department of Energy, the National Science Foundation, and other entities in order to maximize the effectiveness of research and development; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9477037EADE4572A8018564B475931E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with other Federal agencies, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H05CD07FC67A1471086CD4B2A517DF835"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary and the Director shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report detailing the following:</text><paragraph id="H5D94D84AAD034CE0845FF86965D6C6E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Interagency coordination between each Federal agency involved in the research and development activities carried out under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECBD5F2EA95F4908B1E3DD790C3B4A96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Potential opportunities to expand the technical capabilities of the Department of Energy and the National Science Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8639A6EA32534C9A87827029229F25A0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaborative research achievements.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22A7C10FA0AA48D8AF8DDB094DCD42A0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Areas of future mutually beneficial successes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H254F4886A2214289B5FE94B7C0DC1911"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Continuation of coordination activities between the Department of Energy and the National Science Foundation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8965B0C0F71E4735A403B397613420F2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Research security</header><text>The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (enacted as division B of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>)).</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

