<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7FF223BA592F41C99B6308F0B499EBD6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 912 IH: Comparison of Sustainable Transportation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 912</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct an analysis of the costs of converting light-duty vehicles in the Federal fleet to electric vehicles, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD007640FC35D4D318EBAF8A391F21556" style="OLC"><section id="H6BA40A027C21410DB63BF571BA86BDB3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comparison of Sustainable Transportation Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COST Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H56BA0F390D784E70A3B10973188B9E85"><enum>2.</enum><header>Cost analysis of converting Federal fleet to electric vehicles</header><subsection id="HFB878732C2B84720BDA38FF43B7049BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Cost analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct—</text><paragraph id="HE183F44024854D8186BDF5279B1FCCF7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of the costs of replacing the light-duty vehicles in the Federal fleet that are fueled by gasoline with electric vehicles, including plug-in hybrid electric vehicles; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H938E6B6BAE244E5A941D4958EDACE67C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of the costs of replacing the light-duty vehicles in the Federal fleet that are fueled by gasoline with flex-fuel ethanol vehicles.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H708A3E689C384E79AA2D5607DBC32808"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>Each analysis conducted under subsection (a) shall include the costs necessary for deployment of infrastructure for each applicable type of electric vehicle or flex-fuel ethanol vehicle that it is feasible to be used in the Federal fleet nationwide.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFC38C842C2CB45C78B4E3C8AFE1EC210"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall publish online the cost analyses conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H461DABFEC9E24EA8BF8A1618B21332EE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Analysis of lifecycle emissions of E85 capable flex-fuel and electric vehicles</header><subsection id="H9C29F1BE21A747D0B281155BC9D962B1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy, utilizing the most recent Greenhouse gases, Regulated Emissions, and Energy use in Transportation model (commonly referred to as the “GREET model”) developed by Argonne National Laboratory, shall conduct a lifecycle analysis of greenhouse gas emissions from each of the following types of vehicles: </text><paragraph id="H334C707FAD3048388764A457DC323D0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A conventional gasoline vehicle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CCE1CAB56F74B539BFA6D0F0D3FC93A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An E85 capable flex-fuel vehicle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78544FADDAD348D5BAB7357D5CE092E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A battery electric vehicle.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB6658DF5095D451CA502EE10ED96A645"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the lifecycle analyses conducted under subsection (a). </text></subsection></section><section id="H286DF091D5C544629FF532ADAFBCE0F4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H89E869AE9C074C31A047510CD1A66FDF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>E<enum-in-header>85</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>E85</term> means a fuel containing 85 percent ethanol and 15 percent gasoline.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67200194287D41588B893797E4285990"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal fleet</header><text>The term <term>Federal fleet</term> means the fleet of federally owned or operated motor vehicles as reported in the most recent Federal Fleet Report of the General Services Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A9CD8FEB4EA4C309998D51D26D2F07C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Light-duty vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>light-duty vehicle</term> means a vehicle with a gross vehicle weight rating of less than or equal to 8,500 pounds. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

