<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H72F3BC2B3CCB48328F716A5ECBC4F032" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3267 IH: Comforting Our Military Families through On-base or Remote Treatment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3267</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the provision of non-medical counseling services to a member of the Armed Forces, or a dependent of such member, by a mental health professional, without regard to the location of the provider or recipient of such services.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1EACB98D1054ABA9B12D8E6C6174B27" style="OLC"><section id="H6A3963BD5D7A4840892EF44322502390" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comforting Our Military Families through On-base or Remote Treatment Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COMFORT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6238F1F696E241B0AE0CB15188F57643"><enum>2.</enum><header>Non-medical counseling services for military families</header><subsection id="H71ED3DF0369E461C98383BF46C5D5E40"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Non-Medical counseling services</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a mental health professional described in subsection (b) may provide non-medical counseling services to military families at any location in a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States, without regard to where the provider or recipient of such services is located, if the provision of such services is within the scope of the authorized Federal duties of the provider.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA8E56A1709814486B5C29A325DE0F511"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered mental health professionals</header><text>A mental health professional described in this subsection is a person who is—</text><paragraph id="H73A68EECE05141FABE114B944503ACE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a currently licensed or certified mental health care provider who holds an unrestricted license or certification that is—</text><subparagraph id="H8CF64F3CAB2140E0B56D80790DF55080"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issued by a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5837894CE751425C9C663844BA0DEABF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognized by the Secretary of Defense;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9568D3CAAD0A46768DF4B6596FACF7A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a member of the Armed Forces, a civilian employee of the Department of Defense, or a contractor designated by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FCF5B42665D4F00B0A71D636587467C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>performing authorized duties for the Department of Defense under a program or activity referred to in subsection (a). </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

