<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC5D2C70210DC4773B266E76336F06FDA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6140 IH: Facilitating Access to Swiftly Transport Goods during a Publicly Announced State of Emergency Situation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6140</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To facilitate access to swiftly transport goods during a publicly announced state of emergency situation.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H70F9B4DD705E4D0CA240D9626996D76E" style="OLC"><section id="H3B8E4CA818094E809EE24C0F9FC3FC50" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Facilitating Access to Swiftly Transport Goods during a Publicly Announced State of Emergency Situation Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAST PASS Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HFC856858E5884173A6D98563B4FF9077"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on critical cargo</header><subsection id="HD80FD1266F5D425AB02E355425818A58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Transportation shall initiate a study to examine—</text><paragraph id="HD729FC8D0ACE4BD4B1E05A4E2EC0DD6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>efforts to expedite the movement of critical cargo through ports and marine terminals; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCED07FEFCE2C4AECB77C9B814ADB98EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>methodologies, practices, and processes for moving such cargo during an event for which an emergency is declared by the President or a Federal agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4ECDCB6B9F5940979D053D453DDB2D6B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall examine methodologies, practices, and processes for—</text><paragraph id="HDF58F5BB3792441994F0390DF595B243"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying critical cargo and expediting the movement of such cargo through the marine terminals and ports;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B02C25CCE04DA6817E45CCA4CD059E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expediting the movement of critical cargo across all modes of transportation after leaving marine terminals and ports; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C1F9D61CD1740F3B6D60447D9E5EB84"><enum>(3)</enum><text>mitigating the impact on the movement of other cargo that is not critical.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF2801E95DD5A4B6AB9353736C8762E68"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with—</text><paragraph id="HA236337F023F436D80BD8F4E1F49028E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD12894440B634117868680F7697DB18C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>other relevant Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB6A2E7BE0E8A494AA15EC67ED219469E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Request for information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall issue a request for information in the Federal Register seeking public comment on the matters to be considered in the study required under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA726DA8EE8840B2A1D9F9923D4D426B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report containing—</text><paragraph id="HDE0AEDB4D5714AB2998B040471F598C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the findings of the study conducted under subsection (a); and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01C163A65828422691C753BAE7429B33"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations for methodologies, practices, and processes described in such subsection, including recommendations for using data from commercial and government data tracking initiatives to—</text><subparagraph id="HD4EABDF7CDDD4DE3A5FA28240B306CEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine when cargo is critical and needs to be expedited;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H571650198159487094EC0D78D6D57EF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify such critical cargo at port and marine terminals; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7759A90B617942B5B973B2BA7F6F2277"><enum>(C)</enum><text>expedite the movement and distribution of such cargo to end users.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5787C6BF24954700BEE53F8B6A664A26"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Secretary may establish 1 or more voluntary pilot programs to test the effectiveness of methodologies, practices, and processes for expediting the movement of critical cargo through ports and marine terminals.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

