<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H91E969181C7C46CA8392A7CCB95ACF3F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 915 IH: Motor Carrier Safety Selection Standard Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 915</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a national motor carrier safety selection standard for entities that contract with certain motor carriers to transport goods, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H22F2C496D37E454C8371E87458957E92" style="OLC"><section id="H7786C22A927B4BB4A26EBFC8A3271B5B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Motor Carrier Safety Selection Standard Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5D4F47DB42E542149E7F73FA96EF05BF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Motor carrier selection standard of care</header><subsection id="H55AD5296B0C44273A8186B23AE7230F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H15104E105D3941C38FF6969C3C86445E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selection standard</header><text>For any applicable legal requirement with respect to a covered entity contracting with a covered motor carrier for the shipment of goods or household goods, the covered entity shall be considered reasonable and prudent in the selection of such motor carrier if the covered entity verifies, not later than the date of shipment and not earlier than 45 days before the date of shipment, that the covered motor carrier—</text><subparagraph id="H4F28F9796F1946228E95D87F9DA8074F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is registered under section 13902 of title 49, United States Code, as a motor carrier or household goods motor carrier;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD913461CE43C4A12886F32A19C77C4B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has at least the minimum insurance coverage required by Federal and State law; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H005AE96E576D425DB8DDE047F9D17F87"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not determined unfit to operate safely commercial motor vehicles under section 31144 of title 49, United States Code, or otherwise ordered to discontinue operations by the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration (including not renewing a Department of Transportation registration number) or a State, for intrastate commerce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8505FBE312C24CE3B9B6FDF4EA1E0196"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The standard established under paragraph (1) shall sunset on the effective date of a regulation issued pursuant to subsection (c). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3EF4B0FB5C1C49CB854CD2996DA75BE2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Revocation of registration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 31144(a) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF8D7E54775BC452DB51DC48BB275E6C3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3) by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C37A3870242442BBCBAE49503438FA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4) by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67C5279E265842BBB72401E289AAA234"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC173BCF1C5054D119A9ECDCB7A1B15ED"><paragraph id="HD5C65AD9967A4067A9652A74A6E56301"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prescribe by regulation a process for revoking the registration of an owner or operator determined unfit to operate safely a commercial motor vehicle under this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4D2024E4575B4A9E8EB4145253C1BEAF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><paragraph id="HCAEE0FBF11AD4A91A3205DAFEEBF88A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HAD85EFA989A946B68D5C73190534C093"><enum>(A)</enum><text>update and revise the regulations issued pursuant to subsection (b) of section 31144 to include the requirements of subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27828BD21AC94E048BDED759C8170DFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>issue such regulations as are necessary to carry out section 31144(a)(5), as added by this Act. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CFC9E0C1DC74C48BA1993375599A056"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors for an unsatisfactory rating</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations updated under paragraph (1)(A) shall provide a procedure for the Secretary to determine if a motor carrier is not fit to operate a commercial motor vehicle in or affecting interstate commerce in accordance with such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H39642389EDA2411893513BE289AC238B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to preempt or supercede any State law or regulation relating to drayage. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4289795CB89D41F6858B3938E57B6BDA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H892DAAD07D9B408099C3EE636137F6F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means a person acting as—</text><subparagraph id="HCF62B92D668D4ADF962B18218C125FF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a shipper or cosignee of goods, except that such term does not mean a person acting as an individual shipper (as such term is defined in section 13103 of title 49, United States Code);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF84BD5BA2F68407EBBFF50A55BEE2A2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a broker, a freight forwarder, or a household goods freight forwarder (as such terms are defined in section 13102 of title 49, United States Code);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDE5B754756E433E83F2A56F0251FA34"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an ocean transportation intermediary (as such term is defined in section 40102 of title 46, United States Code), when arranging for inland transportation as part of an international through movement involving ocean transportation between the United States and a foreign port;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F84A565EE7D46B0BFDC151C741B6D3D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an indirect air carrier holding a Standard Security Program approved by the Transportation Security Administration, only to the extent that the indirect air carrier is engaging in the activities as an air carrier as defined in section 40102(2) or in the activities defined in section 40102(3); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5E05EBCBA6344DF858EC49D9F73877A"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a customs broker licensed in accordance with section 111.2 of title 19, Code of Federal Regulations, only to the extent that the customs broker is engaging in a movement under a customs bond or in a transaction involving customs business, as defined by section 111.1 of title 19, Code of Federal Regulations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA006F91AC19640A7BD4A204D48112A49"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a motor carrier registered under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/139">chapter 139</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE41F75DA4D294A9AA9699452014A7E4D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered motor carrier</header><text>The term <quote>covered motor carrier</quote> means a motor carrier or a household goods motor carrier (as such terms are defined in section 13102 of title 49, United States Code) that is subject to Federal motor carrier financial responsibility and safety regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE17655CC056947C38F74657E3AFBB547"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Household goods</header><text>The term <quote>household goods</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 13102 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEB14A459CA546528691EC2E14B3D154"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

