<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H07219C11DAB243A285762923A4EE047D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5055 IH: Office of Technology Assessment Improvement and Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5055</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To rename the Office of Technology Assessment as the Congressional Office of Technology, to revise the functions and duties of the Office, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3987A514ADD14DFDB60798ADD6133453" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H7018EA8541D346EF9EF194CB57CFBD61"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Office of Technology Assessment Improvement and Enhancement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HE9605C0D9F054F11BCA1E0A801A70A69"><enum>2.</enum><header>Renaming of Office of Technology Assessment as Congressional Office of Technology</header> <subsection id="H512A3A7560D747DE8B3BCFF9C4F70246"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Renaming</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(a) of the Technology Assessment Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/472">2 U.S.C. 472(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>the Office of Technology Assessment</quote> and inserting <quote>the Congressional Office of Technology</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB972FB781ACC435A977A1B0061BAA6DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/474">2 U.S.C. 474(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>Director of the Office of Technology Assessment</quote> and inserting <quote>Director of the Congressional Office of Technology</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC6C51CC60B9948E5A145E5EA6B1F25FB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The heading of section 3 of such Act is amended by striking <quote><header-in-text style="traditional" level="section">Office of Technology Assessment</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="traditional" level="section">Congressional Office of Technology</header-in-text></quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7429169007154138B66B6D38D96FEC9E"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">References in law</header><text>Any reference in any law, rule, or regulation to the Office of Technology Assessment shall be deemed to be a reference to the Congressional Office of Technology.</text></subsection></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H1F194A9CA2E042019E279434AC9CFBF2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Revision of functions and duties of Office</header> <subsection id="H4C75A1800A164350A20AE701D7DB7182"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Basic functions and duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(c) of the Technology Assessment Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/472">2 U.S.C. 472(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFA0ADD9AE30444CBA3ADCF1B0C495B4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting after the first sentence the following: <quote>This information should be provided as expeditiously, effectively, and efficiently as possible while maintaining a forward-looking, holistic, and rigorous approach to the assessment of the impacts of technology.</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99CE311542414376A0D3FBDDD076A006"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>completed analyses</quote> and inserting <quote>completed analyses, as well as preliminary findings of ongoing analyses,</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2343BF8C847946DE82FAC721BBFB654E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (7);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE6C2D995A1A41D7A5B8AD34FBF70794"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (8) and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF589F64F95E849B48734688D6607C535"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6FA4FB9411BA4F4E9FC5223CEB273B6A"> <paragraph id="HF45CC5834C0A4780B0CA84E927284445"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information to Members and committees of Congress in the form of briefings, informal conversations, documents, and similar formats which may be provided expeditiously on the basis of existing research and staff expertise without the need for review by the Board;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H601C57CDEA2F4B3F905B1195EAE00B9D"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide technical assistance to Members of Congress on legislation related to science and technology which may be provided expeditiously on the basis of existing research and staff expertise without the need for review by the Board; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3F14BBBF7204B7B8CF08A2CF8D491B7"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">when requested, provide objective policy options to Members of Congress on how the Members may achieve goals with respect to science and technology policy.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBB846B24BA3D4DCE9E195017603247C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements for initiation of assessment activities</header><text>Section 3(d) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/472">2 U.S.C. 472(d)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BDC10FF7FC7467A8237CEFBFB348A01"> <subsection id="HE59A70A74015447EBF97A32FADC747F8"><enum>(d)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H127D3D020D484C748FE5D8BDB6B84398"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assessment activities undertaken by the Office may be initiated upon the request of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H79E134240C0B447184CD1806825046BB" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (2), any Member of Congress (including a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress), any standing, special, or select committee of either House of Congress, or any joint committee of Congress;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F9B648D23F34DCCB3C7B17E24618132" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Board; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD47021FE553046B89A1AE1689979A476" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director, in consultation with the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D00BFC1C097497497A5CBC6CB8236AC" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB5834019923F4CD9B49787D7E124BE62"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A Member of Congress or committee requesting that the Office undertake an assessment activity under paragraph (1)(A) shall submit the request to the Board, which shall review the request. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EC824D8E4554948A9D683B74EA71409"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office shall determine whether or not to undertake an assessment activity in response to such a request in accordance with such policies and procedures as the Office shall establish, under which—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA8A8764C14245D79E7E5AAE1D65EE96"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Office may give priority to those requests which, in the Board’s determination, relate to technology issues of the greatest relevance and importance;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD9AE62B160614C60B7C752E5B7EC3863"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the greatest extent practicable, the Office shall ensure that the number of assessment activities undertaken during a year in response to requests which are submitted by members of one political party is equal to the number of assessment activities undertaken in response to requests which are submitted by members of another political party; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8B4773D4A744B528DDBF8708DF312CF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the greatest extent practicable, the Office shall provide the Member of Congress or committee submitting the request with information regarding how the Office reached its determination in response to the request.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H69EE91D065C549C1B606CA47131D13FB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public availability of findings of completed analyses</header><text>Section 3(e) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/472">2 U.S.C. 472(e)</external-xref>) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), in the second sentence, by inserting after <quote>may be made available to the public</quote> the following: <quote>(and, in the case of findings of completed analyses, shall be made available to the public)</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1516FEA552734728AE85DA1F26ACD0F0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorizing appointment of technical and professional personnel on leave from academic, industrial, or research institutions</header><text>Section 6(f) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/475">2 U.S.C. 475(f)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>The Director may, under the authority provided by this subsection and in accordance with such policies as the Board chooses to prescribe, appoint for a limited term, or on a temporary basis, scientists, engineers, and other technical and professional personnel on leave of absence from academic, industrial, or research institutions to work for the Office.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H27214BAB4AB947F0BFED4E46F8C626A9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Avoiding unnecessary duplication of research activities with other offices</header> 
<paragraph id="H34DC01A51690474CB4BA541483D26E93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Congressional Research Service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/477">2 U.S.C. 477</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4063D612EA84D468CAF42CB20B8BC0D"> <subsection id="HE3B06F87EFCE4C21AE77471E902109F0"><enum>(e)</enum><text>The Office and the Congressional Research Service shall coordinate technology assessment activities to avoid unnecessary duplication or overlapping of research activities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H482D216DCC654B4DAFAFA504EF88904F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Government Accountability Office</header><text>Section 9 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/478">2 U.S.C. 478</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H417B817B6AED49F2B0A623B1A9BD0786"> <subsection id="H4202020BAB2E4C51939CCB0B88DD79EF"><enum>(e)</enum><text>The Office and the Government Accountability Office shall coordinate technology assessment activities to avoid unnecessary duplication or overlapping of research activities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC074871D159846E0B30C911288E91C9D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Technology Assessment Board</header> 
<subsection id="HE0C05D594F24473BAAEB4ADC4E11FEC5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Appointment of members of Board by Congressional leadership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4(a) of the Technology Assessment Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/473">2 U.S.C. 473(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H2E526C21392E4789B9D87C0C21A766B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>appointed by the President pro tempore of the Senate</quote> and inserting <quote>appointed jointly by the Majority Leader and the Minority Leader of the Senate</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7217CF13F54B4069803EF498BE138469"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>appointed jointly by the Speaker and Minority Leader of the House of Representatives</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8B173E81BF9D43978F783EF5C09F243B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Invitation to Members of Congress To attend annual meeting of Technology Assessment Board; annual report</header><text>Section 4 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/473">2 U.S.C. 473</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB6A016C5EB104B8F8500654AB6AD141B"> 
<subsection id="HB0268BE8B90E40528DE5935301F2BAE9"><enum>(e)</enum><text>At least once during each calendar year, the Board shall hold a meeting at which Members of Congress may appear and present information to the Board regarding any technology assessment activities the Members may wish the Board to undertake.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3C21C8986FA24EBE806B242A2BA790DF"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of each calendar year, the Board shall submit to the Subcommittees on the Legislative Branch of the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on the activities of the Office during the year, and shall include in the report a description of the technology assessment activities undertaken by the Office during the year, including the number of requests received from Members and committees of Congress under section 3(d)(1)(A), the number and type of assessment activities undertaken in response to such requests, and the current status of such assessment activities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

