<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9F80D52C6C6C499285EC4A92F9F96EE5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 198 IH: Drug Pricing Transparency and Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 198</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase reporting requirements and transparency requirements in the 340B Drug Pricing Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H94C10F7BE5E7486C9D3DC03EE9D8BCCC" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4093E2D32D604604A595A0EBB8616869" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drug Pricing Transparency and Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7E5338732B4940AFBEE3ECDC8A53D0CB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Moratorium on registration of new non-rural section 340B hospitals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 340B(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256b">42 U.S.C. 256b(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H89C5880ED05D411B8BC6943DB424B84A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(L), by striking <quote>A subsection (d) hospital</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to paragraph (11), a subsection (d) hospital</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2149B72642B24B9891B7C8D2583A2F03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC913B2E880884802B779B12897814D15" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HC1ACB4F1B36745D7BB93B38EB53060A5"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Moratorium on registration of certain hospitals</header><text>During the 2-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this paragraph—</text> <subparagraph id="H8A27C54BD71B490C95F56810C8E15A08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an entity described in paragraph (4)(L) shall not be considered a covered entity under this section unless such entity was a covered entity on such date (as evidenced by the entity having been identified as a covered entity as of such date under the covered entity identification system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv)); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1565D83C56BB40CA8A93169AC7D20183"><enum>(B)</enum><text>no site shall be added to the covered entity identification system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv) or be permitted to begin participating in the drug discount program under this section, as a <quote>child site</quote> or otherwise, on the basis of association with a covered entity described in paragraph (4)(L) unless such site was identified as a child site as of December 31, 2020, under the system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCDB5A249B7C84A89BF462E12FD77727A"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Regulations to be issued during the moratorium period to implement statutory requirements clarifying hospital eligibility criteria and hospital child site standards and enhancing hospital transparency</header> <subparagraph id="HFF833E7DB150495C83CCF820AF05E72C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Issuance of regulations</header> <clause id="HC57F767F834146C4B1850A3AF6381D80"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>During the moratorium period under paragraph (11), the Secretary shall promulgate regulations through notice and comment rulemaking to implement the standards and requirements described in subparagraph (B).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D8865C6B5424C95B5B3320C357C516F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>Such final regulations shall be promulgated and take effect—</text> <subclause id="H0EA1E662913343A4A006E940A72760B4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>before the end date of the moratorium described in paragraph (11); or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H282C9DACA28E4337A367458C14D44541"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the event that any of such regulations have not taken effect by such end date, the moratorium under subparagraph (11) shall be extended until such regulations are final and effective.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H20E389A813624C50B69CDB671B936D04"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The authority to promulgate regulations under this paragraph is limited to setting forth the details necessary and appropriate to carry out the requirements of subparagraph (B) efficiently, effectively, and in conformity with such subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73C30F1DFEEF417F873301105BBEA297"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Standards and requirements</header> 
<clause id="H7EC65CB3D3184F5CBFD7B83E3EC8506C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Hospital Child Site Standards</header> 
<subclause id="H9E32FFBD9B5C420E9EA0535DBDB8CA83"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Hospitals described in subparagraphs (L) and (M) of paragraph (4) may register off-campus outpatient facilities associated with the hospital (also known as <quote>child sites</quote>) to participate in the drug discount program under this section (beginning after the moratorium under paragraph (11) ends), if—</text> <item id="H9541BA72089D41268A0A01F2E2A62897"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the site is listed on the hospital’s most recently filed Medicare cost report on a line that is reimbursable under the Medicare program (or, if the hospital is a children’s hospital that does not file a Medicare cost report, the hospital submits to the Secretary a signed statement certifying that the facility would be correctly included on a reimbursable line of a Medicare cost report if the hospital filed a cost report);</text></item> 
<item id="HBFD9D7E84A6644DC98EF26EA290341E6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>such cost report demonstrates that the services provided at the facility have associated costs and charges for hospital outpatient department services under title XVIII of the Social Security Act (or, if the hospital is a children’s hospital that does not file a Medicare cost report, the hospital submits to the Secretary a signed statement certifying that the services provided at the facility include or consist solely of outpatient services);</text></item> <item id="HF7313CE6809442DDB352306402D2F23A"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the facility is wholly owned by the covered entity;</text></item> 
<item id="H0B38D6B6C572497F8ED9335AD4D749FE"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>the Secretary has made a determination, under the process described in section 413.65(b) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), that the facility meets the Medicare provider-based standards under section 413.65 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations);</text></item> <item id="H021F08EA354941E9932451C7FAD976A6"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>the facility provides a full range of outpatient services, in addition to drugs; and</text></item> 
<item id="H1B502753505A4218BEC4DA48BAB8D460"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>the facility adheres to the charity care policy and any sliding fee scale policy of the parent hospital.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H46AA5F4D5D584AE2A04ECA74DEBB91DB"><enum>(II)</enum><header>De-registration</header><text>If at any time following registration one or more of the standards listed above are no longer satisfied, a registered hospital shall immediately notify the Secretary, de-register the facility, and keep the facility from making any purchases under the drug discount program under this section or representing to third parties that it may purchase under such program.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE182B39B233E4892A636C3DB415EAB6F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Hospital eligibility standards for hospitals not owned or operated by a unit of State or local government</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (L)(i) of paragraph (4):</text> <subclause id="H3F901E58869247C6BD8ABCD6011F5D26"><enum>(I)</enum><text>A private hospital has been formally granted governmental powers by a unit of State or local government if the Secretary receives a certification from a State or local governmental entity that such governmental entity has formally delegated, through State or local statute or regulation or, if permitted by applicable State or local law, through a contract with a State or local government, to the hospital such a power, described in detail in the certification.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2229A194E8E04F7C903973A54301F5D7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>A private hospital has a contract with a State or local government to provide health care services to low-income individuals who are not entitled to benefits under Medicare or Medicaid if—</text> <item id="H57BA558D7DE04DDEA1B8AE9D8894091F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the hospital submits a copy of the contract to the Secretary for review;</text></item> 
<item id="H71ED2CEE875446FDA595F186CAEA2B17"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that the contract creates an enforceable obligation for the hospital to provide direct medical care to low-income individuals ineligible for Medicare and Medicaid in an amount that represents at least 15 percent of the hospital’s total costs for all items and services furnished at such hospital; and</text></item> <item id="HFC680F8BC531479CB04DC2FBAA2147F0"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the contract is available to the public as part of the information describing the hospital in the covered entity identification system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv).</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H523BE3AFF1724AEBADC870B3786FD4F6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>If at any time a hospital not owned or operated by a unit of State or local government no longer meets one or more requirements under subclause (I) or (II), the hospital shall immediately notify the Secretary, dis-enroll from the drug discount program under this section, and stop making purchases under such program and representing to third parties that it may purchase under such program.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H94C5C5DC9F3B4792AF7CFA29869335A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Hospital transparency requirements</header> <subclause id="H008F1483E8EE4D0089BD7972AF7D781D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Hospital requirements to identify section 340B drugs</header><text>In the case of covered entity hospitals described in subparagraph (L) of paragraph (4):</text> 
<item id="H76D1404E14514EFBB34194C9A53CB790"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>Claims for covered outpatient drugs purchased under the drug discount program under this section shall be submitted to public and private payors using the 340B modifier established by the Secretary under the prospective payment system for hospital outpatient department services, in conformance with paragraph (22) of section 1833(t) of the Social Security Act, subsection (h) of 1847A, subparagraph (F) of section 1927(a)(5), and paragraph (5) of section 1857(g), that is <quote>JG</quote>.</text></item> <item id="HD2D77028304446F3A767A114A527DAD5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>Such hospitals shall report to the Secretary on an annual basis, in a form and manner specified by the Secretary—</text> 
<subitem id="HEFEC9A42D7474B128B4D8AB580DC212B"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the hospital’s aggregate annual revenue from drugs purchased under the program under this section, minus its aggregate annual acquisition costs for such drugs, broken out by hospital and by each child site;</text></subitem> <subitem id="H1DD76C8A62E74CCCA4B7F9A373365406"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>any dispensing fees paid by the hospital or child site to contract pharmacies for such drugs;</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="H175878A96A0A44479565398148822323"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>the patient mix, broken down by expected payment source (including at least the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act, a State plan under the Medicaid program under title XIX of such Act, private insurance, and uninsured individuals), for each such hospital, and each child site of the hospital listed in the covered entity information system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv), and the costs incurred at each such hospital and site for charity care (as described in line 23 of Worksheet S–10—Hospital Uncompensated and Indigent Care Data to the Medicare cost report or as reported in any successor form);</text></subitem> <subitem id="HF34FA64770CD4A028EE57161DCD7F2C3"><enum>(DD)</enum><text>the percent of total revenues (net of any discounts) at each site derived from infusion or injection of physician-administered drugs, including any associated items or services furnished incident-to the administration of such drugs; and</text></subitem> 
<subitem commented="no" id="HDC5073C9B8A54F8E8F526EEEC96BFCBE"><enum>(EE)</enum><text>with respect to such hospital and each child site of the hospital, the names of all third-party vendors or other similar entities (including split fee vendors and contract pharmacies) that the covered entity contracts with to provide services associated with the program under this section (broken down by covered entity and by each child site).</text></subitem></item></subclause> <subclause id="H3AE5C5DDF9594044AE1859D97125BCF8"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make the information reported to the Secretary under subclause (I)(bb) available to the public (with redactions of any information the Secretary determines to be proprietary or confidential) in an annual compilation of the reported information available on the internet website of the Department of Health and Human Services, and as part of the information describing the hospital and the relevant child site in the covered entity identification system established under subsection (d)(2)(B)(iv).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HE458E75D667045DB8D02DBF6B39ACA0A"><enum>3.</enum><header>340B claims modifier</header> 
<subsection id="HB01A2E4C817C4B8F895F3840FC2B62C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>Section 1927(a)(5) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-8">42 U.S.C. 1396r–8(a)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE91F4E34A10431CBDAD9C48B78D3215" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HE6E5E73AFB6245748A81FD690CA507C5"><enum>(F)</enum><header>340B claims modifier</header> <clause id="HB29926E56C8A4425BC69CAE0B1C364B4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All claims submitted to a Medicaid fee-for-service program or a medicaid managed care organization (as defined in section 1903(m)(1)(A)) for reimbursement of a unit of a covered outpatient drug subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act shall include the 340B modifier established by the Secretary under the prospective payment system for hospital outpatient department services under section 1833(t) that is <quote>JG</quote> or the Submission Clarification Code of <quote>20</quote> developed by the National Council for Prescription Drug Programs (NCPDP).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC742E8BD9E64464097E711A7B5B960B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Data sharing</header><text>Each single State agency shall make available to a manufacturer of a covered outpatient drug any fee-for-service or managed care claim for reimbursement for a unit of such drug for the purpose of verifying the propriety of any claim for a rebate payment under an agreement under subsection (b) with respect to such drug. At the manufacturer’s request, in lieu of making such a claim available to the manufacturer, the single State agency may instead provide a list of claims (and relevant data concerning each claim) for covered outpatient drugs that were purchased under an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act or other summary data specified by the manufacturer.</text></clause> <clause id="H9CB0B33CE9BD4BA5AF41018AF453ACD5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Each single State agency shall publish an annual report on utilization of covered outpatient drugs subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act by the Medicaid fee-for-service program or a medicaid managed care organization (as defined in section 1903(m)(1)(A)) during the preceding calendar year. The State agency shall not include confidential patient-specific, drug-specific, or manufacturer-specific information in any such annual report.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4AF43E8064814110B9F004E0CEF05642"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medicare</header> 
<paragraph id="HE746EBB6D8DA4F1B8F29B588E12FF4C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medicare part B</header> 
<subparagraph id="H571B45E061944592BDB82396EB05E5B4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Hospital outpatient department services</header><text>Section 1833(t) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F977EC4E5D64831857A36175BD66971" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HB2DD365DEA2F49EE92FFA416AB907C60"><enum>(22)</enum><header>340B claims modifier</header><text>All claims submitted under the system under this subsection for reimbursement of a unit of a covered outpatient drug subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act shall include the 340B modifier established by the Secretary under such system that is <quote>JG</quote> (or <quote>TB</quote> in the case of a claim for reimbursement under such system submitted by a hospital described in subparagraph (M) or (N) of section 340B(a)(4) of the Public Health Service Act or a rural sole community hospital described in subparagraph (O) of such section).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC568CE7BA85D49ACB64823CC8C9E7D2A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other part B claims</header><text>Section 1847A of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-3a">42 U.S.C. 1395w–3a</external-xref>) is amended by adding the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H689C82168DF94C3DBA1D7854E0634269" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H9C6143733ED6400086B3DBBA420F3DFE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>340B claims modifier</header><text>All claims submitted under this part (other than under the prospective payment system for hospital outpatient department services under section 1833(t)) for reimbursement of a unit of a covered outpatient drug subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act shall include the 340B modifier established by the Secretary under such payment system that is <quote>JG</quote>.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2788A89BB2C4EC6A5D2CE113FF1ADA7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Medicare Advantage and Medicare part D</header><text>Section 1857(e) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-27">42 U.S.C. 1395w–27(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83659B670D9A4C4BB30343525DE6CA5D" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H3055BBF9AFFB4B65BD2FECFDEA7600F3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>340B claims modifier</header><text>All claims submitted to a Medicare Advantage organization or a PDP sponsor under this part and part D, respectively, for reimbursement of a unit of a covered outpatient drug subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act shall include the 340B modifier established by the Secretary under the prospective payment system for hospital outpatient department services under section 1833(t) that is <quote>JG</quote> or the Submission Clarification Code of <quote>20</quote> developed by the National Council for Prescription Drug Programs (NCPDP).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD9F72272FE442479E3315F72F933A7A"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report on utilization under Medicare part B</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall publish an annual report on utilization under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j et seq.</external-xref>) of covered outpatient drugs purchased subject to an agreement under section 340B of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256b">42 U.S.C. 256b</external-xref>) during the preceding calendar year. The Secretary shall not include confidential patient-specific, drug-specific, or manufacturer-specific information in any such annual report.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD54AA50776404C6F8A2FAF6412C9172A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section take effect on the date that is 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act and apply to claims submitted on or after that date.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF061BC6B65404F8386693902DE38F3E6"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 340B of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256b">42 U.S.C. 256b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF952877591AB48B59DEB1DA6ADE74982" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H650A8A1D3E004A938BD04CE034057447"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header> <paragraph id="H87732D381F05432280438E5E2F037C1A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>OIG report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Office of the Inspector General shall submit to Congress a final report on the level of charity care provided by covered entities described in subparagraph (L) of subsection (a)(4) and separately by child sites of such covered entities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DA3CB26F5EA455EAA3B4ECC9AD1E721"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GAO reports</header> 
<subparagraph id="H2820A7E101C740DCA1C4AEBE5E644CCB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report—</text> <clause id="H493D92CC6DEC4E459D37B5848AE8B6EC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>analyzing the State and local government contracts intended to satisfy the requirement under subsection (a)(4)(L)(i) for a covered entity to qualify as an entity described in subparagraph (L) of subsection (a)(4);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0F478637BB1B44D7B8DB2748C3F047D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assessing the amount of care such contracts obligate such entity to provide to low-income individuals ineligible for Medicare under title XVIII of the Social Security Act and Medicaid under title XIX of such Act; and</text></clause> <clause id="H440D800AE07C4F1A9A5A38ED3E07DACF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">analyzing how these contracts define low-income individuals and whether the Secretary reviews such determinations.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17D6389F86B84867B8FAA87D9647D3C1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a final report on the difference between the aggregate gross reimbursement and aggregate acquisition costs received by each such covered entity (including child sites of such entity) for drugs subject to an agreement under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HC8CE061694424490B108139935FB7E72"><enum>5.</enum><header>Medicare requirement for hospitals regarding 340B drug information</header> <subsection id="H6A52DD0F449449638A34B73FE01AEE8F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1866(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H759D8EA38E8A43F8A00249279414B23F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (X), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2FFD0BB2E5D44ED6BC7969F2D1BE20BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (Y), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9868136866324ABBA2EA1B4B5C75FF8F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (Y), the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H514F29679621448A8523DCD5D8A1F677" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H0C8771BFA9DE4DBFB407ADFC5E9DE575" indent="up1"><enum>(Z)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a hospital that is a covered entity under subsection (a)(4) of section 340B of the Public Health Service Act, to include in any cost report submitted to the Secretary under this title information on—</text> 
<clause id="H593F25CD5E2C444B9E9E17A5C57BB3F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the aggregate acquisition costs of the hospital for drugs, the purchase of which were attributed to the hospital, during the period covered by such cost report and for which the hospital received a discount under such section 340B; and</text></clause> <clause id="H0708B13CD94B41ADB725741C191EEF2A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the aggregate revenues the hospital received from all payors for such drugs, disaggregated by insurance status (including the Medicare program, the Medicaid program, the Children's Health Insurance Program, private health insurance, and uninsured).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F6FFD08FDBD4313BE7C3E5C3394FCB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply to contracts entered into or renewed on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

