<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCF483A625134411B8B74D0BB36BED172" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4658 IH: Sanction Transactions Originating from Pernicious Chinese Companies and Policies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4658</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit securities investments that finance certain companies of the People&#8217;s Republic of China and to expand the Non-Specially Designated Nationals Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies List of the Office of Foreign Assets Control, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBB051172B5F1462FBC74FAFD78FC2A1A" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6D330FD0690E4CA099C7C83EFC855057"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sanction Transactions Originating from Pernicious Chinese Companies and Policies Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STOP CCP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5924F5FCDEE84A31895F7B4B98720610"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HFCE7F868F18847F696CDF9536929D0F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chinese entity</header><text>The term <term>Chinese entity</term> means an entity organized under the laws of the People's Republic of China or otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Government of the People's Republic of China. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7F0F6A5F94974820994874FFB906FDF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publicly traded securities</header><text>The term <term>publicly traded securities</term> includes—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HB0C43BD8635243EEA814008BE79C524D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any security (as defined in section 3(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>)) denominated in any currency that trades on a securities exchange, or through the method of trading that is commonly referred to as <quote>over-the-counter</quote>, in any jurisdiction; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE90D9E7C26854A40914143FE008EDF59"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any security that is derivative of or designed to provide investment exposure to a security described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0E83E417C4454059AE82334A0C370CC2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term <term>United States person</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H7869D8C6316E4DB78ABEEA89C0111E0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE608ED05773740CE9A4C45C1941A1E05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H965E6204104948C59B2A6B0D3DE196A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any person in the United States. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="HC80D76B15C7B486A8F7EA2813D2A2D44"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on securities investments that finance certain companies of the People's Republic of China</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The following activities by a United States person are prohibited: </text> <paragraph id="HB2E90D0EED204D36992BBC3789BECBDD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The purchase or sale of any publicly traded securities, or any publicly traded securities that are derivative of such securities or are designed to provide investment exposure to such securities, issued by any person determined by the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of State, and, as the Secretary of the Treasury deems appropriate, the Secretary of Defense—</text>
<subparagraph id="H85F387BD05384FBABF0EA28B78979A64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to operate or have operated in the defense and related materiel sector or the surveillance technology sector of the economy of the People's Republic of China; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H632CC9E80FFA46899CD9DCCF19073ECC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to own or control, or to be owned or controlled by, directly or indirectly, a person described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8F63F967691A4E79AB38403FEA7FE03D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The execution, support, or servicing of a purchase or sale described in paragraph (1). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA212D2A861E4CD9AD5E840D4D5EC89C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any transaction that evades or avoids, has the purpose of evading or avoiding, causes a violation of, or attempts to violate the prohibition under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC9F37ABF6EAF4747901AA353869D133F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any conspiracy formed to violate the prohibition under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA2A4C1DAA75F4A3C9630870FA497D7BD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expansion of Non-Specially Designated Nationals Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies List</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall prescribe regulations to expand the Non-Specially Designated Nationals Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies List (commonly referred to as the <quote>NS–CMIC List</quote>) of the Office of Foreign Assets Control to include—</text>
<paragraph id="H23A1626167C34F778A217DC11D3C8995"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any entity engaged in supporting the Chinese military-industrial complex; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFC368B647614C0AB41A0A1BC941F1BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any entity that is owned or controlled by an entity described in paragraph (1); </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H494CFF3BF0EE46348772DE35B11AE4CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any entity that is formed from a spin-off, merger or acquisition, or sale of a business unit involving an entity described in paragraph (1) or is otherwise a successor to such an entity; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB3D5ABBCDA24EC997DD84E3CA0028C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any entity that provides financial services for an entity described in paragraph (1), (2), or (3).</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H6163AFCC229E4A42904F2A1B650768C6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Closing sanctions loopholes</header>
<subsection id="H191EF510ABED453CB7C84EBD6E045A16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If sanctions are imposed with respect to a Chinese entity under any statute or Executive order described in subsection (b), sanctions shall be imposed with respect to the Chinese entity under each other applicable statute and Executive order described in subsection (b) unless—</text> <paragraph id="H9C9BA35A0B924C2AA5C175D462771763"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President waives the imposition of such sanctions; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF8B3D457FDC44C12A9D69919D71C7861"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a waiver provided for under such other statute or Executive order applies.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4B152C8E651F47C1AED06090A5488437"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statutes and executive orders described</header><text>A statute or Executive order described in this subsection is a statute or Executive order that provides for the imposition of sanctions.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF39CE243365A4FF884158D7D73718F01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National security waiver</header>
<paragraph id="H554280E4DD3242529C3A033C868B6189"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President may waive the application of any sanction imposed with respect to any person under subsection (a) if the President determines and certifies to Congress that such a waiver is important to the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H063540F121494E1C93E22EFB78C621F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification of and report to Congress</header><text>If the President decides to exercise the waiver authority provided under paragraph (1), the President shall, not less than 20 days before the waiver takes effect, submit to Congress a report—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6A0D1E5854EC4FC1BCB4524749E721CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notifying Congress of the decision to exercise the waiver authority; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3C90657CD04F424D831128BECAA3BC6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fully articulating the rationale and circumstances that led to the decision.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H25CDC3B984204DA893E3EE91AD4DA3AF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Termination of sanctions To be reported to Congress</header><text>Not later than 20 days after the termination of any sanction under subsection (a), the President shall promptly submit to Congress a report on that termination and the reasons for the termination. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

