<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE20D9F48B4974C4E85291AEFB9192445" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4680 IH: Train More Doctors Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4680</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to extend the period for certain teaching hospitals to establish full-time equivalent residency caps for new residency training programs impacted by the COVID&#8211;19 pandemic, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4290795BC13643FDA4E2E9CA3B3809BE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7E436F02B755419499730CD93DECD3C8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Train More Doctors Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H598F6FEFE4B14FA791165A10C6680D30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Two-year extension of graduate medical education FTE resident cap building period for certain teaching hospitals impacted by the Covid–19 public health emergency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1886(h)(4)(H)(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(h)(4)(H)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9F07DA3723FA44AEB6212E612C4FFFAF" style="OLC"> 
<subclause id="HA8CCB7B725754CB5B7960C7F8C994397" indent="up1"><enum>(VI)</enum> 
<item id="H7AE6A4493AD64793A15DF83EEB5CEC78" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>In applying this clause in the case of a hospital that first began training residents in a new approved medical residency training program or programs on or after July 1, 2018, and before July 1, 2021, in determining the limitation on the number of total full time equivalent residents under subparagraphs (F) and (G) and under clauses (v) and (vi)(I) of subsection (d)(5)(B) with respect to such new approved medical residency training program or programs of such hospital, the Secretary shall extend by two years the cap building period (as defined in item (bb)) applicable to such new approved medical residency training program or programs of such hospital to take into account the impact of the COVID–19 public health emergency on such program or programs.</text></item> <item id="H8184F50E906F4E0D9042EFAC3B02CF95" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>For purposes of item (aa), the term <term>cap building period</term> means the 5-year period used to calculate the total adjustment of the limitation under subparagraph (F) for a hospital for a new approved medical residency training program under the relevant provisions of paragraphs (d) and (e) of section 413.79 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations, and such other relevant provisions of such regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this subclause).</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

