<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC35E466C4C74961B0A5D56F91ACB514" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5146 IH: Advancing Gig Economy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5146</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000615">Mr. Pence</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Commerce to conduct a study on the gig economy and the impact the gig economy has on the United States overall economy, including the impact that State laws have had on the gig economy.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H00886BF4046043C58F5ACF6CAE6B35D0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8EBECC105F71436C914FBA20D9B08724" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing Gig Economy Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H59229D9B16424B2C920F55EBCBE92834"><enum>2.</enum><header>Gig economy study</header> <subsection id="H471EB7076E794610BEA527226E608DA3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="HB3B8CB86734949649FD258352101CE6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Commerce shall conduct a study on the impact of the gig economy on United States businesses conducting interstate commerce.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBDF371DE8D2B40518D0D0D55F5568110"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for study</header><text>In conducting such study, the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HD5AEDA2670BE49D0AFCF0F411C4E9385"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and conduct a survey of the gig economy through outreach to entities participating in the gig economy to—</text> 
<clause id="H0F91D653FCC34D4390F332D6AD5DD92B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish a list of industry sectors that participate in the gig economy;</text></clause> <clause id="HC0A862A8A9174077A8D937D5B5A0A795"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>review and briefly explain the impact the gig economy has on the United States economy, including any benefits or detriments; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC9A88F0FBDC34E92B95399B87720C30E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>review the impact the gig economy has on innovation, startups, and small businesses; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0B8C0462524E4E4AA4B493C840CD65B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and conduct a survey of Federal activity on the gig economy to—</text> 
<clause id="H4D80F9793D344F0294E882269A92812E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop a comprehensive list of Federal agencies asserting jurisdiction over the entities and sectors participating in the gig economy;</text></clause> <clause id="HD0A38F5E5A6E4B6D8EB839203488F89F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify all interagency activities related to the gig economy;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8C3B37EED8B64DA1B266B7B7567AC11F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>develop a brief description of the jurisdiction and expertise of the Federal agencies listed under clause (i) as it relates to the gig economy; and</text></clause> <clause id="HF1D44BFDD2D34D1789F091BED783781E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identify all regulations, guidelines, or any other policy implemented by such Federal agencies with respect to the gig economy; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7AA6FFDEF0684C3AB610EB35A8F1418B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop and conduct a survey of State laws enacted on the gig economy to—</text> <clause id="HE486A90946EC432C93FE59FC669C7904"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine the impact such laws have had on the gig economy, including in the transportation and mobility industry sector, the media and journalism industry sector, and any other industry sector impacted by such laws in each State; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC75993D4C25147B388CB26D4C9135EEF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>determine the impact such State laws have on the United States economy.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H83B99275F42347A288F12322A8608299"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that contains—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF7B43CCCB5BB473A8107A64A11A89AFB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the results of the study conducted under subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H577591A10D7B4E989600A0F74CAE1252"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any recommendations to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H603BBF13972046C6B75205C1DBE49CDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>address duplicative Federal rules, Federal regulations, or any Federal activity acting as a barrier to the growth of the gig economy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6C99C201BBBD4B5787164C3F2B06AEE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and implement a comprehensive plan to promote the growth of the gig economy; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5BC6D02218F841AD8204073F7C2694C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop policies that States can adopt to encourage the growth of the gig economy in each State; and</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H39C53A2F89EC4A98ABD2B470017F526F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any recommendations for legislation necessary to accomplish the recommendations made under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F2930A9B4E1437FA40292CDDE23C2CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Gig economy defined</header> 
<paragraph id="HF25D2C5901A344E7BB30C5571CF0E13B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>gig economy</quote> means, collectively, the activities conducted by entities described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3209A070C8DD48CA94065BF043A9459B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>An entity described in this paragraph is a business entity that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAB549002CA1B4565BCF0B2228478C140"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintains an online-enabled application or platform to facilitate the exchange of goods or services by users of the online-enabled application or platform; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDE96AB7FB0994C42A898B0BAD93C39D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not require a person using the online-enabled application or platform to generate business to accept any specific job request as a condition of maintaining access to the online-enabled application or platform.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

