<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5ABC96E3B2AD44B7A538A46E65EAB5DC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6770 IH: Improving Newborns’ Food and Nutrition Testing Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6770</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. C&#225;rdenas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to ensure the safety of infant and toddler food, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1A3ECF56C712499E9BD08F9654BFDF71" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF7C9824592894337875FC875AA01D6C9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Newborns’ Food and Nutrition Testing Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>INFANTS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC302A9FC30084B6DA83AF1F9E1BD5384"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition of infant and toddler food</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H14AA2670D303447EA3ABAF1C8580CF4F" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H1DCD635742EA4EDA80B4FBEEB5200BB8"><enum>(tt)</enum><text>The term <term>infant and toddler food</term> means food which purports to be or is represented as food for children up to 24 months of age, including infant formula.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H88C7E61CAE714F3C881587FAF8784B25"><enum>3.</enum><header>Contaminants in food</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Chapter IV of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/341">21 U.S.C. 341 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H4502EA7730064E08B81524D3FE1EA253" style="OLC">
<section id="H4FEC2E2C3ED0436BB848D8A799E65A6A"><enum>425.</enum><header>Sampling and testing for contaminants in food</header>
<subsection id="H1AC6AE7A677C4D8497511A426B905475"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sampling and testing</header>
<paragraph id="HEC48D7DBB98549F4BE90522C7EE870FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The owner, operator, or agent in charge of a food facility that manufactures or processes food, including infant and toddler food, in final product form intended for sale to consumers shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HA7113741DD2B4E29B9E97FAB3C365240"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collect representative samples of each such food; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBB399742D50240FF9B41C08F665093DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conduct testing of the samples for contaminants, including toxic elements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7427CF41C3724C368917396CD219152B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement for sampling plan</header> <subparagraph id="HB90BC77CE5E14CE7BAB239485567EE50"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The owner, operator, or agent in charge of a facility described in paragraph (1) shall—</text>
<clause id="HB1287D9190954200B932C7940296ABEF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prepare a written sampling plan for all sampling and testing required under this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE8E084B1A673488292A14028F2366431"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that all sampling and testing conducted under this section is conducted in accordance with the sampling plan.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC3E507CAA8B74BB996C64EC10E553157"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A sampling plan under subparagraph (A) shall identify—</text> <clause id="H9C08B7E5F7A64B2FB1EF6E080EAD8036"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of sampling units and sample unit size based upon appropriate criteria for identifying, in a representative fashion, the levels of contaminants in each food; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HEF6B16918712407084396E03B47C4D12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>one or more appropriate test methods and procedures to be used to analyze the samples.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBE1113541E81483BA97A4BC627368DCB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall issue guidance to assist food facilities in developing sampling plans. Such guidance may, as determined appropriate by the Secretary, address when samples should be tested for specific species of contaminants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F6DA29A1CDD4CAAA969CF271416A885"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contaminants to be tested</header><text>Each sample taken pursuant to a sampling plan under this section shall be tested for levels of lead, cadmium, mercury, arsenic, and any other contaminant, including other toxic elements, that the Secretary may specify by regulation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB8913C5F41604C619EFBB01163AB4E41"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Frequency of testing</header><text>The sampling and testing conducted under this section shall be conducted at least once per quarter of each calendar year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0670E8085C6D473282EC00D162064BCA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foods to be tested</header><text>The sampling and testing conducted under this section shall be conducted for—</text> <subparagraph id="HB24859B6875142178BC09AEE9033EF8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>infant and toddler foods, in final package form; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H615488120D744D0997E5B7F0752E5CCF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such other foods as the Secretary may specify, by regulation, as appropriate to protect public health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1EC12B98E2504E1096BC09CC2059EDB1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recordkeeping</header> <paragraph id="H771389306B6B44D79CE805D7645B61B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The owner, operator, or agent in charge of a facility described in subsection (a)(1) shall maintain, for not less than 2 years or the shelf-life of each infant and toddler food manufactured or processed at the facility, whichever is longer, records documenting the sampling and testing conducted under this section with respect to the food.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H40EFBECAF3A24E689C4C9AF07C2C4670"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Records required by paragraph (1) to be maintained shall include a detailed description of the foods sampled and tested, the number of samples and tests performed, the size and number of items in each sample unit, a copy of the facility’s sampling plan, identification of the entity conducting the sampling, identification of the entity conducting the testing, and the analytical methods used to perform the sampling and testing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C6956C4F9AC4D228D1425FA5CB99958"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This subsection applies to all records of sampling and testing conducted under this section, regardless of the findings.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H41B2B57051F24C099B61FF2FC7439D83"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Laboratory accreditation</header><text>The owner, operator, or agent in charge of a food facility described in subsection (a)(1) shall ensure that testing conducted pursuant to this section is performed in accordance with international standards by a laboratory that is accredited by an accreditation body that conforms to international accreditation standards. Testing conducted under this section is not subject to the requirements regarding laboratory accreditation described in section 422.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H90710356605447FEAA6D2BB8D7DFFA26"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Records availability</header> <paragraph id="H9B503D9CF5A04865A256222B5337F2B4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The owner, operator, or agent in charge of a food facility described in subsection (a)(1) shall make all records required under this section available promptly to the Secretary, upon request, for inspection and copying. Upon request of the Secretary, such an owner, operator, or agent in charge shall provide within a reasonable time an English translation of records maintained in a language other than English.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7FB9844AFAEC4C45BDE404B358AC1B27"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Records availability in lieu of an inspection</header><text>Any records that the Secretary may inspect under this section shall, upon the request of the Secretary, be provided to the Secretary by the owner, operator, or agent in charge of a food facility described in subsection (a)(1), in advance of or in lieu of an inspection, within a reasonable timeframe, within reasonable limits, and in a reasonable manner, and in either electronic or physical form, at the expense of such owner, operator, or agent. The Secretary’s request shall include a sufficient description of the records requested.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB1F933E2C4734518A47276C763A6E22E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Confirmation</header><text>Upon receipt of records requested under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall provide to the person confirmation of receipt.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDE35399B943E412F850073CF6EE8FBED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authority of the Secretary</header><text>Nothing in this subsection supplants the authority of the Secretary to conduct inspections otherwise permitted under this Act in order to ensure compliance with this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3915C1C1B6BB4524BE661BD4B5B95ED6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Delayed applicability</header><text>The requirements for sampling and testing under this section apply beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date on which the Secretary publishes the guidance required by subsection (a)(2)(C).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H732A544118814FA096ADC3525179EAC0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Adulteration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 402 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/342">21 U.S.C. 342</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H8425C40122F04887A416F11C669B91D1" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HE8A01C45A42844129DD1E3AFA25AC60B"><enum>(j)</enum><text>If it is an article of food and the owner, operator, or agent in charge of a food facility that manufactures or processes such food—</text>
<paragraph id="H6662095EF2134FB6ACED079B38517D50"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is subject to the requirements of section 425; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H577FA3CAA1D2443DBAE04A8A7F3CCEEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fails to comply with the requirements of such section with regard to that article.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H2A7C6B668C414B138F046E70AD6CBD0E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Records for or in lieu of certain inspections</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 704(a)(4) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/374">21 U.S.C. 374(a)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HD23356B0CA0B4F7B9EBA99632D208BFF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B), (C), and (D) as subparagraphs (C), (D), and (E), respectively;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H72BB4110DC6E4F549BD24B5DA7D9E044"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HC1BFCDA912134EBB96183C3B7E13C640" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HC31E734FCCF34B3C8BF5646D5A58269A" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause id="HD57A4B22B4BD4CE689E4595F9988B995" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Any records or other information that the Secretary may inspect under authority of this Act from a person that owns or operates an establishment that is engaged in any of the activities described in clause (ii) shall, upon the request of the Secretary, be provided to the Secretary by such person, in advance of or in lieu of an inspection, within a reasonable timeframe, within reasonable limits, and in a reasonable manner, and in either electronic or physical form, at the expense of such person. The Secretary’s request shall include a sufficient description of the records requested.</text></clause>
<clause id="H7B1F0CF8231E4106B2AD155D096B8109" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The activities described in this clause are the following:</text> <subclause id="H6CD69B3CADFE4207A613D95977B5CD6C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The manufacturing, processing, packing, transporting, distributing, receiving, holding, or importing of an article of food.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H22503D38968843009420E615F98266BA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The distribution or use of animal feed bearing or containing a veterinary feed directive drug, or the issuance of a veterinary feed directive.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45E2904E542D47C4867E7E2DCFA9485D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HA86B86548766458694039E2C40FA642E" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H198CDF03FC3F4139B2DE629630E3BB5E" indent="up2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Section 703 does not apply to requests for records or other information when those requests are made under this section.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HC5726CC4560A446A96FA24AEFEFB5124"><enum>6.</enum><header>Mandatory recall authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 423(a) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/350l">21 U.S.C. 350l(a)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>or if the Secretary determines through any means that an article of infant and toddler food (other than infant formula) bears or contains a contaminant that renders the product adulterated under section 402(a)(1),</quote> after <quote>animals,</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H0028063A3E014FD3974A2D076CB502F6"><enum>7.</enum><header>Report final product positive test results for relevant pathogens in infant formula</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 412 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/350a">21 U.S.C. 350a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H9C54BC63746647A08A04668E5C32F1AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB26C6846937F4A329949C73B8AAFD050"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="HBC53F98CF1D141B0BEDBC7ED61691672"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the first sentence, by striking <quote>promptly</quote> and inserting <quote>, within 24 hours of acquiring such knowledge,</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HF11D68DED09E4560A7D2382E57D1F201"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the second sentence, by striking <quote>the infant formula</quote> and inserting <quote>an infant formula</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC40468A8E4074F03A6B16FDB254524BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3DA45A17592348CEA23180B8E2677FD3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>paragraph (1)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (1) and (2)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC96F96D65A114E11B6A7629FA28D0511"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H32EB794A44DF4DA890FF57836DBA48F9" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="H3E61E5C1206948D5941CF020E8928B6C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>If the result of any in-process or finished product testing of an infant formula that has been processed by the manufacturer is confirmed as a positive analytical result for any environmental pathogen (as defined in section 117.3 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation)), the manufacturer shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H8664260426F84E8D8D6CCDC631C903B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>within 24 hours of acquiring such confirmation, notify the Secretary of such confirmation regardless of whether such infant formula has left an establishment subject to the control of the manufacturer;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3C377CF079E04E17A72424E457926A08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consult with the Secretary for proper disposal and properly dispose of the affected product; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA50F28BAFF4742F287D1296EC6546B39"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary results and isolates from a positive sample of such infant formula.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H619EF6716305436FAA8A498DE789C767" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Not later than 90 days after receipt of a notification under paragraph (1) or (2), the Secretary shall confirm through the collection of documentation that the manufacturer submitting the notification performed, or is performing, appropriate corrective action. The manufacturer shall make such documentation available to the Secretary during an inspection and, upon request of the Secretary, electronically or by other means.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H10C0BC0ECE314645A66D0D9A425DD3E4"><enum>8.</enum><header>Environmental monitoring</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 412 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/350a">21 U.S.C. 350a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H1EAA2A8245334F22BB7A349F7D3C57A0" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H5EA4636B70EA4AA5BF3AE998B83C3D6B"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Requirements for environmental monitoring for Cronobacter spp and Salmonella</header>
<paragraph id="H2A2DD787133B42049E551C91BB0E2AF4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A manufacturer of powdered infant formula shall establish and implement an environmental monitoring program to verify the effectiveness of sanitation and hygiene controls where the food has the potential to be exposed to Cronobacter spp. or Salmonella. The environmental monitoring program shall be written and include procedures for determining sampling location, number of samples to be taken, and timing and frequency of sample collection and testing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E8A2E3EB78B40A7B212AC2C624FA88E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sampling location and number of samples</header><text>A manufacturer of powdered infant formula shall ensure that the sampling locations from which samples will be taken, and the number of sites to be tested during routine environmental monitoring pursuant to an environmental monitoring program under paragraph (1), are adequate to determine whether sanitation and hygiene controls are effective.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9CAC81F5F5AE431EA6771782F0621E01"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timing and frequency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A manufacturer of powdered infant formula shall ensure that the timing and frequency for collecting ant testing samples pursuant to an environmental monitoring program under paragraph (1) are adequate to determine whether sanitation and hygiene controls are effective.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95119AA165CE45D79E1B984325140F16"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Records</header> <subparagraph id="H772430377E50425A82FD9AB4D452C2E6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Availability to the Secretary</header><text>A manufacturer of powdered infant formula shall make all records required under this subsection available promptly to the Secretary, upon request, for inspection and copying.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H087BC2A2C82B4A979D1A2431BDEBB8F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maintenance</header><text>Records of environmental monitoring conducted pursuant to this subsection shall be maintained for not less than 2 years or the shelf-life of the infant formula, whichever is longer.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF0FE440135BC4D56833BB16D86FF8468"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Conditions of inspection</header><text>Any records that the Secretary may inspect under this subsection shall, upon the request of the Secretary, be provided to the Secretary by the manufacturer of powdered infant formula, in advance of or in lieu of an inspection, within a reasonable timeframe, within reasonable limits, and in a reasonable manner, and in either electronic or physical form, at the expense of such manufacturer. The Secretary’s request shall include a sufficient description of the records requested.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF83BFCFE0F4D4E43B9CF9D110F8A0CAE"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Confirmation of receipt</header><text>Upon receipt of records requested under subparagraph (C), the Secretary shall provide to the person confirmation of receipt.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB24C4D55F8F94204B5BFB848BDE2F27B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Authority of the Secretary</header><text>Nothing in this subsection supplants the authority of the Secretary to conduct inspections otherwise permitted under this Act in order to ensure compliance with this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB642587EACF24148BE180920C4CA415F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Delayed applicability</header><text>The requirements of this subsection apply beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63CFF2D4EDCF4823876E8ABD14FE77A0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to exempt an infant formula manufacturer from the requirements of this Act, including the requirements of this section and section 418.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

