<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB10434B8356A4BF28F7253AC3F84DC32" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3749 IH: Retail Revitalization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3749</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230530">May 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to modify the treatment of certain rents received by real estate investment trusts from related parties.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8928DBA3BD1E48328904FB60A78EF96E" style="OLC"><section id="H2E89448B61DA4634B4310A5CBFA24016" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Retail Revitalization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H44AC38355A1B40A084D150554C63E32F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of treatment of certain rents received by real estate investment trust from related parties</header><subsection id="H4D7BA0F527EC43C6B0003D3B198A3546"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Special rule for distressed tenants</header><paragraph id="H05F927FE93AD47379CF3370D975955DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/856">Section 856(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H80EB49C79D60412A91BE4CD9E6B4EA87" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H97995CD5D56B4D0E882EB36D871D42C4"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Special rule for distressed tenants</header><subparagraph id="H50B7BEFFA3AA49289C9FFFFB0006AC28"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided by the Secretary, in the case of a real estate investment trust which makes a qualified acquisition of a qualified tenant during the 4-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this paragraph, paragraph (2)(B) shall be applied with respect to such tenant by substituting <quote>50 percent</quote> for <quote>10 percent</quote> each place it appears therein.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D60806093E141F9900C67E52DC733C3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Qualified acquisition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph—</text><clause id="H4B3E350B628449228E45331E55473ACF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified acquisition</quote> means the acquisition by a real estate investment trust of stock, assets, or net profits in connection with the bankruptcy, insolvency (within the meaning of section 108(d)(3)), or cash flow insolvency of a qualified tenant.</text></clause><clause id="H05750C4356AA48029C777B7955AE44E5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Cash flow insolvency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of clause (i), a qualified tenant shall be treated as having cash flow insolvency following a reasonable determination by the real estate investment trust, based upon an examination of the facts and circumstances, that such tenant’s revenue is insufficient to cover its debt service payments based on such tenant’s applicable financial statement (as defined in section 451(b)(3)). </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1A8C1B13F174B4E8A6B8883AEEE517C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Qualified tenant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph—</text><clause id="H174958A949C64ED6A1A1FCADD393A66F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified tenant</quote> means, with respect to any acquisition referred to in subparagraph (B), any person from which the real estate investment trust received or accrued rents from real property pursuant to a lease which was in effect on the date of the enactment of this paragraph.</text></clause><clause id="HBC6D76EE9DAC4202BF79AAE93A061C26"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Renewals, etc., of existing leases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of clause (i), a lease shall be treated as in effect on the date of the enactment of this paragraph if the conditions of paragraph (9)(C) are satisfied.</text></clause><clause id="H9AA5F56593EE4623A5388F43C268C630"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Successors</header><text>The term <quote>qualified tenant</quote> shall include a person if such person is a successor to a qualified tenant within the meaning of subsection (g) (without regard to such person’s status as a real estate investment trust or any continuity of shareholder interest requirement) or for purposes of section 381.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC463A9A865A847EBAA12DC8807C7BAC3"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation on period for which treatment applies</header><text>With respect to any qualified acquisition, subparagraph (A) shall apply only to amounts received or accrued during the 7-taxable-year period beginning with the taxable year which includes the date of such acquisition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32EB68C3872F4103B28A3B2F65F987C8"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Coordination with certain other provisions</header><text>For purposes of clauses (i) and (v) of paragraph (8)(A), whether a person is described in paragraph (2)(B) shall be determined after application of subparagraph (A) of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBE0B2CE4FA7406CB19D355F6B7910BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 856(d)(2)(B) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>paragraph (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (8) and (10)</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H387A7AEEF24D4D9D9D7231EF6C58CAFE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to qualified acquisitions (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/856">section 856(d)(10)(B)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as added by this subsection) after the date of the enactment of this Act, in taxable years ending after such date.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC402D403DAC64AB7846BD5A4E13552D5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Increase in percentage of ownership at which rents are generally disqualified</header><paragraph id="H31ED23CF52D24B47AD6D27EE1F6D987A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 856(d)(2)(B) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>10 percent</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>30 percent</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9955D0FA8104AE78953387BF8F30E2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H074639FE5B1F4FC0854ACE731E0AF850"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Increase in percentage of ownership at which constructive ownership rules begin To apply</header><paragraph id="H082D389BAE46462581F24833D0BCB377"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 856(d)(5) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H4C43E6E436F0448297501F334A029B73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>10 percent</quote> in subparagraph (A) and inserting <quote>30 percent</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7180704407A1454C847103212E913F2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>25 percent</quote> in subparagraph (B) and inserting <quote>30 percent</quote>. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB10AB27836D0499B9E1D9EBBB39CFCEB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DF26E0E815346D295EEDDDC3BF94D5A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on application of constructive ownership rules</header><paragraph id="H82B384D99BF14A2E9C3F3E230D01A0C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 856(d)(5) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (A), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (B) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA51DF593A3024E0A9EA2373B075E2D6F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H24CC3EEBFC604BCBA2B8E978F48C053F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as otherwise provided by the Secretary, stock, assets, and net profits constructively owned by a partnership, estate, trust, or corporation by reason of the application of section 318(a)(3) (after application of subparagraphs (A) and (B)) shall not be considered as owned by it for purposes of again applying such section in order to make another person the constructive owner of such stock, assets, or net profits.</text></subparagraph><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">Subparagraph (C) shall not prevent any person from being the constructive owner of stock, assets, or net profits of any person as the result of any other application of section 318(a) (as modified by this paragraph).</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HDABE98A5C31242C48B75FC7C077CBD0F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No inference</header><text>Nothing in the amendments made by paragraph (1) shall be construed to create any inference with respect to the proper application of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/318">section 318</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to cases other than cases to which such amendments apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H044E3860F032405FA0B43D7674E7FF36"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF529BEA16794A51AD98869363F7C50D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Modification of rental exception for taxable REIT subsidiaries</header><paragraph id="H2461AAA0DBA64E2AB924154BA10AC75F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 856(d)(8)(A)(i) of such Code is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFC891047CBE046F6B57FFF6DBC9F3019" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HF553D7C97F5A49C4BF1F8FA89231D154"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of this subparagraph are met with respect to any property if—</text><subclause id="HFB4C070EA31042ABA1408E4A1A27D3ED"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not more than 30 percent of the leasable space of such property is rented to taxable REIT subsidiaries and other persons described in paragraph (2)(B) (determined without regard to paragraph (10)), and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4E4F8F86419548D893088F50E0558032"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not more than 50 percent of the leasable space of such property is rented to taxable REIT subsidiaries and other persons described in paragraph (2)(B) (determined after the application of paragraph (10)).</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H95F551BB484C4E819F8734F358B8636E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

