<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC6F5C0FB38FB44D6AD0F6D2E60EE28E9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2866 IH: Critical Technology Security Centers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2866</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to establish Critical Technology Security Centers in the Department of Homeland Security to evaluate and test the security of critical technology, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB0D59C4933D84FF3ACB161040518E701" style="OLC"><section id="H7E5A443642B24510A4C5F5285104BDF0" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Critical Technology Security Centers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8C02A060F9F14832A7EA5AA1460D4581"><enum>2.</enum><header>Critical technology security centers</header><subsection id="HE48E0E183F8842E5B0F1192B758B67E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Critical technology security centers</header><text>Title III of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/181">6 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="HAEE778EAAA3F43B4B28657491BA5038F" style="OLC"><section id="HE5A4BA79B0EE4ACE914AC6CD772162FC"><enum>324.</enum><header>Critical Technology Security Centers</header><subsection id="HC646A2D6435E4C2497C40003CFB431B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary for Science and Technology, and in coordination with the Director, shall award grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements to covered entities for the establishment of not fewer than two cybersecurity-focused Critical Technology Security Centers (in this section referred to as <quote>Centers</quote>) to evaluate and test the security of critical technology.</text></subsection><subsection id="H947CA1F350504219838EB830B050E4CD" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Evaluation and testing</header><text>In carrying out the evaluation and testing of the security of critical technology pursuant to subsection (a), the Centers shall address the following technologies:</text><paragraph id="H9349CF20CA9246818934740C2F5B13B1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The security of information and communications technology that underpins national critical functions related to communications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F37704FAD034C3DA4C5AE5B092BE706" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The security of networked industrial equipment, such as connected programmable data logic controllers and supervisory control and data acquisition servers. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D382AE2BB04487A8C30C0E1C55A2F6B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The security of open source software that underpins national critical functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F36D5C4A0A3431CB828F5A409603705" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The security of critical software used by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D9E43E67C4040BE93BCF34A5C84963B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Addition or termination of Centers</header><paragraph id="H4349B457D1F0435786B325E923CDE2FE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Science and Technology may, in coordination with the Director, award or terminate grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements to covered entities for the establishment of additional or termination of existing Centers to evaluate and test the security of critical technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADB7D99221A743D182BA15B701D6E370"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The authority provided under paragraph (1) may be exercised except if such exercise would result in the operation at any time of fewer than two Centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06B8B9FC3894493681C1CBE90A76DD30"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of critical technologies</header><paragraph id="H12592E6C912F4C78B9D6E9D594F318C7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before awarding a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement to a covered entity to establish a Center, the Under Secretary for Science and Technology shall coordinate with the Director, who shall provide the Under Secretary a list of critical technologies or guidance on such technologies that would be within the remit of any such Center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25B6104099E34EE2AC913CFFC1C4AF44" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expansion and modification</header><text>The Under Secretary for Science and Technology, in coordination with the Director, is authorized to expand or modify at any time the list of critical technologies or guidance on technologies referred to in paragraph (1) that is within the remit of a proposed or established Center.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBF54D378C0847C098BFED043C9632C9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the evaluation and testing of the security of critical technology pursuant to subsection (a), the Centers shall each have the following responsibilities:</text><paragraph id="H3BB292B3FFFD4898AE2CD2F487E27270"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Conducting rigorous security testing to identify vulnerabilities in such technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19990E46B1384960ABBAAC6CCCF452D5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Utilizing the coordinated vulnerability disclosure processes established under subsection (g) to report to the developers of such technologies and, as appropriate, to the Director, information relating to vulnerabilities discovered and any information necessary to reproduce such vulnerabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H984F5A2754C74602AA559B86B0F6C27D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Developing new capabilities for improving the security of such technologies, including vulnerability discovery, management, mitigation, and remediation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63200BB2B2A54F6F81D74FB5E6398F54"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Assessing the security of software, firmware, and hardware that underpin national critical functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61FF79D328CE415E8BEC7F61173174B1" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Supporting existing communities of interest, including through grant making, in mitigating and remediating vulnerabilities discovered within such technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF484339857DC43BB9285AFB945159DA7" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Sharing findings to inform and support the future work of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H752F94B745A84E4B897F17E69DD39F77" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Risk-Based evaluations</header><text>Unless otherwise directed pursuant to guidance issued by the Under Secretary for Science and Technology or Director under subsection (d), to the greatest extent practicable activities carried out pursuant to the responsibilities specified in subsection (e) shall leverage risk-based evaluations to focus on activities that have the greatest effect on the security of the critical technologies within each Center’s remit, such as the following:</text><paragraph id="H46285E29150E45D99ED9AA42B103B49D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Developing capabilities that can detect or eliminate entire classes of vulnerabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60C26C2D78394570A9C022A52025CD9F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Testing for vulnerabilities in the most widely used critical technologies, or vulnerabilities that affect many such critical technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C2E6C57C4464284B2948766810A3B81" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Coordinated vulnerability disclosure processes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Center shall establish, in coordination with the Director, coordinated vulnerability disclosure processes regarding the disclosure of vulnerabilities that—</text><paragraph id="H77CDA81A8C9C45338063EECE3CA30DE2" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are adhered to when a vulnerability is discovered or disclosed by each such Center, consistent with international standards and coordinated vulnerability disclosure best practices; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23FEA2B8A8EC4C5CA1EF71EDBC61556A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are published on the website of each such Center.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H07E577EF1C0E4BE7917664BE0A8593A3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for an award of a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement as a Center, a covered entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and including such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6ACEFE31094F4958846353C4825B2D91" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Public reporting of vulnerabilities</header><text>The Under Secretary for Science and Technology shall ensure that vulnerabilities discovered by a Center are reported to the National Vulnerability Database of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, as appropriate and using the coordinated vulnerability disclosure processes established under subsection (g).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1089021D3A694DE59FD1E8E8C236DAB2" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Additional guidance</header><text>The Under Secretary for Science and Technology, in coordination with the Director, shall develop, and periodically update, guidance, including eligibility and any additional requirements, relating to how Centers may award grants to communities of interest pursuant to subsection (e)(5) to mitigate and remediate vulnerabilities and take other actions under such subsection and subsection (k).</text></subsection><subsection id="H11E260B2FA964724BB7C525A5FBC150A"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Open source software security grants</header><paragraph id="H80D11B7FE89D42CAAE07A5F10ADF763B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any Center addressing open source software security may, in consultation with the Under Secretary for Science and Technology and Director, award grants to individual open source software developers and maintainers, nonprofit organizations, and other non-Federal entities as determined appropriate by any such Center, to fund improvements in the security of the open source software ecosystem.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CCE951B74E14DBAAECA46325D38515B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Improvements</header><text>A grant awarded under paragraph (1) may include improvements such as the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8EA3FEE2E31540EA8784A2C14491C8F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Security audits.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF20B630E95D417399C609E8DDC70C07"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Funding for developers to patch vulnerabilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67749FACEDC4447F819A060A36212CD7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Addressing code, infrastructure, and structural weaknesses, including rewrites of open source software components in memory-safe programming languages.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC224DF99543448DBEE5132002D3636E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Research and tools to assess and improve the overall security of the open source software ecosystem, such as improved software fault isolation techniques.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89C32BD01A3F4CAA83C397F806BCD89E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Training and other tools to aid open source software developers in the secure development of open source software, including secure coding practices and secure systems architecture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF67A457832834656ADEE0A89B3049827"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under paragraph (1), a Center shall prioritize, to the greatest extent practicable, the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF16AFB8C39424794AC15C3B0702759E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Where applicable, open source software components identified in guidance from the Director, or if no such guidance is so provided, utilizing the risk-based evaluation described in subsection (f).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2445B69AC60E47F8922D8A633A094B94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Activities that most promote the long-term security of the open source software ecosystem.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H39FB4BED698140D58127BDD871002397"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Biennial reports to Under Secretary</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section and every two years thereafter, each Center shall submit to the Under Secretary for Science and Technology, Director, and the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HDA5A1C2CB4F742728E539221D5928E90"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A summary of the work performed by such Center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF964426C4172456CA7FD94A492EF8351"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Information relating to the allocation of Federal funds at such Center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06EA5948E8884BD19FED489EF7949E4D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A list of critical technologies studied by such Center.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H617AF00FA3ED43DBB89FA5BAACAD3CB1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of each vulnerability that has been publicly disclosed pursuant to subsection (g), including information relating to the corresponding software weakness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22AD6A6697D84E74B7B815B7D23E5EEB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An assessment of the criticality of each such vulnerability.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D24E33315C3469E85565C50FFC386CD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An overview of the methodologies used by such Center, such as tactics, techniques, and procedures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H591A163E3C774778B20390F37A2E2A8D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A description of such Center’s development of capabilities for vulnerability discovery, management, and mitigation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCB53E20B44B4503BAD4049D7819D680"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A summary of such Center’s support to existing communities of interest, including an accounting of dispersed grant funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2676132CC5684566993E218C2061DD97"><enum>(9)</enum><text>For such Center, if applicable, a summary of any grants awarded during the period covered by the report that includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="H9D9D3EDFBA9E42B2A42B5AA3B5E3F5E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An identification of the entity to which each such grant was awarded.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H241A5C3DEA734FAD8ABFF7A56C920761"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The amount of each such grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4106EB5906834AE996D7868E3CB9425E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The purpose of each such grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12B6A9822C4E495E9CF93A49CF95EB73"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The expected impact of each such grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2586D0AE01B146B18065C65426F14D7D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The coordinated vulnerability disclosure processes established by such Center.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD0AFE931FCC4688ADF438EF93004B4E" commented="no"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon receiving the reports required under subsection (l), the Under Secretary for Science and Technology shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a summary of such reports, and, where applicable, an explanation for any deviations in the list of critical technologies studied by a Center from the list of critical technologies or guidance relating to such technologies provided by the Director pursuant to subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB0755A6556424255A671CD3AAF8624EC"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Consultation with relevant agencies</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Under Secretary shall consult with the heads of other Federal agencies conducting cybersecurity research, including the following:</text><paragraph id="H1E09E4B86B754D8AB70BDB6CD9734B0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B9B0132E40148DBAC8A32D21453849C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The National Science Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70FE9123FFA14E4EBC7AB8A200596CE9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Relevant agencies of the Department of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7F3C5A82AE0404E917BCBF9BCE953BD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Relevant agencies of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76EAFB980A694E78935CDBAA3A9D94B3"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section the following:</text><paragraph id="HED1BA8C046524D7CB4FB380A1E52C6DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$42,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9950846E4C845D0A9DDA325D88828CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$44,000,000 for fiscal year 2025.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77701062600B4CD78F7FA3EECC026571"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$46,000,000 for fiscal year 2026.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7188AC436C5406BB3AF4310A6609BB9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$49,000,000 for fiscal year 2027.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75D87B3CB2CA4524BB24356A5FE9B336"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$52,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4FB127808AC4E7BAEDC77EC9DBC128A"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE4D8342487FC49ED8C27CFD37F85B917"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H33498E7F93B64F20864AFA4CB281B801"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC74D09F86074AE092E0CB122BC03DD4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77676001D2C04B17AE33FFFC7DF96D2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means a university or federally-funded research and development center, including a national laboratory, or a consortia thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9001ACD5245D494D947B785EC0ED0529"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical technology</header><text>The term <quote>critical technology</quote> means technology that underpins one or more national critical functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CA3769BD6E64E019FB3CC56D873A67E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Critical software</header><text>The term <quote>critical software</quote> has the meaning given such term by the National Institute of Standards and Technology pursuant to Executive Order 14028 or any successor provision.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD79DB8FD1CE54A7086F4BF0B91CD9061"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Open source software</header><text>The term <quote>open source software</quote> means software for which the human-readable source code is made available to the public for use, study, re-use, modification, enhancement, and redistribution.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA515E077A6DE482096B44DBC6BE102F3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H54F161034D4242B7AF313F36628B28DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Identification of certain technology</header><text>Paragraph (1) of section 2202(e) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/652">6 U.S.C. 652(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="H203BB5151F12491BA10EB3AE3442376F" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H06CD780D5724434780C245D05B74A836"><enum>(S)</enum><text>To identify the critical technologies (as such term is defined in section 324) or develop guidance relating to such technologies within the remits of the Critical Technology Security Centers as described in such section.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H87DB4A748D0F4BC7B9886A5FF143384E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 323 the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="HE963E0C7CFB4414F97E8C41A0E7C1278" style="OLC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 324. Critical Technology Security Centers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

