<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H12B7417527FE43D09EEE920950C1F65A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6038 IH: Preventing Opportunities for Teen E-Cigarette and Tobacco Addiction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6038</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231024">October 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to provide for a Reducing Youth Use of E-Cigarettes Initiative.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5D071BE7D69C4189B17E47AB1745F363" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H664F7B70C6324D0EAA085ACC0CA28D8F"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Opportunities for Teen E-Cigarette and Tobacco Addiction Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PROTECT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" id="HC1E07B6C93F443CFA2495520B75B3C95"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reducing Youth Use of E-Cigarettes Initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 317V of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-24">42 U.S.C. 247b–24</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H328C6E396F4E40C8849D6856FC566E2A"><section commented="no" id="HD554B7CFD44946FA9BDEA502AF08E7B6"><enum>317W.</enum><header>Reducing Youth Use of E-Cigarettes Initiative</header><subsection commented="no" id="HA9811270415F4AE2BDBF099992B114CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall carry out an initiative, to be known as the Reducing Youth Use of E-Cigarettes Initiative, which shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H59CB3ECE49B5431B9D6039398F7CC6BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conducting research, (including by enhancing State-level surveillance and by using rapid surveillance methods) on use by youth and young adults of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products, including research on—</text><subparagraph id="H35013EDBDD564B00814C6C6B34D86BC0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the types of products youth and young adults use;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DF1F61E8EEA4B51A5B0EB0381D03643"><enum>(B)</enum><text>patterns of products used by youth and young adults, including initiation, frequency of use, use in combination with other tobacco products, and use of flavors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H197E0D406B054F3D8A509A2F431601BF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the association between the use by youth and young adults of electronic cigarettes and the initiation of smoking with cigarettes or cigars;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82197D0739BF41799CB6B6696318C09D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>use of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products among different demographic groups;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6130918CD4234E958B860EAF9063EE24"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the means by which youth and young adults access electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products, and methods of distribution of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H219E47B23BBB4B14A45E9567DBFDD728"><enum>(F)</enum><text>youth and young adult exposure to advertising of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03056B28AFEF4B31B4F350F8127ADEA5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>marketing and advertising strategies used by manufacturers, including the channels and messaging used and strategies that target different demographic groups;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H577C932DDB4444988685CBC92D56D7B9"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the reasons youth and young adults use such products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6471A427BF24139A0667CD0797B5E22"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which youth and young adult electronic cigarette users are nicotine dependent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B5079C5BA634562BF7E0F518A8B26CD"><enum>(J)</enum><text>patterns of youth and young adult electronic cigarette cessation behaviors, including patterns in motivation to quit, quit attempts, successful cessation, and associated factors; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30922E9DAA8349D7B64E88E081D96638"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">resources youth and young adults are using to quit tobacco use.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H119B8412312641F6A2884375D62B3B38"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Conducting research on—</text><subparagraph id="H5267C5F494934FB8AC52F7D2FA905D2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the characteristics and nicotine delivery technology of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF5C742E3B0043D4A32821962872C709"><enum>(B)</enum><text>biomarkers of exposure to electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products and resulting health impacts from such exposure; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D2EEF50339A4C5A84BF184AF4B7FA3F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the levels of nicotine in electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F85FCB4896E4495A49070547F3C450B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing, in collaboration with professional medical organizations, guidance for health care providers, schools, and other entities, as appropriate, on intervening with, and treating, youth and young adults who use electronic cigarettes and other emerging tobacco products, and disseminating such guidance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2354843CE95444D89036827B19098B42"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying promising strategies to—</text><subparagraph id="HCA5F12CD0F714C0B8235BDA058B9140A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevent and reduce the use by youth and young adults of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H229990AD01B147C38FC8961DA4A436C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify existing, and develop new, cessation strategies and quit support that are appropriate for youth and young adults; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71D7C79F88064F059EF6025DA68982B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improve access to, and the delivery of tobacco cessation services for, youth and young adults, including the use of technology-delivered services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H11FBA753E322439683DD9AC7808AB14C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Identifying effective messages and communication efforts that prevent initiation of tobacco product use and reduce use, including the use of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products, among youth and young adults.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E4D83F5753B47C6BD939F2991D07FA3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Developing and implementing, in coordination with the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, a campaign, in coordination with the Surgeon General, to reduce tobacco initiation and use by youth and young adults, and to educate the public about—</text><subparagraph id="HB2F44B08DA7846F6A5151D2D832D9108"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rapidly evolving tobacco product landscape; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6005194A478945DCA0ED0D2BE68DFADD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the harms associated with the use by youth and young adults of electronic cigarettes and other emerging tobacco products; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B4BA6950ABF49A59154430F50961A22"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">culturally-competent strategies for intervening with youth and young adults who use tobacco and providing or directing them to appropriate cessation services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD659129FEA44B7FBE790F02EF8035B2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Continuing to provide funding through the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s National Tobacco Control Program cooperative agreement to State, local, territorial, and island health departments and Tribal organizations, as appropriate, for—</text><subparagraph id="H44C83A43CF814218856DD525F6ED44B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>preventing and reducing the use by youth and young adults of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4FA51DB9971483DAE8B4DF5FD7853EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving access to and delivery of cessation strategies that are appropriate for services to youth and young adults addicted to nicotine, including through quitlines and provider education on cessation services available through the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act and the Children’s Health Insurance Program under title XXI of such Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8B474E5AC464AB2AA3797556919A779"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Evaluating State, community, and school-based strategies for—</text><subparagraph id="H6A8A7BF03289405F9F1DA7812117679B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>preventing the initiation and use of electronic cigarettes and emerging tobacco products among youth and young adults; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B6A4631A5114C51A72EE1FC57F5D14C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>intervening with youth and young adults who use tobacco and providing or directing them to appropriate cessation services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4315F19545C14F25A1648578AA8E0C76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No duplication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that activities under this section do not duplicate other activities of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subsection><subsection id="H32922C5D59194FB284B50E14B6B48994"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Strategy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, and make available to the public on the internet website of the Department of Health and Human Services, a strategy for carrying out the Reducing Youth Use of E-Cigarettes Initiative.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA7813C6F9A794C54A85C2B80B3925EDC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

