<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3523595864CF473491BAC7B870F317A4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5301 IH: Eliminate Useless Reports Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5301</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 31, United States Code, to require agencies to include a list of outdated or duplicative reporting requirements in annual budget justifications, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H70EC50BF556243D98F2C96CB462D24A4" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H2D562F58E82A4CC58BC48C4274142645"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eliminate Useless Reports Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H95C3FE0172474671B4D9D46EB233C9DB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sunsets for agency reports</header> <subsection id="HE199238332E144B3A6A005AF8C0C1C83"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1125 of title 31, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6F13F673804B41C388D023E1760389F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE0D0DFF8FB744E5FB1B1746E10E2E22C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (a) and (b) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CEFC0C388AA4815B30A05E22703D7DA"> 
<subsection id="H8348AC9166224E36B970DCC024CEF28B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H16ED25585BC643D694A9A51D403A3374"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Budget justification materials</header><text>The term <term>budget justification materials</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3(b)(2) of the Federal Funding Accountability and Transparency Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/6101">31 U.S.C. 6101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/282">Public Law 109–282</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H892CDE253B554BC886987B0A9A058F6A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recurring plan or report</header><text>The term <term>recurring plan or report</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H3A4DF0A22F864AF9B7E21D3BC4673C57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any plan or report submitted to Congress by not less than 1 agency on a recurring basis—</text> 
<clause id="H34F9D754ED1446609409B4F9A34077B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in accordance with Federal law; or</text></clause> <clause id="HC52701C8BB0844609D979395D275E713"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at the direction of a congressional report; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32941B2EDAD04B91BD7D685D74702674"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include any plan or report that is required to be submitted to the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEDC7917BC42A45D2B0B7D0D6CEF3FC42"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committee</header><text>The term <term>relevant congressional committee</term> means a congressional committee to which a recurring plan or report is required to be submitted.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H53ED58AF4C5B473CBBCD162EE1C9D483"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agency identification of unnecessary reports</header> 
<paragraph id="H6BBB173D3A4F4A1D94BAAFEB05FB6747"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The head of each agency shall include in the budget justification materials of the agency—</text> <subparagraph id="HAAD96E3CC79E44A49F92625798DBBA4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (2), a list of each recurring plan or report submitted by the agency that the head of the agency determines to be outdated or duplicative;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H586C2B3655E9499DB9462BD13B004D16"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to each recurring plan or report described in subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="H0D0478D6390E4B43B6B534A143CDF96C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a recommendation on whether to sunset, modify, consolidate, or reduce the frequency of the submission of the recurring plan or report;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9B694786A3B745918EB86343EBF5697B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a citation to each provision of law or directive in a congressional report that requires or requests the submission of the recurring plan or report; and</text></clause> <clause id="HF13DAF2EB9D14F0A942B84E1BB0B238F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a list of the relevant congressional committees for the recurring plan or report; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H208B364990944DDE99DE44A54C63DD44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a justification explaining, with respect to each recommendation described in subparagraph (B)(i) relating to a recurring plan or report—</text> <clause id="H9D849E7DA9104EF8BFA8723387735748"><enum>(i)</enum><text>why the head of the agency made the recommendation, which may include an estimate of the resources expended by the agency to prepare and submit the recurring plan or report; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H93FA5A5608B4445AABCD03B185E83B0F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the understanding of the head of the agency of the purpose of the recurring plan or report.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA97591CAE634201924D19D8B21CB680"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agency consultation</header> <subparagraph id="H85B906E69B4E40C7A1EF00DED57262DB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In preparing the list required under paragraph (1)(A), if, in submitting a recurring plan or report, an agency is required to coordinate or consult with another agency or entity, the head of the agency submitting the recurring plan or report shall consult with the head of each agency or entity with whom consultation or coordination is required.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1DB5605C36134CF58E76070268ED5729"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion in list</header><text>If, after a consultation under subparagraph (A), the head of each agency or entity consulted under that subparagraph agrees that a recurring plan or report is outdated or duplicative, the head of the agency required to submit the recurring plan or report shall—</text> <clause id="HD65CE6663A374B4296FDDF762A8D02E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include the recurring plan or report in the list described in paragraph (1)(A); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDC3081C1E5674DC9AE2D7D74F59094E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify each agency or entity with which the head of the agency is required to coordinate or consult in submitting the recurring plan or report.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H04E676EAF6DE42BF8FE8357B9875EA8A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Disagreement</header><text>If the head of any agency or entity consulted under subparagraph (A) does not agree that a recurring plan or report is outdated or duplicative, the head of the agency required to submit the recurring plan or report shall not include the recurring plan or report in the list described in paragraph (1)(A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H589E692A806A4C7387EFC3F3DA81644A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Government-wide or multi-agency plan and report submissions</header><text>With respect to a recurring plan or report required to be submitted by not less than 2 agencies, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5432C051E4254B8B849116664AF88724"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine whether the requirement to submit the recurring plan or report is outdated or duplicative; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B1B56216A164E04979070386DC8A878"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make recommendations to Congress accordingly.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA9158BD6EB9145C482A3093960F386DB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disposition of recommendations</header> <paragraph id="H2A0F3FD2E91A42C3A9187BFE58EBE0D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to a recommendation on a recurring plan or report included in budget justification materials by the head of an agency under subsection (b)(1)(B)(i), the chair and ranking member of each relevant congressional committee may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H534E71D6FF7C41559E96717FF5797405"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in coordination with any other relevant congressional committee, as necessary, agree or disagree with the recommendation or postpone a decision on the recommendation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H141C12B2B71541A382EDBF83200A6659"><enum>(B)</enum><text>notify each agency that submits a recommendation of the disposition of the recommendation under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H83460EA9A36C4F04B0C88A3284E297DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Legislative steps</header><text>If a relevant congressional committee agrees with an agency recommendation submitted under subsection (b)(1)(B)(i), the relevant congressional committee may take the necessary legislative steps to accomplish the recommendation, which may include consulting with the agency that submits the recurring plan or report that is the subject of the recommendation to prepare appropriate legislation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H745E413A89744B6884F0D78610D78C54"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Agency requirements</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to relieve the head of an agency from a requirement to submit a recurring plan or report.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44DAFB27FB504C11A1024B6E30D323DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>in the budget of the United States Government, as provided by section 1105(a)(37)</quote> and inserting <quote>in the budget justification materials of each agency</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H547E6B13CBF142C1B42350F7C0B189A9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Budget contents</header><text>Section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, is amended by striking paragraph (39). </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

