<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H47ED7D8033DA4A378487319D07C8E65E"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>107 HR 5686 IH: Preventing Ethnic Cleansing and Atrocities in Nagorno-Karabakh Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5686</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230922">September 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prevent ethnic cleansing and atrocities against ethnic Armenians, promote accountability for the same, protect and provide humanitarian assistance to Armenians in Armenia and Nagorno-Karabakh impacted by actions taken by the Government of Azerbaijan, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF3805E6C410D472EBB9ED7E7807658A9"><section id="HB5313DE63F724236BAFED8000B19AB95" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Ethnic Cleansing and Atrocities in Nagorno-Karabakh Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDF25ABEA7A6B486A95136EEDD9DA9062"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H3F8ECBD8B6AE4D1993A590972ED631AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In September 2020, Azerbaijan invaded Nagorno-Karabakh, resulting in conflict in which more than 6,500 people in Armenia, Azerbaijan, and Nagorno-Karabakh were killed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H612688028EBB4D729F9216BDF4BCDF70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Azerbaijan’s 2020 invasion resulted in the displacement of more than 91,000 individuals from Nagorno-Karabakh, with the vast majority, primarily women and children, living in a <quote>refugee-like</quote> situation in the war’s aftermath.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3F13517EC1C48F2A88BE3F3613E3EC4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>People displaced by Azerbaijan’s invasion of Nagorno-Karabakh continue to have acute humanitarian needs, including access to drinking water and health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6581BFF406934C5B8A1B838F6045BB9C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Human Rights Watch found that Azerbaijani forces indiscriminately used cluster munitions and artillery rockets against civilian targets and destroyed civilian infrastructure, including hospitals and schools during the 2020 war.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA241ADFC83D42F69F8BB1BD6DCFA2EF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In September 2022, Azerbaijan unleashed another assault on Armenian territory, including the cities of Vardenis, Sotk, Artanish, Ishkhanasar, Goris, and Kapan, which killed almost 400 military personnel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01D3B86C353C477D8C0F9AFE7CD13D97"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Azerbaijani forces shelled Armenian communities in September 2022, killing at least 4 civilians, injuring 14, and displacing at least 7,600 people, including almost 1,500 children and 100 people with disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49DF05B0B5204519992DA691BBA1906B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In December 2022, Azerbaijan imposed a blockade of the Lachin Corridor, a road by which 90 percent of food consumed by residents of Nagorno-Karabakh previously entered the enclave.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D2DACAA2C3C488B8D052ADD04488487"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The International Court of Justice ordered Azerbaijan in February 2023 to <quote>ensure unimpeded movement of persons, vehicles, and cargo along the Lachin Corridor in both directions</quote>, a ruling with which it has failed to comply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE697519B0BB4248AC2F7934132076E9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Azerbaijan’s installation of a military checkpoint in the Lachin Corridor in April 2023 further threatened the supply of urgent humanitarian goods to Nagorno-Karabakh.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A95540A6AB249C0A1E7A7217BB825AC"><enum>(10)</enum><text>On August 6, 2023, the Armenian Ombudsperson reported that no humanitarian aid had entered Nagorno-Karabakh since June 15, and that miscarriages had tripled.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B0809E15F034500AC10EB712A5DCB25"><enum>(11)</enum><text>On August 7, 2023, a United Nations group of experts stated that Azerbaijan’s ongoing blockade of the Lachin Corridor <quote>is a humanitarian emergency that has created severe shortages of essential food staples</quote> and threatens medical reserves.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1538896C08C4BBFA853C589E492028D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>On August 7, 2023, Luis Moreno Ocampo, former Prosecutor of the International Criminal Court (2003–2012) released an Expert Opinion that the actions of the Government of Azerbaijan toward ethnic Armenians in Nagorno-Karabakh constituted the crime of genocide under the Genocide Convention, and urged that members of the United Nations Security Council seek to refer the matter to the International Criminal Court for investigation and prosecution under the Genocide Convention.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8BDA41F2AED45E48E48D5A4283870D0"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In certain instances, Azerbaijani authorities have detained residents of Nagorno-Karabakh traveling to Armenia through the Lachin Corridor, leaving ethnic Armenians who choose to depart for Armenia to avoid starvation to wonder if they can depart safely.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB16D2F340AD947D4A1A16A1D64D64D8E"><enum>(14)</enum><text>According to the International Committee of the Red Cross, residents of Nagorno-Karabakh lack life-saving medication, hygiene products, and baby formula, and basic foodstuffs are increasingly scarce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2116AC28D6184B78BBF3A8AD5577BB4D"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The United States Commission on International Religious Freedom’s 2023 Annual Report noted the documented destruction of Armenian heritage sites in Nagorno-Karabakh, including St. Sargis Church, while the European Parliament in March 2023 condemned an Azerbaijani policy to <quote>erase and deny Armenian cultural heritage in and around Nagorno-Karabakh</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD63751ADBF5B4E788E51763B28497192"><enum>(16)</enum><text>In a September 2022 report, the United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination expressed deep concern in Azerbaijan regarding ‘‘[i]ncitement to racial hatred and the propagation of racist stereotypes against persons of Armenian national or ethnic origin, including on the Internet and social media, as well as by public figures and government officials, and the lack of detailed information on investigations, prosecutions, convictions, and sanctions for such acts’’.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA458CBCE6B2341BBA94BED282DA344EB"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Any peace agreement between Armenia and Azerbaijan will only be sustainable if its includes protections for the Armenian population of Nagorno-Karabakh.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB7FFF27C8E44944A39C38DBE3469E0F"><enum>(18)</enum><text>On September 19, 2023, Azerbaijan launched an assault on Nagorno-Karabakh, and in the first days of that attack killed more than 200 civilians, including children, and wounding 400.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0CCB5D81A41B464198D892399C79D470"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H2398BDE9AF9A44D98968792060978280"><enum>(1)</enum><text>long-standing U.S. policy not to recognize changes to borders or political status that a party to a conflict attempts to make by force or aggression should be applied in relation to Azerbaijan, Nagorno-Karabakh, and Armenia;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H718386E991F44D2CA61040311AA69DB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>long-standing U.S. policy has been and should remain to facilitate a negotiated settlement of Nagorno-Karabakh’s political status, neither recognizing Azerbaijan’s claim to sovereign authority over Nagorno-Karabakh, nor Nagorno-Karabakh’s claim to independence, but to promote resolution of the question of its status through negotiation within the OSCE Minsk Group;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BBD7D778DE7446AA4AE7EE59C87F179"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the U.S. should not recognize any settlement of Nagorno-Karabakh’s political status that is achieved as a consequence of Azerbaijan’s military invasion of Nagorno-Karabakh in 2020, its blockade of Nagorno-Karabakh since December 12, 2022, or the invasion that began on September 19, 2023, or its threats and coercion of Armenian leaders in Nagorno-Karabakh, including by creating an atmosphere of terror;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88BD06E0A29F40D7B800516F5FF8A574"><enum>(4)</enum><text>numerous documented reports and evidences of atrocities, war crimes, crimes against humanity, and genocide committed by Azerbaijan in and around Nagorno-Karabakh should be investigated and those responsible should be held accountable, and the U.S. should play a leading role in promoting this process;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE26FA02C6A94724A9E9317515EB7B2A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>due to credible reports of ongoing atrocities against ethnic Armenians following the Azerbaijani invasion of Artsakh that began on September 19, 2023, the U.S. should press for immediate access by international observers, including U.S. diplomats, to promote verification of these reports;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70C5680899D24E02B33D1A25CE0A0F0F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the United States should direct the United States Representative to the United Nations to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States to refer the actions of the Government of Azerbaijan toward ethnic Armenians in Nagorno-Karabakh to the International Criminal Court for investigation and prosecution under the Genocide Convention;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE47905BFA3B04514992733B384826A08"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Azerbaijan is conducting a campaign of ethnic cleansing against Armenians living in Nagorno-Karabakh and the United States and the international community have a responsibility to provide immediate humanitarian support;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CD5F3AB5E5E408F9EA8750D3FC3550D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Government of Azerbaijan must immediately cease actions that undermine the mission of the International Committee of the Red Cross and restore unfettered humanitarian access to the region, including by facilitating the transfer of food, fuel, medicine, and hygiene products; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC56F6622BF54CC3962524024DC0F66A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Government of Azerbaijan should immediately release all Armenian prisoners of war.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD15EE512527D4CAF9B815C6E9B870A41"><enum>4.</enum><header>Humanitarian assistance for Armenians in Armenia and Nagorno-Karabakh</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the United States Agency for International Development, for fiscal year 2024, $30,000,000 to provide humanitarian assistance to groups in Armenia and Nagorno-Karabakh impacted by the 2020 Nagorno-Karabakh War, Azerbaijan’s September 2022 attack on Armenia, and Azerbaijan’s blockade of the Lachin Corridor.</text></section><section id="HD91DC99B4B3049008CC2C06E0E69FB33"><enum>5.</enum><header>Freedom Support Act section 907 waiver repeal</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Foreign Operations, Export Financing, and Related Programs Appropriations Act, 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/115">Public Law 107–115</external-xref>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5812">22 U.S.C. 5812</external-xref> note) is amended, under the heading <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph">assistance for the independent states of the former soviet union</header-in-text></quote>, by striking paragraphs (2) through (6) of subsection (g).</text></section><section id="HDB905420216A4D08AF45A57D40E47C19"><enum>6.</enum><header>Foreign military financing</header><subsection id="H2D53922F8AAB4DC58F82728E680B5264"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $12,000,000 for the Department of State for fiscal year 2024 for Foreign Military Financing program assistance for the Republic of Armenia.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7F341FE3184C4C85A1FD85DD680A193E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The Foreign Military Financing program assistance authorized by subsection (a) shall be used to—</text><paragraph id="H3A387EE3587541FFA1E957CC7E17E256"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support Armenia’s sovereign independence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC795F974B0F4D66A14F884822D1E24D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support joint training and exercises with the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AF01D5F29E0423483666E26F61B747E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enhance United States-Armenia interoperability; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8387EABB85A6400B96B8637C19170C33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>train Armenian forces for future international peacekeeping operations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD76C236BB55A4BCC9ACB5704E133DE12"><enum>7.</enum><header>Strategy to protect the rights of people in Nagorno-Karabakh</header><subsection id="H0E880959B1C541A1B516635E279C1E3B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy required</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a detailed strategy to ensure the durable security for the people of Nagorno-Karabakh.</text></subsection><subsection id="H76A2369E12C8483A961CCC9B0878BDB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy required by subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H1397DFF416FF472CA68C0DF47B95A55A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>incorporating the rights and security of the people in Nagorno-Karabakh into any and all efforts to facilitate peace talks between Armenia and Azerbaijan, including the right of the ethnic Armenians to live safely in Nagorno-Karabakh; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FBF8B9C087845AABB5BEC1F3F5AF13C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan to work with leaders of Nagorno-Karabakh and the international community to ensure—</text><subparagraph id="HABA821F8A9C544D0BD7E64FE6E94086B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the establishment of accountability measures to ensure the rights and security of the population of Nagorno-Karabakh in the event that the Governments of Armenia and Azerbaijan reach a peace agreement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H740B23374A044E26B050581AB0A0C270"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the stationing of U.S. diplomats in Nagorno-Karabakh in order that they can observe, interact with and receive reports from inhabitants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADA67008D9454288B5F31AB460196A03"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support for the protection of Armenian cultural heritage sites in Nagorno-Karabakh, including the 24-hour video monitoring of those sites;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C6141C3756F4D88AA109282C7E00773"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Armenians in Nagorno-Karabakh are able maintain their right to study according to a curriculum designed by local representatives, worship according to their chosen religious beliefs, and speak their preferred language; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H493518B338694248B499432DF7263D9D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the survival of Armenian cultural heritage in Nagorno-Karabakh, including monasteries, churches, and cemeteries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB71E037EF44D4A90B46F994EA85140B7"><enum>8.</enum><header>Accountability for alleged Azerbaijani atrocities during September 2022 attack on Armenia</header><subsection id="H17AD6D3F88584E5BA2F1556D0A125053"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a detailed report regarding evidence that Azerbaijan and its proxies violated international humanitarian law and committed atrocities and war crimes during its attacks on Armenia in September 2022 and on Nagorno-Karabakh in September 2023.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA6340494600F4D5BA90517DB09BC9174"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include the following elements:</text><paragraph id="HCC8369C994E8437194F4880581901679"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the status of efforts to investigate, verify, and promote accountability for alleged atrocities, including war crimes and crimes against humanity that Azerbaijani forces committed during the course of Azerbaijan’s attacks on Armenia in September 2022 and on Nagorno-Karabakh in September 2023, and a description of any documented atrocities to date.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDBA8B700EDC4C99BBA7D0670DC610F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of United States support for efforts to investigate, verify, and promote accountability for alleged atrocities, including war crimes and crimes against humanity that Azerbaijani forces committed during the course of attacks on Armenia in September 2022 and on Nagorno-Karabakh in September 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E34A7CA130E4FA09C8B5ACDBC0032D1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of efforts to promote justice for victims of alleged atrocities, including statements by civilians who were victimized.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55FD670B30FA49D484FACA7248A4240C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A strategy for diplomatic engagement to build support multilaterally for widespread accountability for these atrocities, including multilateral engagements, economic sanctions, and visa restrictions, and freezing of foreign assets by the perpetrators and their family members.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9675CF328BBB4346A6D00E1F6026A409"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Plans to deter future Azerbaijani attacks against Armenia by expanding U.S.-Armenia joint exercises and other forms of security cooperation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF82C8599B0C74755A840DE5CBC704ADC"><enum>9.</enum><header>Enhanced reporting re incitement to ethnic hatred and violence, human rights violations, atrocities, war crimes, crimes against humanity and genocide</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The State Department shall assess incitement of ethnic hatred and violence, human rights violations, atrocities, war crimes, violations of international humanitarian law, crimes against humanity, and genocide, including elements of these crimes committed in Nagorno-Karabakh and surrounding areas of Azerbaijan in relation to the conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh since January 1, 2020. Such enhanced reporting shall include gathering and evaluating evidence, including that which is publicly available on Columbia University’s Artsakh Atrocities website, and including a description of documented atrocities, and should also include information on perpetrators in Azerbaijan’s Armed Forces, as well as militias including Islamist armed groups engaged on the ground.</text><subsection id="H6B6C4557D3D64FBAADE510F0BF952AB1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Such enhanced reporting shall be made available on the website of the State Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBB5FF68E55614B0DA107D94672587F48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Evidence gathered pursuant to subsection (a) shall be available to appropriate law enforcement or judicial authorities, including appropriate national, regional or international justice mechanisms for use as evidence to support the indictment and trial of any persons responsible for human rights abuses including incitement to hatred, violence, atrocities, ethnic cleansing, war crimes, crimes against humanity and genocide.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBA399CD0C41D4B4398811E56E48329DA"><enum>10.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to officials of the Government of Azerbaijan related to ethnic cleansing in Nagorno-Karabakh</header><subsection id="H6F1993635A9749F982AE828B94673517"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and after making the determination required by subsection (c), the President shall impose sanctions described in subsection (d) with respect to each official of the Government of Azerbaijan—</text><paragraph id="HE7B50816F9184DC4BE6C07CB3062C484"><enum>(1)</enum><text>specified in subsection (b); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8BA4DD5DEE54B229D0740D5D906101D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determined by the President under subsection (c) to have directed an attack or the blockade described in that subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H845F392FDA954D65ADC0B74A4158AE47"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Officials specified</header><text>The officials specified in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H805895C0E4194D33B212A9AC02859715"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The President of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDE11A251DF944A083CD6CD4FC752B3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Minister of Defense of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17CB380573A346D49CE117599CD550B0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Minister of Defense Industry of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF43191A7FC744F2D85BF00629AE73CD8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Chief of the State Border Service of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F286EA5BB4249D988CD1AADA097930C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Chief of the State Security Service of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA174922F92E44500BF748448DE82A62B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Chief of the Foreign Intelligence Service of Azerbaijan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D284A484C0A4484830CE05F72202560"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Identification of additional officials</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall determine whether any officials of the Government of Azerbaijan, in addition to the officials specified in subsection (b), directed— </text><paragraph id="H7070F445C7E3460BA1A20BA2E919B776"><enum>(1)</enum><text>operations that instigated the 2020 Nagorno-Karabakh War;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H174B9B8AFDCE41D481DD6321097BBBB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>attacks on Armenia in September 2022;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B3D6779C93D4D208A6DFBBCDD16DEB3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the blockade of the Lachin Corridor beginning in December 2022; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADBD566242584C51A81AC21336E5324D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>attacks on Nagorno-Karabakh in September 2023.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H49051D9BD5044D828815ABE43353A46C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions to be imposed under subsection (a) with respect to an official described in that subsection include any of the sanctions authorized under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>), the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref>), or any other provision of law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H274378A0303D408EAD1709D977816D9F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National security waiver</header><text>The President may waive the imposition of sanctions under this section with respect to an official described in subsection (a) if the President—</text><paragraph id="H981CEA66AF96430189DE228B6BB81ACD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determines that such a waiver is in the national security interests of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H729C05D089F845A88414091E94196728"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submits to the appropriate congressional committees a notification of the waiver and the reasons for the waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9106ED676E1A4DA3BE730CEED23117D4"><enum>11.</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HD40E7903C5C24CDC86D1F71A108BBC43"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0DF7E9AD42B4F599212324C2B90CCA0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

