<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7A1352967CAB4D4295BEF24B501D4DF0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6666 IH: 2 for 1 Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6666</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To codify Executive Order 13771 (relating to reducing regulation and controlling regulatory costs).</official-title></form><legis-body id="H97DD80CCD019472385DA8CB7E3417CD1" style="OLC"><section id="H1550D88C18574155A8ABD8529066D665" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>2 for 1 Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H50D940904A274916979FFDC7D093F6DC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement to identify 2 rules to be repealed when proposing or promulgating a new rule</header><subsection id="H9027F49C24674388BA404D5A59158A31"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Identification of 2 rules To be repealed required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of an agency shall identify at least 2 of the rules of the agency to be repealed when the agency publicly proposes for notice and comment or otherwise promulgates a new rule.</text></subsection><subsection id="H19E75628A0EB4B10B5E044C36F246025" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Incremental cost of new rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each fiscal year, the total incremental cost of all new rules, including any repealed rule, to be finalized in that fiscal year may not be greater than zero, unless a rule is required by law or consistent with advice provided in writing by the Director.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA87BDE9EE9AE4ED999DFF1A977EA4A17"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Incremental cost offset</header><text>Any new incremental cost associated with a new rule issued on or after the date of the enactment of this Act shall be offset by the elimination of costs associated with at least two other rules identified to be repealed pursuant to subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H34EAB53E28014A7E904FA549B2AA90F0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agency guidance by Director</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and periodically thereafter as the Director determines to be necessary, the Director shall provide the head of each agency with guidance on the implementation of this section that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H5AEE776083084900ACC7309359F52A45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Processes for standardizing the measurement and estimation of the regulatory cost of the rule on private entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5CF63D254B54ABC9887C3AEF50918FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Standards for determining what qualifies as a new and offsetting rule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB063B6BD1923442AAEF940293ADBBA31"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Standards for determining the cost of a rule that may be eliminated.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H693E97792333478AB17AE9BA2418765A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Processes for accounting for costs in different fiscal years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12E08B4EF04947E0ACAC0E512866A4A0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Methods to oversee the issuance of new rules with costs offset by savings at different times or different agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A9E8E70199E4F03999257BBED1051E9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Emergencies and other circumstances that might justify individual waivers of the requirements of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02980AFDE7C94B2D9B4B6A9EE7CB237C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual regulatory cost submissions to OMB</header><paragraph id="HA8ACC277870F460A9745C54EBC0C1823"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency identification of incremental and offsetting costs for rules</header><text>Beginning with the regulatory plans required under Executive Order 12866 (58 Fed. Reg. 51735; relating to regulatory planning and review) for the fiscal year of the date of the enactment of this Act, and for each fiscal year thereafter, the head of each agency shall identify, for each rule that increases incremental cost, the offsetting rules described in subsection (c), and provide the best approximation of the total costs or savings associated with each new rule or repealed rule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B627E1D47DF42968D6CC6D8377A5FAE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on issuance of rule not included in the Unified Regulatory Agenda</header><text>The head of an agency may not issue a rule if the rule was not included on the most recent version or update of the published Unified Regulatory Agenda as required under Executive Order 12866, unless the issuance of the rule was approved in advance in writing by the Director.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEFB622B19954D58A61C739593903EC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>OMB identification of incremental costs for rules</header><text>Not later than the first Monday in February of each year, the Director shall identify a total amount of incremental cost for each agency that will be allowed for the agency to issue and repeal rules for the next fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2164FFE877F043848D38D2894EE36B8E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Issuance of agency rules required to be within total incremental cost allowance</header><text>The head of an agency may not issue a rule that exceeds the total incremental cost allowance for the agency identified by the Director under paragraph (3), unless the rule is required by law or approved in writing by the Director. The total incremental cost allowance may allow an increase or require a reduction in the total regulatory cost of the rule on private entities. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2ACCB1B1492644CE84DA995D6ECBB300"><enum>(5)</enum><header>OMB guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall provide to the head of each agency guidance on the implementation of the requirements in this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA5E5F2653504424796C7C4F450EAEE42"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE2AD4ED2822E483EA72D1180823999B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H272F764408124A118250397C64EEC228"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC553DB28BF3C4EAAA7D20FC75DDD5FC3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule</header><text>The term <term>rule</term> means an agency statement of general or particular applicability and future effect designed to implement, interpret, or prescribe law or policy or to describe the procedure or practice requirements of an agency, but does not include any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H218D737F11424DDD9BC11468BB7F46FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A rule issued with respect to a military, national security, or foreign affairs function of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B109A37EE974A8BB730B1D6E56FA3FB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A rule related to agency organization, management, or personnel.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE13213259AB2497FB1355427A2B998AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any other category of rules exempted by the Director.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

