<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" dms-id="H6CE83950585C4AE5A150F3103A036A86" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 140 : Protecting Speech from Government Interference Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 140</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSGA00">Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to prohibit Federal employees from advocating for censorship of viewpoints in their official capacity, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="HB256422439D74CF2949343C2EC4C8EE7"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="HB5BF6BA5C6714262AFD1BA0AEC5FA3E3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Speech from Government Interference Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H03303A77D03B43509EA7A361CBDAB718"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal employee censorship</header><subsection id="HF7A0BE75918E45469C6E3A02F034ABE1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/73">Chapter 73</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H0B6AA663B19A4D8382F7592A0BCB8256" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subchapter id="H90CC204EA66847E490A5D567DBAA95CB"><enum>VIII</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal employee censorship</header><section id="HDA47CD25C9B0427D97549066F43487C7"><enum>7381.</enum><header>Policy regarding Federal employee censorship</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the Congress that employees acting in their official capacity should neither take action within their authority or influence to promote the censorship of any lawful speech, nor advocate that a third party, including a private entity, censor such speech.</text></section><section id="HDCA65CA20ED1406EBE5B90941B7F397B"><enum>7382.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal employee censorship</header><subsection id="H588BD0C9FCD347D0BCBB223197E4B71F" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee may not—</text><paragraph id="HBCE1F50BA54D4A46A21AC752429A146C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use the employee's official authority to censor any private entity, including outside of normal duty hours and while such employee is away from the employee’s normal duty post; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9F49C1CC1B84551ADC89A7A64D83C9A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>engage in censorship of a private entity—</text><subparagraph id="H4CE49CCD16B6458D9662214C63165AFC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>while the employee is on duty;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H219A920B3A9E46FD9108AB155279FBEB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in any room or building occupied in the discharge of official duties by an individual employed or holding office in the Government of the United States or any agency or instrumentality thereof;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FF03CE2354942429CD2C5BA65BDF486" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>while wearing a uniform or official insignia identifying the office or position of the employee;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H218D1971B798487AB9558E2D1E46B1A9" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>while using any vehicle owned or leased by the Government of the United States or any agency or instrumentality thereof; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9015C082C2B4D48AB11D025B5C9FF86"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> while using any information system or information technology (as defined under section 11101 of title 40).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA83B3EFFF2C24A4C8CF31498B0B70A53" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions for law enforcement functions and reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="HF9236EBA1E4C46BA8E69E9718533E190"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit an employee from engaging in lawful actions against unlawful speech within the official authority of such employee for the purpose of exercising legitimate law enforcement functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C7F97EE5824479893A87034F206D591"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting</header><subparagraph id="H85725DB3E790493DAD4144A301D5B37C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 72 hours before an employee exercises a legitimate law enforcement function under paragraph (1) to take any action to censor any unlawful speech (in this paragraph referred to as a <quote>censorship action</quote>), and consistent with subparagraph (D), the head of the agency that employs the employee shall submit, to the Office of Special Counsel and the chair and ranking member of the committees of Congress described under subparagraph (B), a report that includes—</text><clause id="H59621788AA7F4497B6C4B5E80C316F75"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an overview of the action, or actions, to be taken, including a summary of the action being taken and the rationale for why a censorship action is necessary;</text></clause><clause id="H8E212B99CAEC41B99DA238F1BDE74B60"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the name of the entity which the action is being requested of;</text></clause><clause id="HE08DD5E8B1AE4D07AE9FFFF35F855761"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the person and entity targeted by the censorship action, including the associated name or number of any account used or maintained by the entity and a description of the specific speech content targeted;</text></clause><clause id="HD8EBC0EA1ADA4D8EACA7C7B7E92F0002"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the agency’s legal authority for exercising the law enforcement function;</text></clause><clause id="H049D973591974E318F92A9C74711EB20"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the agency employee or employees involved in the censorship action, including their position and any direct supervisor; </text></clause><clause id="H8C511871E0954AA99A9231819F074965"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a list of other agencies that have been involved, consulted, or communicated with in coordination with the censorship action; and</text></clause><clause id="H42EA34ACB2BE41E28B27D727007CF308"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>a classified annex, if the agency head deems it appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0C8F4D178594D9FAE6B915C37C099BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The committees of Congress described under this subparagraph are the following:</text><clause id="H0F0BD64EDA5E42ABB85B9D50356C9E25"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Oversight and Accountability, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives.</text></clause><clause id="H95BE662FAF3943758DFEC4D065BE51B1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADBF3FCB62514F1AB6498F9A324ABBC4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Clarification of Office of Special Counsel reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reporting requirements in this paragraph do not apply to the Office of Special Counsel’s advisory and enforcement functions under subchapter II of chapter 12. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9315DDCB837740BEB9607F530793CEFC"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Reporting requirements for certain actions</header><clause id="H7BB34501C54745E184D221593A28D3D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Any censorship action relating to combating child pornography and exploitation, human trafficking, or the illegal transporting of or transacting in controlled substances shall be exempt from the reporting requirement under this paragraph.</text></clause><clause id="H616F1C0CFE0F4CDDAA96A773361B0E97"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>With respect to any censorship action related to safeguarding, or preventing the unlawful dissemination of, properly classified national security information, subparagraph (A) shall be applied by substituting <quote>Not later than 72 hours after</quote> for <quote>Not later than 72 hours before</quote>. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8DC29964ECC74C39AA506F9135AA0C4D" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><paragraph id="H509E5FD95B774EE09F03834B56585EE2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An employee who violates this section shall be subject to—</text><subparagraph id="H4595BBA2F86D4F95A2C1AB5FBE67D62A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disciplinary action consisting of removal, reduction in grade, debarment from Federal employment for a period not to exceed 10 years, suspension, or reprimand;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CCDE30ED5E5455F9A4C279450D88CD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of a civil penalty not to exceed $1,000; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FF952BE50A046938D1DB6BB7B2B8722"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any combination of the penalties described in subparagraph (A) or (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7E691D920664B06A9B138BB55A43281"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application to senior Government officials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1)(B) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$50,000</quote> for <quote>$1,000</quote> for any employee who is—</text><subparagraph id="HEC8CE43DDC3C483892D4862357812B24"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">paid from an appropriation for the White House Office; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4DB4193B3874B49B7675CC725C2F05F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3ED537CDD59429386E1565DF10C80B7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph id="HF12231AB59F24ABBB3C35D674D0EEAA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2) and subsection (c)(2), this section shall be enforced in the same manner as subchapter III of this chapter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29C6C055A3474ED0B88969B07F105CA2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 1215(b), the Special Counsel may, in lieu of sending a report to the President under section 1215(b), seek civil monetary penalties under subsection (c)(2) pursuant to section 1215(a). This paragraph shall not be construed to limit or otherwise affect the President's authority to enforce any disciplinary action against an employee described under subsection (c)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D7CB4D7A22644409F17474F734057A3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H2A58D8383008481C8BA15458565119FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 240 days after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Attorney General, in consultation with the Assistant Attorney General for Civil Rights and the Office of Special Counsel, shall submit to the committees of Congress described in subsection (b)(2)(B) a report evaluating the compliance by the Federal Government with this section, including a description of any action by the head of an agency or department in the executive branch to—</text><subparagraph id="H9A6CF35A8BE94527BF4EF41E266AA4A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with any third parties about censorship by employees in the executive branch; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81D850BC45FF42689A335D228823BF87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>engage in any activity prohibited under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD60DF2CD91754896AE64179E36DD7755"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This subsection shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of the enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2AF325A35AB4B99BB004A7C907A8D91" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than annually, the head of each employing agency shall provide mandatory training on this section and the requirements of this section to each agency employee.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1D9793EA536E40BCBB85F8DE01B9C275"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subchapter—</text><paragraph id="HB5DCB036724D4313A49E865FA069EF9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>censor</term> or <term>censorship</term> means influencing or coercing, or directing another to influence or coerce, for—</text><subparagraph id="H3787A10BA9FD4D4E88E5A507A4DE5440"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the removal or suppression of lawful speech, in whole or in part, from or on any interactive computer service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59AA1E69122F41CCBC736A834CD6E22B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the addition of any disclaimer, information, or other alert to lawful speech being expressed on an interactive computer service; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7555E8E1C2DE4544BDD1A11C04722367"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the removal or restriction of access of any person or entity on an interactive computer service generally available to the public, unless such person or entity is engaged in unlawful speech or criminal activities on such service; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4B1C2DD39AA448F9E9B1270BFE7B589" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>employee</term> has the meaning given that term in section 7322; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12D6B959AF7D4681B1B6DC7F7B878DF5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>interactive computer service</term> has the meaning given that term in section 230(f) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230(f)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C56D3614E3E4B8EB74FC8060F1BF6B8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>lawful speech</quote> means speech protected by the First Amendment of the Constitution; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD46AAE5C2847479390889142BAB5C054"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>unlawful speech</quote> means speech not protected by the First Amendment of the Constitution.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H8BA240A06DB74582975E7F958DEB36A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H39F9D60784E44730B6E8A0A35AC1BF65" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H0B6AA663B19A4D8382F7592A0BCB8256" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H90CC204EA66847E490A5D567DBAA95CB" level="subchapter">Subchapter VIII—Prohibition on Federal employee censorship</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDA47CD25C9B0427D97549066F43487C7" level="section">7381. Policy regarding Federal employee censorship.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDCA65CA20ED1406EBE5B90941B7F397B" level="section">7382. Prohibition on Federal employee censorship.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H25D60F453FD4459F83A985318184903F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Including censorship activities under jurisdiction of Office of Special Counsel</header><text>Strike paragraph (1) of section 1216(a) of title 5, United States Code, and insert the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HCD1AEB3ECFC6452C89910060F27D35EE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H313474D7CBF64DCBB1669AA5C8F36C2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">political activity and censorship prohibited under subchapter III and subchapter VIII of chapter 73, relating to political and censorship activities, respectively, by Federal employees;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HB600E13C199D4EEC99E4AC73B1CECDF0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or any amendment made by this Act should be interpreted as prohibiting a lawful action by a Federal agency to enforce a Federal law or regulation (including any action to enforce a Federal law or regulation addressing obscene matters), to establish or enforce the terms and conditions of Federal financial assistance, or to prohibit a Federal employee from using an official Federal account on an interactive computer service to communicate an official policy position, and relevant information, to the public, or provide information through normal press and public affairs relations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H751A904C1ACA4B11A39DEE6B9D229B1D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Severability</header><text>If any provision of this Act or any amendment made by this Act, or the application of a provision of this Act or an amendment made by this Act to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, and the application of the provisions to any person or circumstance, shall not be affected by the holding.</text></subsection></section><section id="H73958C29ED564CB0B96535973F8787E8" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds that inspectors general should not less than annually for the next seven years publicly report the number of complaints and tips received, the number of investigations opened, and statistics on how investigations were managed and their disposition by that inspector general related to compliance with this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230309" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives March 9, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

