<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC791059B28543CF90513F954B090931" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4716 IH: Keeping our Allies Leading in Advancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4716</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Arms Export Control Act in support of Australia and the AUKUS partnership.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8467037D8764488898EBBDBBFC4EA31A" style="OLC"><section id="HAE16634EAD5C4F6783C4C1F3E75F7D3D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Keeping our Allies Leading in Advancement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>KOALA Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0BABB8177769430D8E4E4E39647E6270"><enum>2.</enum><header>Exceptions for Australia relating to licensing of defense articles and defense services for export under the Arms Export Control Act</header><subsection id="HBBC7B6436AE741C098F8F6A4F7A52704"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 38(j)(1) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(j)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H6723D81E9B1C4729B4F7E77970BF3DE4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (D); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43554AD425FF448F82C24F517FE28895"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text><quoted-block id="H882EF5B87FF144609EAED8817066F65D" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H55C20C7C4033457791063873CCEC01CB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exceptions for Australia</header><clause id="HA7233B56843D40FD9C0D9231CDFEFF2F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to clause (iii), the requirement to conclude a bilateral agreement in accordance with subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to an exemption for Australia from the licensing requirements of this Act for the export of defense articles or defense services that is issued in furtherance of or in connection with the multilateral cooperative partnership between Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States announced on September 21, 2021.</text></clause><clause id="HB58CF349ECBC4AD09833D40496037913"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Relating to other licensing and approval requirements</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section (other than clause (iii)), the President shall exempt from the licensing or other approval requirements of this section exports and transfers (including reexports, retransfers, temporary imports, and brokering activities) of defense articles or defense services between the United States, Australia, and the United Kingdom.</text></clause><clause id="H7A74C03DBE854FD78E62A1F8D881546B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval</header><subclause id="HC96CB725412D4A06AA25E0BA9E308733"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No exemption described in clause (i) or (ii) may be made if Congress enacts a joint resolution disapproving of the exemption.</text></subclause><subclause id="HADEFC9AB91A8464A94B0D049F8C0236F"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Consideration in Senate</header><text>Any joint resolution under this clause shall be considered in the Senate in accordance with the provision of section 601(b) of the International Security Assistance and Arms Export Control Act of 1976.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB3F67E652D5C4D4EBE25A900775D8B2D"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Consideration in the House of Representatives</header><text>For the purpose of expediting the consideration and enactment of any joint resolution under this clause, a motion to proceed to the consideration of any such joint resolution after it has been reported by the appropriate committee shall be treated as highly privileged in the House of Representatives.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBA96B78460E047589796CB5959104D21"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Inapplicability of certain certification requirements</header><subclause id="HE59D175B59714B02BB717EAFFE5AA162"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraphs (1) through (3) of section 3(d) shall not apply to transfers (including transfers of United States Government sales or grants, or commercial exports authorized under this chapter) of defense articles or defense services to Australia.</text></subclause><subclause id="HF8D4A449E3F24C8E8AA4AFDC47BCA795"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The President shall submit to the Speaker of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate on a semiannual basis a report on all transfers that would be subject to the requirements of paragraphs (1) and (2) of section 3(d) but for the application of subclause (I), except for marketing or brokering activities, temporary imports, or amendments to existing marketing or brokering licenses. Any such report shall contain all of the information required to be contained in certifications issued pursuant to section 3(d)(1) for each transfer identified.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBC742ED318914260A6C676343DE9F974"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Aukus transfer reporting requirements</header><text>Any United States person transferring a defense item between or among the United States, the United Kingdom, and Australia that would have required a license under this section but for an exemption issued pursuant to clause (i) or (ii) of this subsection shall report that transfer to the Secretary no later than 90 days after the transfer occurs.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA9544C0974944626BCB877F16DF72E26" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Modification of exception for defense trade cooperation treaties</header><text>Subparagraph (D) of section 38(j)(1) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(j)(1)</external-xref>), as so redesignated by subsection (a)(1), is further amended—</text><paragraph id="H3FB5F7FFC3534A6385EEB3E9D61E02AA" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(D) <header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Exception</header-in-text></quote> and all that follows through <quote>(i) <header-in-text level="clause" style="OLC">In general.—</header-in-text>The</quote> and inserting <quote>(D) <header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Exception for defense trade cooperation treaties</header-in-text>.—The</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB76672E140184964B91A0230F466F7DD" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(I) The Treaty</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="HE58F317207B9434E8275A2B1169145F7" style="OLC"><clause id="HF326866B204D434DB02DF4F6DFEA7739" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Treaty</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E18D7D8501C495BB40515A42D4ECE2D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(II) The Treaty</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="HBD8C049CD3B84903B91F2BFC70624E2D" style="OLC"><clause id="HCA6E395D3581443292C79D2D60716FCE" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Treaty</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H888747B7A8DF4BC4936B6E2990249BB4" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking clause (ii) at the end.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA249A1DBB79146F98C44EE9C43520BFE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advance certification</header><text>Paragraph (3) of section 38(j) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(j)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>export of defense items</quote> the following: <quote>subject to the requirements of paragraph (1)(A)</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H06A68936CAEE4AECBD44A52A6E3F4F1C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Modifications of civil and criminal penalties under sections 38 and 39 of the Arms Export Control Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (c) of section 38 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8BD983BB772743FFB0F72625A3E45D0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$1,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$5,000,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H345078798C8F4C789AED6FD5B76D4B56"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>20 years</quote> and inserting <quote>25 years</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H474B52A6D1E94A34A86FF619EF753BC8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by sections 2 and 3 shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

