<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA7540E8CA76F486D9C2664E1DE974740" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4938 IH: Disclosure of Tax Havens and Offshoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4938</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Act of 1934 to require country-by-country reporting.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H777CCE8E411A4D599EF14A87FB432CAD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5950ED9DF74641229726E28F38BCEB80" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Disclosure of Tax Havens and Offshoring Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H282F0AEBAF0D4C56BA9BB14306C282B1" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Country-by-country reporting</header> <subsection id="H2A5A58FB9D374412855C4801394F4E3B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Country-by-Country Reporting</header><text>Section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H531AB5C4CC5942E595553EDD4141A053" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H7E5176F5E4CA432680506FFB329374C3"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Disclosure of financial performance on a country-by-Country basis</header> 
<paragraph id="H560A125F83214E4EA39FBED5694A4CCF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="H5FFFBA743F7D4E578193019174D51A9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>constituent entity</term> means, with respect to a covered issuer, any separate business entity of the covered issuer;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC5FD9163FC6A40EBB52C098F0C222925"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered issuer</term> means an issuer who—</text> <clause id="H2FBAAB935D134FF3B58039BF3A8A40FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a member of a multinational enterprise group; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD15E10604F4E40DE9CB96C4A744B5962"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the multinational enterprise group of which the issuer is a member has annual revenue for the preceding calendar year of not less than an amount determined by the Commission to conform to United States or international standards for country-by-country reporting; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5F2FBAAF775845FFAB0572F4BF5B095A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>tax jurisdiction</term>—</text> 
<clause id="HC26CFA0D0E804F44A2D4B5024AB81133"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means a country or a jurisdiction that is not a country but that has fiscal autonomy; and</text></clause> <clause id="H464F4077A432458F9BD82312FDA3F3F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes a territory or possession of the United States that has fiscal autonomy.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9CD345A371A146519CEED302BBAA70BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure</header> 
<subparagraph id="HAB492182A3DC411BBD30C9A38733C8D8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each covered issuer shall file a report with the Commission that includes information described in subparagraph (B), and any other information required by the Commission, with respect to the reporting period described in subparagraph (C).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE798C991EF70469290B40D52089A5059"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information required</header><text>The information described in this subparagraph is as follows:</text> 
<clause id="H1C7032CC65A342D98D2C4FCE5A5BDD77"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Constituent entity information</header><text>Information on the constituent entity, including the following:</text> <subclause id="H70616698BB8A4D12B722F3E11E61F056"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The complete legal name of the constituent entity.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA82D796FDB35457CA4D295748BB5CFF8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The tax jurisdiction, if any, in which the constituent entity is resident for tax purposes.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HED9478CCF903432499B05EA06D8B02EF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The tax jurisdiction in which the constituent entity is organized or incorporated (if different from the tax jurisdiction of residence).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA71007F9D5774D65A21CDCF9D62692B8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The tax identification number, if any, used for the constituent entity by the tax administration of the constituent entity's tax jurisdiction of residence.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H340D3C5294F545418857182E55A05346"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The main business activity or activities of the constituent entity.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HA9867BE778E6444A8CA7E2DE94107972"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Tax jurisdiction</header><text>Information on each tax jurisdiction in which one or more constituent entities is resident, presented as an aggregated or consolidated form of the information for the constituent entities resident in each tax jurisdiction, including the following:</text> <subclause id="H61371E4C6646432AAF577CA857AB79DB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Revenues generated from transactions with other constituent entities.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA8526E1CEC80405CB67319E0312A9188"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Revenues not generated from transactions with other constituent entities.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5B5FC7EB5BF24589910E0BD12B072BBF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Profit or loss before income tax.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7D9CBA163E8A436C9FAD989B1B3CDA7B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Total income tax paid on a cash basis to all tax jurisdictions.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0206B304031C460CAA60FDF58C355664"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Total accrued tax expense recorded on taxable profits or losses.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5B196A1699C944DE97DF99A5A3BE90A3"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Stated capital.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE08409EB051D4988A32A5C7DC11E1FE5"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Total accumulated earnings.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HAE6858B7924A4774A7573A5CF5BDFA95"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Total number of employees on a full-time equivalent basis.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H799D34DD3E0E45C4A1B605508D40B868"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Net book value of tangible assets, which, for purposes of this section, does not include cash or cash equivalents, intangibles, or financial assets.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H7972D5BC3DF44E08A9BC64CD5A9CA1FA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Special rules</header><text>The information listed in clause (ii) shall be provided, in aggregated or consolidated form, for any constituent entity or entities that have no tax jurisdiction of residence. In addition, if a constituent entity is an owner of a constituent entity that does not have a jurisdiction of tax residence, then the owner's share of such entity's revenues and profits will be aggregated or consolidated with the information for the owner's tax jurisdiction of residence.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H36E26BC2C0484CF6B508732C2C5E559A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reporting period</header><text>The reporting period covered by this paragraph is the period of the covered entity's applicable financial statement prepared for the 12-month period that ends with or within the taxable year of the covered issuer. If the covered issuer does not prepare an annual applicable financial statement, then the reporting period covered by this paragraph is the 12-month period that ends on the last day of the taxable year of the covered issuer.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFE672C49B98842FC9DBACD1D35406EF0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Filing deadline</header><text>Each covered issuer shall submit to the Commission a report required under this section on or before the due date (including extensions) for filing that covered issuer’s tax return in the tax jurisdiction in which the covered issuer’s multinational enterprise group is resident.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9DBC53DCF9AA42BAB567CDAF6667395B"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Regulation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall, in consultation with the Commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service and Secretary of the Treasury—</text> 
<clause id="H8746FEBA01494136BBB6CBC2A039BCE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>promulgate regulations carrying out this subsection that conform to United States or international standards for country-by-country reporting, including regulations promulgated by the Internal Revenue Service; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7D584A14BB2F4C749530FE20302A85D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require disclosure of the accounting methods used in calculating the information contained in each report filed pursuant to this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE2E8E606C8F3412B897F0DB4E63068D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header> 
<paragraph id="H99A4114D12FA414E9D8403AFAFF8D463"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission (in this section referred to as the <term>Commission</term>) shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H3FCBD6EA972E48CAA961A73435BAB302"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, issue a proposed rule to carry out this section and the amendment made by this section; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C2D43473A0F4F28815B437CA1F97AEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, issue a final rule to carry out this section and the amendment made by this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDBF670CAD89C405EA8E9EB7503871D05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Data format</header><text>The information required to be provided by this section shall be provided by the issuer in a report in a machine readable format prescribed by the Commission, and such report shall be made available to the public online, in such machine readable format as the Commission shall prescribe.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8626529BB8449ED90E2E694E7A2499F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Subsection (t) of section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as added by this section, shall become effective 1 year after the date on which the Commission issues a final rule under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

