<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4678 IH: PLANE Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4678</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, and the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency to establish procedures for the deployment of microreactors at airports, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HED389BF5C80F4F688226A8C68036F552" style="OLC" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"> 
<section id="H0FD9CB06BEFF4B7681A3610C8B6BC486" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Provide Logistical Aid to airports via advanced Nuclear Energy Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>PLANE Act</quote>. </text></section> <section id="HC8808302347C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H22E0D2E09F424CA99150DD473F4195EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Airports generally have diesel generators on site as a backup power source in the event a natural disaster disrupts the primary power source of the airport.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12D7F7FACBD543CAB38B4E701D0BA80B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Backup diesel generators are subject to potential fuel supply chain disruptions, especially in the event of a natural disaster, which may negatively impact public safety and may severely disrupt the airport’s operating procedures if the backup diesel generators aren’t available during a primary power source disruption event.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H80E348A8555D4689A93A167F33BF3820"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Generally speaking, airports store enough diesel fuel on-site to power their backup diesel generators for approximately 72 hours after the primary power source disruption event occurs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBCFD5449D804437818071BA21F20924"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Electricity is fundamental to aviation operations and the operation of many essential systems, equipment, technology, and tools of the airport, therefore maintaining a sufficient backup power capacity should be a priority.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H581560A65DA74F2A9D80F0BB52560BC4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Back-up power sources, such as diesel generators or microreactors, are critical to an airport’s operational continuity and may drive key airport functions in the event of a primary power source disruption event stemming from a natural disaster, including lights critical to illuminating runways, all electronics within the airport, airplane refueling stations, ticketing, signage, security checkpoints, retail and commercial concessions, and elevators and escalators. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H447B849BDFDE470D977A9DA975564849"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Microreactors have the inherent benefit of avoiding diesel-related supply chain constraints, and have the potential to provide consistent, reliable, and clean electricity to power the airport during a primary power source disruption event.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HBA926269EF9B421DB82FEFA2740F6543"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="H552A5A077C304D9492F35A3099C9AC25"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal Aviation Administration-certified airports should consider utilizing microreactors as an alternative to diesel backup generators in the event of a primary power source disruption;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H33DC3B9A4D094F74BA10632D4BC9B46E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Federal Government should initiate discussions to deploy microreactors to respond to a primary power source disruption event stemming from a natural disaster; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03FE5564F5B745BB8401EFA41C9B69E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Nuclear Regulatory Commission should collaborate with the Federal Aviation Administration and the Federal Emergency Management Agency to consider expedited licensing of microreactors to deploy in the event of primary power source disruption.</text></paragraph> </section> 
<section id="H64936AF70B3647E4880AC2612E600FC9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Microreactor deployment at airports</header> 
<subsection id="HDA85D164DA88442BBA8709C9B52CE0DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and the Secretary of Energy, or the designees thereof, shall collaborate to establish procedures to, as soon as practicable, deploy microreactors at airports to respond to a primary power source disruption event stemming from a natural disaster.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9FD1EB39F44748ED946EAC69E4567CE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing procedures under subsection (a), the Chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and the Secretary of Energy shall consider, if the Chairman, Administrators, and Secretary determine appropriate—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0AE78A421FFE42EEA2343967436FF7E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expediting the Nuclear Regulatory Commission licensing process associated with deploying microreactors in the event of a natural disaster;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21FE53509BDB4CB19F0B126F001A21FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>pre-deployment strategies of microreactors, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2209D1D827C34F549AC0899229B934D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">where airports currently store backup diesel generators and an overview of the process, including pros and cons, of utilizing backup diesel generators;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5987F998FEAF4771B4029D239B27016E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the inherent benefits of utilizing microreactors instead of a backup diesel generator and when a backup diesel generator will suffice;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98B61817C17E4A86AA196AD02405A28B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how a microreactor would be transported to an airport and transportation-related processes associated with deploying the microreactor via plane, boat, rail, or truck, depending on the location of the airport;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8CC9E856D90D46938340BE94990D120F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any associated environmental considerations that would have to be alleviated to do so; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H75742E875BB04787B7D4F37D8C38C38F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>how to integrate microreactors into existing electrical grids in primary power source disruption events, including grid connection points, site load limits, and existing infrastructure; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H225BD355796A422C88C3CB6917515B21"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the timeliness of deploying the microreactor, including—</text> 
<clause id="HCF56E5D8FBAB4EAD94BD19A056F69511"><enum>(i)</enum><text>how long it would take to deploy the microreactor;</text></clause> <clause id="H965501C982CE4D6F88652C3D431E8B10"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>how long it would take to set up the microreactor to get the microreactor operational; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFF39BDA54B25444D98D05B9303334E78"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>how long it would take to disconnect the microreactor after the operational use; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA5F245C2F4C4F0AB7B6F952BF34C8C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>deployment strategies of microreactors, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HED4CAE691D7A43049BA4143A9801FEDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operating the microreactor in the deployment event, including considerations relating to—</text> <clause id="HA9A46BE48DB14FE7B2A46F3AA37759B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>personnel and labor and any associated training; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB365AD8A343F48F6B57CEBB363EC6D4B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>qualifications and considerations for who should be responsible for oversight of such personnel described in clause (i) and the deployment of the microreactor; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC298C25C729C4767AEE1E6E6479CC757"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether the operation of a microreactor would inhibit normal airport operations, in the event of a primary power source distribution, in comparison to a diesel generator; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H777F4A11FC92486D96A8EDC4B029DBD7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>what facilities the microreactor would provide electricity to;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11BA277272A146A4B7A232DD5E57AEA3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>post-deployment strategies of microreactors, including potential public-private partnerships that could be used to assist with maintenance, replacement, storage, and disposal; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B7E8FA7BF534E41AD4D1B17F90EA40A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>other considerations, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HB9790FD810CF40F6BECAD0B0A245670B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>what entity would own the microreactor and any contractual agreements or leases necessary for the operation of the reactor, including potential contracts with local utilities, the armed forces, or industry stakeholders to deliver the microreactor when necessary;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2118A32B16FD4911813065144C3F541E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the Nuclear Regulatory Commission can leverage ongoing and existing licensing procedures to maximize the effectiveness and efficiency of establishing procedures to deploy microreactors at airports; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C4D62AF699641E5831331B3E5CC2FBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other considerations that would be necessary to carry out the objective of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H06C711658E0C46EBB108D7319E7534B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after a determination on appropriateness of the considerations described in subsection (b) is made, the Chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and the Secretary of Energy shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure, and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report outlining the reasoning, findings, and any recommended procedures found in making such considerations. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H6156A3EFD5EA400399CC3C6600300233"><enum>(d)</enum><header>FAA guidance update</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the procedures under subsection (b) are finalized, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall update guidance from the Administration to consider the use of microreactors in airport emergency plans.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4489403ED6F44B2D8FA5392B3143D4F7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Airport emergency plan update</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the procedures under subsection (b) are finalized, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall issue such regulations as are necessary to update section 139.325 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, to encourage certified airports to consider utilizing microreactors to provide backup power in the case of a primary power source disruption event as a result of an incident under subsection (b) of such section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAD35FD7351544F4A91900E56D2FD3613"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H58839B0D93804AD380164DAB2EC05528"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Microreactor</header><text>The term <quote>microreactor</quote> means an advanced nuclear reactor (as such term is defined in section 3 of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2215">42 U.S.C. 2215</external-xref> note)), including a portable nuclear reactor, that has an electricity generating capacity of not more than 20 megawatts of electricity and not more than 100 megawatts of thermal energy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB54C978FCF704344BCF925BE37D4C5F2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Natural disaster</header><text>The term <quote>natural disaster</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>major disaster</quote> in section 102 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5122">42 U.S.C. 5122</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

