<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8A780FFD70154A41B64CBCC10012D2F4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3458 IH: Reinstate Our Troops Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3458</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000929">Mrs. Spartz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001314">Mr. Bean of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish certain remedies for certain individuals involuntarily separated from the Armed Forces solely on the basis of refusing to receive vaccinations against COVID–19.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H452C253AC90B4A42BB8659294AEEF91F" style="OLC"><section id="H134939BCD60E4D7FA2C50764BA318AC0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reinstate Our Troops Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H711056DF318542CF8EEE662CF554C4C1" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certain remedies for certain individuals involuntarily separated from the Armed Forces solely on the basis of refusing to receive vaccinations against COVID-19</header><subsection id="HBED6F4AA419B4C7891493C4F4E971515"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reinstatement</header><paragraph id="H6A9D43B026204969957A4D3066A9A257"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the election of a covered individual, the Secretary concerned shall reinstate the covered individual as a member of the Armed Force concerned, in the same rank and grade the covered individual held at the time of separation from such Armed Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF62DE768F2E64FA892F498AE5FDCD062"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered individual may make an election under this subsection during the one-year period following the date of the enactment of this Act. The Secretary concerned shall reinstate a covered individual who makes such an election not later than 30 days after such election.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5212E611E34E49E1B6A8C2A564E053EC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Bonuses for reinstated or reenlisted individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a covered individual who makes an election under subsection (a):</text><paragraph id="HECF644B1EBFE44F299C1B6C017EE0549" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Enlisted members</header><subparagraph id="H3FCC05F5DBA34AE9919779C3700F91F2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inapplicability of repayment provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (g) of section 331 of title 37, United States Code, shall not apply to such an individual who fails to complete a period of service as a member of an Armed Force solely because such individual was a covered individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD85199060602454381C964BE3858CF9B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Return of repaid bonus</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after an individual described in subparagraph (A) makes an election under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall return to such individual a bonus paid under such section to such individual and repaid by such individual pursuant to such subsection (g) and section 373 of such title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HECC27598800D4736B6D92060167328AE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Officers</header><subparagraph id="H632C6874711F4C83A81B329AF1C6434F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inapplicability of repayment provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (f) of section 332 of title 37, United States Code, shall not apply to such an individual who fails to complete a period of service as a member of an Armed Force solely because such individual was a covered individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9B17AC212444C899548CAA450112ED4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Return of repaid bonus</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after an individual described in subparagraph (A) makes an election under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall return to such individual a bonus paid under such section to such individual and repaid by such individual pursuant to such subsection (f) and section 373 of such title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H225D3DC3DA0F42CA99CF2CA51D5073AA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retroactive characterizations of discharge</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a covered individual who does not make an election under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned shall ensure that the discharge of such individual is characterized as honorable.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD3C57A282CF340DF8E485CA84CADEF7C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expungement of adverse action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary concerned shall expunge from the military service record of a covered individual any reference to adverse action against such individual solely on the basis of the refusal of such individual to receive a vaccination against COVID-19.</text></subsection><subsection id="H031971BE6F0340A49DD642DF2F260C76"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on progress in carrying out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3720CB0D69674E40A236B02A8AF20C69"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H982A911A9E6F493483CACA051EEF3D19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered individual</quote> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H81EF3CA9272044298CA3C0432B4B5525"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as a member of an Armed Force, requested an exemption from an order to receive a vaccination against COVID-19; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDC8EA80AEEA4ECF8B760F30221F4215"><enum>(B)</enum><text>was involuntarily separated from an Armed Force solely on the basis of the refusal of such individual to receive such a vaccination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H90DD964B014B4C539119EA2A4CA4992F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>Secretary concerned</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

