<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF181017241524896BE85D5F5F27366DF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 700 IH: Supply Chain Disruptions Relief Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 700</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230201">February 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To treat certain liquidations of new motor vehicle inventory as qualified liquidations of LIFO inventory for purposes of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF3372B4B5724456D8928780A8C6E8723" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC17A09A142024F9CA3190104CEA56FBF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supply Chain Disruptions Relief Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H780F6BD34EFE4998919D690D92B2BBF3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of certain liquidations of new motor vehicle inventory as qualified liquidations of LIFO inventory</header> <subsection id="H7ABB0E0AFA184E3994098C9F51C8AE9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any dealer of new motor vehicles which inventories new motor vehicles under the LIFO method for any specified taxable year, the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (2) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/473">section 473(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall be treated as satisfied with respect to such inventory for such taxable year.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA61312C3E4F24714A74379D3C3CE6F11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional relief</header> 
<paragraph id="H52AA17E566734C74AEE7222CAB1DF9C0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, not later than the date which is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, prescribe regulations or other guidance under which dealers of new motor vehicles with a qualified liquidation (determined after application of subsection (a)) of new motor vehicles for any specified taxable year may elect—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B347D89D2B34691A29385437BE7EBA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to not recognize any income in the specified taxable year which is solely attributable to such qualified liquidation, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9977C644C3884EE1A4721B69CE33F1D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to treat the replacement period with respect to such liquidation as being the period beginning with the first taxable year after such specified taxable year and ending with the earlier of—</text> <clause id="H983BE6B674C444FFBB6A74A036355A05"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the first taxable year after such liquidation with respect to which such dealer does not inventory new motor vehicles under the LIFO method, or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H32C1E186F0E84371AB10D264557E7E0C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the last taxable year ending before January 1, 2026.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D4F1926C8FA4417B91D932A19A3B207"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to fully replace liquidated vehicles during replacement period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, as of the close of the replacement period, the taxpayer has failed to replace all liquidated vehicles with respect to a qualified liquidation to which paragraph (1) applies, the taxpayer shall increase gross income for the last taxable year of the replacement period by the sum of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H67D03059C54B4A9499942836430F1206"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the aggregate amount of income that would have been required to be recognized in the liquidation year had the taxpayer elected to apply the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/473">section 473</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and not made the election in paragraph (1), plus</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA84D06C4063453A82A8940E56597020"><enum>(B)</enum><text>interest thereon at the underpayment rate established under section 6621 of such Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD0C98A80B5144BB9E3C9E8141E0C999" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Elections</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF7646D3541814011958A6408D05A0BCA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except to the extent provided in subparagraph (B), an election under paragraph (1) with respect to any specified taxable year shall be made by the due date (including extensions) for filing the taxpayer’s return of tax for such taxable year and in such manner as the Secretary may prescribe. Once made, any such election shall be irrevocable.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6642CCE2F69465FB1E7A3C66B7B82EE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain elections treated as change in method of accounting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an election with respect to a specified taxable year for which the return of tax has already been filed before the date of the enactment of this Act, any election under paragraph (1) for such specified taxable year may be made on the return of tax for the first taxable year ending after the date of the enactment of this Act and shall be treated for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/481">section 481</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 as a change in method of accounting initiated by the taxpayer and made with the consent of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2C821DAD9292496A90D7523A30FD0196"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="H7F21B0C7AD514375A2A3BEAF92796AE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Specified taxable year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>specified taxable year</quote> means any liquidation year ending after March 12, 2020, and before January 1, 2022.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7FCFC4330AC24768BC4A8DC0D5FA6632"><enum>(2)</enum><header>New motor vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>new motor vehicle</quote> means a motor vehicle—</text> <subparagraph id="H4E13DB495E304ACCBE645E084223A95F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>which is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/163">section 163(j)(9)(C)(i)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H28CC0ECA2C8042CE9D9DD7BB7E4D3676"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the original use of which has not commenced.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7122CC0B66F7411598E019956F9BB757"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary’s delegate. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BC554D8A6304A32A2B15D5A32A7B609"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other terms</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, terms used in this section which are also used in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/473">section 473</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall have the same meaning as when used in such section 473.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

