<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H99D37B754D344F5BB72C563E41BE3843" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5847 IH: International Children with Disabilities Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5847</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the International Children with Disabilities Protection Program within the Department of State, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD43887991A564E98AE4E2E2FB241F849" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H115E286C1C5E4A12908F095DD5447A87" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>International Children with Disabilities Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC621BF6D43554757A3AA0404ACE125A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
<paragraph id="HB0D51CC851D14A2D9593A29DCFC80F77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), there are at least 240,000,000 children and youth with disabilities in the world, including approximately 53,000,000 children under age 5.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5EF16BAB2C744419B717EE37212BF5CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Families and children with disabilities together make up nearly 2,000,000,000 people, or 25 percent of the world's population.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCB87CAD931A644BBB8D7644248CCB810"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Millions of children, particularly children with intellectual and other developmental disabilities, are placed in large or small residential institutions and most of those children are left to grow up without the love, support, and guidance of a family. The vast majority of children placed in residential institutions have at least one living parent or have extended family, many of whom would keep their children at home if they had the support and legal protections necessary to do so.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22BC14FF24F54B7189650731473A9474"><enum>(4)</enum><text>As described in the 2013 world report published by UNICEF, many parents who wish to keep their children with disabilities feel that they have no choice but to give up their child to a residential institution because of prejudice and stigma against disability, the lack of support and protection that families receive, and the fact that education and community services are often inaccessible or inappropriate for children with disabilities.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5C3498C11B284C5BAA9B83E427F3E3EC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Extensive scientific research demonstrates that placing children in residential institutions may lead to psychological harm, increased developmental disabilities, stunted growth, rapid spread of infectious diseases, and high rates of mortality.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A44D208E335447C9615C214B4063D8B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Leading child protection organizations have documented that children and adolescents raised without families in residential institutions face high risk of violence, trafficking for forced labor or the sex industry, forced abortion or sterilization, and criminal detention.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCF410E716FC84D38B801F1DCBE4E21E6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The danger of family breakup and institutionalization has grown enormously as a result of the COVID–19 pandemic. According to a study published in The Lancet, as of September 2022, a minimum of 10,500,000 children globally have lost a parent or co-residing caregiver to COVID–19 and are now at increased risk of placement in a residential institution.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA81CC9ACEF140EA9C56732E69AD8023"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The disability rights movement in the United States has been a world leader and an inspiration to the growth of a global disability rights movement. The United States has many models of practice that could be shared with countries around the world to support laws, policies, and services to promote the full inclusion of children with disabilities in families around the world.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4CF85099F7024F7E8C7D76850A1795E4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Advancing Protection and Care for Children in Adversity strategy of the United States Government (APCCA) and the Global Child Thrive Act of 2020 (subtitle I of title XII of division A of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 3985) commit the United States Government to investing in the development, care, dignity, and safety of vulnerable children and their families around the world, including efforts to keep children with their families and reduce placement of children in residential institutions.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HC2753B41542A4494A5F570DEFB0A4516"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
<paragraph id="H42EABF0BC20D41E2B3511389FA00052E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>stigma and discrimination against children with disabilities, particularly intellectual and other developmental disabilities, and lack of support for community inclusion have left people with disabilities and their families economically and socially marginalized;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84A188E5FA5D46C6B413A295DDF92CA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>organizations of persons with disabilities and family members of persons with disabilities are often too small to apply for or obtain funds from domestic or international sources or ineligible to receive funds from such sources;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD13127EFAB3B487DADCD1D5ACB6EF1BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>as a result of the factors described in paragraphs (1) and (2), key stakeholders have often been left out of public policymaking on matters that affect children with disabilities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BFDACB9E7784D22A8AB3C4246280A9C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>financial support, technical assistance, and active engagement of people with disabilities and their families is needed to ensure the development of effective policies that protect families, ensure the full inclusion in society of children with disabilities, and promote the transition of children with disabilities to independent living as adults.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H0FD172CE2809451B945665DBDD014F6F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HA8086F9847CB4D1F8155F05355EE13DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of State.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDCB7D0723CE246399B4E0191C3911650"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Family</header><text>The term <term>family</term> includes married and unmarried parents, single parents, adoptive families, kinship care, extended family, and foster care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2A242EF2C741474FAC40F7B5D6242840"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Organization of persons with disabilities</header><text>The term <term>organization of persons with disabilities</term> means a nongovernmental civil society organization with staff leadership and a board of directors the majority of which consists of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4179F4F5844F46338F07AB85B65A94CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>people with disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDCB3D19529904BEFAB62B5D7AB9517AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals who were formerly placed in a residential institution; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H48566880923041F587C3AFFF6415A1FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family members of children or youth with disabilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72635D84766A4937B540BB060A80A1FA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Residential institution</header><text>The term <term>residential institution</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA9A946F830C74B03AA3250BD3ACD5663"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a facility where children live in a collective arrangement that is not family-based and that—</text> <clause id="HC9E2BC0CFE4D4053B3D9034CCF4C8084"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may be public or privately managed and staffed;</text></clause>
<clause id="H12419C722F3144C3A8DF1831727E1B87"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may be small or large; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA6AAC648BBBE458BA4288DE780313178"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>may or may not be designated for children with disabilities; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8B85D30658D24B389348BF5647EDDFE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes an orphanage, a children’s institution, a group home, an infant home, a children’s village or cottage complex, a boarding school used primarily for care, and any other residential setting for children.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H2F5BA608852C4BB4BA7BFF59D1151704"><enum>5.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to—</text>
<paragraph id="H49CB3C841156478CA8BC60802F1AF3D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assist countries abroad in creating rights protection programs for people with disabilities and developing policies and social supports to ensure that children with disabilities can grow up as members of families and make the transition to independent living as adults;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0F56F72C9494D36BA53BF5D64F1312E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote the development of advocacy skills and leadership abilities of people with disabilities and family members of children and youth with disabilities so that such individuals can effectively participate in their local, regional, and national governments to promote policy reforms and programs to support full inclusion in families of children with disabilities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H07C349F5C4454483879E9314C92CB69D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promote the development of laws and policies that—</text> <subparagraph id="HAEE3ED81D2D547F1B527BA3A202CFE24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strengthen families and protect against the unnecessary institutionalization of children with disabilities; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5FB98E69B8CA4CCA8624DCEBA036DC27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>create opportunities for youth with disabilities to receive the resources and support needed to achieve their full potential and transition to independent living as adults;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABAB47427CBB493BA17CB6FAD0AEB531"><enum>(4)</enum><text>promote participation by different groups of people with disabilities and their families in advocating for disability rights and reforms to legal frameworks; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A3D93044D2D47C289712411F3C2329A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>promote the sustainable action needed to bring about changes in law, policy, and programs to ensure full family inclusion of children with disabilities and the transition of children with disabilities to independent living as adults.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H84BAA1A22A54404295417FA17987F986"><enum>6.</enum><header>International Children with Disabilities Protection Program and capacity building</header> <subsection id="HE5BB68C10ED34234AB31EA33AAEC32BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>International Children with Disabilities Protection Program</header> <paragraph id="H47CE133911A5446EBC3FFE430EA3DB8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text>There is established within the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor of the Department a grant and capacity-building program to be known as the <quote>International Children with Disabilities Protection Program</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC87A0FC09D4E40358F29486644758487"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the Program is to assist organizations of persons with disabilities and family members of children with disabilities in communicating about and advocating for policies that ensure the family inclusion and transition to independent living of children with disabilities to advance the policy described in section 5.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09FAF49850FF4B0D982DE439EDE63B9E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Secretary of State, in consultation with leading civil society groups with expertise in global disability rights, shall establish criteria for—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC48FF60797C5424187075FB8A2342440"><enum>(A)</enum><text>applications for grants awarded under paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD3E53047D39445DE82EC9A7BB8AC9C8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the selection of—</text>
<clause id="HA099F1EF946242D787F27D064EDCAF8A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the countries or regions targeted under the Program;</text></clause> <clause id="H9BA5CED4D6694F1B9E0DA35349D1D48B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>priority activities funded through grants awarded under paragraph (4); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H737C3471D41D4DF0A744D4098FE1345D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>capacity-building needs of recipients of grants awarded under paragraph (4).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A568BA0B0A94EC4AD2C4745B10FC37C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disability inclusion grants</header> <subparagraph id="H605AE2B40C684C708652AA7C452A346C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State may award grants to eligible implementing partners to administer grant amounts directly or through subgrants.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1A8BDBB87085415EA06B8B73A6374108"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible implementing partners</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, an eligible implementing partner is a nongovernmental organization or other civil society organization that—</text> <clause id="H1D7EFB120C984FAA9F9FEB9E63B7D18D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the capacity to administer grant amounts—</text>
<subclause id="H52E93E0C4E3A473B993397751C50D968"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2422A3AF04A0418D9FC151A42EB08799"><enum>(II)</enum><text>through subgrants that can be effectively used by emerging new organizations of persons with disabilities; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HF041CBB187134C289B0381D3A0EB36AA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has expertise in disability rights.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2674553F2F6D49CF8C038338E17522EB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary of State shall prioritize awarding grants under this paragraph to eligible implementing partners with experience operating or administering subgrants in countries for which the Assistant Secretary of State for Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor, in consultation with the United States Government Special Adviser and Senior Coordinator for the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development on Children in Adversity, has determined that there are significant populations of children living in residential institutions.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6FC55FEA1296418AA19CEC6CA22E98F6"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible implementing partner that receives a grant under this paragraph should seek to—</text> <clause id="HD0CD3386D65F43FE92BA510F33F13136"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide not less than 50 percent of the grant amount through subgrants to local organizations of persons with disabilities and other nongovernmental organizations working in country to advance the policy described in section 5; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H3011844F993C44FC8ADB5ED7E87AB5BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide, of any amount distributed pursuant to clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="HA9BA5752A94E4768928AC73D682D8690"><enum>(I)</enum><text>75 percent to organizations of persons with disabilities; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HA24F68B3A00D464DB7ADDD9457A1F8E3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>25 percent to other nongovernmental organizations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H31C48996F4DA445CAC569A8E04867910"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Capacity-Building programs</header><text>The Secretary of State is authorized to provide funds to nongovernmental organizations with expertise in capacity building and technical assistance to develop capacity-building programs to—</text>
<paragraph id="H7EEE537201DB43878924D67CF25358B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop disability leaders, legislators, policymakers, and service providers to plan and implement programs to advance the policy described in section 5;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB33F78762864BA3A6D37812CC7ED9B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>build the advocacy capacity and knowledge of successful models of rights enforcement, family support, and disability inclusion among disability, youth, and allied civil society advocates, attorneys, and professionals to advance the policy described in section 5;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H59A9A5BD7AC148E8AD6352CF46AFB8CA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>create online programs to train policymakers, activists, and other individuals on successful models of reform, services, and rights protection to ensure that children with disabilities can live and grow up with families and become full participants in society, which—</text> <subparagraph id="HD6902BCCB9B34F6EBC97E8FCCF4DF990"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are available globally;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC0C83819E9C24BC2BC172A2D092DB1C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offer low-cost or no-cost training accessible to persons with disabilities, family members of such persons, and other individuals with potential to offer future leadership in the advancement of the goals of family inclusion, transition to independent living as adults, and rights protection for children with disabilities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20470DA50A744E598C656D852FCE1866"><enum>(C)</enum><text>should be targeted to government policymakers, disability activists, and other potential allies and supporters among civil society groups; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1FE779B2FB5740E88345242317308380"><enum>(4)</enum><text>create study tours so activists and policymakers from abroad can observe and better understand the operation of successful models of family and community inclusion and rights advocacy, including exposing such activists and policymakers to models of good practice in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFDD35716E67844F09CE44055627D3049"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> <paragraph id="H4A3347D30DC648D78CBF279076F868C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section amounts as follows:</text>
<subparagraph id="H6382E78008F840C99A130FC93BF7A71D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35A16AAA835B463993A1A8886186C8E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2029.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H98B06B5D183A478CB7348618692EEC8A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Capacity-building and technical assistance programs</header><text>Of the amounts authorized to be appropriated by paragraph (1), not less than $1,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and not less than $3,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2029 are authorized to be available for capacity-building and technical assistance programs to support disability rights leadership and to train and engage policymakers, professionals, and allies in civil society organizations in foreign countries.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HCFB3B9CCE34843D281067CE2B091FC14"><enum>7.</enum><header>Briefings and reports on implementation</header> <subsection id="H327BAC59C1E5441CB357A62BBD230C9F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual briefing required</header> <paragraph id="HFA700F638A364DA9B43F8F67E8F7BF3B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than annually through fiscal year 2029, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a briefing on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H704F18820CF54B3F95790E31773E54CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the programs and activities carried out to advance the policy described in section 5; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0AF49178B2D84150A13967189355E000"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any broader work of the Department in advancing that policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5FE4F25BFB014076AC7C4AD099313D07"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each briefing required by paragraph (1) shall include, with respect to each program carried out under section 6—</text> <subparagraph id="HF0937A620D4242589E42D6DD8B3594D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rationale for the country and program selection;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9BDA4730E9A047749107BCD1C4DA9416"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the goals and objectives of the program, and the kinds of participants in the activities and programs supported;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69D66619164F4996A079BDDD119A4F40"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the types of technical assistance and capacity building provided; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA4E73880F44A43CDA8BF90B6ADE10190"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an identification of any gaps in funding or support needed to ensure full participation of organizations of persons with disabilities or inclusion of children with disabilities in the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE31CF1F1A57E4598A583847A2F3E110C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports required</header> <paragraph id="H51748275534C432B953DB29BAE681C07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than once every 3 years through fiscal year 2029, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report on the matters described in subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7EE70D3F3B834FAF8ADC99A0187F0208"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall include the elements described in subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D180F54E3F749FD994DD1BB0CC05AD7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In preparing each report required by paragraph (1), the Secretary of State shall consult with organizations of persons with disabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H47ED3BFF67F145DEA574C22034BC345B"><enum>8.</enum><header>Promoting international protection and advocacy for children with disabilities</header>
<subsection id="HA524BF3059FD4508B4E8DA67AC9B9346"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress on programming and programs</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HF8FE395EFE8F44968AFEF73B6AB677DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all programming of the Department and the United States Agency for International Development related to childcare reform, improvement of health care systems, primary and secondary education, disability rights, and human rights should seek to be consistent with the policy described in section 5; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC80DA84456C84869B56A773A052D7F3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>programs of the Department and the United States Agency for International Development related to children, health care, and education—</text> <subparagraph id="H6563BE8D44AD47169FBDED4591B1D016"><enum>(A)</enum><text>should—</text>
<clause id="H93E0F5EA0C9E4B7BA5412CEE860E5761"><enum>(i)</enum><text>engage organizations of persons with disabilities in policymaking and program implementation; and</text></clause> <clause id="H99C44BAAD8B346CD93789EDF07E8948E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>support full inclusion of children with disabilities in families; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3C09BE64A74E4AF18A8642CDD7E91A54"><enum>(B)</enum><text>should aim to avoid support for residential institutions for children with disabilities except in situations of conflict or emergency in a manner that protects family connections as described in subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB1D100A34D548B5892220B6FAC1124A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress on conflict and emergencies</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
<paragraph id="HEE72B752405C48ECB3DA9D82774B6D57"><enum>(1)</enum><text>programs of the Department and the United States Agency for International Development serving children in situations of conflict or emergency, among displaced or refugee populations, or in natural disasters should seek to ensure that children with and without disabilities can maintain family ties; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E430FD6DB594A93BCD13610322A1682"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in situations of emergency, if children are separated from parents or have no family, every effort should be made to ensure that children are placed with extended family, in kinship care, or in a substitute family. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

