<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H60D2DCCDEBE1437E8164DA1D6F56E49F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4037 IH: Airline Employee Assault Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4037</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 49, United States Code, with respect to submissions of certain Employee Assault Prevention and Response Plans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF2670CFACAA9404DA91FDD413F4E2C84" style="OLC"><section id="H6434C5691D694DE3BFDD57F52C2546D6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Airline Employee Assault Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9B8586125CF0465FA5554CA7FB9C4D6E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Implementation of employee assault prevention and response plans</header><subsection id="HCF494F75F51C424080D29942570C1D66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 551(a) of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44903">49 U.S.C. 44903</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting <quote>of the Federal Aviation Administration and the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration</quote> after <quote>Administrator</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HEF4837EE3E8147D39D7698468EE7BDFF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notice and cure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, air carriers described in subsection (a) of section 551 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44903">49 U.S.C. 44903</external-xref> note) shall comply with the requirements of such subsection with respect to submission to the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0DAD12AB0E5F41ED8C2342D6206C4826"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in consultation with the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration, shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report on all the Employee Assault Prevention and Response Plans submitted pursuant to section 551 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44903">49 U.S.C. 44903</external-xref> note), to date, listed by each air carrier described in subsection (a) of such section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD40D7221B20E498DAA88EEDB1CD1C57F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification regarding passenger service agents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 46503 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, including employees performing ticketing, check-in or baggage claim, or boarding functions,</quote> after <quote>air carrier employee</quote>. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

