<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC6F93766C3F246B18613EF925C93FA03" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1273 IH: Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1273</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Peace Corps Act by providing better support for current and returned volunteers, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H448AD90B558F438A921AEEE3ED02FD87" style="OLC">
<section id="H5CD3AFE987014AC5811A6445A1A73D0E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB579535A4CB948E69134CAC28E04C575"><enum>2.</enum><header>Funding for the Peace Corps; Integration of information age volunteer opportunities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2502">22 U.S.C. 2502</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H503AF20380334B5186B5C66B198A411F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(2), by striking <quote>that fiscal year and the subsequent fiscal year</quote> and inserting <quote>obligation until the last day of the subsequent fiscal year</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9043067425A34F39B25EDCEEEDB6F999"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (h) as subsection (e).</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HE6F79E41C40D4FDEBCB7E16B44431E55"><enum>3.</enum><header>Readjustment allowances for volunteers and volunteer leaders</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504">22 U.S.C. 2504</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HCC3FB306E4874C0C81A12EE29726EFC9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>insure their health</quote> and inserting <quote>ensure their safety, their health, and</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEFB897B3733C49BBB937DB5FF8BB34AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="H44AA7755BBEF4881A5D747EE70BA5F63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$125</quote> and inserting <quote>$375</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H42F3F2DD7791472199E87C0C8BF4798A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>his</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>the volunteer’s</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H510586B4F6824DD08E631136C0251881"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the volunteer</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5D321B4233824B909A2A49F51158BF19"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (e) as subsection (d);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE42FF83DFD484B168880C15864CD03CF" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (d), as redesignated, the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC3937BCBC9AD4838B73CD2AE8ADE9FBB">
<subsection id="HD6C8AFAF70A2457BBE0AE5AB815C83D7" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><text>The Director shall consult with health experts outside of the Peace Corps, including experts licensed in the field of mental health, and follow guidance by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention regarding the prescription of medications to volunteers.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B95A488EA3F4D1A8A2943AE793BF045"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (h), by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the President</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4800C84F6530484294D0DD37B02A8F15"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (n)(2)—</text> <subparagraph id="HF565C9EADA194382A377446089E99486"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (e)</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>subsection (d)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC939AD48B31C4AD9B0627C9961524BB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the President</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAFC89AA8CE6D47F0AAE02D3804429ECC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in subsection (o), by striking <quote>his</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>the volunteer’s</quote>.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H367A69BF524B422DB73ADADCB6FDFB98"><enum>4.</enum><header>Restoration of volunteer opportunities for major disruptions to volunteer service</header>
<subsection id="H4FB7E19DB11D45A8AC660CE8AC93606A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 5 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504">22 U.S.C. 2504</external-xref>), as amended by section 3 of this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96E1ABB08DBA4B07BE738EA8E862B380"> <subsection id="H8B849370ADDA4D1BBABD0A3AB28AF6A7"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Disruption of service protocols</header> <paragraph id="H77C28F7132C54F8D9FB07BC1A2342E44"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall establish processes for the safe return to service of returning Peace Corps volunteers whose service is interrupted due to mandatory evacuations of volunteers due to catastrophic events or global emergencies of unknowable duration, which processes shall include—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF5605FA4CCCF4B0EAB22845729DB82BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the establishment of monitoring and communications systems, protocols, safety measures, policies, and metrics for determining the appropriate approaches for restoring volunteer opportunities for evacuated returned volunteers whose service is interrupted by a catastrophic event or global emergency; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3802586606AB4334AC21D283A7AD51CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>streamlining, to the fullest extent practicable, application requirements for the return to service of such volunteers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDF11A88022E8412D958A97D8686754D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Return to service</header><text>Beginning on the date on which any volunteer described in paragraph (1) returns to service, the Director shall strive to afford evacuated volunteers, to the fullest extent practicable, the opportunity—</text> <subparagraph id="H5FE9B953BB9941D98C18ADC7537409C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to return to their previous country of service, except for Peace Corps missions in China; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF783408F911945FEBEEE49E366371A75"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to continue their service in the most needed sectors within the country in which they had been serving immediately before their evacuation due to a catastrophic event or global emergency, except for Peace Corps missions in China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H95DE8A662BAE4218AD750C0867D9C5D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medical personnel</header><text>Section 5A(b) of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504a">22 U.S.C. 2504a(b)</external-xref>) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, mental health professionals</quote> after <quote>medical officers</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H292B7DF726A34912A10D2F5BFEDCB4E7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Volunteer leaders</header><text>Section 6 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2505">22 U.S.C. 2505</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H1BF8BA5FEA0646A487A2EA2F6443470F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>$125</quote> and inserting <quote>$375</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7E1CAE8874F14CA69DC1485D212D423B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the President</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H1D9D304223CD41BEAA0C52031DC327C8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Health care continuation for Peace Corps volunteers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(d) of the Peace Corps Act, as redesignated by section 3(3) of this Act, is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H836A54417E064A1697DC9CBA7A869549">
<subsection id="HF5DD87F595DC4B919CF2229DB1467DF5"><enum>(d)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H92E998BA3FCB4920A178059CB36660A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Volunteers shall receive such health care during their service as the Director considers necessary or appropriate, including, if necessary, services under section 8B.</text></paragraph> <paragraph indent="up1" id="H0F125CFA262A419D88DB2C6E35181940"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Applicants for enrollment shall receive such health examinations preparatory to their service, and applicants for enrollment who have accepted an invitation to begin a period of training under section 8(a) shall receive, preparatory to their service, such immunization, dental care, and information regarding prescription options and potential interactions, as may be necessary and appropriate and in accordance with subsection (F).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph indent="up1" id="H2698D7B523A34737B42DA43A1AB6F477"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Subject to such conditions as the Director may prescribe, the health care described in paragraphs (1) and (2) for serving volunteers, applicants for enrollment, or returned volunteers may be provided in any facility of any agency of the United States Government, and in such cases the amount expended for maintaining and operating such facility shall be reimbursed from appropriations available under this Act. Health care may not be provided under this subsection in a manner that is inconsistent with the Assisted Suicide Funding Restriction Act of 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/12">Public Law 105–12</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph indent="up1" id="HD6FB7171C28042A0952A9C529D56159F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Not later than 30 days before the date on which the period of service of a volunteer terminates, or 30 days after such termination date if such termination is the result of an emergency, the Director, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall provide detailed information to such volunteer regarding options for health care after termination other than health care provided by the Peace Corps, including information regarding—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC2D8A067D27C46F58F4DBD1025CAFE45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how to find additional, detailed information, including information regarding—</text> <clause id="H1CCF0E995C334553B662FEB408ED0361"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the application process and eligibility requirements for medical assistance through a State Medicaid plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>), or under a waiver of such plan; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H76D66347D0514863A2692CC2EB24CDBB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>health care option identification services available through the public and private sectors;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB7C6732FB1B34BC78A5374F1364E91CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>where detailed information on health plans may be obtained; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H18BD682174CD4A1685F59C0614E54F91"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if such volunteer is 25 years of age or younger, the eligibility of such volunteer to enroll as a dependent child in a group health plan or health insurance coverage in which the parent of such volunteer is enrolled in such plan or coverage offers such dependent coverage.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph indent="up1" id="HEB9A7E682EF5474190AC38AF8487E6B4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Paragraph (4) shall apply to volunteers whose periods of service are subject to early termination.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H029F795E7EE04C54A56CBD191032DF69"><enum>6.</enum><header>Access to antimalarial drugs and hygiene products for Peace Corps volunteers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5A of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504a">22 U.S.C. 2504a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H6F03FD3DC1CE4F52A39F55F37FF8DC5F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsections (c) and (e);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H657B5BC212E24C3E88264BA79435AC9C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (d) as subsection (e);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A3F927F93B84F1EBD5DB07A05F82F3F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF4D2EE4E62D14A78BBA9F8970723FB7E">
<subsection id="H08A5CF8D19F74DD2B4A59A97701E6733"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Antimalarial drugs</header>
<paragraph id="HE1B9B281B90A4B7689D85F676D43A166"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall consult with experts at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention regarding recommendations for prescribing malaria prophylaxis, in order to provide the best standard of care within the context of the Peace Corps environment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A1A3EB19BF74FCC83BE766DD3BB5001"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain training</header><text>The Director shall ensure that each Peace Corps medical officer serving in a malaria-endemic country receives training in the recognition of the side effects of such medications.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H488259FFCED345C880012E4BA1BD8164"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Director shall consult with the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Health Affairs regarding the policy of using mefloquine in the field as an antimalarial prophylactic.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE62F0F1C2EE1453088B568A8D1AFA46B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Access to hygiene products</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title>, the Director shall establish a comprehensive policy to ensure Peace Corps volunteers who require hygiene products are able to access such products.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="HF147D3FB0EF843E18E286137CAA0349F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Codification of certain Executive orders relating to existing noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers and extension of the period of such status</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 5A the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35BFFCA74CF844539B18CA5ECF3F6BB8"> <section id="HBB18622F149044B5A95203FEFBDA840E"><enum>5B.</enum><header>Codification of Executive orders relating to noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers</header> <subsection id="H174B23ED80E84297BAACD6970C8E2A7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (b), Executive Order 11103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504">22 U.S.C. 2504</external-xref> note; relating to Providing for the Appointment of Former Peace Corps Volunteers to the Civilian Career Services), as amended by Executive Order 12107 (44 Fed. Reg. 1055; relating to the Civil Service Commission and Labor-Management in the Federal Service), as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title>, shall remain in effect and have the full force and effect of law.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H80426BB921E34357A152DB2F870157FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Period of eligibility</header>
<paragraph id="H45ECDC0878CC481E8B248C2810D12487"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H879D21C5D1DF44A5867E8D001F88C614"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>the term <term>Executive agency</term>—</text>
<clause id="HD6FB4C454EA14437B1E2F94887968AD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the meaning given such term in section 105 of title 5, United States Code;</text></clause> <clause id="H300B0CEF62BE4C74837AEBD79CE29D93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes the United States Postal Service and the Postal Regulatory Commission; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H9772F677AACB41468D1FA21EC1E5BE6A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>does not include the Government Accountability Office. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCDEC8C5D5BBB48069271F7FB572D82BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Hiring freeze</header><text>The term <term>hiring freeze</term> means any memorandum, Executive order, or other action by the President that prohibits an Executive agency from filling vacant Federal civilian employee positions or creating new such positions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9CA0BCB7C886467185F0CDD47D9BB44F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The period of eligibility for noncompetitive appointment to the civil service provided to an individual under subsection (a), including any individual who is so eligible on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title>, shall be extended by the total number of days, during such period, that—</text> <subparagraph id="HD9F22F97DAE04A39AB51FDF02F5AA8AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a hiring freeze for civilian employees of the executive branch is in effect by order of the President with respect to any Executive agency at which the individual has applied for employment;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEA751914F69E4816829A609FDD6715FB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there is a lapse in appropriations with respect to any Executive agency at which the individual has applied for employment; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H247A1C6FF87A4F0DBCC10B8CEBDE1F12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the individual is receiving disability compensation under section 8142 of title 5, United States Code, based on the individual’s service as a Peace Corps volunteer, retroactive to the date the individual applied for such compensation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1B273B7EC1954A589C679AC27AD23760"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The period of eligibility for noncompetitive appointment status to the civil service under subsection (a) shall apply to a Peace Corps volunteer—</text> <subparagraph id="HB64DA16FF71F4BF685ABD6B2E90B5145"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whose service ended involuntarily as a result of a suspension of volunteer operations by the Director, but may not last longer than 1 year after the date on which such service ended involuntarily; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB6CB72B9D134AD7B9B7693A98887EFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who re-enrolls as a volunteer in the Peace Corps after completion of a term of service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H32B17362E1554C86A596CB209FB2B4AC"><enum>8.</enum><header>Extension of period of existing noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 5B, as added by section 7 of this Act, the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DD0D92F91CF4BA5888C8D1D29C7C564">
<section id="HB3051F21AB7C4282BCB8C44B55B21C49"><enum>5C.</enum><header>Extension of period of existing noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers</header>
<subsection id="H7C5D3C63870F47BBA34CF3EA2299D49A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to section 5B, Executive Order 11103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504">22 U.S.C. 2504</external-xref> note; relating to Providing for the Appointment of Former Peace Corps Volunteers to the Civilian Career Services), as amended by Executive Order 12107 (44 Fed. Reg. 1055; relating to the Civil Service Commission and Labor-Management in the Federal Service), as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Peace Corps Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title>, shall remain in effect and have the full force and effect of law.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8A25505F30C54D7BB42ACD53BAC73D68"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status</header><text>Subject to subsection (d), any volunteer whose Peace Corps service was terminated after April 1, 2020, and who has been certified by the Director as having satisfactorily completed a full term of service, may be appointed within two years of completion of qualifying service to a position in any United States department, agency, or establishment in the competitive service under title 5, United States Code, without competitive examination, in accordance with such regulations and conditions as may be prescribed by the Director of the Office of Personnel Management.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7C42A15AA46648FE990C6D03FB676E57"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>The appointing authority may extend the noncompetitive appointment eligibility under subsection (b) to not more than 3 years after a volunteer’s separation from the Peace Corps if the volunteer, following such service, was engaged in—</text> <paragraph id="H557F4B01959B47F8B7D768E721863A18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>military service;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEC76EAF23AD0496BA52E4AF3881E8693"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the pursuit of studies at a recognized institution of higher learning; or </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23C64A7228034C4EAE730FFA1E3425BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other activities which, in the view of the appointing authority, warrant an extension of such eligibility.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB48368B873894DCDB15C80ECF3126BEE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The appointing authority may not extend the noncompetitive appointment eligibility under subsection (b) to any volunteer who chooses to be subject to early termination.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HCE9D9BDF8A7D42819D110630918D3550"><enum>9.</enum><header>Comprehensive illegal drug use policy with respect to Peace Corps volunteers</header> <subsection id="H0A546640982A434DB93632236642D4D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 8I (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507i">22 U.S.C. 2507i</external-xref>) the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block id="H91BF77E6503C4C5189C49B23216BF939" style="OLC" act-name="">
<section id="H65B4474C39AF4C2894CFAE10258055C3"><enum>8J.</enum><header>Comprehensive illegal drug use policy with respect to Peace Corps volunteers</header>
<subsection id="HC8965FAD47184F02BC9E03F42BC38E2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall develop and implement a comprehensive drug use policy with respect to Peace Corps volunteers. The policy shall—</text> <paragraph id="H02F6719870D3407A902AC5CD73969916"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a zero tolerance policy regarding volunteer or trainee involvement with illegal drugs; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H102E53F6773D40A8994AC80745AADDBB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require that every case of volunteer or trainee illegal drug involvement be brought immediately to the attention of relevant Peace Corps leadership, including the Director, and be reported expeditiously by the Peace Corps to the Office of the Inspector General.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H32B6DB5B6CCD48C09A587AD631C3A8B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the policy described in subsection (a), the Director may consult with and incorporate, as appropriate, the recommendations and views of experts in the field of substance abuse, and shall consult with the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HDEFA9D7FD542490D93B40C9790449E5C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the illegal drug use policy required to be developed and implemented under section 8J of the Peace Corps Act, as added by subsection (a). </text></subsection></section> <section id="HE7155BD9F3E64F85BF6FFDA2C6C7A982"><enum>10.</enum><header>Protection of Peace Corps volunteers against reprisal or retaliation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8G of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507g">22 U.S.C. 2507g</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H651DBFBC48C845C2B5347DFEBC282D17">
<subsection id="HA6090E35A0D24D4D9ECBC567E8C0DFCB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prohibition against reprisal or retaliation</header>
<paragraph id="H75903899B19045A491E9CDE5AABFBBB5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H0D682692718C43E6A0179DD91180F632"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered official or office</header><text>The term <term>covered official or office</term> means—</text>
<clause id="H83DD9A13D0594F9E979B772ACCEEEEFB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any Peace Corps employee, including an employee of the Office of Inspector General;</text></clause> <clause id="H0E06B8A9441C4CFA8A513C5855135847"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a Member of Congress or a designated representative of a committee of Congress;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6C7FB452867D46C19BEFA9159696030E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an Inspector General (other than the Inspector General for the Peace Corps);</text></clause> <clause id="H84DF97F7534843BBB6F4C5EBD7C9F792"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Government Accountability Office;</text></clause>
<clause id="H54FE3BAFC8B4417793448218100578AC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any authorized official of the Department of Justice or other Federal law enforcement agency; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC9721A3EA4CD4436A415A797B37F0FDA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a United States court, including any Federal grand jury. </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC4D81D9E32B24119A977B026D5F8B945"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relief</header><text>The term <term>relief</term> includes all affirmative relief necessary to make a volunteer whole, including monetary compensation, equitable relief, compensatory damages, and attorney fees and costs. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC452702CC68C4EFBAFEA0754C65B2268"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reprisal or retaliation</header><text>The term <term>reprisal or retaliation</term> means taking, threatening to take, or initiating adverse administrative action against a volunteer because the volunteer made a report described in subsection (a) or otherwise disclosed to a covered official or office any information pertaining to waste, fraud, abuse of authority, misconduct, mismanagement, violations of law, or a significant threat to health and safety, if the activity or occurrence complained of is based upon the reasonable belief of the volunteer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBD3C277F5D32497D9648D0813C9015D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps shall take all reasonable measures, including through the development and implementation of a comprehensive policy, to prevent and address reprisal or retaliation against a volunteer by any Peace Corps officer or employee, or any other person with supervisory authority over the volunteer during the volunteer’s period of service.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D23FB533FA24635AF554886C608C5E0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting and investigation; relief</header> <subparagraph id="HA635B383A6FB44DD95A73A009E74C1B9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A volunteer may report a complaint or allegation of reprisal or retaliation—</text>
<clause id="H1E52F7B0924C4EBEA5546FF1F9A5E1AD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>directly to the Inspector General of the Peace Corps, who may conduct such investigations and make such recommendations with respect to the complaint or allegation as the Inspector General considers appropriate; and</text></clause> <clause id="HAD476AB954C9481FB14B8C035EF9495F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through other channels provided by the Peace Corps, including through the process for confidential reporting implemented pursuant to subsection (a).</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H678CA6B9A73E4195BC736798CDE1C949"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relief</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps—</text> <clause id="H25296E0212B94D28960B144576DAF556"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may order any relief for an affirmative finding of a proposed or final resolution of a complaint or allegation of reprisal or retaliation in accordance with policies, rules, and procedures of the Peace Corps; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H2745DFB1F659431D823ACE6402BDB841"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall ensure that such relief is promptly provided to the volunteer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H255A17744C544076BF88A052304D61F0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appeal</header> <subparagraph id="HC0153E49DB3E441CB635D1ED14FA8F7B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A volunteer may submit an appeal to the Director of the Peace Corps of any proposed or final resolution of a complaint or allegation of reprisal or retaliation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4FB0E4A66FB9436E9946CAB0AD3672BD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph may be construed to affect any other right of recourse a volunteer may have under any other provision of law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA3C352B657A4A0BB4B22B96F8257EAD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Notification of rights and remedies</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps shall ensure that volunteers are informed in writing of the rights and remedies provided under this section.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H319ED39FAB154D5FAACE5F20FDB86065"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Dispute mediation</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps shall offer the opportunity for volunteers to resolve disputes concerning a complaint or allegation of reprisal or retaliation through mediation in accordance with procedures developed by the Peace Corps.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2F3B35171E4402B9FDCA6C9C978C5C3"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Volunteer cooperation</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps may take such disciplinary or other administrative action, including termination of service, with respect to a volunteer who unreasonably refuses to cooperate with an investigation into a compliant or allegation of reprisal or retaliation conducted by the Inspector General of the Peace Corps.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H49379447B946444897110A042CE27C7D"><enum>11.</enum><header>Peace Corps National Advisory Council</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 12 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2511">22 U.S.C. 2511</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HFBD29FB451E34BAF8C7819994FBC65D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6949D693C77A42CBB704B1B08CA05F4A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>(subject to subsection (d)(1)) conduct on-site inspections, and make examinations, of the activities of the Peace Corps in the United States and in other countries in order to</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4BB71E19310B4D2ABB886B65C2C690E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1F95DCB0855D4090B65D13B59ED0FA1B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (D) as subparagraph (G); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H37B6D4B8A88944E8B776411400CB82C8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6A4671CA13114770BD276FADD5E6D2BD">
<subparagraph id="HD6723087756041AAA85A03D25B85042E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>make recommendations for utilizing the expertise of returned Peace Corps volunteers in fulfilling the goals of the Peace Corps;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6A17A54032CB4620BC59D1CBF60A2725"><enum>(E)</enum><text>make recommendations on strengthening diversity, equity, inclusion, and accessibility principles in the workforce and daily work of the Peace Corps, including by—</text>
<clause id="HF575F8496A1F461D8D5F1D5C6914437B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>increasing the recruitment of volunteers from diverse backgrounds and better supporting such volunteers during their training and enrollment in the Peace Corps;</text></clause> <clause id="H7323B0C04DD54EF6BC17D3F9F7E3F895"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>increasing and sustaining a diverse and inclusive workforce through data collection, anti-harassment and anti-discrimination measures, recruitment, retention, professional development, and promotion and leadership initiatives that also consider the work and roles of contractors;</text></clause>
<clause id="H735FF072144E46959480CC813EEC0375"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensuring that advisory committees and boards represent the diversity of the agency; and</text></clause> <clause id="H693282B5EF564B5586B69A79AB42CB08"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>increasing opportunities in operations, programming, and procurement through work with partners and communities that are underrepresented or traditionally marginalized;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2A28E61FDE804C3B935C6E2585F2B0A8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>make recommendations to reduce any financial barriers to application, training, or enrollment in the Peace Corps, including medical expenses and other out-of-pocket costs; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0EAE40C0814E4ADE971DE3E3E333B5E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by amending paragraph (2) to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H154CC2EAB853469EBFFC3CF8A216DE8E">
<paragraph id="HC64F1729DF2E4802A27CB7229BD7AE98" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7793BDA286C94552B7B92F221FA0969D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Council shall be composed of 7 members who are United States citizens and are not being paid as officers or employees of the Peace Corps or of any other United States Government entity.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="H661B2E058A40433AA5D70F6264F9E6A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Of the 7 members of the Council—</text>
<clause id="HBA68404180C3447DA8FD8595C7D40FEE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>1 member shall be appointed by the President;</text></clause> <clause id="HD4A1079EB3D94DC8BD9F6503C21C58DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>3 members shall be appointed by the President pro tempore of the Senate, of which—</text>
<subclause id="H7C22E5B0FA0E41758B49163D8E8B98FF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>2 members shall be appointed upon the recommendation of the leader in the Senate of the political party that is not the political party of the President;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H1EC8E5C7583E4545B4DC74DF1BA02D64"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 member shall be appointed upon the recommendation of the leader in the Senate of the political party of the President; and </text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB51C70432F894E1C8A795E4AFCF4B478"><enum>(III)</enum><text>at least 2 members shall be former Peace Corps volunteers; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8DEBD97CDC594CC5B994D2AD27FD28B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>3 members shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives, of which—</text>
<subclause id="H5E424009C90743EBB5AEA2AEC1F572BC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>2 members shall be appointed upon the recommendation of the leader in the House of Representatives of the political party that is not the political party of the President;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H263D49D562ED4B53839594476963D077"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 member shall be appointed upon the recommendation of the leader in the House of Representatives of the political party of the President; and </text></subclause>
<subclause id="H2F02CF02B95D4B009AFA1BCF7B314797"><enum>(III)</enum><text>at least 2 members shall be former Peace Corps volunteers.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC2DA61F534B450CAD9DF09FE69DBC6F" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Council members shall be appointed to 2-year terms. No member of the Council may serve for more than 2 consecutive 2-year terms.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="H914B53E539094C65978E280E5A3AAEAD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Not later than 30 days after any vacancy occurs on the Council, the Director shall appoint an individual to fill such vacancy. Any Council member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the member’s predecessor was appointed—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BFA89180BDB496B905D99BCE2517392"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be appointed for the remainder of such term; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4654A181A401447E8C809C50D87FD8F3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may only serve on the Council for 1 additional 2-year term. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="HCD0EBC5A6EC44E0FAE6A0F9F15D24FED"><enum>(E)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H135A25C08F4C455592DA082D9AA9DB01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), Council members shall not be subject to laws relating to Federal employment, including laws relating to hours of work, rates of compensation, leave, unemployment compensation, and Federal employee benefits. </text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="HCF4E89D5E1F24C749160021AE8304220"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Notwithstanding clause (i), Council members shall be deemed to be Federal employees for purposes of—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC04DDA208A14133A4E77BF5FA58C415"><enum>(I)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/81">chapter 81</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code (relating to compensation for work-related injuries);</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H096ABB6D0CFC44699F96267051FAE3F6"><enum>(II)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code (relating to conflicts of interest);</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA9F9F3A8F7134243A0E77C2F0069DFF3"><enum>(III)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code (relating to tort claims); and</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1774ABA7F972441783CBF06E4DC8114F"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>section 3721 of title 31 (relating to claims for damage to, or loss of, personal property incident to service).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="HACE6B0DE9912458D8D50F0BD477D76E6"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Council members shall serve at the pleasure of the Director. The Council may remove a member from the Council by a vote of 5 members if the Council determines that such member—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCBA908FD6DEF46B2BD9A31675256EECC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>committed malfeasance in office;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26DBD7E4309740FEB90A0010A4029294"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>persistently neglected, or was unable to successfully discharge, his or her duties on the Council; or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17C89E9A3A9B4AFB8AF23F5365559649"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>committed an offense involving moral turpitude.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H69BAC8CB8A1B474188A7579CAA485317"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (g)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H92D37DD95655496396462F5DB3A7D9F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and at its first regular meeting in each calendar year thereafter</quote> and inserting <quote>at its first meeting each subsequent calendar year</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H085A91018D6949CAB260FD23661CE961"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Chair and Vice Chair shall each serve in such capacity for a period not to exceed 2 years. The Director may renew the term of members appointed as Chair and Vice Chair under this subsection.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8FBCF1F03ED3410A87F8C08035396415"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (h), by amending paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB56BFF6E147449CCA16FDE1CFA2391A1"> <paragraph id="HE5E7E3240AB6466CBCBE5868AA5BED9A" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Council shall hold 1 regular meeting per quarter of each calendar year at a date and time to be determined by the Chair of the Council or at the call of the Director.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H227043A848CA411E821CE7EB34E2A1B5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F18E6566D94428CB60737DCA25C5D76"> <subsection id="HA1F1EB3532C74E2A8D12DFB31EE7E58C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Independence of Inspector General</header><text>None of the activities or functions of the Council authorized under subsection (b)(2) may undermine the independence or supersede the duties of the Inspector General of the Peace Corps.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA9D93B3718444B1FB4F846382872AFD2"><enum>12.</enum><header>Memorandum of Agreement with Bureau of Diplomatic Security of the Department of State</header>
<subsection id="HB7401504A9FA43398AC0629115272356"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Quinquennial review and update</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and at least once every 5 years, the Director of the Peace Corps and the Assistant Secretary of State for Diplomatic Security shall—</text> <paragraph id="HF710889450D24AACBB4E2A7B1DC9AB94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review the Memorandum of Agreement between the Bureau of Diplomatic Security of the Department of State and the Peace Corps regarding security support and protection of Peace Corps volunteers, and staff members abroad; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H33A256471980460A827A5C207F3D765C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>update such Memorandum of Agreement, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2C512A0005264577AA953048C515907B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification</header> <paragraph id="HDF1551B117234B34AEC76CF9DDF859CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Peace Corps and the Assistant Secretary of State for Diplomatic Security shall jointly submit any update to the Memorandum of Agreement under subsection (a) to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7DB2C14D516C400E99172909B352B586"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H31774057E05A4D958334F670CCCECA0B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4E8B9B3DCFB74FCD95A6F548B31A04D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing of notification</header><text>Each written notification submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) shall be submitted not later than 30 days before the update referred to in such paragraph takes effect.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H40699B800BDE44139F117F108F926B67"><enum>13.</enum><header>Clarification regarding eligibility of United States nationals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H69F52532C51149CEAEB16F67EC7D5576"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 7(a)(5) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2506">22 U.S.C. 2506(a)(5)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>United States citizens</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>United States nationals of American Samoa and citizens of the United States</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H441E1FB845594E4895087B3C2D323DA2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 8(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507">22 U.S.C. 2507(b)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>United States nationals of American Samoa and</quote> after <quote>training for</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF5483634051D4A2AA87CF1BF17A6A34D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 10(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2509">22 U.S.C. 2509(b)</external-xref>), striking <quote>any person not a citizen or resident of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>any person who is not a United States national of American Samoa nor a citizen or resident of the United States</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDEEBE20DA6924A7F88DB46790656A621"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 12(g) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2511">22 U.S.C. 2511(g)</external-xref>, by inserting <quote>United States nationals of American Samoa or</quote> after <quote>who are</quote>.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HC8F88889E90A417BA0A67569905CCA07"><enum>14.</enum><header>Sexual Assault Advisory Council</header>
<subsection id="H43B9D1E754E043D0BCD9238A545A9781"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report and extension of the sexual assault advisory council</header><text>Section 8D of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507d">22 U.S.C. 2507d</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HADE4037A4C864B83AF27B00F5E64F0B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending subsection (d) to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F45ECA188214B718E957F78A0835DAB">
<subsection id="H0CF98C3BFA504AE4B74B0FCD145ECA9C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>On an annual basis through the date specified in subsection (g), the Council shall submit a report to the Director of the Peace Corps, the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>, the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name>, the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>, and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name> that describes its findings based on the reviews conducted pursuant to subsection (c) and includes relevant recommendations. Each such report shall be made publicly available.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD14E007BEFC44259FEE4DBFFA84F611"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (g), by striking <quote>October 1, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>October 1, 2028</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H5D436BF5252E4B5FA87ADAA9CAC59122"><enum>15.</enum><header>Suspension without pay</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7 of the Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2506">22 U.S.C. 2506</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subsection (a) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89E93300D4874EF6A9846F7AC2A45AB4"> <subsection id="H3B1A4F3A89D948A4B969211AA59C61A0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Suspension without pay</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4B390C0D35A94B0C97AC90EA20BF301F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Peace Corps may suspend (without pay) any employee appointed or assigned under this section if the Director has determined that the employee engaged in serious misconduct that could impact the efficiency of the service and could lead to removal for cause.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCC21238DC0C0421EA27310904CA98B98" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any employee for whom a suspension without pay is proposed under this subsection shall be entitled to—</text> <subparagraph id="H9F76C78B9FED4A49BEDF4F6293FF3371"><enum>(A)</enum><text>written notice stating the specific reasons for such proposed suspension;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H34629F2B70E14900BB9833086E76736C"><enum>(B)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1C221051D12E48FC883F920506E377BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>up to 15 days to respond orally or in writing to such proposed suspension if the employee is assigned in the United States; or</text></clause> <clause indent="up1" id="H4B36D2964F8C4D8299D0CC1A56498614"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>up to 30 days to respond orally or in writing to such proposed suspension if the employee is assigned outside of the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H39B6FAA3553F49958CEE07C942D9F938"><enum>(C)</enum><text>representation by an attorney or other representative, at the employee’s own expense;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H076758078F974F7FABE83BCA09205B18"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a written decision, including the specific reasons for such decision, as soon as practicable;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H63229DACAF6C4B25AB3461B5B51E1852"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a process through which the employee may submit an appeal to the Director of the Peace Corps not later than 10 business days after the issuance of a written decision; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6B715DECA92D4569BDED0C9196C4EEA7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a final decision personally rendered by the Director of the Peace Corps not later than 30 days after the receipt of such appeal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph indent="up1" id="HAF242A2F315B4C258D18D6AC72EEC441"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a final decision under paragraph (2)(F) shall be final and not subject to further review.</text></paragraph> <paragraph indent="up1" id="H19790A0C785643C89A763AF4956B324B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>If the Director fails to establish misconduct by an employee under paragraph (1) and no disciplinary action is taken against such employee based upon the alleged grounds for the suspension, the employee shall be entitled to reinstatement, back pay, full benefits, and reimbursement of attorney fees of up to $20,000.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H5251C076ADE34FCE9132BCDEC3DF4F5B"><enum>16.</enum><header>Oceania Peace Corps partnerships</header>
<subsection id="H688E981F3B544E93966F693275049667"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Peace Corps shall submit to Congress a report on strategies to reasonably and safely expand the number of Peace Corps volunteers in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania, with the goals of—</text> <paragraph id="H4273E51C68994BB8A46F6F7EC4DAA690"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expanding the presence of the Peace Corps to all currently feasible locations in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H98E8283676A44805AD8EE18BBA37087E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>working with regional and international partners of the United States to expand the presence of Peace Corps volunteers in low-income communities in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania in support of climate resilience initiatives.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H453C5A8E328445D58ECDCF9EF1DC33E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H2C9220A3F31C4341A9BBB447BFEF60C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assess the factors contributing to the current absence of the Peace Corps and its volunteers in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H987575553D624736979A8763AC5D7144"><enum>(2)</enum><text>examine potential remedies that include working with United States Government agencies and regional governments, including Governments of United States allies—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD8CE3E3CA8AC4B558AB6CE76ABDD2F42"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to increase the health infrastructure and medical evacuation capabilities of the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania to better support the safety of Peace Corps volunteers while in those countries;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83D7C963964D4846914A7E9F8BA7341F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to address physical safety concerns that have decreased the ability of the Peace Corps to operate in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H007823DF78584568ABCA1DBE554395C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to increase transportation infrastructure in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania to better support the travel of Peace Corps volunteers and their access to necessary facilities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA51F94D2F3744DE85F6969E62D8EAE7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>evaluate the potential to expand the deployment of Peace Corps Response volunteers to help the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania address social, economic, and development needs of their communities that require specific professional expertise; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0DEB1DDAB4644984937A4BD12F3AC13C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>explore potential new operational models to address safety and security needs of Peace Corps volunteers in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HE2799FC3A5DF485BBB8CA3B19CD12160"><enum>(A)</enum><text>changes to volunteer deployment durations; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H987C1D4480B4494BB38508E399183DA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>scheduled redeployment of volunteers to regional or United States-based healthcare facilities for routine physical and behavioral health evaluation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H67AEF07786C648B7BA72A7C3B72826E5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Volunteers in low-Income oceania communities</header> <paragraph id="H1B832F334E024185974B946941D27E2F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In examining the potential to expand the presence of Peace Corps volunteers in low-income communities in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania under subsection (a)(2), the Director of the Peace Corps shall consider the development of initiatives described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4F7682368B684F7E93246CFBE98B0C8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initiatives described</header><text>Initiatives described in this paragraph are volunteer initiatives that help the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania address social, economic, and development needs of their communities, including by—</text> <subparagraph id="H40D6F169257D47EDA75435D154B23B33"><enum>(A)</enum><text>addressing, through appropriate resilience-based interventions, the vulnerability that communities in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania face as result of extreme weather, severe environmental change, and other climate related trends; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCAF28F4675C546E58257DE2639CE9684"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving, through smart infrastructure principles, access to transportation and connectivity infrastructure that will help address the economic and social challenges that communities in the Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania confront as a result of poor or nonexistent infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF14DF8D18684491BBC54618102DAC17E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania defined</header><text>The term <term>Indo-Pacific countries of Oceania</term> means Fiji, Kiribati, Republic of the Marshall Islands, Micronesia, Nauru, Palau, Papua New Guinea, Samoa, Solomon Islands, Tonga, Tuvalu, and Vanuatu. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="H4E0AA9FE796F48BE81683DD63F6F613B"><enum>17.</enum><header>Reports</header>
<subsection id="H72531A86CAA04C1498F70D105762FA9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on mental health evaluation standards</header>
<paragraph id="H4343B5AC252B416BAD61B3EF5DE4F448"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Peace Corps shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the guidelines and standards used to evaluate the mental health of Peace Corps applicants prior to service. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C42CAF5807A4619B95D13C96A9BD544"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall include the following elements:</text>
<subparagraph id="H090F3F1B51C748F39CAF6C6DE6AA0827"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A detailed description of mental health screening guidelines and evaluation standards used by the Peace Corps to determine medical eligibility of applicants for service, including a description of the most common mental health conditions of applicants.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE88FFA58E364D46AD72851563BEC5E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Specific standards in the mental health screening process that could lead to an applicant’s disqualification from service, and a description of how these determinations are made.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD9C30D0CF1334741A2FA288C5314E8BC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of any expedited mental health clearance process for severe or recent symptom presentation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC1DDDE89DB894EAE842696EE614ED08F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of periods of stability related to certain mental health conditions and symptoms recommended prior to an applicant’s clearance to serve.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAA20B6C62F5E41C5BDED1B075E7281DB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An assessment of the impact of updated mental health evaluation guidance, including a comparison of mental health related volunteer medevacs in years before and after updated guidelines were implemented.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2AB2C250BAD4D039D1599413693C593"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A review of these screening guidelines, conducted by a panel of certified and qualified medical professionals in the United States, that evaluates these standards based on scientific evidence and mental health research and proposes relevant updates or additions to current guidance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H479A9D2E920F4CF2BDC8FF81986FAA62"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on volunteer medical evacuations</header>
<paragraph id="HD6B5C2DA8B0548CE926AAB2B8FEAF089"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the first May 1 occurring after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for five years, the Director of the Peace Corps shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on volunteer medical and mental health evacuations. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H91C7BAED3FDF446E945D9965A1A532CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall include the following elements: </text>
<subparagraph id="H049D65F5DABA40E79D7B8646C5E9EBFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of Peace Corps volunteer medical and mental health evacuations during the previous year.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2A71677A04D047819854F4E52624D10D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A breakdown of these evacuations into medical and mental health evacuation categories.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCA5917FF4CEB4AD589EB5AC76199DA86"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The estimated cost of these evacuations for each year, including a breakdown of costs between medical and mental health evacuation categories. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HEAD55B7AA10C41A3BA96F6BE3ED70012"><enum>18.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H3EE6741C1BEE45978228E396E9CE72F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending section 1 to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05D6274834E34CB88C26F095A8CB7D6B"> <section section-type="section-one" id="H4397942C8B334277886E4347191FDBBE"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> <subsection id="H9313B35EA1474B448E962AF518DAEF94"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Peace Corps Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B9A8062AA2C4039917092FA79BC8D59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> <toc> <toc-entry level="title">TITLE I—The Peace Corps</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section" idref="H4397942C8B334277886E4347191FDBBE">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 2. Declaration of purpose.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 2A. Peace Corps as an independent agency.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 3. Authorization.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4. Director of the Peace Corps and delegation of functions.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 5. Peace Corps volunteers.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 5A. Health care for volunteers at Peace Corps posts.</toc-entry> <toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 5B. Codification of Executive orders relating to noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers.</toc-entry> <toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 5C. Extension of period of existing noncompetitive eligibility Federal hiring status for returning volunteers.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 6. Peace Corps volunteer leaders.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 7. Peace Corps employees.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8. Volunteer training.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8A. Sexual assault risk-reduction and response training.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8B. Sexual assault policy.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8C. Office of Victim Advocacy.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8D. Establishment of Sexual Assault Advisory Council.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8E. Volunteer feedback and Peace Corps review.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8F. Establishment of a policy on stalking.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8G. Establishment of a confidentiality protection policy.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8H. Removal and assessment and evaluation.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8I. Reporting requirements.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 8J. Comprehensive illegal drug use policy with respect to Peace Corps volunteers.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 9. Participation of foreign nationals.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 10. General powers and authorities.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 11. Reports.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 12. Peace Corps National Advisory Council.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 13. Experts and consultants.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 14. Detail of personnel to foreign governments and international organizations.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 15. Utilization of funds.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 16. Foreign Currency Fluctuations Account.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 17. Use of foreign currencies.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 18. Activities promoting Americans’ understanding of other peoples.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 19. Exclusive right to seal and name.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 22. Security investigations.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 23. Universal Military Training and Service Act.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 24. Foreign language proficiency.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 25. Nonpartisan appointments.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 26. Definitions.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 27. Construction.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 28. Effective date.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="title">TITLE II—Amendment of Internal Revenue Code and Social Security Act</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="title">TITLE III—Encouragement of voluntary service programs</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 301.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H52FAB0CC915E45B9A0D7B67A2AB1E2EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 2(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2501">22 U.S.C. 2501(a)</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H66DD4AF9A0174F9989FDB223A4515DF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>help the peoples</quote> and inserting <quote>partner with the peoples</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85ABEBAF158842088E09B79584545D58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>manpower</quote> and inserting <quote>individuals</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H34F9B9E23D79473392FC105FE133C216"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 3 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2502">22 U.S.C. 2502</external-xref>), in subsection (e), as redesignated, by striking <quote>disabled people</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>people with disabilities</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2FF043F9992421C89942B49CA0A09E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 4(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2503">22 U.S.C. 2503(b)</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H623BA1D25285432997C80B7A01BF26DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>him</quote> and inserting <quote>the President</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5E592FD836343ED9E3E63205A0F29DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the Director</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE4F24E5BF9B4425396C118240AA0664A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>of his subordinates</quote> and all that follows through <quote>functions.</quote> and inserting <quote>subordinate of the Director the authority to perform any such function.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDADC909E4E57489BA596583E13E3195E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 5 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2504">22 U.S.C. 2504</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCBBA7E6C36414A809C7D2001F2335011"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>: <italic>Provided, however,</italic></quote> and all that follows through <quote>the amount</quote> and inserting <quote>. Under such circumstances as the President may determine, the accrued readjustment allowance, or any part thereof, may be paid to the volunteer, members of the volunteer’s family, or others, during the period of the volunteer’s service, or prior to the volunteer’s return to the United States. In the event of the volunteer's death during the period of his service, the amount</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA0DDBBD0BFC9411F81BEFFFEB4406DDD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (o) by striking <quote>the date of his departure</quote> and all that follows and inserting <quote>the date of the volunteer’s departure from the volunteer’s place of residence to enter training until not later than 3 months after the termination of the volunteer’s service.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H09CEB9C60E954894A22379ECBE53BCC5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 6(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2505">22 U.S.C. 2505(3)</external-xref>), by striking by striking <quote>he may determine</quote> and inserting <quote>the President may determine</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H537F12F1E3C24F17B2BB93EE6DB14132"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in section 7 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2506">22 U.S.C. 2506</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7164F84EC4E340F296AB2EF3101E6C0F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by moving paragraphs (7) and (8) 2 ems to the left; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A0B7EF35D2B4E27ACC44A1F9BAF8FD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b), as redesignated, by striking <quote>in his discretion</quote> and inserting <quote>in the President’s discretion</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H247F3EB0513C4DC881CF5453A4FDB9F4"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in section 8A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507a">22 U.S.C. 2507a</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HDF3E298C232F4E429B4F13057E4169B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>his or her</quote> and inserting <quote>the volunteer’s</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HD48F8F47C75549A986B4BF7863C8F897"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(2), by inserting <quote>the</quote> before <quote>information</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5D02733AE86040A7B117E6C72A8D2BBE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text>
<clause commented="no" id="H9697434D61B34E899E28400F41F12E4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>his or her</quote> each place such phrase appears and inserting <quote>the volunteer’s</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HA11AB10AE4874ECD8384CB4559071907"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(A), by striking <quote>his or her</quote> and inserting <quote>the person’s</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE7F83DFD56D9408998BEA6829BE3E75B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in section 8C(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507c">22 U.S.C. 2507c(a)</external-xref>), in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Victims</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Victim</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33C7D1F5BD7C4516853E8EC28C874A0D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in section 8E (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2507e">22 U.S.C. 2507e</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H2B7199E502FC450996B0748C3DFF5B51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>subsection (c),,</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (c),</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5D10C881BF7F4D83BE7AF6E36C015C20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)(F), by striking <quote>Peace Corp’s mission</quote> and inserting <quote>Peace Corps’ mission</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H302AFC4121644C2E8775BF6E29D99194"><enum>(11)</enum><text>in section 9 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2508">22 U.S.C. 2508</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="HF1B76EC30BBE46DBAAD96F5929A6479E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>under which he was admitted or who fails to depart from the United States at the expiration of the time for which he was admitted</quote> and inserting <quote>under which such person was admitted or who fails to depart from the United States at the expiration of the period for which such person was admitted</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEA0C8B94832442D588301A4E2C99BD90"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Act proceedings</quote> and inserting <quote>Act. Removal proceedings</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C4EF34436534D67846DC9993C47F4A1"><enum>(12)</enum><text>in section 10 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2509">22 U.S.C. 2509</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF807EF69CAD5457DB22CE5F17809D3B7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), by striking <quote>he may prescribe</quote> and inserting <quote>the President may prescribe</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB20CE3B8323043C2A2384FB95CE5C7A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d), by striking <quote>section 3709 of the Revised Statutes of the United States, as amended, section 302 of the Federal Property and Administrative Services Act of 1949</quote>; and by inserting <quote>sections 3101(a), 3101(c), 3104, 3106, 3301(b)(2), and 6101 of title 41, United States Code</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA8573D1527384E5F826CE628D5FE1FE3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (j), by striking <quote>of this section.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA6C34ED1386A4398A1EF55A24036AC45"><enum>(13)</enum><text>in section 12(d)(1)(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2511">22 U.S.C. 2511(d)(1)(b)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>his or her</quote> and inserting <quote>the member’s</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57E1221C192B41F4AC387C749CF69EC4"><enum>(14)</enum><text>in section 14 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2513">22 U.S.C. 2513</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H53127553277B45C2A6580FBC55576C60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>his agency</quote> and inserting <quote>such agency</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3BD8BC9A59C841E99CF5E1D700BFFCDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <clause id="H7D2C2830D26A4DC5B4EA9010A4CCBAAA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>his allowance</quote> and inserting <quote>the</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HBF5075F7DAB046DA8362C4B3F873D6D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>he</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF382D8B8CA44EBFBEE4287040CBDCDD"><enum>(15)</enum><text>in section 15 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2514">22 U.S.C. 2514</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1837891B9B0945F59B4FC61092A35DFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>that Act</quote> and inserting <quote>that subchapter</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8A6EB888B5314E27B9750878F5CF75A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(7), by striking <quote>his designee</quote> and inserting <quote>the Director’s designee</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4340D06AEEEE452085D5ABC2EE6AFAA0"><enum>(16)</enum><text>in section 19(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2518">22 U.S.C. 2518(a)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>he shall determine</quote> and inserting <quote>the President shall determine</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA05EA30C8A34BD793DC300B00BAA4B3"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 23 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2520">22 U.S.C. 2520</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1713CF596DA04405BEFF9C502A4EF84B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">Universal Military Training and Service</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">Military Selective Service</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC74F78C1966F4C06A3D1B47771C104CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Universal Military Training and Service Act</quote> and inserting <quote>Military Selective Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3801">50 U.S.C. 3801 et seq.</external-xref>)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H45DF7D7323DF468F82647EB042F13D91"><enum>(18)</enum><text>in section 24—</text> <subparagraph id="HD0DF266EFCBC4D60B9025D96204798A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>he</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>the volunteer</quote>; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H374FA001108D4881BA2D232B521CA42E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>his</quote> and inserting <quote>the volunteer’s</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21D332DA9E9044499924290B6F0E1928"><enum>(19)</enum><text>in section 26—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC201CFD15E05426D8789D0D45DA0ACF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2) through (9) as paragraphs (3) through (10), respectively;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H22D23289D9F447508B887C4FC88A33B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9975C9F1F37842518A8987CEEE7B3FE4">
<paragraph id="HA28E4812BDDC4D57BE142D32CE5C7A51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Peace Corps.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5A436758BC144FB9AAFD1D16710D9867"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), as redesignated, by striking <quote>he or she</quote> and inserting <quote>the medical officer</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB47FEDA5BDBB40F1B6D8847481ED249F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), as redesignated, by striking <quote>5(m)</quote> and inserting <quote>5(n)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE881AF677FD14F5FB3CC69F372595EC1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), as redesignated—</text>
<clause id="H8BB0C2BC7D5D462597E686F168545870"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i) and (ii) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1EF3C9E5EED4454AAA6AB9EE4D924CF6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), as redesignated, by striking <quote>section 5(f)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 5(e)</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9B56FE88C71B416990CB9F6C162A2151" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(20)</enum><text>in section 301(a), by striking <quote>manpower</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>individuals</quote>. </text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

