<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5EE29FF190E34ACCBA1DBA501E91BE72" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2984 IH: Clarifying Law Around Insurance of Marijuana Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2984</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To create a safe harbor for insurers engaging in the business of insurance in connection with a cannabis-related legitimate business, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9F8DB08C010247278F21B44F578F3579" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3257BFCC74C94A3180D038120B083F5C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clarifying Law Around Insurance of Marijuana Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CLAIM Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5AA6FA05F84D4D05B536D95C33958B9F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Safe harbor for insurers and the business of insurance</header> <subsection id="H2E6DDB3B421D4397ADD55801C5A4E9C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H14F46E403E1F406E915DA3B66AACAF3F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cannabis</header><text>The term <term>cannabis</term> has the meaning given the term <term>marihuana</term> in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1AB8E23C731E40E39A12A202990982E2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cannabis product</header><text>The term <term>cannabis product</term> means any article which contains cannabis, including an article which is a concentrate, an edible, a tincture, a cannabis-infused product, or a topical.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD0F83B64E22E49C98A3BCD5E3CBCE329"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cannabis-related legitimate business</header><text>The term <term>cannabis-related legitimate business</term> means a manufacturer, producer, or any person or company that—</text> <subparagraph id="H34CA35E797D74AF78B681F37C1B8D385"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engages in any activity described in subparagraph (B) pursuant to a law established by a State or a political subdivision of a State, as determined by such State or political subdivision; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDAD8D1D8FCCE4DE79278BD393F81F245"><enum>(B)</enum><text>participates in any business or organized activity that involves handling cannabis or cannabis products, including cultivating, producing, manufacturing, selling, transporting, displaying, dispensing, distributing, or purchasing cannabis or cannabis products.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8E9FE99F17C4835BA1C1A71801AF6E2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="H92DE15721FAA4D878253A10491A7B8F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term <term>Executive agency</term> in section 105 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H01A578BE63A74DC5ABA3637420B3C96B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a private attorney described in section 3002(1)(B) of title 28, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HABFD82BCE77446C39C0AD7E01313F697"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Financial service</header><text>The term <term>financial service</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="HBE21E9908A3F4E04B5DD5892E98E85E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a financial product or service, as defined in section 1002 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5481">12 U.S.C. 5481</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H619903445C874EB4BF79BFD2EAE87E6F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text> <clause id="H3456C5967A9F4E3089D9AD02527D1945"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the business of insurance;</text></clause>
<clause id="H61969F95159A421E8327FF971C513C1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether performed directly or indirectly, the authorizing, processing, clearing, settling, billing, transferring for deposit, transmitting, delivering, instructing to be delivered, reconciling, collecting, or otherwise effectuating or facilitating of payments or funds, where such payments or funds are made or transferred by any means, including by the use of credit cards, debit cards, other payment cards, or other access devices, accounts, original or substitute checks, or electronic funds transfers;</text></clause> <clause id="HB3A8B862EBF64F9698437E1E450D7DDA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">acting as a money transmitting business which directly or indirectly makes use of a depository institution in connection with effectuating or facilitating a payment for a cannabis-related legitimate business or service provider in compliance with section 5330 of title 31, United States Code, and any applicable State law; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HCE1F53FA0D18491B8C684DB96C2BA2F1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">acting as an armored car service for processing and depositing with a depository institution or a Federal reserve bank with respect to any monetary instruments (as defined under section 1956(c)(5) of title 18, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB913FA53F70B4B41A417F3987856E604"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Indian country</header><text>The term <term>Indian country</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4D02F3BDBBE3455AA04CB4D8C7383A20"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/479a">25 U.S.C. 479a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB722081810C44A768F06C7F7FE1D1B09"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Insurer</header><text>The term <term>insurer</term> has the meaning given the term in section 313(r) of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD4A29349A77546FE81FC51D7B3814F73"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Manufacturer</header><text>The term <term>manufacturer</term> means a person or company who manufactures, compounds, converts, processes, prepares, or packages cannabis or cannabis products.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79BCACE052264DAAB34356DB411E19FF"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Producer</header><text>The term <term>producer</term> means a person who plants, cultivates, harvests, or in any way facilitates the natural growth of cannabis.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCFF19D0522E24B3191E84A138330C1DA"><enum>(11)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF38B54218D7C477888588111DC69DAAE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Insurers</header><text>A Federal agency may not—</text>
<paragraph id="HF72C67B8896B4B72BD04B672DC159B24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prohibit, penalize, or otherwise discourage an insurer from engaging in the business of insurance in connection with—</text> <subparagraph id="H7AA2437531054B449E12E262ECD57EE8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a cannabis-related legitimate business; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC9F09028BE4C4C8896248A5CC3CD6571"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State, political subdivision of a State, or Indian Tribe that exercises jurisdiction over cannabis-related legitimate businesses;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEAFD01CFC8A645AE821EFC1844B62E76"><enum>(2)</enum><text>terminate, cancel or otherwise limit the policies of an insurer solely because the insurer has engaged in the business of insurance in connection with a cannabis-related legitimate business;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBF4E2E1A008B41578DFDF1C3CD2C4392"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommend, incentivize, or encourage an insurer not to engage in the business of insurance in connection with a policyholder, or downgrade or cancel the insurance and insurance services offered to a policyholder solely because—</text> <subparagraph id="HE2A52510F2DD451CB3009E6046EC7EA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the policyholder is—</text>
<clause id="H011DDDB1DBC24EF4B7852FA9612AF7E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a manufacturer or producer, or</text></clause> <clause id="H140F9D21A6F34496A8BEEA2B765DCC22"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the owner, operator, or employee of a cannabis-related legitimate business;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDCC338E6856A4D0EB455640A78EDB4B0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the policyholder later becomes an employee, owner, or operator of a cannabis-related legitimate business; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0620D951068E4F0EB0AAFDAB40796EFE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the insurer was not aware that the policyholder is an employee, owner, or operator of a cannabis-related legitimate business; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H94273E93533443858DE6DF968C709676"><enum>(4)</enum><text>take any adverse or corrective supervisory action on a policy to—</text> <subparagraph id="H38FBF2EC8BA740E6AB20337FEE40F223"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a cannabis-related legitimate business, solely because the owner or operator owns or operates a cannabis-related legitimate business;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H72F374281FAC4711BB473642393A5685"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an employee, owner, or operator of a cannabis-related legitimate business or service provider, solely because the employee, owner, or operator is employed by, owns, or operates a cannabis-related legitimate business, as applicable; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F52F5D477FF48509FAF63434D502641"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an owner or operator of real estate or equipment that is leased to a cannabis-related legitimate business, solely because the owner or operator of the real estate or equipment leased the equipment or real estate to a cannabis-related legitimate business, as applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFF0F3FE3B33B4555B66592D2DBFCEC02"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Protections under Federal law</header><text>With respect to engaging in the business of insurance within a State, political subdivision of a State, or Indian country that allows the cultivation, production, manufacture, sale, transportation, display, dispensing, distribution, or purchase of cannabis pursuant to a law or regulation of such State, political subdivision, or Indian Tribe that has jurisdiction over the Indian country, as applicable, an insurer that engages in the business of insurance with a cannabis-related legitimate business or service provider or who otherwise engages with a person in a transaction permissible under State law related to cannabis, and the officers, directors, and employees of that insurer may not be held liable pursuant to any Federal law or regulation—</text> <paragraph id="HAFE447EABE36478F90DC01678EFDC611"><enum>(1)</enum><text>solely for engaging in the business of insurance; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H83C52E2958E34E85B20478AED8E15EF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for further investing any income derived from such business of insurance.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H20B4FC8321C44A518CCB45043CA73E03"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H55C94336216443F9B74C515B8042D48C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require an insurer to engage in the business of insurance in connection with a cannabis-related legitimate business; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2DF767933D54FA2BAEB5D0594D997D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>interfere with the regulation of the business of insurance in accordance with the Act of March 9, 1945 (59 Stat. 33, chapter 20; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1011">15 U.S.C. 1011 et seq.</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>McCarran-Ferguson Act</quote>) and the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5301">12 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H119D71514A68482DABEE1EB45D3ED00F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>GAO study on diversity and inclusion</header>
<subsection id="HAC3CF77AA94E46C68B33902DA07D685B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall carry out a study on the barriers to marketplace entry, including in the licensing process, and the access to financial services for potential and existing minority-owned and women-owned cannabis-related legitimate businesses.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC5083163044D41E5A6C3344A117BFA40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Comptroller General shall issue a report to the Congress—</text>
<paragraph id="H1975483AFB764D11BCF09B1E0E910B2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>containing all findings and determinations made in carrying out the study required under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F93256FA0A04C169332F6084F00BC12"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">containing any regulatory or legislative recommendations for removing barriers to marketplace entry, including in the licensing process, and expanding access to financial services for potential and existing minority-owned and women-owned cannabis-related legitimate businesses.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

