<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC129E2374E8445DA91C6D37A966FC4EF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3957 IH: Providing for Unhoused People with Pets Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3957</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Agriculture to make grants to modify and upgrade structures to serve as interim and permanent housing to accommodate unhoused individuals with pets, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3E4FA4FEE5564D769FD33E2E953ECC17" style="OLC"><section id="H7879E34E8A4648A293A0C607DB1CC83F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providing for Unhoused People with Pets Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PUPP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA149AB4513404B29BD59F2C5BDF2DC13"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program for upgrading structures to serve as interim and permanent housing to accommodate unhoused individuals with pets</header><subsection id="HEB370AB412CA48639B5DF799F9729B94"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, acting in direct consultation with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, may carry out a program under this section to make grants to eligible entities for providing interim and permanent housing that accommodates homeless persons, and homeless families, who have pets.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC439FA0A7D304D71815EFDB4C406E964"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under this section may be used only for—</text><paragraph id="HF2ED8577B4CC4CC8B583F73C20175C6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>costs of acquiring, renovating, rehabilitating, re-purposing, retrofitting, or constructing a property to be used as interim or permanent housing that accommodates homeless persons, and homeless families, who have pets;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F4F2F6B364A4654839D7C5B3C911C3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>pet-related costs of operating such housing as provided in this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE75FAB0EC0D64DAEB247EBFB365BA1CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">costs of training staff and volunteers associated with such housing in basic pet care, including nutrition, behavioral training, and health maintenance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A150A2CC7074D1A83D1E95D7FD5A30E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Interim or permanent housing assisted with amounts from a grant under this Act shall comply with the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H604415C609534FF2A11EBD3733F3A0F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Services</header><subparagraph id="HF6D27C00862743209F9D59F150CB12C8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Supportive services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriate supportive services, including mental health, employment, substance use disorder, and wellness services, shall be made available to occupants of the housing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D4BCD6706164231BC3528B9CC6F06C2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Veterinary services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Basic veterinary care and behavioral support for pets, including spay and neuter, basic wellness examinations, vaccinations, dental care, heartworm treatment and prevention, flea and tick treatment and prevention, and basic medical procedures, shall be made available for pets of occupants of the housing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF009194951B46EDB92CC08DC02B893F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Location</header><text>Services required under this paragraph shall be made available on-site in such housing, except that services that cannot be furnished on-site may be made available off-site, but only if direct linkage to transportation services is made available to occupants to access such services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1049E5979D3E40AB921B3CCF8FFA037C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Animal housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The housing shall provide accommodations for pets of occupants of the housing that are appropriate for the layout and type of the interim or permanent housing, which may include crates and kennels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H340CB4C318954192A03DC7060AD6E4E8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The manager of the housing shall—</text><subparagraph id="HED20AEA1F2FA4401A4F43307D332070C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate with public services and law enforcement agencies to provide services and safety for the housing, as the Secretary shall require;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70D22C0607D04EFEA1F5011F90F7CBFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate with local veterinary service and animal care providers to provide care for pets that accompany occupants of the housing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0379670E504489DA84447891F0DC498"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in making occupancy available in the housing, coordinate with the administrative entity for the Continuum of Care under subtitle C of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11381">42 U.S.C. 11381 et seq.</external-xref>) for the area in which the housing is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H07FCE39309384571AE7CF840171F5F05"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications; plan</header><paragraph id="H081D188AE7F34CDAA29AA8EE61314D8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for eligible entities to submit applications for grants under this section and shall require such applications to include a plan under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14DFAE3BD214D2B82591BE803E038DB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Plan</header><text>A plan under this paragraph shall—</text><subparagraph id="HA116A7F615364254B58F6E6D6ABE8BD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify existing housing, shelters, or unused structures or land within the area served by the eligible entity submitting the application that will be used for providing the housing to be assisted under subsection (b) with amounts from a grant under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H825451112819446A8FE3E2A122F50C77"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify the extent of need, in the area of such housing, shelters, structures, or land identified, for interim or permanent housing for homeless persons with pets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6F863FF346449688722D6959B1DDBC5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify partnering veterinary service and animal care providers that will provide care for pets that accompany occupants of the housing and any partnering animal welfare organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9CC842118A9423094D8A9BEB77449AC"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include such assurances as the Secretary considers necessary to ensure that such housing will be provided using grant amounts, that such housing will accommodate homeless persons, and homeless families, who have pets, and that such housing will comply with the requirements under subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E5E6044058440F2926B4691686B48FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provide for targeted outreach to individuals experiencing homelessness within the area served by the eligible entity receiving a grant under this section to inform such individuals regarding the availability of the housing assisted with grant amounts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F8F068E45464A12991C568CEF72200B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>The Secretary shall select applications to be awarded such grants on a competitive basis, based on criteria that the Secretary shall establish.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H802D479EBE0348B5ABC2EF239CE37B0D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section for a fiscal year shall submit a report to the Secretary, not later than 90 days after the end of the fiscal year for which the grant was made, that shall include the following information:</text><paragraph id="HF2E0ED4AA0B44D38A8714A1DFED975DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the activities undertaken by the eligible entity using such grant amounts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61F86C8330F54DD186AB0A55F86FD953"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Identification of the costs of each of the services provided in connection with the housing assisted with such grant amounts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58973B6C62DD49D79A0EDECA88B3949F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An assessment of the effectiveness of the program grants under this section and any recommendations for improving the program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H729B1C10C5A44CA5B6D9F43742696B87"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text><paragraph id="H1D57A811EA274D149B39B6B006569CEC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><subparagraph id="H2B306C26D4DF4D44A054E40529BBE582"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text><clause id="HBECFF1DF8363432385F376F745337774"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a unit of general local government;</text></clause><clause id="H23FFBAF3B78746EFB1D91AD84DF19395"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization; and</text></clause><clause id="HA70CFAD6632A4F44A510964D66AB681B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an entity providing housing or shelters for homeless persons.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8A26A61758E4EF4B365F2EDF7536FC1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such term does not include an animal wellness or welfare organization or an animal shelter, except that this subparagraph may not be construed to prevent any such organization or shelter from partnering with an eligible entity to provide interim or permanent housing assisted with amounts from a grant under this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD773A9B3A4546CAA8918BAF4D73600B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Homeless</header><text>The term <quote>homeless</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 103 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11302">42 U.S.C. 11302</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA57B47034814F1BB8AF9F17623154E5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interim housing</header><text>The term <quote>interim housing</quote> means any housing or shelter that does not provide permanent housing. Such term includes transitional housing (as such term is defined in such section 401) and emergency shelters (as such term is defined in section 321 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/13351">42 U.S.C. 13351</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D8220943342463596E8222288D77CAB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Permanent housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>permanent housing</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 401 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02F23470746D44AE8D0051AC6317F410"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Pet</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>pet</quote> means any domesticated animal that is normally maintained as a companion or pet animal near the owner or person who cares for the animal, such as a domestic dog (including a service dog), domestic cat, ferret, gerbil, mouse, rat, guinea pig, rabbit, hamster, or bird.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E3EF9859254A37ACC79F9630ADB34E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Agriculture. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67BB87A1EA0B44DA8D0D2B2BCA627016"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Unit of general local government</header><text>The term <quote>unit of general local government</quote> has the meaning given such term in the first sentence of paragraph (1) of section 102(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5302">42 U.S.C. 5302(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85532E7CA47F46B4A9BA6ABE7D1F6560"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

