<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C6EBD4156694801B466F814A9B31C32" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4607 IH: Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4607</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site in the State of Illinois, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2CB4376AC0014514909B514CA901FFF0" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H12D06407D7EB4F3E93F963C6C94E7A25"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H6F1CD411B52B4757BE29A542B9C5B6B0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HA55A37D892D34D468D06E0C749FE3292"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National Historic Site</header><text>The term <term>National Historic Site</term> means the Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site established by section 3(a). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2FBEBA0E12FA44CE81F5C7039C5BF53B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Roberts Temple</header><text>The term <term>Roberts Temple</term> means the Roberts Temple Church of God in Christ, Chicago, Illinois. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEBBCAD32FFD64880847E6F3E82EB21FA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H422783E484EC4EA4935F092A2C1420D9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site</header> <subsection id="H09CFECC24508438C9D486BE0E2EFA350"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Subject to subsection (b), there is established the Emmett Till and Mamie Till-Mobley and Roberts Temple National Historic Site in the State of Illinois as a unit of the National Park System.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDEA72414FBB34C8EBACE44790C891CF2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conditions of establishment</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6517FD2DE8DE4A32A057116B513ADE37"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Historic Site shall not be established until the date on which the Secretary determines that an agreement entered into between the Secretary and the Roberts Temple providing for public access to, and interpretation, operation, and maintenance of, the National Historic Site that is sufficient to constitute a manageable park unit.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7DABEB6C29054936AE89AADC90A6BAF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Secretary makes a determination under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall publish in the Federal Register notice of establishment of the National Historic Site.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5D80667B595147D7BD58681BFE81D17B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the National Historic Site is to preserve, protect, and interpret for the benefit of present and future generations resources associated with—</text> <paragraph id="HD687108086C2457E9C102AFF930C899C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Great Migration;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64FEC8636AC14CD7B186F1F89E3EF54F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the memorial service and funeral of Emmett Till;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H19DEE74951E04BF487C926D2C35B8527"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the story of the courage and activism of Mamie Till-Mobley that was demonstrated as Mamie Till-Mobley transformed the murder of her son into a powerful symbol of racial injustice; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1892FD1400394AC5B689A6E08D12D074"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the civil rights movement.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC9A01297B89B4B739C104B19765B417B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Map; Boundaries</header> <paragraph id="H40ED5FF098E04278A6E6DD9FC2576ECE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Map</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall prepare a map of the National Historic Site.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H397168C29CE3487EB51623EFFCE265A2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text>The map prepared under paragraph (1) shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45FBB7FD9E964A1CA29C7A12F2D5C17F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Boundaries</header><text>The boundaries of the National Historic Site shall be the boundaries generally depicted on the map prepared under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE7B7646E0800475FB35AA5F29067A4C9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Acquisition authority</header><text>The Secretary may acquire any land or interest in land located within the boundary of the National Historic Site by—</text> <paragraph id="H1B224F7575424C12B5382F0E50DF3EF7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>donation;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37DA60AF7D734E54A9EADE98AAFA8EE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase from a willing seller with donated or appropriated funds; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H87BAE9F645AB446C9377DB3145A677AA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exchange.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H92085D7D7BAF4E8ABFA0547A3009DFDD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Administration</header> 
<paragraph id="H876FC9F07C1240AAA672CC53E0BA5276"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall administer the National Historic Site in accordance with—</text> <subparagraph id="HB6508C4570A54D92B44AC87044B1A0E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>this Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H230235F3C8F64387BDE43FC768E72352"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the laws generally applicable to units of the National Park System.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0414528165A14AA8B3A649AC438BF1BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>The Secretary may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF5B6C5A410E541AE871D98F2EC695FE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enter into an agreement with the Roberts Temple for the purpose of providing public access to, and interpretation, operation, and maintenance of, the National Historic Site; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3B70F6BC33DB4C0B956D8E0ACD039003"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enter into cooperative agreements, leases, or other agreements, as appropriate, with public and private entities to provide and facilitate interpretive and educational services, administrative support, and technical assistance relating to the National Historic Site, within or outside the boundaries of the National Historic Site. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H912E9F9C272C49E3B80329BDE69DEE0C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Management plan</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2EA06FD1177B43AF99A9E3B6E49F4FD1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Deadline for completion</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date on which funds are first made available to the Secretary for the preparation of a general management plan for the National Historic Site, the Secretary shall prepare a general management plan for the National Historic Site in accordance with section 100502 of title 54, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2196DEC8AAED46CE9BE6B3FC6B210D21"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The general management plan prepared under subparagraph (A) shall identify, as appropriate, the roles and responsibilities of the National Park Service and any applicable management entity in administering and interpreting the National Historic Site and areas affiliated with the National Historic Site in a manner that does not interfere with existing operations and the continued use of existing facilities at the National Historic Site, unless agreed to by the Roberts Temple and in accordance with the agreements described in paragraph (2) and subsection (b).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HDD9045D0E37B460F9CC4F049174AC838"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text>On completion of the general management plan under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives the general management plan prepared under that subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

