<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA07B895EC24943EA8B380B34399D7637" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5322 IH: Time Off to Vote Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5322</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide employees with a minimum of two consecutive hours of paid leave in order to vote in Federal elections.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEC38D635879B423592BEFF6BE5069319" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H796B24BCFB5E4668B156FA5FAD89576B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Time Off to Vote Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H926D4DA66A2C424686B279D448D52C9B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement for two hours paid leave to vote in Federal elections</header> <subsection id="H69951A71E3404E0EA7204695EE05E26F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement To provide leave</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the request of an employee, an employer shall provide to each employee a minimum of two consecutive hours of paid leave on the day of any Federal election in order to vote. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE0F2A42DCC8144CE92BECC4E812D19D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Employer right To determine two-Hour period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each employee taking leave under subsection (a), the employer of such employee may specify the hours during which the employee may take such leave, including by requiring that the employee take the leave during a period designated for early voting instead of on the day of the election, as applicable under State law. Any lunch break or other break period may not be included in the two-hour period designated for leave, but may be taken consecutively with the 2-hour period described in subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H787FF86935F04A849DF6075673F3D774"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No loss of benefits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The taking of leave under this section shall not result in the loss of any employment benefit accrued prior to the date on which the leave was taken.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H520788A0174F46009B86D1FD91A995A9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prohibited Acts</header>
<paragraph id="H1FB6D81F6F664D18947BFFA0F7FFDB8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interference with rights under this Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any employer to interfere with, restrain, or deny the exercise of or the attempt to exercise, the right to take leave under this Act, or to discriminate against an employee in any manner for taking leave under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50F81B4F11DF48019FF1835B3FACAF0A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Retaliation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any employer to discharge or in any other manner discriminate against any individual for—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1798798D5AC640F98C81D4A76AC75AB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>opposing any practice made unlawful by this section;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H078315692DF045788AADA51533926898"><enum>(B)</enum><text>filing any charge, or instituting or causing to be instituted any proceeding, under or related to this section;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H916868321B2D4FB29A4C7B9AD0DA538F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>giving or preparing to give any information in connection with any inquiry or proceeding relating to any leave provided under this section; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFD16826F1867447EA577417D6B8B0B16"><enum>(D)</enum><text>testifying or preparing to testify in any inquiry or proceeding relating to any leave provided under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4F452477390E46C7B7D0D8C04439F455"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Investigative authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall have investigative authority with respect to the provisions of this subsection in the same manner and under the same terms and conditions as the investigative authority provided under section 106 of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2616">29 U.S.C. 2616</external-xref>), and the requirements of section 106 of such Act shall apply to employers under this subsection in the same manner as such requirements apply to employers under section 106 of such Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE44D114334004EE5B9857A580392330E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <paragraph id="H28C8F940486848CEA3E2015E29B753D1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any employer that violates this Act may be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $10,000 per violation. Civil penalties shall be assessed by and paid to the Secretary of Labor for deposit into the Treasury of the United States and shall accrue to the United States and may be recovered in a civil action in the name of the United States brought in the United States district court for the district where the violation is alleged to have occurred or where the employer has its principal office.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8D3A56143E0A4FBB865BCBEB3A4FA276"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In assessing a civil penalty under this Act, the Secretary shall give due consideration to the appropriateness of the penalty with respect to the size of the business of the employer being charged, the gravity of the violation, the good faith of the employer, and the history of previous violations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H77DD8F91A59E4D48B55D7F8724253D49"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="H82DC7FBBB3BB416BB6DF56405BE160BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>employee</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41DA96E627AA436F9135B482E059ABCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>employer</term> means any person engaged in commerce or in any industry or activity affecting commerce who employs 25 or more employees during a calendar year, and includes any person who acts, directly or indirectly, in the interest of an employer to any of the employees of such employer and any successor in interest of an employer. In the previous sentence, the terms <term>commerce</term> and <term>industry or activity affecting commerce</term> have the meaning given such terms in section 101(1) of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8070FCC5CD8845C3B85CE222CBB66E5C"><enum>(h)</enum><header>State and local laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to supersede any provision of any State or local law that requires an employer to provide leave to an employee, for the purpose of voting in any Federal, State, or municipal election, in an amount greater than that required under this Act, or under terms more beneficial to an employee than those provided under this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H8E54BAEE4E4E493C839AE8BF585878CA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect beginning with the first Federal election held after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

