<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9C84E62A520347B7BD5CFA5E00757711" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6634 IH: Workers Protecting Our Wage Earners Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6634</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase the capacity of the Department of Labor and labor enforcement agencies of States to address labor violations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H07B4E4E015B04C30BDD55495686DEA7E" style="OLC"><section id="HE4CEFA0BFAA1496C92C83F811E0B7743" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings; definitions</header><subsection id="H1D943B86A65945ACB017BE9DA65F8EDF" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Workers Protecting Our Wage Earners Rights Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Workers POWER Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5B9469BAC53B4C2CAE27B9CD7F46C022"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H7FBBCCBCDE7646E2AD4A27BF50F57635"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Labor’s Wage and Hour Division and Occupational Safety and Health Administration require robustly increased appropriations to adequately address the size and scope of oversight of the United States workforce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC77A2F13D7D404DB09A0E7A7D7EDC12"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The continued presence of child labor violations, wage and hour violations, and occupational safety and health violations are a scourge on the national conscience and must be rebuked with the full resources, funding, and strengthened laws necessary to address these violations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC1F54A288DB43FE8B913599827789EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This necessary increased funding for the Department must be leveraged to invest in a strengthened workforce through increased full-time employees, incentive structures, compensation, and other mechanisms to support the dedicated public servants of the Department in enforcing Federal labor law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4137FC14BED2489E9F322B54887BC16F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act—</text><paragraph id="HD5FD96BC4DCE4AC297847DFF58B9316A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>Administration</term> means the Occupational Safety and Health Administration; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3CA14EA4A224232B5A9094560C99C3A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Labor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56A5C833B5234E7FBBC5D6D2458B78FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>Division</term> means the Wage and Hour Division of the Department; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21B79183C9A945AFB989244C98D5731B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H745ED3F3AE854B2C9978AC7197CFE1E0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expansion of Department of Labor post-secondary student program, recent graduates, and PMF programs</header><subsection id="HF869E66ADA4D4FAC8C01BBB10859DFCD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Post-Secondary student program</header><paragraph id="HB2CFA25FF8F04DECA753AF4D2EE02A11"><enum>(1)</enum><header>New positions</header><subparagraph id="H2338BC813C0C435799C473DBC57FECD4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall establish at least five paid post-secondary student program positions within the Wage and Hour Division of the Department of Labor. Such positions shall be—</text><clause id="HA2B29942B1504154AEDBD6009B8BD0A6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>located at the office of the Division located in Washington, DC; </text></clause><clause id="HA2AC4A4AA1A54EE2ABF5D9FEA71E9905" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">part of the post-secondary student program under the Pathways Programs at the Department; and</text></clause><clause id="HA67FC485F5ED446BBEC098F2A271F2CB" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be in addition to any post-secondary student program positions at the Department as of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD84E0546DC654F5AAB92EDCFD69886BD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other positions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the positions established under subparagraph (A), not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish at least two additional internship positions in each Division regional office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BD42A6A5F3948638A634D3D769F650B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensation; status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any intern participating in the Department post-secondary student program—</text><subparagraph id="H1F496D04AE554CEBA27953FBDE5ED409"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be entitled to an hourly rate of pay that is not less than the annual rate of basic pay for step 1 of GS–7 level (computed on an hourly basis under section 5504 of title 5, United States Code); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57E0122B1AE54C169C50B299277A51E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be considered a Federal employee for any purpose other than for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/81">chapter 81</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, (relating to compensation for injury) and sections 2671 through 2680 of title 28, United States Code (relating to tort claims).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A3F446F74A94F849F4D2127F86ADE63" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recent graduates program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall increase the number of positions under the Recent Graduates program at the Department by 100 percent. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC0CA79D0B84A440F99B16E804E1DA49C" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>PMF</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Office of Personnel Management, in consultation with the Secretary, shall establish one additional Presidential Management Fellowship Program position at each of the Division and the Administration.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBE5A5F8F998F41CE9A24AA6CD5DE7410"><enum>3.</enum><header>Child labor fellow position</header><subsection id="HA29D9FBA42CF41A5A403E52F51AF3AB9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish within each of the Division and the Administration at least five additional fellowship positions. Each such position shall—</text><paragraph id="H2967704E38A841B89F938C63C85E3C92"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">work with investigatory teams to enforce labor rights violations regarding children;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0B8EEB245744CB19C4748D24476A607"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve as additional investigators or provide other functions, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H197FC763D3814A95A5A4A92FB53B491B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be a time-limited appointment of one-year, except that the Secretary may modify the time-period of such appointment as the Secretary deems necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F083D303D004A369A001929E2CBE842"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fellows in the positions under subsection (a) shall be competitively selected, in such form and manner as the Secretary may prescribe, from State and local labor enforcement agencies, labor organizations, institutions of higher education, research organizations, advocacy organizations, non-profits, and other community organizations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H67EE7F6854D741EFA6C518A5777EFF5F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conversion</header><text>The Secretary may convert any fellow appointed under this section to a career appointment in the competitive service.</text></subsection></section><section id="H38A92A167D4342E3AB3A7B36A9F52E41"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expand the DOL Honors Attorneys program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall increase the number of positions in the Department’s Office of the Solicitor’s Honors Program for Attorneys to a minimum of twenty positions with a focus on creating a pipeline of attorneys into the Division and Administration. </text></section><section id="H5D5568E8DB324517801D82C507567DDC" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Performance, recruitment and relocation, and retention bonus programs</header><subsection id="H3F561A84753E4021A10D81ADE7B1C25B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Bonus program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish and carry out a bonus and incentive program for any covered employee. Such program shall award bonuses based on performance, with an emphasis on performance of investigatory and enforcement efforts.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F69A3043F4540BCA35ECA9C102E8E45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recruitment and relocation bonuses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary may pay a recruitment or relocation bonus under section 5753(e) of title 5, United States Code, to a covered employee without regard to any requirements for certification or approval under that section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3F7FDF8FDA4C4E5F88855B085701EB93"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retention bonuses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act—</text><paragraph id="H9D6553EFF9F1477A885DA790941625B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary may pay a retention bonus under section 5754(f) of title 5, United States Code, to a covered employee without regard to any requirement for certification or approval under that subsection; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4466A3CF1E64459807C481C6BBE37B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary may pay a retention bonus as specified in subsection (e)(2) of section 5754 of such title 5 to a covered employee and may pay the bonus as a single lump-sum payment at the beginning of the full period of service required by an agreement under subsection (d) of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H50CD948C99DB49979345E6174AA5DBBA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Merit awards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary may grant a cash award under section 4502(b) of title 5, United States Code, to a covered employee without regard to any requirement for certification or approval under that section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H286837EEA80D412B9B42D7A25563D4FC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Incentives for critical skills</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD452CCFCFFA04696AC5403A6E571CCE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary may provide a critical skill incentive to a covered employee if the Secretary determines—</text><subparagraph id="HC2C928F9F5EF4B87821E5F1E1CF5B4BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the employee possesses a high-demand skill or skill that is at a shortage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF48050632C55482FB7E118B441C8AD6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such skill is directly related to the duties and responsibilities of the employee’s position; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB45621F333A42F59C63D4117DBB88B3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>employment of an individual with such skill in such position serves a critical mission-related need of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1B06D79C39942D8B2F6BA5815CA7AF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An incentive provided to an employee under paragraph (1) may not to exceed 25 percent of the basic pay of the employee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF1EFF8A35DB4994B3DB6AE59CE7A4A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Provision of an incentive under paragraph (1) shall be contingent on the employee entering into a written agreement to complete a period of employment with the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F3BBA03A7754E9D97451C6157A7E44A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An incentive provided under paragraph (1) shall not be considered basic pay for any purpose.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03993A797ABC408A8051BDB2A46C8D0B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Secretary may prescribe conditions, including with respect to eligibility, and limitations on provision of incentive under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE86517B738DB4F1B87ED5799E89A7873"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Covered employee defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered employee</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H949E946096804EA5A9A8F72C3C3710A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an employee of the Division or the Administration; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79BF3DD156804BFD96A2D4C7F6F90F88"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other employee of the Department that supports enforcement efforts of the Division or the Administration, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H80756A7F10E948769833549EA018D8B0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Increase in student loan repayment for Department employees</header><subsection id="H04C62D607D3F46C0AAB16B8AF90FD2EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Consistent with subsection (b), with respect to any covered employee who is otherwise eligible for student loan repayments under section 5379 of title 5, United States Code—</text><paragraph id="HDB7C514EE1644260B26B534B9ACA796E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>subsection (b)(2)(A) of such section shall be applied by substituting <quote>$30,000</quote> for <quote>$10,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BFF4ADAC88A482C96B30647C3D1474C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subsection (b)(2)(B) of such section shall be applied by substituting <quote>$180,000</quote> for <quote>$60,000</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F55A73C04794AB5B2AFF8C6CB6472CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered employee described in subsection (e)(2) or (3) may not receive increased student loan payment under this section until on or after the date the employee enters into a written service agreement, in such form and manner as the Secretary may prescribe, to complete a period of employment with the Department of at least 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H365F8493FAC04B6E9BAFD35ECDE6DF53"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The increased loan repayment provided under subsection (a) shall cease to apply after an individual leaves employment with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC9452B9AA97549E0B4723BD3F90F43D2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Covered employee defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>covered employee</term> means any employee of the Department—</text><paragraph id="H5CDFD7E649F04C25A6A6B77EDB31CA09"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has been such an employee for a period of at least five consecutive years; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA13AA5FADA084E2097522915B1BAC211"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who, on the date of enactment of this Act, has less than five years of continuous service with the Department; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8EAB7709DAA4726B511FBCDCF27AACF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">initially appointed to a position in the Department after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H91130100C8864EBDA7FFF53B75C3FAAB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>7.</enum><header>Reports</header><subsection id="H61D1147BBED547FEA58AB466FE18E8D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in collaboration with the Comptroller General of the United States, shall submit to Congress and make publicly available a report that identifies necessary and recommended changes to increase the ability of the Department to enforce Federal labor laws, including—</text><paragraph id="H32B19C0C049F4AF6B5E3F1905F5D3CF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how to address the need for increased capacity at the Department, including the need for more personnel, funding, and other resources as determined by the Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5BE955D397D4403B143A3F25FA4297D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifying any limitations on the Secretary with respect to enforcing Federal labor laws due to—</text><subparagraph id="HB5240C6393DB4CD0BC185A8FD4381DD6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of employees of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF25C1B364BB041308E59F81C486D8261"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the organizational structure of the Department; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC0483A8A80E47B38EC6304DA6A353BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identifying any opportunities for, and limitations on the ability of, the Secretary to work with labor organizations or community-based organizations to enforce Federal labor laws;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD6F3BE01883420F8180C0D8E51531A6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how to develop a recruitment strategy intended to increase outreach to, and the employment of, underrepresented populations, including through outreach and partnerships at historically Black colleges or universities, Hispanic-serving institutions, Tribal colleges or universities, and other minority-serving institutions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73D6BCAE17DB47BC8B47F796EF18DA83"><enum>(5)</enum><text>how to best utilize incentives such as bonuses, loan repayment, and other benefits to increase recruitment and retention.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H92289F307BFC4FD9B0D9F0A13B3A7AB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Discretionary grant and report</header><text>The Secretary may award a one-time grant, on a competitive basis, to an institution of higher education to—</text><paragraph id="HEFB812A0585F4106A0A67A014CDACA96"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out a study that identifies necessary and recommended changes to increase the ability of the Department to enforce Federal labor laws; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7566AC18DEC34A9E93C5D52DD6152B45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress and the Secretary a report that includes the findings from the study under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDCC79265F6E4294BAF3308E219B2328"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H94BC893313874A55882FC33FADE48D58"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hispanic-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>Hispanic-serving institution</term> has the meaning given such term in section 502 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101a">20 U.S.C. 1101a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEF62389609147A5BABD3D63848454A8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Historically Black college or university</header><text>The term <term>Historically Black College or University</term> has the meaning given the term <term>part B institution</term> in section 322 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1061">20 U.S.C. 1061</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20B80C9237494B6E910ABB0E33F1CADB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB11A273BD9284E13BD4AF5735504F210"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Labor organization</header><text>The term <term>labor organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA30C4DE647F34D1EA8671A4BBE791B6F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Minority-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>minority-serving institution</term> means an institution listed in section 371(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067q">20 U.S.C. 1067q(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37F1978659954725B425260C46FF68C7"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal college or university</header><text>The term <term>Tribal college or university</term> has the meaning given such term in section 316 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63150F4941924547AD0F12592F9871D2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Underrepresented population</header><text>The term <term>underrepresented population</term> means a population of individuals (based on race, color, religion, sex (including pregnancy, sexual orientation, or gender identity), national origin, age (40 or older), disability status, and genetic information (including family medical history)) who have been historically less represented, as defined by the Secretary, in the workforce of the Department of Labor.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3E3E6448C95944CF89B5E2FB4AD0E78A"><enum>8.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="H2E1FF3738442440A88D92D02E4A6A875"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under subsection (i), the Secretary may award grants, on a competitive basis, to States to increase the capacity of State and local departments of labor to enforce labor laws.</text></subsection><subsection id="H17E8A12BA8414ECABC63E4E975D75249"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a State shall submit to the Secretary an application at such a time, in such a manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, which shall include—</text><paragraph id="H8B05FBC5F4C64C1F99FF5B165D92C2F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the intended uses of grant funds; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AAAC77983704BE8BFDC688FA7C99E88"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the needs of the State, or a unit of general local government, with respect enforcing labor laws, including—</text><subparagraph id="HC5F476B724F34B7DBB60E9B537B976A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>insufficient capacity of a department of labor or other similar agency due to insufficient personnel, funding, or other resources; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CBD0BA5F5DC4FA28BFA8FFEC973B1B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether there are case backlogs or personnel working overtime at such department, and any other relevant information; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50AAA051876449369CA86E8D8C212706"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an assurance that the State will—</text><subparagraph id="H55347B504ACD4209925DB4AF39715008"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enter into a data sharing agreement as required under subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12394CDDD18D438689901EA796F57688"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comply with subsection (f).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDFABBDDCEF234610944CA7640B36CFB6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize States that demonstrate the greatest need for assistance in enforcing labor laws, as compared to the other States submitting applications under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD726106BE4EB485DAF5F8079CA6769B2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Data sharing agreement</header><text>Not later than two years after the receipt of a grant under this section, a State that receives such grant shall enter into a data sharing agreement with the Secretary to—</text><paragraph id="H9FBE654AEBFF4327A70729C31C9F4E0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>share investigation data related to potential and confirmed labor law violations, including—</text><subparagraph id="H3456FF84C6EF4C8693891FA822149C4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the locations of such violations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC695C61DB1A416DA720D7F41CA87410"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of—</text><clause id="H56EF58FA276247F8AAF64C204B8D54DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>entities that routinely commit labor law violations; and</text></clause><clause id="HCE95C29D22724B818E6867F9C6E2AC37"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the most common labor law violations; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55EBFF83C9E14A778AAE9DE4D3D026D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other relevant information as determined by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB827CAEBC92B4FB1B9797A0DD254A9A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote communication and enforcement efforts between the Secretary and State and local departments of labor, or any agency that enforces labor laws.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H62AB1E0BC5E14F3BA2D5727F5610AB08"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Required uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State receiving a grant under this section shall use grant funds to increase the capacity of the relevant labor enforcement department or similar agency of the State, or one or more similar agencies of a unit of general local government, to enforce labor laws, by—</text><paragraph id="H117EB91BC93E4EF9912B6B45FB734C60"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recruiting and retaining employees in departments of labor or similar agencies; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55F8834920FB4F1B97484E5135B26577"><enum>(2)</enum><text>carrying out any activity the Secretary determines necessary to increase the capacity of the State, or a unit of general local government in the State, to enforce such laws; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E795B5767E049ABB0C46AAC735C806B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>distributing grant funds to a unit of general local government in the State for such unit to use the funds for a purpose described in paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD64180E192B14E5A87F0408345DE6A82"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State receiving a grant under this section shall use such grant to supplement, and not supplant, State and local funding for labor enforcement departments or similar agencies of such State or unit of general local government.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD96C96757AFB428EB8BC344D3DC9A52C" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a mechanism or process to regularly monitor and audit the uses of grant funds by a State, or a unit of local government of such State, to ensure that the funds are used in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6FC6D8BB76914EC2BC97AE809665ABA2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF4BB912091EF4CAE87E6CBE9E97FA6F2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Labor laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>labor laws</term> includes Federal, State, and local labor laws, including child labor law, wage and hour law, occupational safety and health law, and any other relevant labor law as determined by the Secretary, State, or unit of general local government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA47A04EED00D4B2D9FF0BA723C5102CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H7F26929C737643A58E77B54108AD0748"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any of the 50 States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2B3E039D69546B7B9E8DB6EEC339FC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB55A302EA22E497997452A6F9C60F448"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AEBD3BEC24C41019AF3595A08E39AC0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Unit of general local government</header><text>The term <term>unit of general local government</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2BA34B97837481580AEDF2A38685DC5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $250,000,000 to carry out this section for each fiscal year.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

