<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H656F5D8C88AE4758A0D5F51CF6B1F057" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3544 IH: Remote Naturalization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3544</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To permit remote oath ceremonies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB9DC86E1572749D89C1924D84EE1FBA8" style="OLC"><section id="H8CE5EB6FFD3740F7B567499088386EFA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Remote Naturalization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDAE49CF7D9C547A5A681A308E5351899"><enum>2.</enum><header>Accommodations for naturalization oath ceremonies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 337 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCC9453D57D994D92B5EDC68A2D8ACCCF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H843B821CBDBF4B08B85732553DA1475D"><enum>337A.</enum><header>Remote oath ceremonies</header><subsection id="H57E4067B73BE4BAA9FA0DA22AF3165DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Remote oath ceremonies</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish procedures for the administration of the oath of renunciation and allegiance under section 337 using remote videoconferencing, or other remote means for individuals who cannot reasonably access, understand, or use remote videoconferencing, as an alternative to an in-person oath ceremony.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB68E5706E28E46E39112E47F00F0CADB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible individuals</header><text>Notwithstanding section 310(b), an individual may complete the naturalization process by participating in a remote oath ceremony conducted pursuant to subsection (a) if such individual—</text><paragraph id="H871C2F623B714B12BC43995DE772E831"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has an approved application for naturalization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C8069EA5C1D493D8B10293991DE1E2F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is unable otherwise to complete the naturalization process due to—</text><subparagraph id="H6475FC303B8D45E68BD63EC6E7A88384"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the cancellation or suspension of in-person oath ceremonies during—</text><clause id="H4F19D7913A8A4F2BBF948F46DA36F9E9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a national emergency declared by the President under the National Emergencies Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1601">50 U.S.C. 1601 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H3E6F916CA9584B54B7B88B19621A5938"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an emergency or major disaster declared by the President under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H64897E1B10834198A1A4FF5334E5F201"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a public health emergency declared by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="HB83C7B4AF15648298835932ECC734F7D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any emergency that, in the judgment of the Secretary of Homeland Security, is appropriate for the cancellation or suspension of such ceremonies; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29B3EA10DE3F466F90324AA7353290E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the inability of the individual to attend the ceremony in person; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H08D9753004554BAC97C20261FAAC1541"><enum>(3)</enum><text>elects to participate in a remote oath ceremony in lieu of waiting for an in-person ceremony.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H753FFA19F4FD488ABB9B9EFA46E3D93B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>Upon establishing the procedures described in subsection (a), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text><paragraph id="H1E62163C6DE34DBCB5F748A0A663DB6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>without undue delay, provide written notice to individuals described in subsection (b)(1) of the option of participating in a remote oath ceremony in lieu of a participating in an in-person ceremony;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3B8B90A86014C6AA047C795C0E1D486"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the greatest extent practicable, ensure that remote oath ceremonies are administered to individuals who elect to participate in such a ceremony not later than 30 days after the individual so notifies the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB2820FE545D415FA2506A31DF595545"><enum>(3)</enum><text>administer oath ceremonies to all other eligible individuals as expeditiously as possible after the end of the public health emergency referred to in subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC98B351E9186417091F3E477588BB034"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>Failure to appear for a remote oath ceremony shall not create a presumption that the individual has abandoned his or her intent to be naturalized.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8E7490255C414B09A5EB7CB9E33D7C8A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and each year thereafter, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit a report to Congress that identifies, for each State and political subdivision of a State, the number of—</text><paragraph id="HCE0DBA8052CD4A399D76A829E49EACC0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>individuals who were scheduled for an in-person oath ceremony that was cancelled due to an emergency described in subsection (b)(2)(A);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9C07F61DD6B4FA3AD87F7C6543B4CDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>individuals who elected to participate in a remote oath ceremony in lieu of an in-person public ceremony;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71964C9D1C0B4191BFF063DA49EEDF2A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>individuals who completed the naturalization process by participating in a remote oath ceremony; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1E9AEF3F7CE4A0A9740EC3C9AC6323F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>remote oath ceremonies that were conducted in the previous year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64BC5BC9858E4168A926D685B78FABCE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>In addition to any funds appropriated to carry out this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security may use funds from the Immigration Examinations Fee Account under section 286(m) to carry out this section. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

