<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1EAC193BCD51482DAD44FA11665B8D40" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2985 IH: Help Empower Americans to Respond Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2985</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To regulate firearm silencers and firearm mufflers.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H1C01DD517FC44160995E7197DEB3F783" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="HA8C790B54B8148519282A22A04830614"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Help Empower Americans to Respond Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HEAR Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HEFA82C82C8444F08A47DEFA90B4F5026"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD326A66A68F945688F7B234CB86459FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>(C) any firearm muffler or firearm silencer; or (D)</quote> and inserting <quote>or (C)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29035513493B4B2686A8504354B259CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67569B9C06DF47BDA07EBCC14D3E47D0">
<paragraph id="H13051ACA89EB44F1B0154105F088EEA7" indent="up1"><enum>(38)</enum><text>The term <term>qualified law enforcement officer</term> has the meaning given the term in section 926B.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H14416A81022448379EDD5A09824FDEFD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Restrictions on firearm silencers and firearm mufflers</header> <subsection id="H68CD3CD6D3E94C5FB2259BE566C4E08B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after subsection (u) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H768E8E8B119745D982DF7760E95F8758">
<subsection id="HB1E70FCBF40B4092A1249A794B8E0450"><enum>(v)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H87F91BD59B654A928D59C385B4336641"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), it shall be unlawful for a person to import, sell, manufacture, transfer, or possess, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, a firearm silencer or firearm muffler.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67BF77B2FF2B449CB67DAAD5E42428D8" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H055A3B13DA2D46F58AEA4BC38B6DEEDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the importation for, manufacture for, sale to, transfer to, or possession by the United States or a department or agency of the United States or a State or a department, agency, or political subdivision of a State, or a sale or transfer to or possession by a qualified law enforcement officer employed by the United States or a department or agency of the United States or a State or a department, agency, or political subdivision of a State for purposes of law enforcement (whether on or off-duty), or a sale or transfer to or possession by a campus law enforcement officer for purposes of law enforcement (whether on or off-duty);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEE9A4708A189476A9E306E61E6D2EE7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the importation for, or sale or transfer to a licensee under title I of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2011">42 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>) for purposes of establishing and maintaining an on-site physical protection system and security organization required by Federal law, or possession by an employee or contractor of such licensee on-site for such purposes or off-site for purposes of licensee-authorized training or transportation of nuclear materials; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H53EA28D54336457DA3B45A9F14BEE043"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the importation for, manufacture for, sale to, transfer to, or possession by a licensed manufacturer or licensed importer for the purposes of testing or experimentation authorized by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79AE77A190274DF8B23CD8F87FD39FCD" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>For purposes of paragraph (2)(A), the term <term>campus law enforcement officer</term> means an individual who is—</text>
<subparagraph id="H264EFF781F4841E0B86171BA9B8FBED5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employed by a private institution of higher education that is eligible for funding under title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0473F4AF39194924906DA1BA3E43CED6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>responsible for the prevention or investigation of crime involving injury to persons or property, including apprehension or detention of persons for such crimes;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1E0CFF667AE4400BBCD915446A08B620"><enum>(C)</enum><text>authorized by Federal, State, or local law to carry a firearm, execute search warrants, and make arrests; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H063782A3399748C291C2EA3F981C4A63"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recognized, commissioned, or certified by a government entity as a law enforcement officer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H794E7D90C2E04D859FB5496D0C2610A8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Seizure and forfeiture of firearm silencers and firearm mufflers</header><text>Section 924(d) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H25EB6232FE004165A47DB3CDB3A2D7D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>or (k)</quote> and inserting <quote>(k), or (v)</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H502C6117BDEC41E1A22BAD0D42399D5C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(E), by inserting <quote>922(v),</quote> after <quote>922(n),</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HAB095F314622431BA6727DF217B13DD7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 924(a)(1)(B) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>or (q)</quote> and inserting <quote>(q), or (v)</quote>.</text></section>
<section commented="no" id="HC23F9E85E9CC48158D6DB62FBD525EBD"><enum>5.</enum><header>Use of Byrne grants for buy-back programs for firearm silencers and firearm mufflers</header>
<subsection commented="no" id="H9B4B1FB73E22446DB5CAF3D76FFC949C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 501(a)(1) of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10152">34 U.S.C. 10152(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9FABD28EFEE843B9847C0E5194C3DFAE"> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H04454A91932441BEBEC2E396A56F3ADF"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Compensation for surrendered firearm silencers and firearm mufflers, as those terms are defined in section 921 of title 18, United States Code, under the buy-back program for firearm silencers and firearm mufflers required under section 5(b) of the <short-title>Help Empower Americans to Respond Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H3EC341B9E8774B7FA759328A55F94305"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>During the 90-day period described in section 6, the Attorney General shall establish and implement a buy-back program, to be carried out across the United States, to purchase firearm silencers and firearm mufflers (as defined in section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code) from individuals seeking to comply with the requirements of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section commented="no" id="H80601F3BE1D7406DAD8CF3AA1C48AA68"><enum>6.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by sections 2, 3, and 4 shall take effect on the date that is 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section>
<section id="H019B0EC65C4444B6B04AA1451814D78E"><enum>7.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, the amendments made by this Act, and the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance shall not be affected thereby.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

