<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3903EFB13B3A481782658BA66EB4A1E8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>107 HR 3166 IH: Building Cyber Resilience After SolarWinds Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3166</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security to submit a report on the impact of the SolarWinds cyber incident on information systems owned and operated by Federal departments and agencies and other critical infrastructure, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H716DDC38C352435981D0708DC49BDF60" style="OLC"><section id="H07785330B3164C7DA6F17BA9782117D9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Cyber Resilience After SolarWinds Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H5977672C53A249009D5D9BE4F26653B4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Building cyber resilience after SolarWinds</header><subsection id="H5BF4572E0DB24F6BB814C55E41A3193B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6BC5C90BC4C741F7B9B4AAB800AACC52"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1016(e) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/56">Public Law 107–56</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30C77ADBEADB4DFA9821B0C681E2B6E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44795F9401E24E2FAB11CEF0492F4BCB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information system</header><text>The term <quote>information system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2200 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31E44EF3699C4B4D92F40E2E5E49CB6F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Significant cyber incident</header><text>The term <quote>significant cyber incident</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2240 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/681">6 U.S.C. 681</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD39376E313D049178E6389C33D671FF3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Solarwinds incident</header><text>The term <quote>SolarWinds incident</quote> refers to the significant cyber incident that prompted the establishment of a Unified Cyber Coordination Group, as provided by section V(B)(2) of Presidential Policy Directive 41, in December 2020.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0D3840F91864E3F854B90A21513DE01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>SolarWinds investigation and report</header><paragraph id="H9FCFD7E88DF14055B6750A9DF424FC0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Investigation</header><text>The Director, in consultation with the National Cyber Director and the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall carry out an investigation to evaluate the impact of the SolarWinds incident on information systems owned and operated by Federal departments and agencies, and, to the extent practicable, other critical infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22642DFB96B9494E8B2B7EA7E656EE68"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>In carrying out subsection (b), the Director shall review the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE6BA4184A2C5403CA00FC12ABBD34CB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The extent to which Federal information systems were accessed, compromised, or otherwise impacted by the SolarWinds incident, and any potential ongoing security concerns or consequences arising from such incident.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94DBC85635524095B4EC82BC6E61284C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The extent to which information systems that support other critical infrastructure were accessed, compromised, or otherwise impacted by the SolarWinds incident, where such information is available to the Director.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE395FBA880C9484495371BA768D7C9AC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any ongoing security concerns or consequences arising from the SolarWinds incident, including any sensitive information that may have been accessed or exploited in a manner that poses a threat to national security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DA623546DE7450BA55F895FAA4EED43"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Implementation of Executive Order 14028 (Improving the Nation’s Cybersecurity (May 12, 2021)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H082F15F9F4434AE0A3F99A1D305FFB16"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Efforts taken by the Director, the heads of Federal departments and agencies, and critical infrastructure owners and operators to address cybersecurity vulnerabilities and mitigate risks associated with the SolarWinds incident.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00328F2FD1CA4FE1A381139A15DA0AEB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H77BF339711AE4E1297D9085B6D19C938"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Findings for each of the elements specified in subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57D1424662824E038C2E6E014655652A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recommendations to address security gaps, improve incident response efforts, and prevent similar cyber incidents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7808881B985F41F4B260C89C42E60E26"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any areas with respect to which the Director lacked the information necessary to fully review and assessment such elements, the reason the information necessary was unavailable, and recommendations to close such informational gaps.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H475678CAB36C4123A998A12D460DF4D1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GAO report on Cyber Safety Review Board</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall evaluate the activities of the Cyber Safety Review Board established pursuant to Executive Order 14028 (Improving the Nation’s Cybersecurity (May 12, 2021)), with a focus on the Board’s inaugural review announced in February 2022, and assess whether the Board has the authorities, resources, and expertise necessary to carry out its mission of reviewing and assessing significant cyber incidents.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

