<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAE3031FEDEC84B1A9F62914F6D5FBD82" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1131 IH: To require the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to authorize the use of flexible air permitting with respect to certain critical energy resource facilities, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1131</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to authorize the use of flexible air permitting with respect to certain critical energy resource facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H320F0AD1D03A46AFB89D4E1098BF367B" style="OLC"><section id="H6F8730E1E8AF48BBB9A65A62277E227A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Flexible air permits for critical energy resource facilities</header><subsection id="HD63C256756BE4B6AA636ADCA6F39CE69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall, as necessary, revise regulations under parts 70 and 71 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations, to—</text><paragraph id="H437BDC16E8A64CCC8FA15420D1A40A75"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorize the owner or operator of a critical energy resource facility to utilize flexible air permitting (as described in the final rule titled <quote>Operating Permit Programs; Flexible Air Permitting Rule</quote> published by the Environmental Protection Agency in the Federal Register on October 6, 2009 (74 Fed. Reg. 51418)) with respect to such critical energy resource facility; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7D45983831F42DC99CB278A7208E3AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitate flexible, market-responsive operations (as described in the final rule identified in paragraph (1)) with respect to critical energy resource facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF989902C76C45248F4D1BB60364E602"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC61A7D2CFE0E4F21A2499C7F6B86E2C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical energy resource</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>critical energy resource</term> means, as determined by the Secretary of Energy, any energy resource—</text><subparagraph id="H8182CD797ABB456FB6FDB8AC6BE24172"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is essential to the energy sector and energy systems of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D0060AEE3EE44A99E7B1E2FC67F2EBF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the supply chain of which is vulnerable to disruption.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B247843728F4AC48252FE1289E66C55" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical energy resource facility</header><text>The term <term>critical energy resource facility</term> means a facility that processes or refines a critical energy resource.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

