<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H60E85EFE07994146A50E208E4603EEEB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4376 IH: Brianna Lieneck Boating Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4376</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230627">June 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the department in which the Coast Guard is operating to study and report to the Congress regarding recreational vessel operator training.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6599A6508B254775B3B1C2B41CB98343" style="OLC"><section id="H7576F139B8F543739BD5C0344F583353" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Brianna Lieneck Boating Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC4D4C0FB44AC4BE6AA1FA4E4842CB347"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recreational vessel operator education and training</header><subsection id="H532FD97AE0BB477A95DA832BC5B0A2E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the department in which the Coast Guard is operating shall study and report to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate regarding recreational vessel operator training. The study and report shall include a review of—</text><paragraph id="H86884856730E454F8D80B16737F18D45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coast Guard Auxiliary and Power Squadron training programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA675CABAD171462897737049F293AF74"><enum>(2)</enum><text>existing State boating education programs, including programs by the National Association of State Boating Law Administrators (in this section referred to as <quote>NASBLA</quote>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A170F0B8D194E70BC3E88364238DCFB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other hands-on training programs available to recreational vessel operators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3CCFC869C7FE4B8E983872F8B6B9A986"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Included subjects</header><text>The study shall specifically examine—</text><paragraph id="H328CA0157BA34410BFF390B9CB29A9E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>course materials;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2CCC0D358C2462E85C3D8A48A3811F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>course content;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16FBB17D314245F5A7E2F623287B3D61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>training methodology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6738FB1E95745029BD5F505B078D438"><enum>(4)</enum><text>assessment methodology; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD011A6BC6A4041FC9548B6481D3AF8A1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>relevancy of course content to risks for recreational boaters.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF730B2668F04E9FB7026B683AFBC246"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>The report under this section shall include—</text><paragraph id="H2E64E24127584C4C8ECAD3A6F22337AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a section regarding steps the Coast Guard and NASBLA have taken to encourage States to adopt mandatory recreational vessel operator training;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBC6F1A9755944AEB303F4F99AD884D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an evaluation of the ability of the States to harmonize their education programs and testing procedures;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC570DFA0F0814841A216B5F849A0348D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an analysis of the extent States have provided reciprocity among the States for their respective mandatory and voluntary education requirements and programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1DB2879D64A4B48A06C0847BDE5EAF9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a section examining the level of uniformity of education and training between the States that currently have mandatory education and training programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2F93F80869F417790F0FE469CCB2B41"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a section outlining the minimum standards for education of recreational vessel operators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4797359FA0F4088AC1276C4BEBB91BE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a section analyzing how a Federal training and testing program can be harmonized with State training and testing programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9199D1375A274987AE2D07649CE4B9D7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an analysis of course content and delivery methodology for relevancy to risks for recreational boaters;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5ADB8658610C497FA8600A6BFB8BEF94"><enum>(8)</enum><text>a description of the current phase-in periods for mandatory boater education in State mandatory education programs and recommendation for the phase-in period for a mandatory boater education program including an evaluation as to whether the phase-in period affects course availability and cost;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E2BB8F33A034DD588F948B4D0895CCF"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a description of the extent States allow for experienced boaters to bypass mandatory education courses and go directly to testing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA3EBE3A0204700ABD265614034E427"><enum>(10)</enum><text>recommendations for a bypass option for experienced boaters;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7F1217FA2434C2EADBFD97BD556DC84"><enum>(11)</enum><text>a section analyzing how the Coast Guard would administer a Federal boating education, training, and testing program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CB600E32E174685ABCCD3430A6E93C2"><enum>(12)</enum><text>an analysis of the extent to which a Federal boating education, training, and testing program should be required for all waters of a State, including internal waters.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

