<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBE03709B247B4F9E9D12F46AF799B6AD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5783 IH: Blue Collar and Green Collar Jobs Development Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5783</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To establish and carry out a comprehensive, nationwide, energy-related industries jobs program, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HDB3693C7B3BA4409B82C86C7E97E8A9E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7D1CACDA012C4C6FAEA8AB0BCC469573" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Blue Collar and Green Collar Jobs Development Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3244DC58277741CFABB9D7530BEA1B4D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Energy workforce development</header> <subsection id="H8F7E93B2978646D28CA8E294391197D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary of Energy, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Education, shall establish and carry out a comprehensive, nationwide program to improve education and training for occupations in energy-related industries to increase the number of skilled workers trained for such occupations. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7C65E4C3285440D6A79A771C0E65674B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Direct assistance</header> 
<paragraph id="HA39B301D27DD4F108E1B4809141A5BDD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy may provide—</text> <subparagraph id="HE92FBC71ECFC40938E719B10AA5EE1BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>financial assistance awards, technical assistance, and other assistance the Secretary determines appropriate, to educational institutions and covered organizations and programs, including those serving unemployed energy workers; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1254795103E40D4A28AE9B0633A2DD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>eligible opportunities at the Department of Energy, including at the Department of Energy national laboratories.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0EAB7F1CEBF14C61BA2ABB51B3600C91"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy may only provide financial assistance for training programs under paragraph (1)(A) that have been approved by the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44B626B7822C4D48BE50EF230B319F65"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>Subject to subsection (c), the Secretary of Energy shall distribute assistance described in paragraph (1) in a manner proportional to the needs of energy-related industries and demand for occupations in energy-related industries, consistent with information developed under subsection (e).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0F30962582934142AC8FE369B474A0AB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDB058C5E07734EDFB294AB67C05AD19C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prioritize the education and training of individuals from disadvantaged communities for in-demand occupations in energy-related industries, including by providing eligible opportunities and employment at the Department of Energy, including at the Department of Energy national laboratories; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47641339EFE64ABDAA4C8660C570D489"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in providing research grants and technical assistance to educational institutions, give priority to minority-serving institutions.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2EEC4439C44E4882A3C1EE61FCD61AEA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Collaboration and outreach</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall—</text> <paragraph id="H7E38BA464E6842378028D982A6A7B975"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collaborate with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3B42AFA92D8A465BAB9064F78FD65F39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>State workforce development boards and local workforce development boards, to maximize program efficiency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9FC23FFFE2364B139E7BCCE42E00D561"><enum>(B)</enum><text>educational institutions and covered organizations and programs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCBB5A83209BA457297BD2B410D049DFA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>energy-related industries and covered organizations and programs to increase the opportunities for, and enrollment of, students and other candidates, including students of minority-serving institutions and unemployed energy workers, to participate in industry eligible opportunities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1BB3501A6BFD45368D808D87F5D09786"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal-State Regional Commissions, including the Appalachian Regional Commission, the Delta Regional Authority, the Denali Commission, the Northern Border Regional Commission, and the Southeast Crescent Regional Commission; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE852A57A29B847598FB5652D6ECC3E27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conduct outreach activities to—</text> <subparagraph id="HD33132BC2B1D4DBFA88FDE0D45157523"><enum>(A)</enum><text>encourage individuals from disadvantaged communities and unemployed energy workers to enter into the STEM fields; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8475EFB7D5E5486FBB7F01C6B80756CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>encourage and foster collaboration, mentorships, and partnerships among energy-related industries, and covered organizations and programs, that provide effective training programs for in-demand occupations in energy-related industries and educational institutions that seek to establish these types of programs in order to share best practices and approaches that best suit local, State, and national needs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1F93CB116D214F2D80AEE92B0F311E48"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clearinghouse</header> <paragraph id="HBA50EE36B0764BEC83CE70EFA4D0A492"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy, in collaboration with the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Commerce, the Director of the Bureau of the Census, and energy-related industries, shall establish a publicly accessible clearinghouse to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC3D91C41120846258269145DDE08D8BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop, maintain, and update information and other resources, by State and by region, on—</text> <clause id="H6A65014C2AB8469BB85B6473A0BE93D4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the current and future workforce needs of energy-related industries, and occupations in energy-related industries, including identification of in-demand occupations in energy-related industries; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H2F24626E30BE450396339B337B23E7F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">training programs for such in-demand occupations (including training programs provided by a provider of training services on any list described in section 122(d) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3152">29 U.S.C. 3152(d)</external-xref>)), which meet the guidelines prescribed under paragraph (3); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAD8718D71B7D4CB5B55017F268237254" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>act as a resource for educational institutions and covered organizations and programs that would like to develop and implement the training programs described in subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78D115FA15884AF497CCFB62DF8D36BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of existing resources</header> 
<subparagraph id="H2218433C7CD2498FA57F40E0D1FA93C2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Modification of existing online resource</header><text>In a case in which the Secretary of Energy determines that the modification of an existing online resource of the Department of Labor or the Department of Education would be an efficient and effective means of carrying out the purposes described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1), the Secretary of Energy may—</text> <clause id="H933F28432A1944D5B2B0DE347DEE0D0C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>request that the Secretary of Labor or the Secretary of Education, as appropriate, make such modification; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBD66C4079BFF46F799BE207FE8A3A32D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if such modification is made, elect not to establish the clearinghouse under paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9BA2123D32BD406C8BBB84707A00EC70"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Informational resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing and maintaining the clearinghouse under paragraph (1) or modifying the online resource under subparagraph (A), the Secretary of Energy shall, to the greatest extent practicable, utilize existing resources and information made available to the Secretary by the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Commerce, and the Director of the Bureau of the Census.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE80DB1A86F44E5F8AD2451109E2995A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, shall prescribe guidelines for the training programs described in paragraph (1)(A)(ii), which shall be similar to the requirements for providers of training services described in section 122(b) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3152">29 U.S.C. 3152(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A2832FA699B4BD2BDD4BF1E71CB1AB4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary of Energy shall annually publish, on a publicly accessible website of the Department of Energy, a report on the information and other resources developed, maintained, and updated on the clearinghouse established under paragraph (1) or the online resource modified under paragraph (2)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD8834A9B6B474280B9750AE5357C0E8B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Guidelines To develop skills for an energy industry workforce</header> 
<paragraph id="H00DDB6FEF9344D4FA6960B6B767960FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy, in collaboration with the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Labor, and the National Science Foundation, shall develop voluntary guidelines or best practices for educational institutions to help provide students with the skills necessary for in-demand occupations in energy-related industries, including in-demand occupations in—</text> <subparagraph id="H59C26D09C35744BAB3FB875DC5311709"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the energy efficiency industry, including in-demand occupations in energy efficiency (including architecture, design, and construction of new energy efficient buildings), conservation, weatherization, retrofitting, inspecting, auditing, and software development;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA759723ADFC6421090ECE29848E0A683"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the renewable energy industry, including in-demand occupations in the development, engineering, manufacturing, and production of energy from renewable energy sources (such as solar, hydropower, wind, and geothermal energy);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD5EB1C385B0B434DA324EE36CBE6C9F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the community energy resiliency industry, including in-demand occupations in the installation of rooftop solar, in battery storage, and in microgrid technologies;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H52C46820C20642E3AE3C8435A68C458D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the fuel cell and hydrogen energy industry;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F6834AB297C4B4DB087028510108C21"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the advanced automotive technology industry, including in-demand occupations relating to electric vehicle batteries, connectivity and automation, and advanced combustion engines;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4262C2D416BC4E23A3E2D5E55113A01B" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the manufacturing industry, including in-demand occupations as operations technicians, in operations and design in additive manufacturing, 3–D printing, and advanced composites and advanced aluminum and other metal alloys, and in industrial energy efficiency management systems, including power electronics, and other innovative technologies; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7808EA0AC1504275A0C47F942C3BC3D5"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the chemical manufacturing industry, including in-demand occupations in construction (such as welders, pipefitters, and tool and die makers), as instrument and electrical technicians, machinists, chemical process operators, engineers, quality and safety professionals, and reliability engineers;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE86A1414B9540FFA1F3AC48129514FE" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the electric utility and gas utility industries, including in-demand occupations in smart grid technology, cybersecurity management, and the generation, transmission, and distribution of electricity and natural gas, such as electricians and utility dispatchers, technicians, operators, lineworkers, engineers, scientists, and information technology specialists;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57E6BEDDE4EA494E947A040D936ABE11"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alternative fuels industry, including in-demand occupations in biofuel and bioproducts development and production;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBDFA4E840E25431DB95B1AC0C1A93642"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the pipeline industry, including in-demand occupations in pipeline construction and maintenance and occupations as engineers and technical advisors;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB929C7490F2C4500A0F65AE3EBB733F7"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the nuclear energy industry, including in-demand occupations as scientists, engineers, technicians, mathematicians, and security personnel;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8B8320AACA974BB188994D719034B985"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the oil and gas industry, including in-demand occupations as scientists, engineers, technicians, mathematicians, petrochemical engineers, and geologists; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA506C876A3694CC6BFF6D9C6A5946501"><enum>(M)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the coal industry, including in-demand occupations as coal miners, engineers, developers and manufacturers of state-of-the-art coal facilities, technology vendors, coal transportation workers and operators, and mining equipment vendors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B5E1D06F2D1450F9C9D7AF2C2CB1EDA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Input</header><text>The Secretary of Energy shall solicit input from energy-related industries in developing guidelines or best practices under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H932149AA703F4547B065EC623366BA98"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Energy efficiency and conservation initiatives</header><text>The guidelines or best practices developed under paragraph (1) shall include grade-specific guidelines for elementary schools and secondary schools for teaching energy efficiency technology, architecture, design, and construction of new energy-efficient buildings and building energy retrofits, manufacturing efficiency technology, community energy resiliency, and conservation initiatives.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F962D2170E14CC3BE75199F766D892E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>STEM education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The guidelines or best practices developed under paragraph (1) shall promote STEM education in educational institutions as it relates to in-demand occupations in energy-related industries listed under such paragraph.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2368C1460406407B8517D50A37260BD6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize the Secretary of Energy or any other officer or employee of the Federal Government to require or coerce a State or educational institution to adopt or carry out the guidelines or best practices developed under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8537CFCAB16A435281C1C368E8208DE9" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>21st Century Energy Workforce Advisory Board</header><text>If the Secretary of Energy has approved a strategy developed by the 21st Century Energy Workforce Advisory Board established under section 40211 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18744">42 U.S.C. 18744</external-xref>), the Secretary shall, to the extent the Secretary determines practicable and appropriate, carry out the program established under subsection (a) in accordance with such strategy.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDA07BAF849854B4B8506BD84C22D172B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Consolidation</header><text>To the extent practicable, the Secretary of Energy shall, to avoid duplication of efforts, carry out the Equity in Energy Initiative of the Department of Energy, the Minority Educational Institution Student Partnership Program of the Department of Energy, and any other program of the Department of Energy that the Secretary determines appropriate, through the program established under subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4A5271B894AE472CB031D0F982C474D1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE732F5288521460DA3BF8EDAD9966B68"><enum>3.</enum><header>Energy workforce grant program</header> <subsection id="H78FDC10ED7714C20A97B457061D29CFB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program</header> <paragraph id="H6394AEED6BB84104A54DB64F223B57C3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall establish and carry out a program to provide grants to eligible entities to pay the eligible wages of, and eligible payments for, individuals during the period that such individuals are receiving training to work for an eligible business. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6E54821D40E644EA9D030DC69F5D43AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy and eligible businesses, shall establish guidelines that identify—</text> <subparagraph id="H2798095885F74E46AFEFF0F769B7FA75" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>criteria for determining—</text> 
<clause id="H773C055D3204424AA5A09947790EF4E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">wages that are eligible for purposes of the program under paragraph (1); and</text></clause> <clause id="HF75B9338C6634988A5114AEB5A0CE4D6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>payments that are eligible for purposes of the program under paragraph (1), including payments that cover—</text> 
<subclause id="HCA6176EA08784452B030816601EAF663"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the costs of training that individuals receive under the program; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0206DE4F54E44E17BABD6DB482BA7179"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the costs of services that are necessary to enable the individuals to receive such training; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H31D6DD52511F4199B224E25657413D29"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">training that is eligible for purposes of the program under paragraph (1), which shall include any applicable training services described in section 134(c)(3)(D) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)(3)(D)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB115D23663994A1D8BD8204462295625"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grants</header> <paragraph id="H56EB343599C44146A80034615A862D2F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible wages</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under subsection (a) that is (or includes) an eligible business with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC6F6A8C790C24BBA9814CBD009304AC5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>20 or fewer employees may use such grant to pay up to 45 percent of the eligible wages of individuals for the duration of the applicable training for such individuals;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCBF5D86A4FDB48259578AC50F816F618" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">21 to 99 employees may use such grant to pay up to 37.5 percent of the eligible wages of individuals for the duration of the applicable training for such individuals; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFE70A0846BA247E4B4CCA63225E2907D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">100 employees or more may use such grant to pay up to 25 percent of the eligible wages of individuals for the duration of the applicable training for such individuals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D1E6ADB8DCF460BB9AD4105CE2A8732" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity may use a grant provided under the program established under subsection (a) to pay up to 100 percent of the eligible payments for individuals for the duration of the applicable training for such individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H117DBA78BB544B49B4D1E6A9B233CA53"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority for targeted communities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In providing grants under the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall give priority to an eligible entity that—</text> <paragraph id="HCBA8D93EA463488EBC4CAF3A9E13CA3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recruits or selects for training, or trains individuals, who are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2827B0C3279F48D0ADA860A09466DB0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>from the community that the eligible entity serves; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1EED4ABCDC304DFEBB00FAAAB27D7F2B"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE71F1D0C24004C95A49FB4FCCFA97CF3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>from disadvantaged communities;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE9C11DF8C3C24A9CB50692E9D7F75E48" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>individuals with barriers to employment; or</text></clause> <clause id="H00F1C4D24C20424A94AA4836A294C802" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>unemployed energy workers; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9157B6A554E648E0B1B57069C31ED47D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>will provide individuals receiving training with the opportunity to obtain or retain employment at an eligible business.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8698434B0E104F50B7DEAC282FD15F26"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limit</header><text>An eligible entity may not receive more than $100,000 under the program established under subsection (a) per fiscal year. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBB595A227BE14959BCBC2FA847CC6ABB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall submit to Congress, annually for each year the program established under subsection (a) is carried out, a report on such program, including—</text> <paragraph id="H77EB4B99B3B94FA193F57E37F36EC3C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of such program for the previous year, including the number of jobs filled by individuals trained pursuant to such program; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34BED183AAFC4B84B48C40C442C33E21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations on how to improve such program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA50A1EF8EAAA430BA3B7B6843526466B" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Integration of services for Tribes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of the Interior has approved a plan for an Indian Tribe in accordance with section 8 of the Indian Employment, Training, and Related Services Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3407">25 U.S.C. 3407</external-xref>), and such Indian Tribe is part of a Tribal consortium that receives a grant from the program established under subsection (a), such Indian Tribe may elect to integrate the grant, in whole or in part, in accordance with section 4 of the Indian Employment, Training, and Related Services Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3403">25 U.S.C. 3403</external-xref>), if all Indian Tribes in such Tribal consortium agree to such integration and the Secretary determines that such integration will not produce an inequitable result for any Indian Tribe in such Tribal consortium.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H010B28F97602480E9D3A0217404E8731"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H129EDAD88F724930BB91EEFD30C4E5E7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB70E1F5E842647CB95AE2324D77AF587"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprenticeship</header><text>The term <term>apprenticeship</term> means an apprenticeship registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the National Apprenticeship Act; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H73A4A89BF4EA43A9992AE2C5903F4C98" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered organizations and programs</header><text>The term <term>covered organizations and programs</term> means local workforce development boards, State workforce development boards, Indian tribes, Tribal organizations, Tribal consortia, nonprofit organizations, qualified youth or conservation corps, labor organizations, pre-apprenticeship programs, and apprenticeship programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H53CAF4F623034900927D98498FB6672F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disadvantaged community</header><text>The term <term>disadvantaged community</term> means a community that the Secretary of Energy determines, based on appropriate data, indices, and screening tools, is economically, socially, or environmentally disadvantaged.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H251EAA4E99EA44CF9015938CE63DFBC6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Educational institution</header><text>The term <term>educational institution</term> means an elementary school, secondary school, local educational agency, State educational agency, or institution of higher education. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD98CC9D52FD491D90120FEFA4B7DB6E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Elementary school and secondary school</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6DCF3C02B51B43C8B4685331B1A35C71" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible business</header><text>The term <term>eligible business</term> means a business that provides services related to— </text> 
<subparagraph id="HE6DD3EAC819D413986B721F18D0BCA9D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>renewable electric energy generation, including solar, wind, geothermal, hydropower, and other renewable electric energy generation technologies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83C056A86F4F459EBE1D6D381A30501C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>energy efficiency, including energy-efficient lighting, heating, ventilation, and air conditioning, air source heat pumps, advanced building materials, insulation and air sealing, and other high-efficiency products and services, including auditing and inspection, architecture, design, and construction of new energy efficient buildings and building energy retrofits;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBACD0F4EF54B43CB8AEF53093883E1F8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>grid modernization or energy storage, including smart grid, microgrid and other distributed energy solutions, demand response management, and home energy management technology;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9425BD77BF7143E0B212D5D78F06B379" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>advanced fossil energy technology, including—</text> 
<clause id="H078BB507A13647EE91B2EE1EB198F08F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advanced resource development;</text></clause> <clause id="H75DAC375F5CC44669585B2EEC4780683" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carbon capture, storage, and use;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6BA5EAC43D3F44A8A686EF63328C5548" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>low-carbon power systems;</text></clause> <clause id="H2244532341984F93A76E4BD439F1879D" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>efficiency improvements that substantially reduce emissions; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0C5D5348774148919605FC27A1944A96" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>direct air capture;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4D7635DCA7984669B3E64DA8369AD78F" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>nuclear energy, including research, development, demonstration, and commercial application relating to nuclear energy;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9ECB65DB5CF1421B8C00A3E2DF1FBF0C" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>cybersecurity for the energy sector, including infrastructure, emergency planning, coordination, response, and restoration;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF9D40AE2915413782EF6BB052CF9653" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>alternative fuels, including biofuel and bioproduct development and production;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD767A530DA9B4C1C8ED5024C675D06D8" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>advanced automotive technology, including electric vehicle batteries, connectivity and automation, advanced fueling or charging stations, and advanced combustion engines; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75FA1B558F3B46F2A8ABD82399F1BD98" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fuel cell and hybrid fuel cell generation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA77B563B8BD1443FB96E13326AD5456F" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H826AA52D13134B6AB3EFC85B414E5F3E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an eligible small business; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H25068FDCC82B42D9B99BE13262A98F32" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an partnership between or among—</text> <clause id="H484A00E40A3E4370BA89CECC29473796" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an eligible business; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE205D569E76044048E1840A5EBAD6770" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>one or more of the following:</text> <subclause id="H13C01739A98D48F89EBAD852AF14EE05" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A labor organization or joint labor-management organization with experience working in energy-related industries.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEA332605CFAE4FC68B8D0EACFE35898D" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>A nonprofit organization dedicated to helping individuals gain employment in energy-related industries.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAE25BBDE25994F4DB1D8DDF9D091DB4D" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>A community college or technical college with experience in providing training for individuals seeking employment in energy-related industries.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H27F582F684A24F819245AA819D471362" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>A qualified youth or conservation corps.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H781D2F0CEBD7400DB51FE5ED8583C516" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>A State development board or local workforce development board.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3FA382A0579B41C6BE771CA4FA5D9C07" commented="no"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>An Indian Tribe, Tribal organization, or Tribal consortium.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4CE2987881BB4A95B8E576DD1E38BC89" commented="no"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>An industry or sector partnership relating to energy-related industries.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B2612878D5F49F59B5D84C17A6DFFF9"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Eligible opportunity</header><text>The term <term>eligible opportunity</term> means a paid—</text> <subparagraph id="HBECC54ACFD6B4E8996B70CCC82D7C11D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>internship;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0874BD02C88A4221802A1FABAC4A4ABC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fellowship;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06A08E17FCE74FA99C171A58EA832B66"><enum>(C)</enum><text>apprenticeship; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE79B32C230074793ACDA68A5557550A5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>another work-based learning opportunity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0C069DF5BB9460E95D607156B10D52B" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Eligible payment</header><text>The term <term>eligible payment</term> means a payment that meets the criteria identified pursuant to the guidelines established under section 3(a)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCAE8A3A0126F4FA3A410D2D62533AB45" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Eligible small business</header><text>The term <term>eligible small business</term> means an eligible business with 75 or less employees. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H24FAE2E339D646239DB05700C054B483"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Eligible wage</header><text>The term <term>eligible wage</term> means a wage that meet the criteria identified pursuant to the guidelines established under section 3(a)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB251C8F2676A465B93D399D83E7631BC"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Energy-related industry</header><text>The term <term>energy-related industry</term> includes the energy efficiency industry, renewable energy industry, community energy resiliency industry, fuel cell and hydrogen energy industry, advanced automotive technology industry, chemical manufacturing industry, electric utility industry, gas utility industry, alternative fuels industry, pipeline industry, nuclear energy industry, oil and gas industry, vehicle fueling and charging industry, and coal industry.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF4540910A81465FAD60ACE0D62C26C6"><enum>(13)</enum><header>In-demand occupation</header><text>The term <term>in-demand occupation</term> has the meaning given the term <term>in-demand industry sector or occupation</term> in section 3(23)(A)(ii) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(23)(A)(ii)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38A3FE462D58463EB88C13A3D9975FCE" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Indian tribe and tribal organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Indian Tribe</term> and <term>Tribal organization</term> have the meanings given such terms in subsections (e) and (l) of section 4 of the <short-title>Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act</short-title> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22E304D275F5480DABB9B6762CD939F6" commented="no"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Individual with a barrier to employment</header><text>The term <term>individual with a barrier to employment</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F35154A3A434ECE944E6C784FF627B4" commented="no"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Industry or sector partnership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>industry or sector partnership</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA98A9A4C0304EAAA9D39EE1E2AD7631"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>), except that such term does not include institutions described in subparagraph (A) or (C) of subsection (a)(1) of such section 102.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9735597D777D456D855C223299C6D457"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Labor organization</header><text>The term <term>labor organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30DA47359B4545EAB92C0041D4B2424D"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Local workforce development board</header><text>The term <term>local workforce development board</term> means a local board, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H734A7A46570F450E8100590F753993FC"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Minority-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>minority-serving institution</term> means an institution of higher education that is of one of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HAEE7A69F75494C7F8B9977C8D9AC8568"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A Hispanic-serving institution (as defined in section 502(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101a">20 U.S.C. 1101a(a)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D20138E1A894399AEFBFA00B9B2E134"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A Tribal College or University (as defined in section 316(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H957A6F76213B4281994FD57DAF5C0826"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An Alaska Native-serving institution (as defined in section 317(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFC06EA2ED88940DDBAD004611276A8D5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A Native Hawaiian-serving institution (as defined in section 317(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H691A3823B5564F048AAEF652AF252E9A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A Predominantly Black Institution (as defined in section 318(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059e">20 U.S.C. 1059e(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H67041A8959EF45A286406143A4A93388"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A Native American-serving nontribal institution (as defined in section 319(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059f">20 U.S.C. 1059f(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4B41AB26692A4571B3B1F4941B5C2A90"><enum>(G)</enum><text>An Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution (as defined in section 320(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059g">20 U.S.C. 1059g(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5B5FE346E5014817B9C9F8EB026989ED"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A part B institution (as defined in section 322 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1061">20 U.S.C. 1061</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H919F5D04025F42B7A820F0292097B904"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Pre-apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term pre-apprenticeship program means a program designed to prepare individuals to enter and succeed in an apprenticeship, and includes each of the following elements:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6CF4E4865AAD4485897E1BFACAC8976B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Training and curriculum that aligns with the skill needs of employers in the economy of the State or region involved.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D28A90EE486497CB7C15C658E4D6D14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Access to educational and career counseling and other supportive services, directly or indirectly.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAEDD723C51FA4B2AB48E0D9F2D9EDD14"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Hands-on, meaningful learning activities that are connected to education and training activities, such as exploring career options, and understanding how the skills acquired through coursework can be applied toward a future career.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA6DD3DE5CEC45598B039211100CE230"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Opportunities to attain at least one industry-recognized credential.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFFFE67A6274E4855803012E85E25EFE7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A partnership with one or more apprenticeship programs that assists in placing individuals who complete the pre-apprenticeship program in a apprenticeship program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H366D5E77925C48968DEB77F662D8EEFC"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Qualified youth or conservation corps</header><text>The term <term>qualified youth or conservation corps</term> has the meaning given such term in section 203(11) of the Public Lands Corps Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1722">16 U.S.C. 1722(11)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72DC18BCD50945B69A7AFD76A08DAEE6"><enum>(23)</enum><header>State workforce development board</header><text>The term <term>State workforce development board</term> means a State board, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB57331A59EC24697AF3932717BBCF6D3"><enum>(24)</enum><header>STEM</header><text>The term <term>STEM</term> means science, technology, engineering, and mathematics.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB1477448F0EF4AF5976BAC91079EEC66"><enum>(25)</enum><header>Work-based learning</header><text>The term <term>work-based learning</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

