<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H50F2D5140C4D481CB38C1D7B822E5080" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5590 IH: No More Hard Stops Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5590</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require an officer or employee of the Federal Government who is required by law to appear on a regular basis to give oral testimony at a hearing of a committee of Congress to remain at the hearing until each member of the committee has been provided with the opportunity to question the officer or employee.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7F113CD07F3C4C50B8B95A55E7EBFB7D" style="OLC"><section id="HDC2537982D304302B6B2DE3457FAA77A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No More Hard Stops Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFB0092CCF0FA40ED870FE90476724249"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring Federal Government officials testifying at hearings of committees of Congress to remain until each member has been provided the opportunity to question</header><subsection id="H0A0A5E5834334578ACEC08573961303E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An officer or employee of the Federal Government who is subject to a requirement under law to appear on a regular basis to give oral testimony at a hearing of a committee of Congress shall not be considered to meet such requirement unless the officer or employee remains at the hearing until each member of the committee who is present at the hearing has been provided with the opportunity to question the officer or employee.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2B7982AE351947C88A4BE135628F9CF6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ensuring opportunity To question for each Member</header><paragraph id="H64AA30C906884561932DDC56F1F862DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The chair of a committee of Congress who presides at a hearing of the committee at which an officer or employee of the Federal Government appears pursuant to a requirement described in subsection (a) may not provide a member of the committee with a second opportunity to question the officer or employee at the hearing until each member of the committee who seeks to question the officer or employee has been provided with an opportunity to do so.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFF506C0CB9D4B7CADB81677418F14EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exercise of rulemaking power</header><text>This subsection is enacted by Congress—</text><subparagraph id="H7702FA4E8482438081DCD05FF0C1DB9E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and House of Representatives, respectively, and as such it is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, but applicable only with respect to the procedure to be followed in that House in the case of a Commission joint resolution, and it supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AC63B9F7D1A4D5FACC54F3EE45835AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8FBBD09DDC64726BF812BDECC9661F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act shall apply with respect to hearings held on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

