<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9BE8D515F723481C9EE62AD131F55439" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6662 IH: Transforming Hiring in Rural Industries and Vital Economies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6662</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000395">Mr. Rogers of Kentucky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a White House Rural Council, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCAF3C09AE1B448DBADA87718A89B9011" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0DC2DB1C15CF42C18856EAA81FEB855E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transforming Hiring in Rural Industries and Vital Economies Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5629B8192EBB4099A2854D459C3D18C0" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>White House Rural Council</header> <subsection id="H751543114EC747A492DD7B6AF979CC0B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Executive Office of the President a White House Rural Council (in this section referred to as the <quote>Council</quote>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8439327C608E43EEA35EC078B2A8D191"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<paragraph id="H0B4A1B128D06465AA9AD00CAF491AD4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chair</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall serve as the Chair of the Council.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H768EE88B85414C2AA434E012A0A647D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Members</header><text>The Council shall be composed of the heads of the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H72504ECC76C44F81AD31A2CC97E41266"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H020E895A024E409C96C7CCC171FEE454"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Defense.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7894C7D66BA045089A40E8AA092E0906"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA2F35E2F63354FBB8BC037B7C3063B0D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Department of the Interior.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4224512429F44B2AB44A0DD45030C77B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Department of Commerce.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDFF6C32250754BE0B45D815AB041F966"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Department of Labor.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H05447211667A451CBD935C43C71A9F61"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H91CCE38E802347AF84C80B5E1AA77E93"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF6D899F9C30A40D0BF7AAA6837953FDB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Department of Transportation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H14CA3FD0EAB8432B9A323CAE06040424"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD7A2EB462FF04F9AB550E2672E813D08"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Department of Education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H39E95CC614D84259A23FFE32411B4F10"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD9547B57DBBD4DC392739BF1B916F387"><enum>(M)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5E1B803CA7EF43729A0ED305CF8CB296"><enum>(N)</enum><text>The Environmental Protection Agency.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE19E2DC8332D4727A49CC9666A0F4B40"><enum>(O)</enum><text>The Federal Communications Commission.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE3EF0FA9C5264963894770BA470C8C45"><enum>(P)</enum><text>The Office of Management and Budget.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3186B497A4F747B39A808AEE6D25092B"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>The Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H82A64B109F1B48CDADA688DEE75F67C9"><enum>(R)</enum><text>The Office of National Drug Control Policy.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H5A0964E0483F41B3A3387A8721EC6CB7"><enum>(S)</enum><text>The Council of Economic Advisers.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HAC63A5E336BC45E28151DD79750FEDBC"><enum>(T)</enum><text>The Domestic Policy Council.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7A04378EB3004263B53A074B626CCC15"><enum>(U)</enum><text>The National Economic Council.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6BB0726C83FB48839D54B69C4E1352A3"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The Small Business Administration.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H15C79F352D904589A407D6426701934F"><enum>(W)</enum><text>The Council on Environmental Quality.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HFB4165934B714DD59389E0E8A882D7A3"><enum>(X)</enum><text>The White House Office of Public Engagement and Intergovernmental Affairs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6DD28F09CF06488CBBDFF9F21AE01C8F"><enum>(Y)</enum><text>The White House Office of Cabinet Affairs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H44BECC95804847E697750C10AE209AA5"><enum>(Z)</enum><text>Any other department, agency, or office of the executive branch as the President or Secretary of Agriculture may designate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HFE6D55B15304461EB8158821E7C50845"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Designees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any member of the Council may designate a senior-level official, who is employed full-time in the department, agency, or office of such member, to carry out the duties of the member under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H548820B2A35841D2AE4AC73057E285FB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every six months thereafter, the Council shall convene a meeting of representatives of the executive departments, agencies, and offices represented on the Council to develop plans to coordinate the efforts of such executive departments, agencies, and offices and facilitate efficient services to stakeholders. At such meetings, each such representative shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H88B295BE94AE4FC381FB4698DB22A57D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>share information regarding the rural economic development efforts and activities of the representative’s executive department, agency, or office;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H769FDB06788C4D2297DED05A4A8B983D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify opportunities for collaboration and coordination of research agendas, vulnerability assessments, data collection and analysis, and planning and implementing rural economic development projects;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF303DBF7C42428DB05E1777D9656F6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify rural economic development information needs, research gaps, and decision support needs that are not met by any executive department, agency, or office represented on the Council and make available such identification for purposes of information to be submitted to the Council;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74D07E5D04BA46D3BDA95C0FDDA8C679"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify common and complementary goals for rural economic development within each region to be prioritized for the coming year and beyond;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5E35EEBBEAB34E248488E0C9F26C61BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify barriers to rural economic development planning and implementation that can be overcome or minimized through Federal action and specific suggestions for improvement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B7034B4099F45A385EECDC3CFFD084B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>evaluate progress and jointly develop a strategy for realizing rural economic development-related goals, including clearly identified responsibilities by each collaborating regional office, center, or program; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H04EA18B442DA496FB8A1068AC8760644"><enum>(7)</enum><text>share experiences and best practices in stakeholder engagement and communication, decision support, and economic development interactions that support the realization of identified rural economic development goals.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H53D6D03CF07548F3943AB65523BD8657"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Council shall carry out the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H7C646B65EA784447B7BABB8B40A54D3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinate with the Domestic Policy Council and the National Economic Council to develop the policy of the Council.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF550E1809BA64588AA6D9EBC1BEB9489"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Coordinate with departments, agencies, and offices of the executive branch to develop policy recommendations that promote economic prosperity and quality of life in rural areas (as defined by the Secretary of Agriculture) throughout the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB911D6464AAA43E291B67380D4A8C1FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Make recommendations to the President, through the Director of the Domestic Policy Council and the Director of the National Economic Council, on how to best use Federal investments in rural areas for the purpose of facilitating job growth and economic development.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AEA6808C8324FB790A1669B0B56F107"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate and increase the effectiveness of Federal engagement with rural stakeholders, including agricultural organizations, small businesses, education and training institutions, health care providers, telecommunications services providers, research and land grant institutions, law enforcement, State, local, and Tribal governments, and nongovernmental organizations regarding the needs of rural areas throughout the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H749536A087F546D0B3303A906E7FF8F2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate Federal efforts directed toward the growth and development of geographic regions that encompass both urban and rural areas.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0EB380A38094339ADCB6C82D0A55DA0"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identify and facilitate rural economic opportunities associated with energy development, outdoor recreation, and other conservation-related activities.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF5826EA0A3314F4D9D429E40AEF392C2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture (or staff designated by the Secretary) shall provide to the Council administrative support services and additional resources, as appropriate, to the extent permitted by law and within existing appropriations. The Secretary shall determine the amount of funding and personnel necessary for the Council to carry out its duties and the amount of funding and personnel each department, agency, or office represented on the Council should contribute in order for the Council to carry out such duties. Such department, agency, or office shall, upon the request of the Secretary, make available to the Council personnel, administrative support services, and information.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCAFA558F8E774CF091357092810C1610"><enum>(f)</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header><text>No additional funds are authorized to carry out the requirements of this section. Such requirements shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

