<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H6DA0634D70464939B1B1903F428051C1">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5866 IH: Substance Use Disorder and Family Engagement in Recovery Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5866</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To ensure comprehensive wraparound services for families impacted by substance use disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE144EA09D67D46E79241E3DDD5EBEBCE">
<section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Substance Use Disorder and Family Engagement in Recovery Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAFE in Recovery Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="idcd0c983935a04896ad318369fc1fde9c"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring care and no undue family separation of families impacted by substance use disorder</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8cfe3ed0601e402dae96a8a3abdaf2c6"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 503 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/703">42 U.S.C. 703</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
<quoted-block id="id243F7A690791423F8D989709F750A762" style="OLC" act-name="">
<subsection id="id6A325106264044BBA77C7EC2EA3F36DB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitations on toxicology testing To detect substance use</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id60597285a92940ddbf0ee7e6ee566720"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>As a condition of receiving payments under this section, each State— </text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id98918214c78c494f8d8ed082e07b5dc1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not require the birthing parent of an infant who is identified as being affected by substance abuse or withdrawal symptoms resulting from prenatal drug exposure or a Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder to undergo toxicology testing to detect substance use unless the parent—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd8195c5e37724b1895f1fba1511471f7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gives clear and informed consent prior to such testing; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3995ed87a31048dba34d008f2ebb3be3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is able to access, if necessary for purposes of giving such consent, interpretation services and reasonable accommodations for disabilities;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8de0f10540114d969ececf64b50442e1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall ensure that a pregnant or postpartum individual taking a prescription drug, including a prescription drug for the treatment of a substance use disorder, in accordance with the recommendations of the prescribing practitioner, shall not be subject to investigations of child abuse and neglect on the basis that such individual is taking such prescription drug; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1532c8effc9740cda23b4ef93ad5aa10"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall ensure that— </text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1e9c7bff8ebf4851b39f5e4110026a7c"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any toxicology testing to detect substance use that is provided to a pregnant or postpartum individual taking a prescription drug, including a prescription drug for the treatment of a substance use disorder, in accordance with the recommendations of the prescribing practitioner is consented to by the pregnant or postpartum individual in accordance with subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc78c1a65ac3d4cc4a926e5ca9a709fc7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such testing (and the results of such testing) shall not affect the individual's access to care or public assistance and shall not be the sole factor in a family separation determination involving the individual; and </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="idebe3a64e8c544966896eca4c8cd340ce"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall ensure that any health care provider involved in the delivery or care of an infant identified as being affected by substance abuse or withdrawal symptoms resulting from prenatal drug exposure, or a Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder, is not required to notify the child protective services system of the State or any unit of local government of the State of the occurrence of such condition in such infant if such condition is the result of the birthing parent of the infant taking a prescription drug, including a prescription drug for the treatment of a substance use disorder, in accordance with the recommendations of the prescribing practitioner, and such provider has no other reason to suspect that the infant is in imminent danger of abuse or neglect. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ideba64caac30f4766bd72ccd360b78adc"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definition of prescription drug</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>prescription drug</term> means a drug approved under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>) or licensed under section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>) that is subject to section 503(b)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/353">21 U.S.C. 353(b)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="id91687460d1fe43e7b303029921746f68" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall take effect on the date that is 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id140ec4fb888842198c6bcc2f038a7b00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ensuring a whole-of-government approach through a Federal interagency task force to support families impacted by substance use disorders</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id406808f426324502b4ba8d3c543b8782"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><text>There is established within the Federal Government an interagency task force to improve—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd2b80e2bfa1d41e094515f02cdb194bc"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">efforts, resources, and services of the Federal Government to support families impacted by substance use disorders;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idafdc2d3650db43b685e425264f9396ce"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the utilization of such efforts, resources, and services; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id58325f01064145c2adcb25a2e4fe155e"><enum>(3)</enum><text>strategies to streamline the provision of comprehensive wraparound care for families impacted by substance use disorders. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PHA78EFCCE7FFE4CA195B5CBA0FDB6782F"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Membership</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH88968EABA4F64363BF38AFC6BF205FF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The task force shall be composed of the heads of the following Federal departments and agencies, or their designees:</text>
<subparagraph id="PH30BC3BF76E8645F49BB17D630BA1F00F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PHA3350B3DD20E4494950DFE2D83BE4533"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHBDC3D1170D1B4C55897FD491A1897994"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH7D4C5569CEC94A2D92027CBCBB87AA90"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH3898F0BABAF94B5787A7F70F1F0E0252"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Indian Health Service.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PHA4C4E87ECA5346308F6A584355F76FEA"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH88D74A6B95654E75ACBF46679E483BFB"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The National Institutes of Health.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PHEE12243BC16B4E329ECC99BECAB10F84"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Food and Drug Administration.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHA0B27228560247EBA0F46FFDB6EFE0C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Health Resources and Services Administration.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PHB798DDD5E549468380AD77AEA00BD91C"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Department of Defense.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH9879EA1E75064123A56035B3E6312A61"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Office of Minority Health of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH5238FF4997F648EE8D99FA565CD9BAEB"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The Administration for Children and Families.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH8F4D2EB89B484C31BC9EBD6D3DDBFF08"><enum>(M)</enum><text>The Office of the Assistant Secretary for Planning and Evaluation of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH9DEEBE5CFCBD43A6B4204CDBA42F1ED2"><enum>(N)</enum><text>The Office for Civil Rights of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH2EA4CC696EBD4E2BB05BC940A1EC4A5D"><enum>(O)</enum><text>The Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH6CA54CA18DA241949F22D5B4226CB6B2"><enum>(P)</enum><text>The Office of Community Oriented Policing Services of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH77BA3DCC799049728347137BCC369E1D"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>The National Center for Education Evaluation and Regional Assistance of the Department of Education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH4DF8390F6CC6462C89CE8056E8865B3A"><enum>(R)</enum><text>The National Center for Special Education Research of the Institute of Education Science.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHAAEC16F54C2F469A80BE40D42FB29555"><enum>(S)</enum><text>The Office of Elementary and Secondary Education of the Department of Education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH47B5C89B23234C53B1297B88902A2A5D"><enum>(T)</enum><text>The Office for Civil Rights of the Department of Education.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHC2B1B5F654784B039B3D8D4C1BD0ACA8"><enum>(U)</enum><text>The Office of Special Education and Rehabilitative Services of the Department of Education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH43217AB1CB1F4913BC11CC9130F960EB"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The Bureau of Indian Affairs of the Department of the Interior.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHBBD4DAE87B5B4FE1BC073477324B037A"><enum>(W)</enum><text>The Veterans Health Administration of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH914C33A76050407A9B159C2F6432248A"><enum>(X)</enum><text>The Office of Special Needs Assistance Programs of the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PHC5E1C722E7E34C3B8DD69DF236410659"><enum>(Y)</enum><text>The Office of Head Start of the Administration for Children and Families.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PH4B22A6BEA9154970B0DDF375676B8F96"><enum>(Z)</enum><text>The Children’s Bureau of the Administration for Children and Families.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="PH1F7CFA20880248EBAEE803D5FC978442"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>The Bureau of Indian Education of the Department of the Interior.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="PHFA27248563434EFBB328203473167C15"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>Such other Federal agencies as the Secretaries determine to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH65D22A79801C4080A25BF1D458E7ECBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Date of appointments</header><text>The heads of Federal departments and agencies shall appoint the corresponding members of the task force not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH2FD61092C9DD4157A29003013FE84633"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The task force shall be chaired by the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idEFC9A7BF685D44E89718E3381B4076BD"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Duties</header><text>The interagency task force shall carry out each of the following activities:</text> <paragraph id="idb991923d2681470b866c3806a78f97ea"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Solicit input from stakeholders, including frontline service providers, educators, mental health professionals, researchers, experts in infant, child, and youth trauma, child welfare professionals, people in recovery, and the public, in order to inform the activities under this subsection. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="ideb1d90d31b9a47b3874d752f07576687" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Compile a comprehensive list of all Federal Government efforts, resources, and services to support families impacted by substance use disorders.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="ida40dc0045c77417b9bb7cab216baab73" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Assess the effectiveness of care, services, and resources available to families impacted by substance use disorders.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id3ee34cb26f7b4ec8bf5408acbadb5f0a" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Analyze and make recommendations for means of eliminating barriers that prevent individuals with substance use disorders from entering and remaining in care for the disorder involved.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id7dd3383e93424ab08e639b4d1b5407f4" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Analyze and make recommendations for means of eliminating barriers to social services for individuals with substance use disorders and their families.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id3a41f9aeb8da4c77a00d1d002697d87d" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Provide recommendations for effectively streamlining the provision of comprehensive wraparound care for families impacted by substance use disorders.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="id1a5757acef5d4b988af058c84af118cb" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Recommend a plan for addressing the comprehensive wraparound care needs of families impacted by substance use disorders and specifically address in the plan the needs of populations most disproportionately affected.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="id6c08732481114e8ab51dff56e6b59fe7" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Other activities as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH7EA83255D1CA465CB288BF8A2A59348B"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Operating plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the task force shall hold the first meeting. Not later than 2 years after such date of enactment, the task force shall submit to the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of the Interior, the Attorney General, and Congress an operating plan for carrying out the activities of the task force described in subsection (c). Such operating plan shall include—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH2D3ABB9E4E144A74A3A27571ADFBF938"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a list of specific activities that the task force plans to carry out for purposes of carrying out duties described in subsection (c), which may include public engagement;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH5F5FB3D2CEB34CD19C79E382F6872391"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan for carrying out the activities under subsection (c);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PHA673098D4FB14300976EA8A3CE08F70F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a list of members of the task force and other individuals who are not members of the task force that may be consulted to carry out such activities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PHC93C5E0A8A5C4366B0034E7B01D63874"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an explanation of Federal agency involvement and coordination needed to carry out such activities, including any statutory or regulatory barriers to such coordination;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH05D84FC7D92B4DD78FBBFC5BA6A5D0FA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a budget for carrying out such activities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH9DA63366153A4F3198A584FE9254E59A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a proposed timeline for implementing recommendations and efforts identified under subsection (c); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PHD56C631BEB7F4513B2C0A4B2A5096BF5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>other information that the task force determines appropriate as related to its duties.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="idb262171d377740138b913856c0f0b4d5" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress and the general public a final report that contains the findings and recommendations (including the recommended plan described in subsection (c)(7)) of the task force.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH38B399ADDD3B48F0A8020F8D253C69D8"><enum>(f)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Additional reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the final report under subsection (e), the task force shall submit—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH59FE4B7BA6D34046BA7D8621702A26E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a report to Congress identifying any recommendations identified under subsection (c) that require additional legislative authority to implement; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PHD40718B5FC8D4084AD9153B876A15971"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a report to the Governors describing opportunities for local- and State-level partnerships, professional development, or best practices to support families impacted by substance use disorders.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="PH13F383D8BD3A4916A19FE6B95B712128"><enum>(g)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The task force shall sunset on the date that is 60 days after the submission of the report under subsection (e), but not later than September 30, 2028.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="id9ea75d30d98f429fac88b696dbf92f44" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definition of comprehensive wraparound care</header><text>In this section, the term <term>comprehensive wraparound care</term> includes clinical, ancillary health, mental health, substance use disorder, and social support services, to address a substance use disorder. </text></subsection></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfc6422f6a0b94b17b3c6413d81cf441c"><enum>4.</enum><header>Increasing access to behavioral health care through community health centers</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id84f144d146fb4070b4428f9975891ee8"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Required primary health services</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id45e8fb250eb34d78a2774dd6618671e7"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Section 330(b) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide4552bb887854c3f992a6982a4a5eac3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1)(A)(i)—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide652a56f73ec4303af2f54a778e71cc9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subclause (IV), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddece3b11e7cd4fb8aea8382457c8ff88"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subclause (V), by striking the semicolon and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide1bf1fbddb874b2495839e08f30f2fe0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8A0B4A9B39CA4AF8BAA54DFC56DF6651">
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3efafd3797df42ae89d9575f3505bf7a"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>behavioral and mental health and substance use disorder services;</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id909285ba7cb445e18b151a2f5fbe181e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A)(ii), by inserting <quote>, including such referrals to certified community behavioral health centers</quote> before the semicolon; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb7e05dce90cc484d97eb73dd516fc7f9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id085d2305191a4f34b5d4dbffccb449b1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subparagraph (A); and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb9d21ba9b8ce4f2ca7375c9e73d911b3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (D) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd3eeda215780445eaf1153ee6b49f95b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>For purposes of assisting health centers in incorporating behavioral and mental health and substance use disorder services into the required primary health services offered by such centers, there is appropriated to the Secretary of Health and Human Services, out of amounts in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $500,000,000 for fiscal year 2025, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5a47ddc3349a4009ad1e48ef9aa2ceec"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date that is 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit a report to Congress on—</text> <subparagraph id="idc31a16ebf36943e084b5b918014a709b"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the impact that the amendments made by paragraph (1) has had on access to behavioral and mental health and substance use disorder services; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id095662c1fcd94903b683f7ea90397f8e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>employee recruitment and retention for behavioral and mental health and substance use disorder providers, including for health centers, certified community behavioral health centers, and other community care settings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idaaa9d8b5500a461fa91b7b85f872b764"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Environmental justice communities</header><text>Section 10503 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b-2">42 U.S.C. 254b–2</external-xref>) is amended— </text>
<paragraph id="idf8e9fd7279134cb797311cd2301378aa"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc42874c58f3e4629b8637048c406b9f6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0e7b30a382c04083a8ea987a1768be55"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9CBADAEBDE4749F8AA9580DE58E322A1"> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1239972623dc4ab69c7ed283abf73bd4"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$130,000,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subparagraph>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide196686a3e8744f0ade73010881238a0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Environmental justice communities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that not less than 50 percent of the amounts appropriated under subsection (b)(1) for fiscal year 2024 or any fiscal year thereafter are awarded to entities for use with respect to projects or sites located in or serving communities with significant representation of communities of color, low-income communities, or Tribal and Indigenous communities that experience, or are at risk of experiencing, higher or more adverse human health or environmental effects.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0680bf24ad434afb8e850c469a313c84"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No amounts made available under this section may be used for any activity that is subject to the reporting requirements set forth in section 203(a) of the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/433">29 U.S.C. 433(a)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="idf66fdf1a07694e1aa9ce173a7dcc4e69"><enum>5.</enum><header>Improving outcomes for pregnant and postpartum patients with substance use disorder and payments to incentivize care for opioid use disorder</header>
<subsection id="ide5b3f602222a43a3a7988ad1abc3a49b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1866F(b)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc-6">42 U.S.C. 1395cc–6(b)(1)</external-xref> is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idDB969D73F3CB47AFAD9D53F80479D563"> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id123457f6d0644b0180c7c04d74c8c6d5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Improves outcomes for pregnant and postpartum individuals with opioid use disorder.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="id816332be191e489db5869c7ef8fe11bf"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payments</header><text>Section 1866F(e)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc-6">42 U.S.C. 1395cc–6(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0c43c0a6dce34615befcb45b70e3b360"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>pregnancy and postpartum services and</quote> after <quote>including</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id81aa6e98ede340cc844c8226662f364e"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id33a5ac76f7ed4c619a7cd79bc6d679d2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id327fb00ebce442d7b475a2044b3d4c95" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc0f504f5def94452a36d78f1e0b1e8c5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id108E6054E20C4779A1E9FBD02BF8049E">
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0481da37dcfb4a86a963670e9c17d6f0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>pay a higher per applicable beneficiary per month care management fee for an applicable beneficiary who receives pregnancy or postpartum services from a participant.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2679d11c6eed4d7495ad8a5fb65d26d2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on January 1, 2024, and shall apply to services furnished on or after that date. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="id9b100169aead48fc98b02f8b343cba09"><enum>6.</enum><header>Increasing access to wraparound services for children from families impacted by substance use disorder</header>
<subsection id="id77c35c42bc034d4ba288ee5fb6751e2e"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Head Start Act is amended by inserting after section 645A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9840a">42 U.S.C. 9840a</external-xref>) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id073AF2342A184CFF88BA4564E4F1D2E8"> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf668fc19ba164243919a311bda6a4803"><enum>645B.</enum><header>Children from families impacted by substance use disorder</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida36f128009d34f8da432443bc2d7e368"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id74b6a5dfcbc04a4da8e0a3cae8be38c9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make grants, in accordance with paragraph (2), to Head Start and Early Head Start agencies to enable the agencies to provide comprehensive health, educational, nutritional, social, and other services to children in Head Start and Early Head Start programs, respectively, from families impacted by substance use disorder, or referring the children to such services, to assure best outcomes for the health, wellness, and school readiness of the children.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id19088EFB2BE44746962E519306FC637F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Formula</header><text>The Secretary shall make those grants, to fund the activities described in paragraph (1) for a fiscal year, by—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7382c38ba7494eeba9c1a6d8bd19d871"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using the amount appropriated under subsection (c) for that fiscal year; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8f561e2b6474435eb5cec9d20037abbd"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">distributing that amount in accordance with clauses (i) (with respect to additional funding for the comprehensive services described in paragraph (1)) and (ii) of section 640(a)(4)(C). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id36edbd74ba9a46daba034b7a05ba76dd"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Construction</header><text>A reference in this subchapter (other than this section) to funds appropriated or provided under this subchapter shall not be considered to include funds appropriated or provided under this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc9235a8783a547a09f06b40864134fe2"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $60,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each subsequent fiscal year.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="idffd98c0e0abb4380ab680d643ba54fff" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 639 of the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9834">42 U.S.C. 9834</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 657B</quote> and inserting <quote>sections 645B and 657B</quote>. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="id328e94f4f87b46489dd4c71f61955c0a"><enum>7.</enum><header>Coordinating research of the National Institutes of Health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/281">42 U.S.C. 281 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4dc3c75502fd476f9cc6e2cc28d51472"> <section id="id024af7f442124ce6ac1c794f1c783498"><enum>404P.</enum><header>Research with respect to co-occurring pregnancy and substance use disorder</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the National Institutes of Health shall establish a consortium on pregnancy, postpartum recovery, and substance use disorder research to establish research priorities and steward research activities across the national research institutes and national centers to understand and mitigate the harms of substance use disorder for pregnant and postpartum patients and their children.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="idc195924a5eb64c52a08644d3b9c03c05"><enum>8.</enum><header>Ensuring the use of best available medical practices through a GAO report on clinical guidelines for treating pregnant and parenting patients with substance use disorder and their children</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text> <paragraph id="id3a1532d2e5764d919e16d4c05ba95b38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a study assessing—</text>
<subparagraph id="id548ba2eb69b94a009b134adc63e90cdb"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the extent to which clinical guidelines for treating pregnant and parenting patients with substance use disorder and their children are implemented;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="id11b681cfe67448ee9a7046dc77b366c4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any systemic and other barriers to ensuring that patients and children described in subparagraph (A) get access to up-to-date care that addresses the complexity of co-occurring substance use disorder and pregnancy; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="id2e2c66b065674aea9965af48aa31aeea"><enum>(C)</enum><text>access to treatment for pregnant and postpartum individuals with substance use disorder and the impacts of interactions with child welfare systems; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="id97783ba49caa4a63aecd0720f528a04f"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, submit a report to Congress on the results of such study. </text></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


