<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD86D8B5BAD7410EBC9C5E006EB7C021" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6195 IH: Wildland Firefighter Fair Pay Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6195</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to establish a special limitation on pay for wildland fire responders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8FE22BC822EF49B4ADCDB15C2CF674F4" style="OLC"><section id="H5CBE478160B94EC7A56FD6580E53D991" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wildland Firefighter Fair Pay Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD2DE2B56EE6743D49B134CCC810D081A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Special limitations on pay for wildland fire responders</header><subsection id="HAFF6517BE4714D97BA796B2292C5D51D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1A4D1E66116F40F08CD2056A5EF2971B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 5541(2)(xi), by inserting <quote>, 5547a(h),</quote> after <quote>section 5544</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60A0E48FC1474C2299980F86E3CDF808"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 5547 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47639FD6107B4CB59CB4705AC90B92BA"><section id="HD6BE753279114019B1B19EB9848BCCA0"><enum>5547a.</enum><header>Special limitations on premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header><subsection id="H314E96F4FDDC40198A8CB0451BCCBDEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HBC18434B2B7A4E459E869232EB3BD042"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>covered employee</term> means an employee of the Forest Service, the Department of the Interior, or the National Weather Service who—</text><subparagraph id="HFFF4BE41E54D48D9AB918A957E375827"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a wildland firefighter;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA7E68798CA6408593D7BC9B27F55895"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is an incident meteorologist accompanying a crew of wildland firefighters;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2704A7E5CD44507B155E7AFD321A087"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is serving on an incident management team or at a wildland fire operations center; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H963E6D2506AC428286F2FD9B3AB0EB7D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is otherwise certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident related duties during the period that employee is assigned to a qualifying incident;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7D65AFCF85E468BA8DB77A9832706B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>covered services</term> means services performed by an employee that are determined by the Secretary of the Interior, the Secretary of Agriculture, or the Secretary of Commerce, as applicable, to primarily involve emergency wildfire suppression activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEDBE2CC3DD545068CAB5617DD0F4252"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>emergency wildland fire suppression activities</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H1390CD86CBE949ABB4419D8674F51B9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means initial-response and extended-response activities that directly relate to suppression of a wildfire;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26777E1F3500442782243F02FA5D54E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes activities associated with a severity incident; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A848C09FAAF4B219839F1283285C4E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not include activities associated with a prescribed fire incident;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H96BCC2A23B9E48E1B5A60CD2308260AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>firefighter</term> means an employee who—</text><subparagraph id="H6A33D11CAC524EAEB24445DBD4FD5D73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a firefighter within the meaning of section 8331(21) or section 8401(14);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E62D5CEE90C488AB344A518FC8D65C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who holds a supervisory or administrative position and is subject to subchapter III of chapter 83, but who does not qualify to be considered a firefighter within the meaning of section 8331(21), would otherwise qualify if the employee had transferred directly to that position after serving as a firefighter within the meaning of that section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7D47899F0FB4A6FA3D207A78DB57858"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who holds a supervisory or administrative position and is subject to chapter 84, but who does not qualify to be considered a firefighter within the meaning of section 8401(14), would otherwise qualify if the employee had transferred directly to that position after performing duties described in section 8401(14)(A) for at least 3 years; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F134A81F7C048F08A5EA008762C275D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who is not subject to subchapter III of chapter 83 or chapter 84, holds a position that the Office of Personnel Management determines would satisfy subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) if the employee were subject to subchapter III of chapter 83 or chapter 84;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66D725C2C1E742FEB6215F3A9698683D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>prescribed fire incident</term> means a wildland fire originating from a planned ignition in accordance with applicable laws, policies, and regulations to meet specific objectives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54B2CB87D40C4915B79B711EFFF71763"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>premium pay</term> means the premium pay paid under the provisions of law cited in section 5547(a), except as otherwise provided in subsection (g);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F7732A66C40407D8188A32A39FF8CCC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>qualifying incident</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HC3A7DC5B29CD484E872334D184185A06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a wildfire incident, a prescribed fire incident, or a severity incident; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1F038BF537548A3A4FFC6B89E0C53AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an initial response incident involving a single operational period of less than 36 hours (unless a longer period is approved by an authorized agency due to exceptional circumstances) if the applicable employee is in continual work status with no designated sleep and rest period established by the agency;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCED7AAB0422E49F69FA57B893A12AA88"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the term <term>severity incident</term> means an incident in which a covered employee is pre-positioned in an area where conditions indicate there is a high risk of wildfires;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C8C74A4724747A3A71727145389C481"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the term <term>wildfire incident</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H6B370845B3A64A10AE019E24B655AA67"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a wildland fire originating from an unplanned ignition, such as lightning, volcanos, or a human-caused fire; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD46985C4B0D446E88B0BD1D3F5DC2574"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a prescribed fire that is declared to be a wildfire; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H98DCFD9EF9C640CB85B696669DC2A233"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the term <term>wildland firefighter</term> means a firefighter—</text><subparagraph id="H31692D07BE6340CA8E81354E2B2BABC5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is employed by the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A91A16955FA40CE96A30067641D29FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the duties of the position of whom primarily relate to fires occurring in forest lands, range lands, or other wildlands, as opposed to structural fires.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08EAA375CF7C4486AABD1EF7A2867B16"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of premium pay</header><text>Any premium pay earned by a covered employee for covered services shall be disregarded in calculating the aggregate of the basic pay and premium pay of the covered employee for purposes of applying a limitation under section 5547.</text></subsection><subsection id="H35E074DFF5D54138BD9BEFEACFEF8766"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of disregarded premium pay</header><text>Any premium pay that is disregarded under subsection (b) shall be disregarded in calculating the aggregate pay of the applicable covered employee for purposes of applying the limitation in section 5307.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB71BFD2E3DE4303A52E09CB920DAD04"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><paragraph id="HD5434098BCF84A8FB6EB3C6FA6926A85"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Pay that is disregarded under subsection (b) may not be paid to the extent that such pay would cause the aggregate of the basic pay, premium pay, and hazard pay of the applicable covered employee under section 5545(d) payable in the applicable calendar year to exceed the rate of basic pay payable for a position at level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313, as in effect at the end of that calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD73A2189F7AB476EA7338035A7678939"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Biweekly limitation</header><text>For the purposes of paragraph (1), any premium pay that is subject to a biweekly limitation under section 5547(c) shall be paid first before other premium pay in applying the level II limitation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3FB1216D2544DE98E947A414B3F1810"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Relationship to lump-Sum payment</header><text>Any additional pay resulting from application of this section may not be used in computing a lump-sum payment for accumulated and accrued annual leave under section 5551 or 5552.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B95B33129BC496DB2D0AA612CD5797D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Records</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior, the Secretary of Agriculture, and the Secretary of Commerce shall each maintain records that document uses of the authority provided under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBFD325EFE393422985CA3BB3783D7CB4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation for prevailing rate employees</header><paragraph id="H78188C57A9CD48DABC8BDD2CE2D357DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HCBF3831926B4468D92ADEF4C8FF59D5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>basic pay</term> means wages, environmental differential pay, and night shift differential pay; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4806CEF5785A41128F8D09326A230055"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>premium pay</term> means overtime pay, Sunday premium pay, and holiday premium pay.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC65C37CD355D48D9A25018C35E057FE0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>For a prevailing rate employee described in section 5342(a)(2)(A) who is a covered employee, premium pay may not be paid to the extent that payment would cause the aggregate of the basic pay and premium pay of the covered employee in the applicable calendar year to exceed the rate of basic pay payable for a position at level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313, as in effect at the end of that calendar year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDB089DA52E742159885F0D46E48040C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item for section 5547 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H140145312C1740AA82008267D3658265" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">5547a. Special limitations on premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC00C677221F74787801C99FC8D31A900"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disregarding of premium pay for certain purposes</header><text>For the purpose of applying section 5547 of title 5, United States Code, as carried out pursuant to the requirements of section 1701 of division B of the Extending Government Funding and Delivering Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5547">5 U.S.C. 5547</external-xref> note) (as amended by section 601 of title VI of division HH of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2022 and section 440 of title IV of division G of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023), in calendar year 2023, incident standby premium pay shall be included in premium pay that is subject to the limits established pursuant to those requirements, as so amended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D9EF13ACC0E480DB28B5072F5256A22"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><paragraph id="HEE24B5523C1B4F10A4A2D25718753CDE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall take effect on the first day of the first pay period that has a payment date in January 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEE34A75A30B45A395F18A0E4551E281"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disregarding of premium pay</header><text>Subsection (c) shall take effect on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB359658FFB2A440DA14DBC95340BCF56"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports on hiring wildland firefighters and incident meterologists</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE961B600CE7846FD843C84A532A9DFDC"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H9C0677C59E734218872731C309BD4972"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees defined</header><text>The term <term>relevant congressional committees</term> means—</text><clause id="HCC2CE37BBDDF4280A4195C562DAC2620"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></clause><clause id="HED612BB81ACF40EDAA40B9F198712BB1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on Oversight and Reform of the House of Representatives;</text></clause><clause id="H567C69E2E8174C088740E306DE621E61"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></clause><clause id="H5912CB27091E4B6C9104444D3BDB4DE6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2BB69C1746C4535AAB8DCB39DD55802"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB728992586B34FF486048614D28F90A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Agriculture;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D2F52DA756F4A1FA1E80BDDB60EC1B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7942275D97041BDA0DA8796EE5CDCBB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77990E5105D241D58085B9A5065D1286"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports required</header><text>Not later than March 30, 2024, each Secretary concerned, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Management and Budget and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a plan that addresses the needs of the Department of Agriculture, the Department of the Interior, or the National Weather Service, as applicable, to hire and train additional wildland firefighters or incident meteorologists (as those terms are defined in section 5547a of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a)) such that sufficient personnel resources are available throughout the year without causing those wildland firefighters or incident meteorologists to receive compensation, in a typical calendar year, in excess of the annual rate for level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

