<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF18307CC3A04492D9A099C12A55B1207" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 3589 IH: Affordability is Access Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3589</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require group health plans and group or individual health insurance coverage to provide coverage for over-the-counter contraceptives.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H771A0A5E15E34D4DBDDA751761E5A33E" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H11F4F9198F3E4CF885DA90E543BCF23B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Affordability is Access Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF548A2AB173F4285BB5087D0FF49AD6D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to ensure timely access to affordable birth control by requiring coverage without cost-sharing for contraceptives that are approved, granted, or cleared by, or otherwise legally marketed under regulation by, the Food and Drug Administration for use without a prescription.</text></section><section id="H5FCF9A9790D1400EBA37B47877C309EC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HCA78085F1A0A4092B53DE763BB0AE070"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Birth control is critical health care that almost all women, as well as many trans men and nonbinary people, will use at some point in their lifetimes. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A02AD878C16402B92031E4A664E4256"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Access to the full range of reproductive health care, including birth control coverage as guaranteed under Federal law, provides individuals with the opportunity to lead healthy lives and get the care they need to reach their goals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5DF1E5590B44CB49BE6203CAB6CD750"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Contraceptive access is associated with health benefits for women, newborns, families, and communities and can lower the risk of harm to maternal and infant health. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB240C3DA6CD84329B2F7082EB91DC0EC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An estimated 73 million women of reproductive age (ages 15 through 49) live in the United States. Among the 46 million of such women who are sexually active and not seeking children, 89 percent use a form of birth control. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2149E56F8B74C648A449D649FA265C5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The birth control benefit enacted under the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>) has been a crucial step forward in advancing access to birth control and has helped ensure 58 million women have the power to decide for themselves if and when to become pregnant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF051259DB7E4A45AD00950E440AA6A2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Despite legal requirements for birth control coverage and access to services, gaps remain for millions of individuals. Nearly 1 in 5 women are not using their preferred method of contraception, and of those women, a quarter say it is because of cost. As a result, many women have gone without the birth control they want to use, also creating inconsistent use. Access to birth control is particularly difficult for the 19 million women of reproductive age with lower incomes who live in contraceptive deserts and lack reasonable access to a health center that offers the full range of contraceptive methods. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3DBF515E20748BBAFD0240D2692C62C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Due to systemic discrimination, people paid low wages, people of color, LGBTQ+ individuals, immigrants, and people with disabilities are more likely to face barriers to, and lack access to, health coverage and health care providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8771ABFE4F044C19AF1717454BE0FDB3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>There are numerous social and economic factors that make it harder to access birth control, including rising income and wealth inequality, gaps in insurance coverage, and barriers to accessing health providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AD630650154453DAB8D40E4058C5242"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Leading health experts support over-the-counter birth control pills.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H59E7F169E4D44D1C88666B60C0C7C253"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HE4BCBA65CA7749549E840BBFD8A32C6C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in order to increase access to oral birth control, such birth control must be both easier to obtain and affordable and, to make such birth control either easier to obtain or more affordable, but not both, is to leave unacceptable barriers in place;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABD4A7C59F53417AB6F43717D5DB31DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>it is imperative that the entities that research and develop oral birth control and whose medical and scientific experts have developed clinical and other evidence that oral birth control for routine, daily use is safe and effective when sold without a prescription, apply to the Food and Drug Administration for review and approval for sale of such birth control without a prescription;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0777AE3308A14981B2E78E3D998736B4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>upon the receipt of such an application, the Food and Drug Administration should determine whether the oral birth control meets the rigorous safety, efficacy, and quality standards for over-the-counter use under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>), and if the product meets those standards, the Food and Drug Administration should approve the application without delay; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E655D0A83664D95B2C614F881EFBA20"><enum>(4)</enum><text>if and when the Food and Drug Administration approves an oral birth control that is available over-the-counter, such birth control should be covered by health insurance, without a prescription and without cost-sharing.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0243F37F7788442BBB5F37EC248D0A95"><enum>5.</enum><header>Clarifying coverage requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretaries of Health and Human Services, Labor, and the Treasury shall clarify that coverage of contraceptives pursuant to section 2713(a)(4) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-13">42 U.S.C. 300gg–13(a)(4)</external-xref>) includes coverage of over-the-counter contraceptives approved, granted authorization for emergency use, or cleared by the Food and Drug Administration, even if the enrollee does not have a prescription for the contraceptive.</text></section><section id="H252B240F0D7043188BF8C1A6408CB7B0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><subsection id="H76B7586C09B543AF8C3B3BFE37496532"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Non-Interference with FDA regulation</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to modify or interfere with Food and Drug Administration processes to review, approve, clear, or authorize for emergency use, or otherwise determine the safety and efficacy of, and make available, non-prescription drugs or devices, modify or interfere with the scientific and medical considerations of the Food and Drug Administration, or alter any other authority of the Food and Drug Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7A8147C3595543BB8D44BE3D2C48FBD6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Non-Preemption</header><text>Nothing in this Act preempts any provision of Federal or State law to the extent that such Federal or State law provides protections for consumers that are greater than the protections provided for in this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3D5A6EE7FB294B8491E5437B607ACF18"><enum>7.</enum><header>Duties of retailers to ensure access to contraception for use without a prescription</header><subsection id="HA9A6328F6C354D62A89F9A91B97A7AFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any retailer that stocks contraception that is approved, granted authorization for emergency use, or cleared by, or otherwise legally marketed under regulation by, the Food and Drug Administration for use without a prescription may not interfere with an individual's access to or purchase of such contraception or access to medically accurate, comprehensive information about such contraception.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE51F1642D76E4A7F976B6FC01A448BF2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Nothing in this section shall prohibit a retailer that stocks over-the-counter contraceptive products from refusing to provide an individual with such contraceptive product that is approved, granted, or cleared by, or otherwise legally marketed under regulation by, the Food and Drug Administration if the individual is unable to pay for the contraceptive product, directly, through insurance coverage, or through other payment mechanism.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

