<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF4E365641AEA4D05A9158F37D33BC184" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 66 IH: Native American Education Opportunity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 66</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand opportunity for Native American children through additional options in education, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB8E550FFD9944B8592C0F0F6909698EB" style="OLC"><section id="H9516B32142C34E15B3097CC824CFC2D6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Native American Education Opportunity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5BD8A3B2D5C147C5956684E9405CAB56"><enum>2.</enum><header>Native American education opportunity program</header><subsection id="H811F9DAC39E54827A6F23180B80BAFB2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part B of title XI of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2000">25 U.S.C. 2000 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3A5DFAEBEA954D80BC3F538E6FD67007"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 1141 as section 1142; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B152D51B9914EF7876C155B5D71A33E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 1140 the following:</text><quoted-block id="HCE54E7F799D0430FAD7B4965135E4271" style="OLC"><section id="H187A28A8F6F64978B4D97AE4930BA86F"><enum>1141.</enum><header>Funding of Tribal-based education savings account programs</header><subsection id="HA2BFEB0CC1C9470FB2F26E348A22D3D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><paragraph id="H93D8EAEEF70D4119965E2141740B6CF8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disbursements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request of Tribes, the Secretary of Education and the Secretary of the Interior shall, for the 2023–2024 school year and each subsequent school year, disburse amounts transferred under section 2101(a)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6611">20 U.S.C. 6611(a)(2)</external-xref>) for the fiscal year to such Tribes that administer education savings account programs to enable the Tribes to award grants to education savings accounts for ESA eligible students for such school year, in accordance with subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE4D0AC708D540DF84EA76A1E0C36C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This section shall apply with respect to ESA eligible students who have submitted their application for participation under this section to the Tribe of which the student is an enrolled member on or after January 1, 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEBE7AF16C1B4DDFA876E202AA03E843"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Account administration</header><text>A Tribe may enter into an agreement with a nonprofit entity for the administration of the accounts created through the Tribe’s education savings account program.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE9E013DBC8004BE883C4B306A6C18B7B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Required use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds disbursed to a Tribe under this section shall be used to deposit $8,000 each year in the Tribal education savings accounts of ESA eligible students who have not yet attained a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D708296D7A44585A3C60E2EDD0CC413"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Permissible use of funds</header><text>Funds disbursed to a Tribe under this section may be used for—</text><subparagraph id="H7457882DF34541FDAB2D239748A0ED58"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">private tutoring, including academic, Native language, or cultural tutoring;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9791D0AFF52C413A8687C7F93AD4BF2C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>costs of attendance at a private elementary school or secondary school recognized by the State, which may include a private school that has a religious mission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E7B5F50AC834235AE1470E9094D11A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>private online learning programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AF58FF859E94902A406D0B45EE9D085"><enum>(D)</enum><text>services provided by a public elementary school or secondary school attended by the child on a less than full-time basis, including individual classes and extracurricular activities and programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A6E79AC93A4484396F551BBADCC1E8A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>textbooks, curriculum programs, or other instructional materials, including any supplemental materials required by a curriculum program, private school, private online learning program, or a public school, or any parent directed curriculum associated with K–12 education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0C5D08AF29F4FA3A0C193BC971F0EE5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>computer hardware or other technological devices that are used to help meet a student’s educational needs, except that such hardware or devices may not be purchased by a parent more than once in an 18-month period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5DA541D5DB844B1A75A41C843074BD7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>educational software and applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE8A5847F4EA4D08A01BF15709792A7B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>uniforms purchased for attendance at a private school recognized by the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA098055006BE419890EC54AECD679F40"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fees for nationally standardized assessment exams, advanced placement exams, any exams related to college or university admission, or tuition or fees for preparatory courses for such exams;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC889F19EC0FC4B34B96EAAC1D96F48BB"><enum>(J)</enum><text>fees for summer education programs and specialized after-school education programs (but not including after-school childcare);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C76A711D61E4DD2AEE23A32186D17A1"><enum>(K)</enum><text>educational services and therapies, including occupational, behavioral, physical, speech-language, and audiology therapies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB11F42EECD734C9E9F53D9463B397C72"><enum>(L)</enum><text>transportation to receive a service under paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58E0F79A6ED34864B4858D39EFA22F77"><enum>(M)</enum><text>costs of attendance at an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98F37DC61CC5486EBBB0A720C0E886C8"><enum>(N)</enum><text>costs associated with an apprenticeship or other vocational training program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H399E8F9E34644F969965A9B8C8F32E44"><enum>(O)</enum><text>fees for State-recognized industry certification exams, and tuition or fees for preparatory courses for such exams;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H998138EE4F704173A0AA56565B7975A8"><enum>(P)</enum><text>contributions to a college savings account, which may include contributions to a qualified tuition program (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529">section 529(b)(1)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) or other prepaid tuition plan offered by a State; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0317B19A83D4F53AC6F6B459B268315"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>any other educational expenses approved by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BDFB174AB53429CAD281C19AB75E01F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disbursements</header><paragraph id="H60E4B98481FC4319B367663E0A735A1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual disbursements</header><text>A Tribe that receives a disbursement amount under subsection (a) shall make semi-annual distributions of such amount to education savings accounts for ESA eligible students.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFC0D7FFF4104F42BB75370C892F4C4A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>A Tribe shall allocate not more than 5 percent of the amount received per pupil under this section to the administration of the education savings account programs of the Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23386FE4502D4BAE87B2D7CDBDB63A64"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Roll over and remaining funds in an account</header><text>Amounts remaining in the Tribal education savings account of a student at the end of a school year shall remain available until expended for use in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C098E28D4E84344A29F41B835750381"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terminition and return of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Tribal education savings account of a student shall terminate on—</text><subparagraph id="H3007E4656BF2431F974C8B2D34F0B537"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the student enrolls in a public elementary school or secondary school on a full-time basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C744A16A1D740E0B8CD0926006BEB4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a student who is pursuing postsecondary education, the earlier of—</text><clause id="HEF442F8C7D3E44E597D09D3C6C5B4D0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the student completes postsecondary education; or</text></clause><clause id="H1D8EA402E7714B10B6F27A44793458CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date on which the student attains the age of 25 years;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H566068E8C563433591C5384D6031C508"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a student who is an individual with a disability, the date on which the student attains the age of 26 years; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64B17D1F14CD4B5B93F83388AC41AE44"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the case of an individual not described in subparagraph (B) or (C), the earlier of—</text><clause id="HDAD4904243E64E759E50828A4B4CB2A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the student attains the age of 25 years; or</text></clause><clause id="HB4A8653217C74D579804FB5B12EFEC91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the expiration of any 2-year period during which funds in the account are not used in accordance with this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5827CAC211BE44868EF7C8EC8C37FABF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Compulsory attendance requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State that receives funds under this title shall consider a child with a Tribal education savings account for a school year as meeting the State’s compulsory school attendance requirements for such school year.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAA1779CA21784716B835035F4034D046"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a child with a Tribal education savings account who attends a public school on a less than full-time basis in a school year—</text><paragraph id="H11E647C5BB71440983BD60E7B641B63E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the child may not attend the public school free of charge; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88B0A4B6B1C946028FF0AB938C33367B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>funds in the account, in an amount determined pursuant to an agreement between the parent of the child and the local educational agency concerned, shall be used to pay for the child’s costs of attendance at such school.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D4F9B2D89BB4586977D0EC246A1523C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Tribal consultation</header><paragraph id="HF4357AC19E0C44BD8E38D6D678E20300"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before providing educational services to ESA eligible students, and on an annual basis thereafter, a participating educational service provider shall engage in consultation with appropriate tribal officials before providing educational services to ESA eligible students.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7451FAE3FF974786A70818C3F87AF55F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Documentation</header><text>The participating educational service provider shall maintain in the provider’s records and provide to the Bureau of Indian Education a written affirmation signed by the appropriate officials of the participating tribes or tribal organizations approved by the tribes that the consultation required by this section has occurred. If such officials do not provide such affirmation within a reasonable period of time, the affected educational service provider shall forward documentation that such consultation has taken place to the Bureau of Indian Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC3E1C3855CF48BEAF8838A04817FE76"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to require the participating educational service provider to determine who are the appropriate officials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55F0575BB4E94D139157DBAA65CDD4C1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Consultation required under this section shall not interfere with the timely approval and operation of participating educational service providers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2016910686DA4C9394B2527C962AA713"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>A grant awarded to an ESA eligible student under this section shall be considered assistance to the student and shall not be considered assistance to a school that enrolls the ESA eligible student or any other educational service provider from which the ESA eligible student receives services. The amounts provided on behalf of an ESA eligible student under this section shall not be treated as income of the parent or the student for purposes of Federal tax laws or for determining eligibility for any other Federal program.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HEF001AE5DA6E492EB895E30B589256FE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The authority to carry out this section shall expire on the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC55F79EF7A24C3495B3E5A4C7232F89"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H68DF3CB5E1514A799F1C1563B9EE9DCC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate officials</header><text>The term <term>appropriate officials</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H75C14D600B3C4791BE4F91297087D788"><enum>(A)</enum><text>tribal officials who are elected; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA00D6E60BEA40958D96A5ED1B8A7AF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>appointed tribal leaders or officials designated in writing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DADC44F643241F49E50330A5093B557"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Educational service provider</header><text>The term <term>educational service provider</term> means an educational service provider that has entered into an agreement with a Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EBD1614BF8C46A790AF732BB9989186"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESA eligible student</header><text>The term <term>ESA eligible student</term> means an individual who is—</text><subparagraph id="HCEA142A11ED04E2E9C6F9CF111C46DF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an elementary school or secondary school Tribal enrolled student who attended a school operated by the Bureau of Indian Education in the semester preceding the date on which the student first applies for participation in an education savings account program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H765F374C84FD422FA7B2C6C7AF093547"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a child who—</text><clause id="HF104FB53BA88479CA7F92FB0090AA2A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will be eligible to attend a school operated by the Bureau of Indian Education for kindergarten or any other elementary school grade in the next semester that will start after the date on which the student first applies for participation in an education savings account program; or</text></clause><clause id="H4CF42451726D41E48E15A45D3FA5580B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will not be attending a school operated by the Bureau of Indian Education, receiving an education savings account from another Tribe, or attending a public elementary school or secondary school, while the student is participating in an education savings account program of a Tribe.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FFF94805AA04AD8A37BC276CE98A131"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Education savings account program</header><text>The term <term>education savings account program</term> means a program administered by a Tribe in which the Tribe awards a grant to an account managed by the Tribe or a nonprofit entity on behalf of a parent of an elementary school or secondary school student from which the parent may purchase goods and services needed for the education of the student.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C8EA6ABFD84415D83C9A3B28A3AA58A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nonprofit entity defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>nonprofit entity</term> means an entity that is described in the <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD4DBFBE156E64919B948FA66ABFD20EA"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Parent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>parent</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CEF4C6A29BF4D83AD151C7D310C3465"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Tribe</term> means any recognized Indian tribe included on the current list published by the Secretary under section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4EDA0210501D4E6C80F744A73E5F00D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1126(c) of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2006">25 U.S.C. 2006(c)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 1141(12)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 1142(12)</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H59BDA9255E45454EB2706C371C318B57"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendments to the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2101(a) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6611">20 U.S.C. 6611(a)</external-xref>) is amended at the end by inserting the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FDCC85F53FC4F1E971B0DE6243C04A2" style="OLC"><paragraph commented="no" id="H3AB496818A5947FD837E3075AE5D36CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">one-half of one percent for Tribes that administer education savings account programs under section 1141 of part B of title XI of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2000">25 U.S.C. 2000 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H5CB61EACD82D4BCFB1FDA531DDBF5B38"><enum>4.</enum><header>Charter schools authorized</header><subsection id="H1CA90D112D7C443EB5CB24C0B17AF012"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Bureau of Indian Education is authorized to approve and fund a Bureau-Funded Charter School at any school operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8B37CF1F89AF41C3A74D6463A5F84205"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of bureau facilities</header><text>Tribes are authorized to use existing Bureau of Indian Education facilities for the operation, management, and expansion of grades in Bureau-funded charter schools, as defined in section 4(d)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H8E87DB7D36234F65A1834929115BB19A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Funds dispersed to tribes under this section may be used for subcontracts with a tribal organization or developer to manage or operate Bureau-funded charter schools.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0D127C8FC77B45958E8B2A016AB240B9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2803BD44D00C46FDB07BA92EA428F004"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bureau-funded charter school</header><text>The term <term>Bureau-Funded Charter School</term> means a school that—</text><subparagraph id="H6866C3503D9D4AD5AF8D47430D062EB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is approved by the Tribal government where the school operates and is approved and funded by the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4A084B4B29A49B0A19F5C9CFCF98078"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is exempt from significant Federal, State, or local rules that inhibit the flexible operation and management of Bureau-funded schools, but not from any rules relating to the other requirements of this paragraph;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H009B479D21CD405E953A1B500BDF79FC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is created by a developer as a Bureau-funded school, or is adapted by a developer from an existing Bureau-funded school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DA919E9538C448F8531B272389A33DE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>operates in pursuit of a specific set of educational objectives determined by the school’s developer and agreed to by each Tribe served and the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H865B99DCAAC1424B835C50D9A8F23E7F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provides a program of elementary or secondary education, or both;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H158AEDD7B1C3420889974EDD44E87773"><enum>(F)</enum><text>is not affiliated with a sectarian school or religious institution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81EEC243934E4282A7AF2ABB97AAEBBF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>does not charge tuition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69E89CA72F9C41CDA8B5351EDBC9D10A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>complies with the Age Discrimination Act of 1975 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6101">42 U.S.C. 6101 et seq.</external-xref>), title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>), title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>), section 1232g of this title (commonly referred to as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>), and part B of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1411">20 U.S.C. 1411 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF05837986094EFFACD2748F6903E033"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is a school to which parents choose to send their children, and that—</text><clause id="H971482A1F35E4EECB92AAC63D26AFB37"><enum>(i)</enum><text>admits students on the basis of a lottery, consistent with section 4303(c)(3)(A) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7221b">20 U.S.C. 7221b(c)(3)(A)</external-xref>), if more students apply for admission than can be accommodated; or</text></clause><clause id="HE06EC492150446BC886C2C17CD60B15D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>automatically enrolls students who are enrolled in the immediate prior grade level of Bureau-funded schools and, for any additional student openings or student openings created through regular attrition in student enrollment in the affiliated charter school and the enrolling school, admits students on the basis of a lottery as described in clause (i);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H852F9EAD9836495091BF07FE24778608"><enum>(J)</enum><text>agrees to comply with the same Federal audit requirements as do other Bureau-funded schools, unless such Federal audit requirements are waived by the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1CE7F9ABF6141F78AB5EAB60B11D2AA"><enum>(K)</enum><text>meets all applicable Federal health and safety requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22952CBF4D9B4D6C86D60059709E5AE2"><enum>(L)</enum><text>operates in accordance with Federal law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1375F2E7BAED430699FEB2AD2DF8FA76"><enum>(M)</enum><text>has a written performance contract with the Bureau of Indian Education that includes a description of how student performance will be measured in charter schools pursuant to assessments that are required of other schools and pursuant to any other assessments mutually agreeable to the Bureau of Indian Education, tribe(s) served, and the charter school; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F2F036D6F004B6E8F12EAFB4D7C064F"><enum>(N)</enum><text>may serve students in early childhood education programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B774438C59F4AF98AF4B01121592A9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Developer</header><text>The term <term>developer</term> means an individual or group of individuals (including a public, private, or tribal nonprofit organization), which may include teachers, administrators and other school staff, parents, or other members of the local community in which a charter school project will be carried out.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA911466A02BF4BF2B0EF56FCFA190FE8"><enum>5.</enum><header>GAO study</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><paragraph id="H10069732FEFD4291863CC2DF80D191D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a review of the implementation of the programs established by this Act during the preceding 3-year period, including any factors impacting increased participation in education savings account programs established pursuant to the amendments made by this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98AB3CA213CA42B2AF82C174C6423714"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit a report describing the results of the review under paragraph (1) to—</text><subparagraph id="HBF5B6A3B239344E5BD12AC04FF928693"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Indian Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA9FCDDFC65B4C2B8BAC8A80C4E23E1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Subcommittee on Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs of the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A5701ECF5D04136B775EEA70CA514A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make the report described in paragraph (2) publicly available.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4AB5D29818924C699F93F68D5D69FB6A"><enum>6.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance, is held to be invalid, the remainder of this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

