<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HABDCA0243CCD48EBA91BBF4D478F00BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4249 IH: Veterans Exposed to Toxic PFAS Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4249</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to furnish hospital care and medical services to veterans and dependents who were stationed at military installations at which the veterans and dependents were exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, to provide for a presumption of service connection for certain veterans who were stationed at military installations at which the veterans were exposed to such substances, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6656D00FD1FD4A928B7EE1FCA9C53267" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA5B112C1602E4C8A9A3611D18C066C71" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Exposed to Toxic PFAS Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>VET PFAS Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H68EB61F3B7AF4F5AB44EBDEA711CAD21" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Hospital care and medical services for veterans and dependents exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid and other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances</header> <subsection id="H2368A8B876424C199E9748F50BDC3AAB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Hospital care and medical services for veterans</header> <paragraph id="HCD072B31696D40B29395C4C7254FFDCC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of section 1710(e) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
<quoted-block id="HB828A45C95A144D9A76EC5B12C8B2BA3" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H1A1F9912397F4399A473D78ECBC7FB94" indent="up2"><enum>(J)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H55892257D491440C8629C73F14CC083B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, subject to paragraph (2), a veteran who served on active duty in the Armed Forces at a covered military installation at which individuals were exposed to substances specified in clause (ii) is eligible for hospital care and medical services under subsection (a)(2)(F) for the diseases, illnesses, or conditions as specified in such clause, notwithstanding that there is insufficient medical evidence to conclude that such illness or condition is attributable to such service.</text></clause> <clause id="H383760501C1F4EDC8C496A4C0127E0D0" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The substances and diseases, illnesses, or conditions specified in this clause are the following:</text>
<subclause id="H4C25D156651C44EBA3F121AF61056D2E"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to exposure to perfluorooctanoic acid—</text> <item id="H1F53ECEC45724B68AEB0D2DFE8E43E1D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>diagnosed high cholesterol;</text></item>
<item id="HF444B5036116493A86D93F27FB348C3C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>ulcerative colitis;</text></item> <item id="H7AEB85DB6BA241D6B971CA0BC55DCE7E"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>thyroid disease;</text></item>
<item id="HAA532CB3C4944890A21847BE6E1DFE83"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>testicular cancer;</text></item> <item id="H72E64C1B11F648478B372D972287D574"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>kidney cancer; and</text></item>
<item id="H26007AC90E6A4881867D76C1E194FFB0"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>pregnancy-induced hypertension.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H439292E33BD04A8FA5C4F1E0FA8D4008"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to exposure to other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, any disease, illness, or condition that the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Administrator of the Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry of the Department of Health and Human Services, determines pursuant to the study conducted under section 316 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>) that a positive association exists between exposure to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances and such disease, illness, or condition.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HFA7CD1555D4C4DB0B6BA10C86372F504" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, any service by a member of the reserve components for a period specified by the Secretary at a covered military installation at which individuals were exposed to substances specified in clause (ii) shall be treated as active duty service, notwithstanding section 101(21) of this title.</text></clause> <clause id="H240D2761661E483498E27BA61910C574" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subparagraph, the term <term>covered military installation</term> means a military installation at which individuals were exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, including exposure through a well that provides water for human consumption that is contaminated with such substances.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEF834417FE244F45B9B20CC559FE1926"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Paragraph (2)(B) of such section is amended by striking <quote>or (I)</quote> and inserting <quote>(I), or (J)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0733675A68A8407FB2124A901C72D74C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Family members</header> <paragraph id="H7EC29B54774B4142A07B1B0EA819B2FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter VIII of chapter 17 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block id="HC939F496152A4CE488431AE5C6AA0FFE" style="USC">
<section id="H72C6D833F16047E2B562793DADB4062E"><enum>1787A.</enum><header>Health care of family members of veterans stationed at certain military installations</header>
<subsection id="H5392F69171A2461FA55183AA61C43C77"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this section, subject to subsection (b), a family member of a veteran described in clause (i) of section 1710(e)(1)(J) of this title (or who would be so described but for the condition by which the individual was discharged or released from the Armed Forces) who resided at a military installation covered by such clause or who was in utero while the mother of such family member resided at such location shall be eligible for hospital care and medical services furnished by the Secretary for any disease, illness, or condition for which a veteran may receive hospital care and medical services under clause (ii) of such section, notwithstanding that there is insufficient medical evidence to conclude that such disease, illness, or condition is attributable to such residence.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC0D2476242E6401B875594833055B074"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5DA6582435C441B899B5183622A60E10"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may only furnish hospital care and medical services under subsection (a) to the extent and in the amount provided in advance in appropriations Acts for such purpose.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0428BE781C864D36B83D2D0565C9FD26" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hospital care and medical services may not be furnished under subsection (a) for a disease, illness, or condition of a family member that is found, in accordance with guidelines issued by the Under Secretary for Health, to have resulted from a cause other than the residence of the family member described in that subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B5F465A972F4DE4919D98FF17F81D4D" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary may provide reimbursement for hospital care or medical services provided to a family member under this section only after the family member or the provider of such care or services has exhausted without success all claims and remedies reasonably available to the family member or provider against a third party (as defined in section 1725(f) of this title) for payment of such care or services, including with respect to health-plan contracts (as defined in such section).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H90E72250961742358AAF4C04BA78F17B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1787 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block id="HB67498E3F4EE45B980B8EAE09AE040FF" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">1787A. Health care of family members of veterans stationed at certain military installations.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCA2C87C68D3C40799283B1D22779A931"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual reports</header> <paragraph id="H469F770DAC1B46E1A96FA9905AFB29AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the three-year period beginning in the year in which the study conducted under section 316 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>) is submitted to Congress, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives an annual report on the care and services provided under sections 1710(e)(1)(J) and 1787A of title 38, United States Code (as added by subsections (a) and (b)(1), respectively).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7E0209B00E0647938DFFBBF21C8ED7BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report under paragraph (1) shall set forth the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HFAB92699F1EB4F0DA2803DC50F5AE356"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of veterans and family members provided hospital care and medical services under the provisions of law specified in paragraph (1) during the period covered by the report.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H859535495D844102B85D4AFE76E186AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The illnesses, conditions, and disabilities for which care and services have been provided such veterans and family members under such provisions of law during that period.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9353480D3B104FE585B7CBB6364F4B86"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of veterans and family members who applied for care and services under such provisions of law during that period but were denied, including information on the reasons for such denials.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H278E308CF10E41C4AC720E33CA16FF32"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The number of veterans and family members who applied for care and services under such provisions of law and are awaiting a decision from the Secretary on eligibility for such care and services as of the date of such report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA6978364B30B4FBABD20B9BBD4A5B72A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Veteran defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>veteran</quote> includes a former member of the reserve components of the Armed Forces covered by such section 1710(e)(1)(J). </text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HEA1D054580F14BAF82FD4141355D9798" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Presumption of service connection for certain veterans exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances</header>
<subsection id="H6FFE0BCA78174C92BDC73F2830A5B53B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/11">Chapter 11</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1116B">section 1116B</external-xref> the following new section:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9781584DE90342D0A850B4C7D54FC544" style="USC"> <section id="HA53A39B3876847BEA7461E79DE4222EC"><enum>1116C.</enum><header>Presumption of service connection for certain veterans exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances</header> <subsection id="HCB4F8C49BDF2452FBBAFAC12D0FE52DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presumption of service connection</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3A2E691212B947B09478009921241098"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of section 1110 of this title, and subject to section 1113 of this title, each disease or illness specified in subsection (b) that becomes manifest in a veteran described in paragraph (2) shall be considered to have been incurred or aggravated in the line of duty in the active military, naval, or air service, notwithstanding that there is no record of evidence of such disease or illness during the period of such service.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD88AC000AF45403280086710CC3FAFED" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran described in this paragraph is a veteran who, during active military, naval, or air service, served at a military installation at which individuals were exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, including exposure through a well that provides water for human consumption that is contaminated with such substances.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5B42F53A25F343519EEC168BFBB98F47" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Diseases or illnesses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A disease or illness specified in this subsection is any of the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H7207332F6B7E4A0A8B7D5B8C72230707"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to exposure to perfluorooctanoic acid—</text> <subparagraph id="H63F6E8D56A8C41828814F44D8B1A0FB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>diagnosed high cholesterol;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9B9F363347D74AC4B9E946E8CFA1BFF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ulcerative colitis;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB62C63BC15824C26BB7450B54FCEA818"><enum>(C)</enum><text>thyroid disease;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8273BB492085409DAE64CB4204C3E223"><enum>(D)</enum><text>testicular cancer;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2D7FE325E564B2E970B341BD5012EBD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>kidney cancer; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5B39A0E79486479A9783D81D7872AF36"><enum>(F)</enum><text>pregnancy-induced hypertension.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFEAE6A00894C4703A48934611A604BF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to exposure to other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, any other disease, illness, or condition that the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Administrator of the Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry of the Department of Health and Human Services, determines pursuant to the study conducted under section 316 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>) that a positive association exists between exposure to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances and such disease or illness.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2F88C8D177724BF2BF207801C9D2B85C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Active military, naval, or air service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, any service by a member of the reserve components for a period specified by the Secretary at a military installation described in subsection (a)(2) shall be treated as active military, naval, or air service, notwithstanding section 101(24) of this title.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H95F4E66A2A9147EC934882638653270B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1116B the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4985E41C31834636A38E653ADD51D038" style="USC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">1116C. Presumption of service connection for certain veterans exposed to perfluorooctanoic acid or other per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

