<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H40ADA41465E5418B9EE1C2D7532BAC7E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4690 IH: Gray Zone Defense Assessment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4690</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To assess the capacity of the United States to effectively marshal disparate elements of national power to counter adversary political warfare campaigns, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCD0BA18C3B474FDCBA2F478B559C7D81" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE28D976377F545C0A48ADD493167B14C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header> 
<subsection id="HD06142D6FF024BAC97547ED645897D73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Gray Zone Defense Assessment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD50DC30FF2234383A6B638486CF29D6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="HE28D976377F545C0A48ADD493167B14C" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H51C102726B8B4904AD52A7D395B1F318" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE61F11B76FFD4DFCBC7066950134DE0D" level="section">Sec. 3. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6A0378E6BD2749EF8278619FB4DD159F" level="section">Sec. 4. Statement of policy.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H38003B0F518941E3A8890866C602FA18" level="section">Sec. 5. Evaluation of national capacities for conducting gray zone operations.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H791EDAC26C96467096D8BE14067699F1" level="section">Sec. 6. Report on Department of State capacity to respond to gray zone aggression.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H00244B4FE3EC46F7A61794D290F6558F" level="section">Sec. 7. Expansion of intelligence community assessment regarding gray zone assets.</toc-entry> </toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="H51C102726B8B4904AD52A7D395B1F318"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="HDC2CBD1C38B6476E9FEC5AEB3E6BB543"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 1948, George F. Kennan observed that, <quote>In broadest definition, political warfare is the employment of all the means at a nation’s command, short of war, to achieve its national objectives.</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98147F32596A43AFB0C70F738151B5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Today, this coercive activity is referred to by many names within the United States Government and the academic community, most notably <quote>gray zone</quote> operations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1454BF21E11A45A7AF45C3E4D07245C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Although increasingly employed as a means of political warfare, the full contours of gray zone operations remain ambiguous. However, central features of gray zone operations include that they are ultimately directed by state actors, consist of efforts not associated with routine statecraft, and are intended to advance a country’s objectives at the expense of a rival, without crossing a threshold that results in kinetic military conflict. They include such operations and tactics as the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9746ACE9C06648209A07F9E25DDD338A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Information warfare, including conducting disinformation campaigns or the spreading of propaganda.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7B5FC2208FE341D6BFD2A1066BD98226"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Encouraging internal strife within target countries.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H534099A09AD248B0A66D9DBBBF6F76C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subversive economic practices, such as economic coercion, systematic IP theft, blocking international shipping lanes, and overproduction of commercial commodities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23C07F2C080149CE868BF5EBC5F04465"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Cyber operations, below the threshold of conflict, aimed at coercion, espionage, or otherwise undermining a target.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE55D1C45F3C040E58B87F67C7274E64D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Support of domestic or foreign proxy forces.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAC64D1EE39184EDFA233CF5CAA0BCE57"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Coercive investment and bribery for political aims.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H21A5D8D5AD8144F39EFD26DDE497ECB9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Industrial policy designed to monopolize a strategic industry or to destroy such an industry in other nations, especially when coordinated with other gray zone operations.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC317AA645EA42C2B00C48760D465DA1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Military, paramilitary, or similar provocations and operations short of war.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H624B6A040D414434B08C586C31EEFA85"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Hostage diplomacy.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD5FAE6E27A6B498BAE8A1C7AC3D53A65"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Gradual changes of internationally recognized borders.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9CA55AF923E407A9338BD9304589926"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Government financing or sponsorship of activities described in subparagraphs (A) through (J).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EA8C7119598461DA43F7251CAD7EDB8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Various gray zone operations are frequently linked together into a coordinated campaign, that may also include tools of routine diplomacy, and that is designed to achieve a state’s political or military objective.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF755008862934D6E95E9A2E4B2C3DFC4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Gray zone campaigns are attractive to state actors for several reasons, including reduced costs compared to the deployment of conventional forces, thereby allowing states to pursue their objectives with limited resources.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26A050E050394791AE0CCF839E06E52B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, the Islamic Republic of Iran, and other countries actively advance their own strategic objectives and challenge United States interests through the extensive use of gray zone operations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61B240EFEF934CAAA4F5C6A59B49981F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Unwelcome escalation by adversarial powers—especially over the last decade—from routine statecraft into gray zone competition is a defining feature of the recent reemergence of great-power competition and requires an appropriate United States response.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE52B511F0574B78A1CF975CBA0AB25A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States has not sufficiently deterred or responded to gray zone campaigns, thereby risking undermining United States national interests, diminishing United States influence and credibility, and encouraging rivals to further employ such tactics.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4CD3A2E97C8428B8F2FDCD359E4A58F"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Successfully responding to adversary gray zone campaigns relies upon the full integration of instruments of national power across multiple domains and the ability to deploy such capacities in a coordinated, real-time campaign.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HE61F11B76FFD4DFCBC7066950134DE0D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H24E822288006456D85112213210E75D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>gray zone competition is a central and enduring aspect of great-power competition, and the United States should elevate the effective response to adversary gray zone campaigns as a central feature of its approach to great-power competition;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D33A461D8584E718B7F0188DAFA309E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an effective, whole-of-government approach is essential to meeting the gray zone challenges posed by competitors of the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H884B3201AB8D4AB5B54D994B33508CA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>since gray zone activity takes place below the threshold of kinetic military conflict and since narrative formation is frequently a critical aspect of gray zone campaigns, the Department of State should take a preeminent role in coordinating, within applicable interagency processes, the disparate means of national power as the United States seeks to respond to adversary gray zone campaigns.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H6A0378E6BD2749EF8278619FB4DD159F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H02BC0DF0D1924124B2ABF70113A37DEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>seek effective responses, particularly at the Department of State, to adversary gray zone campaigns and to recognize the paramount importance of such responses to the national interests of the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE7A057C641A0416AB46532AAE17E0D85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>continue upholding the international rule of law and the rules-based international order, which is a core national security interest of the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE169B4D6EF694173A4AEC3E4A3B97D26"><enum>(3)</enum><text>call on United States allies and partners to employ sufficient national resources to equitably contribute to the response to gray zone challenges.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H38003B0F518941E3A8890866C602FA18"><enum>5.</enum><header>Evaluation of national capacities for conducting gray zone operations</header> <subsection id="H4399DB67FBE64EFA8583FCC57D15CBF0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall conduct a review and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the processes and capabilities by which the United States responds to gray zone campaigns and recommendations to enhance such processes and capabilities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEE2AF1C0935D4226AA765739C7D24BA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H459DC74BDD184FC9BA1BE2618D00E7B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of the capability and capacity of the United States interagency to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H36451902E4814BDFA91DA952606B78ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify adversary activity as a gray zone campaign, including the adversary’s intent, capabilities, interactive effects, and impact on United States interests;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D3EE48AF512434AA05B6E310C2D2C93"><enum>(B)</enum><text>devise effective theories of deterrence; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA0F75E57C0943178D2F82F6BA7DCF7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordinate instruments of United States national power to consistently and effectively respond to adversarial gray zone campaigns against the United States or allies and partners;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C91CB6C4DA54F68ACE720E1A6EB046B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the process for determining the threshold at which adversary gray zone activities or campaigns targeting the United States, allies, or partners threaten United States interests, including the methods and mechanisms for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE73C89191ADD497FB11D7DD0BF5B7550"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determining which such activities or campaigns warrant a United States response;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H536BFF27FFD140AB9E03955871B988A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>calibrating such response;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9AD7C95271B43EF8AAAF212E52C1B9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>communicating such thresholds to adversaries; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H31F144C0D75D402A970A09EDC7EC38CD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>establishing and regularly reviewing protocols with allies and partners to respond to such activities or campaigns; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DC77D62262447B1B18FA2D5E8AFBE15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations for further enhancing the ability of the United States to deter and respond to adversarial gray zone campaigns, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H8D93148ACA8249A691D6524312F3E7D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>institutional reforms to enhance United States interagency coordination in response to adversarial gray zone campaigns and, as necessary, additional statutory authorities required to implement those reforms;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD70D16F6AAD4977881635174BE1F370"><enum>(B)</enum><text>additional resources, authorities, or institutional capacities necessary for United States agencies to counter gray zone threats; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4E808C253B40440C996A7DCC6AE6F61A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>budget estimates for the implementations of the recommendations made pursuant to this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF50EEC8F1914492EBA232DD99E30A6F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in a classified form and shall contain an unclassified summary.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H27E720F932014569BB4688ED72BFB51A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Appropriate Congressional Committees Defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD5E4E66D873748AE9E43950872A7DF9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD716D695E7094DEC848795CDC9D9383D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H791EDAC26C96467096D8BE14067699F1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on Department of State capacity to respond to gray zone aggression</header> 
<subsection id="H2121C8EAB9C94462B919B9626DE26C7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report discussing the capacity of the Department of State to contribute to coordinated United States responses to adversary gray zone campaigns and the Department’s understanding of the gray zone threat environment.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE47C9ECEC3724487B52DBCD5CFC5821B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall also include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H98D93D8688D14F42BDECB9107287ABCE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The capabilities, offices, and entities particularly suited to countering adversary gray zone operations and a description of the roles each can play.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA316DB32D6834BA0A9CEBA37EE79104E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An evaluation of the adequacy and utility of established Department of State definitions for understanding adversary gray zone activity.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52A791CD8B4B4B8F9C0DFF672548EEBA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Recommendations, including proposed necessary investments and the rationale and expected costs of such investments, for further enhancing the capacity of the Department of State to effectively respond to adversary gray zone operations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB974E7C28218495EBEF7F0A7345A6B48" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of 25 priority countries at the front lines of adversary gray zone aggression and a discussion, developed in consultation with relevant embassy country teams, of the matters described in paragraphs (1) through (3) with respect to each such country.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H453A000AF6CF47C3AC0721D20310CEDE" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A list of activities that are currently being undertaken to respond to adversary gray zone campaigns conducted against such priority countries.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF2594D125CF24F8B94E95D1E1D35C6A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in a classified form and shall contain an unclassified summary.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H00244B4FE3EC46F7A61794D290F6558F" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Expansion of intelligence community assessment regarding gray zone assets</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6516 of the Intelligence Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 (division F of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>; 136 Stat. 3548) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H449B02E6CB7E4661A0173F73E4770C7C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote>Russian</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED1874285A434DC69DB88C348D91799B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H76B7EDD2717747FA9DE533EB6F186A73" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H07544080AE654BA886D0EBE674AF7044" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>country of concern</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H426BA64DCE7C4C89B0E54C8B9AF299C2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the People’s Republic of China;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE1FE784A93C64E82BF4506C60ED18ABB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Russian Federation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE5646A89380F41ADAA9786CF8865A288" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Islamic Republic of Iran;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2839319D6CA4D25831A2ED3631E3B32" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H35CF509BD0AB48B4855A78FBBA93B78D" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Republic of Cuba; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA41D9EF238BC4252BC011BBDEB0B5F3D" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Syrian Arab Republic.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H765D1859B8D341E2B906C2695445148E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="HC2014DD70EC0421DA9D299717E2A44B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading—</text> 
<clause id="H445D5F16EBA14F7E86E74ADB33DDF2B7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Annual</header-in-text></quote> before <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Intelligence</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></clause> <clause id="H75FFEBADA7C04081BDBCDB06AA86BC12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Russian</header-in-text></quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7FC7F2D91FC945C7BBADF4651F0608BA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="HEE29E51408D0409A85B5FFD4C1B05F97" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="HD5548AD173214B5395948BB3C0FDBB98"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>annually</quote> before <quote>produce</quote>; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="HF87701907E3E422A8AE81D2468913324"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>with respect to each country of concern</quote> after <quote>intelligence community assessment</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H9EB4ADBD194C42278491AA8BFAB932FA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Russia</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>the country of concern</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCAD16F156924479A954AFA1CAB1095A9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<clause id="H3070C80A1A2644E78C1F2DD98282077D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>Russia</quote> and inserting <quote>a country of concern</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H2481E48206B74DB496455E983AF5DA1C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (B), (C), and (D), by striking <quote>Russia</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>the country of concern</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE944F18E3E9D417FA81686BA564BBD02" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <clause id="HDE192AEABDE641BD940ADDD46A066A22" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>Russia</quote> and inserting <quote>each country of concern</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB77E5E8D6DB44FC89529FB5B74A655CD" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>Russia</quote> and inserting <quote>the country of concern</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

