<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8F24EA9E38994A1D80D6B3840504FB77" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3108 IH: Tim Hart Wildland Firefighter Classification and Pay Parity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3108</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To reform and enhance the pay and benefits of Federal wildland firefighters, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0AC3C58D311F4095AFAB165F5410A745" style="OLC">
<section id="H5916B35D31E34A889CA6BEE8387BA626" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; definitions</header>
<subsection id="H8461937CCED2429EBBC328351CF1A97B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tim Hart Wildland Firefighter Classification and Pay Parity Act</short-title></quote> or <quote><short-title>Tim’s Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6A2823AE21904093AD0EFBBD30560730"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HFF06BF089E1940B8A3499AC2445A4DB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Office of Personnel Management.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5793639CA5E24BDEABE10BDA502ECDB7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal wildland firefighter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Federal wildland firefighter</quote> means any temporary, seasonal, or permanent position at the Department of Agriculture or the Department of the Interior, and Tribal Firefighters, that maintains group, emergency incident management, or fire qualifications, as established annually by the Standards for Wildland Fire Position Qualifications published by the National Wildfire Coordinating Group, and primarily engages in or supports wildland fire management activities, including forestry and rangeland technicians and positions concerning aviation, engineering heavy equipment operations, dispatch, or fire and fuels management.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H277606BDDC834F1BA9A09B63A94B0617" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <quote>Secretaries</quote> means the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDA31FC9377CF43F29C23AAA61D8CA2E4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Special base pay rates for wildland firefighters</header> <subsection id="H191E60E69FB841D5BC03D4E05B30C51D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after section 5332 the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HAF0F0899E9E94FE38659C6620CB9E142" style="USC">
<section id="H2BB38A3308BE4C498A546B4255CD7D3E"><enum>5332a.</enum><header>Special base rates of pay for wildland firefighters</header>
<subsection id="H0AD72BCA1A7343409177D8E67FF40AA6"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H4EF081DB7E1B43C98CAE8AF54968ABD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>firefighter</quote> means an employee who—</text>
<subparagraph id="HBDF894C12C564F06B3B435D89B32B1BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a firefighter within the meaning of section 8331(21) or section 8401(14);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEBDD3D60BBB14F93A601DDAF1876C235"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who holds a supervisory or administrative position and is subject to subchapter III of chapter 83, but who does not qualify to be considered a firefighter within the meaning of section 8331(21), would otherwise qualify if the employee had transferred directly to such position after serving as a firefighter within the meaning of that section;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5F1041A9020741B3B101C42E562981CC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who holds a supervisory or administrative position and is subject to chapter 84, but who does not qualify to be considered a firefighter within the meaning of section 8401(14), would otherwise qualify if the employee had transferred directly to such position after performing duties described in section 8401(14)(A) for at least 3 years; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F0F6E733C9A48F4ACAEA0C8AEFF141F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the case of an employee who is not subject to subchapter III of chapter 83 or chapter 84, holds a position that the Office of Personnel Management determines would satisfy subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) if the employee were subject to subchapter III of chapter 83 or chapter 84;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H099D66C9CBB4459FB4F98DC5704B29B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>General Schedule base rate</quote> means an annual rate of basic pay established under section 5332, before any additions such as a locality-based comparability payment under section 5304 or 5304a or a special rate supplement under section 5305;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA7B22D5126424260B12A3CD2C9BEE0BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>special base rate</quote> means an annual rate of basic pay payable to a wildland firefighter, before any additions or reductions, that replaces the General Schedule base rate otherwise applicable to the wildland firefighter and that is administered in the same manner as General Schedule base rates; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7796188CD0EC4847BC399A4B0D3CA43F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> means any temporary, seasonal, or permanent position at the Department of Agriculture or the Department of the Interior, or Tribal Firefighters, that maintains group, emergency incident management, or fire qualifications, as established annually by the Standards for Wildland Fire Position Qualifications published by the National Wildfire Coordinating Group, and primarily engages in or supports wildland fire management activities, including forestry and rangeland technicians and positions concerning aviation, engineering heavy equipment operations, dispatch, training, development and technology, or fire and fuels management. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDCFD0906019F472CBABF53DC4927C211"><enum>(b)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H48EAEBE8B1334BEF973A189828C786F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Notwithstanding section 5332, a wildland firefighter is entitled to a special base rate of pay at grades 1 through 15 of the General Schedule, as prescribed by this subsection. This special base rate shall replace the otherwise applicable General Schedule base rate and shall be basic pay for all purposes, including the purpose of computing a locality-based comparability payment under section 5304 or 5304a. Such special base rates shall be computed as described in paragraphs (2) and (3) and adjusted at the time of adjustments in the General Schedule.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H74EEF27488D94C5E93A4F45FE3AB3AB2" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minimum rate of basic pay for any wildland firefighter in levels 1 through 5 of the General Schedule shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H1317371D0D1248C0825349AB9C3CFE94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be not less than the rate of pay for step 3 of GS–6, as adjusted by the pay locality designated as <quote>Rest of U.S.</quote> under section 5304; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8B912EC2C8E54133856DACB2BE5DAF7A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not be greater than the minimum rate of basic pay provided to GS–6 under paragraph (3). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE778C391CD94416828A8F468683A3B0" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The special base rates for a wildland firefighter in levels 6 through 15 of the General Schedule shall be derived by increasing the otherwise applicable General Schedule base rate on the date of enactment of this Act by the applicable percentage for the wildland firefighter’s grade as shown below and rounding the result to the nearest whole dollar:</text>
<subparagraph id="H6E58FA81C3AF40A7B4A073F1B11CA8F3"><enum/><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–6, 27 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H995FE4D5C9FB441888BBB43862505BDC"><enum/><text>GS–7, 24 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEA64FCF8800B4696A2D6B2E165E81588"><enum/><text>GS–8, 21 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2FA13A69B564C288E0CDD9D97FCCE5B"><enum/><text>GS–9, 18 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5279CC8B63334157B8DEFD3F39D89621"><enum/><text>GS–10, 15 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF7EE34E6B07E4E9CB6A3E4FA2461A4AB"><enum/><text>GS–11, 12 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7CDCCAD79CB7464BA69F813C10F961FF"><enum/><text>GS–12, 9 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF0870A9C13AC453492EA782C8365A403"><enum/><text>GS–13, 6 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6847207564D443A59F821B87B2880B19"><enum/><text>GS–14, 3 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA2EA36A076274A649EC1AFC06EAAB197"><enum/><text>GS–15, 1.5 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H73B9D94E6B604094A57DDAE902D7094F" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>When the special base rate is expressed as an hourly, daily, weekly, or biweekly rate, the rate is computed from the appropriate annual rate of basic pay derived under paragraph (2) or (3) in accordance with the rules prescribed by section 5504(b).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H1492BA7704DF4445978D65E6D48EF1D5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (d) shall be effective on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HC80B8C26091A491B9EDF421E38819BE3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5332">section 5332</external-xref> the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H7E8BFC9B65FC450981E05CC229C0449C" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">5332a. Special base rates of pay for wildland firefighters.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H100D48901ABA4E9F92B816E8804C85F3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prevailing rate employees</header><text>Section 5343 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H6FD21EAF9E8C4F6D89A376AD75484A57" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HFDAA964D2C4A4D5E9CC23BF9CFB167BD"><enum>(g)</enum><text>For prevailing rate employees described in section 5342(a)(2)(A) who qualify as a <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> based on the definitions of <quote>firefighter</quote> and <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> in section 5332a(a), the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior (as applicable) shall increase the wage rates of such employees by amounts (determined at the sole and exclusive discretion of the applicable Secretary after consultation with the other Secretary) that are generally consistent with the percentage increases given to wildland firefighters in the General Schedule under section 5332a. Such an increased wage rate shall be basic pay for the same purposes as the wage rate otherwise established under this section. An increase under this subsection may not cause an employee’s wage rate to increase beyond a rate that would produce an annualized rate in excess of the annual rate for level IV of the Executive Schedule.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HE218A17F33CC47DCA65047BFBEC057BC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Wildland fire incident standby premium pay</header> <subsection id="H720951F72D9445C8953E0FFD44355371"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after section 5545b the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H648E96BC61504841951D55AE3E72DAB0" style="USC">
<section id="H0EF071762EC94946B461B6EDF9265266"><enum>5545c.</enum><header>Incident standby premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header>
<subsection id="H3F0D498E978C48FEA60C9451C697359E"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H9F029A92BD6D4E9CBF2806D67B67E528"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered employee</quote> means an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD17E0FB064D9480E94312BC1BDDED6E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>qualifies as a wildland firefighter based on the definitions of <quote>firefighter</quote> and <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> in section 5332a(a); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H93502D606B0E43C19A43D7059DED1550"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident related duties during the period such employee is assigned to a qualifying incident;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2800C1AEF29A4AEF8413EF5ACCDCC8EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>designated sleep and rest period</quote> means the hours during an incident deployment that a covered employee is deemed to be in sleep or rest status for pay computation purposes, regardless of actual hours spent in that status;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H439D5422C72D4059B92630F97431FA25"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>incident standby premium pay</quote> means pay to which a covered employee is entitled under subsection (c);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3FE0FD0217054EA391590BCC0BD26381"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>prescribed fire incident</quote> means a wildland fire originating from a planned ignition in accordance with applicable laws, policies, and regulations to meet specific objectives;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD78105BD288429AA62A6992330E9C35"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <quote>qualifying incident</quote> means a wildfire incident, a prescribed fire incident, or a severity incident, but excludes an initial response incident involving a single operational period of less than 36 hours (unless a longer period is approved by an authorized agency official due to exceptional circumstances) if the employee is in continual work status with no designated sleep and rest period established by the agency;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1BB43001BC7049F2951AE71C3C157439"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <quote>severity incident</quote> means an incident in which a covered employee is pre-positioned in an area where conditions indicate there is a high risk of wildfires; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF50917C7F48143D38ADF8DB7685EED4E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <quote>wildfire incident</quote> means a wildland fire originating from an unplanned ignition, such as lightning, volcanos, unauthorized and accidental human-caused fires, and prescribed fires that are declared wildfires.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3E85878DA61B40B28D35D13351D8B0BD"><enum>(b)</enum><text>A covered employee is eligible for incident standby premium pay under this section when meeting all of the following conditions:</text> <paragraph id="HB8C5D17EF9834960991BE61F89F83617"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The employee is deployed to the field by the employing agency to respond to a qualifying incident.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H662EACCE1D474B2A9323F5E03E937955"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The employee is placed by the employing agency in continuous duty status during the incident deployment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBB6E89C34B34B16822498361D4A5421"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any periods of sleeping and resting occur in a field location associated with the duty assignment.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H691C77BDC1C348F099FAFE0D0C3C48C9"><enum>(c)</enum><text>A covered employee who meets the conditions in subsection (b) is entitled to incident standby premium pay for designated sleep and rest periods, and such pay shall be the only compensation payable to the employee for those periods, notwithstanding any other law. Such premium pay shall be paid at an hourly rate equal to 50 percent of the employee’s hourly rate of basic pay, rounded to the nearest whole cent. In determining an employee’s minimum wage and overtime pay entitlements under the Fair Labor Standards Act, incident standby premium pay and associated hours shall be disregarded.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDE627F7DF8B346F5AD6CFD3EC2D81710"><enum>(d)</enum><text>A covered employee’s designated sleep and rest periods shall be fixed at 9 hours for every 24-hour duty period associated with a qualifying incident, including necessary travel time. If the hours of an incident deployment are not an exact multiple of 24-hour periods, the ratio of 9/24 shall be multiplied by hours for the less-than-24-hours period of duty to derive the designated sleep and rest period for that duty period, with the result rounded to the nearest fractional increment established by the agency in tracking hours of work.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4B50DC0156814947AEA33A1A30BD5735"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Incident standby premium pay under this section—</text> <paragraph id="H787A8D7CB4724754B87E021D8BE11E90"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not considered part of the basic pay of an employee for any purpose;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H10BA650B3D8A46B384EB3A00FECDCFF7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not be considered in determining an employee’s lump-sum payment for accumulated and accrued annual leave under section 5551 or section 5552;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C4C619C4FB34108ADC8B6B328A54A9B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may not be used in determining pay under section 8114 (related to workers’ compensation); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF7EB292224E24CC78423D3106CF8448B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may not be considered in determining pay for hours of paid leave or other paid time off during which the premium pay is not payable.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H41198A1CE84E4904B2173464AD2A75AE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Other employees</header><text>Title 5, United States Code, is further amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H6B1BB6D6A0414B3D88957F579D7692B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 5544, by—</text> <subparagraph id="H56C56D16AED94E56B9A48CF57FBD119B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>adding the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HCC204A9A0ADB4E7B8407BCD54C46F433" style="OLC">
<subsection id="HF5095B8F0D544CFBAFC519907E4FD757"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A prevailing rate employee described in section 5342(a)(2)(a) shall receive incident standby premium pay under the same terms and conditions that apply to a covered employee under section 5545c if such employee is employed by the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior and—</text> <paragraph id="HDDF7070BA4BC418099B6F3558C813C96"><enum>(1)</enum><text>qualifies as a wildland firefighter based on the definitions of <quote>firefighter</quote> and <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> in section 5332a(a); or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H215DC92042F14EBFB7D3810B04E6BAB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident related duties during the period such employee is assigned to a qualifying incident (as defined in section 5545c(a)(5)).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAE156A3784F14102B41B27BF691909D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>amending the section heading to read: <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">Wage-board overtime, Sunday rates, and other premium pay</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8CAAD54F935F47EBA8D9BA883990D9B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 5545, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H99B5826853194FD28F4D5F3F0F5A39B8" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H773565305B4F40BC840F426B02883A25"><enum>(e)</enum><text>For an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who is temporarily deployed to perform wildland fire incident related duties, subsection (c)(2) shall not apply to hours during such temporary deployment notwithstanding any other provision of law.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0A49C3C577A64831BE978606F9CC8388"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 5545a, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HDD96D4B99787420EAB2DEEB607D3B560" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HFC2D9924B177499C921BDF32664ABBC3"><enum>(l)</enum><text>For an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who is temporarily deployed to perform wildland fire incident related duties, subsection (c)(2) shall not apply to hours during such temporary deployment notwithstanding any other provision of law.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB4571856232E4EF186D63E3EF56703EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 5547(a), by inserting <quote>5545c,</quote> after <quote>5545a,</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H16B5F205321B40BB8A4AAF9E3C69A335"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall be effective on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HB8027925234E49878F0AF6761A14B52D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by—</text> <paragraph id="HE7F666C37895481FA6C32E736DF46AAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>amending the item relating to section 5544 to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HA2DFA8E36B85430EB4C46EC3D5187AB6" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">5544. Wage-board overtime, Sunday rates, and other premium pay.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">and </continuation-text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H891522089CF94691A13B83BE618CA0E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>inserting after the item relating to section 5545b the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H4D460FBFBD69478FB5E72C07857E8FA4" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">5545c. Incident standby premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H9A6E002F432D407EB5D544CDC6DBC790"><enum>4.</enum><header>Special limitations on pay for wildland firefighters</header> <subsection id="H458CB8AF24134C25BCA9165450F01F97"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD7A297155DE1424B806248EAAB806AA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after section 5547 the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H3E889DEEF38841F99C7454FE5AA79E2F" style="USC"> <section id="H4055ED2DA53B4C659CB1BF7E92BE0421"><enum>5547a.</enum><header>Special limitations on premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header> <subsection id="H863F61B7B43E4E48A82CD181F84C6684"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text>
<paragraph id="H26B5C3D8F4F84560825414A096698186"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered employee</quote> means an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who—</text> <subparagraph id="HB7EE9E08D71B4819B03F61587F9980C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>qualifies as a wildland firefighter based on the definitions of <quote>firefighter</quote> and <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> in section 5332a(a); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCB99A75426B049FFAA2D454FC363BB1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident related duties during the period such employee is assigned to a qualifying incident;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9DDF079F379F4BEC93330773102DB076"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered services</quote> means services performed by an employee that are determined by the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Agriculture, as applicable, to primarily involve emergency wildfire suppression activities, including any periods of duty when the employee is sleeping or resting during an extended period of deployment to engage in those activities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3966031E73B042509F044745A6079C60"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>emergency wildland fire suppression activities</quote> means initial-response and extended-response activities that directly relate to suppression of a wildfire, including activities associated with a severity incident but excluding activities associated with a prescribed fire incident (as those terms are defined section 5545c); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D383F40F0F54128B549071B9F5404A9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>premium pay</quote> means the premium pay paid under the provisions of law cited in section 5547(a), except as otherwise provided in subsection (h).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7336657B26794145B243399D14085190"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Any premium pay earned by a covered employee for covered services shall be disregarded in calculating the aggregate of such employee’s basic pay and premium pay for purposes of applying a limitation under section 5547.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFF7950E88ACE40569BC373E46094EDAE"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Any premium pay that is disregarded under subsection (b) shall be disregarded in calculating such employee’s aggregate pay for purposes of applying the limitation in section 5307.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2450B2C2747C409083A70535944B49ED"><enum>(d)</enum><text>Pay that is disregarded under subsection (b) may not be paid to the extent it would cause the aggregate of the employee’s basic pay, premium pay, and hazard pay under section 5545(d) payable in the applicable calendar year to exceed the rate of basic pay payable for a position at level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313, as in effect at the end of such calendar year. Any premium pay that is subject to a biweekly limitation under section 5547(c) must be paid first before other premium pay in applying the level II limitation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H434CFBD2062543AC8EECCF39DDA6AEC4"><enum>(e)</enum><text>Application of the limit in subsection (d) or subsection (h) to a covered employee may be waived at the sole and exclusive discretion of the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Agriculture, as applicable. Before authorizing such a waiver for employees of their respective agencies, each Secretary, after consulting with the other Secretary, shall prescribe criteria that will be applied in making a determination to grant a waiver.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H61B19ADD9E684845B586940BB312932C"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Any additional pay resulting from application of this section may not be used in computing a lump-sum payment for accumulated and accrued annual leave under section 5551 or section 5552.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H29796E7D02A24BE3A227B9A1384DD18D"><enum>(g)</enum><text>The Departments of the Interior and Agriculture shall maintain records that document uses of the authority provided by this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H16143B15CB88446FBED1A6EF507418EC"><enum>(h)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD17A61AC593544538F99790C737BFF9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For prevailing rate employees described in section 5342(a)(2)(A) who meet the requirements in subsection (a)(l) to qualify as a covered employee, premium pay may not be paid to the extent it would cause the aggregate of the employee’s basic pay and premium pay in the applicable calendar year to exceed the rate of basic pay payable for a position at level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313, as in effect at the end of such calendar year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF6CEEC2BD8B4D2B8388A87961DD899B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For the purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>basic pay</quote> means wages, environmental differential pay, and night shift differential pay, and the term <quote>premium pay</quote> means overtime pay, Sunday premium pay, and holiday premium pay.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H50BBE58052FD4E2E95D8CD29AF457B70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 5541(2)(xi), by inserting <quote>, section 5547a(h),</quote> after <quote>section 5544</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB650BB653B734E2E96FFD469343E99E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Calendar year 2023</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of applying section 5547 and section 1701 of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/43">Public Law 117–43</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5547">5 U.S.C. 5547</external-xref> note) in calendar year 2023, incident standby premium pay shall be included in premium pay that is subject to the limits established in those sections.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFCA3B7603D034236B9A4F01FD50B08C0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the first day of the first pay period that has a payment date in January 2024. Subsection (b) shall be effective on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0BCA3DCC3E6943F1A63823359EEFA9FA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is further amended by inserting after the item for section 5547 the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H513103DA47F84FB98631B5178122A66A" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">5547a. Special limitations on premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="H406E4AFBEEA34D0FA0307952B4DFC618"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rest and recuperation leave for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header>
<subsection id="H361197B59DF946679FFA7F63E2A8CF2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after section 6329d the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HFFA81DCB855542C3B0614E3ED5F0876C" style="USC"> <section id="H1BBBCC2436604C6DB704A69A222CC0B6"><enum>6329e.</enum><header>Rest and recuperation leave for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header> <subsection id="HB248669566844E9AA0742219A7B88909"><enum>(a)</enum><text>In this section—</text>
<paragraph id="HDEE4227C1F64434E850E226D52EC012B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>applicable Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98FB0B6EDA88478EB5E11F9F4132A13C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered employee</quote> means an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4945BCDE49AF4DB8AFD8E00BFF09D90C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>qualifies as a <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> based on the definitions of <quote>firefighter</quote> and <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> in section 5332a(a) (applying the definition of <quote>employee</quote> in section 6301(2) in lieu of the definition of <quote>employee</quote> in section 5331(a)); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5F5F763AE2274C1C996FC3B0E8DB99F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident related duties during the period such employee is assigned to a qualifying incident; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H823B2DCD1B49459B9C0D810C4F39875F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>qualifying incident</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 5545c(a)(5).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD1D16E872CA84A9B86D9D6C95E5DD78F"><enum>(b)</enum><text>A covered employee may receive paid rest and recuperation leave following the completion of service under a qualifying incident, subject to policies established at the sole and exclusive discretion of the Secretary of the Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior, as applicable. Each Secretary shall prescribe such policies after consulting with the other Secretary.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HAC4E5723B943454FAC64F22765B33663"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Rest and recuperation leave granted under this section shall be used during scheduled hours within the covered employee’s tour of duty established for leave-charging purposes and shall be paid in the same manner as annual leave. Rest and recuperation leave must be used immediately after a qualifying incident and may not be set aside for later use. A covered employee may not receive any payment for unused rest and recuperation leave.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3386768C5F824959B95F05F77E3851CB"><enum>(d)</enum><text>A covered employee with an intermittent work schedule shall be excused from duty during the same period of time that other covered employees in the same circumstances are entitled to rest and recuperation leave and shall receive a payment as if the covered employee with an intermittent work schedule were entitled to rest and recuperation leave under subsections (b) and (c).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H83EDA54B90984AA590956ED27B07031F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall be effective on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2E70311CBDF44501AD86A361D1BBCF44"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/63">chapter 63</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/6329d">section 6329d</external-xref> the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H3D5E2B43FE6C4435BEED8908DB6C116D" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">6329e. Rest and recuperation leave for employees engaged in wildland firefighting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="HF1EA8897A4A442AF9D45E4F6831A4B72"><enum>6.</enum><header>Health provisions</header>
<subsection id="HDBA976B8AD0147C6A61D9A34F79D0970"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Database; recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretaries shall—</text> <paragraph id="H3797595B6096445397D7343391C7847F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish and maintain a publicly accessible, searchable database on a website, to be called the <quote>Federal Wildland Firefighter Cancer and Cardiovascular Disease Database</quote>, to track chronic disease caused by on-the-job environmental exposure over the lifetimes of current and former Federal wildland firefighters;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1DF191E8AECC4711A1D1AA69B8253477"><enum>(2)</enum><text>update such database not less than on a yearly basis; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H05B797C966374CCA803F2747EA04C89E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and adhere to recommendations on mitigation strategies to minimize exposure to environmental hazards for Federal wildland firefighters. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HCED8F020F00F4AC18439997C2D2AB5C0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mental health</header>
<paragraph id="H7CC1CCAF8B3D4FD0A2859C7A865B3EF9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mental health program</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2024, the Secretaries shall establish and carry out a program for Federal wildland firefighters for mental health awareness and support. Such program shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H4C941695BA2B41E4B484052D5035C741"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A mental health awareness campaign.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0F074CAF66214C74A1FB67A5E7A81D5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A mental health education and training program that includes an on-boarding curriculum.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5730CA33506F423B8BCD8F8342272653"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An extensive peer-to-peer mental health support network for Federal wildland firefighters and their immediate family. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H820CD103650745A9A808B1C00360654C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Expansion of the Critical Incident Stress Management Program, to develop and retain a larger pool of qualified mental health professionals who are familiar with the experiences of the emergency response workforce. The Program shall monitor and track mental health in the profession to better understand the scope of the issue and provide ongoing assistance and professional long term care to patients.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H17F1C61D144545B686C1405C7060F2E0"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish and carry out a new and distinct mental health support service specific to Federal wildland firefighters and their immediate family, with culturally relevant and trauma informed mental health professionals who are readily available, and not subject to any limit on the number of sessions or service provided.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H84B584065B56451D88683320EC8E93EA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mental health leave</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal wildland firefighter shall be entitled to 7 consecutive days of leave, without loss or reduction in pay, during any calendar year. Leave provided under this paragraph shall not—</text> <subparagraph id="H13F5B1AA7DEE46E380C51F94B5E64A8E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>accumulate for use in succeeding years; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H510437CA6EA240B9A61D41FA0F41918A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be considered to be annual or vacation leave for purposes of section 5551 or 5552 of title 5, United States Code, or for any other purpose.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H22AF943B3B3D443C9495C64C6A519E3B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsections (a) and (b), the Secretaries may enter into partnerships or cooperative agreements with other Federal agencies, universities, or non-profit institutions.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H62B9BF9347AA48F79A3C2A5CCCBF1CB1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>OWCP</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Workers’ Compensation Programs within the Department of Labor shall—</text> <paragraph id="HF48F1640B04B48F3815FAED04B60DA79"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recognize post-traumatic stress disorder and psychological stress-related injuries or illnesses correlated to fire protection, suppression, and incident support activities, and ensure long term coverage for the duration of the illnesses; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDD25ECF19C249038D12E67C2D0842A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expand the Special Claims Unit to ensure adequate unit staffing levels are sufficient to expedite the claims process and shorten response times to wildland firefighter and incident support personnel injured or effected on the job in order to alleviate the psychological and financial burdens placed on the patient and their families.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H5C0466E9E57A4259BD84AC6FA02915C1"><enum>7.</enum><header>Retirement for firefighters</header> <subsection id="HEF6DD07AFA9C4B7BB73670C07872F3EC" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Deposit service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any service performed by an individual as a Federal wildland firefighter on or after January 1, 1989, for which retirement deductions under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, have not been made shall be creditable under such chapter, but only if such firefighter—</text>
<paragraph id="HF9EBF71A84C8408BAB886BFDB5F2E265" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submits a written election to the Director; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H785FA3DB6A7648A7A9A739AB8E5D97A5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the deposit requirements of section 8411(f) of such title had been met with respect to such service.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0362422DDF3545D8B821E7E221D5094C" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disability annuity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date of enactment of this Act, any Federal wildland firefighter who suffers from a disease described in section 8143b(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code, due to environmental job-related exposure, including smoke inhalation, silicate inhalation, and firefighting toxic exposure, shall be considered to be disabled for purposes of section 8451 of such title. Such section 8451 shall be applied to any such firefighter by substituting <quote>12 months</quote> for <quote>18 months</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H11ADEB7058A04A959A7786474572187B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Including overtime as basic pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8331(3) of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H17B9B8C6CE2B487F8263815500972BEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC62DCC8541954A0B94E9C46FEFE522A8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A3A72EC58E64DA1A577FD2EFC333B08"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (I) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0C75ACB6DEBF4124BA0C9280C931F0E6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H7F4C5CDC972D46E28A9019544AE2626D" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a Federal wildland firefighter (as that term is defined in section 1(b) of the Tim Hart Wildland Firefighter Classification and Pay Parity Act), overtime pay received on or after the date of enactment of this subparagraph; </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80CFB89B69444F65B52308AB2A76FE8F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in the undesignated matter following subparagraph (J) (as added by paragraph (3)), by striking <quote>subparagraphs (B) through (I) of this paragraph</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraphs (B) through (J) of this paragraph,</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFBEB26DA65454D38A9ADBBA36FA5FC34"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Separate normal-Cost percentage</header><text>Section 8423(a)(1)(B)(i) of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <quote>firefighters,</quote> the following: <quote>Federal wildland firefighter (as that term is defined in section 1 of the Tim Hart Wildland Firefighter Classification and Pay Parity Act),</quote>. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="H34B2E34A39D94060800E827917D0BCFA"><enum>8.</enum><header>Pay parity for Federal structural firefighters</header>
<subsection id="H649D89E5AD0848558785F2D436E09A3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, any pay, benefits, and bonuses provided to any Federal structural firefighter shall be comparable with the pay, benefits, and bonuses provided for Federal wildland firefighters under this Act and the amendments made by this Act. Not later than 1 year after the date the pay scale is established under section 5332a of title 5, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act, the Director shall submit a report to Congress on whether pay for such Federal structural firefighters is competitive with Federal wildland firefighters.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4A12F428C344457E806251CDC6DDED25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal structural firefighter defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>Federal structural firefighter</quote>—</text>
<paragraph id="H045708F21A644AE791B1B165ADF2B004"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term <quote>firefighter</quote> in section 8401 of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFBAE83BD0F424BF189BC54E50021A29B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not include any Federal wildland firefighter.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H92474E7D7C7244F5A3509F669C44699E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>9.</enum><header>Other matters</header>
<subsection id="H289FEF996392447296B814CB5CFB4A10" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual adjustments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, beginning in the first pay period beginning on or after the date that the pay scale is established under section 5332a of title 5, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act, and annually thereafter, the basic rate of pay for each Federal wildland firefighter occupying a position within such pay scale shall be increased by not less than the percentage equal to the percent change in the Consumer Price Index (all items—United States city average), published monthly by the Bureau of Labor Statistics, for December of the preceding year over such Consumer Price Index for the December of the year prior to the preceding year, adjusted to the nearest one-tenth of 1 percent.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7428B9F19604459D92FACA6833E72227" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compensation comparable to non-Federal firefighters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date the pay scale is established under section 5332a of title 5, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act, the Secretaries shall submit a report to Congress on whether pay, benefits, and bonuses provided to Federal wildland firefighters are comparable to the pay, benefits, and bonuses provided for non-Federal firefighters in the State or locality where Federal wildland firefighters are based. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H67897295608C4980A696955830AAB519" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Hazardous duty pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal wildland firefighter carrying out work completed during prescribed fire, parachuting, tree climbing over 20 feet, hazard tree removal, and other hazardous work as identified by the Secretaries, shall be entitled to be paid the appropriate differential under section 5545(d) of title 5, United States Code, as if such employee was covered by such section. The Director may prescribe regulations to carry out this subsection.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H74D830D7946A426E958F4CEB372E9AF0" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other matters</header> <paragraph id="H0F93AA2164AD4D7F8D91D87B2408C998" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unpaid leave to care for family member</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal wildland firefighter not covered by the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 or subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/63">chapter 63</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall be allowed a period of unpaid leave, during each calendar year, not to exceed 180 days in order to care for the spouse, or a son, daughter, or parent, of the employee, if such spouse, son, daughter, or parent has a serious health condition. Leave provided under this paragraph shall not accumulate for use in subsequent years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B4342FB6FA64542B49A43DFCE13DA6E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recruitment and retention bonus</header><text>In order to promote the recruitment and retention of Federal wildland firefighters, the Director, in coordination with the Secretaries, shall establish a program under which a recruitment or retention bonus of not less than $1,000 may be paid to a Federal wildland firefighter in an amount as determined appropriate by the Director and the Secretaries. The minimum amount of such bonus in the previous sentence shall be increased each year by the Consumer Price Index in the manner prescribed under subsection (a)(2). Any bonus under this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="H9AAE7CE4AD1849AC95FDC79CB8E6D186" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be paid to any primary or secondary Federal wildland firefighter upon the date that such firefighter successfully completes a work capacity test; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D5CC933534540029D9A70B659BFAC19" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may not be paid to any such firefighter more than once per calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C316405183140B59892B73F96D7FCE5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Housing allowance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries shall provide a housing allowance to any Federal wildland firefighter deployed to a location more than 50 miles from their primary residence. Such allowance shall be in an amount determined appropriate by the Secretaries and adjusted based on the cost of housing in the area of deployment. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H510B56CE50DC478F8AD49856E9C5CF6C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Career transition</header>
<subparagraph id="H550523141F344CB2B0430E34BD3BC1AE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretaries shall establish, maintain, coordinate, and operate a voluntary tuition assistance program for Federal wildland firefighters occupying a permanent position that encompass a broad range of educational experiences (either in-person or through distance-learning), including academic skills development, vocational programs, career and technical programs, and programs leading to the award of undergraduate and graduate degrees.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF180C640A5614C19AAED9D4313756C6D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program under subparagraph (A) shall provide, not more than once during each calendar year, a payment of not less than $4,000 to each Federal wildland firefighter who elects to participate in the program. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAF60F5392A6449F4BD048D1204E41ED8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries shall conduct an annual review of whether the amount provided under subparagraph (B) is adequate, in consideration of inflation and other effects.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

