<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0E7333AE23824DBE89B70A5B0DF02D46" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4883 IH: Medicare Common Ownership Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4883</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require the disclosure of certain ownership information relating to health care provider and pharmacy ownership, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H01FF0887B2BB426882E011E86B45CD05" style="OLC">
<section id="H54910D1774E742408162EF6B7D4DC509" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicare Common Ownership Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0DD8806D752647B4BF529A2817CF5A52" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on integration in Medicare</header> <subsection id="H6EA7C9332B424BE493E9295B45186980"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required MA and PDP reporting</header> <paragraph id="H293EC81C7AEF4CD1933E4F65CD5C24CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>MA plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1857(e) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-27">42 U.S.C. 1395w–27(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC2E1BB26B57346549159AD9748993D81" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H08B790BBBF5A43E59B026BA07E2BC10C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Required disclosure of certain information relating to health care provider ownership</header>
<subparagraph id="HD5369ECA74CF4ECFBCFE20A6C743ED38"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan year 2025 and for every third plan year thereafter, each MA organization offering an MA plan under this part during such plan year shall submit to the Secretary, at a time and in a manner specified by the Secretary—</text> <clause id="HABBBF9A2657142A9BA69242FC3C8891A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the taxpayer identification number for each health care provider that was a specified health care provider with respect to such organization during such year; </text></clause>
<clause id="H90C986E6FB944F8481412C4C5290A39E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total amount of incentive-based payments made to, and the total amount of shared losses recoupments collected from, such specified health care providers during such plan year; and</text></clause> <clause id="HDC83D87438314D2BA650F43F49DCA3C3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the total amount of incentive-based payments made to, and the total amount of shared losses recoupments collected from, providers of services and suppliers not described in clause (ii) during such plan year.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3FBCF9B992CF487CBEC670C56D597F5C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>specified health care provider</quote> means, with respect to an MA organization and a plan year, a provider of services or supplier with respect to which such organization (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such organization) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9ACDFF3E333F4618A6F7E285FBC7E430"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prescription drug plans</header><text>Section 1860D–12(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-112">42 U.S.C. 1395w–112(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6689919E5CEC4EA98D960E3D79A7C0C1" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H6A5AFBFF580748CCBB582F5911F1F65B"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Provision of information relating to pharmacy ownership</header>
<subparagraph id="H09D691B462F747BDA4CD5225CA30C19B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan year 2025 and for every third plan year thereafter, each PDP sponsor offering a prescription drug plan under this part during such plan year shall submit to the Secretary, at a time and in a manner specified by the Secretary, the taxpayer identification number and National Provider Identifier for each pharmacy that was a specified pharmacy with respect to such sponsor during such year.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2B267D3E4EB4DC1B3805FD0104FF06C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>specified pharmacy</quote> means, with respect to an PDP sponsor offering a prescription drug plan and a plan year, a pharmacy with respect to which—</text>
<clause id="H994D9F2EFDEB45748018F66B2A437D4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such sponsor (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such sponsor) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined); or</text></clause> <clause id="HC20EB4828FD64754833A6EAC713ECCF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a pharmacy benefit manager offering services under such plan (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined) in such sponsor) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC100A4F6390A4C849D9EFBB06AE19B18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>MedPAC reports</header><text>Part E of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA11715CCCB114B37A044A95AEE291020" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H2FD05CA211C047EEB2AC3C063AF18BFE"><enum>1899C.</enum><header>Reports on vertical integration under Medicare</header> <subsection id="HDF47CD07377641D9B428BD4F9EA6C266"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 15, 2029, and every 3 years thereafter, the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission shall submit to Congress a report on the state of vertical integration in the health care sector during the applicable year with respect to entities participating in the Medicare program, including health care providers, pharmacies, prescription drug plan sponsors, Medicare Advantage organizations, and pharmacy benefit managers. Such report shall include—</text>
<paragraph id="H1E00A79D4A1346B68A322AE34082EEDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to Medicare Advantage organizations, the evaluation described in subsection (b);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H62DE77A8CF824F91A0A3087E39F0B495"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to prescription drug plans, pharmacy benefit managers, and pharmacies, the comparisons and evaluations described in subsection (c); </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAC1E54F009C14380A624526E4F4914F5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>with respect to Medicare Advantage plans under which benefits are available for physician-administered drugs, the information described in subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC04032A84A4C4778B4FF57283C6F53D0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the identifications described in subsection (e); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDEDE0414536420093513E29177789C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an analysis of the impact of such integration on health care access, price, quality, and outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H656272D22D61485CA08BC5865A599C8A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medicare Advantage organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a)(1), the evaluation described in this subsection is, with respect to Medicare Advantage organizations and an applicable year, an evaluation, taking into account patient acuity and the types of areas serviced by such organization, of—</text>
<paragraph id="HC7F92248FAC740D9A70DD9B5E77DDEB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the average number of qualifying diagnoses made during such year with respect to enrollees of a Medicare Advantage plan offered by such organization who, during such year, received a health risk assessment from a specified health care provider;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3B1E648B8C124C8F83982C015F622230"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the average risk score for such enrollees who received such an assessment during such year;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF40A9D29B6014CB2BDC6DE3221F381F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any relationship between such risk scores for such enrollees receiving such an assessment from such a provider during such year and incentive payments made to such providers; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CE5F538DB994109B8F094857D6165D4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the average risk score for enrollees of such plan who received any item or service from a specified health care provider during such year; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H32A48A2F1C4244BAB297F4F7249FF4DC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any relationship between the risk scores of enrollees under such plan and whether the enrollees have received any item or service from a specified provider; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53995364E5C84A13AA9F251B7F401C0C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any relationship between the risk scores of enrollees under such plan that have received any item or service from a specified provider and incentive payments made under the plan to specified providers.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA952DDEA52A644BAAD7FCB0E1104FB2F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prescription drug plans</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a)(2), the comparisons and evaluations described in this subsection are, with respect to prescription drug plans and an applicable year, the following:</text> <paragraph id="H295ED8B3526A463C83F2C1923CF72984"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each covered part D drug for which benefits are available under such a plan, a comparison of the average negotiated rate in effect with specified pharmacies with such rates in effect for in-network pharmacies that are not specified pharmacies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H99B91AA93EAB49F08DA00EDC8A981BA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Comparisons of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HE0FA571494814958BCB0A32D73F47437"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The total amount paid by pharmacy benefit managers to specified pharmacies for covered part D drugs and the total amount so paid to pharmacies that are not specified pharmacies for such drugs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2E2937C1E5454D79ADF09F043A8FFB71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The total amount paid by such sponsors to specified pharmacy benefit managers as reimbursement for covered part D drugs and the total amount so paid to pharmacy benefit managers that are not specified pharmacy benefit managers as such reimbursement.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA461ED42EA94327AA6F3FAC37196BE4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fees paid under by plan to specified pharmacy benefit managers compared to such fees paid to pharmacy benefit managers that are not specified pharmacy benefit managers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA0D6B159A39C47A38246784F4EFD2F1F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of the total amount of direct and indirect remuneration for covered part D drugs passed through to prescription drug plan sponsors and the total amount retained by pharmacy benefit managers (including entities under contract with such a manager).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9A481FCC801415C8BB38C949EBAFC2C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To the extent that the available data permits, an evaluation of fees charged by rebate aggregators that are affiliated with plan sponsors. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H716F4E6BD2B640BF91D763B374E239B9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Physician-Administered drugs</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a)(3), the information described in this subsection is, with respect to physician-administered drugs for which benefits are available under a Medicare Advantage plan during an applicable year, the following:</text> <paragraph id="H33D999823CA845F886C641CDF55D2634"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each such plan, an identification of each drug for which benefits were available under such plan only when administered by a health care provider that acquired such drug from an affiliated pharmacy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68DD71D148704741A473A7DDFBC895E1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of the difference between the total number of drugs administered by a health care provider that were acquired from affiliated pharmacies compared to the number of such drugs so administered that were acquired from pharmacies other than affiliated pharmacies, and an evaluation of the difference in payments for such drugs so administered when acquired from a specified pharmacy and when acquired from a pharmacy that is not a specified pharmacy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0F7214E6351E49D89D22F3C2B3AC786C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An evaluation of the dollar value of all such drugs that were not so administered because of a delay attributable to an affiliated pharmacy compared to the dollar value of all such drugs that were not so administered because of a delay attributable to pharmacy that is not an affiliated pharmacy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2936E5CAFAD74DBB98F86D4AF816FFBB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The number of enrollees administered such a drug that was acquired from an affiliated pharmacy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA72929E5873145C6B6318327E3E58EBE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of enrollees furnished such a drug that was acquired from a pharmacy that is not an affiliated pharmacy.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H37C61D0AC4974A12AECD42563556F189"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Identifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a)(4), the identifications described in this subsection are, with respect to an applicable year, identifications of each health care entity participating under the Medicare program with respect to which another health care entity so participating is a person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320a-3">42 U.S.C. 1320a–3(a)(3)</external-xref>)).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDD09EDC6241B49B8833FEFF863F85069"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HF54B44B9AA5E4A9F9BA06AD4BB4DBBA0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Affiliated pharmacy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>affiliated pharmacy</quote> means, with respect to a Medicare Advantage plan offered by a Medicare Advantage organization, a pharmacy with respect to which such organization (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such organization) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7106BEBDA0EF44A786F0B97F942AC1C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable year</header><text>The term <quote>applicable year</quote> means, with respect to a report submitted under subsection (a), the first calendar year beginning at least 4 years prior to the date of the submission of such report.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB2B7AD8059D4448DAF38298CC83E7DC7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered part D drug</header><text>The term <quote>covered part D drug</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1860D–2(e).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8EE52CA26C74CDFB519408343A71A30"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Direct and indirect remuneration</header><text>The term <quote>direct and indirect remuneration</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 423.308 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H964E8054652D4B7BB4C4FCCF95A4CA46"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Qualifying diagnosis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>qualifying diagnosis</quote> means, with respect to an enrollee of a Medicare Advantage plan, a diagnosis that is taken into account in calculating a risk score for such enrollee under the risk adjustment methodology established by the Secretary pursuant to section 1853(a)(3).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H711E6DD5F40B4E629E72B0F061D0B5F9" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Risk score</header><text>The term <quote>risk score</quote> means, with respect to an enrollee of a Medicare Advantage plan, the score calculated for such individual using the methodology described in paragraph (5).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFAD56511328F4F90BDD8C78F679E9EC2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Physician-administered drug</header><text>The term <quote>physician-administered drug</quote> means a drug furnished to an individual that, had such individual been enrolled under part B and not enrolled under part C, would have been payable under section 1842(o). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEFB78E178965437A9358D9202FE796AE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Specified health care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>specified health care provider</quote> means, with respect to a Medicare Advantage plan offered by a Medicare Advantage organization, a health care provider with respect to which such organization (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such organization) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2F8BD69856E4FAA92940C8734500D27"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Specified pharmacy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>specified pharmacy</quote> means, with respect to a prescription drug plan offered by a prescription drug plan sponsor, a pharmacy with respect to which—</text> <subparagraph id="HFB17FB152F2D4E2F816BD438AC781DB5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such sponsor (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such sponsor) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6510EB13061D42069F6FD3B209F7DCC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a pharmacy benefit manager offering services under such plan (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined) in such sponsor) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB21BE749272C4DBB9C61A83C2B58BA4B"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Specified pharmacy benefit manager</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>specified pharmacy benefit manager</quote> means, with respect to a prescription drug plan offered by a prescription drug plan sponsor, a pharmacy benefit manager with respect to which such sponsor (or any person with an ownership or control interest (as defined in section 1124(a)(3)) in such sponsor) is a person with an ownership or control interest (as so defined).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


