<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC132375FBBBE414F8E4F993B96F78B7F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2766 IH: Uyghur Policy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2766</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000377">Mr. Armstrong</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To support the human rights of Uyghurs and members of other minority groups residing primarily in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region and safeguard their distinct identity, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9C03214B3218401EAC44F5F907AE68D1" style="OLC"><section id="H609B751D13BF4F3AB3400A6AC33144E4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Uyghur Policy Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2809BEDE171948178E98390CAF0492EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD7A5F785F0E24F47B4DA586361ED2B25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The People’s Republic of China (PRC) continues to repress the distinct Islamic, Turkic identity of Uyghurs and members of other minority groups of the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) in northwestern China and other areas of their habitual residence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D662140B2DD487DB5F947B462BE01D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Uyghurs, and other predominantly Muslim ethnic minorities historically making up the majority of the XUAR population, have maintained throughout their history a distinct religious and cultural identity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H329FF873CBC3456B83A122A82C8A58F5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Human rights, including freedom of religion or belief, and respect for the Uyghurs’ unique Muslim identity are legitimate interests of the international community.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE784CE448F24C3996849714B12840D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The People’s Republic of China has ratified the International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights and is thereby bound by its provisions. The PRC has also signed the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights. Article One of both covenants state that all peoples have the right to self-determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AD35F67BB224CABA25DDF4F681A1274"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An official campaign to encourage Han Chinese migration into the XUAR has placed immense pressure on those who seek to preserve the ethnic, cultural, religious, and linguistic traditions of the Uyghur people. Chinese authorities have supported an influx of Han Chinese economic immigrants into the XUAR, implemented discrimination against Uyghurs in hiring practices, and provided unequal access to healthcare services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCA042367966428E81D801C137028FF9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The authorities of the People’s Republic of China have manipulated the strategic objectives of the international war on terror to mask their increasing cultural and religious oppression of the Muslim population residing in the XUAR.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADBAD1A877B648D0B7C37735BB3FA472"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Following unrest in the region, in 2014, Chinese authorities launched their <quote>Strike Hard against Violent Extremism</quote> campaign, in which dubious allegations of widespread extremist activity were used as justification for gross human rights violations committed against members of the Uyghur community in the XUAR.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D54F06BB6E248BF8EF164C31806BC77"><enum>(8)</enum><text>PRC authorities have made use of the legal system as a tool of repression, including for the imposition of arbitrary detentions and for torture against members of the Uyghur community and other populations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCD68F778A7B4007A66ADCB7798FB6AF"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Uyghurs and Kazakhs who have secured citizenship or permanent residency outside of the PRC have attested to repeated threats, harassment, and surveillance by PRC officials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97A0289D37894FA4A19D42A07696E85C"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Reporting from international news organizations has found that over the past decade, family members of Uyghurs living outside of the PRC have gone missing or been detained to force Uyghur expatriates to return to the PRC or silence their dissent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8C900EDECA54C858B6167826AB19114"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Credible evidence from human rights organizations, think tanks, and journalists confirms that more than 1,000,000 Uyghurs and members of other Muslim ethnic minority groups have been imprisoned in <quote>political reeducation</quote> centers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CFB9F943905479494DAB688192A51EA"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Independent accounts from former detainees of <quote>political reeducation</quote> centers describe inhumane conditions and treatment including forced political indoctrination, torture, beatings, rape, forced sterilization, and food deprivation. Former detainees also confirmed that they were told by guards the only way to secure release was to demonstrate sufficient political loyalty to the PRC Government and the Chinese Communist Party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27EE3F1A57B54193AB76A1E8BB3DC4A3"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Popular discourse surrounding the ongoing atrocities in the XUAR and advocacy efforts to assist Uyghurs remains muted in most Muslim majority nations around the world.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C3653A7603D46C7B9DD62A6EE8D3B55"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Both Secretary of State Antony Blinken and Former Secretary of State Michael Pompeo have stated that the PRC Government has committed genocide and crimes against humanity against Uyghurs and other ethnic and religious minorities in the XUAR.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5011C30921E74EA69A662C1A0BCB5E92"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Government bodies of multiple nations have also declared that PRC Government atrocities against such populations in the XUAR constitute genocide, including the parliaments of the United Kingdom, Belgium, Czechia, Lithuania, the Netherlands, and Canada.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H98E725EC8F9B45F98146D54309C28D78"><enum>3.</enum><header>Declarations of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress—</text><paragraph id="H0D4CF8E4781A4DDEB79C7EA7C96C929F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>calls upon the Government of the People’s Republic of China to open the XUAR to regular, transparent, and unmanipulated visits by members of the press, Members of Congress, congressional staff delegations, the United States Special Coordinator for Uyghur Issues under section 4, and members and staff of the Congressional-Executive Commission on the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EB2CD5C399F4925B63DDF62C117DE30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>calls upon the Government of the People’s Republic of China to recognize, and seek to ensure the preservation of, the distinct ethnic, cultural, religious, and linguistic identity of Uyghurs and members of other ethnic and religious minority groups in the XUAR;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC32A667D3FFD4D8997A8B4BE3CB09905"><enum>(3)</enum><text>calls upon the Government of the People’s Republic of China to cease all government-sponsored crackdowns, imprisonments, and detentions of people throughout the XUAR aimed at those involved in the peaceful expression of their ethnic, cultural, political, or religious identity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC46C53F50DF54801AB00AE1037E8D17A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>commends countries that have provided shelter and hospitality to Uyghurs in exile, including Turkey, Albania, and Germany; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB15DAC2278C04F77A5C466631E41E9D6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>urges countries with sizeable Muslim populations, given commonalities in their religious and cultural identities, to demonstrate concern over the plight of Uyghurs.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H9C9DE2A50CF24391834DD0C0A0C2817E"><enum>4.</enum><header>United States Special Coordinator for Uyghur Issues</header><subsection id="HD8DA01FE75664951AD059CA9B3D66C54"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be within the Department of State a United States Special Coordinator for Uyghur Issues (in this section referred to as the <quote>Special Coordinator</quote>), to be designated by the Secretary of State in accordance with subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6EABA7F18C464008B84758BE2D80924E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Secretary of State shall consult with the Chairs and Ranking Members of the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives prior to the designation of the Special Coordinator.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB437057AD8FC4C05A863022ABE7509A7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Central objective</header><text>The Special Coordinator should seek to promote the protection and preservation of the distinct ethnic, cultural, religious, and linguistic identities of the Uyghurs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3DF00137FA5448C7974D46A18E52409A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties and responsibilities</header><text>The Special Coordinator should, as appropriate—</text><paragraph id="HCDE115B046A04F6E964272B6CDD6095C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate United States Government policies, programs, and projects concerning the Uyghurs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H103B1527011841C4AE54D29AFDF33DD6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>vigorously promote the policy of seeking to protect the distinct ethnic, religious, cultural, and linguistic identity of the Uyghurs and seek improved respect for human rights in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8A6336EF70449EE95E09EA2C3760944"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintain close contact with Uyghur religious, cultural, and political leaders, including seeking regular travel to the XUAR and to Uyghur populations in Central Asia, Turkey, Albania, Germany, and other parts of Europe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F70DC08A8794E6787AD682EDC831362"><enum>(4)</enum><text>lead coordination efforts for the release of political prisoners in the XUAR who are being detained for exercising their human rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FF654E236984ECBB024BD26A6E02CE3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>consult with the United States Congress on policies relevant to the XUAR and the Uyghurs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H829428A1DA184F1BAB0E29050719EA5B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>coordinate with relevant Federal agencies to administer aid to Uyghur rights advocates; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0ED1F5286FBD42D0A20C618E5509D08C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>make efforts to establish contacts with foreign ministries of other countries, especially in Europe, Central Asia, and members of the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation, to pursue a policy of promoting greater respect for human rights and religious freedom for Uyghurs and other ethnic and religious minority groups persecuted in the PRC.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD985B90FCE04232A1054D3421DE3689"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Support</header><text>The Secretary of State shall ensure the Special Coordinator has adequate resources, staff, and administrative support to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9050FB0B0DB24F1A81B1ED883D614E06"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of State has not designated the Special Coordinator by the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report detailing the reasons for the delay.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFD88ABD44E0545B29208F6002B1B97FB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall terminate on the date that is five years after the designation of the Special Coordinator.</text></subsection></section><section id="H13C1E6FC88D547E6962538F38B7543EC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Public diplomacy in the Islamic world on the uyghur situation</header><subsection id="H33D717505D0E41C39784BAF8AB18F8E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Funding for human rights advocates</header><text>Of the amounts authorized to be appropriated for the U.S. Speaker Program in the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs of the Department of State, $250,000 for each of fiscal years 2024, 2025, and 2026 is authorized to be available for human rights advocates on behalf of the Uyghurs and members of other ethnic and religious minority groups persecuted in the PRC, whose names may be provided by the Department of State and the United States Special Coordinator for Uyghur Issues in consultation with representatives of the global Uyghur community, to speak at public diplomacy forums in Organisation of Islamic Cooperation countries and other regions on issues regarding the human rights and religious freedom of Uyghurs and members of other ethnic and religious minority groups persecuted in the PRC.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA8B95ED3213142FA8674E7599C5C0CAE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>United states agency for global media</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the United States Agency for Global Media should facilitate the unhindered dissemination of information to Organisation of Islamic Cooperation countries on issues regarding the human rights and religious freedom of Uyghurs and members of other minority groups in the XUAR.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6DC0800B79BE4B7D96D69CB44ABE5646"><enum>6.</enum><header>Access to detention facilities and prisons and the release of prisoners</header><subsection id="H107960050AD64AF78802B7D5FF84B2FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress on political reeducation and detention facilities</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the United States Government should, in cooperation with other like-minded countries, develop a strategy to—</text><paragraph id="H058ABDF2CA41498D92CDF2141B2FEC0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pressure the People’s Republic of China to immediately close all detention facilities and <quote>political reeducation</quote> camps housing Uyghurs and members of other ethnic minority groups in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C3FF6C081434FF68640122AAF5DDD0A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support the United Nations Commissioner for Human Rights and numerous United Nations Special Rapporteurs’ urgent calls for immediate and unhindered access to detention facilities and <quote>political reeducation</quote> camps in the XUAR by independent international organizations and the Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights for a comprehensive assessment of the human rights situation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE9592802A774E3C9907191FD2385DE1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of congress on prison access and prisoner release</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the President and Secretary of State, in meetings with representatives of the Government of the People’s Republic of China, should—</text><paragraph id="HA8A64BE121D04E1BA93EDE2D0AA30A8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>request the immediate and unconditional release of all prisoners detained for their ethnic, cultural, religious, and linguistic identities, or for expressing their political or religious beliefs in the XUAR;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77C97338BF134A0CA830FF4BA2E68D73"><enum>(2)</enum><text>seek access for international humanitarian organizations, including the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies, to prisoners in the XUAR to ensure such prisoners are not being mistreated and are receiving necessary medical care; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E5B529738B84995A06E81D7DFAE27F8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>seek the immediate release of all prisoners who have been arbitrarily detained and sentenced without due process, including Ekpar Asat, who participated in the Department of State’s International Visitors Leadership Program in 2016, was incarcerated after returning to the XUAR, and is now serving a 15 year prison sentence on charges of <quote>inciting ethnic hatred and ethnic discrimination</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4CE11DD4E60C4807996EA04ED470692E"><enum>7.</enum><header>Requirement for Uyghur language training</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall ensure that Uyghur language training is available to Foreign Service officers as appropriate, and that every effort is made to ensure that a Uyghur-speaking member of the Foreign Service (as such term is described in section 103 of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/3903">22 U.S.C. 3903</external-xref>)) is assigned to United States diplomatic and consular missions in China.</text></section><section id="H280FB1F68E8D48E7A343C485B70D4FF3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Uyghur considerations at the United Nations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HC3A380939DCA437E8F1004D46B4364E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the United States Government should oppose any efforts to prevent consideration of the issues related to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) in any body of the United Nations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H300CBE10BE0242FBB73883CAADC6B96F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States Government should oppose any efforts to prevent the participation of any Uyghur human rights advocates in nongovernmental fora hosted by or otherwise organized under the auspices of any body of the United Nations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEA040B3EFF4493C91861B555B8BAF97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary of State should instruct the United States Permanent Representative to the United Nations to support the appointment of a special rapporteur or working group for the XUAR for the purposes of monitoring human rights violations and abuses in the XUAR, and for making reports available to the High Commissioner for Refugees, the High Commissioner for Human Rights, the Human Rights Commission, the General Assembly, and other United Nations bodies.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

