<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC303F94DBAB64A7DB591FB6C5369F307" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4662 IH: Corporate Governance Examination Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4662</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Securities and Exchange Commission to conduct a study of certain issues with respect to shareholder proposals, proxy advisory firms, and the proxy process, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCD2880F37F7946D892693CDF189D6131" style="OLC"><section id="H0E725B79365044B6912AC4DDA85F7DB8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Corporate Governance Examination Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H9D86661EAF4749F483DBA568A1E712AB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study of certain issues with respect to shareholder proposals, proxy advisory firms, and the proxy process</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4(j) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78d">15 U.S.C. 78d(j)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5BB014A52C354416A3C20152449AB05E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H92D43B6079E74376B116F0C263E33967"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Study of certain issues with respect to shareholder proposals, proxy advisory firms, and the proxy process</header><subparagraph id="HAE5CD3D631EE42F5BA334E7E19C49075"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, and every 5 years thereafter, the Commission shall conduct a comprehensive study on shareholder proposals, proxy advisory firms, and the proxy process.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB960AFC3F14E446E96AAEDAF33D8C470"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Scope of study</header><text>The studies required under subparagraph (A) shall cover—</text><clause id="H6F9B7A1A0E3748BE8153176132ADF337"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the previous 10 years, with respect to the initial study; and</text></clause><clause id="HE40E4E1D58D74C67A012911E3BEACCFD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the previous 5 years, with respect to each other study.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB9DF4EE4161456CACE2E612032C038A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each study required under subparagraph (A) shall address the following issues:</text><clause id="H89A22DC54F554E5F8B8DB48EB0954435"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The financial and other incentives and obligations of all groups involved in the proxy process.</text></clause><clause id="HF807CB1D81C64C2C9D70E1D68DA66F90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A consideration of whether financial and other incentives have created a process that no longer serves the economic interests of long-term retail investors.</text></clause><clause id="H9F967CC05D26487F9076C4F9A7B15A12"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of whether regulations and financial incentives have created and protected the outsized influence of proxy advisors or a duopoly in proxy advice, and if so, what are the benefits and costs of that outsized influence or duopoly.</text></clause><clause id="HC1D2BC23E91F4119B427E99E8BD7D132"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The costs incurred by issuers in responding to politically-, environmentally-, or socially-motivated shareholder proposals.</text></clause><clause id="H0C34AFA7C37A47E1BC95956C8C4368FB"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment, including a cost-benefit analysis, of the adequacy of the current submission thresholds in Rule 14a–8 (17 C.F.R. 240.14a–8) to ensure that shareholder proponents have demonstrated a meaningful economic stake in a company, which is appropriate to effectively serve markets and shareholders at large.</text></clause><clause id="HF75408764A054B3CB1CFF0F459AF7651"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>An examination of the extent to which the politicization of the shareholder proposal process is increasing the operating costs of public companies.</text></clause><clause id="HBB34F06A928E48C0BD07CA90FDEAA58A"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>An analysis of the impact that shareholder proposals have on discouraging private companies from going public.</text></clause><clause id="H1604407480CB426BA1ED4D4A137D0E16"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>An evaluation of the risk that shareholder proposals may contribute to the balkanization of the U.S. economy over time.</text></clause><clause id="H9D35AEA238164F52B7F2B2613F83CCDD"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>A thorough assessment of the economic analysis, if any, conducted by proxy advisory firms and institutional shareholders when recommending or voting in favor of shareholder proposals.</text></clause><clause id="H08EC89EA4DAC4761AE96A3DD89CEFB25"><enum>(x)</enum><text>A review of the extent to which institutional investors, who owe fiduciary duties, rely on proxy advisory firm recommendations.</text></clause><clause id="H69515D8A77A6490BA1FA7EC86E3446BB"><enum>(xi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of whether, in light of their significant influence on corporate actions and vote outcomes, proxy advisors are subject to sufficient and effective regulation to ensure that their policies and recommendations are accurate, free of conflicts, and benefit the economic best interest of shareholders at large.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CBE6939BF4F47D8B529B67C8C4D2796"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the completion of each study required under subparagraph (A) the Commission shall issue a report to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives that includes the results of the study.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A84002C367843CA8AE0CA49009B78B1"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Proxy advisory firm defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <term>proxy advisory firm</term>—</text><clause id="H0473A13AC44E4DB5975FDB81EE838C30"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any person who is primarily engaged in the business of providing proxy voting advice, research, analysis, ratings, or recommendations to clients, which conduct constitutes a solicitation within the meaning of section 14 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934; and</text></clause><clause id="HC316DE00CA3C4F159A3B260870608CE3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not include any person that is exempt under law or regulation from the requirements otherwise applicable to persons engaged in such a solicitation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

