<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE2C084FF350240AFA7FED46433367AAB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 948 IH: Dr. Li Wenliang Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 948</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To posthumously award a Congressional Gold Medal to Dr. Li Wenliang, in recognition of his efforts to save lives by drawing awareness to COVID–19 and his call for transparency in China.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6734D578581E47298C8CD266E50BF409" style="OLC"><section id="H2D9AB8F9857640E48BC564CB763FF8D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Dr. Li Wenliang Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6A6CCADA8B87480B89799A29D59E50B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB305B63B49A148E2824D63A0234A4299"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Dr. Li Wenliang was a 34-year-old ophthalmologist in Wuhan, China, who died from COVID–19 after he bravely sought to draw attention to the spread of the virus despite the Government of the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party’s effort to suppress him.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3B7424326AD4B51A1E6AA23F753AF04"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In December 2019, Dr. Li Wenliang courageously notified his medical colleagues in China about the outbreak of a novel coronavirus known as COVID–19.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC714751735B3490B919012FAD82D1C16"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On January 3, 2020, after raising concerns about the spread of COVID–19, Dr. Li Wenliang was detained and questioned by Chinese officials for <quote>spreading false rumors</quote> and forced to sign a statement retracting his warnings about COVID–19.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H592E0632F21D44198D65267C9497E05F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Dr. Li Wenliang continued to work at Wuhan Central Hospital despite his knowledge of the outbreak.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FF1309BC6B349A092C4F30B5966E0B1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Tragically Dr. Li Wenliang died in February 2020 in the hospital where he worked after contracting COVID–19.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H562C21D9E2504237962CBBDE36B2EC07"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Before his death, Dr. Li Wenliang stated, <quote>If the officials had disclosed information about the epidemic earlier, I think it would have been a lot better. There should be more openness and transparency.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E2C68B616B542958D977C947C19F81C"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The people of China expressed their grief and anger on social media after the death of Dr. Li Wenliang with the phrase <quote>I want freedom of speech</quote>, which was quickly censored by the Government of the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20EE6306CAF443D2ABC8755DB09F2C88"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party inflicted incalculable damage on their people and the world by trying to extinguish the news of the COVID–19 rather than mobilize global efforts to battle it.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A49DF2A021542108F49A3C432344B6B"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Awarding Dr. Li Wenliang the Congressional Gold Medal would recognize his bold actions to draw attention to the spread of COVID–19 and call global attention to the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party’s lack of transparency and censorship of speech.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H26BB60E577874606A89ACF88764C641A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="H368048F56E3E407DBD696D5E33B3C211"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the posthumous presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design in commemoration of Dr. Li Wenliang’s efforts to save lives by drawing awareness to COVID–19 and his call for transparency in China. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7B737D30FE454683822172E748F6803C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the presentation referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary. The design shall bear an image of and the name of Dr. Li Wenliang.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94D2B59F1014436FAEC32C66BC022D77"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian Institution</header><paragraph id="HA89028CCA74841D5AAAF651CFA8DB633"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Following the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where it shall be available for display as appropriate and made available for research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H241456F670F04648B948BB187C4197A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Smithsonian Institution shall make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available for display elsewhere, particularly at appropriate locations dedicated to preserving the history of the Chinese pro-democracy movement.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H267E467AB500437DA0AC6A3A48BBC588"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section><section id="H68A9688F878D49C7BA49CBF6B768B955"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><subsection id="H2DBD789887F04B878195A72F0B2A9B66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA5ACEF1368C4454986CCC3F5D4894FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB89DB810BA8541E58023A6E08AFF7F1A"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="HAACEA968E81942BEA1E128FA652A5AFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE18572708BF040879B1D34AC231CFDBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

