<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H0DD9F2CDC72D46F99A71DB9B6E3ED77B"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2682 IH: Veterans Medical Marijuana Safe Harbor Act.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2682</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To allow veterans to use, possess, or transport medical marijuana and to discuss the use of medical marijuana with a physician of the Department of Veterans Affairs as authorized by a State or Indian Tribe, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Medical Marijuana Safe Harbor Act.</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="ide6de56af8f1f486489d45fd280d1687b"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="id67a970b638ea4b07bd32a14675eaa27f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Chronic pain affects the veteran population, with almost 60 percent of veterans returning from serving in the Armed Forces in the Middle East, and more than 50 percent of older veterans, who are using the health care system of the Department of Veterans Affairs living with some form of chronic pain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3ecafbdc25c14571afb49bd8ee9669dd"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 2020, opioids accounted for approximately 75 percent of all drug overdose deaths in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc38ad1060b6a4e5f88bbcc2ba8699868"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Veterans are twice as likely to die from opioid related overdoses than nonveterans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id379444eb225149d69be8d620b5c2c71a"><enum>(4)</enum><text>States with recreational cannabis laws experienced a 7.6 percent reduction in opioid-related emergency department visits during the 180-day period after the implementation of such laws.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6bf1e8b54fad450d866fef1c60c0391c"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Marijuana and its compounds show promise for pain management and treating a wide-range of diseases and disorders, including post-traumatic stress disorder.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4922a6e089dd4531b1d72351305e7921"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Medical marijuana in States where it is legal may serve as a less harmful alternative to opioids in treating veterans.</text></paragraph></section><section id="idcc9cf0c029664f30913518e589d796e0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Safe harbor for use by veterans of medical marijuana</header><subsection id="id4a212d794e454d53903b1cedd344eeda"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Safe harbor</header><text>Notwithstanding the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801 et seq.</external-xref>), the Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/951">21 U.S.C. 951 et seq.</external-xref>), or any other Federal law, it shall not be unlawful for—</text><paragraph id="idb654d7bdaa664ba38b4e65a9e3a14934"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a veteran to use, possess, or transport medical marijuana in a State or on Indian land if the use, possession, or transport is authorized and in accordance with the law of the applicable State or Indian Tribe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9cf5e31f926f4a3097c9ec9f42495725"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a physician to discuss with a veteran the use of medical marijuana as a treatment if the physician is in a State or on Indian land where the law of the applicable State or Indian Tribe authorizes the use, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, delivery, and transport of medical marijuana; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7b25a6aa4e7a48f2a169277cecb65716"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a physician to recommend, complete forms for, or register veterans for participation in a treatment program involving medical marijuana that is approved by the law of the applicable State or Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id8c95d7e56efc4de8871529b45d65e8c9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id77c5439effb1411e9e29d8bd0ce34abb"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian land</header><text>The term <term>Indian land</term> means any of the Indian lands, as that term is defined in section 824(b) of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1680n">25 U.S.C. 1680n</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6FCC58CE635D4670AC405B17D083E5C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given that term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idAF6ED09F4BEB42539B47F524873158D8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Physician</header><text>The term <term>physician</term> means a physician appointed by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs under section 7401(1) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="id9432C78D01CE4F86B1BB5104B91D10E2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb513c32720d349d8b145d814b601bc5e"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Veteran</header><text>The term <term>veteran</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id23d7ee2e81744b508d0003cd02d22c9b"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall cease to have force or effect on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="id45cf16a8761f4e828193b3c7d72fe4f8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Research on use of medical marijuana by veterans</header><subsection id="idce999c232e464d4a9e1865d1ebd88d9c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research on effects of medical marijuana on veterans</header><paragraph id="id98c6b005662045c0afd7f58575af4b0e"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall support clinical research on the use of medical marijuana—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id00ec25957ba8478bbd73b45862892456"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by veterans to manage pain; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd96c5ae548894e438fbad6d075cf84f0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the treatment of veterans for diseases and disorders such as post-traumatic stress disorder.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4a2f550950d64d04b282e753e9ada423"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate and collaborate with other relevant Federal agencies to support and facilitate clinical research under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd0827133a6d14d7aa57a8408035cbebe"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the ongoing clinical research supported by the Secretary under paragraph (1), which shall include such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Secretary considers appropriate to continue to support the management of pain and the treatment of diseases and disorders of veterans.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="iddf89300497064015878c6e55d9bcb5b3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study on use by veterans of State medical marijuana programs</header><paragraph id="id40c51e7ed3504ab88a3863d00665e0b1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall conduct a study on the relationship between treatment programs involving medical marijuana that are approved by States, the access of veterans to such programs, and a reduction in opioid use and misuse among veterans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5544ea550be54dc89d6f83995f746f5d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the study required under paragraph (1) is completed, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the study, which shall include such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7e7a6a1a00ed4532be2da4ac734dc6ef"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Veteran defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>veteran</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="id35a3a2123bd0448587081fd90a5fab04"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

