<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H00D7AF4568414EE8A647305C9A126C21" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5950 IH: Quantum Instrumentation for Science and Engineering Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5950</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231012">October 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Quantum Initiative Act to upgrade and improve access to quantum research resources, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H68AE741204D249C38D3FE6DF764E2029" style="OLC"><section id="H02EB2F9FAA1F41E18B5DE7972E97F6C0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Quantum Instrumentation for Science and Engineering Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7976382F9022497391B6F85747100DD0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Upgrading and improving access to quantum research resources</header><subsection id="H940164A4431A4714A71DD5FD4AF84733"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the National Quantum Initiative Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8841">15 U.S.C. 8841 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H47058E15A9814BFEB7D953904A65271D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(1) of section 301—</text><subparagraph id="HC0EF24EC6E0C492B806D6431F16FC273"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE73B0053CE344B49A1C86FF1E0E613A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89FB79A8FEC045569FCD2006DD10E549"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC276C26719A44AEBB1A34223A8F4EC93" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H02B95327B142403AA52C78261AF99EBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhance research facilities and access to research resources to accelerate quantum information science, technology, and engineering research.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DC29E13E38744559E1EE7AC1803C8AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE5ED354DF11E4618960CF470D5A51E58" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HACDC8903BC8F418795022FD15D50CA6F"><enum>303.</enum><header>Upgrading and improving access to quantum research resources</header><subsection id="HB283D2B780F443D59D33ED5EEBD83F70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the activities described in sections 301 and 302, the Director of the National Science Foundation, in consultation with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies, as appropriate, shall award grants to institutions of higher education or eligible nonprofit organizations (or consortia thereof) to upgrade research facilities and improve access to research resources, such as equipment and instrumentation, that is needed for research and development in quantum information science, technology, and engineering.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D069A62BAF7472494D1EA5947376308"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>Grants under subsection (a) shall be used to facilitate quantum information science, technology, and engineering research and development, including by carrying out the following:</text><paragraph id="HCA9922FCC6D14E3EABD7CB7B7730BDF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Upgrading or adding research resources to accelerate the development of quantum technologies, including capabilities focused on addressing the roadblocks to implementation, and meeting the materials, advanced materials development, and device needs of the scientific community and the quantum supply chain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0388A490DC5D49B3A019B512ACFC122D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Enhancing access to equipment and instrumentation, including at partnering institutions, by facilitating information sharing, coordination, scheduling, education, and training, including activities that provide meaningful hands-on learning experiences for students, including at community and technical colleges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD33C4CF376564F939D3D6ABCFB472406"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Enabling professional staff to support the operation and improvement of research resources used for quantum information science, technology, and engineering research and training.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE08EE0E513004C058282FEA5DC06A515"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>An institution of higher education or an eligible nonprofit organization (or a consortium thereof) and industry partners seeking funding under this section shall submit an application to the Director of the National Science Foundation at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Director may require.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H667CF60486744F09AB8B2461039E7D01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the National Quantum Initiative Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 302 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H32298750F38A4525BE5125D4A54BDB3D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 303. Upgrading and improving access to quantum research resources.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

