<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Received-in-Senate" dms-id="H1086DF04CF14413E9161A8D8F6A542BF" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1530 : Veterans Benefits Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1530</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received</action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve the requirement to publish disability benefit questionnaire forms of Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="H891FEB95C4D045779CBFBAC7DAED28E9"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="HA963AC1E5A8747C1BC6CDDC12923CC19" section-type="section-one" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title; table of contents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Benefits Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H35735B06ED4F4EC999F9B3D895946512" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improvement of publication of Department of Veterans Affairs disability benefit questionnaire forms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5101 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF9B37A55A534414ABB6848B95FE05324" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="HF4EFAF200A87466D80945324E09E802A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by inserting <quote>, including (except as provided in paragraph (4)(A)) all disability benefit questionnaire forms available to personnel of the Veterans Health Administration and covered non-Department providers for the completion of examinations with respect to medical disability of applicants for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary</quote> before the semicolon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3505193FFB84547AF2AB3761C3C9C2D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CB4139B365A4F958B49136F5BE1E4CE"><paragraph id="H67269BECCAAF497FA5DCFDB9F9190F69" indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5A220B06A0814241A5266F14CC77A93C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may exclude from publication under clauses (i) and (ii) of paragraph (1)(A) any form described in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph that the Secretary determines could not reasonably be completed to a clinically acceptable standard by someone not an employee or a contractor of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H8399F457F0A64A76B57A1F6C1167C092" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A form described in this subparagraph is a form that—</text><clause id="H1F52A61921954CC79795BC22490DF6AC" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was available or in use at any time after the date of the enactment of the Veterans Benefits Act of 2023; and</text></clause><clause id="H9F75D924A2134FF9B3B4C0DF03688C57" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has not been published under paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H01EA1DA9B8F9494CBE955B38919E3646" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include on the same internet website as the website on which forms are published under paragraph (1)(A) a list of forms that have been excluded from publication pursuant to subparagraph (A), and for each such form, a justification for the exclusion of the form from publication. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block display="yes">; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD2B6B293C1E4AF99C084697261CA48C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H6ECB3936C78F4CC0B002E8D627B1A593" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H39D85DB4D9DD425693CBEDAD8808F802"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered non-Department provider</quote> means a medical provider who is not an employee of the Department and who provides examinations with respect to medical disability of applicants for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary pursuant to a contract with the Department.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H7171CE01C21446CCA650B53B1EDC26E2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Improvement of provision of medical disability examinations by contractors</header><subsection id="H86B7D35229C84788980D555180B0E259"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on improving reimbursement for travel relating to medical disability examinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, after consulting with the Secretary of State and the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration, shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on the efforts of the Secretary to reimburse veterans for expenses incurred traveling to a facility of the Department or of a covered non-Department provider incident to an examination with respect to the medical disability of the veteran for purposes of benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary, regardless of whether the facility is located inside or outside the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H672E845940EC45358943A6CC3B27C27E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Communication by non-Department providers providing medical disability examinations with individuals and organizations designated for preparation, presentation, and prosecution of claims</header><text>Any contract entered into by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs after the date of the enactment of this Act under which a covered non-Department provider agrees to provide examinations with respect to medical disability for applicants for benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary, shall include a requirement that every communication from the covered non-Department provider to such an applicant regarding the scheduling of a covered medical disability examination be contemporaneously transmitted to any person or organization—</text><paragraph id="H4615D9ABF3AE4E47A317C6B61237CE16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>designated by the applicant by a power of attorney filed with the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBDAC0C454CA47C8A80CC4767A221F56"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recognized under sections 5902, 5903, and 5904 of title 38, United States Code, for the preparation, presentation, and prosecution of claims.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H434E987747A54586B94D1243015B3803" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Department of Veterans Affairs outreach regarding contact information for contractors providing covered medical disability examinations</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in partnership with veterans service organizations and such other stakeholders as the Secretary considers relevant and appropriate, shall implement an outreach program to provide veterans with the following information:</text><paragraph id="H1B19A239F6D34CEC887D847CB67D9219" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contact information for covered non-Department providers that provide examinations with respect to medical disability of applicants for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary, including the telephone numbers such providers may use to contact veterans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F4B2F619F094F01A4367F77EBF93BC1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notice of the requirement for a veteran to provide personally identifiable information to such a provider when contacted in order to verify the identity of the veteran.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1732822F5F2548BD8EA3EAC942A38C83"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Covered non-Department provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>covered non-Department provider</quote> means a medical provider who is not an employee of the Department of Veterans Affairs and who provides examinations with respect to medical disability of applicants for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs pursuant to a contract with the Department.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE0435095A3484F90BD5F404D4623BFED" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report on supporting governmental veterans service officers who prepare, present, and prosecute benefits claims before Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H2A46E34A97FE43578AF755451FD62CDD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act and after consulting veterans service organizations and such other stakeholders as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs considers relevant and appropriate, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on improving the support by the Department of Veterans Affairs of covered governmental veterans service officers.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD2D1D7A471524F0AAC43EB062E354133" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HB1F4C990051E40528F63A6140B60886D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the feasibility, advisability, and current technical limitations of providing covered governmental veterans service officers enhanced access to certain Department systems to better serve veterans those governmental service officers may not have authorization to represent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5402F631CB9C439E8A530468D592FA7E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment as to whether the Department would benefit from the establishment or designation of an office or working group within the Department to serve as an intergovernmental liaison between the Department and governmental veterans service officers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9C319266ECA4809A1101A3CDCC245E3" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other recommendations to improve how the Department monitors, coordinates with, or provides support to covered governmental veterans service officers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB72C255E1E4F475D8AB27E74E333D800" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H429FF7F3210C4FC9910CEE51E71E3CDE" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered governmental veterans service officer</term> means an employee of a State, county, municipal, or Tribal government—</text><subparagraph id="HD758858A7BD8485988BEB92F0E80D839" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who is recognized by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs as a representative of a veterans service organization to serve as a veterans service officer; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD948D42C3F145338205F51D0526F6AA" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whose primary responsibilities include preparing, presenting, and prosecuting before the Department of Veterans Affairs claims for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE01C435CD2694EBEA22F8EA1795B8395" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>veterans service organization</term> means an organization recognized by the Secretary for the representation of veterans under section 5902 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDC8CEBE2F53449F2B8A67D3DA16EB889" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Board of Veterans' Appeals internship program</header><subsection id="H14CCF1B6D5194D3FAE4AA64B2A005005" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/71">Chapter 71</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section: </text><quoted-block id="H74E3330F7E3647CCB7C67A3DBC751469" style="USC" act-name="" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H8C0965C1732347A4BF2104F5C8063E1D" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>7114.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Internship program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a competitive internship program of the Board for individuals enrolled in the first or second year of law schools accredited by the American Bar Association.</text></section><after-quoted-block display="yes">.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA60ECEBB83D3482990C7604C06F19E78" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 71 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new item: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H705D4439860E4168BBB5A538F481DE6E"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">7114. Internship program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block display="yes">.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7811E5CBFFB04290AA44ED0EDCEDAA12" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish the internship program required by section 7114 of such title, as added by subsection (a), not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="H09DF694072054C918DF521CF3B3118F6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Benefits for participants in certain programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="HD3032F23E66447DFA7FCF189CF320B5D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a program to furnish certain benefits to covered participants.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E9273F984FB4B338F9671FE5EC5863B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Benefits: student loan repayment; reimbursements</header><paragraph id="H1B9DD13C6A4B4F3B9C811D07E6CAC45D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to an agreement under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall provide to each covered attorney—</text><subparagraph id="H48059CFA46DF4958BB51643237DF59B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">student loan repayment benefits under section 5379 of title 5, United States Code, in the case of a covered attorney who is eligible for such benefits; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H977A88DE3EDF4A08B4774EEDE25B7EC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reimbursement for the cost of—</text><clause id="H3184FFBCFC414C53880F791640C0B629"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enrollment in a course designed to prepare an individual for licensure to practice law in a State;</text></clause><clause id="H1714258F5458448DA86F55709E65C169"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sitting for a bar examination in a State; and</text></clause><clause id="H5E46AC6070324EC1840584CC312D188F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>annual dues required to maintain membership in the bar of any State.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7A46286068F4D19AA08498CFCEB15C7" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with a covered attorney who will receive benefits under paragraph (1). Each such agreement shall specify that—</text><subparagraph id="H667AF95C98624D69B82900B4CFC99872"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the covered attorney agrees to remain in the service of the Department for a period of not less than three years, unless involuntarily separated; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H680D6543AD814F4CBAEE862CC12A5332"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if separated involuntarily on account of misconduct, or voluntarily, before the end of the period specified in the agreement, the covered attorney shall repay to the United States the amount of any benefits received by the covered participant under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5FA208326E0046A0AC0CFCDD431357BF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Professional development activities</header><paragraph id="H589BEE3B644A482E9571332022954E56" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Mentorship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date on which an individual becomes a covered participant, the Secretary shall assign the covered participant a mentor who is an employee of the Department who is—</text><subparagraph id="H0E8F0648A5BE4320A2CDED0DEC0BDF4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, a managerial employee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD53BC498CBA5467092DC3888B080C18E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outside the participant's chain of command.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6048797E7BB4CE6AF554B51832352CE" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assignments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the election of a covered participant who has completed at least two years of service to the Department, the Secretary shall assign such covered participant to:</text><subparagraph id="H3F3E0445A04445F6BFDD24A8215705A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Office of General Counsel, in a position—</text><clause id="HCF630CD0E0BD4F0EB4B9042346C36ABD"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that includes full-time legal responsibilities in order to further the professional development of the covered participant; and</text></clause><clause id="H3A33296C95EE4CC8AA49A1ECC1C8C5D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for a period of not less than 120 days and not more than 180 days, or longer at the discretion of the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC52FF70DA51E49AC9086A0FFF9BAE196"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a covered participant who has already held a position described in subparagraph (A), an assignment described in clauses (i) and (ii) of such subparagraph with the Board of Veterans’ Appeals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E0EA9BCBAF442ECBF439179C5BCC708" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other rotational assignments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide a covered participant one or more other short-term rotational assignments. Such an assignment shall be for a period of not less than 30 days and not more than 180 days, at the discretion of the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H105B19D1331845AE862FF660C5C96354" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Periodic reports</header><paragraph id="H80BE99458EB74558B4619250AC7FC051" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reports required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than three years after the date on which the Secretary begins to carry out the program under this section, and not less frequently than once every three years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives regarding such program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF63FE7CB9D1D436B9E71213283926C7F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following elements:</text><subparagraph id="H10F2D5FC4B50427AAE0A380F6152D0DF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Costs to the United States to provide benefits under subsection (b).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CA45F2A333A45EB8B721A56AF35FCD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rates of retention of covered participants compared to other employees of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8CA821CB438457EB1AF49136BA62E76" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations of the Secretary regarding legislative or administrative action to improve such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD639FC32FB9F45B3B06F6BD757E10290"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2ECD403B2A2447378D4A414FD2E28C77" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered attorney</quote> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HB81F721395AB4DFFAE5FD44FE5E7F50F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a covered participant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95CC84D21CEA4BDFB057AC1C77850147"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has graduated from a law school accredited by the American Bar Association; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H062EBFD48640452ABAB1C71D6A835FF2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is a member in good standing of the bar of a State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FDACF97213E443EB99D2B097C3509AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered participant</quote> means an individual who participates in—</text><subparagraph id="HB0C6CDB04261402CB0294D7D655EDEBD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Honors Attorney Program (or successor program) of the Office of General Counsel of the Department of Veterans Affairs; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F57ECA4037940D8851710BFF14788F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Law Clerk Program (or successor program) of the Board of Veterans’ Appeals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE93ABE5E35F43F29677363DAF941C6E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>State</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3BA70AF1D7034BD8974D9345C8699135" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>7.</enum><header>Increase in maximum number of judges appointed to United States Court of Appeals for Veterans Claims</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7253(a) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>seven</quote> and inserting <quote>nine</quote>.</text></section><section id="HAEAA9A2B6CD847D5A56C7EEB0F59E9A9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report on improving access to Board of Veterans' Appeals telehearings</header><subsection id="H965F5E07C2DD4EF7AC6697D5D229CB7F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on improving access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB94342799D774E2CB6DE3F5AE5566FB8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H049AD34A01BE4F20B963F77C36C9A02A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations on the feasibility and advisability of reimbursing veterans for expenses incurred for travel from the home of a veteran to the location at which a hearing before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals is held by picture and voice transmission, if the Secretary determines that travel to such location is reasonably necessary for such a hearing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C38D3BBE0564BA9875AA53FA41E5EEC" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations on establishment of pilot programs to assess the feasibility and advisability of using other methods that could improve veteran access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission from a veteran’s home.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H520867A03F2741109CE6BCA654BD19FF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other recommendations to improve access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission as the Secretary may receive from stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230920" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives September 20, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

