<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H989A883B6FAF4EB49A2B6F0C3D820306" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6317 IH: To require the Administrator of the General Services Administration to submit a report describing a process for seeking public comment about proposed changes to mandatory design standards for public buildings, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6317</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the General Services Administration to submit a report describing a process for seeking public comment about proposed changes to mandatory design standards for public buildings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8EA8323421534D5C9B98AFFEA61D2945" style="OLC"><section id="HADDE919544F34549B0571A7AE58028B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Revision of design standards</header><subsection id="HAC08FB670025491686144FB57AF3FCBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator of the General Services Administration shall revise the process by which the Administrator updates or changes any P100 guidance document or other guidance document establishing mandatory design standards and performance criteria for federally owned buildings under the custody of the Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="H65157924378742BB847AA534F9ECF4CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Process</header><text>The Administrator shall ensure that the process revised under subsection (a) requires—</text><paragraph id="H85E8B4F9988B455F98A6A65470BB9BDB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a public comment period for any updates or changes to the documents described in such subsection;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEA44F6741C74907976C11403B23071D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publication of such updates or changes in the Federal Register and on the website of the General Services Administration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8A2F356E00B4F51A470E3B1E3B9A285"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a summary of any comments received during such public comment period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H437A6A264845457FB0BC3783BAB1A32D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report describing the revisions to the process required under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

