<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA8B974294CDF4BED8F97E22D2D61FBFC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5258 IH: Protection and Advocacy for Criminal Legal Services Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5258</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230822">August 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Attorney General to make grants to protection and advocacy systems to address the needs of individuals with disabilities involved in the local, State, and Federal criminal justice system, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6EB2857ABB144E049A7C62FA92D05183" style="OLC"><section id="HF9169385F1FD4070A1C39ADACAD6951F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protection and Advocacy for Criminal Legal Services Act</short-title></quote> .</text></section><section id="H1D9F360D0FD54453B649B1E6EA860E76"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Criminal Justice Protection and Advocacy Grant Program</header><subsection id="H9C8725E960B54B2E82C2F07D27CA4B9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General, acting through the Assistant Attorney General of the Office of Justice Programs, is authorized to make grants to protection and advocacy systems for the purpose of addressing the needs of individuals with disabilities involved with the local, State, and Federal criminal justice system, including—</text><paragraph id="H360EB5C611B543C2AB5DA644E73F4AB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>making sure individuals with disabilities are not inappropriately placed in the local, State, and Federal criminal justice system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BED794BA7964B88B4B90D079981C3EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">representing and advocating for the rights of individuals with disabilities who are under arrest, incarcerated, or under pre-trial or post-sentencing supervision; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D402D18D05D4C779C6536BD61099BAB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensuring that adequate re-entry planning is available for successful reintegration of individuals with disabilities back into the community after incarceration in order to decrease recidivism rates among individuals with disabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A2D34EDF54C439689CEACB320D92DC6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A protection and advocacy system may use a grant under this section to—</text><paragraph id="HB104883F49C24EE7941B1EEF667DFFC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">monitor whether local, State, and Federal law enforcement officers have violated the constitutional or statutory rights of individuals with disabilities who are under arrest, incarcerated, or under pre-trial or post-sentencing supervision, and identify any conditions of incarceration or practices of any such law enforcement officers that unlawfully discriminate against such individuals with disabilities; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6288D52E52F463FBFDB1443AC816A8A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information and training on the constitutional and statutory rights of individuals with disabilities, including under the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and hate crime statutes, and on services and diversion programs for such individuals made available by applicable criminal justice systems to—</text><subparagraph id="H137099007E854CB3AF6CAD21C92C03AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>incarcerated individuals with disabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H139032A3BA40470F8343552179007CF1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the families of such individuals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC57BB7F175184915875C3AC1932EE7B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>correctional facility staff (including correctional officers, administrators, and medical personnel);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7032A6C3D8C64203AC4BCA96E5B51E12"><enum>(D)</enum><text>individuals with disabilities who are victims of or witnesses to crimes; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41B81D1C9F9944BBACBFF69B4DBD05F4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>judges, court personnel, and lawyers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A37DB957E6B495691375FB702DDCD09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide training to law enforcement personnel and correctional facility staff (including correctional officers, administrators, and medical personnel) regarding the referral of individuals with disabilities for services, the signs and symptoms of mental illness, communicating with individuals with disabilities, and alternatives to secure confinement, solitary confinement, and other forms of restrictive housing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4551E28018664231951C895FF5514FD5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide training to law enforcement personnel and correctional facility staff (including correctional officers, administrators, and medical personnel) regarding evidence-based rehabilitation and diversion strategies and programs to reduce recidivism among individuals with disabilities; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H232FC10780E7469DB406931DB7EDADAC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>advocate for safe and humane conditions of confinement and the elimination of dangerous practices in the incarceration of individuals with disabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE909A755E9D8489A8408B267D841FD54"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to be eligible for a grant under this section, a protection and advocacy system shall meet all of the requirements described in section 143(a)(2) of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15043">42 U.S.C. 15043(a)(2)</external-xref>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H3500BBE7788944E8A60520C1BB8924DA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H7E36E7659CEC4662943B237B3DFD21C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text><subparagraph id="HDDE869A40CA44C3289A5A5DC18ED07FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$7,000,000 for fiscal year 2024; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5895E50698A64739A0744C2A8633BC0A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$9,000,000 for fiscal year 2025; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBED15FE0943A42D2964FF91E90EBEE73"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$11,000,000 for fiscal year 2026; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB36D8549D4194F74B047198683888C51"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$13,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0510F352D2664F7AA7AD683DCB39284B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>$15,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8574E8F8429647F4A0543765CDEB1239"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriations less than $6,200,000</header><subparagraph id="HF55F6277B7A84E598480F84E95EB21C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to any fiscal year in which the amount appropriated to carry out this section is less than $6,200,000, the Attorney General shall make grants from such amount to protection and advocacy systems that apply for a grant under this section. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8BB4BC455604F20ABFBF17D591F224D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the amount of a grant shall not be less than—</text><clause id="H2855226871D34C19AE2F7B504B20638D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$110,000 for a protection and advocacy system located in one of the several States, the District of Columbia, or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; and </text></clause><clause id="HD2256A8BE9F04DB89C5E7C6C6E41ABA4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$55,000 for a protection and advocacy system located in American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, or the American Indian Consortium.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE81206D02DFE4D16AD15877CB6AB617A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriations of $6,200,000 or more</header><subparagraph id="H6C3B4E1E493A4240A07D226D3949F415"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to any fiscal year in which the amount appropriated to carry out this section is not less than $6,200,000, the Administrator shall make grants from such amount not later than October 1 of the fiscal year to protection and advocacy systems. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3436031FF2C34BB4A6EECD416DEE982D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount of grant</header><text>The amount of a grant to a protection and advocacy system shall be equal to an amount bearing the same ratio to the total amount appropriated for the fiscal year involved as the population of the State in which the grantee is located bears to the population of all States. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CDB033AC7FF48C293DAEB4878C4B8EB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Minimums</header><text>The amount of a grant shall not be less than— </text><clause id="HCAB3160DAA864C8581C1DAE669134560"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$110,000 for a protection and advocacy system located in one of the several States, the District of Columbia, or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; and </text></clause><clause id="H4693881245FA456A875C6814BDA2DAF8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$55,000 for a protection and advocacy system located in American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, or the American Indian Consortium. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17CD95E740664F4ABD23A8875B00624B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each fiscal year in which the total amount appropriated to carry out this section is $9,000,000 or more, and such appropriated amount exceeds the total amount appropriated to carry out this section in the preceding fiscal year, the Attorney General shall increase each of the minimum grant amounts described by a percentage equal to the percentage increase in the total amount appropriated under this subsection during the preceding fiscal year and the fiscal year involved. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H014A7AEFEFE3499894F1CB8B50FE442C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Carryover</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amounts made available to a protection and advocacy system for a fiscal year under this section shall remain available for one additional year. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8E0594513DB4426FBBFD0010F83B19EF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Program Income</header><text>Program income generated from the amount paid to an eligible protection and advocacy system for a fiscal year shall remain available to such system until expended and be considered an addition to the grant. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8CE88C78657E47ABAADD8F029FA43B01"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Annual Report</header><text>Each protection and advocacy system that receives a grant under this section shall submit an annual report to the Attorney General concerning the services provided protecting and advocating for the needs of people with disabilities involved with the local, State, and Federal criminal justice system. </text></subsection><subsection id="H826CFEF0483540B184BE5EC1D743161A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Administrative, reporting, and oversight requirements</header><text>To the greatest extent practicable, reporting, monitoring, program financing, and other administrative and oversight requirements established by the Attorney General under this section shall be consistent with the other administrative, reporting, and oversight requirements for a protection and advocacy system.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5FB343FEE2D44CC889762B94757A475D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Annual Cost of Living Adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on October 1, 2024, the amounts specified under subsection (d) shall at least be increased by the amount of increase in the Consumer Price Index for the preceding 12-month period. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6F5924BA22EC4D40B4F509EC86421FC4"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Technical Assistance</header><text>The Administrator shall make an annual grant, in an amount of $50,000 or 4 percent of the total amount appropriated under subsection (d), whichever is greater, to an eligible national association for the provision of training and technical assistance in connection with grants awarded to protection and advocacy systems under this section. </text></subsection><subsection id="H2E29271B98C648F7943CA83A8CE57381"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H620AD815BFA44766AFC679E40F0103EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>protection and advocacy system</term> means a protection and advocacy system established pursuant to section 143 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15043">42 U.S.C. 15043</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11C6C6DA4F7C498DAAEEA64AC559351F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>American Indian consortium</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15002">42 U.S.C. 15002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2FCC63A9FD14CDBB8DEB6F2900118C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>diversion</term> means a process of screening individuals, particularly individuals with disabilities and individuals with substance use disorders, who are arrested or prosecuted for conduct in which the individual engaged as a result of their disabilities or substance use disorder, which may include developing agreements with law enforcement, prosecutors, judges, or other criminal justice system personnel, to support the provision of community-based services in lieu of prosecution, and to prevent inappropriate incarceration of individuals with disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8BC26928CAD4E1795598DE3F79088C9"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible national association</term> means a national disability association with extensive and demonstrated experience providing training and technical assistance to protection and advocacy systems that monitor the rights of people with disabilities. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

