<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H400E2E8EF44248439815FDE3830136FD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5363 IH: Robert Cleckler (Bobby) Bowden Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5363</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award posthumously a Congressional Gold Medal to Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden, in honor of his achievements both on and off the football field.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H400F0DA9486042DCB4F35354A8A8348C" style="OLC"><section id="H147C9260787B49ACBC664A6D4FF3E4B1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE539613D862C4990AC2EB0456256CCD2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HA323C339FB964AF99065C30C1937848B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden was born on November 8, 1929, in Birmingham, Alabama.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA01CC7B2F3574A0C9ED554AC1DB777EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden served as head coach of the Florida State University Seminoles from 1976 to 2009.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0744CF41301A456788A92F6A12369640"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While coaching at the Florida State University, Bobby Bowden’s teams won two national championships (1993 and 1999) and 12 Atlantic Coast Conference titles.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46953FB7E302449FA8487F5CACCE477B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden posted a 316–97–4 record in his 34 years at Florida State University.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80C3BCD666BF4F75BA5BCC2E3DDC7B86"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Throughout his entire 44 years of coaching college football, Bobby Bowden won a total of 377 games, making him one of the winningest coaches in college football history.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9563B19ABC484824A3244F26F5C0AE02"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden and wife, Ann Estock, his childhood sweetheart, have been married for 72 years. The couple has six children, 21 grandchildren and great-grandchildren.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE22336452D2C49B4B23E5C53CBCC8C42"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In 1999, he coached what would be the first of many games against a team coached by his son, <quote>The Bowden Bowl</quote>. This event was the first of its kind in the history of Division I–A football.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB925B55BBCD54F5F890473816D9FF870"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In 2004, the Fellowship of Christian Athletes’ organization began presenting an annual <quote>The National Bobby Bowden Award</quote> to a football player for philanthropic work.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4ACCC9C7517A47F280121C235FC17D6D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In 2011, he was awarded the <quote>Children’s Champion Award for Leadership Development</quote> by the Children’s Hunger Fund, a charitable organization, in recognition of his humanitarian work.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H415988C73A2C4DC7855C4F89F8E31917"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2021, Bobby Bowden received the inaugural Florida Governor’s Medal of Freedom Award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD38D27BFCD4A45EFB3FEB948EA766D0E"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden leaves a legacy of leadership for his contributions on the football field and in his community.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C463A66B921418BBA555F2E5D8D6A46"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While Bobby Bowden is recognized for his many football accomplishments, he will be remembered as a family man who counted all as part of his family and encouraged us all to recognize our own humanity and love our many brothers and sisters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F5612F8C21B48FE9B6C745803BCE744"><enum>(13)</enum><text>We are better for having known him, even if we never met him. He stood for our best, recognized our failings, and believed we all had merit.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H591112F0B2AB4E1EBC60B73B9C992944"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden’s spirit is the American spirit of which we can be proud and seek to emulate in both large and small ways.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AC4C0D7065240339721F37974C1DC66"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bobby Bowden never asked for accolades, and for this, and the totality of his life and his love, we honor him in perpetuity.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H2E52D2C99A704D32A191A0653892449F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="HA7B9646442044E1A82CE5890B8723849"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the posthumous presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design in commemoration to Mr. Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden, in recognition of his achievements both on and off the football field.</text></subsection><subsection id="H63DF024EDAC04BD689321286BC17E309" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><paragraph id="HB8329CED091941979BBCBF1F023417C5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purpose of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H637F03D7D3D542F7B38CD0251D9A31E9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Image</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The emblems, devices, and inscriptions determined by the Secretary shall include an inscription of the name of Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H72F21C3CD1C04DDC939CF863883B9EC2" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disposition Of Medal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to Mr. Robert Cleckler (<quote>Bobby</quote>) Bowden’s next of kin.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD0CEDB296C3A43C9969CC4AF1D9477D0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><subsection id="HB5AF0A9151CD4983ABB2737493ABD2D5" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Striking of duplicates</header><text>The Secretary may strike duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck under section 3.</text></subsection><subsection id="H788644A740834AD4A5E881FA49000ED2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selling of duplicates</header><text>The Secretary may sell such duplicates under subsection (a) at a price sufficient to cover the costs of such duplicates, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5EEEA1D6B52543A09DB83329B5ADFD30"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><subsection id="H4A604F0E3A0E4E8CB520C53A1232E0AD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>Medals struck under this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H355C7B2C4C68473485E577385B81BA5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of section 5134 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA08FD6FD522849F4A01C89FC8DC9107A" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="HD7574DBDCAB748829A7017294ABBC351" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck pursuant to this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF841ABF3FB24B2AA6E79117F0F06045" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

