<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0A4CE0FE5F5E424EAC17C4C5175AA6DF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3946 IH: Advancing FASD Research, Services and Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3946</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize and extend the Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders Prevention and Services program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD9EAD9CF376547FB9675E9F45953AC0E" style="OLC"><section id="H19C22D655BB4425F8AA261E6E62949FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing FASD Research, Services and Prevention Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FASD Respect Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8CFA0855B52049BF8984E4F57F6162D1"><enum>2.</enum><header>HHS program on fetal alcohol spectrum disorders</header><subsection id="H7FE10893E9C74EA08F1308177717B05B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part O of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280f">42 U.S.C. 280f et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF8727C4DB25E4B15955C9F3301B0E793" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending the part heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="part">Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders prevention and services program</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C50D384AEA84646A39CFB7C7CD96F85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 399H (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280f">42 U.S.C. 280f</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H219EDFBC17264DA2971EB01528932E5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">Establishment of fetal alcohol syndrome prevention</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders prevention, intervention,</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D0618D6450C4AFCAD4C93252941945F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Fetal Alcohol Syndrome and Fetal Alcohol Effect</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>FASD</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B8BBE2672AC4571BE19A6B61C8DFFBF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><clause id="H8AF94EB68B1442478858D015F1802985"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by amending the heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">In general</header-in-text></quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HB4F419077AED49EDA573DF8F00C28376"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text><subclause id="H535001289AE8461A9E635CC2ABC1EDC4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or continue activities to support</quote> after <quote>shall establish</quote>; </text></subclause><subclause id="HD2D38D3658B14FB6AE96F00C3A58F0B5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>FASD</quote> (as amended by subparagraph (B)) and inserting <quote>fetal alcohol spectrum disorders (referred to in this section as <quote>FASD</quote>)</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H682F0900E1304BFA98ED5C88AE7DB893"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>prevention, intervention</quote> and inserting <quote>awareness, prevention, identification, intervention,</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8147C609D2144B9AB7AE8F7846A8575B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that shall</quote> and inserting <quote>, which may</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9B6C91F76F884F0E9C2EA7DED4043A46"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subclause id="HFF286F3CD0CA4350896A28952C67D058"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><item id="HAE05C32935C7477FA82952E179D96AF3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>medical schools</quote> and inserting <quote>health professions schools</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H606AFFF5676A40779D78F5AEFC8E3B1E"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>infants,</quote> after <quote>provision of services for</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H6CCCFF59A2134E9E846D2882551C6602"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>medical and mental</quote> and inserting <quote>agencies providing</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H371DF209C0554099830329B6CC38F1C8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subclause id="H4B65509BC2814DB88A5D04200823CAF6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>a prevention and diagnosis program to support clinical studies, demonstrations and other research as appropriate</quote> and inserting <quote>supporting and conducting research on FASD, as appropriate, including</quote>; </text></subclause><subclause id="H2BB79F6ADBF746BA8D73F72A2937DD65"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7860BE2A6DB4C649F83DDB348400400"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>prevention services and interventions for pregnant, alcohol-dependent women</quote> and inserting <quote>culturally and linguistically informed evidence-based or practice-based interventions and appropriate societal supports for preventing prenatal alcohol exposure, which may co-occur with exposure to other substances</quote>; and</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB7500664532343828A9AFDEAE9530070"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H0D728D1054D94E89842EBE642CCFAF57"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE59527C550E445B8B21D89765DED75C5"><paragraph id="HD2FDF56F6CD3422BAECB309A07EB2CAB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>integrating into surveillance practice an evidence-based standard case definition for fetal alcohol syndrome and, in collaboration with other Federal and outside partners, support organizations of appropriate medical and mental health professionals in their development and refinement of evidence-based clinical diagnostic guidelines and criteria for all fetal alcohol spectrum disorders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88D138358C1942EA887A1C63704922DE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>building State and Tribal capacity for the identification, treatment, and support of individuals with FASD and their families, which may include—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCAE018EC2DD43E38E1B4E0B4A0CE4A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilizing and adapting existing Federal, State, or Tribal programs to include FASD identification and FASD-informed support;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDF01D6D4C3AB4084B3B7C9C4CA4CDD4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing and expanding screening and diagnostic capacity for FASD;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H435E462AA80D489CB7DA1C9983A28361"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing, implementing, and evaluating targeted FASD-informed intervention programs for FASD;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6085C322AFC24D28AD303CCF6FB6A07C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing awareness of FASD; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49F02B5BF7C7427BA8A3BCECA7B7903F"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing training with respect to FASD for professionals across relevant sectors; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2292175CE3D24C8DBEE7D787BD03DB81"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disseminating information about FASD and support services to affected individuals and their families.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF97FFD062CC4F62AC9046C3ACEBCE1E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><clause id="HE06EBD68A06D4FB78B91FF06D8847E1C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>described in section 399I</quote>; </text></clause><clause id="H23E1FA0B1E084D3EA7471D5297FFB843"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Secretary</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1F17F305B094CB8926B0DDB6F0D3E73"><paragraph id="H1D66D6FA7E934635B7A659BD767C0E59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H4D6472907E264F9D8D1D1A021D50CEAE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA843554322844B3A14CBD02249BA259"><paragraph id="H90892E6674284021B41983A01131CB18"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant, or enter into a cooperative agreement or contract, under this section, an entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB7A1E0494D8B40789C1C6F1DBEB50672"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be a State, Indian Tribe or Tribal organization, local government, scientific or academic institution, or nonprofit organization; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91B5FD07E8A64F4DAE8273C6B088402C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prepare and submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a description of the activities that the entity intends to carry out using amounts received under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02272C2EE56345D2BABE148050B842DD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by striking subsections (c) and (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9380E7A8B11C43E4A1B764440D547215"><enum>(F)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4137B065B90049BB94F8B71884C0745C"><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF5C15E44C439487A9091008266C5D311"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of FASD-Informed</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>FASD-informed</term>, with respect to support or an intervention program, means that such support or intervention program uses culturally and linguistically informed evidence-based or practice-based interventions and appropriate societal supports to support an improved quality of life for an individual with FASD and the family of such individual. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9F7451DEF574487ADB2F320442BC60B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking sections 399I, 399J, and 399K (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280f-1">42 U.S.C. 280f–1</external-xref>, 280f–2, 280f–3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8EF89D86489469C8CF625382DBED18C"><section id="HFB693540DC8746E8ACD4BCF23A280329"><enum>399I.</enum><header>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders Centers for Excellence</header><subsection id="H22D0F08C45EC4C0E98FE9E90F9EBC5ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, as appropriate, award grants, cooperative agreements, or contracts to public or nonprofit entities with demonstrated expertise in the prevention of, identification of, and intervention services with respect to, fetal alcohol spectrum disorders (referred to in this section as <quote>FASD</quote>) and other related adverse conditions. Such awards shall be for the purposes of establishing Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders Centers for Excellence to build local, Tribal, State, and national capacities to prevent the occurrence of FASD and other related adverse conditions, and to respond to the needs of individuals with FASD and their families by carrying out the programs described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD58E31949F9D4DE4A37B502B78106DB6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity receiving an award under subsection (a) may use such award for the following purposes: </text><paragraph id="H378B70B4F82340DEBB613CEDCBD834C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Initiating or expanding diagnostic capacity for FASD by increasing screening, assessment, identification, and diagnosis. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70E321227854492C92086C997E55B276"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing and supporting public awareness and outreach activities, including the use of a range of media and public outreach, to raise public awareness of the risks associated with alcohol consumption during pregnancy, with the goals of reducing the prevalence of FASD and improving the developmental, health (including mental health), and educational outcomes of individuals with FASD and supporting families caring for individuals with FASD. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H664A21BEF39B4FB5AACC7B914B53E62C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Acting as a clearinghouse for evidence-based resources on FASD prevention, identification, and culturally and linguistically informed best practices, including the maintenance of a national data-based directory on FASD-specific services in States, Indian Tribes, and local communities, and disseminating ongoing research and developing resources on FASD to help inform systems of care for individuals with FASD across their lifespan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60DA0C6F41BB41CDB1AF0E89E65726E3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Increasing awareness and understanding of efficacious, evidence-based FASD screening tools and culturally- and linguistically-appropriate evidence-based intervention services and best practices, which may include by conducting national, regional, State, Tribal, or peer cross-State webinars, workshops, or conferences for training community leaders, medical and mental health and substance use disorder professionals, education and disability professionals, families, law enforcement personnel, judges, individuals working in financial assistance programs, social service personnel, child welfare professionals, and other service providers. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC374AD2A5EE64BF582104F7A135114C9"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improving capacity for State, Tribal, and local affiliates dedicated to FASD awareness, prevention, and identification and family and individual support programs and services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H439C182A04B748FEAB76DACF8A96B1B9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing technical assistance to grantees under section 399H, as appropriate. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FC5682CCF0B491381F64A8C06F7FEFC"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Carrying out other functions, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF6FCC4A3903A476AAE5A9D94056C35A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement under this section, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6E4DAFCF45774581A78F0E480C22B110"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Subcontracting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public or private nonprofit entity may carry out the following activities required under this section through contracts or cooperative agreements with other public and private nonprofit entities with demonstrated expertise in FASD:</text><paragraph id="HB08486AE1A18483D91589E320A69935F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prevention activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2320E905715641FC934D492F18BE0ECF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Screening and identification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF951FDF46074692803080B9C693A4B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Resource development and dissemination, training and technical assistance, administration, and support of FASD partner networks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE8B2AF8C3064F869D0F6B291116FEA6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Intervention services. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF9785BD370094D6DAC521C09617524C1"><enum>399J.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this part such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECCA9410F3B44C4BBCDC8EE56D0E2195"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report on the efforts of the Department of Health and Human Services to advance public awareness on, and facilitate the identification of best practices related to, fetal alcohol spectrum disorders identification, prevention, treatment, and support. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

