<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5197870DE8B94E5095C1E8C2FBD06E04" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 3783 IH: Mink: Vectors for Infection Risk in the United States Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3783</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230601">June 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To protect public health and human safety by prohibiting the farming of mink for their fur, to compensate farmers as they transition out of the industry, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC7B3B403D0844B55AA9BD18520D6235D" style="OLC"><section id="HDAA6D12F86C14AAF9B21974732D8B574" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mink: Vectors for Infection Risk in the United States Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Mink VIRUS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE32BF93D824E43BF8DDCF1E7EE445E40"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H0347F85E264A44A1A2AAE490CED51762"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pandemic of the zoonotic coronavirus disease 2019 (“COVID–19”), caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (“SARS–CoV–2”), is understood to have passed from wild animals to humans and has infected and killed millions of people globally. SARS–CoV–2 continues to pose a severe threat to public health and human safety.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3420D63D07D54D38AF986A2B9094699C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Mink are highly susceptible to SARS–CoV–2, and there is substantial evidence that humans can transmit SARS–CoV–2 to mink farmed for their fur. Outbreaks have been confirmed on at least 18 mink farms in multiple States, with more than 20,000 mink reported dead from the disease in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H399C41BA829F466C95EF5493FE05891C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Mink can transmit a mutated form of SARS–CoV–2 back to humans. Such cases have been confirmed in Denmark, Poland, and the Netherlands, and according to public communications from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, there is also evidence that farmed mink have transmitted the virus to humans and to wild mink in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8218A73E1C4B492181A127717BD716A5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Animal management and slaughter practices on United States mink farms have facilitated the spread of SARS–CoV–2 from humans to mink. These farms confine large numbers of animals in close proximity to each other, which promotes disease transmission. The animals also experience extreme stress, which increases the potential to shed and transmit viruses over extended periods. This risk is further exacerbated by on-site slaughter practices that create additional points of exposure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EE8D62693114CCBBC158628440DBE35"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Farmed mink have become infected with SARS–CoV–2 in at least 12 countries to date, including the United States. Other countries have taken swift and decisive action to close or quarantine mink farms, cull animals, and pass legislation to address this crisis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11F65ED1C67E49AA89F77B3115A64655"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The World Health Organization has acknowledged human cases of COVID–19 associated with farmed mink and transmission of the virus from farmed mink to humans. It has warned that farmed mink can act as a reservoir of SARS–CoV–2 and pose a risk for virus “spill-over” from mink to humans.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD03DA1864BA543528300BE6391510912"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on mink farming and requirements for mink termination</header><subsection id="H43E1BFA52B414635BBEF7BF2CB1E8918"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Cessation of operations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, no fur farm may farm mink.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAE7D7BAC3E5E4BBE8002FC82BAA26AA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Painless mink termination methods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, any termination of farmed mink, whether performed in order to comply with subsection (a) or otherwise, shall be done in a manner that—</text><paragraph id="HE33132DF963449948112F230A0FFFBD8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>meets the definition of <quote>euthanasia</quote> specified in section 1.1 of title 9, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC9DD32D6CC8417294082B304DE9A821"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is classified as <quote>acceptable</quote> by the most recent version of the American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA) Guidelines for the Euthanasia of Animals made publicly available at the time the termination occurred, without regard to whether the termination is in compliance with other guidelines, including the AVMA Guidelines for the Depopulation of Animals.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H194BCB79630E4BC0A8518AAD83FA5EFA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><paragraph id="H3062C65CDE57479B9C3D37C2FA5CFAE9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to cease operations</header><text>Any person who violates subsection (a) may be assessed a civil penalty of up to $10,000 for each day that the fur farm is not in compliance with the requirements of that subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31F6F30206CB4039BC46F0DB7DA8DFFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty for noncompliant termination of mink</header><text>Any person who violates subsection (b) may be assessed a civil penalty of up to $10,000 for each mink terminated in a manner that does not comply with the requirements of that subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H613431393902457B8C38D09A1528E448"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effect on preemption</header><text>This section shall not be construed to preempt or limit any requirement of any law or regulation of a State or political subdivision of a State that is more restrictive than the requirements of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H91419626CB334C10A13A6127097980D1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Payment program</header><subsection id="H48FA7D66EE434CB8869E6C04965A8F76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish and carry out a program (referred to in this section as the <quote>Program</quote>) to provide payments to owners of fur farms whose operations involve the farming of mink.</text></subsection><subsection id="H48793B84972B48199EFB72D96E1E4A9D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payments</header><text>Under the Program, the Secretary shall provide payments to fur farm owners equal to the sum of the Secretary’s determination of—</text><paragraph id="H14B6E85EC0FE47DE95741AE34B929B33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the reasonable cost incurred by the owner in order to comply with sections 3(a) and 3(b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H600B06D14C32491FAF178C3AF1CE3AFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the market value of the portion of the owner’s fur farm, exclusive of the land, involving mink farming.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66B1D6EE9CF345C1A64EAA1B79E2BBB2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Market value determination</header><paragraph id="H095EC4634E9843759CDAD3D81AA142C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Market value</header><text>The market value referred to in subsection (b)(2) shall be calculated as the amount in cash, or on terms reasonably equivalent to cash, for which in all probability the relevant portion of the fur farm would have sold on the effective date of the valuation, after a reasonable exposure time on the competitive market, from a willing and reasonably knowledgeable seller to a willing and reasonably knowledgeable buyer, with neither acting under any compulsion to buy or sell, giving due consideration to all available economic uses of that portion of the fur farm at the time of the valuation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03137819918441A8BFB856A14D9D72A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date of valuation</header><text>In determining the market value referred to in subsection (b)(2), the effective date of the valuation shall be the day before the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F75319C67044C0F8CA60BB067D9C5AB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant condition</header><text>As a condition of receiving a payment under the Program, the recipient shall—</text><paragraph id="HEA00CCCD064D452ABB4DB632625A6018"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not use any payment funds for any materials, supplies, labor costs, or activities associated with operating a fur farm; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CE5804AE8E141678727014A03D0D692"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary a permanent easement on the property on which the fur farm is located that prohibits the operation of any fur farm on the easement area.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C3AC0E2C4BE4098847480C961D99BDC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer to the Secretary of Agriculture $350,000,000 to carry out this section, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE0806E0241D849EE9E3ABB736ED1A479"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H44D3A9C6E51C48D7A7897EB9007F5E3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fur</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fur</term> means any animal skin or part of an animal skin with hair, fleece, or fur fibers attached, either in its raw or processed state. Such term—</text><subparagraph id="HD6F2AC42F0D4495A8CA471BE693DA5AE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not include animal skins that will be converted into leather or which in processing will have their hair, fleece, or fur fiber completely removed; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CE85C7634B74529B19A4D8D08310541"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include cowhide with its hair attached, deerskin with its hair attached, and lambskin and sheepskin with their fleece attached.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C74B3806CE34B34924F10084C9596A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fur-bearing animal</header><text>The term <term>fur-bearing animal</term> means an animal that bears fur of marketable value.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8614C53F837F4A70B8F52BAFE669FA4D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fur farm</header><text>The term <term>fur farm</term> means an operation that farms fur-bearing animals for the value of their fur, including—</text><subparagraph id="H7DAFF3FBBB7C4B678AAEABDAFA4834D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the land, buildings, support facilities, and other equipment of the operation in which fur-bearing animals are, for the value of their fur, bred, slaughtered, skinned, or sold; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBBDAFE037324E758E4799E53B53093A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fur-bearing animals of the operation farmed for the value of their fur and any fur produced by such fur-bearing animals that is owned by the operation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87E849F21ECC4A9F8E1DC462D39A793B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Mink</header><text>The term <term>mink</term> means an American mink (Neovison vison), a European mink (Mustela lutreola), and any mink hybrid, whether alive or dead, and any parts and products from such mink or mink hybrids.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA4183A01B854A50AD3904D95743A20C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5616C3CA87B045C2B77BB8DACF3B2514"><enum>6.</enum><header>Budgetary effects</header><subsection id="HB61E84DA87584CD89CA2694F130812DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statutory PAYGO scorecards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act shall not be entered on either PAYGO scorecard maintained pursuant to section 4(d) of the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/139">Public Law 111–139</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/933">2 U.S.C. 933(d)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCBF72177850C4EB8A8225F25A9EC0926"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Senate PAYGO scorecards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act shall not be entered on any PAYGO scorecard maintained for the purposes of section 4106 of H. Con. Res. 71 (115th Congress).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

