<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H794714FD85FF4A9995C7702BD2D1972D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5542 IH: Accountability in Assignment Restrictions and Reviews Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5542</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230918">September 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the review and appeal of determinations that personnel of the Department of State should be restricted or precluded from serving in certain assignments, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7F6991B02A384AA48887975E1811B8DA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF2300379B2DC4333A66C8BEB50912A2D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accountability in Assignment Restrictions and Reviews Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBFC00937DD0A4D0CB8FCD770F35D6C87" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increased accountability in assignment restrictions and review</header> <subsection id="H2E113FD9146B47538A11993ED8F60822" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H99861F2A17734AEAAA83E91CBE0B49C1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the use of policies to restrict personnel from serving in certain assignments may undermine the ability of the Department of State to deploy relevant cultural and linguistic skills at diplomatic posts abroad if not applied judiciously; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBB43E791A05449282673E7CB466C0B6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Department should continuously evaluate all processes relating to assignment restrictions, assignment reviews, and preclusions at the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H51936737957F46748036C377526D1CD5" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification of status</header><text>Beginning not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H656DE31A57304050AC0865D324FA1E37" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide a status update for all Department personnel who, prior to such date of enactment, were subject to a prior assignment restriction, assignment review, or preclusion for whom a review or decision related to assignment is pending; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H075973668BE6408995C0288271D1C8B1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>on an ongoing basis, provide a status update for any Department personnel who has been the subject of a pending assignment restriction or pending assignment review for more than 30 days.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBC019EBF2F9344E8A4542FACA752C0ED" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notification content</header><text>The notification required under subsection (b) shall inform relevant personnel, as of the date of the notification—</text> 
<paragraph id="H13C169EEF6FD4D47A7DDE05803B4B58C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>whether any prior assignment restriction has been lifted;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6DCA1D2DB1F446B6ABA644D069BEC7B4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if their assignment status is subject to ongoing review, and an estimated date for completion; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB87A9F3D2599460DB4D5F35816C6FE6A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>if they are subject to any other restrictions on their ability to serve at posts abroad.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF38217A42EEB475B8F4BC91AAB6543C5" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Adjudication of ongoing assignment reviews</header> <paragraph id="H1E6FB0D9F261476EAA07AD7DACF3C2C1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Time limit</header><text>The Department shall establish a reasonable time limit for the Department to complete an assignment review and establish a deadline by which it must inform personnel of a decision related to such a review.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EB7A37B8CBE49C3A5F120B0A33F3ED3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appeals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any personnel the Department determines are ineligible to serve in an assignment due to an assignment restriction or assignment review, a Security Appeal Panel shall convene not later than 120 days of an appeal being filed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H86212C0480DB4C4181032F160B8D3368" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Entry-level bidding process</header><text>The Department shall include a description of the assignment review process and critical human intelligence threat posts in a briefing to new officers as part of their entry-level bidding process.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H39AC1478D2194E4A8137BE3BA37CADDA" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Point of contact</header><text>The Department shall designate point of contacts in the Bureau of Diplomatic Security and Bureau of Global Talent Management to answer employee and Career Development Officer questions about assignment restrictions, assignment reviews, and preclusions.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5EEAFAAD451443E899FEDBADEA45D1B6" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Security appeal panel</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Security Appeal Panel shall be comprised of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3924ADBE119F4F7DAB44202D49157989" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the head of an office responsible for human resources or discrimination who reports directly to the Secretary;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C460208C5AD4FA88A1CD307964DD087" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Principal Deputy Assistant Secretary for the Bureau of Global Talent Management;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC3AB0C0609454F8A81E8FFB52CB67CD0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Principal Deputy Assistant Secretary for the Bureau of Intelligence and Research;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49A2F7985C9648539B382E7F2C89995B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary or Deputy, or equivalent, from a third bureau as designated by the Under Secretary for Management;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B4876EDEB024A7EB3055A800B9DDACE" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a representative from the geographic bureau to which the restriction applies; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE2B6991FD2D4BA0A9B387E7A019C466" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a representative from the Office of the Legal Adviser and a representative from the Bureau of Diplomatic Security, who shall serve as non-voting advisors.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H28EB18BFBB5B45E496223A99A59ACD3F" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Appeal rights</header><text>Section 414(a) of the Department of State Authorities Act, Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2734c">22 U.S.C. 2734c(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking the first two sentences and inserting <quote>The Secretary shall establish and maintain a right and process for employees to appeal a decision related to an assignment, based on a restriction, review, or preclusion. Such right and process shall ensure that any such employee shall have the same appeal rights as provided by the Department regarding denial or revocation of a security clearance.</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2D3A087C34DF4D92B8C8703BCF5CB863" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Fam update</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall amend all relevant provisions of the Foreign Service Manual, and any associated or related policies of the Department, to comply with this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE175B112DEA346F49974E4C98666480B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H0FE315A11B2443409BE2B16016FD8039"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of State.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58886007ED2D47E8B0FB91156553DF25"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

