<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC31D1B38477045669C28CA8B8B976F4B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1549 IH: Criminalizing Abused Substance Templates Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1549</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Controlled Substances Act to prohibit the knowing possession of a pill press mold with intent to manufacture in violation of such Act a counterfeit substance in schedule I or II in a capsule, tablet, and other form intended for distribution, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H30AE8E79E83A45A6ADD9FF8889880486" style="OLC"><section id="H95896EB283404542A8C78D0697530D33" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Criminalizing Abused Substance Templates Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8839A4E920A148C590149119AB7A0A4F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unlawful possession of pill press molds</header><subsection id="HB57E7613DE054BC6B2A6258088BAF9D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA23C3D6B8FB74BCEA5719CBD9A824F19" style="OLC"><subsection id="H39AA76325D1E4F1EA44A4C0E060DCDF1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Offense regarding unlawful possession of pill press molds</header><paragraph id="H714CC1FBE7CC40B08FB66678FE1CB6FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever, with intent to manufacture in violation of this title a counterfeit substance in schedule I or II in a capsule, tablet, or other form for distribution, knowingly possesses a pill press mold, shall be imprisoned not more than 20 years and fined in accordance with title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1188DA94DD16499FA2D39FCED54A047F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>pill press mold</term> means any punch, die, plate, stone, or other object designed to print, imprint, or reproduce on a controlled substance (or the container or labeling thereof) the trademark, trade name, or other identifying mark, imprint, number, or device, or any likeness thereof, of a manufacturer, distributor, or dispenser other than the person or persons who in fact manufactured, created, distributed, or dispensed such product, thereby rendering it a counterfeit substance.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAA23CD8015EF47A5BC4AFCC88E641948"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sentencing guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursuant to its authority under section 994 of title 28, United States Code, and in accordance with this section, the United States Sentencing Commission shall review and amend, as appropriate, the Federal sentencing guidelines and policy statements to ensure that the guidelines provide for a penalty enhancement of not less than 2 offense levels above the offense level otherwise applicable for a violation of section 401(a) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841(a)</external-xref>) if the defendant is found, in connection with such violation of section 401(a), to be in violation of section 401(i) of the Controlled Substances Act, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

