<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H97E65DA40B6544978B430EFB35F89572" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5007 IH: Granting Resources for Eliminating Emissions Now in Hospitals Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5007</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for green and resilient health care infrastructure, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC4BC106436C941EF94E55A2AAB88101B" style="OLC"><section id="H9D8560E30E164C54828C6C1D3C71B2F6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Granting Resources for Eliminating Emissions Now in Hospitals Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GREEN Hospitals Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4D0488072AFA4FF3AE378E76CB4AA92C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Green Hill-Burton funds for climate-ready medical facilities</header><subsection id="H100995D60397401295EAF3E9E5BF370A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants for construction or modernization projects</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35F32A3813F045BCA03FFB43DB09E990"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Section 1610(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300r">42 U.S.C. 300r(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H21A5371303444630AA5BD78CC43B76C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A)—</text><clause id="H012D467D73FF476B8E010F97AFDA2E96"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>, or</quote> and inserting a semicolon; </text></clause><clause id="HEFC3762DF7FF4785BECC33516066450F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H2B27193451F04C7A9EF5DF6CBD94327A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H70B88480E69E43FBA72A8A6B9C8899F7"><clause id="H89D4B38FE4E84938A5FBBC169A07C530" indent="up2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>increase capacity to provide essential health care and update medical facilities to become more resilient to climate disasters and public health crises to ensure access and availability of quality health care for communities in need.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE73D2F06F122416F8B2D1A837055B3B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1255EEDB88444B6AADE87DAEFD03E968"><paragraph id="HFDA09DADCD584CBCBDA14D55ED687940" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to applicants whose projects will include, by design, resilience against natural disasters, climate change mitigation, or other necessary predisaster adaptations to ensure continuous health care access and combat health risks due to climate change, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H674FB36263AF45A19536B509653B0E58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>installation of onsite distributed generation that combines energy-efficient devices, energy storage, and renewable energy in accordance with modern electrical safety standards for medical facilities to allow the medical facility to access essential energy during power outages and optimize use of onsite and offsite energy sources for emissions reductions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB15F48ACB5340EFBC8A8FDEB237BEE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving air conditioning, monitoring, and purifying through installation of high-efficiency heat pumps that provide both cooling and heating, air purifiers, air filtration systems, and air quality monitoring systems integrated with energy systems and energy efficiency considerations in preparation for future natural hazards and public health crises, such as wildfire, smog, extreme heat events, and pandemics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30438050388B48BFB9DA62F536E40F41"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">installation and maintenance of wetlands, drainage ponds, stormwater drainage, and any other green infrastructure to protect the medical facility from projected severe effects with respect to extreme weather, natural disasters, or climate change-related events, including sea-level rise, flooding, and increased risk of wildfire;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FCBB6E79155463BB25CC7F7717A2DD4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>green rooftops, walls, and indoor plantings, particularly those that can provide publicly accessible temperature management and air quality improvements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37E0DFCCD38346C0AECFCE809ADFD6CA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>tree planting and other green infrastructure to create publicly accessible cool space to address urban heat islands;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90356CF7E0ED45088A917BD27A6D77CF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>infrastructure upgrades that protect access routes to the medical facility, such as long-term flood, wildfire, and other disaster mitigation for the roads, sidewalks, and public transit infrastructure that service the medical facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9E31F991EF84F8BA6BF2C019C833659"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the long-term maintenance of decarbonization and zero-emissions infrastructure installed using funds made available pursuant to paragraph (4) or other funds; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52768C6233104609AEADF4F9B2AC23A2"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any other type of plan or project the Secretary determines will increase the sustainability and resiliency of a medical facility, protect patient health and community access during extreme weather, and advance environmental justice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H68C0AB145AC84B5BA3EDF9BD72C4A6AC" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $100,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0343DB44B59B4A7DBBF2C276C8133886"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 1610(b) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300r">42 U.S.C. 300r(b)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDACE9F71B4EB47438D43CFE843146623"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medical facility project applications</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8AC9319FDBE45F6B59DC9D4A1BE2BA8"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Section 1621(b)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300s-1">42 U.S.C. 300s–1(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H936A072F057F420F83D6C20107FC5561"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8808B09F8AC2487A9F8D225796D0B80D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (K), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A78661100E14BA6A1CF459A26350324"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7C320BDD5C834D42A279444D9D580BF0"><subparagraph id="H844F28915B6B4CF59F88ACE0F8015293"><enum>(L)</enum><text>reasonable assurance that the facility will have adequate staffing to fulfill the community service obligation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAFF5E862B16490F81D0DE9899D97E4F" commented="no"><enum>(M)</enum><text>reasonable assurance that the facility—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EE56E5B6B1E4995A70440AD4841F799"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a collective bargaining agreement with 1 or more labor organizations representing employees at the facility; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44E6BD4B1ECB4D2592D3BD827FE13E98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has an explicit policy not to interfere with the rights of employees of the facility under section 7 of the National Labor Relations Act.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5F17494710341AFAE91EB5351F1DACA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application for planning grants</header><text>Section 1621 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300s-1">42 U.S.C. 300s–1</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EE2436B5C094B1E9A2527EB7948D3F9"><subsection id="H40113B3157864CB29175220F8CB7550F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application for planning grants</header><text>An application for a project submitted under part A or B shall deemed to be complete for purposes of section 3(d)(2) of the <short-title>Granting Resources for Eliminating Emissions Now in Hospitals Act</short-title>, and the application shall be deemed to have been submitted for purposes of consideration for a planning grant under that section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9FCE343AAC564F15A632A59134387C2A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Planning and Evaluation Grant Program</header><subsection id="H730CC8B9C04A40B1ABC4B5E2DE2F5DE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE558D580D55D45439449A87B422BAECE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medical facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>medical facility</term> means a hospital, public health center, outpatient medical facility, rehabilitation facility, facility for long-term care, or other facility (as may be designated by the Secretary) for the provision of health care to ambulatory patients. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E292982662244768C9BC9D740B92FFE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Proposed project</header><text>The term <term>proposed project</term> means a construction or modernization project proposed by an eligible entity in a sustainability and resiliency plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43D940E877D84366A79FCA8D13060E66"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9245D15862F04AE1BA98941E168F3853"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Sustainability and resiliency plan</header><text>The term <term>sustainability and resiliency plan</term> means a plan, including comprehensive preproject evaluation, for a construction or modernization project that would, in order to protect patient health and community access, enhance—</text><subparagraph id="H80982009C354425AAF87874D4147F425"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the sustainability of a medical facility and infrastructure surrounding the medical facility; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5D47AF217564C87BC3A4B93C4F1D470"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the resiliency of that medical facility and infrastructure surrounding the medical facility to climate change and public health crises.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0DB311DB1194E71829B0CB3B2F8AEA9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a grant program, to be known as the <quote>Planning and Evaluation Grant Program</quote>, under which the Secretary shall make planning grants to eligible entities to develop sustainability and resiliency plans for medical facilities owned or operated by the eligible entity and infrastructure surrounding the medical facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1B06522C7C82455DBEE56A10E0F31498"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a planning grant under subsection (b), an applicant shall be—</text><paragraph id="H54A6BD9A6F0F4012996F954E6452E979"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a State, Tribal government, or political subdivision of a State or Tribal government, including any city, town, county, borough, hospital district authority, or public or quasi-public corporation; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0840F8FA263447DFAE4076ED54BFEC79"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a nonprofit private entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF0B52DE6BBB741DDA9D640E34D515CB4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="H8D85E51DAE444610A138DF8B6D2F38E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), an eligible entity seeking a planning grant under subsection (b) shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may by regulation prescribe, including—</text><subparagraph id="H9021DE04A660433E8A0DE192D96B3629"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the proposed project; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE47C508F569A4ADE9ECCD8D9E72D3CC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a summary and breakdown of the demographics of the patient population served or potentially served by the medical facility under the proposed project, including information on—</text><clause id="H0986F7C0AEB04CA3A21AAE1867E706F6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether the medical facility is a facility for which a majority of the revenue the facility receives for patient care is from reimbursements for medical care furnished to Medicare and Medicaid beneficiaries under titles XVIII and XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref> and 1396 et seq.); and</text></clause><clause id="H66358F79DE2A40399630968697E33C72"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other indications that individuals vulnerable to climate change are served or potentially served by the medical facility;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BFC106A90BD4792B854EDE61BDC1F5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the ways in which the proposed project—</text><clause id="HB51F738B08154F1D977EFB44AEAD98E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will carry out 1 or more activities described in subsection (g);</text></clause><clause id="HAB9FC4702A3740B2A1F83C4532995D65"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>meet the needs of the community the medical facility serves, especially the needs of vulnerable populations; and</text></clause><clause id="H34A79B814C6B43A89016B6D6AD6583B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>meet the sustainability and resiliency needs of the medical facility due to climate risks and hazards;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAE52367FD924E58BC45F4A6C68EE04C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of whether the community served by the medical facility is an environmental justice community; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53A681C304F54FCEB3FD6BDC4C058EDD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a description of the ways in which the planning grant would be used to carry out 1 or more planning and evaluation activities described in subsection (f); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D328054D08D412784F93D7B93AA36D1" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>reasonable assurance that all laborers and mechanics employed by contractors or subcontractors in the performance of work on a project will be paid wages at rates not less than those prevailing on similar work in the locality as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of chapter 31 of part A of subtitle II of title 40, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Davis-Bacon Act</quote>) and the Secretary of Labor shall have with respect to such labor standards the authority and functions set forth in Reorganization Plan Numbered 14 of 1950 (64 Stat. 1267; 5 U.S.C. App.) and section 3145 of title 40, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB94FFEBF4D894173B5616D578B1631C3" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>reasonable assurance that the facility—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H793E5D6F10F844A4A055B11CDEF37ED4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a collective bargaining agreement with 1 or more labor organizations representing employees at the facility; or </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7EF83E8DB6824F59A541BEE684ABD02F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has an explicit policy not to interfere with the rights of employees at the facility under section 7 of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/157">29 U.S.C. 157</external-xref>). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A20BD310FBA4A159C39A0D1D2DA4604"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional applications</header><text>An application submitted under part A or B of title XVI of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300q">42 U.S.C. 300q et seq.</external-xref> and <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300r">42 U.S.C. 300r</external-xref>) shall be deemed to be a complete application submitted for purposes of consideration for a planning grant under subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H93947CDBDF04482AB5B4469A05B2E963"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HCD7DBB4EA40F4123A78435C0EBC63912"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in coordination with the Secretary of Energy and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, if necessary, develop metrics to evaluate applications for planning grants under subsection (b); and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC991A5B4661A4A7182129CC891334E66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>give priority to applications that focus on improving a medical facility—</text><subparagraph id="H013757E3BA094A21A2E63CB4260DBEEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for which—</text><clause id="H86FBBAF49CAE40FE86DE0F6838AB1CC5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a majority of the revenue the facility receives for patient care is from reimbursements for medical care furnished to Medicare and Medicaid beneficiaries under titles XVIII and XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref> and 1396 et seq.); or</text></clause><clause id="H6B0DD9CB8D0F481ABF85B69E0AFD44B5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a high proportion of patients is uninsured, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89020526D379433C8492544FAB5F1096"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is located in a neighborhood or serves a patient population that—</text><clause id="HAC3CC1B0804B4471B47AAE75F64E9478"><enum>(i)</enum><text>experiences low-air quality;</text></clause><clause id="HFDCF069AC8DE4644A4AB81445FB5B30A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lacks green space;</text></clause><clause id="H31B3A930455A4D84BDFF2D8016352524"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>bears higher cumulative pollution burdens; or</text></clause><clause id="H9B6809BE93C84E76B39FF9C08912F0A6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is at disproportionate risk of experiencing the adverse effects of climate change.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2097D3FF0FB428FB970E9CECF0DAC85"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Planning activities</header><text>Planning and evaluation activities carried out by an eligible entity using grant funds received under subsection (b) shall include 1 or more of the following:</text><paragraph id="H6F22C56CAE5947C3BB8923A7295EC80B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Performing project planning, community outreach and engagement, feasibility studies, and needs assessments of the local community and patient populations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8D023F0132B4894BFDB094060743819"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Performing engineering and climate-risk assessments of the medical facility infrastructure and the access routes to the medical facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H767D0DA3485F4B8BB5D3F9783EAC7B2F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providing management and operational assistance for developing and receiving funding for the proposed project.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H262BF9D5B0E94EC38CF5438A750DBD17"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Other planning and evaluation activities and assessments as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H370FF7D3E135447EB5AF49F9C01BA4F5"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Proposed projects</header><text>Construction and modernization activities carried out by a proposed project under a sustainability and resiliency plan developed pursuant to a planning grant received under subsection (b) may include—</text><paragraph id="H1EB5B25F754E48A49934DA55AB6B564C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improvements to the infrastructure, buildings, and grounds of the medical facility, including—</text><subparagraph id="H96074E549E6B42C4BA67D976F8583478"><enum>(A)</enum><text>installation of onsite distributed generation that combines energy-efficient devices, energy storage, and renewable energy in accordance with modern electrical safety standards for medical facilities to allow the medical facility to access essential energy during power outages and optimize use of onsite and offsite energy sources for emissions reductions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDE3F52CA6834B75A528B8E312D5C477"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving air conditioning, monitoring, and purifying through installation of high-efficiency heat pumps that provide both cooling and heating, air purifiers, air filtration systems, and air quality monitoring systems integrated with energy systems and energy efficiency considerations in preparation for future natural hazards and public health crises such as wildfire, smog, extreme heat events, and pandemics;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E20F92F031C415D9FA2A17EC22CE2DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>green infrastructure projects, such as—</text><subparagraph id="HF165060ED4A14A2FB58CE56154886BAF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>installation and maintenance of wetlands, drainage ponds, and any other green infrastructure that would protect the medical facility from projected severe effects with respect to extreme weather, natural disasters, or climate change-related events, including sea-level rise, flooding, and increased risk of wildfire; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF825383B23E142F68B1A2D76FAC41DDB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>green rooftops, walls, and indoor plantings, particularly those that can provide publicly accessible temperature management and air quality improvements;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8B3B09FFF0140E3A2412F04D7D7D5D6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>resiliency projects to secure local accessibility to the medical facility by protecting the access routes to the medical facility, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H1A1A2656BF71447BADEA12ABE77C83CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>infrastructure upgrades that protect access routes to the medical facility, such as long-term flood, wildfire, and other disaster mitigation for the roads, sidewalks, and public transit infrastructure that service the medical facility; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59A3451648FC4672A4EAFB222F37C0EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the long-term maintenance of decarbonization and zero-emissions infrastructure; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CE4F47459348308353D5D543AA7884"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other type of activity the Secretary determines will increase the sustainability and resiliency of a medical facility and protect patient health and community access during extreme weather. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H552C45ED4FB04E23B90416DFE9FFD276"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Amount of grant</header><text>The total amount of a grant under subsection (b) shall not exceed $500,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4CCF62DEC13E4C48B055D09D2AD318B2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Energy, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Secretary of Transportation, if necessary, directly or through partnerships with States, Tribal governments, and nonprofit organizations, shall provide technical assistance to eligible entities interested in carrying out proposed projects that— </text><paragraph id="H7FF148E676604652B426A56A13C1DB90"><enum>(1)</enum><text>serve environmental justice communities or medically underserved communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H555986275290430A8C3017E84DE74FE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demonstrate a commitment to provide job training, apprenticeship programs, and contracting opportunities to residents and small businesses owned by residents of the community that the medical facility serves;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9AE7ED896334D2EACA445A38263AD1C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify and further community priority actions and conduct robust community engagement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C1B14088C8341DFA4159EC8C5CD7EF1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>employ nature-based solutions that focus on protection, restoration, or management of ecological systems to safeguard public health, provide clean air and water, increase natural hazard resilience, and sequester carbon.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD750A498320A4CFBBE18E501EB1EDA86"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Prohibition on training repayment</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant or technical assistance under this section, an eligible entity shall certify that the eligible entity does not use, and if the eligible entity contracts with any staffing agency or training provider, that such agency or provider does not use, any provision in employment agreements, job training agreements, or apprenticeship program agreements that would require an employee or training or apprenticeship program participant to pay a debt if the employee or training or apprenticeship program participant's employment or work relationship or training period with a specified employer or business entity is terminated. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7F2DBB32E15F47A49DE09014F14DC876"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Environmental justice communities</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that not less than 50 percent of grant funds awarded under subsection (b) are used for sustainability and resiliency plans for proposed projects located in environmental justice communities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H30D84E966AED486BAD3639B58DC8B292" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $5,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

