<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8920018D338B4B5C9EE65876A2A9DB08" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3220 IH: Correctional Facilities Occupational Safety and Health Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3220</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance coverage and oversight of occupational safety and health standards in correctional facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE9A70D062D4D4743900CC0E08DB1ADD2" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HBCEC5B3A746B43C8AEAA15A2C6742F5C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Correctional Facilities Occupational Safety and Health Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAC27944A7F9240ABB65AFE0D8924F1A3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Coverage of incarcerated workers under the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970</header> <subsection id="H67B79612A8A64B69BE990972B868F9F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of correctional facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/652">29 U.S.C. 652</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D392BEE11D54754B15CD008878625EE">
<paragraph commented="no" id="H44FA339961D9405AA66B51F3BC2AE6A1"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The term <term>correctional facility</term> has the meaning given the term in section 901(a) Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10251">34 U.S.C. 10251(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HE5AD29EAF19C47D4A21E9E38454C1857"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State plans</header><text>Section 18 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/667">29 U.S.C. 667</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD761F28B65AD4300B573291B23548537"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB7A50559204B4812A3AEA2D768D37625"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>political subdivisions,</quote> and inserting <quote>political subdivisions and to all incarcerated workers,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB451FF5141D74039AF3FFCF35A302AF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (7)—</text> <clause id="HDCBFE1B83B8945058D964FDDE18E7E1D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(7) requires</quote> and inserting <quote>(7)(A) requires</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HC7E1D623559F4F0C947B89877725543D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D181B2062C243FE8CC7921B80932520"> <subparagraph id="HF3235B196AA2455CB976082A47270A66" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>requires the State to ensure that any public agency of the State (or of a political subdivision of the State) operating a correctional facility or contracting with a private entity to operate such a facility, shall, not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Correctional Facilities Occupational Safety and Health Act of 2023</short-title>, and every year thereafter, submit to the Attorney General and Congress a report on—</text>
<clause id="H536F04DBD65A44E8B2F2067E711DDEF4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the workplace safety and health conditions at each such facility, and</text></clause> <clause id="H3B56FF92030242789CBA61DBE0395C7F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any potential noncompliance of each such facility with the safety and health standards under the State plan, and</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HECA41870F4C24EADAFF0B34B07242F6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4FDA2C35E0094F50B35D37719B11CE21"> <subsection id="H2601AFB1FD1842D8A8056F4BA902465B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition of incarcerated worker</header><text>In this section, the term <term>incarcerated worker</term> means an individual, incarcerated or detained in a correctional facility operated by a public agency of a State or political subdivision of a State (or by a private entity through a contract with a State or political subdivision of a State), who performs work offered or required by or through the correctional facility, including work associated with prison work programs, work release programs, State prison industries, public works programs, restitution centers, correctional facility operations and maintenance, and private entities. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H55C485C89A374649ABEB22ABB21D4D59"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal prisons</header><text>Section 19 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/668">29 U.S.C. 668</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C0E09F005EA46A4AC4E16EBE8B8B93E"> <subsection commented="no" id="H5FABCF189EEA4BFCB0FEC4D78F8EDB21"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Bureau of Prisons</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC8A2602084694E9086E891A35EE23A91"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Bureau of Prisons shall—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H8D05C01B201A4169980D7FD4DFF7CE1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that the occupational safety and health program established and maintained by the Director under subsection (a) shall apply with respect to incarcerated workers in the same manner as the program applies to employees of the Bureau of Prisons; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H256E300C792E4D94879DCAB0E9D5B4AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agree to submit, not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Correctional Facilities Occupational Safety and Health Act of 2023</short-title>, and every year thereafter, to the Attorney General and Congress, a report on—</text>
<clause commented="no" id="HA6B084E2D5A34139888ECA5463D7DEA7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the workplace safety and health conditions at any correctional facility operated by the Bureau of Prisons or a private entity contracting with Bureau of Prisons;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H0FDFEB6D6BED49EA8E766E4D8C1C849D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any injury or death of any employee or incarcerated worker while performing labor with respect to such facility; and </text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="HE71F955E282E45BE8236AFF642BC052B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any potential noncompliance of any such facility of such occupational safety and health program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HAD6A3A182E41430DA5DB7AD5CD8F8789"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition of incarcerated worker</header><text>In this section, the term <term>incarcerated worker</term> means an individual, incarcerated or detained in a correctional facility operated by the Bureau of Prisons (or by a private entity through a contract with the Bureau of Prisons), who performs work offered or required by or through the correctional facility, including work associated with prison work programs, work release programs, the UNICOR program, public works programs, restitution centers, correctional facility operations and maintenance, and private entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="H68921CF9F9C14D239D009A39DA041FB7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Incentives for States to enact protections for incarcerated workers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H97817DA084BA477F85961114A964FFDB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 501 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10152">34 U.S.C. 10152</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H425419BD407E4A1DADF4BEA4315FD21D">
<subsection id="H1F3686446D86422287AA0AB366017CD1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Annual report on workplace safety and health conditions</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Correctional Facilities Occupational Safety and Health Act of 2023</short-title> and annually thereafter, any State or unit of local government that receives a grant under this section and operates a correctional facility or contracts with a private entity to operate a correctional facility shall submit to the Attorney General and Congress a report on—</text> <paragraph id="HE6C33D223BA04773B80A05162375458C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the workplace safety and health conditions at each such correctional facility;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HC06D97873AED41CDAE0B2448788B3727"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any injury or death of any employee or incarcerated worker while performing work with respect to any such correctional facility; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D937D0723B74C139B3E9F6F37DBF339"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any potential noncompliance of any such correctional facility with the occupational safety and health standards that apply to the correctional facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H580B264F435C412D9D88640594C299F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 502 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10153">34 U.S.C. 10153</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H9130F0777363496B8094978527C3CC7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(<italic>A</italic>) <header-in-text level="section" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>In general</enum-in-header></header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">(a) In general</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD5BBE0E27A93466B8B577A75C07FE790"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H475B38F23E3A44C8A6D0B4D39A187FE2"> <paragraph id="H3EFCA8A9454F41E095A264F914C59C4D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A certification, to be verified by the Attorney General, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health, that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HAA05916FF99243AD90115400D59A0D91"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State or unit of local government—</text> <clause id="H2F02F50D9EEF4A9B8B7AD78A19023816"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has provided workplace safety and health protections for incarcerated workers in correctional facilities, either by legislative or executive action, that are at least as effective in providing safe and healthful employment and places of employment for incarcerated workers as the comprehensive occupational safety and health programs established by States under section 18 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/667">29 U.S.C. 667</external-xref>); or</text></clause>
<clause id="H6477F93B46EF4A8FABAC52ADBEAF721A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than the last day of the fiscal year following the fiscal year to which the application relates, will have provided the protections described in clause (i), with the limitation that a certification under this clause may only be submitted one time; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6822DF8226054A7FBC42737EE8CF159F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an appropriate State or local agency monitors and enforces or will monitor or enforce, as applicable, the safety and health protections described in subparagraph (A)(i).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD14FBD768A5D4010AF8CDFEE0714D8FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 506 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10157">34 U.S.C. 10157</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0B0E5BABC6943E6953B35F8E65FA04F"> <subsection id="H3C444373488D4793A1C41284BAC6C73F"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Of the total amount made available to carry out this subpart for a fiscal year, the Attorney General, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health, shall reserve not less than $20,000,000 for use by States and units of local government to establish and implement workplace safety and health protections for incarcerated workers in correctional facilities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8FD67384711D46FA99F4CDB391BF3BC2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 901(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10251">34 U.S.C. 10251(a)</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H13F933CB0604458ABD90886A30485F5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (27), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H70A3106AE6C144B4AEDFE8D9EE854976"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (28), by striking the period at the end and adding <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H04901C5884B84FF3AB85221448BE922A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (28) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7AE1BC9FB1F4FD8B8C7E566E34994E3">
<paragraph id="HD3602BAF7ED14DD3AD5D68BFCD76BDED"><enum>(29)</enum><text>the term <term>incarcerated worker</term> means an individual, incarcerated or detained in a correctional facility operated by a State or a political subdivision of a State (or by a private entity through a contract with a State or political subdivision of a State), who performs work offered or required by or through the correctional facility, including work associated with prison work programs, work release programs, State prison industries, public works programs, restitution centers, correctional facility operations and maintenance, and private entities.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HBF55E228582742B981E8C17C092A1EFA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants to assist States in covering incarcerated workers</header> <subsection id="H0CC192972397425D94D9D1EA55EB1B96"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall establish a grant program to award a grant to each State that submits an application satisfying the requirements under subsection (b) to assist the State in amending the occupational safety and health laws of the State to cover incarcerated workers and to enforce those laws as appropriate through inspections, investigations, citations, penalties, and other enforcement mechanisms. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE37EE410A24D4F2BB113C5C2957F71F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A State seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H981EC01E61304190B92DE575ECB42D00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of incarcerated worker</header><text>In this section, the term <term>incarcerated worker</term> has the meaning given such term in section 18(i) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/667">29 U.S.C. 667(i)</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HCEBD834A1EB9459BA9599A3AF8E91DB8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029, to remain available until expended. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

