<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAB6F48DB1A4F45638EAB20499D23A98F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4717 IH: Locally Led Restoration Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4717</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 with respect to third-party contracts for wildfire hazard fuel removal, to amend the National Forest Management Act with respect to the threshold for advertised timber sales, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC546817965934BB7B8550DA5C98110CE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFB9BB219C2D44C5C9A1FFE89AEB41C41" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Locally Led Restoration Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCB4477F0B37D4BEC8B8332AEA2D03396"><enum>2.</enum><header>Third-party contracts for wildfire hazard fuel removal</header> <subsection id="H9DBBD675E25C44528D3C6CECCCCBC81B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 604 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H33E10734AEE14951BD0CE9B7F280516E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by inserting <quote>(including contracts proposed by such entities)</quote> after <quote>private entities</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BEDD26B5320477BAEDE6CD660A419E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5DD3883234FA47B0935F1CDEDA7AC613" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HB34C367A81B640EABC0314A43AD114DF"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Salvage requirements</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD5B5E64894304D6587501322CD6E1B18"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A contract or agreement for a stewardship contracting project proposed by a private person or other public or private entity may only be entered into under subsection (b) if—</text> <clause id="H7C01B0A34CC54E6B8DE62E207F349CFA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the land management goals of the project include the removal of vegetation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H986A74B03F314393978D37475AB17D54"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at least 10 percent of the vegetation proposed to be removed is salvage.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED5A78EC4382476F91590EB040325379" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Salvage defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>salvage</term> includes wildfire kill, beetle kill, and dead or dying organic material.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89406D084BB14BD8BCB4E3337EEF6F27"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Notifications and responses</header> 
<subparagraph id="H662F3C22B9C74A5E90F68EC44FF57446" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notification of opportunity to submit proposals</header><text>Not less than once per year, the Chief and the Director shall publicly notice the opportunity to submit proposals for stewardship contracting projects under subsection (b).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5963BFCD68D34111BB06A0A8E341A0A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Response to proposal</header> <clause id="H306260AD7CFC449C8536F7F2CE53A2D8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a stewardship contracting project proposed by a private person or other public or private entity, the Chief and the Director shall not later than 120 days after receiving such a proposal, provide the person or entity submitting such proposal a response with respect to such proposal.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1E2AE003336E465C81263B619BC0EAB9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notice of denial</header><text>In the case of a response referred to in clause (i) that is a denial, such response may—</text> <subclause id="H02FEB319A0994940AFCFFA83E432C53A" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>identify the specific factors that caused, and explain the reasons that support, the denial; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H71F6D3BED0CA456D9A0CAC01466E2429" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>identify potential courses of action for overcoming specific issues that led to the denial.</text> </subclause> </clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75B9E5E9A95D44B19F7C58503694AA82" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed as requiring the Chief or the Director to enter into a contract or an agreement with respect to a stewardship contracting project proposed by a private person or other public or private entity.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2B54C6D44CD43EC829EC5590528DECA" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Environmental review</header> 
<subparagraph id="H22186C966AC8475F980C2876D491CCCA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date on which a private person or other public or private entity submits to the Chief or the Director a proposal to enter into a stewardship contracting project under subsection (b), the Chief or the Director may issue public notice of initiation of any necessary environmental review.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAA31EC06FA4940FCAA304F0D68D2B4C3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agreements and contracts</header><text>Following completion of any necessary environmental review, the Chief or the Director may enter into an agreement or contract with the private person or other public or private entity under subsection (b).</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA3A2769B758F4B55AB7C361D0471BBDA" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Conflicting proposals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of conflicting proposals for a stewardship contracting project under subsection (b), the Chief and the Director shall have sole discretion in determining which such proposals, if any, are accepted.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11B4030EBDD94F479DC2059BD728788C"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Other requirements</header><text>A contract or agreement entered into under this section—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H759BF879CF8747AA889BB8D12C379CCB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be made on a best value basis, as determined by the Chief and the Director;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3B7FEBEE764944A6AACA89922F67FA8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not be carried out—</text> 
<clause id="H80FCB83683DC4D139D3AF9E2E3B86A4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on acres that are—</text> <subclause id="H98AE8B00402A490FAEFF037CABD564D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>included in the National Wilderness Preservation System; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HDF90ABF98C9E4C9D89332C6E8B1C6CA9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>located within an inventoried roadless area; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H08A92BC309D34751B7C0D2778F922940"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on any area where removal of vegetation is prohibited by Federal statute; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H22167950CB5F424AA940B00C4A4E68FB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may only be carried out if the Chief and the Director determine the stewardship contracting project is in accordance with the forest plan or land and resource management plan applicable to the land on which the project will be carried out.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0EF6B1608F3347EE93A8A7ED58802509"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to Congress that includes, with respect to the preceding 5-year period, information on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6BBBEA83312D488683C7205209C7BE84"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of project proposals under section 604 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c</external-xref>) received by the Chief of the Forest Service and the Director of the Bureau of Land Management;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H78F8A54A42444FDB9E1CE9D6CC39D6F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of contracts and agreements entered into under such section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB22271B929A742EFB6E3342F4FBDDD99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of acres on which forest thinning and hazardous fuels reduction were carried out pursuant to such contracts and agreements. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H64B988DFB4514964BEDCAEBAA061C27A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Threshold for advertised sales</header> <subsection id="HCAB9FD782AF7446C82847B4E8D45B655" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the threshold above which the Secretary of Agriculture shall advertise timber sales, absent extraordinary conditions, established in section 14(d) of the National Forest Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/472a">16 U.S.C. 472a(d)</external-xref>), is adjusted by the amendments made by subsection (b) to reflect the inflation that has occurred since the date of enactment of such section and to address any inflation that may occur after the date of enactment of this section.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H543C95486097402CAF54E07B0B02E0CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Threshold adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 14(d) of the National Forest Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/472a">16 U.S.C. 472a(d)</external-xref>) is amended by—</text> <paragraph id="H6F34AF8CA8FC43FC9E82C0F6705A4958"><enum>(1)</enum><text>striking <quote>$10,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$55,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1A80BD13424E47F09DB0CA25F79E274B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>Beginning the first year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Locally Led Restoration Act of 2023</short-title>, the amount in the first sentence of this subsection shall be adjusted annually by the Secretary for changes in the Consumer Price Index of All Urban Consumers published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor.</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

