<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB429BEF37D2641F9B7236E0FCB9D69D1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4328 IH: National Nursing Shortage Task Force Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4328</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for establishment of the National Task Force on the Nursing Shortage.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1C3B35D0CEF947E4B6EDADDC5E75A77A" style="OLC"><section id="H149F998AD47747C694B0386FB4319AB5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Nursing Shortage Task Force Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5658E4B4D45C4E4984AEB2BA452535AD"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Nursing Shortage Task Force</header><subsection id="H6897876F4F37446DA03CBACB8D52A924"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a task force to be known as the National Nursing Shortage Task Force (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H08E5F58F3EF04955B6722D052AB297F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of the Task Force is to issue policy recommendations to the President and the Congress to address the growing nursing shortage across the United States, with a particular focus on addressing the shortage in health professional shortage areas designated under section 332 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0A0B66111C804C96ADFD28383E73829D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Task Force shall—</text><paragraph id="H62EF4E19C8CB4FFAB5263DE2973EB191"><enum>(1)</enum><text>examine, assess, and report on the United States nursing workforce capacity, including—</text><subparagraph id="HFA6393193AFF40BEB84F03D4FD5F18FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>trends in the overall nursing workforce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD26E0A916CBE41918F99D2112BDB8EE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the capacity to educate future nurses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31AC9CCA9A7D42AA95E3F4202A4C8F18"><enum>(C)</enum><text>causes for the existing nursing shortage; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99E4D3D0B7A64ADE8750DCD1A053C993"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Federal policies to bolster nursing education and the nursing workforce;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67A3313A3361472FB4DCA63120312C0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build upon existing or ongoing evaluations, and avoid unnecessary duplication, by reviewing, as appropriate, the findings, conclusions, and recommendations of other task forces, committees, commissions, and other public and private entities with respect to the national nursing shortage;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA335343CDCCF4FEC83C3288B467F96D6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify areas of Federal policy that have impacted the ability of the United States to respond to the growing nursing shortage, including—</text><subparagraph id="H756A85097EE94E76A81AFABA3251AAD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Federal support of nursing education programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FC34C5685EA43798A099F5798D0F94C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal support of increasing diversity in the nursing workforce; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9BD73D2237142A5BE8240233D76BE32"><enum>(C)</enum><text>incentives for nurses to work in underserved areas and communities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C5F8B6C08B24D9290335CB1B12F0313"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify and recommend a set of possible solutions to the nursing shortage for policymakers, including legislative and regulatory recommendations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE528398B0E5B42209E2ABDFB7D42E36D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>submit to the President and the Congress a report on the Task Force’s findings, conclusions, and recommendations to bolster nursing education and the nursing workforce in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB18C15EB6554D438E9DC2681565E4DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Composition of Task Force</header><paragraph id="HCD6F2180F4CE4CFFBDD69B6B0C498298"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The members of the Task Force shall be appointed by the Secretary and be composed of not fewer than 12 members, of which at least one-third shall be registered nurses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC18FBE6D30D14287B1B52527855570F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expertise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The members of the Task Force shall include individuals with national recognition for their expertise in one or more of the following areas:</text><subparagraph id="H3ED680B4A80E4FB3A067C9322C0EB470" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The demands of practicing nurses, in particular individuals currently working in the profession.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62E9165A037148B9A7D6EF3F1096E0C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Nursing labor market analysis.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA806C5C5C1D7480FBA81F1A484F56181"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Health care finance and economics.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07FCD9DEECE047788C85047426F1153D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Health care facility management.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H480B7967861640B7BD248C3E5F84341B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Nursing education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC568FE1F5D5D4BA58DE1BEA25BCB1A6C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Delivery of health care services, prioritizing individuals with expertise on delivering services in underserved regions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB07CF0E09CD246BF9354A0F8031A03CA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Health care organization culture and its impact on nurses.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88043AEC41DE4C328FC3410B397143FA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Federal, State, local, Tribal, or territorial governmental programs that support the health care workforce and other relevant public administration, such as State nursing licensing agencies. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42E392C6EEC54DE79D25E6221081190E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Nursing labor unions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8B3671A05FD4E098AB6AA5864A4B405"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Any other area of expertise that the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA511B67368634E4A8DFE34CFD0EC8EA3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Geographic representation</header><text>The members of the Task Force shall collectively represent—</text><subparagraph id="H863049EB2CF145BE8BCFCF1A34C8FB7D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>urban, suburban, and rural regions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD53B3FBAA98D41C0930D6050EC606F6A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>regional diversity across the Nation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CA2C3BD58DF4247B7CBDBE6B4485DC0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Co-chairs</header><text>There shall be two co-chairs of the Task Force, both designated by the Secretary at the time of appointment from among the individuals appointed under paragraph (1). One co-chair shall be a registered nurse. The other co-chair shall have a background in nursing education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C94EDBD044844229C38CD04D9A6CB66"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text>The Secretary shall appoint all members of the Task Force not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H959CDE6D230A4EECB1221C81C21B6983"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Task Force shall meet and begin the operations of the Task Force as soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act. After its initial meeting, the Task Force shall meet at the call of the co-chairs acting jointly or at the call of a quorum of its members.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FB33D5566B245A59987F0001E1C973B"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Quorum; vacancies</header><subparagraph id="HE7715D42A76B4DBCB321475BF4CEE3BB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the total number of members of the Task Force shall constitute a quorum.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD748E59E8B9048FF89DB07C2560261AB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the Task Force shall not affect its powers, but shall be filled in the same manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94F4F4D4D8284AE68327CDFAE11CE275"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Final report of Task Force; termination</header><paragraph id="H773B36656A4946A48114E1CD4481AE20"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the last member of the Task Force is appointed, the Task Force shall submit to the President, the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a final report containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations as have been agreed to by not less than a majority of the members of the Task Force. The Task Force shall make such final report available to the public online.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE2B2575A3374EE18C02B9C6806C77CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination</header><subparagraph id="H7AFCCDDCD31248E38EC957ED6DC2B1B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force, and all the authorities of this section, shall terminate 90 days after the date on which the final report is submitted under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BD37B1541C84C3BBE99EC10061DF3E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Administrative activities before termination</header><text>The Task Force may use the 90-day period referred to in subparagraph (A) for the purpose of concluding its activities, including providing testimony to committees of Congress concerning reports of the Task Force and disseminating the final report under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H079DBF01BE3F442EA4418C417429F842"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph id="HC02A44D588F24AA7BC7676C25A3A6DFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duration of availability</header><text>Amounts made available to the Task Force shall remain available until the termination of the Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4221007C19A4417191A9B333082F022A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Gifts and donations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force may accept gifts and donations for the purposes of carrying out this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

