<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD424AF0B8D954A9E9BBDB96B35F814DE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 6881 IH: AI Foundation Model Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6881</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231222">December 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Federal Trade Commission to establish standards for making publicly available information about the training data and algorithms used in artificial intelligence foundation models, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H45D90CAE335141049565C367DABF80EA" style="OLC"><section id="HC74AB93096074801AC299CE27AABA030" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>AI Foundation Model Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBBAAA24B0680414DAB73566D1DB29DA4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H6D3726FDFD894115AA4AE87EE183FDA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With the increase in public access to artificial intelligence, there has been an increase in lawsuits and public concerns about copyright infringement, including in court cases such as the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7712997265FC4CDBB495F340C25A667F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Doe 1 v. GitHub, Inc., No. 22–cv–06823, 2023 WL 3449131, at *1 (N.D. Cal. May 11, 2023).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC210281F16514A05930894D56DD7380E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amended Complaint, Getty Images, Inc. v. Stability AI, Ltd., No. 23–cv–00135 (D. Del. Mar. 29, 2023).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAF3951257E344B6B0CCA777675DDA48" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Andersen v. Stability AI Ltd., No. 23–cv–00201, 2023 WL 7132064, at *1 (N.D. Cal. Oct. 30, 2023).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AD8EEA34ACD45C4B00C797530555B67"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public use of foundation models has led to countless instances of the public being presented with inaccurate, imprecise, or biased information during inference, based on limited training data, limited model training mechanisms, or a lack of disclosures about the training data composition or foundation model training procedures, including in facial recognition technology usage, artificial intelligence inferences relating to health, artificial intelligence inferences relating to loan granting and housing approval, and more.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A2D43C7D54C4D3E8C9D50B6D5374909"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transparency with respect to high-impact foundation models has become increasingly necessary, including to assist copyright owners with enforcing their copyright protections and to promote consumer protection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0734B38A81804A39ACAD50E7B9596F22"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While not compromising the intellectual property rights of those who develop and deploy foundation models, users should be equipped with the information necessary to enforce their copyright protections and to make informed decisions about such foundation models.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0046A401A2D74A4BB23ADE12A770A4FB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Foundation model data source and training transparency</header><subsection id="H4D4B31A0F69542D19C32340BEEC9488E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of standards</header><text>Not later than 9 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall—</text><paragraph id="H40486349734441CCB21D86D197CA08F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, promulgate regulations that establish standards specifying information to improve the transparency of foundation models by covered entities with respect to training data, model documentation, data collection in inference, and operations of foundation models; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A0C2D9F31514FC99930E0AB1E69A5A3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue guidance to assist covered entities in complying with the standards established under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35C06AAD899240F6B5F68927CA4C68FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the standards and issuing the guidance required by subsection (a), the Commission shall consult with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, the Register of Copyrights, and other relevant stakeholders, including standards bodies, covered entities, academia, technology experts, and advocates for civil rights and consumers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3252F281E9DB4315B75921A19EF3D1DA" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Submission to Commission and public availability of information</header><text>The standards established under subsection (a)(1) shall include requirements, with respect to a foundation model, for—</text><paragraph id="H1A0E1B2C0E0E4C5C978FCA2968CD3B6A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>what information specified under such subsection shall be submitted to the Commission by the covered entity that provides such model; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H668BA8E98BAB4DE8BA561303864D104C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>what information specified under such subsection shall be made publicly available by the covered entity that provides such model.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H306D82F36C914C2C8A126774F08A7ACE" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form and manner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards established under subsection (a)(1) shall specify the form and manner in which certain information specified under such subsection, selected at the discretion of the Commission, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the other actors described in subsection (b), shall be made publicly available by covered entities, including—</text><paragraph id="HDABFF4073D434F00A9D48F746E77CF53" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>what information shall be made available on the website of a covered entity that relates to any foundation model provided by such covered entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7130BF020D6946A0ADBB247FB16D7E0C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what information shall be displayed in a central location on a website hosted by the Commission, which shall include, with respect to a foundation model, information that is substantially similar to the information required under paragraph (1) to be made available on the website of the covered entity that provides such model;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B2CCA3C825F4DA4A8C760F93A7F86DF" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that a machine-readable format shall be used with respect to the information specified under paragraphs (1) and (2);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3577EE26BB1646D6BACF780DE6499688" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the URL at which the information specified under paragraph (2) shall be hosted by the Commission; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86D2028D931448669F080B6C63C7400A" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such additional specifications as the Commission considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7C1BB9A95F5941BBB5FD53C8BF07D82D" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards established under subsection (a)(1) shall specify a process by which the information required under subsection (c)(1) shall be submitted to the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="H507FF52C8ABD44809CF3A520E04CA088"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Information To be considered</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall consider specifying in the standards established under subsection (a)(1), with respect to a foundation model, the following information:</text><paragraph id="H5583B010CF23426AA17D1F1C474290CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sources of training data (including, as applicable, personal data collection and information necessary to assist copyright owners or data license holders with enforcing their copyright or data license protections) and whether and how data is collected and retained during inference.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H295BD94C2D96490CA651B77F56153AAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the size and composition of such training data, including broad demographic information, language information, and other attribute information, while accounting for privacy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0ED99CBF65E467CBDB7A6AFD110745D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Information on data governance procedures, including how such training data was edited or filtered.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3CAB7DBFB214CC3A0191D2AAD767F92"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How such training data was labeled, and information regarding how the validity of the labeling process was assessed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H763A2FC9EF924B59858DE590D9F34DC4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of the intended purposes and foreseen limitations or risks of the foundation model, an overview of past edits to such model, the version of such model, and the date of release of such model.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD9D237188334B6A91492B040920AF81" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the efforts of the covered entity to align the foundation model and the transparency of such model with—</text><subparagraph id="HFFAB9E06C8B84A7D8A477A7B4D2E48AA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the AI Risk Management Framework (or any successor framework) of the National Institute of Standards and Technology; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB394D1A872042FEA4D890CFD5F4EC7E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a similar Federal Government-approved consensus technical standard.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DC90BAE69F246769430427020B4452B" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Performance under evaluation, either self-driven or through audit, on public or industry standard benchmarks, including what precautions the foundation model takes to answer or respond to situations with higher levels of risk of providing inaccurate or harmful information, including, if such model responds to such questions, relating to the following:</text><subparagraph id="H6B1510F8DB9C492A9B4BC8EBDF91B0A1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Medical, health, or healthcare questions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A8C1C47BA314F39807E82FAC41E20F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Biological or chemical synthesis.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08576C6138A642F38A3B959DBEE69207"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Cybersecurity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF9244FABCD4405D98973E9B6ABA4B29" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Elections.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CBA973F11AF453CA6B5C2750E61B451" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Policing, including predictive policing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE61E455D1CCF45479601C7A30975B674"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Financial loan decisions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECE0867257994EB98FFA44362E4BAC98"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB89A5F3656C24CEB9B8F0278E664F8D4" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Employment or hiring decisions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A52A880D233403B9B97A44D169528CA" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Public services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4719C14D36F6444D9EAB34156C48D29B"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information relating to vulnerable populations, including children and protected classes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H253D335C527944B4BA9C7A1FF8CC9A01" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Information on the computational power used to train and operate the foundation model.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1164369E45054C82BEF267D8B69A26BA" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other information determined necessary by the Commission, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, to improve transparency of foundation models.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H58136B549D4A4E478D5372A46AF13060"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Consideration of alternative provisions for specific types of foundation models</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the standards and issuing the guidance required by subsection (a), the Commission shall consider whether to include alternative provisions for—</text><paragraph id="H1A089C1F269A42F993279B9BE49E3B0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>open-source foundation models; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD07E76DDF6104D3EB378ED2DF9C09E92"><enum>(2)</enum><text>foundation models that are a derivation of or built upon another foundation model, having been retrained or adapted from such other foundation model to any extent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06AC3430B22547BB80E2B74CE8A7D716"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations required by subsection (a)(1) shall apply beginning on the date that is 90 days after the date on which the Commission promulgates such regulations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD435038A44224A7EBE1AF183C105E778"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Updates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Commission promulgates the regulations required by subsection (a)(1), and not less often than annually thereafter, the Commission, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall assess the standards established by such regulations and update such regulations so as to incorporate appropriate updates (if any) to such standards.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDF248C25E4F14B0EA5AEFF3EC0002597"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="H2ADBDC903AB04683AA36DADA194815A1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of a regulation promulgated under subsection (a)(1) shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FA7947CD2AB443C8CB6023444E2DCD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (m)(3)(C)—</text><subparagraph id="H3D938D3087E94D328057A854584A0D19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Commission shall enforce the regulations promulgated under subsection (a)(1) in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99C68C8CCEE04D12B50AB2E772742BF1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any covered entity that violates a regulation promulgated under subsection (a)(1) shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0653418C4F1343BA998BAE755A60E53B" commented="no"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the establishment, implementation, and enforcement of the standards required by subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H5BE42DD893644731BC18F810EB6F4F93" commented="no"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="H115496E2AEC2408C906DD1220E49427C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$10,000,000 for fiscal year 2025; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB890D75EBFE4D2D94DB1382CC5227E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for each fiscal year thereafter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H46A1C04733A545F1A0953274282347E1"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H136234AE0E0F431093B02176CE3AA7A6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>artificial intelligence</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>; enacted as division E of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82D9B73A815849F085DD8AFEB1218E56"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <quote>Commission</quote> means the Federal Trade Commission. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB82D37E53248494589E7D98BED94A808" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><subparagraph id="H4495A804BB75467CB857C2BD98FE0515"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means any person, partnership, or corporation described in subparagraph (C) that provides—</text><clause id="H05EBB1B813BB4EE99C0FAB1654886545"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use of or services from a foundation model which generates, in aggregate, over 100,000 monthly output instances (whether text, images, video, audio, or other modality), including output instances generated from use by users of second party entities that use such model; or</text></clause><clause id="HD6BF69D2FBE14B62AE84CFE3D52CD686"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use of or services from a foundation model which has, in aggregate, over 30,000 monthly users, including users of second party entities that use such model.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58D57DA9F8B44EA9B9BC50AEF278FE06" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updating of thresholds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission, in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, may, by regulation promulgated in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, update the number of monthly output instances for purposes of subparagraph (A)(i) or the number of monthly users for purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii), as the Commission considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F26A93E5FB940D0B63234C4E3596C33"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Persons, partnerships, and corporations described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The persons, partnerships, and corporations described in this subparagraph are—</text><clause id="H5529A51F04EC499CB47561DC6400F0A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any person, partnership, or corporation over which the Commission has jurisdiction under section 5(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(a)(2)</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="H205208D0D45A430CB8DE98DAED223BEC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notwithstanding section 4, 5(a)(2), or 6 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/44">15 U.S.C. 44</external-xref>; 45(a)(2); 46) or any jurisdictional limitation of the Commission—</text><subclause id="H918EE8CB18BD42D9B78D5CE9757554AA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any common carrier subject to the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) and all Acts amendatory thereof and supplementary thereto; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0A689B2D2FDC43C3AC54FE41AD2BD17E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any organization not organized to carry on business for its own profit or that of its members.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H64AAB979C619420A85CF317109AE09E0" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><subparagraph id="HD018797BE7C64F95B26CE82C7D2602B1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>foundation model</quote> means an artificial intelligence model that—</text><clause id="H055E6F515672436096791E22B32798C7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is trained on broad data;</text></clause><clause id="H12166DCF98F94D66B68A584E7099A715"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>generally uses self-supervision;</text></clause><clause id="HE426738503B849C7A044FFBDB87D6842"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>generally contains at least 1,000,000,000 parameters;</text></clause><clause id="H674A9F40210E499B8EBCC952E40BF73A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is applicable across a wide range of contexts; and</text></clause><clause id="H3792EFB6B1E44B66AE4CFE3AEA49277D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>exhibits, or could be easily modified to exhibit, high levels of performance at tasks that could pose a serious risk to security, national economic security, national public health or safety, or any combination of those matters.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB618FE82D2A74CBE86B33653345EF182" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of technical safeguards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foundation model</quote> includes an artificial intelligence model otherwise described in subparagraph (A) even if such model is provided to users with technical safeguards that attempt to prevent users from taking advantage of any relevant unsafe capabilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H42F19F89E74E462DA55E8FD482BAE393" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Inference</header><text>The term <quote>inference</quote> means, with respect to a foundation model, when such foundation model is operated by a user to produce a result.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FE46F87B12545D3B456E2C4797C8188" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Training data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>training data</quote> means, with respect to a foundation model, the data on which such foundation model was trained.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

