<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H001D95F7E5424773881F7B81D4EC2A38" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1166 IH: Public Health Emergency Medical Supplies Enhancement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1166</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance authorities under the Defense Production Act of 1950 to respond to the public health emergencies, to provide additional oversight of such authorities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H14B2B7983291402E8B44653458F36CB4" style="OLC"><section id="H3A2796E1CD6A4B3B85B839F90C007262" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Public Health Emergency Medical Supplies Enhancement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H8806D2660F9D498C9ACE9220B9247907"><enum>2.</enum><header>Public health emergencies</header><subsection id="H1B832D5188FF443D9AA8258CC5F73811"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Future preparedness for health emergencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 702(14) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 is amended by striking <quote>and critical infrastructure protection and restoration</quote> and inserting <quote>, critical infrastructure protection and restoration, and public health emergency preparedness and response activities</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8CA8E1ABBF5A43EE9059ACA6AE566BE3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public health emergency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4501">50 U.S.C. 4501 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 711 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H36D9C16CE4974A4DB20A0FB19F9DA15C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H39B5BE8B19C94709A6CA989356091215"><enum>712.</enum><header>Public health emergencies</header><subsection id="H793AE00C675942C181E1D66F4CDAF835"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Scarce and critical materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During a public health emergency, any medical equipment or supplies determined by the Secretary of Health and Human Services or the Secretary of Homeland Security to be scarce and critical materials essential to the national defense for purposes of section 101 may be deemed by the President to be a scarce and critical material essential to the national defense for purposes of section 101 and otherwise meet the requirements of section 101(b), and funds available to implement this Act may be used for the purchase, production (including the construction, repair, and retrofitting of government-owned facilities as necessary), or distribution of such medical equipment or supplies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF04B87E93F444156ADFF492779BF3DB4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exercise of title I authorities in relation to contracts by State, local, or Tribal governments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In exercising authorities under title I during a public health emergency, the President (and any officer or employee of the United States to which authorities under such title I have been delegated)—</text><paragraph id="H9682853191E64E74B559C2EA558A8B8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may exercise the prioritization or allocation authority provided in such title I to exclude any materials or supplies described in subsection (a) ordered by a State, local, or Tribal government that are scheduled to be delivered within 15 days of the time at which—</text><subparagraph id="H88572F67CDA040979834ECD13385FD10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the purchase order or contract by the Federal Government for such materials or supplies is made; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H292BAE6E87214F619CC89A644C4C7230"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the materials or supplies are otherwise allocated by the Federal Government under the authorities contained in this Act; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8236B3B2C4D7416DA080AB366BA8E8C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall, within 24 hours of any exercise of the prioritization or allocation authority provided in such title I—</text><subparagraph id="H5A16719D307A4BB6B20E63091C7E408B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the extent practicable notify any State, local, or Tribal government if the President determines that the exercise of such authorities would delay the receipt of such materials or supplies ordered by such government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H922DF88D5C8A41608FD99954F5522B0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>take such steps as may be necessary, and as authorized by law, to ensure that such materials or supplies ordered by such government are delivered in the shortest possible period, consistent with the purposes of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8809F35BD53048C0BE8FC210F687BFDF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Engagement with the private sector</header><paragraph id="HB7A219895D90428890A4D9EF30036BE5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Outreach representative</header><text>Consistent with the authorities in this title VII, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, may designate or appoint, pursuant to section 703, an individual to be known as the <quote>Outreach Representative</quote> for any public health emergency. Such individual shall—</text><subparagraph id="HA2CFBBE052A84B878650095104CB9115"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be appointed from among individuals with substantial experience in the production or distribution of medical supplies or equipment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56B78A32468B4CBBA75F1DED9C89ABF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>act as the governmentwide single point of contact during the public health emergency for outreach to manufacturing companies and their suppliers who may be interested in producing medical supplies or equipment, including the materials described under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H315DA7D8F204481B8EDCAF810089F329"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Encouraging partnerships</header><text>During a public health emergency, the Outreach Representative shall seek to develop partnerships between companies, in coordination with any overall coordinator appointed by the President to oversee the response to the public health emergency, including through the exercise of the authorities delegated by the President under section 708.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15802BD6B8304EC8889636DC7A5620A3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enhancement of supply chain production</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In exercising authority under title III during a public health emergency with respect to materials described in subsection (a), the President shall seek to ensure that support is provided to companies that comprise the supply chains for reagents, components, raw materials, and other materials and items necessary to produce or use the materials described in subsection (a), if applicable, to the extent necessary for the national defense during the public health emergency.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA70BD636DE114FE1B183E383AAB85738"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enhanced reporting during a public health emergency</header><paragraph id="H42FE6A8BE1B24ACF93F0EB94D3ED0024"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the use of authorities under this Act with respect to a public health emergency, and every 120 days thereafter until the termination of such public health emergency, the President, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the exercise of authorities under titles I, III, and VII with respect to the public health emergency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H701BA907229A4A9BA897AC0FA9AFEFE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report required under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H10DF1CAFEF5D4744975C5CC3BC3F5EBB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to each exercise of such authority—</text><clause id="H4D66869415A34F6896E580C42B5A9C2E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an explanation of the purpose of the applicable contract, purchase order, or other exercise of authority (including an allocation of materials, services, and facilities under section 101(a)(2));</text></clause><clause id="HEBD2DEEAB2494535857B1B396DC48AC8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the cost of such exercise of authority; and</text></clause><clause id="H62C82396A41442A287B38CD0C3408918"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if applicable—</text><subclause id="H7CC5B914453C4BCFB14F2CDBCEAE8D2E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount of goods that were purchased or allocated;</text></subclause><subclause id="H798D90177D884D9F9789B27833BB1320"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an identification of the entity awarded a contract or purchase order or that was the subject of the exercise of authority; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB1FF2BC464DD4075A0E89C9DFD873410"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an identification of any entity that had shipments delayed by the exercise of any authority under this Act.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H730C83A711984E71AD3AD991EE9967D7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>A description of any consultations conducted with relevant stakeholders on the needs addressed by the exercise of the authorities described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA83DDC526BB4C9C946DAC948C511394"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Update</header><text>The President shall provide an additional briefing to the appropriate congressional committees on the matters described under paragraph (2) no later than four months after the submission of each report.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0DF7073294B34D40999E73973E38E2C9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA2F64906F3DB4057A7763816F96AF580"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committees on Appropriations, Armed Services, Energy and Commerce, Financial Services, and Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Appropriations, Armed Services, Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H063D577268E3467FB8C846B4B335FFE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relevant stakeholder</header><text>The term <term>relevant stakeholder</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H7D04D44314A34608BCE13B9BDA44731E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>representative private sector entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EE8BA6DD348410185DF7C2BD18B5802"><enum>(B)</enum><text>representatives of the nonprofit sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64E54A34259D4107AEC57E6B797BF12F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>representatives of primary and secondary school systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFB703F942444E54B4BF323B93283590"><enum>(D)</enum><text>representatives of organizations representing workers, including health workers, manufacturers, teachers, other public sector employees, and service sector workers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H17090A955E5541179A61B6DFE13D1484"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6099433A528A4D4E92BA9F97F13D12F4" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Update to Federal regulations</header><paragraph id="H36518B55C18245FC98EC6DEE65269E6B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>DPAS</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Defense Property Accountability System regulations (15 C.F.R. part 700) shall be revised to reflect the requirements of section 712(b) of the Defense Production Act of 1950.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDDB8373587F4E8289589082B8270407" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>FAR</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the revisions required by paragraph (1) are made, the Federal Acquisition Regulation shall be revised to reflect the requirements of section 712(b) of the Defense Production Act of 1950, consistent with the revisions made pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5E3A01F36E0949B2BC3DE47219616B00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on activities involving small business</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The report required by section 304(f)(3) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4534">50 U.S.C. 4534(f)(3)</external-xref>) with respect to fiscal years 2023 and 2024 shall include the percentage of contracts awarded using funds to carry out the Defense Production Act of 1950 for each of the fiscal years 2023 and 2024, respectively, to small business concerns (as defined under section 702 of such Act).</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

