<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H57F5E0F7805045049A3D9E3AF7472ADF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4476 IH: Election Integrity Mail Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4476</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 39, United States Code, to establish standards for the processing and delivery of election mail, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE14F9CF6E45D472BB0B32FA405D601C6" style="OLC"><section id="H9DF02D5853634116839C8236EA98ADF2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Election Integrity Mail Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB100D59169164E2791155C95BFC56C4D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to election mail</header><subsection id="HF91B8B614454401C849C1E9EAFB05ADF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prioritizing election mail</header><text>Title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding after chapter 36 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H8B619D8CB7384F3FB91DF93E963A82A2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><chapter id="HFA88FD758F9649C697B4149E90B05A93"><enum>37</enum><header>Election and Political Mail</header><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. </toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" idref="HE14F9CF6E45D472BB0B32FA405D601C6" level="section">3701. Prioritization of processing and delivery of election mail.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3702. Use of nonprofit permit for cooperative mailings.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3703. Marking or notice on election mail.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3704. Application to Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act.</toc-entry></toc><section id="H96ABD2DCAC814B9BA9A1C13208665F82"><enum>3701.</enum><header>Prioritization of processing and delivery of election mail</header><subsection id="H5ABE80C00E204CEEB768961EE31990E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service shall give priority to the processing and delivery of election mail. In carrying out this subsection, the Postal Service shall at a minimum—</text><paragraph id="H177969BB31C843E997D1FA38F8F07C34"><enum>(1)</enum><text>deliver any election mail regardless of the amount of postage paid;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ED02A232AD44B978BC6DFE3A1471BA2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall, to the greatest extent practicable, process and clear election mail from any postal facility each day; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H295F9375F06C4DA5900BDE1D4EDA1CC1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>carry and deliver election mail expeditiously.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HED71813EC1424555AD59A92BEF9FF1D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Election mail with insufficient postage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a)(1), the Postal Service shall process and deliver election mail with insufficient postage in the same manner as election mail with sufficient postage, but may collect insufficient postage after delivery of any election mail with insufficient postage.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD33630D441C74A0A809A6B15EA84CF0E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Underfunded or overdrawn accounts</header><text>The Postal Service shall process and deliver election mail, under the standards in place under subsection (a), sent from a customer using an account registered with the Postal Service (including a corporate account or an advance deposit account) even if such account is underfunded or overdrawn. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit or otherwise prevent the Postal Service from seeking reimbursement from any person regarding unpaid postage.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE6703630A44F4BB3BD6B6CB065449157"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Election mail defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this chapter, the term <term>election mail</term> means any item mailed to or from an individual for purposes of the individual’s participation in an election for public office, including balloting materials, voter registration cards, absentee ballot applications, polling place notification and photographic voter identification materials.</text></subsection></section><section id="H93174B77DA16430E8F889D5C64361276" commented="no"><enum>3702.</enum><header>Use of nonprofit permit for cooperative mailings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other law, rule, or regulation, a national, State, or local committee of a political party (as defined under the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971) which is eligible to mail at the nonprofit rate may conduct a cooperative mailing at that nonprofit rate with a candidate, a candidate’s committee, or another committee of a political party, and may seek reimbursement from such a candidate, candidate’s committee, or committee of a political party for the costs of such mailing.</text></section><section id="HB06AD599BAA845F198BD345C8EE28BDC"><enum>3703.</enum><header>Marking or notice on election mail</header><subsection id="H21E9662F231B4DBD9AF00EAB3E7AE53C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of assisting election officials in processing election mail, the Postal Service shall place a marking or notice indicating that a piece of mail is election mail. </text></subsection><subsection id="H705BB0E36B294A608F005DD32BC286EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service may determine the appropriate manner in which subsection (a) is carried out, but at a minimum such marking or notice shall—</text><paragraph id="HBB82C9D651C14375A33DB8BEC4A7AAAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be placed, as soon as practicable, at the time the election mail is received by the Postal Service, in a conspicuous and legible type or in a common machine-readable technology on the envelope or other cover in which the election mail is mailed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24D9B101A6224F6D802AEFB10CDCBCA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>clearly demonstrate the date and time that such marking or notice was so placed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1CDE3ABD75D46D1906A15175A05679D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed as requiring any change to the processes and procedures used by the Postal Service with respect to Postal Service barcodes on envelopes carried or delivered by the Postal Service. </text></subsection></section><section id="HFBBD29733DD047079E8868183C8825D0"><enum>3704.</enum><header>Application to Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This chapter shall not apply to balloting materials under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act and nothing in this chapter shall be construed to alter or otherwise affect the operation of such Act or section 3406 of this title.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF289561AA5094DADB846E161A72103ED" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Postmarking stamps</header><text>Section 503 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H89FA00C6530348D2B8DF50A41D45401B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Whoever forges</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC"><enum-in-header>(a)</enum-in-header></header-in-text> Whoever forges</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE798239416D40A794EE4EEC08F2F78C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or such impression thereof,</quote> and all that follows and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H5E3807399ADC46E99C74485E21B1894A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="section">or such impression thereof—</quoted-block-continuation-text><paragraph id="HBE11B2C334314C629BEFF3D465E10A94"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> shall be fined under this title or imprisoned not more than five years, or both; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H935E69906B4A40A7AD94413C5AA31C31"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the impression from a postmarking stamp or impression thereof forged, counterfeited, used, sold, or possessed in violation of this section is applied to a mailed ballot for an election for Federal, State, or local office, shall be fined under this title or imprisoned not more than 10 years, or both.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HA54BA11CE2984C038171F94D44E4EF19"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H6994EF319F1942AEA3C1B5DE7027F69D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H814E0AE3189B4E879776AC3F56491E52"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Whoever, with the intent to falsify the date on which a postmark was applied, applies to a mailed ballot described in subsection (a)(2) a genuine postmark that bears a date other than the date on which such postmark was applied, shall be subject to the penalties set forth in such subsection.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

