<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H593D6C8CAACA4557A7D924D36C13223E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 859 IH: National Cold War Center Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 859</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230207">February 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize references to the museum located at Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base in Blytheville, Arkansas, as the <quote>National Cold War Center</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9FF40099CE864F1A9DF433A284BAD036" style="OLC"><section id="HE7B767489E484301B26C2C8790D02D78" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Cold War Center Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H436FB03CB42041598CBCB1C738728C9A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HEB39887DD3D74A1FA529EDB6476AAA6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The BAFB Cold War Museum, Inc., a nonprofit corporation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, is responsible for the finances and management of the National Cold War Museum at Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base in Blytheville, Arkansas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BFC0FC1D458465EA705548612EE93FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The National Cold War Center, located on the Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base, will be recognized as a major tourist attraction in Arkansas that will provide an immersive and authoritative experience in informing, interpreting, and honoring the legacy of the Cold War.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BDEFDD2547B48CD9E7362AE4686DAB6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base has the only intact, publicly accessible Alert Facility and Weapons Storage Facility in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E2DFFD0FA704086A87C5368C524F972"><enum>(4)</enum><text>There is an urgent need to preserve the stories, artifacts, and heroic achievements of the Cold War.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48EB5AEB01504C30BECFA164E5579947"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The United States has a need to preserve forever the knowledge and history of the United States’ achievements in the Cold War century and to portray that history to citizens, visitors, and school children for centuries to come.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D209503711D4D92B0598B5BD31ACA47"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Cold War Center seeks to educate a diverse group of audiences through its collection of artifacts, photographs, and firsthand personal accounts of the participants in the war on the home front.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD2439C4B38EC442487F422ACAC59B0B8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="H1A6F660645504058BEE79999FF66BA61"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to authorize references to the museum located at Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base in Blytheville, Arkansas, including its future and expanded exhibits, collections, and educational programs, as the <quote>National Cold War Center</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D0622FE77364367ADBC2980BD643DAB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to ensure the continuing preservation, maintenance, and interpretation of the artifacts, documents, images, and history collected by the Center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE92B3F2EA0644DFEB042AD6CDB2BE213"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to enhance the knowledge of the American people of the experience of the United States during the Cold War years;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C715F52CBCD45D386CA8A55A888B24C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to provide and support a facility for the public display of the artifacts, photographs, and personal histories of the Cold War years; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1D3120C3EFA48DEB7437417B12AE73C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to ensure that all future generations understand the sacrifices made to preserve freedom and democracy, and the benefits of peace for all future generations in the 21st century and beyond.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H61DD2FEF5C4F45538677921D20662199"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reference to America’s Cold War Center</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The museum located at Blytheville/Eaker Air Force Base in Blytheville, Arkansas, is hereby authorized to be referred to as the <quote>National Cold War Center</quote>.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

