<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC3B08D9BD76046F886C4699795A71097" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" star-print="first-star-print"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>101 HR 2746 IH: Pueblo Jobs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2746</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the closure and disposal of the Pueblo Chemical Depot, Pueblo County, Colorado.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7DFBB4B24FDB413DAB66980D7480836F" style="OLC"><section id="HD165D64656A64E45B581BCA212740063" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pueblo Jobs Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HD82A57C2DCD1440F896B5B13286958E1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Closure and disposal of the Pueblo Chemical Depot, Pueblo County, Colorado</header><subsection id="HB7D7835D4B8449C3A7A8C6947A6B984F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Army shall close Pueblo Chemical Depot in Pueblo County, Colorado (in this section referred to as the <quote>Depot</quote>), not later than one year after the completion of the chemical demilitarization mission in such location in accordance with the Chemical Weapons Convention Treaty.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDFAA9F67B94B4BF48A227C020C09BBA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>The Secretary of the Army shall carry out the closure and subsequent related property management and disposal of the Depot, including the land, buildings, structures, infrastructure, and associated equipment, installed equipment, material, and personal property that comprise the Chemical Agent-Destruction Pilot Plant, in accordance with the procedures and authorities for the closure, management, and disposal of property under the Defense Base Closure and Realignment Act of 1990, as amended (part A of title XXIX of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/101/510">Public Law 101–510</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2687">10 U.S.C. 2687</external-xref> note).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD200851DBB314B3E88DCD6F18045014A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Office of local defense community cooperation activities</header><text>The Office of Local Defense Community Cooperation of the Department of Defense may make grants and supplement other Federal funds pursuant to section 2391 of title 10, United States Code, to support closure and reuse activities of the Depot.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E2A124F72F04BD9A9407364BB04FED9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Treatment of existing permits</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent the removal or demolition by the Program Executive Office, Assembled Chemical Weapons Alternatives of the Department of the Army of existing buildings, structures, infrastructure, and associated equipment, installed equipment, material, and personal property of the Chemical Agent-Destruction Pilot Plant at the Depot in accordance with the existing Hazardous Waste Permit Number CO–20–09–02–01 under the Solid Waste Disposal Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6901">42 U.S.C. 6901 et seq.</external-xref>) (commonly known as the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act of 1976) issued by the State of Colorado, or any associated or follow-on permits under such Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF69A992B591C41EDB6176B40DFC77729"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Homeless use</header><text>Given the nature of activities undertaken at the Chemical Agent-Destruction Pilot Plant at the Depot, such land, buildings, structures, infrastructure, and associated equipment, installed equipment, material, and personal property comprising the Chemical Agent-Destruction Pilot Plant is deemed unsuitable for homeless use, and in carrying out any closure, management, or disposal of property under this section, need not be screened for homeless use purposes pursuant to Section 2905(b)(7) of the Defense Base Closure and Realignment Act of 1990, as amended (part A of title XXIX of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/101/510">Public Law 101–510</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2687">10 U.S.C. 2687</external-xref> note).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

