<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC2DF3B01F6B44D9AB815B486DCE5F6DB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1295 IH: Early Voting Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1295</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to allow individuals to vote in an election for Federal office during an early voting period which occurs prior to the date of the election, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE680E955C0554B33BC3FDB901A1AB79D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0C8223AC3FF64160A2701000F3B69F72" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Early Voting Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H02C82D78CF67477C990A6FAC7E158A81"><enum>2.</enum><header>Early voting</header> <subsection id="H1B063243F24945E7AAE1EA4DDC91C7F0" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Subtitle A of title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0D9B5699E13A464F861BC9B0C5A24453" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4052C284DFBD4EFABEBB4BBB1A340453" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HD09FF071DCDE43ACA99B64D5AA6FAED9"> 
<section commented="no" id="HE0601C08F79643669289E7FCBE0789AC"><enum>304.</enum><header>Early voting</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HFBEB22032626478682FBF77DCC690C34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requiring Voting Prior to Date of Election</header><text>Each State shall allow individuals to vote in an election for Federal office during an early voting period which occurs prior to the date of the election, in a manner that allows the individual to receive, complete, and cast their ballot in-person. </text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H7B3AA6443FAE4B01BDAB7B929D44042D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Minimum early voting requirements</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7EE4CB4FB9374455A2DD59E783A9BE8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H99F2B39C14374E94A4274454F5168CD4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Length of period</header><text>The early voting period required under this subsection with respect to an election shall consist of a period of consecutive days (including weekends) which begins on the 15th day before the date of the election (or, at the option of the State, on a day prior to the 15th day before the date of the election) and ends no earlier than the second day before the date of the election.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H6EBFF9FB0E97493AB60A7D85C8724DF8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Hours for early voting</header><text>Each polling place which allows voting during an early voting period under subparagraph (A) shall—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H67782B78923940AFBA11628366AC48FC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>allow such voting for no less than 10 hours on each day during the period; </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HD53CDF939B6B4F049CFE49E4CA050100"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have uniform hours each day for which such voting occurs; and</text></clause> <clause id="H42182B0637DE4A8384096364DA4E350B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allow such voting to be held for some period of time prior to 9:00 a.m (local time) and some period of time after 5:00 p.m. (local time).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF82F0564565B4AD4803096C805380D4F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for vote-by-mail jurisdictions</header><text>In the case of a jurisdiction that sends every registered voter a ballot by mail—</text> <subparagraph id="H91D845460AAC45C2A17C0626F6EB08F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paragraph (1) shall not apply; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H25B6B44A9B5D411BBB123A808FFA11A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such jurisdiction shall allow eligible individuals to vote during an early voting period that ensures voters are provided the greatest opportunity to cast ballots ahead of election day and which includes at least one consecutive Saturday and Sunday; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9C44EC7F506740D28DE99A80FF127BC6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>each polling place which allows voting during an early voting period under subparagraph (B) shall allow such voting—</text> 
<clause id="H0EF3DD7BF6FC44D89A9EDA257BA4A5CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>during the election office’s regular business hours; and </text></clause> <clause id="HB66A127C4886419D96395CF4449174A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for a period of not less than 8 hours on Saturdays and Sundays included in the early voting period.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC97681BA2584C5BAB2BD9000B2F6BED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements for small jurisdictions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3C5081A571AA4082885A626212C23AC4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a jurisdiction described in subparagraph (B), paragraph (1)(B) shall not apply so long as all eligible individuals in the jurisdiction have the opportunity to vote—</text> <clause id="HBD42C93530994C8990AE152649FAF0B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>at each polling place which allows voting during the early voting period described in paragraph (1)(A)—</text> 
<subclause id="H06FFFE5CC5CF48DFB81864F1AF8CA17B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>during the election office’s regular business hours; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="H869AD08A712B4D34B21423B755FE1E79"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for a period of not less than 8 hours on at least one Saturday and at least one Sunday included in the early voting period; or</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE8072D2982F24A0993172077B53CEB0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at one or more polling places in the county in which such jurisdiction is located that allows voting during the early voting period described in paragraph (1)(A) in accordance with the requirements under paragraph (1)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE9E272C971C748DEB36B58BF791691F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Jurisdiction described</header><text>A jurisdiction is described in this subparagraph if such jurisdiction—</text> 
<clause id="HCC672000598B46D6B5470688FAE376A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>had less than 3,000 registered voters at the time of the most recent prior election for Federal office; and</text></clause> <clause id="H9B106949C29548B99BA30A8BDC7DFD98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>consists of a geographic area that is smaller than the jurisdiction of the county in which such jurisdiction is located. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3339C876504044FD983F2CE947E95260"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed—</text> <subparagraph id="H0C3005071C874BE6BEDD240FEC2A3FB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to limit the availability of additional temporary voting sites which provide voters more opportunities to cast their ballots but which do not meet the requirements of this subsection; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDCF8EE04E1D74D6C9D8D38934B029C9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to limit a polling place from being open for additional hours outside of the uniform hours set for the polling location on any day of the early voting period; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB87EA3B40F72494780438FF65AF9EBFE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to limit a State or jurisdiction from offering early voting on the Monday before election day. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7C4FF328EA0A4EF2A58A3CAA641F978E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Location of polling places</header> 
<paragraph id="HC1A8A9FB1F684AA2A8F462551144D2B0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Proximity to public transportation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the greatest extent practicable, each State and jurisdiction shall ensure that each polling place which allows voting during an early voting period under subsection (b) is located within walking distance of a stop on a public transportation route.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5286633A0CE34765B9569C25D70308C2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability in rural areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a jurisdiction that includes a rural area, the State or jurisdiction shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H281A87B25D164060AA659CE080C507FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that polling places which allow voting during an early voting period under subsection (b) will be located in such rural areas; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAFB90D7EF2C6482D876FE1FC8789065F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that such polling places are located in communities which will provide the greatest opportunity for residents of rural areas to vote during the early voting period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE5475F6199E4C458F55084FA9356A17"><enum>(3)</enum><header>College campuses</header><text>In the case of a jurisdiction that includes an institution of higher education, the State or jurisdiction shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H6F40EE18844F4A4192B510C1469DA23A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that an appropriate number (not less than one) of polling places which allow voting during the early voting period under subsection (b) will be located on each branch campus of the institution of higher education; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0D3FD1A350CD4CA191254519A32A41B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that such polling places provide the greatest opportunity for residents of the jurisdiction to vote.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H10BF73CC8B5744E6BA96771D0D3A55DA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 30, 2024, the Commission shall issue voluntary standards for the administration of voting during voting periods which occur prior to the date of a Federal election. Subject to subsection (c), such voluntary standards shall include the nondiscriminatory geographic placement of polling places at which such voting occurs.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCC65FF4E7BF04EAF9C2ABADEC14DE897"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Ballot processing and scanning requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H07470316C42E4D3C8082CDE49AB1FD8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State or jurisdiction shall begin processing and scanning ballots cast during in-person early voting for tabulation not later than the date that is 14 days prior to the date of the election involved, except that a State or jurisdiction may begin processing and scanning ballots cast during in-person early voting for tabulation after such date if the date on which the State or jurisdiction begins such processing and scanning ensures, to the greatest extent practical, that ballots cast before the date of the election are processed and scanned before the date of the election. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01AA156C13F343738C7959529293D594"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5FB7178AEFEF4652AF52C35841156701"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to permit a State or jurisdiction to tabulate ballots in an election before the closing of the polls on the date of the election unless such tabulation is a necessary component of preprocessing in the State or jurisdiction and is performed in accordance with existing State law; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC7212DBE6C14E4786629E6C55A457AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to permit an official to make public any results of tabulation and processing before the closing of the polls on the date of the election. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H0F80AB63A8AE4EB083A8C86113D3B0B9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall apply with respect to the regularly scheduled general election for Federal office held in November 2024 and each succeeding election for Federal office.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H408BC522A96E43E5989762D2A869B87A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to issuance of voluntary guidance by Election Assistance Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 311(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21101">52 U.S.C. 21101(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA5DD80229C944EDB9C341B47001B2AB9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (2);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5359C070B21249BB816FFA8DD1912BD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (3) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H475DDE28448F466B88411A69971FD244"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H477DD17253AB4158B5C0AB510B58E75B" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H0C74C6C0EC5B4FE8B8C5C3741238499D" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of the recommendations with respect to section 304, June 30, 2024.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7FF32AD41F11433A88ADF8B84A4EA6B7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text>Section 401 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>. </text></subsection> <subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE0B5F245E03446D4A976011F5405862D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2055D5A0879849C68D0A3B4B067FBDB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDCC8F32FCFDC495681A9BA3A21F81EBE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC208537BD794C63A572B556EDB8A1F4" style="OLC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Early voting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

