<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H40C91CD5300F44C18BDC11398CE505E1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 591 IH: Strategic Production Response and Implementation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 591</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the development of a plan to increase oil and gas production under oil and gas leases of Federal lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of the Interior, and the Secretary of Defense in conjunction with a drawdown of petroleum reserves from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3225B294C4DB409398E79F4A5C3A16D3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0C6DC202E97D452C938E454AEA3265E2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strategic Production Response and Implementation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4B1D0D8754AE4316A58862F1CC568AC7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Compensatory production increase plan</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 161 of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6241">42 U.S.C. 6241</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA710090CA685467D9B07C98409184955" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H1E9263FEB4D44D21AA76FE86FA3CF51B"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Plan</header> 
<paragraph id="H4199905BC73F4123B58EF5B35B2BD6BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in the case of a severe energy supply interruption described in subsection (d), the Secretary may not execute the first drawdown of petroleum products in the Reserve after the date of enactment of this subsection, whether through sale, exchange, or loan, until the Secretary has developed and implemented a plan to increase the percentage of Federal lands (including submerged lands of the Outer Continental Shelf) under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of the Interior, and the Secretary of Defense leased for oil and gas production by the same percentage as the percentage of petroleum in the Strategic Petroleum Reserve that is to be drawn down in that first and subsequent drawdowns, subject to the limitation under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7058CBA1CBAF4594B7D7CD063764DC13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan required by paragraph (1) shall not provide for a total increase in the percentage of Federal lands described in paragraph (1) leased for oil and gas production in excess of 10 percent.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8A23F715A2A49E39551AFAEB4CB7C74"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prepare the plan required by paragraph (1) in consultation with the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of the Interior, and the Secretary of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

