<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H90A54D5813444770911EF639789044EE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1140 RH: To authorize the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to waive application of certain requirements with respect to processing and refining a critical energy resource at a critical energy resource facility, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 9</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1140</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–16]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000615">Mr. Pence</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed<pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to waive application of certain requirements with respect to processing and refining a critical energy resource at a critical energy resource facility, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="H8FB1B20808D64CD59BE2144465A9C8AE" style="OLC"><section id="H1D7B864117C54861AB8BA9AEF3971E43" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Waiver for national security or energy security</header><subsection id="H078ACB35C9854EA0AE89CDD079F1DFA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Clean Air Act requirements</header><paragraph id="H789CBA5E1904489195C1F7F480273950"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, determines that, by reason of a sudden increase in demand for, or a shortage of, a critical energy resource, or another cause, the processing or refining of a critical energy resource at a critical energy resource facility is necessary to meet the national security or energy security needs of the United States, then the Administrator may, with or without notice, hearing, or other report, issue a temporary waiver of any requirement under the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7401">42 U.S.C. 7401 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to such critical energy resource facility that, in the judgment of the Administrator, will allow for such processing or refining at such critical energy resource facility as necessary to best meet such needs and serve the public interest. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F1D5DD733D4484BB3D38D2F2E6C7B7B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conflict with other environmental laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall ensure that any waiver of a requirement under the Clean Air Act under this subsection, to the maximum extent practicable, does not result in a conflict with a requirement of any other applicable Federal, State, or local environmental law or regulation and minimizes any adverse environmental impacts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1C98E16BC8F45E0BB1C951C57041B7F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Violations of other environmental laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent any omission or action taken by a party under a waiver issued under this subsection is in conflict with any requirement of a Federal, State, or local environmental law or regulation, such omission or action shall not be considered a violation of such environmental law or regulation, or subject such party to any requirement, civil or criminal liability, or a citizen suit under such environmental law or regulation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA6BAC706A6A4E4C85206E2372185F3C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Expiration and renewal of waivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A waiver issued under this subsection shall expire not later than 90 days after it is issued. The Administrator may renew or reissue such waiver pursuant to paragraphs (1) and (2) for subsequent periods, not to exceed 90 days for each period, as the Administrator determines necessary to meet the national security or energy security needs described in paragraph (1) and serve the public interest. In renewing or reissuing a waiver under this paragraph, the Administrator shall include in any such renewed or reissued waiver such conditions as are necessary to minimize any adverse environmental impacts to the extent practicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AE1B540BE9A4250B2489FE732528ED7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Subsequent action by court</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a waiver issued under this subsection is subsequently stayed, modified, or set aside by a court pursuant a provision of law, any omission or action previously taken by a party under the waiver while the waiver was in effect shall remain subject to paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF4439C853F4D8AABE47A343C9483D2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Critical energy resource; critical energy resource facility defined</header><text>The terms <term>critical energy resource</term> and <term>critical energy resource facility</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 3025(f) of the Solid Waste Disposal Act (as added by this section).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCBB30A6F0D54428EA9544A8A68416C55"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Solid Waste Disposal Act requirements</header><paragraph id="HADE30394CD8F4D3AB24CCBD185C89DD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hazardous Waste Management</header><text>The Solid Waste Disposal Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6901">42 U.S.C. 6901 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 3024 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBB4DA29AD946434A83CAA6D63C685C5A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFF5D8FAF2DD74F94BDB2EFF0B02E97A8"><enum>3025.</enum><header>Waivers for critical energy resource facilities</header><subsection id="H1EF185A67A0E44F7BA8FCC138BF703A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, determines that, by reason of a sudden increase in demand for, or a shortage of, a critical energy resource, or another cause, the processing or refining of a critical energy resource at a critical energy resource facility is necessary to meet the national security or energy security needs of the United States, then the Administrator may, with or without notice, hearing, or other report, issue a temporary waiver of any covered requirement with respect to such critical energy resource facility that, in the judgment of the Administrator, will allow for such processing or refining at such critical energy resource facility as necessary to best meet such needs and serve the public interest. </text></subsection><subsection id="H59DBCC95CC1F428EA0F9AECA97096154"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conflict with other environmental laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall ensure that any waiver of a covered requirement under this section, to the maximum extent practicable, does not result in a conflict with a requirement of any other applicable Federal, State, or local environmental law or regulation and minimizes any adverse environmental impacts.</text></subsection><subsection id="H31FD2A7BBE4A45C9AB577041F4BBBB11"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Violations of other environmental laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent any omission or action taken by a party under a waiver issued under this section is in conflict with any requirement of a Federal, State, or local environmental law or regulation, such omission or action shall not be considered a violation of such environmental law or regulation, or subject such party to any requirement, civil or criminal liability, or a citizen suit under such environmental law or regulation. </text></subsection><subsection id="H085962EB01AD4ABA9E2DFEE1BA52FE49"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expiration and renewal of waivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A waiver issued under this section shall expire not later than 90 days after it is issued. The Administrator may renew or reissue such waiver pursuant to subsections (a) and (b) for subsequent periods, not to exceed 90 days for each period, as the Administrator determines necessary to meet the national security or energy security needs described in subsection (a) and serve the public interest. In renewing or reissuing a waiver under this subsection, the Administrator shall include in any such renewed or reissued waiver such conditions as are necessary to minimize any adverse environmental impacts to the extent practicable.</text></subsection><subsection id="H83AAA435150A49C1AE59929E516F4B49"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Subsequent action by court</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a waiver issued under this section is subsequently stayed, modified, or set aside by a court pursuant a provision of law, any omission or action previously taken by a party under the waiver while the waiver was in effect shall remain subject to subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H41E6CEA77CC24E67B700541364823617"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBDDE5A77E3634FFDA78A8C7B9CCDC256"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered requirement</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA87684E360FD4D61A99C0E38B08531C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any standard established under section 3002, 3003, or 3004;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B957F0AA67D4A3698F0A225E3E8DEEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the permit requirement under section 3005; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A233E065F4741AFB19A34FF590F65DE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other requirement of this Act, as the Administrator determines appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H91F9AE37FC984052B6A7A18EED373A51"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical energy resource</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>critical energy resource</term> means, as determined by the Secretary of Energy, any energy resource—</text><subparagraph id="HD36DE4C2C33548CCA0B0C5A6C1D0B3BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is essential to the energy sector and energy systems of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H608A7F646AD74A5DB0FC64E039DCEB67"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the supply chain of which is vulnerable to disruption.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAD281A600F84837BD7339EB7019B75A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical energy resource facility</header><text>The term <term>critical energy resource facility</term> means a facility that processes or refines a critical energy resource. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H64A5E6A24C394A6B803EAF1CAA971FD1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of the Solid Waste Disposal Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 3024 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC4967047DC1742478A569F70633A60E2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 3025. Waivers for critical energy resource facilities.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

