<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H047C6B4340A2494E8268C6D54125F57B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4065 IH: To obtain and direct the placement in the Capitol or on the Capitol Grounds of a statue to honor American humanitarian and star athlete Roberto Clemente of Puerto Rico.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4065</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230613">June 13, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To obtain and direct the placement in the Capitol or on the Capitol Grounds of a statue to honor American humanitarian and star athlete Roberto Clemente of Puerto Rico.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4A0A6E15741D43CD856D9DD0352A0C79" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0B1FE03E5FDE41F48275A0A9104FD188" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H7DB632C235A94A28AB44D5F7AEBA0D2D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Roberto Clemente Walker was born in San Antón Ward, at the time a sugarcane growing community in Carolina, Puerto Rico, on August 18, 1934, to working class parents Melchor Clemente and Luisa Walker.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91A5487CC2D5483AAAE705A688EC45BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Showing an early athletic talent, Clemente excelled in track and field events at Vizcarrondo High School, but baseball was his true passion, and he began his professional baseball career in the Puerto Rico Winter League at age 17.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2EE8A3E2C2C54CC28A4F6A7E177B9C41"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Scouted by the Dodgers at age 18, he spent a short time in the minor leagues in that organization before being drafted by the Pittsburgh Pirates, where he remained for his entire time in Major League Baseball.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4E7C63FE051414F825728951BA502BA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Clemente was one of the pioneers who still had to face persistent discrimination and negative attitudes related to his origin and culture on and off the field and in the media, but his talent and discipline soon spoke louder.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBA972350B25447FB8D392559650B337"><enum>(5)</enum><text>He proved his mettle in the Pirates teams, reaching championships in two World Series, including in 1971 when he was named Most Valuable Player. He was named the 1966 regular season Most Valuable Player. He won 12 Gold Gloves as one of the most effective, hard-throwing, and precise outfielders in the game. He won four batting titles, had a lifetime .317 batting average and 3,000 hits, and was a 12-time member of the All-Star team.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H452563BC4B034DDEBDD4D0617E859168"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Clemente was an exemplary figure off the baseball field as well. Having received a rare opportunity, he made sure that he could be of service to others.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB92FF837A9A49CEB98150224CEC0F7E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>During his rookie season, Clemente also served as a member of the Marine Corps Reserve, fulfilling his commitment to the Nation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H120D1C91DD484AB3A33A53A808D3AC70"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Once he reached stardom, he would spend the off-season actively supporting community efforts in Puerto Rico and in neighboring countries in the Caribbean region, using sports as a vehicle to motivate the progress of communities and specially to provide opportunities for social development for disadvantaged families. One of his desires was the founding of a center for developing underprivileged youth through sport and education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD3C95942FD90468B8BF2A0C90F7FDF40"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A man of strong family values, Clemente in 1964 married Vera Cristina Zabala, with whom he started a family that grew with the birth of his sons Roberto Jr. in 1965, Luis in 1966, and Enrique in 1969. Upon winning the 1971 World Series MVP, he showed that strong bond and his faith when in his interview he sent a blessing to his children and asked for one from his parents.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB2ADCF4C93E1472498B1918D45FA34CD"><enum>(10)</enum><text>After the December 23, 1972, earthquake in Managua, Nicaragua, having earlier that year worked in that country with an international tournament, Roberto Clemente was a leader in efforts to obtain relief supplies for the victims and mobilize aid.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB6EDB6169F949CEAC2D5158B2D24CE6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Concerned over reports that this help may not reach those who needed it but was instead being diverted or misused, on December 31, 1972, he boarded an aid flight, so that he could participate directly in delivering it.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9B1EC9AE79348CC834395DE85EC7528"><enum>(12)</enum><text>That flight, tragically, suffered a mechanical failure during takeoff climb and crashed into the sea just off the coast, with all on board perishing. The loss of Roberto Clemente was traumatic across the Puerto Rican and general Latino community and the sports world.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDB78F0E23D7348898CCE65F2B8461E9B"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The accolades received by Clemente are many, and to this day he continues to accumulate recognition on his home soil and away from it, not only as a sports superstar with lasting fame in that endeavor, but as an example of commitment to humanity in its times of need, even to the ultimate consequences. The Baseball Writers Association almost immediately waived the waiting period requirement and named Roberto Clemente Walker to the Baseball Hall of Fame in 1973. The Major League Baseball Roberto Clemente Award is given every year to the player who best exemplifies the game of baseball, sportsmanship, community involvement, and the individual’s contribution to his team. The Puerto Rico Winter League is now named the Roberto Clemente Professional Baseball League.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B2D7335AC5C4F67B9B54C74B2E010B3"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Roberto Clemente Walker is a hero for whom respect and love is shared by all segments of Puerto Rican communities in the Island and across the Nation and the world.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA86C6B31D6FE4B2682083EDC736B0FB0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statue honoring Roberto Clemente Walker</header> <subsection id="HED3C4800FA3E444C9E907F623C339948"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Obtaining of statue</header> <paragraph id="HC2A9DF59A88C48D0B818BF381508F512"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, in consultation with the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate, and under such terms and conditions as the Joint Committee on the Library considers appropriate consistent with applicable law, the Joint Committee shall enter into an agreement to obtain a statue honoring humanitarian and star athlete Roberto Clemente Walker.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF41DC41CFF0742C585B1780A309320B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration of artists of variety of backgrounds</header><text>In selecting an artist for the statue under paragraph (1), the Joint Committee shall consider artists from a variety of backgrounds, including artists from the Puerto Rican community and underrepresented demographic groups, and shall make public announcements targeting such artists.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H051E89D2B1AA4586899CF718D9C56651"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Donation</header><text>The Joint Committee may obtain the statue under paragraph (1) by donation, subject to the laws and rules governing the acceptance of donated works of art.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H42B361E42DE343028A4B9CD9EB1D6238"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Installation</header><text>The Architect of the Capitol, under the direction of the Joint Committee on the Library, shall permanently install the statue obtained under subsection (a) in an appropriate location in the United States Capitol or on the Capitol Grounds, as described in section 5102 of title 40, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEF461D09C5024D38ADCBB59B6A8CDF97"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorizing funding with amounts in Capitol Preservation Fund</header> <paragraph id="H995329B152094E749359D99FD275A4E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>Notwithstanding section 803 of the Arizona-Idaho Conservation Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2083">2 U.S.C. 2083</external-xref>), the United States Capitol Preservation Commission established under section 801 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2081">2 U.S.C. 2081</external-xref>) may transfer amounts in the Capitol Preservation Fund established under section 803 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2083">2 U.S.C. 2083</external-xref>) to the Joint Committee on the Library and the Architect of the Capitol for purposes of obtaining and installing the statue under this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E59883B20E046248DB7526037C66EA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on amount transferred</header><text>The amount transferred under paragraph (1) may not exceed $500,000.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

