<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA45BA1F5A6C94817B17A26CAA4FC1FEA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4460 IH: Non-citizens: Outlawed from Voting in Our Trusted Elections Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4460</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230703">July 3, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 and the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to ensure that only eligible American citizens may participate in elections for Federal office, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H25471560C043489CBAB88140E4340096" style="OLC">
<section id="H19E62F8662F94C92A586693421BA9E4B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings; sense of Congress</header>
<subsection id="HF8308245E78D4382B4487979012AD93E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Non-citizens: Outlawed from Voting in Our Trusted Elections Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>NO VOTE for Non-Citizens Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE6FF486BFB0D4E4FA8CEF6B6C3679CB4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings; Sense of Congress</header> <paragraph id="HE9F67E7C18D248B2BBEFFB79E4E8FF86"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H49584C98945440EE9E41EDBF996E3BBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every eligible person who wishes to cast a ballot in a Federal election must be permitted to do so according to law, and their ballot must be examined according to law, and, if it meets all lawful requirements, counted.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA3F3778F0AD4BB8A74658D1B1AA10CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has long required States to maintain Federal voter registration lists in a manner that promotes voter confidence.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD235A7990D8F4EBFBEC5081BA4D26A2A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The changes included herein are not intended to be an expansion of Federal power but rather a clarification of State authority.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE81785135F6D4042A0CEC4A817629577"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fifteenth Amendment, the Nineteenth Amendment, the Twenty-Fourth Amendment, and the Twenty-Sixth Amendment, among other references, make clear that the Constitution prohibits voting by non-citizens in Federal elections.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB1279AA90FCE4D5FB31226A21BC389D7"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has the constitutional authority, including under the aforementioned amendments, to pass statutes preventing non-citizens from voting in Federal elections, and did so with the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2BED690CFEAC459490E7F07462A2C2CB"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress may further exercise its constitutional authority to ensure the Constitution’s prohibition on non-citizen voting in Federal elections is upheld.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8ADFBA3216E642B78CA68F55A15D1B0C"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since the Constitution prohibits non-citizens from voting in Federal elections, such ineligible persons must not be permitted to be placed on Federal voter registration lists.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H239F48EA0F0B463EB33ACB2E356857FC"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improper placement of an ineligible non-citizen on a Federal voter registration list leads to—</text>
<clause id="H7AFB4E49108F405CBAA9AC5301807733"><enum>(i)</enum><text>confusion on the part of the ineligible person with respect to their ineligibility to cast a ballot; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBCD65083B1B94C3881C30EE5BBEB8A7D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an increased likelihood that human error will permit ineligible persons to cast ballots in Federal elections.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0AF691BA72414E8E82EE3A85B3BFB049"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State officials have confirmed that poorly maintained voter registration lists lead to ineligible persons casting ballots in Federal elections.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE2183233A1AE4C258507A006FAE723DE"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A former Broward County, Florida, elections supervisor has confirmed that ineligible non-voters were able to cast ballots in previous elections and that she was not able to locate as many as 2,040 ballots during the 2018 midterm recount.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCA5C93657D2745849F8ED648754A7A21"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This clarification of State authority to maintain Federal voter registration lists to ensure non-citizens are not included on such lists will promote voter confidence in election processes and outcomes.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D243419303D4F619189A747A8E5B15E"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has the authority to ensure that no Federal elections funding is used to support States that permit non-citizens to cast ballots in any election.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF84D5E0639D34A2FAA5CC3F352B6A7F9"><enum>(M)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal courts and executive agencies have much of the information States may need to maintain their Federal voter registration lists, and those entities should make that information accessible to State election authorities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23BEC7F0CF7942F883E2A4A7CD03F920"><enum>(N)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is important to clarify the penalty for any violation of law that allows a non-citizen to cast a ballot in a Federal election.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFF2E800334EE4F12850BB2562AA05766"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To protect the confidence of voters in Federal elections, it is important to implement the policy described herein.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H630B1A1577414AA0AA1C2B44EBDB8963"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD37B9F721E51497A918BD72D83C41F5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">many States have not adequately met the requirements concerning the removal of ineligible persons from State voter registration rolls pursuant to section 8 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507</external-xref>) and should strive to audit and update their voter registration rolls on a routine basis;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF58146E7D2EE481E9085BFF542BA4E21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>allowing non-citizens to cast ballots in American elections weakens our electoral system and the value of citizenship and sows distrust in our elections system;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H154EE4814FFB46E49AF5E65C4B6F937B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">even if a State has the sovereign authority, no State should permit non-citizens to cast ballots in State or local elections;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EC93972F894482FA95CA57D5EAB22FF"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">States should use all information available to them to maintain Federal voter registration lists and should inform Congress if such data is insufficient; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5DA17073ADAF46E3AC2DEF2C764909BD"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress may take further action in the future to address this problem.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2779B23BCCBD4904B434408AA092D83E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring only eligible American citizens may participate in Federal elections</header> <subsection id="H00EAA11CA9BE489FBA784BB14F2EA94C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Clarifying authority of States To remove noncitizens from voting rolls</header> <paragraph id="HA911BB20977B4AA3A541C9E6CEC96FD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority under regular removal programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(a)(4) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCDB59EC8C0634CD8836ECA5FA09EC3FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F69FAFCDE574FE58150A87E20E3E2FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (B) as subparagraph (C); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H450C2C973CAF4778AFAF4917BBCE15F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H624C280652AF407395C40701CB549E76" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HF84D87BBCB8F448A98163514C25B062A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the registrant’s status as a noncitizen of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF9C526D774B04DA297F7D1AFC8B94CA8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to ongoing removal</header><text>Section 8(c)(2)(B)(i) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(c)(2)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>(4)(A)</quote> and inserting <quote>(4)(A) or (B)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4299D71835B7420C9C2E24A171C0547E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement To maintain separate State voter registration list for noncitizens</header><text>Section 8(a) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H9E23111DA9FF499BB591012CA244F3CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C78C1E48919442892427BE5E9980D46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H253DAE3D6159486F879D1C472DE884A1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H96CDB25D724E48B3A4C00A935D4F7129" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HE855B487BC57423B9C8ED55229AFC246"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a State that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or any local jurisdiction of the State, ensure that the name of any registrant who is not a citizen of the United States is maintained on a voter registration list that is separate from the official list of eligible voters with respect to registrants who are citizens of the United States. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0D4A1D3CD9D34D288040AB21167B57F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements for ballots for State or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 301(a)(1) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAF4C3D62BA9C49FC9C9551D2A361DC5D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H859B44B20DD54610845CAF916971B673"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction, the ballot used for the casting of votes by a noncitizen in such State or local jurisdiction may only include the candidates for the elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction for which the noncitizen is permitted to vote.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HFC86D8879AF24A08AEC7B55E6671400D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reduction in payments for election administration to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header>
<paragraph id="H8D142D356ACB4670A3E26DA4F670143E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title IX of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21141">52 U.S.C. 21141 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE4F3629FDF914BF997C4471AD59B6E01" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H231B7C11ABC04E52905A01AE9D2D32B3"><enum>907.</enum><header>Reduction in payments to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header> <subsection id="H0A5B6D8FD51A439497A454B3A390D626"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the amount of a payment under this Act to any State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction shall be reduced by 30 percent. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H24522529BAC647ACA6563BE40AB23821"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of funds for certain election administration activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds may be used to implement the requirements of section 8(a)(7) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)(7)</external-xref>) (as added by section 2(b) of the NO VOTE for Non-Citizens Act of 2023) or section 301(a)(1)(D) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081(a)(1)(D)</external-xref>) (as added by 2(c) of the NO VOTE for Non-Citizens Act of 2023) in a State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB7973FCE8C84B6398812EAAE2BDF3B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H671E9D5E19E2473A98DCF42D22AE6529" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 907. Reduction in payments to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF6245FCA7A4A4D5F8A056A9147DF6A59"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Promoting provision of information by Federal entities</header>
<paragraph id="H33BA29C8832C40BFA9F3908EB80F61F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each entity of the Federal Government which maintains information which is relevant to the status of an individual as a registered voter in elections for Federal office in a State shall, upon the request of an election official of the State, provide that information to the election official.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2789A07D01847BE96A78BB1D867CFD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Policies and procedures</header><text>Consistent with section 3506(g) of title 44, United States Code, an entity of the Federal Government shall carry out this subsection in accordance with policies and procedures which will ensure that the information is provided securely, accurately, and in a timely basis.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD278D886FC6F45419B1505E7B1E62153"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to coverage under Privacy Act</header><text>Section 552a(b) of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H9970452C7C074B14B595043F5E82871A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of paragraph (11);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB8A8ECB059D34D37A92561784CE5630A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (12) and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6614C876E281422C94530B90C64150E2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HE2B2C91771804AA3A9CA75EF488FB006" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H3E5B555901834132BE97B8BB9B312742"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to an election official of a State in accordance with section 2(e) of the NO VOTE for Non-Citizens Act of 2023.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H61998B8E790C40929808738CF15B7122"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Ensuring provision of information to State election officials on individuals recused from jury service on grounds of noncitizenship</header> <paragraph id="H1C2FDD5301F745B0A8098A9CE5DE7E36"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement described</header><text>If a United States district court recuses an individual from serving on a jury on the grounds that the individual is not a citizen of the United States, the court shall transmit a notice of the individual’s recusal—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE3554F18F2C54FB4950F27879F9A9CC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the chief State election official of the State in which the individual resides; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DB6796A443F433EB6FF72C1CD36E47D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H61432754B12544D6B2CE7148C49FB6BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="HE2FF79F983DC4F8195C926DFC520238F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <quote>chief State election official</quote> of a State is the individual designated by the State under section 10 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20509">52 U.S.C. 20509</external-xref>) to be responsible for coordination of the State’s responsibilities under such Act; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF1E8D9AA4DB542F1A739D58D41C3C58F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF35CF1CDB29C4DE88EAA459E13270753" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Prohibition on voting by noncitizens in Federal elections</header> <paragraph id="HAC3140ACA7CD4AB19E7AB86A00632E7C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 12 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20511">52 U.S.C. 20511</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB79322902314461F9C16B6B9817FC5AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A person</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In general.—</header-in-text>A person</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9480C31BC8DE4D6989DB98D896B55948"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1860F9A00CAF440188DAF5227044BE12" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HE64834F3922E4712834EF05F676A20E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on voting by aliens</header>
<paragraph id="H1500EF384F0046298D1C8F306222A3E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any alien to vote in any election in violation of section 611 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72E73BDA375E4127A9CB06E290F7B442"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who violates this subsection shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned not more than one year, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A9114985EC148FF8A872C7237642123"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection and the amendments made by this subsection shall apply with respect to elections held on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

