<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD5D4BE7A0214250AC99196B548E4E5A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 247 IH: Chisholm National Historic Trail and Western National Historic Trail Designation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 247</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230110">January 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Trails System Act to designate the Chisholm National Historic Trail and the Western National Historic Trail, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H17387D19DAF04632A2BA01A89E571F0C" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H3626C8688D60465B95D2666AB3E510C6"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Chisholm National Historic Trail and Western National Historic Trail Designation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H416143D05FD342D6B3D6663D19B52BBC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of the Chisholm National Historic Trail and the Western National Historic Trail</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(a) of the National Trails System Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1244">16 U.S.C. 1244(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB98B80F80E5F46F0B83CCBC74E91B217"> 
<paragraph id="H11D921A64F9E49FDA69694D10D56B7A3"><enum>(_)</enum><header>Chisholm National Historic Trail; Western National Historic Trail</header> 
<subparagraph id="H51D09DE26CD546B0BF8D24148799CB39"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header> 
<clause id="H434E2A247C7A4EF0A1CA3D3760B6E60D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Chisholm National Historic Trail</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chisholm National Historic Trail, a trail most heavily used by ranchers and drovers to move cattle to market between 1867 and 1884, extending along a route of approximately 1,378 miles from Kingsville, Texas, through Cuero and San Antonio, Texas, northward through Oklahoma to Abilene, Kansas, as generally depicted on the maps numbered 1 through 6 contained in the report prepared by the National Park Service entitled <quote>Chisholm and Great Western National Historic Trail Feasibility Study/Environmental Assessment</quote> and dated May 2019.</text></clause> <clause id="H9A10E708B6DA4204A9E53B2C5AB60426"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Western National Historic Trail</header><text>The Western National Historic Trail, a trail most heavily used by ranchers and drovers to move cattle to market between 1874 and 1897, extending along a route of approximately 1,350 miles from Kingsville, Texas, northward through Oklahoma and Dodge City, Kansas, to Ogallala, Nebraska, as generally depicted on the maps numbered 1 through 6 contained in the report prepared by the National Park Service entitled <quote>Chisholm and Great Western National Historic Trail Feasibility Study/Environmental Assessment</quote> and dated May 2019.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F1F8FC293AC4CF28206B4D6F6D633B6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The maps described in subparagraph (A) shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the Department of the Interior.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HACDC6AEEFD334B87BCDD8D23EDBBFC3E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Administration</header> <clause id="H29287104BBFE4CE2B791910A82F37401"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Interior shall administer the trails established by subparagraph (A) as a single administrative unit.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6EB19A5140394CC48D7886AC50163F92"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Administration of portions of trail on non-Federal land</header> 
<subclause id="H1494514E513E47E38F2FAD0B45A52FB8"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Requirements for administration</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall administer any portion of a trail established by subparagraph (A) that is located on non-Federal land only—</text> <item id="HC9C9CAE2F32A4FCDBFC97AAC1EDBC9CB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>with the voluntary consent of the owner of the non-Federal land; and</text></item> 
<item id="H8E448DEE631643B8BC024EA2D35CB33B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>if the portion qualifies for certification as a component of the applicable trail, consistent with section 3(a)(3). </text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H6B1B14625D3746429BB426D0D8E2F8E3"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Certification agreement</header> <item id="HFC76BE21E4734492992CCAA52FCCFD69"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The approval by an owner of applicable non-Federal land of a certification agreement shall satisfy the consent requirements of subclause (I)(aa).</text></item> 
<item id="H55730DA35CAA41659F3E95898C6F03E1"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>A certification agreement referred to in item (aa) may be terminated at any time.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H100F74B386C7454A81CF5EF7FB3F0833"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Access to private property</header><text>The establishment of a trail by subparagraph (A) does not authorize any person to enter private property without the consent of the owner of the private property. </text></clause> 
<clause id="HF40194B6F03E4F1FAB9979A9B4FE208B"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Recognition of alternative names for trails</header><text>In referring to a trail established by subparagraph (A) in maps and other documents, the Secretary of the Interior may acknowledge and use any alternative name that was historically used to reference the trail, including the <quote>Great Western Trail</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9F5BB89B31B547DC9E0F4F743D09305C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Land acquisition</header> <clause id="HE6833535A5244F4DB2501C0762C4B36C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Donation</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior may accept a donation of land or an interest in land for a trail established by subparagraph (A).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6B565ED5AA9E4B3FA6978AA8978BEF9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior may not acquire for a trail established by subparagraph (A) any land or interest in land—</text> <subclause id="H75604B85CAD549EBA3344FDD0216F854"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that is located outside the exterior boundary of any federally managed area without the consent of the owner of the land or interest in land; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H483C612EBC85475FAE9B11BDF3A5B91A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that extends more than an average of <fraction>1/4</fraction> of a mile on either side of a trail established by subparagraph (A).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H521B711B002C45CB833ABE0F864D286C"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Effect on energy development, production, or transmission</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph, the acquisition of land or an interest in land authorized by this paragraph, or any management plan for a trail established by subparagraph (A) prohibits, hinders, or disrupts the development, production, or transmission of energy.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB38EC360589647AC959FC7D24A9048ED"><enum>(F)</enum><header>No buffer zones</header> 
<clause id="H413395D5284849EB817A0242511B3ADE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph, the acquisition of land or an interest in land authorized by this paragraph, or any management plan for a trail established by subparagraph (A) creates a buffer zone.</text></clause> <clause id="HF8389C30B5FD4C669FEAD97CE8849DB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Outside activities</header><text>The fact that an activity or use on land outside a trail established by subparagraph (A) can be seen, heard, or detected from the applicable trail, including from any land or interest in land acquired for the applicable trail, shall not preclude, limit, control, regulate, or determine the conduct or management of the activity or use outside the applicable trail. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9D8DDA3FF21649D089D32F735E3CBE4E"><enum>(G)</enum><header>No eminent domain or condemnation</header><text>Land or an interest in land may not be acquired for a trail established by subparagraph (A) by eminent domain or condemnation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1119C13873DF4DC4A188D2F7EA69D8BC"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Inventory of sites; administrative costs</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall be responsible for—</text> 
<clause id="HFDD8FAD568A14DDB84413BF29A89B013"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the costs of any inventory to identify and define potential sites and segments for inclusion in a trail established by subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> <clause id="H8FB85AEB63934B4280899468A0EA1A8B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other applicable administrative costs relating to a trail established by that subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H835707FFC4C942F892249A6824FBAB87"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Not a designation of <quote>lands in the national park system</quote></header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the establishment of a trail by subparagraph (A) shall not have the effect of designating the trail or any land on which the trail is located as <quote>lands in the National Park System</quote> for purposes of section 28(b)(1) of the Mineral Leasing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/185">30 U.S.C. 185(b)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6DD9775AD0949A78F4E9B887137C414"><enum>(J)</enum><header>No new authorities or permits</header> <clause id="H95D5F105FE534AF3A5CB57C4E0AFF650"><enum>(i)</enum><header>No effect on authority to grant easements or rights-of-way</header> <subclause id="H661394609E014D779F8010EA0A15D684"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the establishment of a trail by subparagraph (A) shall not alter or affect the existing authority of any Federal, State, or local agency or official to grant easements or rights-of-way over, under, across, or along any portion of the trail.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H271677872E134132B196C7B933923296"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Authority of heads of Federal agencies to grants easements or rights-of-way</header><text>Notwithstanding the establishment of a trail by subparagraph (A), the head of any Federal agency having jurisdiction over any Federal land on which the trail is located (other than land that is considered to be <quote>lands in the National Park System</quote> for purposes of section 28(b)(1) of the Mineral Leasing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/185">30 U.S.C. 185(b)(1)</external-xref>) as a result of an establishment under any other law), shall have the authority to grant easements or rights-of-way over, under, across, or along any applicable portion of the trail in accordance with the laws applicable to the Federal land.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H42AF51DC1FBF4B9DB943BEC2321A01D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>No new permits required</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the establishment of a trail by subparagraph (A) shall not subject the trail or any land on which the trail is located to any other Federal laws (including regulations) requiring a Federal permit or authorization that would otherwise be made applicable as a result of the establishment of the trail as a component of the National Trails System.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

