<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBBBA80974042446EBF08DCF757D3D296" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3142 IH: Stand Your Ground Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3142</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to provide an affirmative defense for certain criminal violations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE7175ABF1B6B4841B6398397B2024152" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2DC5AB0A31E14CE69EB77D370FC26BD7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stand Your Ground Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H76FAB280E0024BA79D240532A357030E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certain affirmative defenses</header> <subsection id="HE2DABA2FC4924FB0830F421C7903ED91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Affirmative defense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part I of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEC16DC7119E640D99A1A65C209AC21A6" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<chapter id="H28C80DD48D61400682A627428A6DD6BC"><enum>124</enum><header>Affirmative defenses</header>
<section id="H9DCC1FB06B794208BB9D3462E049569E"><enum>2730.</enum><header>Affirmative defense for certain criminal violations</header>
<subsection id="H80516617B78A40C4B1A8FBAE595C4E4E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use or threatened use of force in defense of person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be an affirmative defense to a violation of this title if:</text> <paragraph id="H8FDF4D99C920418DB24CE72A2C77F94D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A person is justified in using, threatening, or attempting to use force, except deadly force, against another when and to the extent that the person reasonably believes that such conduct is necessary to defend himself or herself or another against an agressor’s imminent use of unlawful force. A person who uses or threatens to use force in accordance with this paragraph does not have a duty to retreat before using or threatening to use such force.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAFD8DE0A0D1A4EC291B8A3B2A9DDE5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A person is justified in using, threatening, or attempting to use deadly force if he or she reasonably believes that using, threatening, or attempting to use such force is necessary to prevent imminent death or great bodily harm to himself or herself or another or to prevent the imminent commission of a forcible felony. A person who uses, threatens, or attempts to use deadly force in accordance with this paragraph does not have a duty to retreat and has the right to stand his or her ground if the person using, threatening, or attempts to use the deadly force is not engaged in a criminal activity and is in a place where he or she has a right to be.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCF3CB37BE5CB4803929A11E3BA0212BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H179D32F242F2444E877BB2A23267EAB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duty to retreat</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>duty to retreat</quote> means that if a person is under attack, he or she should first seek retreat as the preferred alternative to using force to act in self-defense. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H349ADB6063834022A9E763AEFA4E2DBA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forcible felony</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>forcible felony</quote> includes treason, murder, manslaughter, sexual battery, carjacking, home-invasion robbery, robbery, burglary, arson, kidnapping, aggravated assault, aggravated battery, aggravated stalking, aircraft piracy, unlawful throwing, placing, or discharging of a destructive device or bomb, and any other felony which involves the use or threat of physical force or violence against any individual. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H482732B2277042E882DF41F9D607B739"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Stand your ground</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>stand your ground</quote> means the allowance of an individual to defend himself or herself by any means necessary when his or her life is threatened.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H91172AFAC71F481A83A667727E9A971E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date; Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made under subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and may be used as an affirmative defense by a defendant in the prosecution of a criminal offense initiated after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

