<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H15F080CC2A304E7D9E0D9DFB218054C4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4250 RH: Protect Reporters from Exploitative State Spying Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 242</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4250</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–299]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="F000478">Mr. Fry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000377">Mr. Armstrong</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To maintain the free flow of information to the public by establishing appropriate limits on the federally compelled disclosure of information obtained as part of engaging in journalism, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="H722BE25257B4482BA44D8CFDC64E734D" style="OLC"><section id="HE31DD2605F9E43689CDCB9877F69A620" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Reporters from Exploitative State Spying Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PRESS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFD28202794734C01A6363239CED472C5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HF9012BD2771D4BE5B2B6DC3C529D5BAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered journalist</header><text>The term <term>covered journalist</term> means a person who regularly gathers, prepares, collects, photographs, records, writes, edits, reports, investigates, or publishes news or information that concerns local, national, or international events or other matters of public interest for dissemination to the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H645F593F691D418BBC4AFC7C85F393F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered service provider</header><subparagraph id="H13B909355C7842568E3CC709249AABF4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>covered service provider</term> means any person that, by an electronic means, stores, processes, or transmits information in order to provide a service to customers of the person.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5549B62BEEEA4C5B87F26786E341E7ED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The term <term>covered service provider</term> includes—</text><clause id="H3DFC4FDEDB584986801B1B17F3818B1D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a telecommunications carrier and a provider of an information service (as such terms are defined in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="HC890D109D9624397A93F59AB46B91DEB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a provider of an interactive computer service and an information content provider (as such terms are defined in section 230 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="HB887ED6F348143E79432F8CD3ECE587B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a provider of remote computing service (as defined in section 2711 of title 18, United States Code); and</text></clause><clause id="HACB01C5D4C474BF3BFAEFC192107E7C6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a provider of electronic communication service (as defined in section 2510 of title 18, United States Code) to the public.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77A1658199E7477298510C3C44D75C5A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Document</header><text>The term <term>document</term> means writings, recordings, and photographs, as those terms are defined by Federal Rule of Evidence 1001 (28 U.S.C. App.).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BD31065DC174E80A09BD5462C416CA6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal entity</header><text>The term <term>Federal entity</term> means an entity or employee of the judicial or executive branch or an administrative agency of the Federal Government with the power to issue a subpoena or issue other compulsory process.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A49BFEFD9094E19AB8CD0F8F62823FF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Journalism</header><text>The term <term>journalism</term> means gathering, preparing, collecting, photographing, recording, writing, editing, reporting, investigating, or publishing news or information that concerns local, national, or international events or other matters of public interest for dissemination to the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30503717F5484233A9CAF9428CF16AA3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Personal account of a covered journalist</header><text>The term <term>personal account of a covered journalist</term> means an account with a covered service provider used by a covered journalist that is not provided, administered, or operated by the employer of the covered journalist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57775AEF3EB94CC8A6BC203B6EBFD2BF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Personal technology device of a covered journalist</header><text>The term <term>personal technology device of a covered journalist</term> means a handheld communications device, laptop computer, desktop computer, or other internet-connected device used by a covered journalist that is not provided or administered by the employer of the covered journalist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D7EA4B5410D45C3A7E0BFB5C25BFE7B"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Protected information</header><text>The term <term>protected information</term> means any information identifying a source who provided information as part of engaging in journalism, and any records, contents of a communication, documents, or information that a covered journalist obtained or created as part of engaging in journalism.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H88C63E15A0ED453F83B910607E4652E9"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Specified offense against a minor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>specified offense against a minor</term> has the meaning given that term in section 111(7) of the Adam Walsh Child Protection and Safety Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20911">34 U.S.C. 20911(7)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H31E0D7D92DAF47ECB2133B9525274920"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limits on compelled disclosure from covered journalists</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In any matter arising under Federal law, a Federal entity may not compel a covered journalist to disclose protected information, unless a court in the judicial district in which the subpoena or other compulsory process is, or will be, issued determines by a preponderance of the evidence, after providing notice and an opportunity to be heard to the covered journalist, that—</text><paragraph id="H96E0C9B0305842148BC8703524B42ACB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>disclosure of the protected information is necessary to prevent, or to identify any perpetrator of, an act of terrorism against the United States; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H232151C0615B4AF79766718E1D8AE0CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disclosure of the protected information is necessary to prevent a threat of imminent violence, significant bodily harm, or death, including specified offenses against a minor.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H579E1928042848519015E5376DF872D4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Limits on compelled disclosure from covered service providers</header><subsection id="H1FBCB10E402C4993A2CC629BE3575F7B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Conditions for compelled disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any matter arising under Federal law, a Federal entity may not compel a covered service provider to provide testimony or any document consisting of any record, information, or other communications stored by a covered provider on behalf of a covered journalist, including testimony or any document relating to a personal account of a covered journalist or a personal technology device of a covered journalist, unless a court in the judicial district in which the subpoena or other compulsory process is, or will be, issued determines by a preponderance of the evidence that there is a reasonable threat of imminent violence unless the testimony or document is provided, and issues an order authorizing the Federal entity to compel the disclosure of the testimony or document.</text></subsection><subsection id="H98237648BB1A46BFAAAD1C008111688B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notice to court</header><text>A Federal entity seeking to compel the provision of testimony or any document described in subsection (a) shall inform the court that the testimony or document relates to a covered journalist.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E5CA1D6964742AB969E33A05D98A0CC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notice to covered journalist and opportunity To be heard</header><paragraph id="HC07A9590867E4BC5AAB73497EC104862"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court may authorize a Federal entity to compel the provision of testimony or a document under this section only after the Federal entity seeking the testimony or document provides the covered journalist on behalf of whom the testimony or document is stored pursuant to subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H31F8BE39A74D4C4E8A3D26AEAF9DA161"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notice of the subpoena or other compulsory request for such testimony or document from the covered service provider not later than the time at which such subpoena or request is issued to the covered service provider; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74E379110F6F49B0816CDED8430D7997"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an opportunity to be heard before the court before the time at which the provision of the testimony or document is compelled. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF2AC892D5F546FAACAA32EF6D351460"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception to notice requirement</header><subparagraph id="HE11DB8E2E1CE4FB4BC17ABB169FACA24"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notice and an opportunity to be heard under paragraph (1) may be delayed for not more than 45 days if the court involved determines there is clear and convincing evidence that such notice would pose a clear and substantial threat to the integrity of a criminal investigation, or would present an imminent risk of death or serious bodily harm, including specified offenses against a minor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD23204579B0F441FA119FCBC9E09E3B2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extensions</header><text>The 45-day period described in subparagraph (A) may be extended by the court for additional periods of not more than 45 days if the court involved makes a new and independent determination that there is clear and convincing evidence that providing notice to the covered journalist would pose a clear and substantial threat to the integrity of a criminal investigation, or would present an imminent risk of death or serious bodily harm, including specified offenses against a minor, under current circumstances.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H23085C3C84FA4304977E6FD417DF57D6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Limitation on content of information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The content of any testimony, document, or protected information that is compelled under sections 3 or 4 shall—</text><paragraph id="HF083D4B83CD94C27959224A27BAD4161"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not be overbroad, unreasonable, or oppressive, and, as appropriate, be limited to the purpose of verifying published information or describing any surrounding circumstances relevant to the accuracy of such published information; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F3CDF519DAA4BFDA4D5399FBEB5555E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be narrowly tailored in subject matter and period of time covered so as to avoid compelling the production of peripheral, nonessential, or speculative information.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC0218A7FB777450D8491CC3D6F7940CC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to—</text><paragraph id="H195D01D0D6014BC69F635BA3C1150E80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>apply to civil defamation, slander, or libel claims or defenses under State law, regardless of whether or not such claims or defenses, respectively, are raised in a State or Federal court; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65175ED7063B422C8FE76A2BCA1C62C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prevent the Federal Government from pursuing an investigation of a covered journalist or organization that is—</text><subparagraph id="H0F800A99CF8547ED8B19DB60EF76263A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suspected of committing a crime;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFE961BD01A245FDB8244C75FFC8B775"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a witness to a crime unrelated to engaging in journalism;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H502C40C8F48D43FCAA324E1EAC42E00E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>suspected of being an agent of a foreign power, as defined in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8ADF0CB74D3946EDA83252A62F9DABBB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an individual or organization designated under Executive Order 13224 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and prohibiting transactions with persons who commit, threaten to commit, or support terrorism);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BBE21C26B2E4210BCC67D56ECF587F0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a specially designated terrorist, as that term is defined in section 595.311 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor thereto); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H787155A22FB948B0948B51D4EE00386E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a terrorist organization, as that term is defined in section 212(a)(3)(B)(vi)(II) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(3)(B)(vi)(II)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

