<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAF672D1F0BA5419D9ADA9CEFEB36B7C4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1494 IH: Hurricane Tax Relief Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1494</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide special rules for casualty losses incurred by reason of Hurricane Ian, Hurricane Nicole, and Hurricane Fiona.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H9AFDB2AD418F44A1BA3B1FA1F2B05FEA" style="OLC">
<section id="H35899AEEF3684BAAA0FC817F9E58126C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hurricane Tax Relief Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H66193A778B91417E88B10B1B98432F31"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tax relief related to Hurricane Ian, Hurricane Nicole, and Hurricane Fiona</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H243F7CC07DF04A42B4F03D04DDD3664F"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48F6AF56BD4B4C5DB4671F3110F60222"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hurricane Ian disaster area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Hurricane Ian disaster area</term> means an area with respect to which a major disaster has been declared by the President before the date of the enactment of this section under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act by reason of Hurricane Ian. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5AC728F420814193B9EA9AFD9503A816"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hurricane Nicole disaster area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Hurricane Nicole disaster area</term> means an area with respect to which a major disaster has been declared by the President before the date of the enactment of this section under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act by reason of Hurricane Nicole. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD7DD82FD3E74A708AA14C8FB825F027"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hurricane Fiona disaster area</header><text>The term <term>Hurricane Fiona disaster area</term> means an area with respect to which a major disaster has been declared by the President before the date of the enactment of this section under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act by reason of Hurricane Fiona. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7C31A5166BB64B2E9F06D7214EDA6B1B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special rules for qualified disaster-Related personal casualty losses</header> <paragraph id="HAE9D98EE7F6248349C119558C161FA7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If an individual has a net disaster loss for any taxable year—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB14CBCDEE8D8483FBAFF16AA6C5B9E32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount determined under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/165">section 165(h)(2)(A)(ii)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall be equal to the sum of—</text> <clause id="H2280F381565D41928D9D74C75F10D9EB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such net disaster loss, and</text></clause>
<clause id="H0E2BFF50E39C4120AC3795D435E33116"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>so much of the excess referred to in the matter preceding clause (i) of section 165(h)(2)(A) of such Code (reduced by the amount in clause (i) of this subparagraph) as exceeds 10 percent of the adjusted gross income of the individual,</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H51126D0B62EE4D6DBD6A10CA8467AFA2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of qualified disaster-related personal casualty losses, section 165(h)(1) of such Code shall be applied to by substituting <quote>$500</quote> for <quote>$500 ($100 for taxable years beginning after December 31, 2009)</quote>,</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H127887FEC883430F9F3C2CCCA3ED368F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the standard deduction determined under section 63(c) of such Code shall be increased by the net disaster loss, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE60E016A2D97463397EB107C6B0064AD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>section 56(b)(1)(E) of such Code shall not apply to so much of the standard deduction as is attributable to the increase under subparagraph (C) of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H104836C0EF474DE990F2E8E248EBDA4D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Net disaster loss</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>net disaster loss</term> means the excess of qualified disaster-related personal casualty losses over personal casualty gains (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/165">section 165(h)(3)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39A76126501B4593B823E2ADCAFFACAF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified disaster-related personal casualty losses</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>qualified disaster-related personal casualty losses</term> means losses described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/165">section 165(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986—</text>
<subparagraph id="HDB24685016AC425EB2FFB446EE92E120"><enum>(A)</enum><text>which arise in the Hurricane Ian disaster area on or after September 23, 2022, and which are attributable to Hurricane Ian, </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF88F675231984F51A0FCD87F4F4D0794"><enum>(B)</enum><text>which arise in the Hurricane Nicole disaster area on or after November 7, 2022, and which are attributable to Hurricane Nicole, or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1B0C6C113DF4538A9EAEAC2DCF0507C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>which arise in the Hurricane Fiona disaster area on or after September 17, 2022, and which are attributable to Hurricane Fiona.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H40AF7E2C32C64BEA8FBA75D29685FA76"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application to Puerto Rico</header> <paragraph id="H6B6FD8A415894998B01C15CC2A1C1B5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall pay to Puerto Rico amounts estimated by the Secretary of the Treasury as being equal to the aggregate benefits that would have been provided to residents of Puerto Rico by reason of the provisions of this section if a mirror code tax system had been in effect in Puerto Rico. The preceding sentence shall not apply with respect to Puerto Rico unless Puerto Rico has a plan, which has been approved by the Secretary of the Treasury, under which Puerto Rico will promptly distribute such payments to its residents.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEEC9352DBC1C47A29DA4B3654E2D77F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition and special rules</header>
<subparagraph id="H0ABDB247F2E44C9DA538B7E7BC8A6BBD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Mirror code tax system</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>mirror code tax system</term> means, with respect to any possession of the United States, the income tax system of such possession if the income tax liability of the residents of such possession under such system is determined by reference to the income tax laws of the United States as if such possession were the United States.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FF8F73EB0F64620AADEA0B5F06EA42F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of payments</header><text>For purposes of section 1324 of title 31, United States Code, the payments under this subsection shall be treated in the same manner as a refund due from a credit provision referred to in subsection (b)(2) of such section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAA1D2AF9FB71466A896CACAE03EF0A49"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Coordination with United States income taxes</header><text>In the case of any person with respect to whom a tax benefit is taken into account with respect to the taxes imposed by any possession of the United States by reason of this section, the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall be applied with respect to such person without regard to the provisions of this section which provide such benefit. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

