<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC04857B966A541D993C0DB3903C61BEF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1330 IH: Taiwan Democracy Defense Lend-Lease Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1330</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the loan and lease of defense articles to the Government of Taiwan, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H39AB15A2441F49D69E0B1D54F0F6A275" style="OLC"><section id="H010A317244A545A88B8E1F8CB2E7CFB0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan Democracy Defense Lend-Lease Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD579AF9CE00B43F094FAFF67178EA477"><enum>2.</enum><header>Loan and lease of defense articles to Government of Taiwan</header><subsection id="HB8D14FFC09F04D949BC1FB70217CFECB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that steps taken to bolster the security relations between the United States and Taiwan should include the following:</text><paragraph id="HC7F7994453C1433F96375E198480A31D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The increased conduct of relevant joint military training and bilateral exercises, or multilateral exercises, with the armed forces of Taiwan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1681A01DCC0543CA9318712EEB1FCC87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The prioritization of capacity building in Taiwan, to ensure the protection of sensitive technology lent or leased to the Government of Taiwan by the United States Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CA63BC66BC545C7A086C3E16AF85B2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority To lend or lease defense articles to Government of Taiwan</header><paragraph id="H2F61CDA30B2B4480903F88372B8FCC01"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 503(b)(3) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2311">22 U.S.C. 2311(b)(3)</external-xref>) or section 61 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2796">22 U.S.C. 2796</external-xref>), the President may lend or lease defense articles to the Government of Taiwan to assist in the bolstering of the defensive capabilities of such Government or the protection of the citizen population of Taiwan from potential aggression carried out by the People’s Liberation Army of China against Taiwan (including through one or more of the means described in paragraph (2)) if, as a condition of such loan or lease, the President requires—</text><subparagraph id="H84A508710CE94621B24D7F999C9B6435"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the payment by the Government of Taiwan of the cost of restoring or replacing the defense article, in the case that the defense article is damaged; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39DC3E964F5D4444BEF7535F2C41B65F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the payment by the Government of Taiwan of an amount equal to the replacement cost (less any depreciation in the value) of the defense article, in the case that the defense article is lost or destroyed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF9DCC5A215042368A5AA2B66E9AB81B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Means of aggression by People’s Liberation Army</header><text>The means described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="HAA8B72A6B86D413093B975AD18969F68"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The full or partial naval blockade of Taiwan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7F85E7D81F641BFBB55EC21D53835B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An amphibious assault and ground invasion of Taiwan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACED73D55087402D94675BF91B77E349"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A missile strike (whether conducted alone or as a part of a broader campaign).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B51E9E986A64721B4D988EE12025827"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Kinetic or non-kinetic operations against military targets or critical infrastructure in Taiwan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD198B210D46843379765F232E5E03896"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A seizure, or attempted seizure, of one or more of the outlying islands controlled by Taiwan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2DF55ED10F246BCAD94FA5AD6CA945B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Defense services and defense construction services</header><subparagraph id="H9371C2D6D8CD4B6C89AAB9138BEEA808"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may finance the procurement of defense services and design and construction services by the Government of Taiwan in connection with a loan or lease of a defense article to such Government under paragraph (1), if, as a condition of such financing, the President requires that, not later than 12 years after the date on which the agreement with the Government of Taiwan for such financing is signed on behalf of the United States Government, the Government of Taiwan pay to the United States Government (in United States dollars) an amount equal to the sum of—</text><clause id="HEA6D66950FE3420DB6E017B1AE585B7E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the value of such services; and</text></clause><clause id="HA07107C10C3F4ED3AAC68C78832EB871"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any interest on the unpaid balance of the obligation for payment under clause (i), at a rate that, except as provided in subparagraph (B), is equivalent to the average interest rate, as of the last day of the month preceding the date on which such agreement is signed, that the United States Government pays on outstanding marketable obligations of comparable maturity.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8B4B29B09964D899A62DCFDCA83C8BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception to interest rate requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President submits to Congress a certification containing a determination that national security requires a lesser rate of interest than the rate calculated pursuant to subparagraph (A)(ii), a justification for such determination, and an identification of such lesser rate, the lesser rate so identified shall apply in lieu of the rate calculated pursuant to subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB5F64E0BDF4D42138A0D27463A47DDBA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Delegation of authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may delegate the authority under subsection (b) only to an official appointed by the President by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H15E7C670875D43E1B858D7C8ABA74811"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Procedures for delivery of defense articles</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall establish expedited procedures for the delivery of any defense article loaned or leased to the Government of Taiwan under subsection (b) to ensure the timely delivery of the defense article to such Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="H67B1867474654C3C9CA7CF054DD8330E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report on determination of defense needs of Taiwan</header><paragraph id="H5A3D93A4C22741C6983B97BEBD16EEBC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in collaboration with the Commander of the United States Indo-Pacific Command, shall submit to Congress a report on the potential loan and lease of defense articles to the Government of Taiwan under subsection (b). Such report shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3ADDCEFCFA4B4B11B41C5D5132ACA6D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An initial assessment of the defense articles that are appropriate for such loan or lease.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7400449CAD964F31ABB057DAB25DE2BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An assessment of any supply chain or other logistical challenges associated with the loan or lease of defense articles identified pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC70294813FE0419B9CFF8A200B08F246"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion of expected timeframes for the provision to the Government of Taiwan of defense articles identified pursuant to subparagraph (A), including—</text><clause id="HC4686E8AAFE248518CFDF1AC2BF9A030"><enum>(i)</enum><text>expected timelines for the delivery of such defense articles; and</text></clause><clause id="HCA248AE0889346BABB2F80A0CBF620C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expected timelines for the full integration of such defense articles by the military of Taiwan, such that the military of Taiwan is able to effectively use defense articles so delivered in the event of a conflict with the People’s Republic of China.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A84BC26605D489A9F9AAD5FED6C8629"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary may consider appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8CD4058DCF84D81B784B41B426F7467"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC7083E61AEBD44009B23E00B71188993" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <quote>defense article</quote>, <quote>defense service</quote>, and <quote>design and construction services</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 47 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2794">22 U.S.C. 2794</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

