<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD96A106956324F6AB0339A75CFF12BFE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6788 IH: Mandating Advisable and Informed Locations and Solutions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6788</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000469">Mr. Fulcher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001148">Mr. Simpson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve communication between the United States Postal Service and local communities relating to the relocation and establishment of Postal Service retail service facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H10F459DD0A2D47928478CB0ED01CD913" style="OLC"><section id="HDDF1C187B826492CBA8A65B9B49E3880" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mandating Advisable and Informed Locations and Solutions Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MAILS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3C2B1014D216405E88D45D92BA49E08A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HE970B65BA97441A29530E74C50E376A8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Post office</header><text>The term <term>post office</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H519CE00BA4A44815A811712F5E747233"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a facility that—</text><clause id="HAA81C4AB43F14A339B3147CD6E36D3EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is owned or leased by the Postal Service;</text></clause><clause id="H0D3C5E698AD541B688147DEC1EB9F048"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is managed by a Postmaster; </text></clause><clause id="H9E649C27BF8B44DCBEA5305EB62AB52C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has responsibility for—</text><subclause id="H828BF0967F1C4C5A8C819128C41A5996"><enum>(I)</enum><text>customer services;</text></subclause><subclause id="H731ED8919BB1499182432D4126EDC1D2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>local delivery; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE1985D7563DB41EC9BAFB2C793BE4EC2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>receipt and dispatch of all classes of mail; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H22CD092690024CDDBA784683E5423297"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>may have responsibility for processing and distribution of mail for other such facilities in the surrounding geographic area; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE153C30AAD3D4027AA8F3738F215D793"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a remotely managed post office, a part-time post office, and an administrative post office. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F4B13B7FBFC4D18907A86A179352F6C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Postal service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Postal Service</term> means the United States Postal Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7CEDE05301B4C7799AC827ED7657965"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Temporary relocation</header><text>The term <term>temporary relocation</term> means a temporary relocation of retail services from a post office to support Postal Service business for a holiday, special event, or overflow business, as described in paragraph (a)(2)(i) of section 241.4 of title 39, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H2E52B22EE06D4670A36F7A8BC19B084C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requests for new post offices</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Postal Service shall establish by regulation a formal process for a local government official to request a new post office within the locality.</text></section><section id="HD0D4A5692BAE4DEF8E0E61BA4B8D8AC4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Communication relating to post office relocation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Postal Service shall amend section 241.4 of title 39, Code of Federal Regulations, to provide the following:</text><paragraph id="HD8CDD2BB67DE4A929E137284B995ADB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service may not implement a temporary relocation, including for a commemorative event, for a period longer than 2 days without collecting and considering community input under paragraph (c) of that section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H721D927E30734BFC9FC605D87CDCDB9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification</header><subparagraph id="HCCC92E94ED2D44A4ABF7983C1B36FD6E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Elected officials</header><text>Not later than 30 days before the date of a temporary relocation, the Postal Service shall—</text><clause id="H748BE42C57914F72BB9050B50699845A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit to 1 or more local elected officials in the area in which the affected post office is located a written outline of the proposal; and </text></clause><clause id="H326CFDA689DD4C7180ED3E05AB205E57"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>offer to discuss the proposal with the elected official under paragraph (c) of that section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD32A1EC796524E75863D91B4C6BFB4B9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public presentation</header><text>The Postal Service shall—</text><clause id="H2D6C77D38B0E46609193B2EE0D617617"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not later than 15 days before the date of a temporary relocation, provide public notice of the temporary relocation in the area in which the affected post office is located; and</text></clause><clause id="H4F68FFCA28634F598DEBF9832CC4B766"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 15 days after providing notice to local elected officials under subparagraph (A)(i), hold a public presentation under paragraph (c) of that section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BB7F4C194024071A5B8CFA0491DADED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Periodic updates</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the end of the initial 30-day comment period under paragraph (c) of that section, and every 60 days thereafter until the date that is 60 days after the last day of a temporary relocation, the Postal Service shall submit to relevant local government officials updates on the status of the temporary relocation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0EC0FCD7E227479585C77050095B1839"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><subsection id="H88C52BEFC04B4063BB5694662FD148BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any temporary relocation for a period that is longer than 180 days (whether due to the originally projected length of the relocation or due to an extension), not later than 30 days after the first day of the temporary relocation (or of the extension that caused the length of the relocation to exceed 180 days, if applicable), the Postal Service shall submit a report relating to the temporary relocation or extension to—</text><paragraph id="H4A4184CECA324385B685337D7C96315E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="SSGA00">Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22D1738BC8BB42088F99F94E854241F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0FCA2D2C96E4B0D8AFE76E9584527C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the members of Congress who represent the congressional district or State in which the affected post office is located.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA099C0FD7AD3450DA3FF0960A2EE66BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report described in subsection (a) shall include a discussion of—</text><paragraph id="H3E37C48121EE4EB0AED909CE344BBE86"><enum>(1)</enum><text>whether the communication requirements were met within the required timelines, and if not, an explanation for the failure to comply with the requirements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D755B4C0F61463B8559DD49F619E848"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether the period of the temporary relocation is being extended, and if so, an explanation for the extension.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

