<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1CE70E82DED84FC98BFEF72D02A6F587" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5625 IH: Fentanyl Awareness for Children and Teens in Schools Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5625</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish education partnership programs between public schools and public health agencies to prevent the misuse and overdose of synthetic opioids by youth, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF22EB1BB261D4C629CA4002A7EE98979" style="OLC"><section id="H9E15A7F1771C430CAD6957DDD110CCC1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H9A7DE3597EEF4BD3B29A94083A9CA5E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fentanyl Awareness for Children and Teens in Schools Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FACTS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D7A3C6FD822454AA9E448897A9EEF3D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H9E15A7F1771C430CAD6957DDD110CCC1" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC314E5AF30C64C819ECBCB327EF5FD3E" level="section">Sec. 2. Purposes.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H15776F545F4B48A98B0DD6308A4E9EB2" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5683F5A4E156497C9E5E1A029B50C208" level="title">Title I—Partnership grants for local and State educational agencies</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9894FBE243F440189E0948DC3146F124" level="section">Sec. 101. Synthetic opioid misuse and overdose education, awareness, and prevention pilot program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDBB79B4AC6F04E08B9152FEDA65CBB4D" level="section">Sec. 102. Authorization of appropriations; reservation.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCDC1DC2E99414EDCA5105DF8BCF94A84" level="title">Title II—Establishment of an interagency task force</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H95D63A8036F641EB8C95774445ECF824" level="section">Sec. 201. Interagency Task Force on Preventing Synthetic Opioid Misuse and Overdose Among Youth.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7D82A39675D44E7085469A9E7F39758F" level="section">Sec. 202. Rule of construction.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H40347220520446C78FE1D8CAEA79E8B1" level="title">Title III—Amendments to the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H648EB46687A144F79B6A42E9886607E6" level="section">Sec. 301. Professional development for school personnel.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8879E83722A4AD78B0F6A58EB5CD809" level="section">Sec. 302. Amendments to local educational agency plans.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8CAE2CE29821453DAB5400C9D8D1394C" level="section">Sec. 303. Amendments to State educational agency plans.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4E24160C2B6142F98E1F99896F6A9C6A" level="title">Title IV—Amendments to Department of Education data collection</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H33220E3A1F4242F099F8B5ABBC6F3CC4" level="section">Sec. 401. Civil rights data collection on access to synthetic opioids.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA93F8AB3E8784C669A15008E2DF7795E" level="section">Sec. 402. National Center for Education Statistics School Crime and Safety Data.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCD8A317466BF416E9E9A2879993D4CF2" level="title">Title V—School-based health centers and reporting</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFDD0093DA4C143E9A394306395C2FD82" level="section">Sec. 501. Naloxone in school-based health centers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H31B977D60559415A9E0AB2A9B793006A" level="section">Sec. 502. Amendments to the Monitoring the Future survey.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7610175EEE9B4905A67CA5492A0D2E95" level="section">Sec. 503. Youth Risk Behavior Survey.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE5D108CAF93944EC897DC823A853A281" level="section">Sec. 504. Evaluation of the effectiveness and reach of the State Unintentional Drug Overdose Reporting System.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HC314E5AF30C64C819ECBCB327EF5FD3E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are to—</text><paragraph id="H980EE75805B641BABBE58E6771E380CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish education partnership programs between public schools and public health agencies to prevent the misuse of and overdose with synthetic opioids by youth;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D71865A4E9E49D4AE02E53F7246CA1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop a whole-of-government approach to identify and disseminate best practices in education and prevention regarding the misuse of and overdose with synthetic opioids by youth;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H851B522057E04A6E883316B9434EEAE9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>increase opportunities for employees of elementary and secondary schools receiving Federal funds to receive professional development on the dangers of the misuse of and overdose with synthetic opioids by youth; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9807917E12ED4752933B52BF72E6302D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>improve the availability and usability of data regarding the proliferation of synthetic opioids.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H15776F545F4B48A98B0DD6308A4E9EB2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H06BB82F1F83045F1A90F81D084C88BA0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Classified school employee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>classified school employee</term> means an employee of a State or of any political subdivision of a State, or an employee of a nonprofit organization, who works in any grade from prekindergarten through high school in any of the following occupational specialties:</text><subparagraph id="HFAD4E42CD846446FB233D73D7B81CB28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Paraprofessional, including paraeducator services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB575829F66E64581B8A5FC02ABBEFEA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Clerical and administrative services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04A3EB5634074C98A76479B85794D43B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Transportation services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3510DB3E386A46F4BF3B2D7791AE6BE9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Food and nutrition services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7BE0772CF864BF68A7015DAFA70E455"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Custodial and maintenance services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CC037237603477F80BBF565786C905A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Security services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF3B6E5AF16845389B2D83F91B418CD4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Health and student services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD571987284AE45499DD5B70B2B9B98E7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Technical services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA65052EA41E4042B8571A959D42CF9F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Skilled trades.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFFB469E1783444CAD01B9E1ACA76795"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Educational service agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>educational service agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 602 of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1401">20 U.S.C. 1401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C85D5921FE34C58B766121A005150B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>evidence-based</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>parent</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, <term>State</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0C4E7F989184FC9834EB609463A8CFC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term>, unless otherwise specified, refers to the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7ABAFD9F4894DDFB1FA146EA2C83A3C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Synthetic opioids</header><text>The term <term>synthetic opioids</term> means substances, including fentanyl and any substituted derivative of fentanyl, that—</text><subparagraph id="HB528074F18AB49CAAAA664C3C27854D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are synthesized in a laboratory; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D35166BE53D4FF882FABC939332DF65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>act on the same targets in the brain as natural opioids to produce analgesic effects.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><title id="H5683F5A4E156497C9E5E1A029B50C208"><enum>I</enum><header>Partnership grants for local and State educational agencies</header><section id="H9894FBE243F440189E0948DC3146F124"><enum>101.</enum><header>Synthetic opioid misuse and overdose education, awareness, and prevention pilot program</header><subsection id="HA0E60AB431494009B1217CC60D3D1147"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall administer a pilot program to eligible partnerships to provide financial assistance for the prevention of, treatment of, and recovery from, disorders stemming from the misuse of synthetic opioids by children, adolescents, and young adults.</text></subsection><subsection id="H667B9FF4E463408FAC8A89D04BC183D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA013148C44E74CF2AD41DDD3C0DBD4B7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible partnership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible partnership</term> means a partnership of—</text><subparagraph id="HD1DBB956D7284569B65529E802FBF964"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a local educational agency, a State educational agency, a Bureau of Indian Education school, an educational service agency, or a consortium of local educational agencies seeking to establish or expand a program to reduce the misuse of synthetic opioids and establish recovery programs or services for children, adolescents, and young adults; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF80113242BEA4234AF547E7AC70AB483"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State, local, territorial, or Tribal health agency or organization, a qualified nongovernmental entity with appropriate expertise in providing substance use disorder education, prevention, and treatment services or programs for children, adolescents, or young adults, as defined by the Secretary, or a consortium of entities that includes a State, local, territorial, or Tribal health agency or organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1385511B6C2B46C597FBD36A473ACAF2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recovery program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>recovery program</term> means a program—</text><subparagraph id="HE62F5B0608AA464EA616CFFB3582FBD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to help children, adolescents, or young adults who are recovering from substance use disorders to initiate, stabilize, and maintain healthy and productive lives in the community; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9304098CBB904B7C8DBA027EFBA0BBBA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that includes peer-to-peer support delivered by individuals with lived experience in recovery, and communal activities to build recovery skills and supportive social networks.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9B648D287F7C41DFB4E5E1518C9B4EF9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot program authorized</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall award 3-year grants, on a competitive basis, to up to 25 eligible partnerships to enable such partnerships to prevent the misuse of synthetic opioids by children, adolescents, and young adults.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF52AB75F65084BD5838EDEFFFBD921CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible partnership that receives a grant under this section shall use amounts made available through such grant for evidence-based activities, which may include any of the following:</text><paragraph id="HE481546A438A49429EF0F63F3758CEFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Developing evidence-based materials for teachers to use as a component of classroom instruction, and sharing these materials with parents and families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AC37E2FA82D4F979FDF5A01E57ADBAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Designing evidence-based professional development for teachers, school leaders, specialized instructional support personnel, classified school employees, and other school staff members.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DB42949CFCC4C39AC8F0F67C4BBB4AD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing in- and out-of-school workshops and accessible and tailored content for students, families, and teachers to attain information about the misuse of synthetic opioids.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41AC3F1096734C539A56D0A96635B1E9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Creating efficient and effective multimedia communication campaigns, including through social media, to maximize outreach efforts to students, parents, and families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB86A8AF8F4B4246990B5A630DAB2DF9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Awarding contracts to nonprofit organizations—</text><subparagraph id="HD871E6835F5D48748B1147A7ACDA0B45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>specializing in substance misuse prevention education efforts; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD539BFAD4F57494D96EE0AB538549D33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with demonstrated success in reaching, engaging, and supporting local and State educational agencies, Bureau of Indian Education schools, and other schools; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A33ECEAFA7B4AD3989A6BEDF24DADA9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with expertise in designing recovery programs for synthetic opioid misuse and overdose prevention.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H490B6700B55044C7B34B542812B11E97"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Establishing peer-to-peer counseling programs for students at secondary schools to support the work of school-based mental health professionals in preventing the misuse of synthetic opioids.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A810BC10C1845C389F5706F30C3A7F3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Other purposes as may be specified by the Secretary</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H253103DD0FB94B40807CBE461EA5FC83"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applications and assurances</header><text>To seek a grant under this section, an eligible partnership shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, which shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HB2FD69BE405B4233A92CAA12A38EF735"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description, containing qualitative and quantitative information, of the existing need for such a grant in the area proposed to be served through the grant, which description may include information on—</text><subparagraph id="H4AB75AC1F78B41BCB226201F08F930B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the rate of misuse of and overdoses attributable to synthetic opioids among children, adolescents, and young adults under the age of 21;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7A986ACD572415CAD1518D6E8AFF0D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if available, data indicating the trend of synthetic opioid misuse and overdoses among children, adolescents, and young adults under the age of 21 over the past 5 years; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B8B50506BE945CBB1ECF832CFC37EF5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the availability of synthetic opioids.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H82152CDE48AB4115A4B3A7E0EA5C6AA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the initiatives, activities, or programs the eligible partnership will fund through the grant, including how such initiatives, activities, or programs will reduce the misuse of and overdoses attributable to synthetic opioids in the area proposed to be served through the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBD16FBD872B4BFCA47C2733DF1F5CD6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of how the eligible partnership will establish a local interagency agreement to ensure adequate and effective collaboration among entities in the partnership to carry out the initiatives, activities, or programs described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCBAB0384F8A462A858EF45BAF041FB6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of how the initiatives, activities, or programs described in paragraph (2) will be linguistically appropriate and culturally responsive for students and families served by the eligible partnership.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF7D755D36F544398A57E1638EDDED96"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of how the initiatives, activities, or programs described in paragraph (2) will support students and families served by the eligible partnership in reversing individual and community-wide effects of synthetic opioid misuse and overdoses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF27086A914E4A62A09E0EBE7AC75453"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An assurance that—</text><subparagraph id="H9E8AD985D9D84E7E90D9B09A72C6206F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>persons providing services through the grant awarded to the eligible partnership will be adequately trained to provide such services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52BD2D7536114F3DA58483735E3962BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">teachers, school leaders, administrators, specialized instructional support personnel, representatives of local Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations as appropriate, other school personnel, and parents or guardians of students participating in services funded through a grant under this section will be engaged in the design and implementation of the initiatives, activities, or programs described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H83CF74D1CDDB4E23B620E35A7EEF63C3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A description of how the eligible partnership will support and integrate existing school, local educational agency, and State initiatives, activities, or programs with the initiatives, activities, or programs described in paragraph (2) to provide synthetic opioid misuse and overdose prevention services for students, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4D1592AA06BD495D8A5D7151A32EEE35"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that have a higher rate of youth illicit drug use, including the use of fentanyl and other synthetic opioids.</text></subsection><subsection id="H485C91E3D9EF435F9ECC6E5E1C75DA2F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Distribution of awards</header><text>Subject to subsection (f), the Secretary shall ensure that grants awarded under this section are equitably distributed among the geographical regions of the United States and among Tribal, urban, suburban, and rural populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H162D0A70A0374083A2736ED062ED368A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any services provided through initiatives, activities, or programs carried out under this section shall supplement, not supplant, existing services to prevent the misuse by students of, and overdoses of students attributable to, synthetic opioids.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7E7B6DFFD8484A2D9D59CAEF18490490"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Accountability</header><paragraph id="H1902E855D6E14700A26C3090C49721F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text>In accordance with section 102(b), the Secretary shall regularly review the initiatives, activities, or programs of eligible partnerships receiving a grant under this section to ensure that such partnerships are using the grant for the purposes for which it was provided.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4BF274B8A934BF5B632BD10C2468F52"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification of reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the Secretary awards grants for the first year of the program under this section, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H47DB52CA7A964683B4BB97810C1B5DE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require eligible partnerships receiving a grant under this section to submit reports, on an annual basis, detailing the initiatives, activities, or programs funded through such grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9491AA61DCE146598F1078FAC9BD4C71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>notify such eligible partnerships of such reporting requirement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7C96E393B8F4C3A9FD2AB5CCA3D0A37"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timeline of reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible partnership receiving a grant under this section shall submit the first report described in paragraph (2) to the Secretary not later than one year after receiving a grant under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82737C6E3C794044959E47FC810AD954"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Content of reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report required under paragraph (2) shall include, at minimum, the following information:</text><subparagraph id="HC2F5DD4A727A482EB45ED13AB059305C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effectiveness of the grant awarded under this section in reducing synthetic opioid misuse and overdose among the students served by the eligible partnership.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15900C253C9E4C7E956C6C302275667C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Details regarding the initiatives, activities, or programs funded through the grant and further details about any subgrants awarded by the eligible partnership to help carry out planned initiatives, activities, or programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA83D4E7D52E409B8E95724FAF636691"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, narrative statements from teachers, school leaders, specialized instructional support personnel, or other relevant stakeholders describing the process of implementing the initiatives, activities, or programs developed through the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9404DEED2E849A5A6EE8D1980A3E1EB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If applicable, any challenges faced by the eligible partnership in reaching or engaging parents, students, teachers, school leaders, specialized instructional support personnel, and other relevant stakeholders with the initiatives, activities, or programs developed through the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD74849F9E0A4E0FBDC629EC1445ABF0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H25CF23B9035C4737B6369FB3A64BA86B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Submission of reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after receiving reports from eligible partnerships receiving a grant under this section, the Secretary shall submit such reports and a brief overview of the data and outcomes described in such reports to the Committees on Education and the Workforce and Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4358F8B873664FE9A7B66AFF9EAD5A22"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Publication of programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible partnership receiving a grant under this section shall—</text><paragraph id="H2A78E389F84B4CF6B9C423DE42EF9405"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">post on the eligible partnership’s website the initiatives, activities, and programs supported through the grant; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47C0278920884600B61784D8613515D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disseminate to families served by the eligible partnership, in widely accessible formats, content from and information about such initiatives, activities, and programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAB13D0C497CC42BE8D7E7E6BB65F734D"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Sharing of best practices</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HFE1C90F798B7457B98536C5FCE4FD5E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collect content from and information about all initiatives, activities, and programs developed by each eligible partnerships through a grant under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38B38AF5B3F34782AB099D746ADFB9BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in conjunction with the Secretary of Education, make such content and information publicly available and widely accessible.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDBB79B4AC6F04E08B9152FEDA65CBB4D"><enum>102.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations; reservation</header><subsection id="H77F586A15CFB42728906DBD6B8D30E7D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 101 $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></subsection><subsection id="H72FC717641EA49EA9EFD5BED65BEE2FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservation for evaluation and technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may reserve not more than 3 percent of the funds appropriated under subsection (a) for any fiscal year to—</text><paragraph id="HE45A6D6E856C48CC839E48BE5EBA3019"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a rigorous, independent evaluation of the initiatives, activities, or programs funded under section 101;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70AAF8FD2EC547CABC815279C3E1E867"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide technical assistance and share best practices with respect to initiatives, activities, or programs that are developed by eligible partnerships through grants under section 101; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DBC093BF6D94685A1CCF17C7270F276"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide technical assistance to eligible partnerships applying for a grant under section 101, through the use of webinars, direct emails, mailed outreach, and other strategies designed to reach underserved eligible partnerships, including eligible partnerships located in rural and remote areas.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HCDC1DC2E99414EDCA5105DF8BCF94A84"><enum>II</enum><header>Establishment of an interagency task force</header><section id="H95D63A8036F641EB8C95774445ECF824"><enum>201.</enum><header>Interagency Task Force on Preventing Synthetic Opioid Misuse and Overdose Among Youth</header><subsection id="HEBFF76AEB28140A989F0DCB3FC152D29"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a task force, to be known as the Interagency Task Force on Preventing Opioid Misuse and Overdose Among Youth (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) to identify, evaluate, and make recommendations to coordinate and improve Federal responses to synthetic opioid overdose and misuse in youth.</text></subsection><subsection id="H10A40C1ECE2E4B03A04A9F6E250F6A36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The membership of the Task Force shall include—</text><paragraph id="H050A5DECDADB4B0FBA8B744799186C4E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the officials serving under paragraphs (1) through (9) of subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H542B5BB8FAC044A4B530A5076C55BA4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the members serving under paragraphs (10), (11), and (12) of subsection (c), to be appointed by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B1A24B9EC5D48B78FDDDDE042E03CE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Task Force shall be composed of at least 12, but not more than 17, members as follows:</text><paragraph id="H57F245A54AFB4D72AFF23892773908DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, who shall serve as Chair of the Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCA19F6C16CD43E2A4A343A786E086D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD025DF2C5E9A4FA7A1313FA1C6264251"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD97CEA890278464691BB87ED455F9272"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary for Children and Families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9184E64FE55B43B4BE749CDFCA3C8585"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E0594C8DDD54E248BE78C2AE0ACEC6E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary for Elementary and Secondary Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7223AAEA9EE14BFB94B06A03AD206410"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Agency for Health Research and Quality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H256AFAF6AB1847A8B20FD6DE73F154A5"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Surgeon General of the Public Health Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3D0A0D1B7094F4C81B8F5F60024F879"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Mental Health of the National Institutes of Health.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AE57E8A7C3E4E6C9EC0B0BFAC9EF3A9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>At least two, and not more than three, non-Federal representatives who are parents of youth who died from an overdose of fentanyl or another synthetic opioid.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H901679DE6B364F95A8CF0B57BCB90127"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least one, and not more than two, non-Federal representatives of one or more nationally recognized nonprofit organizations working to raise awareness about and prevent misuse of synthetic opioids by youth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BBA898B176E4D9F9C58F35481BC2B0D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Such other Federal or non-Federal representatives as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63B54E9F461A4F7382E9B4A7E64A2BCB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Task Force shall—</text><paragraph id="HCA07E2491595416088FDBBE29D147B9B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and regularly update a report that identifies, analyzes, and evaluates the state of Federal, State, and local programs to address synthetic opioid misuse and overdose in youth, and identifies best practices including—</text><subparagraph id="H87B70A27FC124FA5AE7B51FC9587E0C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a set of evidence-based, evidence-informed, and promising practices with respect to—</text><clause id="H9AFA921765D0400E950343EF1704E682"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prevention strategies for youth at risk of fentanyl and synthetic opioids misuse and overdose;</text></clause><clause id="H7B860C5F60C04222A6D43359550B7C7E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the identification, screening, diagnosis, intervention, and treatment of youth affected by synthetic opioid misuse;</text></clause><clause id="H86F28DE612CA47CA9140E02AF3F0C284"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the expeditious referral to, and implementation of, practices and supports that prevent and mitigate the effects of synthetic opioid misuse and overdose in youth; and</text></clause><clause id="H1235ABAEB6EF410DB0C3913E811B107D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>community-based or multigenerational practices that support youth and families affected by synthetic opioid misuse and overdose; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H239EAA481AA541BEAABC4C38F9981609"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal and State programs and activities to prevent, screen, diagnose, intervene, and treat synthetic opioid misuse and overdose in youth; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F0A6D37C731467ABED0861E0F77A630"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and regularly update a national strategy for—</text><subparagraph id="H8705AE2DD1A24DD096B5051793688375"><enum>(A)</enum><text>youth synthetic opioid misuse and overdose prevention, taking into consideration the findings of the reports under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4A620BD627648BBAD9B40720E967086"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the Task Force and Federal departments and agencies represented on the Task Force will prioritize options for, and implement a coordinated approach to, addressing synthetic opioid misuse and overdose.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7D82A39675D44E7085469A9E7F39758F"><enum>202.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this title shall be construed to limit or otherwise alter the authority of any of the Federal agencies referred to in section 201(c) to carry out programs to reduce synthetic opioid overdose and misuse under other provisions of law.</text></section></title><title id="H40347220520446C78FE1D8CAEA79E8B1"><enum>III</enum><header>Amendments to the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</header><section id="H648EB46687A144F79B6A42E9886607E6"><enum>301.</enum><header>Professional development for school personnel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2101(c)(4)(B) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6611">20 U.S.C. 6611(c)(4)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF6D9FC44268947E285E76617D73E1E99"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (xvi) through (xxi) as clauses (xvii) through (xxii), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14FD682E4F14DA982F6FF124D93700E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (xv) the following:</text><quoted-block id="HB10D27C6547D40F5A9F9AE5AAD615E08" style="OLC"><clause id="HB5CFD6E30EFA4D918A14DFFA38F2B45C"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>Providing training for all school personnel, including teachers, principals, other school leaders, specialized instructional support personnel, paraprofessionals, counselors, and mental health professionals, regarding how to address and prevent the misuse of synthetic opioids, including fentanyl or any substituted derivative of fentanyl, among students.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HC8879E83722A4AD78B0F6A58EB5CD809"><enum>302.</enum><header>Amendments to local educational agency plans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1112(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6312">20 U.S.C. 6312(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7296A578C3FA4F38A4C132DF2C929329"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (12)(B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEB7748D1FD2483089C9EF0A1211AB0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (13) as paragraph (14); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F01C9784CF049889FAC7185A08AF4D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (12) the following:</text><quoted-block id="HF6EAAF02192B46CCB30C28637F197B7E" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H929B59991B204E9DA349F54EC9117F8F"><enum>(13)</enum><text>how the local educational agency will engage teachers and school leaders, in consultation with parents, local educational agency administrators, public health officials, paraprofessionals, specialized instructional support personnel, school counselors, and school psychologists, to address and prevent the misuse of synthetic opioids, including fentanyl or any substituted derivative of fentanyl, among students; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H8CAE2CE29821453DAB5400C9D8D1394C"><enum>303.</enum><header>Amendments to State educational agency plans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1111(g)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(g)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HFCFD9CBDD70548DBADFE7D603F5F9B2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03B088E78BD3412497ADDE68E18AD860"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subparagraph (G) as subparagraph (H); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E271A4CD857465CBB124E8BB6867758"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subparagraph (F) the following:</text><quoted-block id="HF89BF7889BF24B4396F9F16F716FB6E3" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HEB3AC105DFC2410CBB78A44616662C85"><enum>(G)</enum><text>how the State educational agency will provide support to local educational agencies receiving assistance under this part in addressing and preventing the misuse of synthetic opioids, including fentanyl or any substituted derivative of fentanyl, among students; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title><title id="H4E24160C2B6142F98E1F99896F6A9C6A"><enum>IV</enum><header>Amendments to Department of Education data collection</header><section id="H33220E3A1F4242F099F8B5ABBC6F3CC4"><enum>401.</enum><header>Civil rights data collection on access to synthetic opioids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For each Civil Rights Data Collection (or any successor to such data collection) required under section 203(c)(1) of the Department of Education Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3413">20 U.S.C. 3413(c)(1)</external-xref>) that is carried out on or after January 1, 2024, the Assistant Secretary for Civil Rights of the Department of Education shall include collection of data on the—</text><paragraph id="HD85B076583BB460986E690A24EAF1ADB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prevalence of fentanyl and other synthetic opioids in secondary schools receiving Federal financial assistance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE25A70D782A84F9FA97DC71D1192184C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>suspensions, expulsions, and arrests of students resulting from the use or possession of fentanyl and other synthetic opioids in secondary schools receiving Federal financial assistance.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA93F8AB3E8784C669A15008E2DF7795E"><enum>402.</enum><header>National Center for Education Statistics School Crime and Safety Data</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 153(a)(1)(H) of the Education Sciences Reform Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9543">20 U.S.C. 9543(a)(1)(H)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4296E4D719F74AF8A135CFB3A582D619"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40815F05E76647EDA027D46FC0DB21DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>and</quote> at the end; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34FE92035680473ABE3D2D5B64792F4A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H986D817FA1D147A283FA841D0F04BE36" style="OLC"><clause id="H8001EAD279134E12B6E2656597E4B1F8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>access to synthetic opioids, including fentanyl, on school premises, and the effects of such substances on school safety and student health and well-being;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title><title id="HCD8A317466BF416E9E9A2879993D4CF2"><enum>V</enum><header>School-based health centers and reporting</header><section id="HFDD0093DA4C143E9A394306395C2FD82"><enum>501.</enum><header>Naloxone in school-based health centers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 399Z–1(f)(1)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280h-5">42 U.S.C. 280h–5(f)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF9CBAB70BC8245CFBCA4A96AAE3D5C8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end and inserting <quote>or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9332AA05929E4DE9B396E8DBF90A753A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HA1EE35D35E024C72A1FF3794B54E25EF" style="OLC"><clause id="H1EF0D9A94B2C4DDC950AB7A76D93E926"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the purchase of naloxone to reverse the effects of opioid overdose, and the establishment of other programs to address and prevent the misuse of synthetic opioids, including fentanyl or any substituted derivative of fentanyl; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H31B977D60559415A9E0AB2A9B793006A"><enum>502.</enum><header>Amendments to the Monitoring the Future survey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning on January 1, 2024, the Director of the National Institute on Drug Abuse, in collaboration with the Secretary and the Director of the National Institutes of Health, shall require the survey funded by the National Institute on Drug Abuse and titled <quote>Monitoring the Future</quote> to include—</text><paragraph id="H3E4E03B3B43A463595A9AFAD5D556ECC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>indicators to measure the use of, perception of harm of, and access to counterfeit or synthetic opioids among youth; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H948F350CB77F490C9BFB1D0975A1EA33"><enum>(2)</enum><text>where applicable, indicators to measure the extent to which respondents are aware of the counterfeit or synthetic nature of any opioids used or encountered by such respondents.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7610175EEE9B4905A67CA5492A0D2E95"><enum>503.</enum><header>Youth Risk Behavior Survey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning on January 1, 2024, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall require the data collection survey for the Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System to include—</text><paragraph id="HDFDB6A2528824DE9A60C9B886DD46E09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>questions related to the use of, awareness regarding, and exposure to counterfeit or synthetic opioids, including fentanyl; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H279A047FB0C24C06BBD3C7CF4F736FB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">where applicable, indicators to measure the extent to which respondents are aware of the counterfeit or synthetic nature of any opioids used or encountered by such respondents.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE5D108CAF93944EC897DC823A853A281"><enum>504.</enum><header>Evaluation of the effectiveness and reach of the State Unintentional Drug Overdose Reporting System</header><subsection id="H9C7A2208747D4E008C82090370DE967C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Beginning on or after January 1, 2024, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall conduct an evaluation determining the effectiveness of the State Unintentional Drug Overdose Reporting System in collecting and reporting data regarding—</text><paragraph id="H59FE8A2BE41447CEBAB6922B0EED6725"><enum>(1)</enum><text>specific synthetic opioids causing or contributing to overdose and death among children, adolescents, and young adults; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC79C191351AD47CFB877B550B4FB3AB1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which children, adolescents, and young adults are aware of the counterfeit or synthetic nature of any opioids used or encountered by such children, adolescents, and young adults.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H83BDCAC5790C4339BC60A87A52B6BEE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after concluding such evaluation, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall develop and submit to the Committees on Energy and Commerce and Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate the findings of the evaluation and, if applicable, recommendations to improve the quality and availability of data described in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H34ED746BD52A45DBAEC08DA890D36891"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $250,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

