<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H708D6CCDDA6F421CB955E0B6AC2C9189" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1482 IH: NOAA Weather Radio Modernization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1482</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide guidance for and investment in the upgrade and modernization of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Weather Radio All Hazards network, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEDD1D8AD688147089F2EDAB5C0F1D0D9" style="OLC"><section id="H9699D690CE874423900B5CD456D9306C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>NOAA Weather Radio Modernization Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>NWR Modernization Act of 2023</short-title></quote> .</text></section><section id="HC47AFF2B4C424551AA5A5EAF9B4D250F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H048C6D9CA17044D3B928A2B94A47331F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere and the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8C0F22AA779459B9C1E18BF20F055FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>NOAA Weather Radio</header><text>The term <quote>NOAA Weather Radio</quote> means the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Weather Radio All Hazards network.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7EC9943578724EC5AB5FFCD6DC20B8FA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H28758DBAA7BC4646B781EB5A85F14DFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The NOAA Weather Radio is a nationwide network of transmitters that are critical to protecting life and property by broadcasting weather and other hazard alerts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA4754D701AB49B8A3DCD01BF0A4DB8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>NOAA Weather Radio broadcasts currently reach 95 percent of the United States population.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA261AACA780A45DE8B86E304118CC8B1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>NOAA Weather Radio broadcasts originate from all National Weather Service Offices, but are only available via a receiver located in sufficient proximity to a radio transmitting tower.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B950E6A8FF14148BD8B1414314461BD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>There are limited options to obtain NOAA Weather Radio broadcasts via the Internet or mobile device application, which are provided by volunteer mechanisms obtaining the audio feed in an ad hoc manner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0D610BAE4FA453E8D749035F47B77B4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>NOAA Weather Radio should provide equal access and availability to unimpeded broadcasts of weather and non-weather hazards to every person located within the United States, its territories, and Tribal lands.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA7976BC4D10147468765A9200292AC12"><enum>4.</enum><header>Upgrading existing systems</header><subsection id="H65D7A1FBA77647B6B5A4B56F0BAB9063"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall, to the maximum extent practicable, expand coverage of the NOAA Weather Radio and ensure its reliability. In carrying out this subsection, the Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="H965966971931495CB0EDE0CBB5F5D4D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>maintain support for existing systems serving areas not covered by or having poor quality cellular service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D993417473A4029AAE7E1504809D0FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure consistent maintenance and operations monitoring, with timely repairs to broadcast transmitter site equipment and antennas; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8191ECADE05A4DCD841AEF4E9041CBAE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enhance the ability to amplify Non-Weather Emergency Messages via NOAA Weather Radio as necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB4586C6B34FA4C5080017EDFD723237E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expanding access</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Administrator shall acquire additional transmitters as required to expand coverage to rural and underserved communities, national parks, and recreation areas.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1C761AD5B7FA4A2A8CB5D55C98DDBC5A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Modernization initiative</header><subsection id="H53040E2C5F7A4B9A9567338D10CD9728" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In parallel to the activities under section 4, the Administrator shall, to the maximum extent practicable, enhance NOAA Weather Radio to ensure its capabilities and coverage remain valuable to the public. In carrying out this section, the Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="H76B355FBEF5C40CDBA6ACB7CCC80F4AC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>upgrade telecommunications infrastructure to accelerate the transition of broadcasts to internet protocol-based communications over noncopper media;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2A197C43639490BA76D51585BF497F4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>accelerate software upgrades to the Advanced Weather Interactive Processing System, or the relevant system successors, to implement partial county notifications and alerts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D3DB29D6C2B43248ABC9BA9DB7C9162" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>consult with relevant stakeholders, including the private sector, to enhance accessibility and usability of NOAA Weather Radio data and feeds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H248967FEBA2144CC8E76BD81534ACF19" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop options, including satellite backup capability and commercial provider partnerships, for NOAA Weather Radio continuity in the event of Weather Forecast Office outages;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A52F55E3C9F40C29F59B374AA12BD5A" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>research and develop alternative options, including microwave capabilities, to transmit NOAA Weather Radio signals to transmitters that are remote or do not have internet protocol capability; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFBB37F93EAC427BBB06B4F4AD409438" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>transition critical applications to the Integrated Dissemination Program, or the relevant program successors.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F12449BDE0443C4B1323E491A8B350A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Administrator shall prioritize practices, capabilities, and technologies recommended in accordance with the assessment under subsection (c) to maximize accessibility, particularly in remote and underserved areas of the country.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5040D07FFEFD4BD698EC177541270900"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment for management and distribution</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall complete an assessment of access to NOAA Weather Radio. In conducting such assessment, the Administrator shall take into consideration and provide recommendations on the following:</text><paragraph id="HE76845BA64254601BBA6C7C22A4DD59B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The need for continuous, adequate, and operational real-time broadcasts of the NOAA Weather Radio in both urban and rural areas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81C07584527E461A8D3FBB17DC766636"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Solicited inputs from relevant stakeholders on the compatibility of NOAA Weather Radio data for third party platforms that provide online services, such as websites and mobile device applications, or deliver NOAA Weather Radio access.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED8F8CE6152F48FAA072B118BECD94A8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Existing or new management systems that promote consistent, efficient, and compatible access to NOAA Weather Radio.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EB0EFDF57184B5180D2C45AD2809F72"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The ability of NOAA to aggregate real time broadcast feeds at one or more central locations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB36B24BBFE5744268F6D5008BC0466E7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Effective interagency coordination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H055D6FFEC6D64E1DBCB93149C211B2B7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The potential effects of an electromagnetic pulse or geomagnetic disturbance on NOAA Weather Radio.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1704A079F26244B7A10D03ABDEB67CC1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other function the Administrator determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

