<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC70C406A70204703A08765CE856672B9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3762 IH: Emergency Vacating of Aircraft Cabin Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3762</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Aviation Administration to establish evacuation standards for transport category airplanes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4691DF3C061148B6984850CF319D63C7" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H90226420F1AC4EA5ACBFB6B0B80825C5"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emergency Vacating of Aircraft Cabin Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFF0D11A575C843449A25B04A5F2CB31D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Evacuation standards for transport category airplanes</header><subsection id="H5C500997DBD740C3AC346108E92EEF7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall issue a final rule establishing evacuation standards for transport category airplanes, as described in part 25 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H71DEE041C1BC413DA23C59BA95720AC7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Considerations</header><paragraph id="HAB1B783F9D1942D78CED178C3D296411"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In issuing the final rule under subsection (a), the Administrator shall consider factors that include—</text><subparagraph id="HD4C6E4AFF7434D26BDA3DE4844542CC5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the ability of passengers of different ages (including infants, children, and senior citizens) to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA053E0043EAA438CB744D64EF6A636A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the ability of passengers of different heights and weights to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3456A77F991483191767E3C92DA2A2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the ability of passengers with disabilities to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56C2B30B038F4FA0AFC2DA53044D3F88"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the ability of passengers who cannot speak, have difficulty speaking, use synthetic speech, or are non-vocal or non-verbal to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D92791C0A5F4CC6977A0EEDF393B390"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the ability of passengers who do not speak English to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H693A4BBAD3934FDEA1BCF7CD79494F06"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the impact of the presence of carry-on luggage or personal items (such as a purse, briefcase, laptop, or backpack) on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56FD718D4B3947CB82DE1E01C2454AA5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the impact of seat size, seat pitch, and aisle width on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F286F1481D54673849197A9A1A5182E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the impact of seats and other obstacles in the pathway to the exit opening from the nearest aisle on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E4BD27866B94339A4ECB9F3352EAFF1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with respect to aircraft with parallel longitudinal aisles, the impact of seat pods or other seating configurations that block access between such aisles within a cabin on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3D85E344BB024FD0858512182945100D"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the impact of passenger load (the number of passengers relative to the number of seats on board) on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H046FDD2CDE7740248A82D9615680E9F1"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the impact of service animals (as defined in sections 35.104 and 36.104 of title 28, Code of Federal Regulations) on the ability of passengers (including such service animals and their handlers) to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H861558E3663D440DA7F40408E74FE4CB"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of smoke, darkness, or other factors that diminish visibility in the aircraft cabin on the ability of passengers to safely and efficiently evacuate a transport category airplane; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05856A0124D0428B875B68F02A5DD716"><enum>(M)</enum><text>any other factor determined appropriate by the Administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE789ACED2DF24F1DA909BA92E9A045B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Passengers with disabilities defined</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>passengers with disabilities</term>—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92E4B1C636EC43F2B06960014DD7727D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any qualified individual with a disability, as defined in section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1E4B2C085FB42CC90E5E9DC543D937B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any passengers—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H073A1CF98A0D40369D1232F931787ECB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with a physical impairment, such as passengers who are blind, deaf, nonambulatory, have limited mobility, or require a wheelchair, walker, cane, brace, prosthetic, or other mobility aid; </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFF317CD17321405EB55A026E287FD89D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whose physical impairment requires the use of a medical device to assist with mobility, such as a portable oxygen concentrator; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15BCE34CBFFE4727AEB1B7A8F37D5CBC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with an intellectual, developmental or mental impairment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

