<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0501DBA36322490A95C8B2A2123094A4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 240 IH: National Jazz Preservation, Education, and Promulgation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 240</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230110">January 10, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To preserve knowledge and promote education about jazz in the United States and abroad.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6F92368461FD4B1597AD813082B898A5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H70BF4933BED3439983155DEB3BEC494C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Jazz Preservation, Education, and Promulgation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0ACDB12655864F58A37562C53DB2D18A"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Jazz Preservation Program</header> <subsection id="HCF83F67CF3384968B916F32AB8FE9086"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a National Jazz Preservation Program, to be carried out by the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution through the Director of the National Museum of American History and in collaboration with other Smithsonian museums, to preserve knowledge and promote education about jazz.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB43CC71A35E5429D9DAD2B1907CA90ED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text>Under the National Jazz Preservation Program, the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution shall—</text> <paragraph id="H9A878243808B401199B08D6DC279235E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>record audio and video interviews with leading jazz artists;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H698B07B8038246808375075AB53D4DF7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>acquire and preserve jazz artifacts, and interpret the artifacts through activities such as exhibitions and performances by the Smithsonian Jazz Masterworks Orchestra;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EA4ED32EC514548B86E95A9EE0F669B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>continue to recognize Jazz Appreciation Month;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H853A698A79064933A0C805E104B8BD5B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish, with governmental agencies, universities, museums, and community-based organizations with jazz archival collections, collaborative agreements for the sharing of jazz artifacts; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3762C3E21C554B389F47E43BF80E991B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage, consult with, and engage in capacity building with community-based and regional organizations with the potential to establish jazz archival collections.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F10E05DEF984E9284B04F1D021026FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $2,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2022 through 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H42A5C28A6F8646439FB9D5D435E5AB0D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Jazz education in elementary and secondary schools</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4107(a)(3) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7117">20 U.S.C. 7117(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3BE3AAB64A3D4D62B2639CC98F7BA252"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53F4D5E158944D16BAD8AC5F76D693DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (J) as subparagraph (K); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC111F4E70CFC4D5D98C8C7CDA185B071"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subparagraph (I) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB3B259BB2C949AE9FF7CD1A342885B1" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HD53651A12CA149218201CAAABEC617AA"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">programs to promote jazz education, which may include—</text> 
<clause id="H26A00D540E8D42EF9955F4263814FDC7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a Jazz Artists in the Schools program to provide support for State arts agencies to bring jazz artists to elementary and secondary schools in collaboration with local educational agencies;</text></clause> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4DE7CF903E5B45768CC58108DDD846CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a program for—</text> 
<subclause id="HABE087C9FE78476CA209F537539D2F17"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the development by jazz artists and educators of lesson plans and other educational materials about jazz;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF79CFC101B514B0DA54E81BD3FE04FBF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the distribution of such educational materials by organizations that may include the National Endowment for the Arts, educational institutions, State and local arts and cultural organizations, or nonprofit organizations; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3E41C3B3B15144838937982A51FC47A8"><enum>(III)</enum><text>teacher training on jazz education by jazz artists and educators; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H2B04577A47BD40E2963AA8AD8847329E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an Ambassadors of Jazz program to send jazz musicians, and jazz orchestras from secondary schools, abroad to perform for diverse audiences on missions of goodwill, education, and cultural exchange, in collaboration with the Secretary of State; or</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H56C3BD12E9F4401EB5E4CCA9A7E2316C"><enum>4.</enum><header>National Jazz Appreciation Program</header> 
<subsection id="H28F4EE052DA84307B5D6599858D67572"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a National Jazz Appreciation Program, to be carried out by the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution through the Director of the National Museum of American History and in collaboration with other Smithsonian museums and affiliates, the National Endowment for the Arts, and the National Endowment for the Humanities, to further the appreciation of jazz music throughout the Nation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD2D6F6B1B0F24C479077E8307F13CF71"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text>Under the National Jazz Appreciation Program, the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution shall establish a series of jazz performances at Smithsonian affiliates throughout the Nation that provides broad geographic access to jazz and supports public appreciation for the diversity of jazz music.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H72517479DDEF478D86BE1A8F5B95AC69"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $1,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2022 through 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

