<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2668575EB4A74455AA8779F6035C26F7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3216 IH: Rural Internet Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3216</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 to reauthorize and improve the ReConnect loan and grant program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H46021AFD14CF4454B6E9D53E5FD94723" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H05E83520128444889B1BA128A7CC15E3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Internet Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA464560AF27F4A3C807C790F999200CA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Streamlining broadband authorities</header> <subsection id="H75D811D5240C4B77BC091E799BC8FB07"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 601 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H256E13F305224AC4ACC501F9165A6BC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the section heading and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">ReConnect Program</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59245614D2AE49E381FDE78A564F48B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD1390ABCAD6C435BA16962D01BA9C850"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49C7E051E6C749DE8D71A7D3B288C65D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA6D145509DA45D18A6FBAF47EC51086"> 
<paragraph id="H7408A607606F405795F9CFB2DCADD012"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ReConnect Program</header><text>The term <term>ReConnect Program</term> means the program established under this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H54C215AD2A654D4FABC863CCF9C7505E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H141EC39D15F04331B96B30CA79CAD99D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A)—</text> <clause id="H8D93CAF154D443B39FE3D3F6E23B7F2D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text> 
<subclause id="HB785E8F9C8A54A27BBC2DD93B5BDE4DD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking <quote>10-Mbps</quote> and inserting <quote>25-Mbps</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7F2072AB0F50452DB2AA88F4D6B197D4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking <quote>1-Mbps</quote> and inserting <quote>3-Mbps</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HBCC377D065B24C0982B40CAC4793C486"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking clause (iv) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H74140E5A016A4B198EA6F4F89CCAAF2A"> <clause id="H9EFC92643091435AB564300580291F09"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>give priority to applications from applicants that have demonstrated the technical and financial experience required to construct and operate broadband networks.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A16711049DF4970B4605DCE23732A30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA141C4B9CA204629B94595D09BBE40FF"> <paragraph id="H1F34DD3F7A4D4BA287B135972630E58B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an application process for grants, loans, and loan guarantees under this section that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCA5DF2EEE478493E99EEEF9A873E808A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reduces the amount of data required to apply by limiting the required data to only—</text> <clause id="H1F3787B19E924604BF52F836878D614C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the entity applying, excluding any parent or affiliate entity that is not a party to the application, to the greatest extent practicable; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H769DB5A195B14D56A7250EC05963A29C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the geographic area affected by the application, if a parent or affiliate is not a party to the application;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC4714F6CD68446F4B22BA022A724FCED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>simplifies the data interfaces for submission to the greatest extent practicable; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8B6A46CDC2E848DA950AC301E45BEB16"><enum>(C)</enum><text>allows all applicants, regardless of whether an applicant is publicly traded, to rely on a bond rating of at least investment grade (when bond ratings are available) in place of financial documentation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA34AC2805A944F0888851A6586519358"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Use of broadband map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making any determination to award a loan, loan guarantee, or grant under this section, the Secretary shall utilize the map created by the Federal Communications Commission under section 802(c)(1)(A) of the Communications Act of 1934.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED641FD6CEA94E4AB68AABD5FD63538B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <subparagraph id="H404D68D6CE7C43BD831D008D60CB3501"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<clause id="HD1FD03FE51E64F798924F32C2CC1CB18"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>subsection (j)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (l)</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6A6DB1433D74462391E79FF38732A56A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD8F68C5C52D4DF0870913368B16655C"> 
<subparagraph id="H0C171EB35BED431E92BE010D596164E2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Grant requirements</header><text>The Secretary—</text> <clause id="H252D0BF6A8F040AF9855444851FA957C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not restrict the eligibility of an entity for a grant under this section based on the legal structure of the entity; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HC1A86BB64135491A965C7E1BBB9854D3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall allow entities to apply for a grant under this section without regard to, or preference for, the legal structure of an entity;</text></clause> <clause id="H1228DB1568334ACDA5551504EC0B6252" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in determining the financial ability of an entity to carry out a project using a grant under this section, shall allow the entity to demonstrate that financial ability by methods that—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HB536F09CD51048069B746C83AFBF9122"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Secretary determines to be the least burdensome; and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H023BAD16B2EA490C89FB74381D9164D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>subject to clause (v), are not limited to providing the Federal Government an exclusive first lien on all grant-funded assets during the service obligation of the grant; </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H9FFD0B57992D4BEDAA28D463BB94FC53"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>subject to clause (v), in determining the required collateral to secure grant funds or to secure performance during the service obligation of a grant, shall allow an awardee to offer alternative security, such as a letter of credit, in lieu of providing the Federal Government an exclusive first lien on all grant-funded assets; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HC0A5A55D4420472F9549E1EDA4D5AC92"><enum>(v)</enum><text>if the Secretary reasonably determines that alternative methods or alternative security established under clause (iii)(II) or (iv) are insufficient to secure performance with respect to a project under this section—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H7C665675C9F74BACBBCFCEFEF4EB8EB4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may require an entity to provide the Federal Government an exclusive first lien all grant-funded assets during the service obligation of the grant; and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="HD6250607FAF44E7EA9771CF8168E9BA6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall release that lien after the Secretary determines that the entity is performing to the satisfaction of the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1EBD74E592FD4E9D8B3C38F9E7139B95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="H32802261374C43D5A11645DFBA0F5423"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(i), by striking <quote>50</quote> and inserting <quote>90</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H83658A5D208E45A39DD4EE300ADD8EC4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6746285D04654F28B57085A134640ADB"> <subparagraph id="HC303CDB985874A8A8D77EB326EA4581B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Obligations to provide broadband service in the same service territory</header> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD40681EEF1E24ADD99BFCCC1233B30B0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition of broadband infrastructure</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <term>broadband infrastructure</term> means any cables, fiber optics, wiring, or other permanent infrastructure that is integral to the structure, including fixed wireless infrastructure, that—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC90BF3F13BF439797856DB84339B8FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is capable of providing access to internet connections in individual locations; and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE20C7420E53B471799B791744D9EF567"><enum>(II)</enum><text>offers an advanced telecommunications capability (as defined in section 706(d) of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1302">47 U.S.C. 1302(d)</external-xref>)).</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H157DD2512FCA413B83DFE89C163A541C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other providers</header><text>The Secretary shall consider a proposed service territory with respect to which an eligible entity submits an application to carry out a project under this section to be served by broadband service if a broadband service provider other than that eligible entity is subject to an obligation by a Federal, State, or local government entity to build broadband infrastructure and offer broadband service in that service territory, subject to conditions—</text> <subclause id="HF3CC36AD1AF24BB48A7E4319D0ECED1C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>under a Federal, State, or local funding award program; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8B2F943E74D14D9F82A4517AEBD8D637"><enum>(II)</enum><text>otherwise required by the Federal, State, or local government entity.</text></subclause></clause> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H8630DA8E9DD747789C888892C5EB5290"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Other funding</header><text>Subject to clause (iv), the Secretary shall not be required to consider a proposed service territory with respect to which an eligible entity submits an application to carry out a project under this section to be served by broadband service if that eligible entity has accepted an obligation under a Federal, State, or local funding award program to build broadband infrastructure and offer broadband service in that service territory, if the proposed project under this section—</text> 
<subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H99BDC209F27240888C9764BF700C8DBA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>would not be duplicative of the obligation under the other award program; and</text></subclause> <subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB36734D0D93C4F458A6EF3D6C044DA41"><enum>(II)</enum><text>would build broadband infrastructure that results in faster speeds or expedited milestones of deployment of broadband infrastructure in that service territory, as compared to the obligation under the other award program.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H64A09592605D44F4A9985DA45740C59B"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Other obligations for lower transmission capacity</header><text>The Secretary shall consider a proposed service territory with respect to which an eligible entity submits an application to carry out a project under this section to be unserved by broadband service if an obligation under another award program described in clause (iii) would not provide broadband service of at least—</text> <subclause id="HEA5A9D753BF54DF2995DC476772B272D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a 25-Mbps downstream transmission capacity; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD19E3A0A76CB48EDB9E3F355AB7A8211"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a 3-Mbps upstream transmission capacity.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A379091B0524E17AAF45ED92D81CF72"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Requirements for funding</header> <clause id="H914FCDE6C97F40DDB5DCA36FE90C8F4B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Affiliate owned and operated networks</header><text>A grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section may be used to construct networks that will be owned and operated by an affiliate of the eligible entity receiving the grant, loan, or loan guarantee, subject to the condition that the eligible entity, the affiliate, or both, as the Secretary determines to be necessary, shall provide adequate security for the grant, loan, or loan guarantee.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8A991091055E44AC8BF6A5C6FE58B580" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Negative covenants and conditions</header><text>To the greatest extent practicable, a project carried out using a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section shall not add any new negative covenants or conditions to the grant, loan, or loan guarantee agreement that were not previously disclosed to the eligible entity at the time of application for the grant, loan, or loan guarantee.</text></clause> <clause id="H69A6E317C0264091AFBD42E091B7FE0D"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Ownership of systems</header> <subclause id="HEA62631958834C61906987D39B05424D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A network constructed with a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section may be transferred to an unaffiliated provider that agrees—</text> 
<item id="HE56A3A11AB334D35A67DFD01C55B8DC1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>to assume the service obligation; and </text></item> <item id="HC5DF8A37C4AD49FFA8CF077999DD07B1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>to provide appropriate and sufficient security for that network.</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H66911FE230134189B5F7B4B6AEAD4DC9"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>The Secretary shall not unreasonably withhold consent to enter into an appropriate agreement described in subclause (I) with the transferee based on an evaluation by the Secretary of the ability of the transferee to assume the agreement and provide security described in item (bb) of that subclause.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H6E15837FA06747808697599678B3AFAE"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Reporting and auditing</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> 
<subclause id="H70A4DCCC9BB64544B9B7DBEBE82277D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>simplify, to the maximum extent practicable, ongoing reporting and auditing requirements for recipients of a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="HE9ACC9A445644446BC0CA59F293B3355"><enum>(II)</enum><text>allow a recipient described in subclause (I) whose financial information is consolidated with the financial information of a parent entity to rely on that consolidated financial information in complying with the requirements described in that subclause if the parent entity is providing a guarantee on behalf of a subsidiary of the parent entity with respect to the grant, loan, or loan guarantee. </text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H241D468D29334A3185E7850C2E3E7EEB"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Procurement and contracting</header><text>The Secretary—</text> <subclause id="HCA698BCE8DBD4192B4B0AB3ED365E01A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall simplify, to the maximum extent practicable, requirements for recipients of a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section relating to the procurement of materials and retention of contractors; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9E77EB16872447A4AC9C7AAFEEF2F1AB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall not unreasonably restrict the ability of a recipient described in subclause (I) to obtain goods and services from affiliated entities.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47AF8F0F83C8416886968F4090D88A7E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0C608CA1F87D4FA1AE7C4EE776B32109"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>25-Mbps</quote> and inserting <quote>100-Mbps</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H897CE453A4104A38B7615053792815A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>3-Mbps</quote> and inserting <quote>20-Mbps</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9742473FDC324242999491717361849E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (j) and (k) as subsections (l) and (m), respectively; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7A53ADD479F840BC8727BC25C26F285E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (i) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F4207FBDA1C4D3FAC65C377AFAF6E50"> 
<subsection id="H529DD85ED12842A695F16B6EC5428BBC"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall issue regulations to carry out this section in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2B27414E6D9F4E568A7A6AC15F86306C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Rural Internet Improvement Act of 2023</short-title>, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H16F8A109659A444B8D306E2990DBB431"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publish a report describing—</text> <subparagraph id="HE6A792BB40054025A73CA309303890DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the distribution of amounts made available under the ReConnect Program for the preceding year;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H83164D985EB84BB8BA2D412CDC668E65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of locations at which broadband service was made available using amounts under the ReConnect Program for the preceding year;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9CDFE5A19C294166A54402A1E7807504"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of locations described in subparagraph (B) at which broadband service was used; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8BBE01FA9E4342BEA5BE0EB83D732D65"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the highest level of broadband service made available at each location described in subparagraph (B); and </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B04A8AC7D934876BF9F1135F2031945"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit the report described in paragraph (1) to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H01B68EB0A7A341349F140A9B0D8D3D17"><enum>(A)</enum><text><committee-name committee-id="SSAF00">the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate;</committee-name></text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8963580EB86647FDA044DB4A3663AFDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text><committee-name committee-id="SSCM00">the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate;</committee-name></text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H196542A676464F7BB439683D99A07789"><enum>(C)</enum><text><committee-name committee-id="">the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives; and</committee-name></text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2038E14DB29F4B13A6F13EED128E7503"><enum>(D)</enum><text><committee-name committee-id="">the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives.</committee-name></text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3BA8CA1D503B44FBBDCE25E3327FE2AB" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in subsection (l) (as so redesignated), in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>for each fiscal year</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE06DCC58190B410D922DDDA0834EFE3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>Beginning on the date that is 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, section 779 of division A of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 399), shall have no force or effect.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFC2B48BF927A47DEAE1EE16A7787E8A9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transfer of amounts</header><text>The unobligated balance, as of the date that is 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, of any amounts made available to carry out the pilot program described in section 779 of division A of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 399)—</text> <paragraph id="H311D0193CDA74BFD804EB111755591FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is transferred to, and merged with, amounts made available to carry out section 601 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2A86B9B5421F46C195DDBFD3603DD244" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall remain available, until expended, and without further appropriation, to carry out the ReConnect Program established under that section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HD0144358A5144424B3E417AE0A6F63E4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Title VI of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H943840AAB6424E9E8A953FB15C482066"> 
<section commented="no" id="HBA4AF2798EF6489E85354E230DA96A48"><enum>607.</enum><header>Effect</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this title authorizes the Secretary to regulate rates charged for broadband service.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H4915636647804B11AB790F17ABB2B008"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public notice, assessments, and reporting requirements</header><text>Section 701 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950cc">7 U.S.C. 950cc</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE4DCC808B3094A49949E05E81B6078AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HA6E7F5DC9F3846138F1D63A1C23FFABC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by inserting <quote>, including a complete shapefile map</quote> after <quote>applicant</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2610C8FF094544FDB127058F22D30205"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(D), by striking <quote>(c)</quote> and inserting <quote>(d)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB348D9D99925486683B194F30D3F307B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (b) through (e) as subsections (c) through (f), respectively;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H0BC6BA9F21474CC2A112FA0917B2C8A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (a) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCB1C24176DBB4099BA1ACEFE8B12A8A6"> <subsection id="HD24F68B3968E4C25A5ABD760AF0E4960"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Challenge process</header> <paragraph id="H5080D1CA30744A35B225AD777CD4598F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a transparent, evidence based, and expeditious process for challenging, with respect to any area for which assistance is sought under an application described in subsection (a)(1), whether that area has access to broadband service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CBCB31DF21140DE9AE8DF25EFFDF926"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The Secretary shall make publicly available on the website of the Department of Agriculture a written notice describing—</text> <subparagraph id="HFD56779E3974408FBA5B9D632CF40BDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the decision of the Secretary on each challenge submitted under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H720D5564EA08463EAC72AD193EB4B06C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the reasons for each decision described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0E610833CFC64DEEA049BC6905EC0DB9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAB7F5F9E04D48B38993E97EC70A8E60"> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H40F44444215347139624C75B7C78B99A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Public notice of eligible funding areas</header><text>Prior to making available to the public the database under subsection (a), the Secretary shall make available to the public a fully searchable database on the website of the Rural Utilities Service that contains information on areas eligible for assistance under retail broadband projects that are administered by the Secretary in accordance with the maps created by the Federal Communications Commission under section 802(c)(1) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/642">47 U.S.C. 642(c)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H2692CA75B5224823B3211B567965E65A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Federal broadband program coordination</header><text>Section 6212 of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb-6">7 U.S.C. 950bb–6</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HEEC3CF08F7754E64977F7884ED5E6E87"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (a), (b), (c), and (d) as subsections (b), (c), (e), and (a), respectively, and moving the subsections so as to appear in alphabetical order;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H712FFDC83F44473D92176CEE5DB959EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a) (as so redesignated), in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>section 601(b)(3) of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936</quote> and inserting <quote>section 601(b) of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb(b)</external-xref>)</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H25F796C417FF43E5BEDA2ED9779CD13F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c) (as so redesignated), in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HD2D915184A5448D1AF6AF514130F3195"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Secretary</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA23567D2E55B4D7EB57928B3A130C432"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H483EAFD0BF5F428794D6CB3A5179A3CC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H6F6F8B3E280A433196FF5376D48D330B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H800127F7C42645C8BAAF9A7D76D8CDFD"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H22640E774F094991B3EC8EB1B0A7607F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>ReConnect Program</header><text>On awarding a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under the ReConnect Program established under section 601 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb</external-xref>), the Secretary shall notify the Commission of that award.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7801A8D508E9487D9E4718C30E9677E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (c) (as so redesignated) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2D0582929F14AD69626D8B6B2998B9C"> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HC70020AF9CA140CBB977842B569CEB9C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding relating to outreach</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into a memorandum of understanding with the Assistant Secretary and the Commission to facilitate outreach to residents and businesses in rural areas, including—</text> <paragraph id="HB1A1A2ECD6874ECE93E28C4E6A349C12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to evaluate the broadband service needs in rural areas;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBEAC8169C93844C7B81084FA5E62F98B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to inform residents and businesses in rural areas of available Federal programs that promote broadband access, broadband affordability, and broadband inclusion; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB82965099AF4E1F94A5F92EA6CCABF0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for such additional goals as the Secretary, the Assistant Secretary, and the Commission determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

