<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8E28C69878964284BEDC6AB5502A7C55" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6129 IH: Studying NEPA’s Impact on Projects Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6129</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000067">Mr. Yakym</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Council on Environmental Quality to publish an annual report on environmental reviews and causes of action based on compliance with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H69934C9CFC5F400F94A215D9C723FBAA" style="OLC"><section id="HD7C07FF17BB646D19215822F585F4D9D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Studying NEPA’s Impact on Projects Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HBB18B16E917249E1B66C359A84DE817A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual report on NEPA’s impact on projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 201 of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4341">42 U.S.C. 4341</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEC19E30759644AB4829616DE62698586" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H259C4265027344619B5797D21E08054A"><enum>201.</enum><header>Annual report on NEPA’s impact on projects</header><subsection id="HCA442AFBC79F474EAC090B0E9F4E8B7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning July 1, 2024, the Council on Environmental Quality shall annually publish on the website of the Council on Environmental Quality, and submit to Congress, a report on—</text><paragraph id="H4DCBA523CF9B490591B09AA275ACFD8C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each cause of action based on compliance with this Act filed during the period beginning June 1 of the preceding year and ending June 1 of the current year, which shall identify—</text><subparagraph id="H2149C0E339AB4E4687CF318381BB52C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to each such cause of action, the lead defendant Federal agency and the lead plaintiff;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92FD9670E05940479DBB2F994A14AB1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of such causes of action, disaggregated by the lead defendant Federal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4956789E050B47EE8CC3C2AA434B6799"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the alleged basis for each such cause of action, disaggregated by type; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC822169A68694243944C3C09EFDB861C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the status and outcome, if applicable, of each cause of action based on compliance with this Act filed during the period beginning June 1 of the preceding year and ending June 1 of the current year, including whether—</text><clause id="H52A32E7D8A0044B1B467DF0763668391"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cause of action resulted in the major Federal action being reversed;</text></clause><clause id="H52DE3AFB8072439FB1D4D506B070B4D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the lead defendant Federal agency was allowed to move forward with the major Federal action;</text></clause><clause id="H8EE35AA4011C45119341BC1582A2E659"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the court issued a ruling directing the lead defendant Federal agency to take additional measures to be in compliance;</text></clause><clause id="H05F8D4251EEF4EFA9C774C0038ABF4F5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the lead plaintiff and the lead defendant Federal agency settled amongst themselves; and</text></clause><clause id="H87A07F865E4E49E6838073752EFE2F62"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the cause of action is still in progress;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3AA5563D4754A8491E283DF127C2AE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the length of environmental impact statements prepared pursuant to section 102(2)(C) during the period of 5 years that ends on June 1 of the current year, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H9B735D498D5843C88DC8E6F5119C4C4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the average and median page count of each draft and final environmental impact statement (including the appendix) published in the Federal Register during such period of 5 years, including such page counts disaggregated by quartiles;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBAB8E8DF84B40B5A3A7B8A032BDC581"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of draft and final environmental impact statements published in the Federal Register during such period of 5 years, disaggregated by lead Federal agency and subagency as applicable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCF29A6B99A543BF9DB23B0F4B1EB935"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of trends in average and median page count of draft and final environmental impact statements published in the Federal Register during such period of 5 years compared to prior reports published by the Council on Environmental Quality; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC70E36B132FB41D3A56AE9E65631DDA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the timelines to complete environmental reviews pursuant to section 102(2)(C) during the period of 10 years that ends on June 1 of the current year, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H66853DD80E4C44DA9E56FB8F691D9A86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to each major Federal action commenced during such period of 10 years, the date on which (as applicable)—</text><clause id="H6E2BCBF9A3F241089A04EF247F52FC89"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the notice of intent to prepare the environmental impact statement was published in the Federal Register;</text></clause><clause id="H2A90DCD5641A47D19436D2AC6D221783"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the draft environmental impact statement was published in the Federal Register;</text></clause><clause id="H8805CEE4A57741068ECDE3833D4D465F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the final environmental impact statement was published in the Federal Register; and</text></clause><clause id="H1E1D0B299C5A4FA695C632E5AA329904"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the record of decision was published in the Federal Register;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA965263C97BB4017B16D6AA9DC49212E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the average and median publication timelines during such period of 10 years for each document described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE40DD85EEAAD4629B44A39584AE34AB6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of trends in completion times during such period of 10 years for such documents compared to prior reports published by the Council on Environmental Quality.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBFB368977D654C2E9AEEDE818BAAEE79"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public availability of data</header><text>The Council on Environmental Quality shall publish with each report published under subsection (a) the underlying data used to prepare each such report.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

