<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8D493DD553AA43CDBC49FB79881FF421" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4498 IH: Jobs of the Future Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4498</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote a 21st century artificial intelligence workforce.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H34AC54582DD945029F9829BE7A2C0E28" style="OLC"><section id="H8FE62DBAD549494698EF67463DE27526" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Jobs of the Future Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H18B1BD2F84EF4417987B62733C554B9E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H915FE02791DB4B748FB94C89A551139B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">while the field of artificial intelligence is evolving quickly and has potential to disrupt jobs, there are opportunities to prepare the American workforce to develop and work alongside this new technology and mitigate job displacement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D915D74D4B14204BCEE11391518A5A7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to ensure these opportunities, it is imperative to identify the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5A859913B07F42AF86BAFF00200B2A6D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data and data access necessary to properly analyze the impact of artificial intelligence on the United States workforce.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBC1FDF429374BEDA106726E1ECD8071"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Industries projected to be most impacted by artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E213859FAEE4B259D4A8C365A1DFDA7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Opportunities for workers and other stakeholders to influence the impact of artificial intelligence across industries.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H658919A00C454829A553E7E26A7AEC1F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Demographics whose career opportunities are most likely to be affected by growth of artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52EE0D963C9C421481A110A4089B93D5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The skills, expertise, and education needed to develop, operate, or work alongside artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D13AF2D6DAD40119745A0BEA914D725"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Methods to ensure necessary skills, expertise, and education are accessible to all segments of the current and future workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HDE783243A2254FEE951848E084BB2EEA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="H905A8F8377A1463E979539AABA52E964"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor and the Director of the National Science Foundation shall, jointly and in collaboration with the individuals and entities described in subsection (c), prepare and submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and the Committee on Commerce, Science and Transportation of the Senate—</text><paragraph id="H8252ADE0C2D449DC8CF0581FCB1CCE48"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, an interim report on artificial intelligence and its impact on the workforce of the United States, which shall include the information and recommendations listed in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0331048EFD4C40E896FE91C70E4D1FA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, a final report on artificial intelligence and its impact on the workforce of the United States, which shall include the information and recommendations listed in subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5EFB94D9177C4BE08019881247D58CCB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required information</header><text>The following shall be included in each report submitted under subsection (a):</text><paragraph id="H2846B3394B9248909430648172C7CEAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of the specific data relating to the workforce, and the availability of such data, necessary to properly analyze the impact and growth of artificial intelligence on the workforce of the United States and outline how much of this data is privately owned, and the effectiveness of Federal, State, or industry efforts (including public-private partnerships) to make privately owned data on the workforce of the United States available for Federal research purposes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA76175D2C614A2BA845FD923D806DFF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of industries and occupations projected to have the most growth in artificial intelligence use, whether the technology is likely to result in the enhancement of workers’ capabilities or their replacement, and level of education currently consistent with industries and occupations identified.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5931C6042B1F4AD491A3A8AB19805704"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of opportunities for workers, educators, institutions of higher education, Congress, or other relevant stakeholders to influence the impact of artificial intelligence on workers across various industries. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF2427B7E03F4788820044DED0372915"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analysis of which demographics (including ethnic, gender, economic, age, and regional) currently stand to experience expanded career opportunities, and which demographics currently appear most vulnerable to career displacement, due to artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1F4E6AEF6E44CD2BACCEE76EFC4A515"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analysis of the skills, expertise, and education (including computer science literacy) needed to develop, operate, or work alongside artificial intelligence over the next two decades, as compared to the levels of such expertise and education among the workforce as of the date of enactment of this Act, with a differentiation between core competencies required across the entire workforce and competencies required within the industries and occupations identified in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1061B08942EE4083BF835877374426AD"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of methods by which necessary skills, expertise, and education can be effectively delivered to various segments of the United States workforce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A6A08E2D55149C192762BEC58632E36"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of industry leaders and institutions of higher education at the forefront of research and application of artificial intelligence in the industries and occupations identified in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D6E048E56C844C5A45BED1521E3109C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of the resources and opportunities required for institutions of higher education, including two year institutions, minority-serving institutions, and institutions of higher education serving rural areas to deliver skills, expertise, and education identified in paragraph (5).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA01A1CB2E5A14A25BD3EDC0844645DE4"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations to alleviate workforce displacement, prepare future workforce members for the artificial-intelligence economy, and any other relevant observations or recommendations within the field of artificial intelligence, which shall include recommendations on—</text><subparagraph id="H43BA488BD9414CF5BCA6E8630BFD41FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>methods to expand public access to privately-owned workforce data, for the purpose of researching the effect of emerging technologies on the United States workforce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD74DD20AE99C43F382A746F9B6B9E4D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>avenues for stakeholders (workers, educators, institutions of higher education, Congress, or other relevant stakeholders) to effectively mitigate perceived negative impacts of artificial intelligence on segments of the United States workforce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95FC4E7647D34C5491FEDAF72A24CC20"><enum>(C)</enum><text>methods to reskill or otherwise offset socioeconomic harm to demographics identified in paragraph (4) as most vulnerable to career displacement, due to artificial intelligence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCC8818223404C2591EB7C63288E6DC7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>methods to encourage low cost, open source sharing of industry valued credentials certifying the types of skills, expertise, and education identified in paragraph (5);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA13B7FC24637460B8F731B9CD222AC37"><enum>(E)</enum><text>methods to ensure core skills and competencies identified in paragraph (5) can be evaluated, updated, and made public by relevant stakeholders as needed, given rapid developments in the field of artificial intelligence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52546850C4CD4437AAC089675110668A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>methods to ensure 2-year institutions of higher education, minority-serving institutions, and institutions of higher education serving rural areas receive resources and opportunities identified in paragraph (8);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA80E857675041F8975B84C614CFB659"><enum>(G)</enum><text>methods to promote knowledge sharing and capacity building between industry leaders and institutions identified in paragraph (7) and two year institutions, minority-serving institutions, and rural institutions of higher education; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBED193402C09489DAB96FDD49B3254D4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other methods to ensure that the skills, expertise, and education needed to develop, operate, or work alongside artificial intelligence are delivered to vulnerable demographics identified in paragraph (4), rural workers, and other historically underserved segments of the United States workforce (to include workers with disabilities).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8653F3E68C414CB58F76FA25DFF15364"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In preparing the report under subsection (a), the Secretary of Labor and the Director of the National Science Foundation shall collaborate, through a series of public meetings, roundtables or other methods, with—</text><paragraph id="HBB4153EAA8D3479BAB9AF1B80C6A5AA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">local educational agencies, institutions of higher education (including community colleges, minority-serving institutions of higher education, and institutions of higher education serving rural areas), workforce-training organizations, and National Laboratories;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91808B9921D84DB6B09E239FC4C1E152"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a broad range of industrial stakeholders in the technology, manufacturing, employment, human resources, and service sectors, including companies (large and small), think tanks, and industry organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75241B35D9B543F88C5CA9865F60BE95"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the National Academies of Science, including by sharing relevant information obtained as a result of the study conducted under section 5105 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB63EF90843B140529B2EDE048C08246D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Education, the Director of the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy, the Director of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Office, the National Cyber Director, and the heads of any other Federal agency the Secretary of Labor and the Director of the National Science Foundation determine appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H94A8EF5FCC2C4356B9805F0BC16B2048"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H483B478AE48C42A99F93DB3FDFD9CAE9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given the term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACA19942CE2D49D7A19780E7FB921759"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community college</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>community college</term> has the meaning given the term <term>junior or community college</term> in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52586C6A335047D4B8C4C1FD930EB426"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1CEBD526B804192AD6AC8D8FE33820D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

