<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6B772B2C2CB2448C976B68743567E129" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5152 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a program to ensure, under certain conditions, that members of the Armed Forces are automatically enrolled in benefits and services under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for which such members are eligible.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5152</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a program to ensure, under certain conditions, that members of the Armed Forces are automatically enrolled in benefits and services under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for which such members are eligible.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6A0DCF4DBB2647798C0160B5E4398335" style="OLC">
<section id="HC9E26167776A47B88F1A43E1335304F6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Program of Department of Defense to enroll certain members of the Armed Forces in benefits and services under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</header>
<subsection id="H85DD12547D894605A6BBF4C0BA3B49D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall carry out a program to—</text> <paragraph id="H27CA3780ABD24EFF917B750EDFED9E87" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify covered benefits, if any, for which each covered member of an Armed Force is eligible to enroll; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF90308F2A9DC447099FA125FD5478C10"><enum>(2)</enum><text>notify each covered member of the relevant covered benefits identified under subparagraph (A); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79DC899991A04A63A9808A86340BF1EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>expect as provided in subsection (e), ensure such covered member is enrolled in such covered benefits.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9BCDB0FB28B344B7A9E8C97F3EC3E122" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification to Secretary of Veterans Affairs</header><text>With respect to any covered member of an Armed Force the Secretary of Defense determines is eligible for enrollment in a covered benefit, such Secretary shall, not later than 90 days before the date on which such covered member is separated from service, submit to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs a notification that includes—</text> <paragraph id="H819D9E26C5484FE6B47DBADAE1C768C5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, contact information, and military service details of such covered member;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H66104F6D6E484CF89B029FF709656F87" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the anticipated date on which such covered member will be separated from service; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04E3ED3FC12C420688D7BCCCFC60AFE7" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any military occupational specialty and training such covered member received during service. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H11E5072D7EB24FCFBA7E7A3CCFFDC0B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Outreach required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after any date on which the Secretary of Veterans Affairs receives a notification under subsection (b), such Secretary shall contact the covered member of an Armed Force described in such notification and provide materials and resources relating to covered benefits.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H42BE1E6F65D94C468C32AD84A25D019F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Information sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish procedures to—</text>
<paragraph id="H751F738C302641D6BC3DE076F1ECE3B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>share necessary information to facilitate the automatic enrollment process under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5DF64D84F23A43D4ABDEF7161FE02C41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure the secure and confidential transfer of data during any such sharing of necessary information.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H13EE4973F770411FA0C0AD6003E10E01"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Opt-Out provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The decision to enroll in a covered benefit pursuant to subsection (a) shall be at the election of the relevant covered member of an Armed Force.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8AB8C380447047DBAC32229828CDFCA8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Working group</header> <paragraph id="HEB01D31BA29C41E0B3CB1234C01F44B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish a working group to address potential barriers and challenges in implementing the automatic enrollment process. The working group shall consist of representatives from the Department of Defense, the Department of Veterans Affairs, and other relevant stakeholders as determined by such Secretaries.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBC7DDE9EE15940449748F6A71D7A8F44"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The working group shall be responsible for—</text> <subparagraph id="HE73FDC5CD9284CEA974C2433AF39A19D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying potential barriers to implementation, such as legal, technological, or administrative challenges; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3B14121247B346BAAE2CE68DFF93B504"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing strategies and recommendations to overcome such potential barriers and ensure the successful implementation of automatic enrollments.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B4924964D3244D6B841A5751791047E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which such Secretaries establish the working group under paragraph (1), the head of such working group shall submit to Congress a report that includes findings, recommendations, and proposed timelines for implementation.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HDF36CF4BC1D34330985831F0CF4C07F8" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>GAO report on notice of automatic enrollment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of a study to determine the best methods for the Secretary of Defense to provide notice under subsection (a)(2). In making such determination, the Comptroller General shall consider needs of veterans based on—</text> <paragraph id="HAFC4E72A46D042359AC0B2E605524CD3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>age;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3C1D926C8E894F5EBDFE5934FD202DED" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>residence in urban areas; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C7F181ECBA34DE894B66FADF4176B6D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>residence in rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H87D0E337014A48F7B09DE9AF811B53C9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H497C315C8D2E47FB94EBCDC0C3DAAE4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered benefit</quote> means a benefit or service under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5CF1CA5AED4B4DCC86E4A5CEFEF011CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered member of an Armed Force</quote> means a member of the Armed Forces participating in the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense under section 1142 and 1144 of title 10, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

