<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H15B57007192E4CC6A96A2541F7F733D1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1164 IH: OFAC Outreach and Engagement Capabilities Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1164</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct a study with respect to outreach activities performed by the Office of Foreign Assets Control, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA49B57DD3E944176B3E0C5A33382A393" style="OLC"><section id="H9E74D6E7324E4047B367840068D19C5D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>OFAC Outreach and Engagement Capabilities Enhancement Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H16F615C56D7340BDA860B03F5C0AAA8E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H417A54989E4F4B2B94019B83B392215C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Office of Foreign Assets Control is the United States Government agency responsible for administering and enforcing economic sanctions programs, primarily against countries and groups of individuals, such as terrorists and narcotics traffickers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE946991E42F54D85AFB20AB819BB6D25"><enum>(2)</enum><text>All United States persons must comply with OFAC regulations, including all United States citizens and permanent resident aliens regardless of where they are located, all persons and entities within the United States, all United States incorporated entities and their foreign branches. In the cases of certain programs, foreign subsidiaries owned or controlled by United States companies also must comply. Certain programs also require foreign persons in possession of United States-origin goods to comply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85CFC4056FE24EDCA0804CC1FA5461C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>While the sanctions announcements are themselves notice of the requirements placed on all United States persons, OFAC conducts additional outreach through its compliance office, serving as OFAC’s primary liaison to the private sector and operating OFAC’s public <quote>hotline</quote> for sanctions-related questions and the conduct of civil investigations for potential sanctions violations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87261487D92245A6ABC74ADF3F20B5A2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>While many industries, such as large multinational financial institutions and industrial firms, have sophisticated sanctions departments to manage compliance with the strict-liability mandates from OFAC and to enact practices to defend their business’ sales and supply chains from abuse by sanctions-designated bad actors, many smaller entities and industries, do not.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28798AE6C3054BF092300B41ECAA2582"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to the U.S. Department of the Treasury’s 2021 Sanctions Review, <quote>Sanctions are only as effective as their implementation, especially with regard to communication and engagement. In order to better calibrate the use of this tool, Treasury needs to communicate and coordinate more effectively with stakeholders affected by the use of financial sanctions. Treasury can build on existing outreach and engagement capabilities through enhanced communication with industry, financial institutions, allies, civil society, and the media, as well as new constituencies, particularly in the digital assets space.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB43A9C9BF2D4C2FAE4858655D07FC6A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary for Terrorism and Financial Intelligence noted in a 2022 speech to a private-sector audience at the American Conference Institute, <quote>We need to redouble efforts—to make sure that these networks do not pass under your radar and around our laws, and that when you obtain information about them, you promptly take action. This is not just a matter of compliance; it is a moral imperative. The choice is between permitting and preventing sanctions evasion—there is no space for neutral ground here.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4BDD712AA04433D85E2AAA18AACDD52"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Examples of successful, robust Federal Government public-private sector outreach programs that support the agency mission abound from the law enforcement, Intelligence Community, and regulatory agencies, such as the Federal Bureau of Investigation’s InfraGard, the Public-Private Analytic Exchange Program from the Department of Homeland Security and the Office of the Director of National Intelligence, and the Financial Crime Enforcement Network’s FinCEN Exchange.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DB7B120B84F4233B14BE495341EFB5B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The FinCEN Exchange, from OFAC’s sister agency within the U.S. Department of the Treasury, was mandated on January 1, 2021, when Congress enacted the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020 (AML Act). Section 6103 of the AML Act establishes the FinCEN Exchange to facilitate a voluntary public-private information-sharing partnership between law enforcement agencies, national security agencies, financial institutions, and FinCEN to effectively and efficiently combat money laundering, terrorism financing, organized crime, and other financial crimes, protect the financial system from illicit use, and promote national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1663E1F370E416098AE66BCBC80E90D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The objective of FinCEN Exchange is to develop, deliver, and sustain innovative public-private information sharing in order to enable the private sector to better identify risks and provide FinCEN and law enforcement with critical information to disrupt money laundering, terrorism financing, and other financial crimes. The program goals of the exchange are to:</text><subparagraph id="H724B4E3231304845B57DAB3153050601"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Enhance communication, collaboration, and partnerships among FinCEN, law enforcement, and financial institutions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EC263A832F34C13A882D68F6B353FA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Support priority national security and counter-illicit finance investigations and policies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBE24016EDDA410EB6F911CCEE05D4D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Enhance the utility of suspicious activity reports and share feedback with the private sector.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H442B2AE8678A477B95B069BAAF6B7FC2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Encourage, enable, and acknowledge a focus on high-value and high-impact activities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2BD7929A146406D867C924C614AD62A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Conduct proactive outreach to allow industry to better prioritize efforts and utilize existing resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HC508A6DF3161436484A09FE64C1985C4"><enum>3.</enum><header>OFAC outreach assessment</header><subsection id="H678AA9CDA02B41E885E6F61E8AA09D91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>GAO Study</header><paragraph id="H8FF3C418EE624A5DAB15A6EDC7A28B86"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall, not later than 360 days after the date of the enactment of this section, carry out a study with respect to the quality and efficacy of outreach activities performed by OFAC in support of the mission of OFAC on or before the date of the enactment of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BE6F082ECDB4617BCC0CF1463A7035B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Study requirements</header><subparagraph id="H1B607D8CE26C46DB86B4B0033FBFF2E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall, in carrying out paragraph (1), examine each of the following with respect to outreach activities performed by OFAC:</text><clause id="HEA3265EBBF474B058434ECA1349085CE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Goals and strategy.</text></clause><clause id="H0D6697FA9C314EAD8615B90FE8E62E07" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Audiences.</text></clause><clause id="HB5891A33B3544CC3A6D2D280EC73FFF9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Resources.</text></clause><clause id="H620973D3AE63481EABA8AA83E961436C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Number and type of engagements with private sector entities.</text></clause><clause id="H54E4DA8AFA1744B3B686409EDBD5E48B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Feedback capabilities.</text></clause><clause id="H9926B35903384338BF952E62A18BB161"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Appropriate privacy and competitive fairness measures for information received from or shared with private sector entities.</text></clause><clause id="HFECC8DD33D014876ACBC9DFAE25C9530"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Compliance with the Federal Advisory Committee Act, where required.</text></clause><clause id="H9201CECA81704CF4A3AEC4405B738FE0"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>How information obtained from outreach activities is used by OFAC to support the mission of OFAC. </text></clause><clause id="HA20AD3F07A2744AC93690A73992D7C31"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>How, if at all, outreach activities help with enforcement functions.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBB889EF70F24F1FB3E3B9A2AA5C1A4C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Survey of similar programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the study required under this subsection, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><clause id="H5906611CBD5C492C8535D27B698AEC9D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>examine outreach programs administered by agencies with similar national security and regulatory missions, including outreach programs administered by similar agencies, including the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network; and</text></clause><clause id="HE5B1623324AC4784A3D2399623D9292F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify best practices, similarities, and differences to inform the evaluation of existing OFAC outreach programs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD66D290F8A6F4D7583932C4549A2221F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">OFAC shall, not later than 60 days after the date on which the Comptroller General of the United States submits a study pursuant to subsection (a), and after considering the results of such study, submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs on the Senate a briefing that describes how OFAC will improve its outreach activities going forward, including, at the time of such briefing, in relation to OFAC outreach activities, how OFAC—</text><paragraph id="HF515502BE33B43A2BEFEC08FAB9B5CBF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides information to those who must comply with OFAC sanctions, especially those in communities and industries that are known to be targeted by bad actors designated by sanctions; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6831344AC97E4C44910DD246DC04CA2C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>uses outreach activities to support to the important mission of OFAC, with minimal redirection of staff and resources;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1697FE8E24FF4CBA9D5DDA3E6F2B0835" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensures that the selection of private-sector participants for outreach activities is free from favoritism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F3CCB20D7204168B384C2EF87398BAA" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensures that private-sector information obtained by OFAC during outreach activities is appropriately safeguarded;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51A36E8C5F094AB8819CDD0EEFF5D36E" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensures that information shared at outreach functions can be publicized in a manner that does not competitively disadvantage those not selected to participate in such outreach functions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA74CAD3B0B6845D78CBF7197A7302A57" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>applies Federal requirements with respect to all outreach activities, including Federal Advisory Committee Act requirements;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE2B64B0861047169F1176CF91BD5918" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>ensures that private-sector participants not use outreach activities as an opportunity to pitch products or services or receive advance information about OFAC or Department of the Treasury procurement opportunities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF75B7D5113854A07A922936FAA03F96A" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>maintains compliance with OFAC ethics requirements. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H61FB056DC70A41C3BEA7F8EED67EA4BD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Feasibility of voluntary exchange program</header><text>OFAC shall, after reviewing the report produced by the Comptroller General of the United States pursuant to subsection (a) and submitting the briefing required under subsection (b), access the feasibility of the establishment of a program by OFAC designed to—</text><paragraph id="H06FE7ADCE35040F4831BE4FFD5E51527" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitate a voluntary public-private information sharing partnership among law enforcement agencies, national security agencies, financial institutions, and OFAC to effectively and efficiently administer and enforce economic sanctions against targeted foreign countries and regimes, terrorists, international narcotics traffickers, those engaged in activities related to the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction, and other threats to the national security, foreign policy, or economy of the United States by promoting innovation and technical advances in reporting;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B94703541594C54A122E4F680AD8BD9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>protect the financial system from illicit use, including evasions of existing economic sanctions programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C69E0DD252C4C7287193207FDAAC0D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitate two-way information exchange between OFAC and persons who are required to comply with sanctions administered and enforced by OFAC, including financial institutions, business sectors frequently affected by sanctions programs, and non-government organizations and humanitarian groups impacted by such sanctions programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFFC03E1C7E8049C6B18785C044B899BE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pilot Program</header><paragraph id="H461BB144E3474F7F9B7E8E8F549A2DEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury may, after considering the results of the study conducted by the Comptroller General of the United States pursuant to subsection (a), the briefing provided by OFAC pursuant to subsection (b), and the feasibility assessment conducted by OFAC pursuant to subsection (c), require OFAC to establish a 3-year pilot of a program designed to—</text><subparagraph id="H692A94ED6F4642E5BE599A0498831CC4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitate a voluntary public-private information sharing partnership among law enforcement agencies, national security agencies, financial institutions, and OFAC to effectively and efficiently administer and enforce economic sanctions against targeted foreign countries and regimes, terrorists, international narcotics traffickers, those engaged in activities related to the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction, and other threats to the national security, foreign policy, or economy of the United States by promoting innovation and technical advances in reporting;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H548791D5F3CE43FCB1B4DFE0B7CEF9AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>protect the financial system from illicit use, including evasions of existing economic sanctions programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF3AE655BDA24DF692C396C53150D837"><enum>(C)</enum><text>facilitate two-way information exchange between OFAC and persons who are required to comply with sanctions administered and enforced by OFAC, including financial institutions, business sectors frequently affected by sanctions programs, and non-government organizations and humanitarian groups impacted by such sanctions programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06F566C161E34BA4BCE88373371C491F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information sharing</header><subparagraph id="H769858F10EFA4FB4A7667A722FE559BA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any information shared by a private sector entity as a part of any program established under paragraph (1) shall be shared—</text><clause id="H6AF53C34EEA449C5A0E5D25130C9257E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in compliance with all other applicable Federal laws and regulations; and</text></clause><clause id="H7332D8270BEE42F7A1D6C4E9705593B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in such a manner as to ensure the appropriate confidentiality of personal information.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B2D3BA64ACF49C2BA608923021C0EEC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of information</header><text>Information received by OFAC from a private sector entity as a part of any program established under paragraph (1) may not be used for any purpose other than identifying and reporting on activities that may involve the compliance with United States sanctions requirements.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD6FD1E688874B36BA15F753E09A6B7B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to create new information sharing authorities or requirements relating to sanctions laws.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8ADC0966DE624EB3B2717504DB7F1500"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a program is established under paragraph (1), OFAC shall, annual submit a report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate that describes the activities of such program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E3517615BAF45CB96874EED294315C8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H5DFDABFAC54344548AD6EB2B1899B3F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>OFAC</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>OFAC</quote> means the Office of Foreign Assets Control. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20A77743A49A4188A6FF3B061C366480"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Private sector</header><text>The term <quote>private sector entity</quote> means a business, a nonprofit organization, a nongovernmental organization, a legal and or advisory firm that supports such a business or organization, and a technology provider that supports such a business or organization. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

