<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF58BCA82D27A412EA42F8EA53E2017F5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5002 IH: Innovative Cognitive Care for Veterans Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5002</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out a pilot program for the cognitive care of veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7AAEF0AEB11841658A4EAD4D8CC56E94" style="OLC"><section id="H0371A4060C6545DA878FBE0AADAC95B1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Innovative Cognitive Care for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H06A7E3655C054B57BE7429507061EACB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HA2F3A78E74D3455F9E60FF38730B79DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a 2020 study by the Office of the Assistant Deputy Under Secretary for Health for Policy and Planning of the Department of Veterans Affairs, it is projected that the number of veterans with Alzheimer’s dementia will increase by 28.9 percent between fiscal year 2021 and fiscal year 2033, amounting to an estimated 48,000 new patients with cognitive impairments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5107C444148E4A52812FE2728170A494"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The cost of expenditures of the Department of Veterans Affairs for long-term care is growing rapidly, as demonstrated by a 2020 Government Accountability Office report that estimates such expenditures are projected to double to $14,300,000,000 by 2037.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BB29BF0275C4864AC255117C6EA1AA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As described in the report specified in paragraph (2), the Department of Veterans Affairs also faces both a current and incoming workforce shortage, in addition to other challenges relating to the provision of long-term care services to the more than 2,800,000 estimated veterans who are enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department established and operated under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code, and live in rural areas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9FB8770CFE24958BA66A588003CB29A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As observed by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, veterans can also be prone to unique factors that increase the risk for future cognitive impairment. For example, it has been found that veterans who served during the Vietnam era and, while so serving, were exposed to Agent Orange are nearly twice as likely as those without such exposure to receive a diagnosis of dementia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D72997B3E654305A70E82AE20A6F8FB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Department of Veterans Affairs, more than 185,000 veterans enrolled in the health care system of the Department of Veterans Affairs have been diagnosed with at least one traumatic brain injury. Traumatic brain injury often affects the cognitive abilities of an individual and can disrupt normal brain function. Veterans with a traumatic brain injury are also 60 percent more likely to develop Alzheimer’s Disease or other forms of dementia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DCE73F142DC44D398898EADEA764405"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This data compels the United States Government to do more for veterans and their cognitive care.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4451F89FFD9C482DBB0709996124F87A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pilot program of Department of Veterans Affairs for addressing cognitive disorders among veterans</header><subsection id="H6D3A2E327B08433080C7D35399995702"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><paragraph id="H404C73CA2EDC46C4935F66F4F30F01DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out, as a part of the Veterans Community Care Program under section 1703 of title 38, and in accordance with the requirements of such program, a pilot program (in this section referred to as the <quote>pilot program</quote>) under which the Secretary may enter into agreements with eligible entities to furnish to participating veterans telehealth, virtual training tools for home health aides, and other innovative services, that slow the progression of cognitive disorders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1F2308BFD914AE4B22AE90135B3DA6A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Veterans Care Agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In entering into agreements under paragraph (1), the Secretary may enter into a Veterans Care Agreement under section 1703A of title 38, United States Code, consistent with the requirements of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88584A6F3DCA45AFA22B21DA9506F295"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection of entities</header><paragraph id="H6CCD1C9A300F4F679D45DF8026C51C5F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity is eligible for entry into an agreement under the pilot program if the entity—</text><subparagraph id="H3CD5C33495CE41DCBD17BDCBF9A8BAAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>furnishes telehealth, virtual training tools for home health aides, or other innovative services, that slow the progression of cognitive disorders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F392C964B0A40C6AB0BF35063801702"><enum>(B)</enum><text>meets such other requirements as the Secretary may prescribe.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4FEFB7DD8994BB2BA5AB12A6B126A6C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting eligible entities for entry into an agreement under the pilot program, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities with—</text><subparagraph id="H84FFE3CDF47742BCAF5B86A53F11A09D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>demonstrated experience in—</text><clause id="H435EA2F408834B1687A1AD0D0B03E459"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing assistance to individuals with cognitive disorders;</text></clause><clause id="H85741CA11E5845AFB068C605A87E1CCE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>addressing behavioral and temperament issues, including through interactive engagement and stimulation solutions;</text></clause><clause id="H3D87E284C28042CE873A513023E0208A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">caregiver or home health aid training; and</text></clause><clause id="H6AC2EF2CA9684114861F9FDA1B36B1C7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">working in the field of cognitive disorders, including through the treatment of, or rehabilitation for, traumatic brain injury or neurodegenerative conditions; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57B44B8280A0492A961C469C9C19FB05"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the ability to provide services under the pilot program to veterans at locations other than a hospital, nursing home, or other medical facility, in accordance with subsection (d)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H11C61795210448EDA59B468F32B7D008"><enum>(3)</enum><header>List of selected entities</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H73DD7958459B49DD8D8D6919F0153036"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish on an internet website of the Department a list identifying each eligible entity with which the Secretary has entered into an agreement under the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7C8AA87528C4285B126B7A7EAD847F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure such list is accessible to veterans selected for participation in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD471CF341CB4C82BE9F5C231F204EB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection of veterans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting veterans for participation in the pilot program, the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="HC2CF893B4CDC4B62BFB3FBA3BF22B7C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall ensure that not more than 500 veterans participate in the pilot program at any given time; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7B3A83A2B024058BBE12427C7308179"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not take into consideration age or risk factors for cognitive disorders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4ABD37A458724A80BEFCD469B62D054C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Services: self-Directed and in-Home nature</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each veteran selected by the Secretary for participation in the pilot program—</text><paragraph id="H3FB05CD297E24A18B9AC274CEEADFD53"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may select, from among the entities listed under subsection (b)(3) that are accessible to the veteran, the entity from which services shall be received by the veteran under the pilot program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBFEB85A503745539A192344BFE18D7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may elect to receive services under the pilot program at a location that is not a traditional medical setting, such as at the residence of the veteran, in lieu of receiving such services at a hospital, nursing home, or other medical facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC1DD405304D14706831A45D8A22A9A08"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The pilot program shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date on which the pilot program commences.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD453ECB5D0D747BC936129F8110FB888"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of termination under subsection (e), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on the pilot program. Such report shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HF4133C96AAA64AA094A1CEEA6E429516" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed overview of each entity with which the Secretary entered into an agreement under the pilot program, and the services that entity provided to participating veterans pursuant to such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA489CCE42024C60A9E8AEBC5AE050B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of the types of technology that eligible entities with which the Secretary entered into an agreement under the pilot program used to provide services to participating veterans pursuant to such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF00C246F43542309787F53352BED743"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An identification of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H828DAC2859F84CF7A77A50A794A71F1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of veterans that participated in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H501D1CC7184E4B2C89C084F6BC97E93F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of veterans that applied to participate in the pilot program but were not selected for participation as a result of the limitation under subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78446D2052FA474D9AF406E4A4DBDBFA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Of the veterans who participated in the pilot program, the number who, for the duration of such participation, received services under the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB84C363899A34650A3B53A9528422665"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the veterans who participated in the pilot program, the number who suffered traumatic brain injury while serving in the Armed Forces, including, for each such veteran—</text><clause id="HC561310C756A494096BCDA1DC359391A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a classification of the traumatic brain injury so suffered as mild, moderate, or severe (as the case may be); and</text></clause><clause id="H7AD3D857F61544F2AE0FACD247538E41"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an identification of the mechanism of injury.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B3E22CB6731497E8E193237747696F3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The percentage of veterans who participated in the pilot program (disaggregated by type of outcome specified in clauses (i) through (iii)) who reported that such participation resulted in the following outcomes, with respect to the individual veteran:</text><clause id="H75A7992C14D04F11BD103C27D0D49B38"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Quality of life improved.</text></clause><clause id="HE6A9F370CFBB425BBF5BE6748305E25D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Quality of life was unaffected.</text></clause><clause id="HB81A6D18B26A47F88585B4C22EA1B0EA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Quality of life worsened.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H561D447129824EF7B203CCBC925CB307"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A socioeconomic and demographic breakdown of veterans who participated in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE995476314DF42168E43DBFD3CD9E77F"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The type of housing in which the veterans who participated in the pilot program reside.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80C25F89F08C46999A9C1230FF66A4FF"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether the veterans who participated in the pilot program have access to personal care services from a caregiver, and if so, whether such services were furnished by the Secretary (including through a non-Department of Veterans Affairs health care provider providing such services under the laws administered by the Secretary).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8E638ADE0FA40C4874C6461D1779518"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Such other information as may be determined relevant by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB43E0EC778F47F29588D05D4EFE6FB9" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Source of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts required to carry out this Act shall be derived from unobligated amounts appropriated to the Veterans Health Administration and determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

