<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H39990C2F018B4BA7B87BA067DD78F00E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1499 IH: Good Jobs for Good Airports Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1499</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require small, medium, and large hub airports to certify that airport service workers are paid the prevailing wage and provided fringe benefits, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC30D7B69566345BE8546B57D4A643A31" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H63A3D787F1E44DB28B29D3FDFE11F3CA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Good Jobs for Good Airports Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H149C2785D75C41E48CAD8169B181A0B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purposes</header> <subsection id="HBE110FA7CA0D496A9B881952DE9B1B3F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFF971E3701244579844D48530D2F0E59"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Safe and effective airport operations are essential to national commerce and the general welfare.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H89F1DEE969754940883C1CDEED836D13"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A well-trained, stable workforce at our Nation’s airports is critical to ensuring public safety and security, as well as the health and safety of the public and protection from infectious diseases.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38553F344B0E41F48F1D95D812CE270C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Federal Government has invested billions of dollars in creating and maintaining our Nation’s aviation infrastructure, reflecting the national interest in maintaining airports across the country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F0A4E0E03524B309B2238EC20C01B14"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Airport services are most effective when the workforce providing those services is able to earn a living wage and able to secure adequate health benefit coverage. In fact, meeting the growing challenges of operating airports securely and efficiently requires the recruitment and retention of excellent staff in all of the classifications of employees who work in airport services and operations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H90816A94B0324B708A7A76E52C24D90B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Effective management of airports and effective airport security requires that workforce turnover be reduced and that the workforce be highly trained and highly motivated.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8A3D61D3D8B4A31863C31A947846355"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In connection with setting workplace standards for those engaged in airport services, there is a need to establish an orderly system that reconciles competing interests without undue disruption.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF792CC68DE8F4AD8931DB7246F0694E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this Act are—</text> <paragraph id="H2A93CD6E7800467385BB1C9B05DBAD0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to provide a mechanism for ensuring minimum workplace standards for individuals who work in airports whose operators are grantees of Federal assistance or derive revenue from fees authorized by the Federal Government; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95DCD150A9C4474D8C3C295F5BF472C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to serve the best interests of the people of the United States by stabilizing the workplace conditions of the labor pool that supports our Nation's airport operations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2D41A4FD3A494E73A380FD4946E5692E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendments to title 49 of the United States Code to ensure minimum wage and benefits for covered service workers</header> <subsection id="H94EC73F44F6A42B9B7E31D205DB3555D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Covered service worker definition</header><text>Section 47102 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD06A08D667494B2DAB3D893841087E1A"> 
<paragraph id="HC5003183ECF34DC1A9EBCD916C9B6F34"><enum>(29)</enum><text><term>covered service worker</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H29F76844330E41DE93EEDE478C92B7A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an individual who furnishes services on the property or premises of a small hub airport, medium hub airport, or large hub airport, performing—</text> 
<clause id="HE09D93C33CCA46FFBF7F8208E4456EB0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>functions that are related to the air transportation of persons, property, or mail, including—</text> <subclause id="H20510302D743489391B88310E36791C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the loading or unloading of property on aircraft or a building or facility on the airport property;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE9D5B286C7C64CE0BCBBCB853DAE1816"><enum>(II)</enum><text>assistance to passengers, including assistance under part 382 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBC28A28529544D1BB38094558888FCAC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>security;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA6AAA1BCAECB4743A682936753D68C76"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>airport ticketing or check-in functions;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H55E7E6D7257041FC8547FFD0DA393102"><enum>(V)</enum><text>ground-handling of aircraft or related equipment (but not including mechanical services, machinery maintenance, car service maintenance, services at maintenance-related stores, fueling, de-icing, or other mechanic-related functions);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2E1009854CD941149B1C7344EE8F3C96"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>aircraft cleaning and sanitization functions or waste removal;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD84CCA677B364292AB753F7AED9CF662"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>cleaning within an airport terminal or other building or facility on the airport property;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA76E0649393C4E08A5E47100B8AE1314"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>transportation of employees or individuals within the airport property; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBB9117A1002B4003B0470206351920A6"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>ramp agent functions;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H73C074F5530244C3AAE0D40583FA4EBC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>concessions services on the property of an airport, including—</text> <subclause id="HAC2A92015E714652B3EF90CC8BF4D4C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>food service, including food and beverage service, wait service, busing, cooks, or cashiers;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H72BB216670414AC68A3C31FC49274CEC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>retail service, including retail related to news or gifts or duty-free retail services;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9B2CFFE8D388486E82FD6BF4FACBCBF2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>cleaning for concession services;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H92C72FF29DC349D1AABD8413DA4B6A3A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>security for concession services; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3A6A90EF71A2438E8D0732072A4E1B91"><enum>(V)</enum><text>airport lounge services, including food, retail, cleaning, or security services for or at an airport lounge;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HFE98DAA9CAB54ECAA27DB26856E8FC75"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>airline catering services (such as the preparation or assembly of food, beverages, provisions, or related supplies for delivery, and the delivery of such items, directly to aircraft or to a location on or near airport property for subsequent delivery to aircraft at the airport); or</text></clause> <clause id="HC3B73735AC8041F695AE2C034A1D3583"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>food or beverage service, housekeeping, or hotel service at a hotel located on airport property;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0C30D4FEB6B8493EA2811874697BC7F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes an individual without regard to any contractual relationship alleged to exist between the individual and a contractor or subcontractor;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H89829486D7E8493D9A347162C7438F45"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall not include an individual to whom the exemption under section 13(a)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/213">29 U.S.C. 213(a)(1)</external-xref>) applies; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0CD66F49E6E04B059AEE5ABAE2F2BB63"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall not include an employee of a State, municipality, or other political subdivision of a State or an authority created by an agreement between 2 or more States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H2E465BEFD6A3438B967CDF44FD3675D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Airport improvement</header><text>Section 47107 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H732B02DF0FC946589A911054AC9537EE"> 
<subsection id="H04679AE86D194D8A95DF7389D70F93AA"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Labor standards for certain airport service jobs</header> 
<paragraph id="HBD472B3C2F8C4F6992A062C26C090F74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation may approve a project grant application under this subchapter for an airport development project at a small, medium, or large hub airport only if the Secretary receives written assurances, satisfactory to the Secretary, that the airport owner or operator will ensure that all covered service workers, including those subject to a collective bargaining agreement, employed by any employer at such airport shall be paid a wage and fringe benefits that are—</text> <subparagraph id="H2AFAD7C9450544F7AC6BE45C2C7CEEB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to such wage, not less than the higher of—</text> 
<clause id="H0FDE3F73935B4E86B39A10D7479D10D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>15 dollars per hour;</text></clause> <clause id="H16AA05014A7C426680DC9F82C2E9BD5F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the minimum hourly wage for the appropriate locality and classification as determined in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/67">chapter 67</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Service Contract Act</quote>), by the Secretary of Labor under paragraph (2)(A)(i), adjusted annually to reflect any changes made by such Secretary in such determinations;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H14582884CAB34633A6CC704CA03E06C8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the minimum hourly wage required under any Federal regulation, policy, or directive issued by the President pursuant to subtitle I of title 40, United States Code, for workers employed in the performance of any Federal contract for the procurement of services; or</text></clause> <clause id="HF3D70C99F0BE46369BEA3D389E726807"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the minimum hourly wage required under an applicable State or local minimum wage law (including a regulation) or policy, including the policy of a political subdivision of a State or an authority created by a compact between 2 or more States or 1 or more States and the District of Columbia, that applies to covered service workers; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAC9800EF725D4D2CB29CA74C64892732"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to such fringe benefits, not less than the greater of—</text> <clause id="HB44E524A314A4985A643CCAE8ED33FB9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the minimum fringe benefits for the appropriate locality and classification as determined in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/67">chapter 67</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Service Contract Act</quote>), by the Secretary of Labor under paragraph (2)(A)(i), adjusted annually to reflect any changes made by such Secretary in such determinations; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1DDA4A7094DA4983A00D717FA67F76A9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the minimum fringe benefits required under an applicable State or local law (including a regulation) or policy, including the policy of a political subdivision of a State or an authority created by a compact between 2 or more States or 1 or more States and the District of Columbia, that applies to covered service workers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H744A3672CF664B9FBBAA8E558229D5FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Classifications and wage determinations</header> <subparagraph id="HDCB2441E986642E58A8F3EC596A85548"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall—</text> 
<clause id="H6945BED086494DE1AB39AA21C42EABC9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this subsection and in accordance with subparagraph (B), issue a wage determination with minimum hourly wage and fringe benefits under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/67">chapter 67</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Service Contract Act</quote>), appropriate for each class of covered service worker for purposes of subparagraphs (A)(ii) and (B)(i) of paragraph (1); and</text></clause> <clause id="H8444E855BCC64D7EB935491BE3C71F2E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this subsection and annually thereafter, provide to the Secretary of Transportation the applicable minimum hourly wage and fringe benefits required for purposes of such paragraph with respect to each such class of covered service worker.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC20375378E3247ED827BF65FEFBF6486"><enum>(B)</enum><header>New occupational categories</header><text>In issuing the wage determinations under subparagraph (A)(i), the Secretary of Labor—</text> <clause id="HAB02DBE2ECD648C380417A18575C1CDD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall ensure that each class of covered service worker is classified appropriately in a category of occupation covered under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/67">chapter 67</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H50BB7E80F4174A418A9D2B475F13E229"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the extent needed to carry out clause (i), may establish 1 or more new categories of occupation covered under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/67">chapter 67</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code, to ensure that all classes of covered service workers have an appropriate determination of minimum hourly wage and fringe benefits.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4FA98FACB2B9480F9806D3F5058D9377"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Airport sponsor certification</header> <subparagraph id="HB798535364F34582A8C4EE8B907EE3AF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requirement</header> <clause id="HD337E6DBFC994B1F8F2140390F890586"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An airport sponsor subject to the requirement under paragraph (1) shall certify to the Secretary, on an annual basis, that each covered service worker, including those subject to a collective bargaining agreement, is paid a wage and fringe benefits that comply with the requirements described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of such paragraph.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2C79878ECD3243FF9E891D74F95F51BE"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Evidence of certification</header><text>Where certification is required under clause (i), an airport sponsor shall obtain from each entity that employs a covered service worker a certification that each such covered service worker at such airport is paid a wage and fringe benefits that comply with the requirements described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0771C0E896B74210BEFDFABF5DA23E80"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compliance report</header><text>In order to ensure compliance, an airport sponsor subject to the requirement under paragraph (1) shall require any entity that employs a covered service worker at such airport to submit a report to the airport sponsor, on an annual basis, certifying compliance with the requirements described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDD90A62929EB471E935EF680FF679EFA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Compliance authority</header> 
<clause id="H3DD2441746E647449F5B4E5BE0C87866"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation shall have the authority to ensure compliance with this subsection.</text></clause> <clause id="H87D0FB178EDA46199C438F9CD307FF6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Good faith compliance by airport sponsor</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation may, at the Secretary's discretion, determine that an airport sponsor shall not be considered to be in violation of this subsection upon a showing of good faith compliance with the requirements of subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA1E64374B294EE9B8B918663A0059DA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Non-preemption of State or local laws</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall preempt any State or local law (including a regulation) or policy that requires a higher minimum wage or otherwise requires greater benefits or protections for covered service workers than the requirements of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0DC89E0A1ABD41F4B39D07257BD2B7DD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Passenger facility charges</header><text>Section 40117(d) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H866EACC7F5454A219D6D4D7C95675AFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32AFF8AEEF2742F1946AF0A45A3FBAD5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H11FA17EFF5484A42A2358BEA97D1F0D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18F0887AEC834BACB27C04BD43DD2C78"> <paragraph id="HB31EB5090ADF4ADEB3230A95B4EFED1B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the eligible agency has certified that it is in compliance with the requirements under section 47107(x), if such requirements apply to the eligible agency; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA086C4FEB63F44049C627F7C8EB755EE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Discretionary grant</header><text>Section 47115(d)(2) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H545C87F264D34FF98C8D7E6A0088CC17"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6DC9551B85534433AEB8301F5DB4A1CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41FAB95420094DD8B2D1A25DA72AE496"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9083144C468345A099FA84522C8FD842"> 
<subparagraph id="H1FA436B9EECF49C7AD74027C512A6926"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the sponsor is in compliance with the requirements under section 47107(x), if such requirements apply to the sponsor.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H70A954E1866E47608A306D91A51B30FC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Restriction on the use of certain funds under the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act</header> <subsection id="HA5146E1C233E47C2A508C5A2E225327C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Airport infrastructure grants</header><text>The amounts made available under the heading <quote><header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-small">Airport Infrastructure Grants (including transfer of funds)</header-in-text></quote> under the heading <quote><header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-intermediate">Federal Aviation Administration</header-in-text></quote> in title VIII of division J of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/58">Public Law 117–58</external-xref>; 135 Stat. 1416) shall only be made available to a person who is in compliance with the labor standards for covered service workers, as required by the Secretary of Transportation under section 47107(x) of title 49, United States Code (as added by section 3(b)).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B4A0D84495E44B4BE3323767AB052F9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Airport terminal program</header><text>The amounts made available under the heading <quote><header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-small">Airport Terminal Program</header-in-text></quote> under the heading <quote><header-in-text style="appropriations" level="appropriations-intermediate">Federal Aviation Administration</header-in-text></quote> in title VIII of division J of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/58">Public Law 117–58</external-xref>; 135 Stat. 1418) shall only be made available to a person who is in compliance with the labor standards for covered service workers, as required by the Secretary of Transportation under section 47107(x) of title 49, United States Code (as added by section 3(b)).</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

