<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9E52CB6DF3264A1FB9CC02A6A5CBD58E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6322 IH: End Financing for Hamas and State Sponsors of Terrorism Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6322</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To evaluate and disrupt financing to Hamas, and to amend title 31, United States Code, to prohibit the exchange stabilization fund from being used to deal in Special Drawing Rights from state sponsors of terrorism, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD082710277BC40868AFDC0EDACEE3F14" style="OLC"><section id="H083253B385B94F3F9D7C5A6D585FB73E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>End Financing for Hamas and State Sponsors of Terrorism Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H16C06517FAC4414F9D445B5DE314608E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on Hamas financing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate a report (which shall be in unclassified form but may include a classified annex) that includes—</text><paragraph id="HF5EF02F64C0546509B2C70643826EDBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of the major sources of financing to Hamas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3183F3F594AB4A7E91367EBDD8A13745"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of United States and multilateral efforts to disrupt illicit financial flows involving Hamas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6318843B365C422A8BFCBC5EE0BD3E8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an evaluation of United States efforts to undermine the ability of Hamas to finance armed hostilities against Israel; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H149F0325B41E4841AB39414566F31D34"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an implementation plan with respect to the multilateral strategy described in section 3.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H3937F0DFADF44509AF13C2DEE1268872"><enum>3.</enum><header>Multilateral Strategy to Disrupt Hamas Financing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury, through participation in the G7, and other appropriate fora, shall develop a strategy in coordination with United States allies and partners to ensure that Hamas is incapable of financing armed hostilities against Israel.</text></section><section id="H9EB97148041F4914B27CFCD552EEFA36"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of the exchange stabilization fund to exchange Special Drawing Rights of, or to benefit, state sponsors of terrorism</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5302 of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBDEC330823E34226BE87B1B4E1718473" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H1AACFA1B7258405487D83CA102B82A52"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of fund To exchange Special Drawing Rights of, or To benefit, a state sponsor of terrorism</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not use the fund to—</text><paragraph id="H475A4AC4E27447C5B1848646C32A80D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>deal in Special Drawing Rights from any country determined by the Secretary of State to have repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism, as designated pursuant to section 1754(c) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019, section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act, or section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CEC5B7DAE0C439FA78FA6F850D2822D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>engage in a transaction with any other entity that will result in the provision of any asset to such a country.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

