<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB9C2B97F6494653A03A77045E132985" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3143 IH: Teachers Leading, Educating, Advancing, and Designing Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3143</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to award grants to eligible entities to carry out teacher leadership programs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H31822B1AE84D4A958C245939C4F4B070" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H8794CF5E32B249A18C4B87489A9009D4"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Teachers Leading, Educating, Advancing, and Designing Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Teachers LEAD Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H45586E50C13E44FF8BEF5161EDE10EBE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HC46F8B203568488FA4FE4E8B61EF3154"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Decades of research have shown that teachers are the single most important school-based factor in student achievement, and an analysis by the Brookings Institution indicates that a high level of teacher turnover is negatively associated with student achievement, and is higher in urban schools and schools with more economically disadvantaged students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H37F6C74A4C1E4BBAA6FD45C786DC5767"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A report by the National Commission on Teaching and America’s Future estimated that districts spend between $10,000 and $17,000 for each teacher who leaves the district, making teacher turnover and attrition a costly issue for school systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5420C7C43DB94849A9A7730E27E1181F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States education system is experiencing an ongoing teacher recruitment, retention, and shortage crisis. According to a National Education Association survey in January of 2022, 55 percent of all teachers, 62 percent of Black teachers, and 59 percent of Hispanic or Latino educators said they were more likely to retire early or leave the profession.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H286F51917F6E4E0990503E98A87430A1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the same survey, 74 percent of teachers report having to fill in for colleagues or take on other duties due to staff shortages, while 90 percent of respondents pointed out that teacher burnout is becoming a very serious issue. As a Nation, we face the possibilities of vacancies and educator burnout being exacerbated by educator shortages.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D99738FE8E24FA388E563C2D2C3ECC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An analysis by the Economic Policy Institute of teacher turnover data suggests that low salaries, lack of professional development opportunities, and a difficult school climate, including lack of teacher input into school policy, are common factors behind teachers leaving the workforce.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0AC070CDCF2B43BBA3633794512ECE2A"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to data from the National Center for Education Statistics, racially and ethnically diverse teachers are more likely to work in high-need schools. Unfortunately, these schools often experience high teacher turnover rates, which can have a negative impact on students.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA091EA24845C45A68BD6969F5F668725"><enum>(7)</enum><text>According to a report by Teach Plus and the Education Trust, teachers of color report that they have considered leaving the profession because they lack agency, autonomy in decision making, and opportunities for leadership.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46AC3D42EA3B41D8B2440FE027F80834"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Studies show that all students benefit from having racially and ethnically diverse teachers. These benefits are magnified for students of color, who experience improved academic performance, higher graduation rates, and increased interest in pursuing higher education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5B9AF72BED5B4BCC8B5859C7F227EE43"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Teachers of color are also underrepresented in schools, with only 20 percent of the teacher workforce identifying as people of color versus over 50 percent of public school students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H42227B9D8F1240B38890768A8D89B9DB"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Studies show that there is a positive link between professional leadership opportunities, job satisfaction, and retention of classroom teachers, and that compensation for teachers’ added leadership responsibilities increases teacher retention.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0977F4273450494C97C8FA1076EC04DB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In a Gates Foundation Survey, only 12 percent of all teachers surveyed reported receiving consistent job-embedded mentorship and professional development from veteran teachers, despite multiple studies showing that consistent mentorship improves student learning.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4002F4CBB1674DED97F7D679698ADB13"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The New Teacher Project found that only 26 percent of high-performing teachers agreed that their school leadership identified opportunities or clear paths for teacher leadership roles.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B856ECC25674CAA9EA2B85E2D279BA5"><enum>(13)</enum><text>According to a report by Teach Plus and the Education Trust, teachers’ investment in their schools and their likelihood of retention is greater where opportunities exist to innovate and advocate on behalf of students, especially when a teacher acts in partnership with school and district administration to address student and teacher needs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80FFAB6D9F4A4F03ADDA7358721D4816"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Structured leadership programs are an effective way to help combat the nationwide teacher shortage and improve teacher retention by empowering teachers and establishing formal peer mentorships between effective and experienced teachers and those just entering the profession, which also leads to academic and socio-emotional benefits for students.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EE6FD8348564964BB949F71CDD15EED"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Federal policies are needed to encourage and fund the establishment of structured leadership programs at public schools, especially in high-need schools and school districts.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H83D3BD59E00640BB85828F0694B9655C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Teacher leadership grant program</header> <subsection id="H6C34F049A67D4E74B8B2AB56B921F514"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H8635AA24E76D4DF3924C46E16F931CBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <quote>educational service agency</quote>, <quote>elementary school</quote>, <quote>local educational agency</quote>, <quote>paraprofessional</quote>, <quote>school leader</quote>, <quote>secondary school</quote>, and <quote>Secretary</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32564015EA534E159516240013F84C77"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Distributed leadership</header><text>The term <quote>distributed leadership</quote> means a range of approaches wherein the school leadership shares aspects of the traditional set of school decisions, organization, management, and operations with teachers in a manner that is coordinated by, agreed to, and led by the teachers and school leadership.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19A554211CA64687B2461CE30AAA5635"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H380B477100F54D298401E5FF4097E4FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency or educational service agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCA55905943AC4A95A0249DF6E4DD55A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a consortium of local educational agencies or educational service agencies; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA7FF89678CE0442A9FF98E675DF1442D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a partnership between a local educational agency or educational service agency and—</text> 
<clause id="H777F375DB5014C80A207579B70A33E7F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization with demonstrated expertise in teacher leadership programs, as determined by the Secretary;</text></clause> <clause id="H8F37A7B41CAB4A26BCA8726B0574A5A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State educational agency in the same State as the local educational agency or educational service agency with demonstrated capacity in supporting teacher leadership programs, as determined by the Secretary;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDC5CCA61AAC14441A8E7AA159C27340D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)) that awards postsecondary teacher certificates or degrees and has a demonstrated capacity in supporting teacher leadership programs or teacher diversity, as determined by the Secretary;</text></clause> <clause id="H7C0C127F1C664624B5A3CE8A922B44CF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a Minority-Serving Institution, Tribal College or University, or Historically Black College or University; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA48031E39CF64172B96CC04F91D8A7F6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D6B4BBF38EC43F29B7DFCA1D6199044"><enum>(4)</enum><header>High-need educational service agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>high-need educational service agency</quote> means an educational service agency that serves a significant number or percentage of high-need local educational agencies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F3ED2217EC344B58A33F297EE0D7105"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High-need local educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>high-need local educational agency</quote> means a high-need local educational agency, as such term is defined in paragraph (10) of section 200 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021(10)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD61963D497AB492D8A03652C12B2C785"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Indian Tribe</quote> means the recognized governing body of any Indian or Alaska Native Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, component band, or component reservation, individually identified (including parenthetically) in the list published most recently as of the date of enactment of this Act pursuant to section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H884EEC1AE49544A3AC48D6060A424BA2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Minority-serving institution</header><text>The term <quote>Minority-Serving Institution</quote> means any of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HF96CB95B19FC464EA12A8AC9EAFAC5AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An Alaska Native-serving institution, as that term is defined in section 317(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB46524FBB6E340F684E6E77DE8C71C41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A Native Hawaiian-serving institution, as that term is defined in section 317(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3C663B49D83C42F9A38397BE6AED58B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A Hispanic-serving institution, as that term is defined in section 502(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101a">20 U.S.C. 1101a(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDCC2B254A21E4B658FFE48571692C154"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A Predominantly Black institution, as that term is defined in section 371(c) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067q">20 U.S.C. 1067q(c)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA3C4006DD0914545801D4A72A0A81D7A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution, as that term is defined in section 320(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059g">20 U.S.C. 1059g(b)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD1D93B74ADC04F03A75AADE927647394"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A Native American-serving, nontribal institution, as that term is defined in section 319(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059f">20 U.S.C. 1059f(b)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2124C077B48F47A5BAD2028AA8FC2E3C"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Tribal college or university</header><text>The term <quote>Tribal College or University</quote> has the meaning given the term as defined in section 316(b)(3) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c(b)(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA61789D91DD34BB1AA063DDDE0637767"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Historically black college or university</header><text>The term <quote>Historically Black College or University</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>part B institution</quote> in section 322 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1061">20 U.S.C. 1061</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H545224E4C5F144D5B97D751276C649E6"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Teacher leader</header><text>The term <quote>teacher leader</quote> means a teacher who is selected to participate in the teacher leadership program under this section. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H84BCE2DD0DC84B72B9D5FEBEB6B8BFBE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header> 
<paragraph id="H913A35BA531847279768F9D7DF240B1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to carry out teacher leadership programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB850FCA1EFB34786B1F6805173D29AEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reservations</header><text>From the total amount appropriated to carry out this section for a fiscal year, the Secretary—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC363828C3B3B449EB913036C40AA1C72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall reserve not less than 5 percent to carry out subsection (h);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEB7219D8D48B4232AA0779A68417CE66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may reserve not more than—</text> 
<clause id="H90E9D60762264618A741B1B9D247FA19"><enum>(i)</enum><text>3 percent to provide technical assistance to, and support the capacity building of, the programs assisted under this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="H5EBE046E0A4D4B3D9E37AC6AEF9B402F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">0.5 percent to support program administration and data collection under this section; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAD1F83A0FA54167B9FD9475F1012655"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may reserve not more than 3.5 percent to award planning grants to eligible entities in order to assist those eligible entities in developing a program proposal in accordance with subsection (h).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50B3BB879D6D494F9B35557C7AA67724"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant period</header><text>The Secretary shall make grant awards for not more than 3 years and may extend grant awards for not more than 2 additional years if the grantee is making progress in achieving program objectives.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46E142119FDF4CA1841E0C7D6AEAEDDE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that, to the extent practicable, grants are distributed among eligible entities that will serve geographically diverse areas, including urban and rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H629E1D71DD704D4BA34B77788CE47F01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header> <paragraph id="H3543D4EE42374F66AAF7F23C6CEE9759"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4ADDB44C2E0A4C0392E45E189E184EE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the eligible entity will implement the program proposal described in paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H901A040C1D6042E4A6442D37094DDBFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how grant funds will be spent, including if and how other Federal, State, Tribal, and local funding sources may be used to supplement grant funds in order to meet the requirements of the teacher leadership program; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3028D674CD0F4CD3B9198BA99CBC9CA0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the eligible entity will continue the teacher leadership activities assisted under the grant after the grant period ends.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7062A92FEF0E4D33A68003C8273328DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program proposal</header><text>The program proposal required under this subsection shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFECE283FD996404F8632BE03A9A52A54"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Program plan</header><text>A plan to establish and operate a teacher leadership program that includes the following:</text> <clause id="H68A9119BA1784D45B414278B1B21BE2C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how the eligible entity will ensure that the program includes the participation of teacher leaders in goal setting, professional learning, or collaboration with content experts, school leadership, colleagues, or leadership of an eligible entity, with respect to—</text> 
<subclause id="H182AC3EAB5D84D619906CBAC108D8FAC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>strategic planning or development at the school level and the level of the eligible entity, including planning and development relating to school climate, community engagement, teacher professional development and mentorship, and student growth; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA16F4608B5A14B198FD7821E396F625A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>implementing practices to support children’s social, emotional, or academic needs, such as—</text> 
<item id="H3139C378159D4959BEBA07F31323D889"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>planning the design of and organizing the physical space, organizational structure, wraparound services, and culture of schools to support positive, healthy, and developmentally appropriate relationships among members of the school and community;</text></item> <item id="HF5AE3CE772B9431EABBDBFC6CCEC41E1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>creating multi-tiered and integrated systems of support to address student academic and non-academic needs; </text></item> 
<item id="HDB08903526D44D4381E2F4C1054974D9"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>creating and fostering safe and inclusive learning environments that enable authentic, culturally and linguistically responsive learning in identity-safe settings; or</text></item> <item id="H367363BA7947451296E8978F4EBAD1EA"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>supporting participating teacher leaders in earning additional certifications or licensure to develop their expertise such as National Board Certification, or licensure in special or bilingual education.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H0266A5E459464FF79F29CD364C5055A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A description of how the eligible entity will ensure that the program offers structures for shared decision making, distributed leadership, common planning, and collaboration between participating teacher leaders and school leaders.</text></clause> <clause id="H5BF445893311472886A94B6237A8D0CF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of how the eligible entity will ensure that teacher leaders receive training and support to improve skills related to acting as instructional leaders, coaches, mentors, or facilitators of professional learning.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE74843DE29C444068BCD790B06C4206A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how the eligible entity will use this program to establish and sustain teacher leadership opportunities to increase teacher retention, including for teachers who are individuals from underrepresented populations in the teaching profession.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2CFFD1044678413596874ACA4E865929"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text>A description of how the eligible entity will meet each of the following program requirements:</text> 
<clause id="H7E03DF8C13CD48988F2875D09A6F829B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Ensuring all full-time teachers with at least 3 years of full-time teaching experience that maintain their roles as classroom instructors and are employed by the local educational agency may apply to participate in such program as teacher leaders.</text></clause> <clause id="H772A61B9C6A348FDB80C48FCB1A1F226"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing the selection criteria for program participation to all eligible teachers described in clause (i), which will include selection based on an eligible teacher’s demonstrated ability in carrying out not less than 5 of the criteria in subclauses (I) through (VIII) and a commitment to growth in other criteria where they do not have a demonstrated ability of—</text> 
<subclause id="HCDB9DD5BF3AE439BBCE46A4428BF2E46"><enum>(I)</enum><text>carrying out leadership responsibilities while maintaining a role as a classroom instructor;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H960E14935E774A5D823B57F4A6BD890B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>focusing on improving or advancing the vision, goals, and priorities of the eligible entity that employs such teacher using evidence-based and practice-based data;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9BE8B2E516CA49569AD70189331EEEDE"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collecting and analyzing data of student social, emotional, and academic outcomes or teacher professional outcomes and taking actions to improve student outcomes, teacher outcomes or professional learning informed by such data;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H36098F8DDF2049C1B6F13A0376659778"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitating collaborative, evidence-based and practice-based, and sustained professional learning with peers, including mentorship and instruction leadership, that lead to improvements in teaching efficacy, professional outcomes or student social, emotional, and academic outcomes;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCDD40572B6A74BE0914CFACEBD7929A6"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">analyzing socioeconomic, cultural, and historical contexts of students, their communities, and the local educational agency, including existing pedagogy, school policies, and school-based outreach to families and the community to create safe, healthy, and inclusive school climates;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7F807424EE8545EF8451238BECF3161E"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>implementing and evaluating strategies aimed at addressing areas of demonstrated need in the school at which the teacher is employed, including increasing wraparound services, academic supports, family engagement, and community-based services;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H841349FD109F477FAA1227211D1CD8B8"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting teachers to effectively serve students with disabilities, English learners, and students who are linguistically, racially, and culturally diverse, economically disadvantaged, or historically underrepresented to increase their social, emotional, and academic needs; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H43F11AEFF34443B680A974F5573130B6"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>using, customizing, or developing lesson materials and instructional resources to meet the unique needs of students and the eligible entity to further students’ academic achievement and social-emotional learning.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H0071DF8AF0DB41D99089D81599AB96B5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensuring that all teachers and paraprofessionals employed by the participating local educational agencies served by the eligible entity are eligible to participate in programming led by a teacher leader, when applicable.</text></clause> <clause id="H08B5729842A94164AC5BC2BED07C7BC9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Providing financial assistance or compensation to teacher leaders who participate in such program for the additional responsibilities that are directly related to the teacher leadership program.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA639FF7A696B46BCA92FE358636729CD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Allowing the financial assistance or compensation described in clause (iv) to be substituted for paid time off or satisfaction of a contract requirement—</text> <subclause id="H654320BA7D584B5296C9BA833C31C268"><enum>(I)</enum><text>at the request of the teacher leader receiving such compensation; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H817E94EDF29D4D66B17FD4E2A4599496"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with the authorization and agreement of the eligible entity that serves the elementary or secondary school at which such teacher leader is employed.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HFAAE757872FE4EBBA122B69D51922827"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Requiring teacher leaders to support their own development and professional growth by evaluating themselves and each other using evidence-, research-, or practice-based rubrics.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8FC7543341224CA2B88C4272F7E4F8CF"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Consulting with other teachers who are not teacher leaders when developing and implementing the program as described in this subparagraph.</text></clause> <clause id="HF81AFDBFEB364068B966F7067BCAB214"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Expending funds granted under this Act to permit—</text> 
<subclause id="HE0C50068D25341759E0ECF776517A2B5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not more than 5 percent of such grant funds for administrative expenses; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H91B0088C2B2F4ED49E6BA3494561D5D9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not less than 95 percent of such grant funds to—</text> 
<item id="HF50589D4D7FA4F12AEE32704D1C5D9FD"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>implement the program proposal described in this paragraph; and</text></item> <item commented="no" id="HF249D13F3A574789AE2563CF4145B3EA"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>carry out 1 or more of the following activities:</text> 
<subitem commented="no" id="H12353FA686FA475886232348A0C61942"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>Facilitating collaboration between program participants.</text></subitem> <subitem commented="no" id="H43253BFEDD5340E2AAEF02E6EA5B5490"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>Developing or improving instructional materials.</text></subitem> 
<subitem commented="no" id="H156A50FCB7A74C48B6698BA39A34613C"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>Supporting the reallocation of work hours for teacher leaders between classroom responsibilities and responsibilities as a teacher leader.</text></subitem></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2E5FC10C2E6140A48194440C80CBF874"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity applying for a grant under this section shall include in such application an assurance that the eligible entity will comply with reporting and evaluation requirements described in subsection (f).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H902D6D976099409D8798F50107C50375"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that are or that include—</text> <paragraph id="H1A572567837A48C6A6EF17D4B9F3EE7D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a high-need educational service agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H704134B432864FF0BC8655054757DA64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a high-need local educational agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB798A20AB1C4571BCF1875319C71E1D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a local educational agency that receives basic support payments under section 7003(b)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7703">20 U.S.C. 7703(b)(1)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2585F7E466A644BAB2CD143AB7810F70"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe, Tribal educational department or agency, or Tribal educational organization;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD24DB293F307408E9FD810DA6DD0DD39"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian community-based organization or Native Hawaiian educational organization (as those terms are defined in section 6207 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7517">20 U.S.C. 7517</external-xref>)) or an Alaska Native organization (as defined in section 6306 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7546">20 U.S.C. 7546</external-xref>));</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEAAD5E327EBF44BA961B358CE83574C7"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a local educational agency that demonstrates in their program proposal under subsection (b)(2) a plan to use this program to establish and sustain teacher leadership opportunities to increase teacher recruitment, including teachers who are individuals from underrepresented populations in the teaching profession;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4DDF6D869AD84418A7C9BDA96ECD23FC"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an eligible entity described in subsection (a)(3)(C) that has a successful track record in supporting teacher leadership models, retaining teachers, or advancing teacher diversity; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E4CC2DD007242BE9BE016050B8E0261"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a Historically Black College or University, a Tribal College or University, or a Minority-Serving Institution.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7563A27FFCC6479D96C9ED481BE1B066"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header> <paragraph id="H99F3D6C4E05544D79E29BDABB3590B3D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity awarded a grant under this section shall use—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H74CD611A818D4BD28B132096A01179BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 5 percent of such grant funds for administrative expenses; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBFD0593C375E40C2B8048F96E81E9C32"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not less than 95 percent of such grant funds to implement the program proposal described in subsection (c)(2) and, at the eligible entity’s option, carry out activities described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE333F7F22C3F413C87C0332C0C6EBC8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permissive uses of funds</header><text>In addition to implementing the program proposal under subsection (c)(2), an eligible entity awarded a grant under this section may use such grant funds to facilitate—</text> <subparagraph id="H617E1CC320EB4B8098C7BB5D6633D56F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collaboration between program participants;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H70F20E4A8E7B431FBD534BCFA293FD91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>instructional materials development; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H308E5D05EC994DBE94B7A2E4FD88B7FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the reallocation of work hours for teacher leaders between classroom responsibilities and responsibilities as a teacher leader.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H268121A89C3F4FE2A98BEE6808474533"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports and evaluation</header> 
<paragraph id="HD645945601724B33809D4DBA4DE679AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports to the secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary, in a timeline determined by the Secretary, all information necessary for the evaluation described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45F7BB8123B04E9C9693EFCCC9A085F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences, shall carry out an independent evaluation measuring the effectiveness of the activities carried out under grants awarded under this section, including information about whether participating eligible entities experience greater teacher retention than non-participants. In carrying out the evaluation, the Director shall collect and analyze the following information, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, and gender:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6ACF5729725C4A0593C906074CF774A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>With respect to each participating eligible entity—</text> <clause id="H4DE8B62325F84443B545A8968F3F86F7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the 3-year retention rate of all full-time teachers, disaggregated by—</text> 
<subclause id="HE85E91BAA9BC40699752F9EA94A6EDA3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>teachers who are in their first year of teaching; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4A523D91FB904D4F8A99BA7231109A64"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">teachers who were hired by such local educational agency in the same school year as one another;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HACB6CD314774440DBC32F47431C1E77A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 5-year retention rate of all full-time teachers, disaggregated by—</text> <subclause id="H44E2638A055645419A22DE8751AAA1E9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>teachers who are in their first year of teaching; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H27B3554DE66941B680867F8CC938FDDD"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">teachers who were hired by such local educational agency in the same school year as one another; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HFC1ECFE18AD844E29606A8ACF838710C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the employment status of full-time teachers who were hired by such educational agency, in the same school year in which such eligible entity received a grant under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6AD5731BFA1749DAB541863D1E65EF25"><enum>(B)</enum><text>With respect to each teacher leader participating in a program established using such grant funds, the following:</text> <clause id="HCD5B99D652B74404AC38EC98D054EDD1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of years of teaching experience such teacher leader had at the time of program participation.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H69ABFFA3B6604DB5928CB43267D2533B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether such teacher leader is employed by a local educational agency served by such eligible entity.</text></clause> <clause id="H44008C3827B44241869CD7D449872E10"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If such teacher leader is not employed by a local educational agency served by such eligible entity, the reason for leaving.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H90554E9644C643AFAD35FC9A92974757"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The year in which such teacher leader was first employed as a teacher.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2356A54F553241AA9FA2D5430969E26C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The aggregated data submitted under paragraph (1) and the results of the evaluation under paragraph (2) shall be made publicly available on the website of the Department of Education, except that such publicly available data and results shall not reveal personally identifiable information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2FD0CEA04A77470599D3407BB6917DC4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the Secretary makes awards to an eligible entity under this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Indian Affairs of the Senate, the Committee on Natural Resources of the House, the Secretary of the Interior, and the Institute of Education Sciences a summary report of the preliminary results and impact of the teacher leadership program. The Secretary shall submit to such committees, the Secretary of the Interior, and the Institute of Education Sciences an annual report of the results and impact of the teacher leadership program for each year of the grant thereafter.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB335DC93648749C5BC6EADA1381283BC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Bureau of Indian Education Teacher Leadership Programs</header> <paragraph id="HFCF9B0639B58458BB42B4B525C33986F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of the Interior, shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H50DF58747EA64B28A92C81F316F88A1A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and implement a teacher leadership program plan for Bureau schools (as defined in section 1141 of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2021">25 U.S.C. 2021</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1EE6F7850F32495B973A5CCC4F7ED3BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>award grants to Bureau-funded schools described in subparagraphs (B) and (C) of section 1141(3) of the Education Amendments of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2021">25 U.S.C. 2021(3)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1997C6724A87472E9A8F52ECE345659D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of the Interior and Indian Tribes, may waive any requirement under this section or prescribe an alternative or substantially similar requirement if the Secretary finds that the waiver or alternative requirement is necessary for the effective delivery and administration of activities under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2E149A9B1B084A18AE2AEED5BF00ED98"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Planning proposal grants</header> <paragraph id="H077E4A8855844EC4AF07618774D8FDD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may award planning grants to eligible entities to enable those eligible entities to develop a program proposal under subsection (c)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4739EF134C2C44DB928CB962D9602363"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each eligible entity that desires a planning grant under this subsection shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD6ABCEC96D94090ACAA0DC57D1BD2EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A planning grant under this subsection shall be for a period of not more than 1 year.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9DBB0AEA25D94114BC773F8B67648D02"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $400,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 4 succeeding fiscal years.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

