<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H92E4D7956CDF42B2847B09AF2DDAD7B3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4802 IH: Accountability for Workplace Misconduct Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4802</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that certain agreements containing nondisclosure clauses regarding claims of discrimination, harassment, and retaliation shall not be enforceable, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H414D565EF4DA466F905C55FC2D554640" style="OLC"><section id="H11544DAE1A914AD19647607452661802" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accountability for Workplace Misconduct Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4A164DB696BD40AC8E46F91BEB44DAA9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Employer requirements pertaining to claims of discrimination, harassment and retaliation</header><subsection id="HA094AE1A35C74745BFBB094A067EF8A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, an employer shall establish a process for receiving and investigating allegations of discrimination, harassment and retaliation. Such process shall—</text><paragraph id="H65DCD8FD438A4A21A1BB47E0FA4307CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide multiple methods (e.g., in writing, verbally, or by electronic submission) for the employer to receive and respond to a report of unlawful conduct under the laws described in section 3,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE037A97D540D44A0B82639D5475C4172"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allow employees to confidentially report unlawful conduct,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3358E811407E4BD9ABDB6C701EB65ED3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be provided to each employee upon the beginning of their employment and be prominently posted for employee reference,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB88746EF03DD41089F9E0D7536F638DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>require prompt investigation of unlawful conduct reported by an employee,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB222277124C74BBEA21D6594ED9064B3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>require notification to the employee of the initiation, conclusion, and outcome of the investigation of such reported unlawful conduct, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2954EFC0C1843638CDDD605C43D90C3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>make available (e.g., through an human resources representative) factual information pertaining to support services (including medical and mental health care, seeking legal representation, information about legal rights) the employee may choose to access.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H672FB2050C2F456DB0241811C7D2992F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investigation</header><text>An employer shall conduct a thorough and neutral investigation into any report of unlawful conduct made by an employee. Such investigation shall include—</text><paragraph id="HCBEFB75D1CB74BC2BECB49DC898F49CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>appointing impartial individual or entity that is adequately trained to investigate such conduct and notifying the employee of the investigator, scope of the investigation, and estimated time frame of the investigation,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3141868906D3404583C8EFB8C5319B90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>notifying the employee of the initiation, conclusion, and outcome of the investigation of the reported unlawful conduct,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94097406F26147C2B05209E691FDC629"><enum>(3)</enum><text>informing the employee of investigation status upon request of the employee, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H107159171805489C8190905111913A41"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the greatest extent practicable, interviewing witnesses or other individuals identified by the employee claiming the misconduct under investigation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H140D4FA60CAA45C9939D524557F7E77B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The employer shall furnish a report to the employee that documents the procedure followed by the employer during an investigation into the unlawful conduct reported by the employee and that shows the investigation complied with the requirements of subsection (b).</text></subsection></section><section id="H04C68EB778604EF0BB7D37138670F724"><enum>3.</enum><header>Unenforceability of certain settlement agreements containing nondisclosure clauses</header><subsection id="H0E963AFF0E2E452F804E7A06D79D32FB"><enum>(a)</enum><text>A nondisclosure clause included in a settlement agreement shall not be enforceable by an employer if—</text><paragraph id="H02114CC0B11449E7BF68428B2DF72720"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">it prohibits a party to such agreement from disclosing information to Congress, a Federal, State, or a local government entity, or a law enforcement entity, relating to conduct that is unlawful, or that the employee has reason to believe is unlawful, under—</text><subparagraph id="H56C6B0D22C1D4773800A634FCF808E61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (42 U.S.C. 2000 seq.),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D7B01E0BF02423FB6A24126812B6A30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 6(d) of the Fair Labor Standards Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(d)</external-xref>),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54F0A6FA98FA449D905181BAED5410B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>title I of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2477F1383B540029A49CCBF9B954383"><enum>(D)</enum><text>sections 501 and 505 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/791">29 U.S.C. 791–792</external-xref>),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D4F440C0E564B5E84B4E970375A43F4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/621">29 U.S.C. 621 et seq.</external-xref>),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78D9776E38FE4257B88D9AA3C3CD9849"><enum>(F)</enum><text>title II of the Genetic Information Non-discrimination Act (29 U.S.C. <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ff-1">42 U.S.C. 2000ff–1 et seq.</external-xref>), or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB55912CC3D7462897EC7AE61DCACC45"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Government Employees Rights Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1201">2 U.S.C. 1201–1224</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAA7A979BEC84CCE86412FB4D0FDB68D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the employer has not communicated to the employee that a nondisclosure agreement does not restrict disclosing information to Congress, a Federal, State, or Local government entity, or law enforcement,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB626139920B24EFF984819D9E76EECC7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the employer engages in behavior to intimidate, hinder, obstruct, impede, retaliate against, or otherwise discourage an employee subject to a nondisclosure agreement from communicating with Congress, a Federal, State, or local government entity, or law enforcement,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AA1C9B6EF784A1EA2FEF8FC59ACD323"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the employer includes terms in the nondisclosure agreement that requires an employee to notify the employer before disclosing information to Congress, a Federal, State or Local government entity, or law enforcement,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45278DF07F2347BCB19FC4ACCF140F1C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the employer fails to include in such nondisclosure agreement the following statement: <quote>Nothing in this agreement prevents you from disclosing information to Congress, a Federal, State, or Local government entity, or law enforcement about behavior you reasonably believe constitutes harassment, discrimination, or retaliation.</quote>, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB24F6DD7AF5C4C4F890F8530C4FD0147"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the employer does not grant an employee at least 21 days to consider an agreement before such agreement takes effect and allow the employee to rescind such agreement for up to 7 days after the agreement takes effect.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3F74FD4E3E674CDC8F41BC87F25F8C31"><enum>4.</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subsection id="H640968E03530416A9DB26FD9C1BD055D"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission shall establish a process by which employees may report a violation of section 2.</text></subsection><subsection id="H97888EEE02DD4D9EB717E85B9D6A61E8"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission shall treat reports of such violations in a manner consistent with title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e">42 U.S.C. 2000e et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H649916E843CE449487144E8B4643B671"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission shall issue rules that prescribe the requirements for employer compliance with, and employee notification of, the requirements of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB2A1F77A29744FC6814D37BBC45D00BC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> For purposes of this Act:</text><paragraph id="HBC46F1AE26E6463FAFFB6D186470B735"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nondisclosure clause</header><text>The term <quote>nondisclosure clause</quote> means a provision in a settlement agreement that forbids a party to such agreement to—</text><subparagraph id="HF306D63C6D984579B32B70C40389FD9E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>make a disparaging statement about a party to such agreement, relating to an allegation or report relating to unlawful conduct described in section 3, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD40D4C5F45048C9926D52CE9B947852"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disclose information regarding the existence of such allegation or such agreement or of any facts relating to such allegation or such report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA87E944E9FD4553984FEBDCB39B118A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Settlement</header><text>The term <quote>settlement</quote> means an agreement to settle an allegation of unlawful conduct described in section 3 and that—</text><subparagraph id="H92B88E975D22438690299DB260F3B88E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>applies to severance and separation agreements, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9B24F5FEE4A4C678AA4BFD2327C75F0"><enum>(B) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">precludes an employee from pursuing legal redress associated with an allegation of unlawful conduct described in section 3.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HE125520B443F44F7809884DFEB866A3E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall apply with respect to agreements made before, on, and after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

