<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H77CCB8ADE9554CE48877A77EB5DF1FB5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 973 IH: Thomas W. Dortch, Jr. Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 973</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to Thomas W. Dortch, Jr., in recognition of his unique and substantial contributions across America in lifting marginalized people, communities, and institutions that continue to struggle for economic mobility, access to greater opportunities, equity, and equality for all people.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAC98881B656C47359B81EF35153CF2AE" style="OLC"><section id="HB9611987E72C4AC5AAC2E38B2020BD5D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Thomas W. Dortch, Jr. Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1EEF701586BF47E586E4E1C3D84D2DA6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H09A15E0F671C480887446ABF121F79EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Thomas W. Dortch, Jr., was born April 12, 1950, in Toccoa, Georgia, to Lizzie Dortch and Thomas W. Dortch, Sr., and went on to become an influential leader and mentor as well as a successful businessperson and crusader for equal justice.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1ACE2FFCEED3487A9765CB84F650271D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After graduating from Whitman Street High School in 1968, Dortch attended Fort Valley State University in Fort Valley, Georgia, and graduated with a bachelor of arts in sociology in 1972. That year, he began his formal career by seeking to aid disenfranchised people through proposing projects for the State of Georgia. In 1974, he became the associate director of the Georgia Democratic Party. In 1978, Dortch began working as an administrative aide for Senator Sam Nunn of Georgia and eventually became State Director, the first African American to serve in this position. Dortch worked tirelessly to represent the interests of small businesses, minorities, and other marginalized individuals and institutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A49E854AFC440BAA60FC3F8E5E93E20"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1986, Dortch joined the 100 Black Men of America, an international mentoring program intended to improve the quality of life and opportunities for education and employment for African Americans. He served as chairman of 100 Black Men of Atlanta and became the chairman of 100 Black Men of America’s national board of directors. That same year, he earned his master of arts in criminal justice administration from Clark Atlanta University and married Carole Dortch.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0418F5BF6C204A81B0427963760E2B25"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 1994, after more than 16 years of government service, Dortch left his position to pursue his own business interests. He became CEO of the consulting firm TWD, Inc., and Atlanta Transportation Systems, Inc., a Fulton County paratransit company. He still holds both positions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93874A343F6B4BEBB170229DF565EFE8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Dortch has won numerous awards highlighting his achievements, including a Presidential Citation for volunteerism from President Barack Obama, the Martin Luther King, Jr., Distinguished Service Award, and the Concerned Black Clergy’s Salute to Black Fathers Leadership Award. Dortch has four children. His unique and substantial contributions across America in lifting marginalized people, communities, and institutions that continue to struggle for economic mobility, access to greater opportunities, equity, and equality for all people.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1F1DFF5CE6440779AAA0BE2822625D5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Dortch is an institution builder that included founding the National Black College Alumni Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc., cofounding the Georgia Association of Minority Entrepreneurs (GAME) to fill a void as an advocacy organization for minority business development, and cofounding the Greater Atlanta Economic Alliance as a capacity building and business development organization for the construction and transportation industries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD09D642CC6074AA09149B8A0AE271C02"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Dortch is the recipient of numerous awards and honors that celebrate his efforts, a partial list includes: listed in the 2001, 2002, 2003, and 2004 May editions of Ebony magazine as one of the 100 Most Influential African Americans; listed in Spring 2001 through 2014 Publications of Atlanta Business Chronicle as one of the 100 Most Influential Atlantans; 2008 Community Service Professional of the Year Award; 2008 FraserNet Community Service Award; and 2008 Global Leadership Empowerment Award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1B2B19F004948769D4972A4F8E6853F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Dortch’s volunteer board service includes serving on the Board of Trustees of Leadership Atlanta, Vice Chairman of the Board, Grady Memorial Hospital Corporation, Chairman of the Board, Friendship Force International, Chairman of the Board, Fulton/DeKalb County Hospital Authority; 2010 was inducted into Atlanta Convention and Visitors Bureau’s Atlanta Hospitality Hall of Fame; three-term Chairman of the Board, The Atlanta Business League: Chair, Fort Valley State University Foundation Board, Member of Operation Hope Board of Trustees, Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University Board of Trustees, Talladega College Board of Trustees, Clark Atlanta University Board of Trustees, and Chairman of the Board, National Coalition on Black Civic Participation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70D22BFAE91D49EB8721830CF4DA2D9B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In 2019, Dortch was inducted into the International Civil Rights Walk of Fame. The Civil Rights Walk of Fame was created to recognize the courageous soldiers of justice who sacrificed and struggled to make equality a reality for all. Dortch’s footstep impression joined those of civil and human rights icons, such as Rosa Parks, Archbishop Emeritus Desmond Tutu, Ambassador Andrew Young, Congressman John Lewis, and others.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5C24561E1DC4CB48BCAD8039E9AB1DA"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Dortch’s philanthropic and investment advice and counsel, particularly to corporate America, have benefitted countless minority organizations, institutions, and communities across America to realize and grow their programming and impact.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8D896F5A3084489947B7B0B2C031A21"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Dortch received honorary doctors degrees from Fayetteville State University, Jarvis Christian College, Fort Valley State University, University of Maryland Eastern Shore, and Livingstone College.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF5A21B71B12451C8620DDD48192DFDB"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Dortch was recently honored by Clark Atlanta University and the National Coalition on Black Civic Participation in 2021 with the creation of the NCBCP Thomas W. Dortch, Jr., Institute for Leadership, Civic Engagement, Economic Empowerment, and Social Justice.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB24C497D9CC448BDA418557948CC9DB6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="HB0C13A606D934C06A57890CAEA3C21EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design to Thomas W. Dortch, Jr., in recognition of his unique and substantial contributions across America in lifting marginalized people, communities, and institutions that continue to struggle for economic mobility, access to greater opportunities, equity, and equality for all people.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD710BDF4A3F24892ACCA99D56BB0B57B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (hereafter in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection></section><section id="H92D30AECE7DE43ECB9856987C9B7B8EC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section><section id="HDC5ABAE2EC2B42A1916C0D2348D546C3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><subsection id="HF2C60E0B6B5840A8AD2C1078EC0773E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6342392D58474CCAB0EEE06B7311E0E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9B2931C43274413FA7E3FEA60D8EBCC8" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="HACC75642126B4AFB820BC82563934417"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFBC000AC911649E782BFA3730875DFA4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

