<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56F3F0C960F34B94AC3140D550F2AC97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 411 IH: Lead by Example Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 411</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230120">January 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that Members of Congress and Congressional staff receive health care from the Department of Veterans Affairs instead of under the Federal Health Benefits Program or health care exchanges.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF7EA30703FE84A0CA47818FF6FD3AE96" style="OLC"><section id="H7853EC9EC742489F9AC570EE09E75990" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Lead by Example Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7D24E4DC29224629A862BB2415B44B4E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Health care furnished by Department of Veterans Affairs to Members of Congress and Congressional staff</header><subsection id="H98AC9E226C28495590EBD72789B058CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Health care benefits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, beginning January 3, 2025, the only health care plan that the Federal Government may make available to Members of Congress and Congressional staff with respect to their service as a Member of Congress or Congressional staff shall be health care provided through the Department of Veterans Affairs, including at facilities of the Department and non-Department facilities pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, and any other provision of law authorizing the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to furnish such care to veterans, as if such Members and staff were veterans.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0CF11B7C06054F258EC67E3C4D6928FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than September 15, 2023, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall jointly submit to Congress a plan to carry out subsection (a), including recommendations for any legislative actions the Secretary and the Director determine necessary to carry out such subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC137272312748A490FAF79A8D2A05DF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3CBDCA0FB7954AB5B2B9414D1E507479"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>Congressional staff</term> means the employees described in section 2107(1) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H277F22A5F814499682D44A8F8329D772"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Member of Congress</term> means a Member of the Senate or the House of Representatives, a Delegate to the House of Representatives, and the Resident Commissioner from Puerto Rico.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2E37495B0B2496BA5548FAB79A2800B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>non-Department facility</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1701 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

