<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H86F9B7ABF05D4987BB18146253376150" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5586 IH: Defending Each and Every Person from False Appearances by Keeping Exploitation Subject to Accountability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5586</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To protect national security against the threats posed by deepfake technology and to provide legal recourse to victims of harmful deepfakes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9620062BECE34449A642ED11FD31E2B8" style="OLC"><section id="H7E258348E6394AB2A871BCA7BFC1776E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defending Each and Every Person from False Appearances by Keeping Exploitation Subject to Accountability Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DEEPFAKES Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H64003B285E334C528AF6B13D631EAB42"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transparency requirements</header><subsection id="H42C01F7F51D54F5E85738F3523D4FFB0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/47">Chapter 47</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CF450B1C3FF461EA8F574D4672B0B5F" style="USC"><section id="H5E57ABA366764968BD337D76AFE6C9FF"><enum>1041.</enum><header>Advanced technological false personation record</header><subsection id="H80B0C5A1CC0E4E5E8EA2696ACA3FC42A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (j), any person who, using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce, produces an advanced technological false personation record with the intent to distribute such record over the internet or knowledge that such record shall be so distributed, shall ensure such record, complies with—</text><paragraph id="H97FB8D775CA845218425C253E7E3887B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the requirement under subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H691E115303D3492CA2C7E965EA3E5102"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEC9C2558316845A19B3B42DE1D72F341"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of an audiovisual record, the disclosure requirements under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8347604294FB46CBACCEFA7835B6D132" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a visual record, the disclosure requirements under subsection (d); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66355832DDC04EC682B2F4081DA60FC4" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an audio record, the disclosure requirements under subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD070E94D3394BE0BC01EC1EBDDC4728"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content provenance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any advanced technological false personation record which contains a moving visual element shall contain technologies, such as content provenance technologies, that clearly identify such record as containing altered audio or visual elements, or as having been entirely created through generative artificial intelligence or similar technologies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF4F4A5847F81426A851146B948284D76"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Audiovisual disclosure</header><text>Any advanced technological false personation records containing both an audio and a visual element shall include—</text><paragraph id="H2C727A9FAEEC4BCC934EFEC45D07FBB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not less than 1 clearly articulated verbal statement that identifies the record as containing altered audio and visual elements, and a concise description of the extent of such alteration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08579FE85F2342EBBA1946EEB89E767A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an unobscured written statement in clearly readable text appearing at the bottom of the image throughout the duration of the visual element that identifies the record as containing altered audio and visual elements, and a concise description of the extent of such alteration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFED65EF578734581B94F47CA29409055" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a link, icon, or similar tool to signal that the content has been altered by, or is product of, generative artificial intelligence or similar technology. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94CFCEEED1C741F7BBD38195471AD3F2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Visual disclosure</header><text>Any advanced technological false personation records exclusively containing a visual element shall include an unobscured written statement in clearly readable text appearing at the bottom of the image throughout the duration of the visual element that identifies the record as containing altered visual elements, and either—</text><paragraph id="H74DFD147CD2D4E76AF2BEC3596D00D58" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a concise description of the extent of such alteration; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33E0AB9316B94B0A9F25E2D757B5D5D3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a clearly visible link, icon, or similar tool to signal that the content has been altered by, or is the product of, generative artificial intelligence or similar technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H079FF63ED5854ED8B9CB9B2A4F928D72"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Audio disclosure</header><text>Any advanced technological false personation records exclusively containing an audio element shall include, at the beginning of such record, a clearly articulated verbal statement that identifies the record as containing altered audio elements and a concise description of the extent of such alteration, and in the event such record exceeds two minutes in length, not less than 1 additional clearly articulated verbal statement and additional concise description at some interval during each two-minute period thereafter.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0EFEA8727ECB4E54A905D1CD95B65F17"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Penalty</header><paragraph id="HE248CE31052B4D8F929F61100A619405"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Criminal penalty</header><subparagraph id="H5754E44FD51B4A3891EA84652A15753D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Failure to disclose</header><text>Whoever knowingly fails to comply with the requirements under subsection (a)—</text><clause id="HF3A7CBDBA7464656ACE969E18166547B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with the intent to humiliate or otherwise harass the person falsely exhibited, provided the advanced technological false personation record contains sexual content of a visual nature and appears to feature such person engaging in such sexual acts or in a state of nudity;</text></clause><clause id="H9099BDBDA1824897A0939111031B8D6C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with the intent to cause violence or physical harm, incite armed or diplomatic conflict, or interfere in an official proceeding, including an election, provided the advanced technological false personation record did in fact pose a credible threat of instigating or advancing such;</text></clause><clause id="H6AC0B4B7FE1946B299A16F3F16F56126"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the course of criminal conduct related to fraud, including securities fraud and wire fraud, false personation, or identity theft; or</text></clause><clause id="H0851B5EB01E844E980A5E39631AAE80A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by a foreign power, or an agent thereof, with the intent of influencing a domestic public policy debate, interfering in a Federal, State, local, or territorial election, or engaging in other acts which such power may not lawfully undertake;</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">shall be fined under this title, imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both. </continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBB2086E35624FCFA9DA95FA98448780"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Altering disclosures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly alters an advanced technological false personation record to remove or meaningfully obscure the disclosures required under subsection (a) with the intent to distribute such altered record and—</text><clause id="H82630567E68146EAA4E66CE12CA620C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with the intent to humiliate or otherwise harass the person falsely exhibited, provided the advanced technological false personation record contains sexual content of a visual nature and appears to feature such person engaging in such sexual acts or in a state of nudity;</text></clause><clause id="H7F67F179234A464B854C237E8EBA6077"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with the intent to cause violence or physical harm, incite armed or diplomatic conflict, or interfere in an official proceeding, including an election, provided the advanced technological false personation record did in fact pose a credible threat of instigating or advancing such;</text></clause><clause id="HB13B2275D43443839AFE9820DC49E4C1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the course of criminal conduct related to fraud, including securities fraud and wire fraud, false personation, or identity theft; or</text></clause><clause id="H3F973385FF514981AA6C1DA8C6DE264A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by a foreign power, or an agent thereof, with the intent of influencing a domestic public policy debate, interfering in a Federal, State, local, or territorial election, or engaging in other acts which such power may not lawfully undertake;</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">shall be fined under this title, imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both. </continuation-text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C3B11CBD10C40079A206F1744821301"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Civil penalty</header><subparagraph id="HEC011EAFD78D4CD9B647037D79AE2C07"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Failure to disclose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who violates subsection (a) shall be subject to a civil penalty of up to $150,000 per record or alteration, as well as appropriate injunctive relief.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC145A297A7D43FA8357FD33F6402807"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Altering disclosures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who alters an advanced technological false personation record to remove or meaningfully obscure the disclosures required under subsection (a) with the intent to distribute such altered record shall be subject to a civil penalty of up to $150,000 per record or alteration, as well as appropriate injunctive relief.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H311C2689D0094399B8667F76EC8A7D6E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><paragraph id="H89A9609C3EF1413EA276C884F19B0FDD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who has been exhibited as engaging in falsified material activity in an advanced technological false personation record may bring a civil action before the appropriate Federal district court for damages under paragraph (2) and injunctive relief under paragraph (3) against a person who violates subsection (a) or alters an advanced technological false personation record to remove or meaningfully obscure the disclosures required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97DC52C171AA4C24B53634E3AE76665B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Damages</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Damages shall consist of the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="H109BFBD88472402089279C4B3FB80BBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">actual damages suffered by the living person or the affiliated corporation or entity, and any additional substantially derivative profits of the person who violated subsection (a) or altered an advanced technological false personation record to remove or meaningfully obscure the disclosures required under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79AD59DF984C4044AD64CF2CB4BE8D91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$50,000 per record, if the living person or affiliated corporation or entity experienced a perceptible individual harm or faced a tangible risk of experiencing such harm;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86787C635D3045B59A7C1108885B342C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$100,000 per record, if the living person or affiliated corporation or entity experienced a perceptible individual harm or faced a tangible risk of experiencing such harm and the record purported to depict extreme or outrageous conduct by the living person; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H596DE9C6E3D04EC093D47EB4DE2645AF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$150,000 per record, if the advanced technological false personation record contains explicit sexual content of a visual nature intended to humiliate or otherwise harass the person falsely depicted as engaging in such sexual acts or in a state of nudity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E260C0548824DBDAE4787205B6859C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Injunctive relief</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Injunctive relief under this subsection shall include a requirement to comply with subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69FD05612BCA4F6DB3B56276752401BA"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Privacy protections</header><paragraph id="H823DCC33FCEE4F8BBADC190A5FC2121B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing this section, the Attorney General shall, to the extent practicable, consult with living persons exhibited as engaging in falsified material activity in advanced technological false personation records regarding measures the Attorney General can reasonably undertake to protect the privacy of such persons and minimize additional public viewings of such records.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H930B9AB54383472EA64B0CFA67636711"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Private actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A court in which a private action is brought under subsection (g) shall permit the plaintiff, upon petition, to file the claim under seal if the plaintiff can demonstrate a reasonable likelihood that the creation of public records regarding the advanced technological false personation record would result in embarrassing or otherwise harmful publicization of the falsified material activity in an advanced technological false personation record.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCE0A757CB28842328D8352E1CC5C98F1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><paragraph id="HC26DF7E8A67842B78AC7B026AC9261E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be interpreted as authorizing the production of an advanced technological false personation record which includes disclosures if such record is otherwise prohibited by law or regulation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA80F4EBBA6E4EFC8B61A1530B3DF41E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The word <term>advanced</term> within the term <term>advanced technological false personation record</term> shall not be interpreted as narrowing the definition of such term. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65055B925A3944D496349BF33FB0153F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be interpreted as a defense against, or as preempting or limiting, any Federal, State, local, or territorial laws, regulations, or policies that prohibit, impose more stringent standards in relation to, or provide additional or alternative remedies or damages in relation to, the production or distribution of advanced technological false personation records, deepfakes, or related content, including criminal and civil laws relating to copyright, tortious conduct, and false personation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H38FE33DF07BA4F8CA2C702CF0618032E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="H817CAFCEC25B4D89BFDD6CD94C1F6E7F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under subsections (c), (d), and (e) shall not apply with respect to any advanced technological false personation record—</text><subparagraph id="H0AECFDF66BE248248CE5C5D89888CA10"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">containing alternative disclosures regarding the falsity of the exhibited material activities which a reasonable person would deem to be more prominent than those required under subsection (c), (d), or (e), as the case may be;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC34A700460AE447DBC96AE44B860B8BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the process of producing such record, provided the ultimately distributed record is in compliance with such requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC914EC1827484212B1F6718262B5D96B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>which primarily contains images or sound recordings of actual persons, such as performing artists, and have not been substantially digitally modified;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98FDC7236F0147188B4FC441B81DD48A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>created in connection with editing a motion picture, television, music, or similar production or creating a derivative production thereof, the original content of which was created prior to the enactment of this section, in which the person appearing provided consent to their original appearance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H169DDB3DB26E48F09DA35DB4B203DA7B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>appearing in a context such that a reasonable person would not mistake the falsified material activity for actual material activity of the exhibited living person, such as parody shows or publications, historical reenactments, or fictionalized radio, television, or motion picture programming; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5F7E0ACD15140DBBCD77B3D239BB11C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>produced by an officer or employee of the United States, or under the authority thereof, in furtherance of public safety or national security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC63BAD3DCEA48F0990FD99970F215AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Digital content provenance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The digital content provenance requirement under subsection (b) shall not apply with respect to any class of advanced technological false personation records which the Attorney General determines by regulation should be excluded from such requirement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1872B7E58D294161BD2E426E61AF2708"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Advisory opinions, waiver, and standards</header><paragraph id="HB3CA99F85A724085B135AFD8420E5B74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisory opinions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD0FAC87BEFEC47E3BA4F8FC5AC83FC3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a process by which any producer of audio, visual, or audiovisual content may seek an advisory opinion from the Attorney General regarding whether their proposed production is required to comply with the requirements under this section; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8DFE86DA3DE453182B2D79DCE2103E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">respond to a request described in subparagraph (A) not later than 30 days after the date of submission; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BD03AFBDD7F4AFFBD8C059B6560C167"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not pursue enforcement action under this section against any producer who relied in good faith on such an advisory opinion.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88A0F61802C5419A8405D70974A4448E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General is authorized to grant, and shall establish and publish procedures to govern the issuance of, waivers from any requirements under this section to additional categories of advanced technological false personation records upon petition of any producer thereof if such producer can demonstrate that compliance with this section would impede their ability to engage in lawful activities protected by the First Amendment of the Constitution. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD52CFF4C6DB14289B14A7B26E0AAC493"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Digital content provenance standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Attorney General shall issue rules governing the technical specifications of the digital content provenance required under subsection (b) which stall include, if such is determined appropriate, a requirement for such digital content provenance to contain embedded or linked metadata.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAAA16DEADCC24DCFA5A319731B2E9E1C"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Venue</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any action under this section may be brought, in addition to in any district otherwise described in section 1391 of title 28, in the district where or the person falsely depicted in the advanced technological false personation record resides.</text></subsection><subsection id="H226D27FFF73F42B59C46CA96E008AC85"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Extraterritoriality</header><text>There is extraterritorial Federal jurisdiction over an offense under this section if the defendant or the depicted person is a citizen or permanent resident of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA969F5F08ECA4777BBA0B46AEA1464C5"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="HF503E8BD4B4B4CABA0C421C361B7F228"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced technological false personation record</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>advanced technological false personation record</term> means any deepfake, which—</text><subparagraph id="H8D3385C1D745448EAA1D00C0B894C1B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a reasonable person, having considered the visual or audio qualities of the record and the nature of the distribution channel in which the record appears, would believe accurately exhibits—</text><clause id="H32D7B557D00943759BD549BC72591127"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any material activity of a living person which such living person did not in fact undertake; or</text></clause><clause id="HAB083201F3334510929FA05B570D3937"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any material activity of a deceased person which such deceased person did not in fact undertake, and the exhibition of which is substantially likely to either further a criminal act or result in improper interference in an official proceeding, a public policy debate, or an election; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02654ECDD05E44CFB7275EE035C4E0BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was produced without the consent of such living person, or in the case of a deceased person, such person or the heirs thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1DF1B7224544DE1AC137A14F230B417"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Material activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>material activity</term> means any speech, conduct, or depiction which causes, or a reasonable person would recognize has a tendency to cause perceptible individual or societal harm, including misrepresentation, reputational damage, embarrassment, harassment, financial losses, the incitement of violence, the alteration of a public policy debate or election, or the furtherance of any unlawful act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD64538A3E774B0496A3DC8C66FF9CFD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deepfake</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>deepfake</term> means any video recording, motion-picture film, sound recording, electronic image, or photograph, or any technological representation of speech or conduct substantially derivative thereof—</text><subparagraph id="H440879DF8022466789A9C79174B609B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which appears to authentically depict any speech or conduct of a person who did not in fact engage in such speech or conduct; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2F21419A05D4A41809CDAEE787636E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the production of which was substantially dependent upon technical means, rather than the ability of another person to physically or verbally impersonate such person.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H036C1807216C4E3C83D1169B5577FB7D"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General, in coordination with other relevant Federal agencies, shall submit a report to Congress 5 years after the date of enactment of this section, and 5 years thereafter, describing trends related to prosecutions and civil penalties pursued under this section.</text></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA237EEB3FB14476B81D66391BBAACB1" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>1042.</enum><header>Deepfakes victim assistance</header><subsection id="H0BF9EE936E474F6CA72E982240269C56"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coordinator for violations directed by foreign nation-States</header><text>The Attorney General shall designate a coordinator in each United States Attorney’s Office to receive reports from the public regarding potential violations of section 1041 relating to deepfake depictions produced or distributed by any foreign nation-state, or any agent acting on its behalf, and coordinate prosecutions for any such violation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H197BECE1E3D74D00AD806EA42F49FD99"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordinator for false intimate depictions</header><text>The Attorney General shall designate a coordinator in each United States Attorney’s Office to receive reports from the public regarding potential violations of section 1041 relating to deepfake depictions of an intimate and sexual nature, and coordinate prosecutions for any such violation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5662EF6F8E246CFA30620BFE8B736FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Plan and guidance</header><text>On the effective date of this section, the Attorney General shall publish a report containing—</text><paragraph id="H793D65EB957642C7BE5E5FCFC2969C5A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan to effectuate and enforce section 1041;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A609309A942477396E0BA72E1C0D76B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the efforts of the Russian Federation and the People’s Republic of China, and such other states or groups as the Attorney General determines appropriate, to use deepfake technology to impact elections or public policy debates in the United States or other democracies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB1A627D881D48FB8672FE0C39C42EF7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the impact of intimate and sexual deepfakes on women and marginalized communities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1B1417917734798A9D7E89ABFB307D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in order to increase the likelihood of such prosecutions, official guidance to Federal prosecutors regarding any potential legal concerns that may impede such prosecutions absent clarification.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H75BF5BBC1E0643B2BCCA0B332FD7F2E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/47">chapter 47</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C9D916958EA4CD1BAF5F066FC518C53" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">1041. Advanced technological false personation record. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">1042. Deepfakes victim assistance.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H26EB59A551964794880B15F0227803D2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transparency facilitation</header><subsection id="H5C50C653313949A3955A76983D4196D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, for commercial purposes, develops a product that such person reasonably believes, in the context of the intended distribution of the product, will be used to produce deepfakes, as such term is defined in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act, shall—</text><paragraph id="H7743EE19A8D24A889410B30055E0C724"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure such product has the technical capability to insert digital content provenance and disclosures of the nature described in such section into such deepfakes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7657A43848F4EDAAE955BE1D6F2FB74"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include terms of use or other analogous disclosures with such product, which require the user of such product to affirmatively acknowledge their general awareness of their legal obligations under section 1041 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCF223EC7A0B4C19A708694037AE6C5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="H79C2796FBA384DFF9E494922E0CC17BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED91EFC1A564443D9FBE56BF23E7D3C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this section and the regulations promulgated under this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section. Any person who violates this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H121A918F1E02434B9CEB9D1EBE6148E1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission may promulgate regulations, in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, to implement this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HC5893F11C66745C6AEED562732E8A318"><enum>4.</enum><header>In rem litigation against foreign and unknown defendants</header><subsection commented="no" id="H6F29AA4CC189495DBDB46E9427087D8F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A living person, or an affiliated corporate or other entity substantially connected to such living person, exhibited as engaging in falsified material activity in an advanced technological false personation record (as such term is defined in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code), and subject to the exceptions under section 1041(j) of such title, may file an in rem civil action against an advanced technological false personation record, in the judicial district in which such living person or related entity resides, if—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H313CD93ABEA341CA89CABFC725A391C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the producer of such advanced technological false personation record is in violation of any provision in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, for which a private remedy is provided; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCED8337DB0E944C08B8550BFE5F6680A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the court finds that such living person or related entity—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8BD576289473477DAEFAF962ADFC5F16"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not able to obtain in personam jurisdiction over a person who would have been a defendant in a civil action in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3B28C06364314AA195920B21BD3B6F87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through reasonable due diligence was not able to find a person who would have been a defendant in a civil action under paragraph (1) by—</text><clause commented="no" id="H65ABF5D38B1C429186A6616872130228"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if practicable, sending a notice of the alleged violation and intent to proceed under this paragraph to the producer of the record;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H815FE21253A545D0A4FA9AFDB3416CD5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publishing notice of the action as the court may direct promptly after filing the action; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H333383F1F69A42D8BB37A3BDA8F65228"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>complying with such other due diligence measures the Attorney General promulgates through regulation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB64D22FE28814377BCEB0D2AB7B3E6DA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Service of process</header><text>The actions under subsection (a)(2)(B)(ii) shall constitute service of process.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H040E3B1A1BD6455C9274F82690385DC7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>In an in rem action under this section, an advanced false personation record shall be deemed to have its situs in the judicial district in which the person falsely depicted as engaging in material activity resides.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H9B7149FBA1D84DB9A9895AE08C985869"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Remedies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The remedies in an in rem action under this section shall be limited to—</text><paragraph id="H5BA81D327A86404A90E165E92C0FD844"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a court order declaring there to be a substantial likelihood that the material activity depicted in such advanced technological false personation record is false and lacking the digital content provenance and disclosures required under section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4383602D5C5148BDB51B3DCEC3F55DEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as appropriate at the discretion of the court, the forfeiture by the producer of such advanced technological false personation record of profits directly derived from the production and distribution of such record.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H651421F8B2EF44BBA5E641834BA7E2F7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Estoppel and additional remedies</header><text>A court order under subsection (d) may not be used for purposes of estoppel in subsequent litigation should the living person or related entity bringing suit file additional actions under other provisions of law. The in rem action established under this Act shall be in addition to any other civil action or remedy otherwise applicable and any other jurisdiction that otherwise exists, whether in rem or in personam.</text></subsection></section><section id="H386B8B6317324B75B130E7F5DBFBA407"><enum>5.</enum><header>Fraud and related activity in connection with audiovisual and biometric identity authentication</header><subsection id="HDFFE38DC5B5D43B78A6293829270F019"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Offense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1028 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7003FCFC05284A2B9F2582CA7C8D5760"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HC90A9B3CC4F745ADB1368B88EF1DE337"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>or a false identification document</quote> and inserting <quote>a false identification document, or a false audiovisual identification record</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F9D9A6D59804253960E4F3387077D8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>or a false identification document,</quote> and inserting <quote>a false identification document, or a false audiovisual identification record,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCB75DA0A301F4727996EE71A2ACD1473" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>a false identification document</quote> and inserting <quote>a false identification document, false audiovisual identification record</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A6F91BF0A7149CD84CCD85892EA3B1E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(1)(A), by striking <quote>or false identification document</quote> and inserting <quote>a false identification document, or a false audiovisual identification record</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD703733A3D4C46E099F2FBAEB3784A2A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c)(3)(A), by inserting after <quote>a document</quote> the following: <quote>or a false audiovisual identification record</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5145527B278345A09994BAAECFF99ADF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H3B83BFCEDE424035A79B19F7DDFDD6D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), insert after <quote>letters,</quote> the following: <quote>biometric indicators</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95C3C2C779BD4717A1EE13BFA45E8E01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), insert after <quote>other unique physical representation</quote> the following: <quote>including facial dimensions or characteristics, or visual imagery or content which appears to authentically depict any speech or conduct of a person who did not in fact engage in such speech or conduct</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E77C69A602D4D2185DB329CFFCCA5F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (11), strike <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC54A6DFA2F946708DE2CA3D5F517FAA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (12)(B), strike the period at the end and insert <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F7D2D567A4444A698712FCE972095B0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36D791F019634396A76212267C5AC632" style="USC"><paragraph id="HBE37B5F242A94FC88DDA20462EF6255C"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>false audiovisual identification record</term> means any advanced technological false personation record (as such term is defined in section 1041)— </text><subparagraph id="HDAC52972DD6546CDA48B4B6480312486"><enum>(A)</enum><text>used or attempted to be used by a person for the purpose of assuming the identity of the person depicted in the advanced technological false personation record without such other person’s consent; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05303667A695471296D14A4A05F72FF7"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H04D59B23C35043ADA31389095C5F01C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the use or attempted use of which is intended to further any unlawful activity that constitutes a violation of Federal law, or that constitutes a felony under any applicable State, territorial, or local law;</text></clause><clause id="HA28670EA7FC04EC0ADDA4D0C7BEEF73C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>depicts obscenity or sexually explicit conduct, considering the extent to which the record appeals to the prurient interest, is patently offensive, and lacks serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value; </text></clause><clause id="HEC6F9A5059EA4F35A6E8296CBF2F4149"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>depicts fighting words, which by their very utterance, inflict injury or tend to incite an immediate breach of the peace;</text></clause><clause id="HC8C2204EDA944EA6BF173B96206F23F0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>constitutes a call to imminent lawless action, and is likely, whether on its own or collectively in connection with related records, to incite or produce such action; or</text></clause><clause id="HA1CDDBB1662045B584DC5CBE4B2B2C23"><enum>(v)</enum><text>depicts or constitutes other activities or speech that the Attorney General determines by regulation pose a credible threat to the national interests of the United States, which, as of the date of such regulation, have been determined by a Federal court to constitute an unprotected class of speech under the first amendment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE76CE73DEF7C4AE78A40C3984FA00FF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) may not be interpreted as imposing any limitations on the applicability of section 1028 of title 18, United States Code, to any item which was covered by such section prior to the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H881EBD11A2A64C6290E897710B6AED4F"><enum>6.</enum><header>False personation</header><subsection id="HC3AB587AEC264FC98965868D2ECBE930"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/43">Chapter 43</external-xref> of title 18 of the United States Code is amended by adding at the end a new section as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA53AD4C8FBBF47B7B11B22482422513C" style="USC"><section id="H89BACA9793794D2CBF5B58352162C981"><enum>918.</enum><header>Deepfake false personation generally</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 911 through 917 of this chapter shall be interpreted to include producers, or persons who substantially and knowingly contribute to the production and unlawful use of, advanced technological false personation records (as such term is defined in section 1041), subject to the exceptions under section 4041(j). </text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H88FE703610F2412497EF18301CA1FD0F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20E9ACCF2F154740885C3F1C68FABF56" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">918. Deepfake false personation generally.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H8F0424ADF9CC47EFB2EF51EE8F7ABDEA"><enum>7.</enum><header>Detection of deepfakes</header><subsection id="HA2E02FE1121F4848803E408301866D4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of task force</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the heads of other relevant Federal entities, shall establish a task force within the Science and Technology Directorate of the Department of Homeland Security (in this section referred to as the <quote>Deepfakes Task Force</quote>), to—</text><paragraph id="H49FBE4F9F9CA4D3DA9A9E196F8F59FA6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advance efforts of the United States Government to combat the national security implications of deepfakes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H942A7028614F40C5882DAABD47FABBD5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as appropriate, research and develop technologies to detect, or otherwise counter and combat, deepfakes and other advanced image manipulation methods and distinguish such deepfakes or related forgeries from legitimate audiovisual recordings or visual depictions of actual events;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BEADEF9A3B344489B614C01A63D7E19"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide support, both administrative and scientific, to other Federal entities researching such technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F8DB521B29243EFB9CC965780C038A8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>encourage efforts of the United States Government to adopt such technologies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H878FBDFFDE9B41CE9D179F4F056222B0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>facilitate discussion and appropriate cooperation between the United States Government and relevant private sector technology enterprises or other nongovernmental entities, including academic and research institutions, regarding the identification of deepfakes or other advanced image manipulation methods.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3EB70194E8E4719B8C517F9D3FD867A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Private sector collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the United States Government develops technologies to reliably detect deepfakes and other advanced image manipulation methods and distinguish such deepfakes or related forgeries from legitimate audiovisual recordings or visual depictions of actual events, the President shall, unless the President determines such is contrary to the national interests of the United States, seek to make such technologies available to appropriate United States private sector internet platforms, including social networks.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDCF3850C66D14857B33880DD4DE0DEB3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter for five years, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate an unclassified report, which may contain a classified annex, describing the following:</text><paragraph id="H249CF96494E24F728DF5684AC9ABDD38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The activities of the Deepfakes Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36863AF2F6534CCCBC31AC7069F37891"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As appropriate, technological progress related to the detection of deepfakes and other advanced image manipulation methods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6636142451DA4E2FB2728A9E04E4E084"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">New developments related to the national security threat posed by deepfakes and other advanced image manipulation methods, which shall include a description of any efforts of the Russian Federation and the People’s Republic of China, and such other countries or groups as the Secretary determines appropriate, to distribute deepfakes or related forgeries in the United States or other democracies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27401B93376B448CBDAE2BA7FF945236"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Related efforts of the United States to combat and counter deepfakes and other advanced image manipulation methods.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H621500B1113943D5997F6E3F6283A2A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>The term <term>deepfake</term> shall have the meaning given such term in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H23D1B273D0BE4925A36A10DEFF89314E"><enum>8.</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall annually submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a classified written notification and, upon request, a briefing, regarding any known attempts of foreign countries to use deepfakes (as such term is defined in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act) or other advanced image manipulation methods to influence or otherwise interfere in an official proceeding within the United States, including an election.</text></section><section id="H06B17B4438ED4C71BE25F5CD6E0B8FAC"><enum>9.</enum><header>Information sharing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall take such actions as may be necessary to establish in the Department of Homeland Security an information sharing program relating to deepfakes (as such term is defined in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act) and other advanced image manipulation methods to permit online platforms (as defined in section 10(d) of this Act) to alert other such platforms to prevent the spread of a malicious deepfake or other related forgery, as well as to promptly alert for public dissemination news organizations regarding such deepfake or related forgery.</text></section><section id="HC7C38691B87C4AD7B2D7F35D5040D87D"><enum>10.</enum><header>Requirements for online platforms</header><subsection id="H0F79B838453B47CEAB2DBA00551D37B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technical capability relating to digital content provenance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A provider of an online platform shall ensure such platform has the technical capability to insert digital content provenance and disclosures of the nature described in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act, into any deepfakes that are distributed on such platform.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1AB5B72C128C4E13879A4A86851948BA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>System To detect deepfakes</header><text>A provider of an online platform shall have in place a system to detect deepfakes in the content distributed on such platform.</text></subsection><subsection id="H36E1FBB2838B49589FF90C52E5A44524"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="H475CAAA37D4645CF8DD03AC761AE9363"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB703B4642E1F4E5887DD330FB5274466"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this section and the regulations promulgated under this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section. Any person who violates this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BDC97D5702C4A7DBEE1B573552191B9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission may promulgate regulations, in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, to implement this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F9F10DD205A441C9FCE6FADD2AFE95D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEACB16A6FB5B4E639C8831E659AE0511"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deepfake</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>deepfake</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1041 of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F635972F0B343A68397A782FF56EB05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Online platform</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>online platform</term> means any public-facing website, online service, online application, or mobile application which is operated for commercial purposes and provides a community forum for user-generated content, including a social network site, content aggregation service, or service for sharing videos, images, games, audio files, or other content.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF224204316B5486BBEDE9A51AE5AB7DB"><enum>11.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect on the date that is one year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

