<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H88EFF9DBB1B14621AB7E90269862CB12" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3171 IH: Taiwan Representative Office Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3171</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to seek to enter into negotiations with the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office to rename its office the <quote>Taiwan Representative Office</quote>, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H119363BD0F0146C4B91A7C1F8AD6F18B" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HEB2EAB3967C14A20A1CFF641F939A472"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan Representative Office Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2BCE62113CF146D49563C54D2F1DA2A2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of and references to Taiwan Representative Office</header><subsection id="HC497B9118887478798F0D887568B16D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>It shall be the policy of the United States, consistent with the Taiwan Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/3301">22 U.S.C. 3301 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Six Assurances, to provide the people of Taiwan with de facto diplomatic treatment equivalent to foreign countries, nations, states, governments, or similar entities, and, consistent with this policy, to rename the <quote>Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office</quote> in the United States as the <quote>Taiwan Representative Office</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA0995DA67D8D4488A5E81C7DADC5E8D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Renaming</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall seek to enter into negotiations with the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office to rename its office in the District of Colombia the <quote>Taiwan Representative Office</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD856EFC0E4E34BDC891CD808727D8F39"><enum>(c)</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office is designated as the Taiwan Representative Office, any reference in a law, map, regulation, document, paper, or other record of the United States Government to the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office shall be deemed to be a reference to the Taiwan Representative Office, including for all official purposes of the Government of the United States, all courts of the United States, and any proceedings therein.</text></subsection><subsection id="H01B9278F404641AAA03404DEA56A8421"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as entailing restoration of diplomatic relations with the Republic of China (Taiwan) or altering the position of the United States with respect to the international status of Taiwan.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

