<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24DD7D6B48234C38B33911600CB071B5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6766 IH: Transparency, Readability, Understandability, Truth, and Helpfulness in Labeling Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6766</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to strengthen requirements related to nutrient information on food labels.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC2F26717645E49838ED2A5181B1A704B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB91B00C5988740FABC5A32672DA20A53" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transparency, Readability, Understandability, Truth, and Helpfulness in Labeling Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRUTH in Labeling Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8DCF8063955D484599795DDDC43E1CE3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H3BA4437C795E4D629626B8E60735B0DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The average American consumes substantially more added sugars, sodium, and saturated fat than is recommended by the Dietary Guidelines for Americans published under section 301 of the National Nutrition Monitoring and Related Research Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5341">7 U.S.C. 5341</external-xref>), potentially increasing their risk for hypertension, type-2 diabetes, and heart disease.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD00817C59F3B44F58F03997951FEBB29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A large body of experimental and real-world evidence has demonstrated that front-of-package labels that highlight high levels of added sugars, sodium, and saturated fat can significantly improve the nutritional quality of foods that consumers purchase or select.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8C7C3549DC7A49A4B43AF1CEC78445AF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Use of the nutrition facts label is lower among individuals with lower educational attainment and lower incomes, and robust research shows that front-of-package labels can be particularly beneficial for busy shoppers and for those with less nutrition literacy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B69C6B335DB4A5596F5CAAFFAA02CA0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Front-of-package nutrition labeling gives consumers quick and easy access to key information about the healthfulness of foods and can support healthier choices.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD74C3D3071FD48BCBAD7C94340627301"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Studies also show that front-of-package labeling can improve consumers’ understanding of the relative healthfulness of different foods.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HB5747ABEE40A41B79CD1AF77F37F378F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Additional requirements for front-of-package labeling for foods</header> <subsection id="H012235A87FD74DBB9C64CA5A923DD8B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Interpretive nutrition information</header><text>Section 403 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/343">21 U.S.C. 343</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4FB1DB33AD546619C7F1B7B39C04AB9">
<subsection id="HB2BBB55161544F2FA96FA4D9F23FDDF3"><enum>(z)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H71A36DBF70AC4D05A1A36E8F41E0F0BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in subparagraphs (3), (4), and (5) of paragraph (q), if it is food intended for human consumption and is offered for sale and otherwise required to bear nutrition labeling, unless its principal display panel bears interpretive nutrition information.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H663A4A8EA82F48BDBBF3F39952132779" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Final regulations regarding the interpretive nutrition information required under subparagraph (1) shall meet the following criteria:</text>
<subparagraph id="H4999E0564A314E2EBBD12C759453635E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>There shall be a standardized symbol system that displays calorie information related to the serving size determined under paragraph (q)(1)(A) and interpretative nutrition information related to the content of any nutrients that the Secretary determines the highlighting of which will assist consumers in maintaining healthy dietary practices (such as added sugars, sodium, or saturated fat), including by highlighting products containing high levels of such nutrients.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H498945F95F884709BFD4D77C02BD045E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The information shall—</text>
<clause id="HDC3726E665024391A09DB949B854AA4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>appear in a consistent location on the principal display panels across products;</text></clause> <clause id="H6A00801367A94A46AD2DE76CC65035D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have a prominent design that visually contrasts with existing packaging design; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H33267D87EC6E4E93AA0FBCDAC41F7FC1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>be sufficiently large to be easily legible.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H729CAEC33A854C81A283A35BDE7768BE" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In promulgating regulations regarding the interpretive nutrition information required under subparagraph (1) and the standardized symbol system required under subparagraph (2)(A), the Secretary shall take into account published reports by the Health and Medicine Division of the National Academy of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine regarding such information, and base regulations on the following principles:</text>
<subparagraph id="H148E1014FB8042F0AE0856FB921E23BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Consumers should be able to quickly and easily comprehend the meaning of the system as an indicator of a product’s contribution to a healthy diet without requiring specific or sophisticated nutritional knowledge.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA18427ACF1AA4AEA9C3E55A3BFFA53F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The nutrition information should be consistent with the Nutrition Facts Panel and with the recommendations of the Dietary Guidelines for Americans.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0B1C41DDEE924F549D60FCCD1D9A449D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The information should be provided to facilitate consumer selection of healthy product options, including among nutritionally at-risk subpopulations.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC726A343351744EEBFCDF5345FB03B66"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Secretary should periodically evaluate the standardized symbol system to assess its effectiveness in providing information to facilitate consumer selection of healthy product options and the extent to which manufacturers are offering healthier products as a result of the disclosure.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE17B22FE28F34797BF2D84E7BDD7439E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The implementation of the information disclosure should be accompanied by appropriate consumer education and promotion campaigns determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD9EB529E8F3841C983E3F73FC3B7951E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="H2BB7D7F7FCE942A0898C4BC6D9AF5D93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the effective date specified in final regulations issued by the Secretary pursuant to section 4(b), the Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall submit to Congress a report that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H872183C03D0C4342AA4480B8DE22DEEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evaluates whether implementation of the amendment made by subsection (a) has been associated with an increase in the prevalence of products containing low- or no-calorie sweeteners in the United States food supply; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD3A8C80F5B34946A71FDE8D1EBB4F2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describes actions that will be taken by the Secretary to quantify the levels of low- and no-calorie sweeteners in such products, if there has been an increase described in subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H062BF1D6B51A45C9A25CA34E14B491C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Update</header><text>Not later than 3 years after completion of the report described in paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to Congress an update to such report based on more recent data.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H3C0E054D723B42E4A3B0631C9F2336AA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Regulations</header> <subsection id="HDC6554A39BF24B56849D75C504B6CBB7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Proposed regulations</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue proposed regulations to carry out the amendment made by section 3(a).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H56284F6B4C1047D5B35DAF2037A96D59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final regulations</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall finalize the regulations proposed pursuant to subsection (a), which regulations shall specify the date on which the amendment made by section 3(a) shall take effect.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

