<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBED9DAABD4FF4352BAFC6BE892385A22" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1371 IH: Student Loan Disclosure Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1371</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve Federal student loan disclosures, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H949B6E3C77054E969933EA07429D9498" style="OLC"><section id="H27B580CA65C5419598E8C90ED988EFFE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Loan Disclosure Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H138FF6B80ADB4C6695E85C6AD4B9BA26"><enum>2.</enum><header>Required disclosures before disbursement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 433(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1083">20 U.S.C. 1083(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H469B917A9F5F4B6E8CFECB3D10FF2080"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (18);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FB0B2ACCDFF4D5A914878A710502C16"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote> at the end of paragraph (19); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36040E4594B4F7D9A7FA46D7982FAD7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F081418D8EA4D8495EF6F0F9DC3FA15" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HAB5CED9AE3604551BE23AD922725C6ED"><enum>(20)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a separate written or electronic statement, in simple and understandable terms, showing—</text><subparagraph id="H0290E8E4B1AD4EC7861B856018927014"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the loan or loans being disbursed—</text><clause id="H0AC572A3383D4EF0B3D43495DDEA0E29"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the principal amount of the loan, the stated interest rate on the loan, the number of required monthly payments to be made on the loan (which shall be based on a standard repayment plan or, in the case of a borrower who has selected another repayment plan, on the repayment plan selected by the borrower), and the estimated number of months before the start of the repayment period for the loan (based on the expected date on which the repayment period is to begin or the deferment period under 428B(d)(1) is to end, as applicable);</text></clause><clause id="HBFC20D9A81C947D994773783533F3AA0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the estimated balance to be owed by the borrower on such loan (including, if applicable, the estimated amount of interest to be capitalized) as of the scheduled date on which the repayment period is to begin or the deferment period under 428B(d)(1) is to end, as applicable, and an estimate of the projected monthly payment; and</text></clause><clause id="HC75044E9DC2F47219C7C52015E68BB38"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an estimate of the aggregate amount the borrower will pay for the loan or loans, including the total amount of monthly payments made over the life of the loan plus the amount of any charges for the loan, such as an origination fee;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82E4544999AE4FB4AAEA22E1D9BE48BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each other loan owed by the borrower to the lender, the information described in clauses (i) through (iii) of subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD699C414B8594050B95C9A27B2CD0D08"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an estimate of the total cumulative amount the borrower will pay for all loans owed by the borrower to that lender, including the loan being disbursed, as determined by calculating the sum of the estimated aggregate amounts the borrower will pay for each loan in accordance with subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H79C982924F4A463C8214DC68537BF7F8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Disclosure of projected monthly payment amounts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 433 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1083">20 U.S.C. 1083</external-xref>) is further amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HA54AC0FA1DF84366B8BB1421D54844D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by amending paragraph (9) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4221A2CAC7F421290053D6CB7110A83" style="OLC"><paragraph commented="no" id="H91632C21DCB6400BBDFFB7329AC0F559"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information of interest charges, accrual, and payments, including—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1AC01F2D93254ED4BE890B6682A34030"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the projected total of interest charges which the borrower will pay on the loan or loans, assuming that the borrower makes payments exactly in accordance with the repayment schedule;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0D8A16BAC0774A7CBB2987D8B710E4A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">projections of the borrower’s monthly repayment amount, assuming interest accrual resulting from capitalization of interest while the borrower, or the student on whose behalf the loan is made, is in school (as applicable), which shall disclose the cost to the borrower of—</text><clause commented="no" id="H06CFC31DCD9F40D59CFECC0F2C30654D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">capitalizing the interest; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HB917AAA530C7484081088D58B9493B1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>paying the interest as the interest accrues; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB2E8684A1227406DB83C04F8D5C5CF28"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if the borrower has already paid interest on the loan or loans, the amount of interest paid;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6F9531D055EB41B5917F87803BA3BBB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (d), and redesignating subsections (e) and (f) as subsections (d) and (e), respectively.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA1CF482BC6264AECAF398E5B04912EF9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Required monthly disclosures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 433(d) of the Higher Education Act of 1965, as so redesignated by section 3 of this Act, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H018F29FC2188466DA8171FF9C3FA5F80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the subsection header, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">during repayment</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">for the life of the loan</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H746A909461704E298EA935FE2326739F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B0C6B87F37E45A3BF6B98D1549B7ABA" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HCA58E9C0196241228C8A60ABFA199105"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Pertinent information about loans provided on a monthly basis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible lender shall provide the borrower of one or more loans made, insured, or guaranteed under this part or part D with a written monthly bill or statement (including through electronic means), in simple and understandable terms, of pertinent loan information described in this paragraph that—</text><subparagraph id="HBE073079C0D3444198EBEAEACFDC82F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to a borrower who is in repayment status, shall include a bill that corresponds to each payment installment time period in which a payment is due;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE8FAE4FD9B9436F9B1EECB260902C37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to a borrower who is not in repayment status, shall be a statement for each month of the period during which the borrower is not required to make a payment to the eligible lender, including while the borrower is in school and during periods of deferment or forbearance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2FB1D546A2A43F2900CAC2199C95B8C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall be provided to the borrower of a loan not more than 30 days after the first disbursement of the loan, and monthly thereafter for the life of the loan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E5533C340094B7894DD65BFA40A69AF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall include, for all outstanding loans made, insured, or guaranteed under this part or part D by the eligible lender to the borrower—</text><clause id="HD2124C9627074F4784919EB1BEAC22C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the original principal amount of each of the borrower’s loans owed to that lender, and the original principal amount of those loans in the aggregate;</text></clause><clause id="H01541384D78F441BA6D908B56B036042"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the borrower’s current balance on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate, as of the time of the bill or statement, as applicable;</text></clause><clause id="H44E63922FAB841D6B37BBEF5EC3A413A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the interest rate on each loan;</text></clause><clause id="HB25AFB36D3A34672A54F5AED8B3F9A3F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total amount the borrower has paid in interest on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HDC77269EA4C347239861D42B851F4609"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the amount of interest that has accumulated on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate since the last statement, and the total interest accrued to date on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate during the life of the loans;</text></clause><clause id="HBECEBB74B94E41FF9213D4AA8389B938"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the aggregate amount the borrower has paid for each loan and all loans in the aggregate, including the amount the borrower has paid in interest, the amount the borrower has paid in fees, and the amount the borrower has paid against the principal;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H4544FA0D425E4305A9904DC4617CA193"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an estimate of the aggregate amount the borrower will pay during the life of the loan for each loan and on all loans in the aggregate, including the total amount of monthly payments made over the life of the loans plus the amount of any charges for the loans, such as origination fees;</text></clause><clause id="H25FE2425C9824801A8243244C24FBF86"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>a description of each fee the borrower has been charged for the most recently preceding installment time period;</text></clause><clause id="HF74EFF330E404532AB73525B219F425B"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the date by which the borrower needs to make a payment in order to avoid additional fees and the amount of such payment and the amount of such fees;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H745632746671483EBFAA4A1B48F4C5F2"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a borrower who is not in repayment, the estimated balance to be owed by the borrower on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate, and an estimate of the projected monthly payment on each loan and on all loans in the aggregate, on the estimated date the borrower will enter (or re-enter) repayment status;</text></clause><clause id="HD080F9D5BCB4473BB668088B7F86DFC1"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>a reminder that the borrower has the option to change repayment plans, a list of the names of the repayment plans available to the borrower, a link to the appropriate page of the Department's website to obtain a more detailed description of the repayment plans, and directions for the borrower to request a change in repayment plan;</text></clause><clause id="HB8EE0FF3A7784D5E8AACF6324B5B7C9E"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>an explanation—</text><subclause id="H85FB3727641D4B8CA62ACF483DC1D0FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that the borrower has the option to pay the interest that accrues on each loan while the borrower is a student at an institution of higher education or during a period of deferment or forbearance, if applicable; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H528770F42A2E4420B61809E4D502D306"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the borrower does not pay such interest while attending an institution or during a period of deferment or forbearance, any accumulated interest on the loan will be capitalized when the loan goes into repayment, resulting in more interest being paid over the life of the loan;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H939B54D1BFB645E7B84D247F00D6F084"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>an explanation that making even small payments of any amount while the borrower is a student at an institution of higher education, or during a period of deferment or forbearance, if applicable, can help to offset interest accrual over the life of the loan;</text></clause><clause id="H58F80CBE4BD247D2A44BD0CFE9356C57"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>the lender’s or loan servicer’s address, toll-free phone number, and website for payment and billing error purposes, including information about how a borrower can make voluntary payments when a loan is not in repayment status; and</text></clause><clause id="HE1145D537B6C46D08DB513F99BA621F0"><enum>(xv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an explanation to borrowers that loans made under this part of part D have significant protections for borrowers that aren’t offered by the private market, including a number of income-driven repayment options, which offer flexible repayments terms and loan forgiveness for struggling borrowers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H4FF3B543D3764F7DB317D5EBD43D085E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report to Congress on consumer testing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HBF7A31E7F2F642D4BBB3A4977C8CFEA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct consumer testing by obtaining feedback from individuals, including borrowers and prospective borrowers of loans under the Higher Education Act of 1965, on the usefulness and effectiveness of disclosing monthly terms of loans under section 433 of the Higher Education Act of 1965, as amended by this Act, to maximize borrowers’ understanding of the terms and conditions of such loans; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A7E1EE3477B405A8FA30B4798485081"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report on the results of such consumer testing.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HABE7941BF8B24090AA7F82CC9C8D8842"><enum>6.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by this Act to the Higher Education Act of 1965 shall take effect 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

