<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H90C51C63B5304B0A8D365E68C15434D9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6901 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to submit to Congress a report on Department of Defense restrictions on the employment of former Department employees by certain countries.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6901</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231222">December 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to submit to Congress a report on Department of Defense restrictions on the employment of former Department employees by certain countries.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB93FE1C96DF1446F9193BA7502CF6A28" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBE24762F21994D3FBC134319E5C30BDB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on Department of Defense restrictions on employment of former Department employees by certain countries</header> 
<subsection id="H36EEE43CC44D4036BEE13E4CBB03409F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than March 30, 2024, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report that includes each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H5EB016E94D0848A1AC7D18B4E5375A8B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The policy of the Department of Defense in effect as of the date of the enactment of this Act with respect to any restrictions on the employment of former Department employees by countries that exhibit adversarial behavior against the interests of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7B373395010A4B168E384E95AC5D02BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An identification of the positions in the Department to which such restrictions apply.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H144A5619A92047EEBFAAA49FFD83080E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of any incident when a former employee of the Department worked for, or sought to work for, any such country in contravention of such a restriction.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H40B8DD5ADB2E47DB8C9D8F09CFD19A91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

