<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3F3983B831D74233B679DCE524EA7025" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6014 IH: Fire Sale Loophole Closing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6014</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231020">October 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, to restrict the ability to transfer business inventory firearms, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H86BACBD0FD6E48468FCE43967526A83E" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H042EB99833C248B29068A8CBF606A9F7"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fire Sale Loophole Closing Act</short-title> of 2023</quote>.</text></section><section id="H79C4ACD2E8CB435F969A75E4AB01C6B3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives has the authority to regulate how Federal firearms licensees discontinue their firearms businesses, and to clarify statutory requirements regarding firearms that remain in the possession of a former licensee (or a responsible person of the former licensee) at the time the license is terminated.</text></section><section id="HAAF157253DEA4B07BCF2C6058E40A68F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Restrictions on the ability to transfer business inventory firearms</header><subsection id="H92D5E67DD39F4771B7806B8A655242B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H777B6513F7194369BEC2ED4A9CCFAEAC"><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF57C22FCDAE42BAAB1DC2EF11269C9E"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Restrictions on ability To transfer business inventory firearms</header><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB6C0351168824692A4114FDE194243ED"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transfer after notice of license revocation or denial of license renewal</header><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB151F78643F847FFB7750E9637558470"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Offense</header><text>It shall be unlawful for a person who has been notified by the Attorney General that the Attorney General has made a determination to revoke a license issued to the person under this chapter to import, manufacture, or deal in firearms, or to deny an application of the person to renew such a license, to—</text><clause id="H3A1E299DBAB84833A5E99BF66A77B5AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>transfer a business inventory firearm of the person—</text><subclause id="H97B2A422CED24AC7A7B85233C1C75051"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">into a personal collection of the person; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HE6097AD46B2947AAA1CE7B5056372270"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to an employee of the person, or to an individual described in section 923(d)(1)(B) with respect to the person; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H22B6EFA8316444BF90E42EE1B92DD829"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">receive a firearm that was a business inventory firearm of the person as of the date the person received the notice.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B129EFDD42C48A1A3F803CFE36DB292"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rescinded determinations</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to a license revocation or denial determination that is rescinded.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCCDA2AB8B1654E3EAF005960CF61A9D1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer after revocation or expiration of license</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H702474BE496A4A358F4A43B9D9E17086"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Offense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for a person—</text><clause id="H4215C502EEAF451584CFFE40F6F5F60B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on or after the effective date of the revocation of a license issued to the person under this chapter to import, manufacture, or deal in firearms, or (in the case that the application of the person to renew such a license is denied) on or after the date the license expires, to—</text><subclause id="H28B0C9D776B541E48470B92695F4D06B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>engage in conduct prohibited by paragraph (1); or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC7C3F8BDA85F4B06874F98763C964318"><enum>(II)</enum><text>transfer to any other person (except a person licensed under this chapter or a Federal, State, or local law enforcement agency) a firearm that was a business inventory firearm of the person as of the effective date or expiration date, as the case may be; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H08D53255142D4A47BA5DEAE912228F36"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">after the 30-day period that begins with the applicable date referred to in clause (i), transfer to a person licensed under this chapter a firearm that was a business inventory firearm of the person as of the applicable date.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD9C78BCDFB0A48BBAF091423C6081349"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reversed determinations</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to a license revocation or denial determination that is reversed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88017289B43646C8A0E2523E37966A24"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transfer of former business inventory firearm out of personal collection</header><text>It shall be unlawful for any person who has transferred a business inventory firearm into a personal collection of the person, to transfer the firearm within 1 year after the transfer of the business inventory firearm.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H067B2121F3064308B5A93617C5FC70F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Business inventory firearm defined</header><text>Section 921(a) of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1AAF8F78B5624E8F9482286EE7276D7E"><paragraph id="H6326BC0D901C4A03A08FDCF21711E691" indent="up1"><enum>(38)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>business inventory firearm</term> means, with respect to a person, a firearm required by law to be recorded in the acquisition and disposition logs of any firearms business of the person.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HE0A96A0B70554BA0991453AC0D2C03B1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 923(c) of such title is amended in the second sentence by inserting <quote>section 922(aa) and to</quote> after <quote>subject only to</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDBCDF2BFAA974924818429305DD400C6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 924(a) of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA443E2C9E4D441EBA954781DC1FA651"><paragraph id="H27CAF0F3688044EDBFC23FA68D21B91E" indent="up1"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates section 922(aa) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 1 year (or, if the violation was willful, 5 years), or both.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H49B81D8CB91141A2BED164B2505CE94A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirement that license revocation or application denial notice include text of law prohibiting dealing in firearms without a Federal firearms license and restricting transfer of business inventory firearms</header><text>Section 923(f)(1) of such title is amended by inserting after the first sentence the following: <quote>A written notice described in the preceding sentence shall set forth the provisions of Federal statutes and regulations that prohibit a person not licensed under this chapter from engaging in the business of dealing in firearms or that are relevant in determining whether a person is doing so, and the provisions of section 922(aa).</quote>.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

