<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB42A9F45A26145BF8FF128BDDC2999E2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4892 IH: Medicaid Bump Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4892</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to provide a higher Federal matching rate for increased expenditures under Medicaid for behavioral health services (including those related to mental health and substance use), and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2EB34FDA0F494D51BB9B6C293E92E05B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC0CBB1E2179A4C619AA82BC5CE467269" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicaid Bump Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0220A62437CC4897BD6980543E8BE062"><enum>2.</enum><header>Higher Federal match for increased expenditures under Medicaid for behavioral health services</header> <subsection id="HAB8694A981994CA98412F8FA8EF5745D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1903 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA3F1FF5803634EAF9A315B4E9E15BC6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(5)—</text> <subparagraph id="HDFD60CBC01B2405285CCB0AA80354F9F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an amount equal</quote> and inserting <quote>(A) an amount equal</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF7A29DAE34024AC3B8469C508D235E3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block id="H9D9BCF2D70C34AEF924F8301A033FF87" style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>and</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCFAB3ED91FE04BC085B36CB82710537C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to subsection (b)(6), an amount equal to 90 percent of the amount by which—</text> <clause id="H57A2170C23E747DCA67879D4039C5952"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the sum of the amounts expended during such quarter which are attributable to the offering, arranging, and furnishing (directly or on a contract basis) under the State plan (or under a waiver of the plan) of behavioral health services (including those related to mental health and substance use), exceeds</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDF5C96AE99104CE08568946C94598553"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sum of the amounts expended during the corresponding quarter in the 4-quarter period ending on March 31, 2019, which are attributable to the offering, arranging, and furnishing (directly or on a contract basis) under the State plan (or under a waiver of the plan) of such services, plus</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H354DA068867A4C24A26ADE14E328C393"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H102BBAE71D0443AA9C598B43FF4F5BA2" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H27607FE601384C7E9ACA21DE2C2B6735"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Accountability and maintenance of effort requirements for additional federal funding for increased expenditures for behavioral health services</header><text>As a condition for receiving the funds the Secretary is otherwise obligated to pay to a State under subsection (a)(5)(B), a State shall meet the following requirements:</text> <subparagraph id="H74AF48CC53934E3C8D36A864223FCA47"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>The State shall use the funds received under such subsection to supplement, not supplant, the level of State funds expended for the offering, arranging, and furnishing (directly or on a contract basis) under the State plan (or under a waiver of the plan) of behavioral health services (including those related to mental health and substance use) through programs and activities in effect as of April 1, 2021.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA816A5115AE341A7985DC97C141AD0F2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of funds for activities that improve delivery of behavioral health services</header><text>The State shall use the funds received under such subsection for activities that increase the capacity, efficiency, and quality in the provision of behavioral health services (including those related to mental health and substance use) delivered by providers, including through increases in payment rates for providers of those services and the adoption of other measures that ensure a reduction in staff turnover.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0AB6335D0E2548DEBDD7115F98723ABD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sub-Regulatory guidance</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue sub-regulatory guidance to States specifying the services that are behavioral health services for purposes of subparagraph (B) of section 1903(a)(5) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(a)(5)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H017756B274364E25BFB016396BBE8607"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to calendar quarters beginning on or after January 1 of the year beginning 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H72A0920026144291A1FD2CDAD686001C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report regarding behavioral health service</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Finance of the Senate a report regarding behavioral health services (including those related to mental health and substance use) provided under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) in each State, specifying the payment rates for such services, the rationale for deriving such payment rates, and utilization of such services, as such data are available.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

