<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7B42156856004E8CB8A3B4A05655E8D4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4181 IH: To designate the area between the intersections of International Drive, Northwest and Van Ness Street, Northwest and International Drive, Northwest and International Place, Northwest in Washington, District of Columbia, as “Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard”, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4181</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000603">Mr. Luttrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the area between the intersections of International Drive, Northwest and Van Ness Street, Northwest and International Drive, Northwest and International Place, Northwest in Washington, District of Columbia, as <quote>Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard</quote>, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H20255A1EBF3A4597B427C52A453956A9" style="OLC"><section id="H6998468DC12D41BF81BB333739879D2D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Designation of Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard</header><subsection id="HF3A70C7348CB4548891AE19CE8248DF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation of plaza</header><paragraph id="HADD5EF31159A4A1EACB8151FFECD52C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The area between the intersections of International Drive, Northwest and Van Ness Street, Northwest and International Drive, Northwest and International Place, Northwest in Washington, District of Columbia, shall be known and designated as <quote>Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B669D0856794E86B685A8AB74A21873"><enum>(2)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any reference in a law, map, regulation, document, paper, or other record of the area referred to in paragraph (1) shall be deemed to be a reference to Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE5E6D98E1C5A45CF9BB36AAAF1DF80E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation of address</header><paragraph id="H41C0F554B18A4E48855B8C288F1E3125"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The address of 3505 International Place, Northwest, Washington, District of Columbia, shall be redesignated as 1 Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCD80C75F87A47C5BDC8DD5BBA9E819B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any reference in a law, map, regulation, document, paper, or other record of the United States to the address referred to in paragraph (1) shall be deemed to be a reference to 1 Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC7487FDAC55142F381ACB8F35B3D64D3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Signs</header><text>The Administrator of General Services shall construct street signs that shall—</text><paragraph id="HE1EB74A5242D48BEB08D2968D9EA6F43"><enum>(1)</enum><text>contain the phrase <quote>Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A0C0BD4E0CF45C9AAB30F5F8A04ACFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be similar in design to the signs used by Washington, District of Columbia, to designate the location of Metro stations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H384FC5EF9C7A448AB3787BD75C33F15A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be placed on—</text><subparagraph id="H8EA0FE27BF904693A8FA23EF49DD4CAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the parcel of Federal property that is closest to 1 Tiananmen Square Memorial Boulevard (as redesignated by subsection (b)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6556EB6629D4C91B3B4362E24597FA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the street corners of International Drive, Northwest and Van Ness Street, Northwest and International Drive, Northwest and International Place, Northwest, Washington, District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

