<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HF19FF4F8B2914788BD2F9DBFD0F2FBBA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1058 RH: Promoting Cross-border Energy Infrastructure Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 16</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1058</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–24, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000377">Mr. Armstrong</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HIF00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on February 17, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a more uniform, transparent, and modern process to authorize the construction, connection, operation, and maintenance of international border-crossing facilities for the import and export of oil and natural gas and the transmission of electricity.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H3062D746B15E41C199EC25A200A2ED59"><section id="HFA6A6EF0E09B4492BDEAB92CFFF7709E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Cross-border Energy Infrastructure Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HA3F8EA0F5A314100999BE0BEEBB1D651"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening North American energy security</header><subsection id="HEC8CEEEEDC6A43BCBAA2744722976814"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of certain energy infrastructure projects at an international boundary of the United States</header><paragraph id="H3A0A6BF520264A4BB604B37EB0539A48"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (3) and subsection (e), no person may construct, connect, operate, or maintain a border-crossing facility for the import or export of oil or natural gas, or the transmission of electricity, across an international border of the United States without obtaining a certificate of crossing for the border-crossing facility under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1DFF9C26C2234C22912E25F24948076E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certificate of crossing</header><subparagraph id="H278883EEAFFC4FE2952D92AEEC40E3EB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after final action is taken, by the relevant official or agency identified under subparagraph (B), under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to a border-crossing facility for which a person requests a certificate of crossing under this subsection, the relevant official or agency, in consultation with appropriate Federal agencies, shall issue a certificate of crossing for the border-crossing facility unless the relevant official or agency finds that the construction, connection, operation, or maintenance of the border-crossing facility is not in the public interest of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9163071F676C41AEB0E5FEEBC0A6D4FC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relevant official or agency</header><text>The relevant official or agency referred to in subparagraph (A) is—</text><clause id="HFF781264FEED4A0CA0EB10F886010A8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission with respect to border-crossing facilities consisting of oil or natural gas pipelines; and</text></clause><clause id="HC9F55F5D89C9414AA22F33E0A825F5D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy with respect to border-crossing facilities consisting of electric transmission facilities.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74004B599796452E859D3A9772FD0ED0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Additional requirement for electric transmission facilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a request for a certificate of crossing for a border-crossing facility consisting of an electric transmission facility, the Secretary of Energy shall require, as a condition of issuing the certificate of crossing under subparagraph (A), that the border-crossing facility be constructed, connected, operated, or maintained consistent with all applicable policies and standards of—</text><clause id="H36DAA96A11794D94AFA6466D0E7E0C5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Electric Reliability Organization and the applicable regional entity; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0C620B076C244984ABC539717406ABE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any Regional Transmission Organization or Independent System Operator with operational or functional control over the border-crossing facility.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB592BBB15DBB448191404E01F10468CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection shall not apply to any construction, connection, operation, or maintenance of a border-crossing facility for the import or export of oil or natural gas, or the transmission of electricity—</text><subparagraph id="H05E8D065B73D4331BBADB4628EE653A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the border-crossing facility is operating for such import, export, or transmission as of the date of enactment of this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BE2E99BDE4648AFB8F2DC0D798D5C9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if a Presidential permit (or similar permit) for the construction, connection, operation, or maintenance has been issued pursuant to any provision of law or Executive order; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7D805F3F69F44B3D8854C89C668E999C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if an application for a Presidential permit (or similar permit) for the construction, connection, operation, or maintenance is pending on the date of enactment of this Act, until the earlier of—</text><clause commented="no" id="H8F745A9948BE42CD8216E47F5DA57C65"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which such application is denied; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HCCF69B0A977C443B89AD6767CDA68C7B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>two years after the date of enactment of this Act, if such a permit has not been issued by such date of enactment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H76AD9BB7DCF24347B5400351C38CE2CC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Effect of other laws</header><subparagraph id="HA9274573FD45458FA7A4BB9B0FC18634"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application to projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection or subsection (e) shall affect the application of any other Federal statute to a project for which a certificate of crossing for a border-crossing facility is requested under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFD9E4401AEA43609163BE874726FD2A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Natural Gas Act</header><text>Nothing in this subsection or subsection (e) shall affect the requirement to obtain approval or authorization under sections 3 and 7 of the Natural Gas Act for the siting, construction, or operation of any facility to import or export natural gas.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE3806D2FE0AE4A698F3572FD9D65B0C8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Oil pipelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection or subsection (e) shall affect the authority of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission with respect to oil pipelines under section 60502 of title 49, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H66E71E35C3DC4514BEB915CA966CEE89"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Importation or exportation of natural gas to Canada and Mexico</header><text>Section 3(c) of the Natural Gas Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/717b">15 U.S.C. 717b(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>In the case of an application for the importation of natural gas from, or the exportation of natural gas to, Canada or Mexico, the Commission shall grant the application not later than 30 days after the date on which the Commission receives the complete application.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB7760F8593D0415AB8978EB2B46D1033"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transmission of electric energy to Canada and Mexico</header><paragraph id="H7B01E9A669D644D2A99B0B5ED4F0655C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Repeal of requirement to secure order</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202(e) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824a">16 U.S.C. 824a(e)</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C2589616D5F451E809DCC95A3DB3EE8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><subparagraph id="HB7DC1D916CAB49D5BC0EBE2E55779C05"><enum>(A)</enum><header>State regulations</header><text>Section 202(f) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824a">16 U.S.C. 824a(f)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>insofar as such State regulation does not conflict with the exercise of the Commission's powers under or relating to subsection 202(e)</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10D64909CEDF4F25808C0ACE6189922F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Seasonal diversity electricity exchange</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 602(b) of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824a-4">16 U.S.C. 824a–4(b)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>the Commission has conducted hearings and made the findings required under section 202(e) of the Federal Power Act</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>the Secretary has conducted hearings and finds that the proposed transmission facilities would not impair the sufficiency of electric supply within the United States or would not impede or tend to impede the coordination in the public interest of facilities subject to the jurisdiction of the Secretary.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H35225290EF824A0AABBC15D0C974C653"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No Presidential permit required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Presidential permit (or similar permit) shall be required pursuant to any provision of law or Executive order for the construction, connection, operation, or maintenance of an oil or natural gas pipeline or electric transmission facility, or any border-crossing facility thereof.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H74858772A79543BEB4E0E2CAFDEF9C5D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Modifications to existing projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No certificate of crossing under subsection (a), or Presidential permit (or similar permit), shall be required for a modification to—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H1DDF9B4EE66F4F99B25C5573B5519621"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an oil or natural gas pipeline or electric transmission facility that is operating for the import or export of oil or natural gas or the transmission of electricity as of the date of enactment of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5BE0E9280D1F4916930BC96F51ED756C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an oil or natural gas pipeline or electric transmission facility for which a Presidential permit (or similar permit) has been issued pursuant to any provision of law or Executive order; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H60F3762CF1514E03ACB723654BBBAAC5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a border-crossing facility for which a certificate of crossing has previously been issued under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0D38A520F484B27A1FEA4045DD03C48" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Prohibition on revocation of Presidential permits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the President may not revoke a Presidential permit (or similar permit) issued pursuant to Executive Order No. 13337 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/301">3 U.S.C. 301</external-xref> note), Executive Order No. 11423 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/301">3 U.S.C. 301</external-xref> note), Executive Order No. 12038 (43 Fed. Reg. 4957), Executive Order No. 10485 (18 Fed. Reg. 5397), or any other Executive order for the construction, connection, operation, or maintenance of an oil or natural gas pipeline or electric transmission facility, or any border-crossing facility thereof, unless such revocation is authorized by an Act of Congress.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA937E3F212BD4418872AC033475078EA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effective date; rulemaking deadlines</header><paragraph id="H2455D65B1165485CA74C72A326BC5DFC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (a) through (e), and the amendments made by such subsections, shall take effect on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D188E2C074A4BC1986A8D819919EE47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rulemaking deadlines</header><text>Each relevant official or agency described in subsection (a)(2)(B) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2AE7A2FD234C46E09E2B576CCFCCBAEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, publish in the Federal Register notice of a proposed rulemaking to carry out the applicable requirements of subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H170716B32D354D149E421236E08DA3E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, publish in the Federal Register a final rule to carry out the applicable requirements of subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1DB7B7134B464A6CA40B84B2CDC572BD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HF723AEEEADFF4AA2B6DFA8D5EEB459D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Border-crossing facility</header><text>The term <term>border-crossing facility</term> means the portion of an oil or natural gas pipeline or electric transmission facility that is located at an international boundary of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA3FDA70EDF64B2783367D4A5D950A9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Modification</header><text>The term <term>modification</term> includes a reversal of flow direction, change in ownership, change in flow volume, addition or removal of an interconnection, or an adjustment to maintain flow (such as a reduction or increase in the number of pump or compressor stations).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7EE0D49EA3064938904FBE2F2A704152"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Natural gas</header><text>The term <term>natural gas</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2 of the Natural Gas Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/717a">15 U.S.C. 717a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3E0FB718BB94692ABABF0602428D791"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Oil</header><text>The term <term>oil</term> means petroleum or a petroleum product.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB32A4C35F1134B6A9096BDC1974A5CC6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Electric Reliability Organization; regional entity</header><text>The terms <term>Electric Reliability Organization</term> and <term>regional entity</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 215 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824o">16 U.S.C. 824o</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H057C3312E72A4358BD39F583AFB8F4A4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Independent System Operator; Regional Transmission Organization</header><text>The terms <term>Independent System Operator</term> and <term>Regional Transmission Organization</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/796">16 U.S.C. 796</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HIF00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date>March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

