<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H768F76EA41E242C3B7717B79D4245CF3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3642 IH: Executive Branch Accountability and Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3642</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230524">May 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000246">Mr. Edwards</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Office of Government Ethics to establish and maintain a centralized database for executive branch ethics records of noncareer appointees.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H887774D70EA1432DB8D4E19B91DB41B6" style="OLC"><section id="HA44260AD60A9417BBA1B959D0984EE28" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Executive Branch Accountability and Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H38BCC610E60F4C97BA30D65E9854615E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Centralized database for publicly available government ethics records</header><subsection id="H70D1E2AA6D6B4507814EBAFA47BA4059"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 210 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall establish a searchable, sortable database through which members of the public can access covered ethics records.</text></subsection><subsection id="H298AD2FDA99140E185A695F470526F8A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Specifications of database</header><text>The database under subsection (a) shall be—</text><paragraph id="H70A17B356BFC499D8FC30FD149198FE0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hosted on a official website of the Office of Government Ethics without charge and without a requirement that members of the public register for access;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA243058F7454EA5822C44FB1BF687C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>accessible through an application programming interface; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00402B9C1CA045FFB89EBEA1FCE41F58"><enum>(3)</enum><text>fully compliant with—</text><subparagraph id="H27E0F76D9E1449BAB06C9F4FA082C1C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BE2172DE24D430FB1293E6CE9CF3AB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the most recent Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (or successor guidelines).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9A3D3FC771C34C6782F0E65400A3D14D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of other inspection procedures</header><text>In establishing the database under subsection (a), the Director of the Office of Government Ethics may not apply the inspection procedures established in section 13107(b) of title 5, United States Code, to any procedures concerning the accessibility of covered ethics records.</text></subsection><subsection id="H98862E4909EF4C0E88334673C29C905E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agency cooperation</header><paragraph id="H4FF66FA9985A46ACA03A78727EA564A1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission of electronic covered ethics records</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (g), the designated agency ethics official of each employing agency shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE504C6F3828D43E18E82AFA1F321E4E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act or within 60 days of receipt or issuance, submit electronic copies of covered ethics records, in such format and through such means as the Director of the Office of Government Ethics may require; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78A48147BF6441FCA75E880D81EEFAF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that the content of all such records is machine readable and compliant with the requirements of subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H62838C6DD72D4A32B188DE373E3CBB63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Costs associated with compliance</header><text>The cost of complying with the requirements of paragraph (1) and uploading covered ethics records to the website of the Office of Government Ethics shall be the responsibility of the employing agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H819F7C8DF09B4DC4B46C96DC55B4FA8F" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reimbursable costs</header><paragraph id="HCA77926DA12544D1ACA76440ED9C804F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Periodic assessment</header><text>In consultation with the Office of Management and Budget, the Director of the Office of Government Ethics is authorized to periodically assess from any agency a share of the costs of establishing and maintaining the database, provided that the total amounts assessed do not exceed costs actually incurred by the Office of Government Ethics, and provided further that any part of the assessment attributable to the cost of services of personnel of the Office of Government Ethics does not exceed the cost of one full-time equivalent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H524B28E8E647486E9F48078475C06E79" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination and reimbursement</header><subparagraph id="H4ED87326F38945CA9C40961739B88EF7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>The Office of Management and Budget shall assist the Office of Government Ethics in determining amounts to assess agencies and in collecting the assessments authorized under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12584B1E64C14429ABB9B2B24548CE8C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reimbursement</header><text>Each agency in the executive branch is authorized to reimburse the Office of Government Ethics for an assessed share of such costs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E67EE10D32042CDA90D68537431BACC" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Redactions</header><text>Covered ethics records may not be redacted except to the extent necessary to—</text><paragraph id="H8BF0D62A4F21412496F2A352CD8BD98C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure the exclusion of information described in subsection (i)(3)(B);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H815CACCE778C4509839596CFA400EE8C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prevent the release of trade secrets or commercial information that is privileged or confidential, unless the disclosure of such information is required pursuant to section 13104 of title 5, United States Code; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FFC1CEC7C6F4F61AA0CE27264A2CF4E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prevent the release of information that, in the opinion of the Director, poses an identifiable risk to the safety of an individual, such as a street address, the name of a minor, or a brokerage account number.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H56914D94DDA3493A9B6950B75A603DC8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Records predating establishment of the database</header><paragraph id="H18CA55C3133943DB8D9054DBDBF974DF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Search for older information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, each employing agency shall complete a search reasonably calculated to find covered ethics records that were created during the 9-year period preceding the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H872FC2F7865B4BDDB343167B65650446"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Included information and certification</header><text>The search shall include all materials in the possession of the agency’s ethics office or readily accessible materials in any other office within the agency that the designated agency ethics official certifies in writing is the most likely office to possess covered ethics records.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC2B28C42A784733956401D8FF890B06"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusion from search</header><text>The agency may exclude information described in subsection (i)(3)(B) from the search.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F718D1E290F40BD8E0B6C8C15F19912"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Electronic copies</header><text>The agency shall provide the Director of the Office of Government Ethics with electronic copies of all covered ethics records in a manner prescribed by the Director and as required by this Act with respect to format and accessibility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C1A086CF61044E2BD6B6D5F704A04DC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the completion of the search under paragraph (1), the designated agency ethics official shall provide the Director of the Office of Government Ethics with a report that describes—</text><subparagraph id="HE47B5D700D0E4ACD999A1ED72E2BD1E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the scope of the search and steps undertaken to identify information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C205D0F411B4F03A381111BEB8299CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a copy of the certification required under paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H334F646CD0EF4D4E80BAF8546E3901F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the best estimate as to the completeness of the collection of information provided to the Director;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4229F339C9CB4F38826E89B4373AB8C3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an identification of any categories of information known to the agency that the agency was unable to find; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE295E4E76DD34ACCB02156E8B0D4769B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a certification signed by the designated agency ethics official affirming that the agency made reasonable efforts in good faith to identify and obtain covered ethics records.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H92113781BB96492E96C8F1D488CE133C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Director shall publish the report under paragraph (5) on the official website of the Office of Government Ethics.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC8516C7A9AC4167B018AE8E1E8C439F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Removal of records from the database</header><text>Notwithstanding any other law regarding the destruction of records or information, all covered ethics records required to be included in the database shall remain publicly available through the database established under this Act for a period of not less than 10 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H876B7106F2774629988CE29D2E97A0AE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H913948BF080346898C2825018AF3B972"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> means each executive agency, as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code, and each component of the Executive Office of the President.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48F02C8BCC8E40C1AC277A1E8C9EEBF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered employee</header><subparagraph id="H73C3B2EBC3F74C42A8166105086357E2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The term <term>covered employee</term> includes the following individuals:</text><clause id="HC161AABDF2C044388C7F797CA46587DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Each individual who is—</text><subclause id="H1101665180F4495B8DF3283D5E0E514C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a noncareer employee; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H83E05500925849C28FF9258A6CD66541"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is described in paragraphs (3) through (8) of section 13103(f) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC035CC5A84DF4EB5A1342774D5C0A4A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Each individual serving in a position with respect to which a determination has been made under section 7511(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause><clause id="H6E8B80949315466D8CE290107D2E287D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Each special Government employee, as defined in section 202(a) of title 18, United States Code, who is employed in the Executive Office of the President, other than a special government employee serving solely on a Federal advisory committee or presidential advisory committee.</text></clause><clause id="H5D2601E4AF1C466DB705C9670A74FF1F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>An individual who previously served in the Federal Government in a capacity described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) within the last 10 years.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44314025B96A41158AD827470996DEEC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>The term <term>covered employee</term> excludes any individual described in section 13107(a)(1) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8AF3B29760342B3A975465A1C294F8B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered ethics record</header><subparagraph id="HB8EA37E3C83B43F991F5A020AC3FC154"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered ethics record</term>—</text><clause id="H141A0ECD678642ADBC9CC93B20BA644A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with respect to any individual, means—</text><subclause id="HFF568F9A985D4153B869AA1F937F5FBD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each approval granted pursuant to subsection (b) or subsection (c) of section 908 of title 37, United States Code; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3CFB5A84C6F7417F8A00AC0E5CB91525"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each report to Congress required under section 908(d) of title 37, United States Code; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9409CACF5654484ABEFFF91BA1DE6BD3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to a covered employee, means each of the following:</text><subclause id="H6DF89A1904C14BCE8899181E6D887E5C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Each public financial disclosure report filed pursuant to section 13103 or section 13105(l) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subclause><subclause id="H33740CFD46744DD99AEA611F82B80872"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Each amendment to a public financial disclosure report filed pursuant to section 13103 or section 13105(l) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subclause><subclause id="HEE1E1D55716C48BE830E2163168F75FD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Each waiver of—</text><item id="HCDD75A291F6D451A9AD38093D5550EF2"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a post-employment restriction, pursuant to subsection (c)(2)(C) or subsection (k) of section 207 of title 18, United States Code;</text></item><item id="HAA33E55E41084595831250494DC213C7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 208(a) of title 18, United States Code, that has been issued pursuant to section 208(b)(1) of title 18, United States Code;</text></item><item id="HA174488CB5484072BB26451EDD9DEDD7"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a public financial disclosure requirement, pursuant to section 13103(i) of title 5, United States Code;</text></item><item id="HC4CF0E0CC32C4D1C841AB20A3F32D263"><enum>(dd)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the requirement to disclose a gift, pursuant to section 13104(a)(2)(C) of title 5, United States Code; and</text></item><item id="H00EF493780C441E79187CE2A1AB9F9F2"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>a provision of any regulation of the Office of Government Ethics, supplemental agency ethics regulation, or Executive order pertaining to government ethics.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H53C51BF255DF4C7B8BE0436363FD826E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Each authorization of an individual to participate in a matter from which recusal would otherwise be required under any provision of law, regulation, Executive order, or policy pertaining to government ethics and applicable to the individual as an employee of the executive branch.</text></subclause><subclause id="H79599383CE464CEB83D513D1B7074DA4"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Each approval or authorization permitting an individual to accept a gift from an outside source that would otherwise be prohibited under section 7353 of title 5, United States Code, or any other provision of law, regulation, Executive order, or policy pertaining to government ethics and applicable to the individual as an employee of the executive branch.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6157ACA984984B7AA6153E9CF7EDD776"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Each determination—</text><item id="H31F2336A28824C14A9681C98009F97FC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that a position may be excluded from otherwise applicable public financial disclosure requirements, pursuant to section 13103(f)(5) of title 5, United States Code;</text></item><item id="HA72DF46F6300491AA7B18BAEA23162A0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that an employee of the executive branch, or the spouse or minor child of an employee of the executive branch, must divest a financial interest; or</text></item><item id="HD9453C18C22743CA980804A09923CD3A"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>regarding an individual that is made pursuant to any other provision of law, regulation, Executive order, or policy pertaining to government ethics and applicable to the individual as an employee or former employee of the executive branch.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HB87A4FDDA1DF43C09E09E7FB4E71BE03"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Each written ethics agreement, recusal, or screening arrangement pertaining to employment in the executive branch.</text></subclause><subclause id="H00B1E39889C4495E8CA7FCAB3E413CC5"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Each record of a presidential appointee’s completion of ethics training required under a regulation of the Office of Government Ethics.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6E5E90351D99405E8ABE42C312850537"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Each Certificate of Divestiture issued pursuant to section 1043 of title 26, United States Code, and each request that resulted in the issuance of a Certificate of Divestiture.</text></subclause><subclause id="H3D828FDD1BF34A368E00C8CA3DA48D1F"><enum>(X)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each qualified blind trust agreement and each record described in section 13104(f)(5)(D) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subclause><subclause id="H47D9C9ED287F417BB09D1FA93EE671D4"><enum>(XI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each record submitted pursuant to section 13103(b)(1) of title 5, United States Code for the purpose of making current, with respect to income and honoraria, a financial disclosure filed pursuant to that paragraph.</text></subclause><subclause id="HF4F74D40144F40218EE579478912729E"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>Each notice submitted pursuant to section 13111 of title 5, United States Code and any certification by a Senate-confirmed presidential appointee as to compliance with an ethics agreement, whether submitted to the employing agency, the Office of Government Ethics, or the Senate.</text></subclause><subclause id="HF8FB13B277104B028D104C20F9B5D245"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>Any written opinion issued pursuant to section 847 of the National Defense Authorization Act for 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/181">Public Law 110–181</external-xref>), except that the employing agency may redact the name of an individual or organization with whom an individual has not yet accepted an offer of employment or compensation.</text></subclause><subclause id="H7BEEC9CD6E9447B1902462ED8683E803"><enum>(XIV)</enum><text>Any notification filed pursuant to section 17 of the Stop Trading On Congressional Knowledge Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/105">Public Law 112–105</external-xref>), except that the agency may withhold the public release of any such notification until such time as the employee has accepted an offer of employment or compensation from an individual or organization that is the subject of the notification.</text></subclause><subclause id="H91FF4010D77A42FFBB1E5802A52C9C91"><enum>(XV)</enum><text>Each certification made pursuant to—</text><item id="H99354D7FDDCA44CAA97008EDD3D9ABFA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 203(e) of title 18, United States Code;</text></item><item id="H5427BA4813DF45F1AFA422FF19489F1F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 205(f) of title 18, United States Code; or</text></item><item id="H7AF776D6E7534D7E9CC8F0033DEFE2C1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 207(j)(5) of title 18, United States Code.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H986C08E2037B494596588D61F1B4A365"><enum>(XVI)</enum><text>Any other category of records that the Director of the Office of Government Ethics determines is appropriate for inclusion in the database.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6067E90CAB4497499DF49DC69DBC02C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered ethics record</term> excludes—</text><clause id="HCBDD4B67DB504F1BAF8E1F5879C50D5E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>national defense information;</text></clause><clause id="H9FABE3FDAC124FBD9EBFB23FC242993C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the subject of an ongoing law enforcement matter which, in the opinion of the agency, requires the information or record to be kept confidential;</text></clause><clause id="H8821B173B97C48A2928DBA82EAC5402F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a confidential financial disclosure report under section 13109 of title 5, United States Code; or</text></clause><clause id="H8438E7C2EBEE4C01B928B3C6AC3AD3ED"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>individualized ethics counseling or advice concerning an interpretation of applicable legal requirements that has been provided by an ethics official to an individual, except that such information or record shall not be excluded from the requirements of this Act if—</text><subclause id="H4857517D31AC4E64B0A54C6988E1C57C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the information or record has the operative effect of altering a legal obligation of the individual, such as the approval of an employee’s acceptance of a gift from an outside source under a regulation requiring approval; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HAE7863D93FF14F2B9EC8304918C329D0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is required by law to be issued, such as a post-employment opinion that section 847 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/181">Public Law 110–181</external-xref>).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2140DE44ED2546E8B3055256C7589546"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Employing agency</header><text>The term <term>employing agency</term> means any agency that employs or employed the individual whose record is the subject of a requirement of this Act, except that the National Archives and Records Administration shall be determined to be the employing agency with respect to any record for which it is responsible.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA22129562244FD5835B1B90E5890F66"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Noncareer employee</header><text>The term <term>noncareer employee</term> means an individual who is—</text><subparagraph id="HF0A2CEF8ABD04379A74FA5306A4C1354"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an employee, as defined in section 2105 of title 5, United States Code, serving in a position in the executive branch; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07372ED40DF846DBA4A05D7A422A03AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="H7DE8F8551EDF40348994E3F1292DB0F7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serving in a position to which the President appointed the individual (without regard to whether the advice and consent of the Senate was required with respect to that appointment), other than an individual who is—</text><subclause id="H1959C1ED0D394691BACC58E6206A3F9C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a member of a uniformed service, as that term is defined in section 210(m) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/410">42 U.S.C. 410(m)</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H2062972A1F554761978AB5FC8B367DAD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a member of the Foreign Service serving under a career appointment, as described in section 301 of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/3941">22 U.S.C. 3941</external-xref>);</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H06FFE7ECE25945D29368C4FBA77609FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a noncareer appointee, as that term is defined in section 3132(a) of title 5, United States Code;</text></clause><clause id="H4F4408216E04475D92D7788939729AC0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>serving in a position in a Federal executive system that is comparable to the Senior Executive Service, the appointment to which is not made through merit-based procedures, such as a position in the Transportation Security Executive Service; or</text></clause><clause id="H68844918C56B422F8024247193A254A8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>serving in a position with respect to which a determination has been made under section 7511(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F23E43232384E78B72E5CC2F2AAB4EE"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Severability</header><text>If any provision of this Act or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, and the application of the remaining provisions of this Act to any person or circumstance, shall not be affected.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

