<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF36026E4C9D448369E15CD5CDC536F0F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 3225 IH: Build, Utilize, Invest, Learn, and Deliver for Veterans Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3225</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the management and performance of the capital asset programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs so as to better serve veterans, their families, caregivers, and survivors, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H212A210F17D4476F956F84B3FDF0D17B" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HB9B7E131D2A5411AAC12B96CAD21A59A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="HCE891FF03A384E67BCDC911F7DD6AA07"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Build, Utilize, Invest, Learn, and Deliver for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BUILD for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEA3DA8E8AB1B40B3B76EDA83A961A465"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="HB9B7E131D2A5411AAC12B96CAD21A59A">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H588C60AB590647AA932D4E39B39C7C99">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="H549603AC44E54C0EB4F905354EB4701F">TITLE I—Capital asset management</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H98B2DE7F020846A3AADFB466E3E918E8">Sec. 101. Improving capital asset staffing of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H260DE9FCF76D4D8194C32D05D506D86E">Sec. 102. Development of performance metrics of capital asset management by Department of Veterans Affairs and monitoring for improvement.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HEF147A04888642F3908C54E101F45520">Sec. 103. Expansion of membership of the Capital Asset Planning Committee.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="H800E96000597473FBD2EEADA0C308017">TITLE II—Strategic plan and reports</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H37558E70DE664A2EAF8EE9C09CAF1380">Sec. 201. Review of climate resilience of facilities, land, and other relevant capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HAE06D2F7A73248EA86653BA3725ECE3C">Sec. 202. Strategic plan to improve planning, management, budgeting, staffing, capacity, and performance of Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H11313A50DFBD46218D25E8F90F1FC6DA">Sec. 203. Centralized management of capital asset disposal and reuse and annual report on completion of disposal and reuse activities of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HE4725549ABD64505BA136FFBE3FE9AFC">Sec. 204. Report on options to improve minor construction program of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF670D1014BD94968920DDD18934D6231">Sec. 205. Report on improvements to alignment of information technology funding and activation of medical and other space of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H345E330F9ABE4B03AAD13D4C96746C61">Sec. 206. Reports on key capital asset investments, activities, and performance of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HB1960FE3203A4D919920552685298345">Sec. 207. Reports on projected need for funding for infrastructure and capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HDCEE9176CA2C4B8B8C7FE9037064C6DF">Sec. 208. Inspector General of the Department of Veterans Affairs reports on Department infrastructure projects.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H0028D6F1EB4C426491CBA05FC414D726">Sec. 209. Comptroller General reports on capital asset program management and execution by Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H47BC5DBA2EC244E4B52288235F5CC826">Sec. 210. Report on dental care physical infrastructure needs of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H0622291FD72A417F99250FBAD74D3B19">Sec. 211. Report on long-term care physical infrastructure needs of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H729C848C8E4147BB87535CAFA242EFB9">Sec. 212. Report on feasibility and advisability of using a dedicated budget account for maintenance of capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H441D46BB88F245EAA408CB3E521BFBCA">Sec. 213. Report on women veterans retrofit initiative.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H43ECF9A66E7847DA86413B8F2CD748FA">Sec. 214. Report on capital asset and information technology needs of the research and development program of Department of Veterans Affairs.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H5D00D3BCF9EE45CAAA6039EE4F2A43A3">Sec. 215. Review and report on provisions of law relating to Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset management and oversight.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HD061D988B5494D748280A865576B0FF5">Sec. 216. Improving prevention, detection, and reporting of waste, fraud, and abuse in Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset projects and activities.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H588C60AB590647AA932D4E39B39C7C99"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HAC7BD8931B604FE4BC3E91634E36208D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H4DF0034B3CBD4F429CD11B248EF314D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D685CFD58C4445EB43C4AAE5E7A032B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66F19327E85D46C5B5FC3D5DF7037E1B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Capital asset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>capital asset</term> means the physical infrastructure, land, buildings, and other related items under the operation and control of the Department of Veterans Affairs, including the information technology and other support systems needed to ensure the physical space can be used to deliver intended services and functions of the Department.</text></paragraph></section><title id="H549603AC44E54C0EB4F905354EB4701F" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Capital asset management</header><section id="H98B2DE7F020846A3AADFB466E3E918E8"><enum>101.</enum><header>Improving capital asset staffing of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H59724438B098464EB8D8AF506BDE7076"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Capital asset personnel of the Department</header><paragraph id="H3B702DD65132487788A196A449595F68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement for dedicated offices and sufficient staff</header><text>Not later than 540 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that the Department of Veterans Affairs has dedicated offices or entities and sufficient staff, including at each medical center of the Department, to conduct relevant critical responsibilities for the life-cycle of capital asset management at the local, regional, and central office level. This may include ensuring such mix as the Secretary considers appropriate of personnel with duties from the following categories:</text><subparagraph id="H9B9A7C5B44384992ADA53C4DB650BC35"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facility planning.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70EA721EE472472C979CCE6802A46F15"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Long-range capital planning. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC914090548F46D88C8743CBDE59473A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Management of projects and capital assets relating to the execution of major construction projects, minor construction projects, major leases, minor leases, nonrecurring maintenance, and related matters at medical centers and facilities of the Department in the surrounding catchment areas of the centers and facilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28927927BFE6469092A3CCE99229FE55"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Property disposal or transfer, environmental remediation, and historic preservation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H709CCB553FD546E99C0C66DA7FA5C029"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Engineering, including matters relating to seismic repairs and projects.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA01924849EE34E648A299C28B2334540"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Maintenance and repair of existing infrastructure.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB07B20946CF4E0AAB5E8287EF5D5940"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The collection of views of veterans and employees of the Department to understand the capital assets needs of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36D0C4F6D19948EA80D15F6684168492"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Other relevant functions relating to the full life-cycle of capital asset management of the Department as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB190AAB867F47AEB6E37B51F36F5E0B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tasks</header><text>To the greatest extent practicable, the Secretary shall ensure that each of the categories of duties under paragraph (1) are assigned to a different individual or group of individuals so as—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H096A708D322F424B928E19B255EA34D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to organize common work in a cohesive manner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5EBB67E7603445FC9B51A2E2807906F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not to overburden a small number of individuals with such requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF29CE5C3A8A04713B0ED5BCBDEED1D9B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Lead official</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2883A47554574B18B91B4AEC4A1A3D41"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">designate one individual as the lead senior official responsible for integration and coordination of, and accountability for, the evaluation of the capital asset workforce needs of the Department, the staffing model established under paragraph (4), and the ongoing implementation and monitoring of actions to ensure adequate capital asset staffing across the Department, including those at the field, regional, and central offices of the Veterans Health Administration, the National Cemetery Administration, the Veterans Benefits Administration, and the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82B24E4137F543499475D80E2BE24B60"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notify the appropriate committees of Congress who has been designated under subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F0C38005DDE478EBBF8B5058796FB0E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Staffing model</header><subparagraph id="HA6A3BEC7B17F451B8603904198A3B4D5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a staffing model for the relevant administrations, staff offices, and other elements of the Department to carry out paragraph (1) that—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD758F849E2A41079ECA6A0315F539C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensures a minimum base level of capital asset staffing; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2A10FFE426E4D299ECC9A506E675F19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is adjusted based on the volume and complexity of capital asset work of a particular facility, catchment area, region, or central office responsibility.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E6C165C1CAA454AA9A9FE838154EFF2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Update</header><text>The Secretary shall update the staffing model under subparagraph (A) regularly to ensure it is effective in carrying out paragraph (1). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06B5FEDB530C4529A616D317F5CB783A" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Treatment of States and territories without a medical center</header><text>In the case of a State or territory of the United States in which the Department does not operate a full-service medical center, the Secretary shall, in carrying out paragraph (1), ensure, to the greatest extent practicable, that the Department has a dedicated office or entity and sufficient staff at the largest medical facility of the Department in that State or territory, and any reference in this section to a medical center shall be deemed to be a reference to that medical facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17263903CE4F4C9A880A68A15D463804"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Purpose and intent</header><text>The purpose of this subsection is to ensure that field, regional, and central offices of the Department of Veterans Affairs have an appropriately sized and credentialed capital asset workforce to allow for efficient and effective execution of their relevant segment of capital asset work. Nothing in this subsection is intended to mandate a realignment of capital asset workforce roles, responsibilities, and reporting structures. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7226238378F1492CA75943EBE263424E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that appropriate professional certifications, educational background, and other qualifications are in effect for individuals employed in a position at a dedicated office or entity required by subsection (a) to manage the duties under the categories set forth under subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0101B3391BDD4D33A87C666BA8F18F99"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties of dedicated offices or entities at medical centers</header><paragraph id="HF7867E58074B4C6EB66ADCEBC1B71333"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The duties of a dedicated office or entity required by subsection (a) at a medical center of the Department may include such combination of the following duties as the Secretary considers appropriate to achieve efficient and effective capital asset management and performance as it pertains to relevant activities at the field level:</text><subparagraph id="H645045FA1C6B46C79D1BE19EC1F3090E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The development, monitoring, and implementation of capital asset objectives for the catchment area surrounding the medical center, including community-based outpatient clinics and other sites of care of the Department in that area.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0807405618E2462E842756522591072D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The coordination of capital asset management and planning with counterparts at other medical centers of the Department in the region and facility planners for the Veterans Integrated Service Network or Networks in the region.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD122271A32AB43418ABE1E4330199A44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Effective delivery of capital asset projects.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90639CE314344FA9B089802B5875AC6A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Maintenance and repair of infrastructure.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0E2DDACC60B4AE88ADE7EB291529AF5"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Capital asset disposal or transfer, environmental remediation, and historic preservation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B8BDB7A0971496A96CCB54A5A2C7688"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Regularly monitoring state-of-the-art best practices in health care capital asset delivery and management.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H872A2B2C695E45F79EE00BB70000833B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Constantly monitoring the needs of veterans and employees of the Department as it relates to medical space and services at the medical center and facilities in the catchment area surrounding the medical center to forward plan and identify and submit plans, through processes of the Department, to meet those needs, including by formulating local and regional capital improvement and asset management plans for medical facilities of the Department through the regular collection of— </text><clause id="HB000D201E9B7492ABCCB1FA58F3003D4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>views and expectations of veterans, including as expressed by relevant local or national veterans service organizations, in that area who are eligible users of health care and related services provided by the Department with respect to—</text><subclause id="H21AFE19622C54E119F8DB3F54888E5FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>preferences and needs of those veterans for the care received from medical facilities of the Department in that area; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0CBC402CCC1B4397A1EA6EDF25D91674"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the need for improvements and enhancements to infrastructure of the Department; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H103FF5DE616545C9BCFCB20BB8201797"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>views of relevant medical staff of the Department at the medical center and facilities in that catchment area regarding their preferences and needs for how to deliver health care to veterans and how those preferences impact the infrastructure needs of the Department. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12C42E6FE2984B6BA9CFF8C802E3A88D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Understanding the capital asset policies, procedures, and directives of the Department, including those issued by the central office of the Department, the Veterans Health Administration, Veterans Integrated Service Networks, the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, the Office of Asset Enterprise Management, the Office of General Counsel, the Office of Information and Technology, or any successor offices, and any other office of the Department with significant responsibility over capital asset management and planning. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE91C315C585D491DAFE6B1168CA62AA0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Implementing locally the policies, procedures, and directives described in subparagraph (H).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8736758D708B4AA4AC1A19D0BB87A8D8"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Providing feedback regarding ways in which the policies, procedures and directives described in subparagraph (H) can be improved.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9489630787EE4F9EA017230CFA42AA2F" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Understanding the importance for collaboration and coordination among all relevant offices of the Department, including the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, the Office of Asset Enterprise Management, the Office of Information and Technology, or successor offices with similar functions, and other internal stakeholders as required to achieve success in all phases of capital asset management. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7299415AD3C439FA1D8634C05D7EF2B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collection of views and expectations</header><subparagraph id="HB0A83AF242E74E6CB809E608E4C62F6B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Views and expectations may be collected under paragraph (1)(G) through multiple channels and the process used for such collection shall ensure that the views and expectations collected provide a representative sample of the population from which such views and expectations are collected.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27825B9C7DD24CB481F823E3519C90E7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>Any information collected under paragraph (1)(G) shall be collected in a manner that provides an option for submission of views that are anonymous and confidential.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H049F2E2ED0924469BDE6FB183BC7A7B2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inclusion of diverse viewpoints</header><text>In collecting views and expectations of veterans and medical staff under paragraph (1)(G), an office, entity, or relevant staff described in subsection (a) for a medical center of the Department shall ensure that the viewpoints of a diverse population of veterans being served by the medical center and medical staff of the medical center or in the catchment area of the medical center are captured.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61619643773748289C7DBF5AF0F16272"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Coordination with existing efforts of Department</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1)(G) and this paragraph, the Secretary shall use, as the Secretary considers appropriate, existing efforts and expertise of the Department through the Veterans Health Administration, Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, the Office of Asset Enterprise Management, and the Veterans Experience Office.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58A53EE0BCBD4D11BC6814B1B42E2D79"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Usage of views and expectations</header><text>The views and expectations collected under paragraph (1)(G) shall be used to inform the offices, entities, or relevant staff described in subsection (a)(1) and the broader leadership of a medical center and Veterans Integrated Service Networks of the Department to develop plans for capital asset improvement. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4E1B71F07C894803B5D429EA3669AE9B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Development of standard process To solicit views on effectiveness</header><paragraph id="HC2FA561830E248CC90D59C6DF3120A61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), the Secretary shall develop a standardized process to regularly solicit feedback from individuals and entities described in paragraph (2) regarding the effectiveness of and ways to improve—</text><subparagraph id="HBEC98C5F4BB642F5A38A51D811D3099E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the infrastructure and capital asset management investment processes and procedures of the central office of the Department and Veterans Integrated Service Networks of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B93C8D5773947AE92D523C57E3B31BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the guidance of the central office and Veterans Integrated Service Networks regarding such processes and procedures to the medical centers, facilities in the surrounding catchment areas of those medical centers, and Veterans Integrated Service Networks, as appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A8AA968524649769BF353E47A6F4172"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individuals and entities described</header><text>The individuals and entities described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H0D6A2FD6F2FE486AA89FA34C71E96A16"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each office, entity, or relevant staff described in subsection (a)(1) for a medical center of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDD1314B8C454137AA7EFDB9CF161599"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Medical staff of the Department at facilities in the surrounding catchment area of the medical center.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA6660B4A98942509071D1C32C01C2DE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Veterans Integrated Service Networks.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4654234D0CBF46BDB31F84E96A52F746"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Staff of offices within the central office of the Department, including the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, the Office of Asset Enterprise Management, and the Office of Information and Technology, or successor offices with similar functions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE093DEA0EFAB435FAD785342378FA407"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Veterans Health Administration, including its Office of Healthcare Environment and Facilities Programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8247AA3891794B508B68AA85D978771B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other offices as the Secretary determines relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77B1C4BE8ACF4FDD958535825FDB32EA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alignment with market area assessments</header><text>To the degree practicable, the Secretary shall align the process developed and standardized under paragraph (1) with the performance of market area assessments under section 7330C(a) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D951D4C96F94131915797D7BB847F56" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>Any information collected under paragraph (1) shall be collected in a manner that provides an option for submission of views that are anonymous and confidential.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H8EE0ADDC9DAD42FDAF418B5A50ECD8FB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of report findings</header><text>The Secretary shall use the results of the report required under section 202 in establishing the offices, entities, or organizational structures required under subsection (a) and carrying out any other requirements of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H260DE9FCF76D4D8194C32D05D506D86E"><enum>102.</enum><header>Development of performance metrics of capital asset management by Department of Veterans Affairs and monitoring for improvement</header><subsection id="H42D2F03DB1644DBCAB573DE4AB2F38FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text><paragraph id="HD9B6C9A1348046C089299FF5333D8FC0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop meaningful and measurable goals and metrics—</text><subparagraph id="H596D45043E7140C7BE9517D5F7BF5569"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to assess the performance of the capital asset management programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs, including those carried out by a non-Department Federal entity under section 8103(e)(1) of title 38, United States Code, to allow the Secretary to make sound decisions regarding construction, leasing, acquisition, maintenance, and disposal of capital assets; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H409832FBFC8049928FABD064B60FDD9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that are in alignment with Department strategic plans, budgets, and mission to serve veterans, their families, and caregivers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0FD067486544E65898F94EB55270B19"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop an internal dashboard or other tool to monitor progress towards meeting those goals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0481F12B5C104AB08F1A34ED8BE43D6B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establish and implement internal governance processes to direct necessary changes to improve performance and achievement of those goals; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFF3849CE05949409C06BC30572CD5FA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>submit to appropriate committees of Congress a report on the development of those goals and metrics in paragraph (1) and the implementation of the internal dashboard or other tool under paragraph (2) and the internal governance process under paragraph (3). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA95068C011624189A528D871785D6C44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Internal dashboard</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the internal dashboard developed under subsection (a)(2) includes meaningful and relevant metrics that—</text><paragraph id="H6D5FB82FB9124C8FAFEF0C076B69860F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate capital asset management performance of the Department and provide relevant information to guide necessary improvements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD447BDA9AD1747A1ADEB79A0A1E73F05"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are developed consistent with recommendations set forth by the Comptroller General of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0F5C6890ACB432E9733BE23ADB81422"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consideration of part two of Strategic Plan to Improve VA's Delivery and Management of Capital Asset</header><text>In developing the internal dashboard under subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall consider the findings in part two of the Strategic Plan to Improve VA's Delivery and Management of Capital Asset required under section 202(a)(4).</text></subsection></section><section id="HEF147A04888642F3908C54E101F45520" commented="no"><enum>103.</enum><header>Expansion of membership of the Capital Asset Planning Committee</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, in order to facilitate Federal health infrastructure planning, coordination, and investment, the Deputy Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Under Secretary of Defense for Personnel and Readiness shall modify the membership of the Capital Asset Planning Committee established as a subordinate entity of the Department of Veterans Affairs-Department of Defense Joint Executive Committee established under section 320 of title 38, United States Code, to include the following: </text><paragraph id="HC36B38DF040A4D8397FB234B95C4FD72" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not fewer than one officer or employee of the Indian Health Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC78E7686E01E441DA3DA72527329A545" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not fewer than one officer or employee of the Department of Health and Human Services who is not an employee of the Indian Health Service. </text></paragraph></section></title><title id="H800E96000597473FBD2EEADA0C308017" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Strategic plan and reports</header><section id="H37558E70DE664A2EAF8EE9C09CAF1380"><enum>201.</enum><header>Review of climate resilience of facilities, land, and other relevant capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H3CED3D90C7114D5191090C5136A6D523"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a comprehensive review of the climate resilience of facilities, land, and other relevant capital assets under the authority and jurisdiction of the Secretary. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA4DC13B2F4DB490D88482760D0AA0515"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><paragraph id="HD0303E3A8B234C82A57B49FF0D6F5D4C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The review conducted under subsection (a) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2E7CC56DD75940AA887F72EB743D26E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide a comprehensive assessment of existing facilities, land, and other relevant capital assets that may be at risk due to changes in the climate, including potential vulnerabilities related to— </text><clause id="H46D20DD3F30E412191A491AD6D248C67"><enum>(i)</enum><text>proximity to a body of water;</text></clause><clause id="H52317F68114241868DCB00A7AC63A834"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>proximity to an area prone to flooding;</text></clause><clause id="HB15480462E9440108A7F8CA843BB2C94"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>proximity to an area prone to wild fire;</text></clause><clause id="HFD5CA698614F4E97B4852EBC1B1023AB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>proximity to an area prone to tornadoes, hurricanes, or other storms; and</text></clause><clause id="H1C4BC6D03D5B4D92B61A1A8DB4461280"><enum>(v)</enum><text>such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate after consulting with the United States Global Change Research Program on the best available observations and forward-looking climate projections by region, including sea level rise data;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AE54078DE1C46E1AA5259F1A0B8889C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include a description of strategies to improve the climate resilience of existing facilities, land, and other relevant capital assets at risk due to changes in the climate, including potential modifications to facility operations and maintenance practices, and the cost of such strategies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H717BF1B5EF2A45B9A6707F0979456E7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include an analysis of the current design standards and building codes used by the Department of Veterans Affairs to site, plan, build, lease, renovate, and purchase land, facilities, infrastructure, and other capital assets of the Department and whether those design standards and building codes reflect both observed and forward-looking climate information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C6E48EBBE294EBA92225DBE75654456"><enum>(D)</enum><text>include an analysis of the effect of climate change on energy usage, energy sources, and utility systems of the Department and the Department’s mitigation strategies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF874CDCC796D4A1F8A99D26B094AD702"><enum>(E)</enum><text>use, in consultation with the United States Global Change Research Program, forward-looking climate information and other projections to anticipate changing environmental conditions during the design life of existing or planned facilities, land, and other capital assets of the Department and make relevant decisions and planning strategies based on this information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8239F27295E4789B11C4743D358A178"><enum>(F)</enum><text>after consulting with the United States Global Change Research Program and other relevant Federal and non-Federal entities, include recommendations for best practices, standards, and solutions for future placement, planning, renovation, leasing, purchase, construction, and disposal of facilities and land of the Department so as to avoid or mitigate the challenges resulting from placing a facility in an area at risk of being vulnerable to harm from the impacts of changing environmental conditions; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H082811FDE4384CA9B87F1CCA66F22B67"><enum>(G)</enum><text>assess how the Department can incorporate climate resilience information into its processes and procedures for capital asset investment decisions. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7093C1B404B4F1D8A6FE9074A5AE54B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sources of information and projections</header><text>Sources of information and projections used under paragraph (1)(E) may include the Bureau of the Census (for population projections), the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (for land use change projections and climate projections), the United States Geological Survey (for land use change projections), the United States Global Change Research Program and the National Climate Assessment (for climate observations and projections), and such other sources as the Secretary considers reliable in consultation with the United States Global Change Research Program. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H030378A3EAE14816A9E3EF6E96A5A709"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H83CF915651944A2E91E0C4E9207EF44B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mission critical assets</header><text>Not later than 540 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report detailing the results of the review conducted under subsection (a) with respect to mission critical capital assets of the Department and the actions the Secretary will take in response to the findings of such review.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC901B799F6E443049ACFE2072B898287"><enum>(2)</enum><header>All assets</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary submits the report under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report detailing the results of the review conducted under subsection (a) with respect to all capital assets of the Department and the actions the Secretary will take in response to the findings of such review.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58B77CAF400A4DAB8FF75D3B3569CBBF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report submitted under paragraphs (1) and (2) shall include, with respect to the assets covered by the respective report, the following:</text><subparagraph id="H1B13519E4F954184AD4890F02F2E2728"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Recommendations for legislative and administrative action to mitigate and respond to the findings contained in the review conducted under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D2B6A6182694820A2EBBAA9214ABAD2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of action taken or to be taken by the Secretary to improve the climate resilience of existing facilities, land, infrastructure and other relevant capital assets under the jurisdiction or control of the Department. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAD5C38EAFC540D1A6295D7E2CA6E8C5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of changes in policy, directives, and procedures of the Department to mitigate, plan for, and improve resilience of future constructed, leased, or other facilities, land, infrastructure, and other relevant capital assets under the jurisdiction or control of the Department. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D3A0371ED904475B9AAAE63E094FB02"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of how the Department will incorporate climate resilience information into its processes and procedures for capital asset investment decisions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E0BAAF242E246618B07308755A83A1B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of changes the Department will make to ensure the facilities, land, infrastructure, and other relevant capital assets of the Department are available to furnish care and services under section 1785 of title 38, United States Code, during or following a disaster or emergency. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB10FB562B03A44839FB1ACB34740DC15"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The estimated cost to implement the changes described in the report.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8E52EC5B71E421A8C3DCE98A66A1234"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The estimated timeline to implement the changes described in the report.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5FB853DD04847C18C7018661D151FFA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Such other matters, recommendations, or requests as the Secretary considers appropriate, including recommendations for relevant legislative or administrative action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4084726191154BEA875150CCE3BB9883"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Updates</header><subparagraph id="H86332CE1C0C447BEB99C7D91B27BADC3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than five years after the date on which the Secretary submits the report under paragraph (2) and not less frequently than once every five years thereafter until the date that is 23 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress an update of the report submitted under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA09293B8F446484BAC1FCA2F71381979"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each update submitted under subparagraph (A) shall describe the efforts of the Department since the submittal of the latest report or update, as the case may be, relating to matters covered by the report and such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BE16EB3D7AE4CFBB5E2D8F43C2B3C78"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Climate resilience defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>climate resilience</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H9949634C115D48AC98E6AAF55570EB41"><enum>(1)</enum><text>anticipating, preparing for, and adapting to changing environmental conditions such as variations in average weather conditions that persist over multiple decades or longer that encompass increases and decreases in temperature, shifts in precipitation, and changing risk of certain types of severe weather events; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DBC9DE8389640C9A5EDE706C78B0F84" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the ability to withstand, respond to, and recover rapidly from disruptions while ensuring the sustainment of mission-critical operations. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HAE06D2F7A73248EA86653BA3725ECE3C"><enum>202.</enum><header>Strategic plan to improve planning, management, budgeting, staffing, capacity, and performance of Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset activities</header><subsection id="HB3E48A24CCD2424F8A30E1A86BFAF5D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial strategic plan</header><paragraph id="H43FD219CE39F4B34A9B107046A2EFD25"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a strategic plan to improve the planning, management, budgeting, staffing, capacity, and performance by the Department of Veterans Affairs relating to capital assets. Such strategic plan shall be known as the <quote>Strategic Plan to Improve VA’s Delivery and Management of Capital Assets</quote> (in this subsection referred to as the <term>Plan</term>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA43254B3C394A4F9DCD2F25E2480D97"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Structure</header><text>The Plan shall consist of not fewer than two parts as set forth in this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9950F4C1F00D4F9190D2B3A8E8C22A00"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Part One</header><subparagraph id="H1B8DD60CE8C845A6896F9F162D801673"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part one of the Plan shall focus on the human capital needs for the capital asset and related areas workforce of the Department (in this subsection referred to as <term>Part One</term>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C63E7F7260B440FA2CA4A3F9D3626D3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Part One shall include the following:</text><clause id="HA6735A52BE78478EAA7A9E86375FEDE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A description of the steps being taken by the Department, including by the lead official designated under section 101(a)(3), and the steps that the Department plans to take during the 10-year period following the date of the Plan, including a specific timeline, to ensure sufficient capital asset personnel at the local, regional, and central office levels of the Department are available and prepared—</text><subclause id="HE8285591F3B2441F8B04450473876B86"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to execute the current level of capital asset work, including maintenance, delivery of new facilities, disposal, and reuse; </text></subclause><subclause id="H22A2CAB202C54AB4A4F537062CFFF8CC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to handle future capital asset work described in subclause (I) during such 10-year period; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H40B467F6F82E4D3D8A0CB59FDA28C7F2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to perform any other capital asset activities as identified by the Secretary. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA5FBCA2389FD4885B958A243E2C3CBFF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A plan that addresses the needed capital asset workforce of the Department by—</text><subclause id="HE1861E025DCE453A9523570DF93C65DA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>identifying and describing the staffing needs and status of such workforce, including—</text><item id="H7205589F7BE845799D1AE96E264CE19E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the number of currently authorized positions;</text></item><item id="HA5BD8805062640069AEFE565578FC814"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the number of filled positions of those positions authorized;</text></item><item id="HEE47876B14BF432D862DF58030A47F56"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the number of unfilled positions of those positions authorized, including reasons why those positions are not filled and steps the Department is taking to fill those positions;</text></item><item id="HF3891D113AE34B76B966C503310EF250"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>the number of current positions needed above the level currently authorized; and </text></item><item id="H94FDA5FF573E4A8881B599F3D4B905F0"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>future needs, including expected growth or reduction of personnel, during the 10-year period following the date of the Plan; </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H9443A7C29B264944AE979173C0599D1C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>providing the data under subclause (I) at the Departmental level, disaggregated by relevant divisions of the Department and by—</text><item id="HAB81CDCDF72F481788F3F5306FF8F9B9"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>data for the Veterans Health Administration, broken out by field, Veterans Integrated Service Network, and central office, including the Office of Healthcare Environment and Facilities Programs; </text></item><item id="H6F5F8F262D4A4E28AFECFDCE586246CD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>data for the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, broken out by field, region, and central office;</text></item><item id="HE71F7B18248645749616821052A9C7AA"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>data for the National Cemetery Administration, broken out by field, region, and central office;</text></item><item id="HC562FBE7A21540A781EAD3ED2B7E5BBA"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>data for the Veterans Benefits Administration, broken out by field, region, and central office;</text></item><item id="H3764E947D4224901BD72E8C7E89D7CBF"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>data for the Office of Asset Enterprise Management; </text></item><item id="HFA7169884EF4469B9BB73FFC25E70602"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>data for the Office of Information and Technology, broken out by field, region, and central office; and</text></item><item id="H5DAF336BF8BF43B68906B80CED4DC608"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>data for all other offices of the Department not covered under items (aa) through (ff) that have capital asset staff or significant capital asset responsibilities or are key enablers and support functions for capital asset management at the field, regional, or central office level; and </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H7846912113234B3BBE2BF47D44E8A61F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>including an estimate of the funding required to accomplish filling the unfilled and future positions specified under subclause (I) during the 10-year period following the date of the Plan. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB0B5A088DC0A47699AF3B5CC99D101E4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of the efforts taken and planned to be taken by the Department to recruit, retain, and develop the existing and future capital asset workforce of the Department.</text></clause><clause id="H9AA3D852B233437CB197B3A296F651D1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A description of any changes needed to the qualifications, standards, position descriptions and other related matters to ensure the qualification standards of the workforce, including those resulting from implementation of section 101(b)—</text><subclause id="H824D5F0CA7AD4DD7AF561846BE2EF8C0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>match the needs of the Department; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA974F6D2F0BC4D8CA344E32DCCF0902F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>align where appropriate with relevant Federal Government and industry standards and best practices. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE4AA12A58F0B48C0AA76318990BFAD42"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A description of how the Department will coordinate the capital asset human capital efforts of the Department across the Veterans Health Administration, the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction, the National Cemetery Administration, the Veterans Benefits Administration, the Office of Asset Enterprise Management, or similar successor offices, and other entities of the Department so as to leverage collective efforts, reduce unnecessary duplication, and identify opportunities for collaboration and efficiency. </text></clause><clause id="H9749055687C842149CDC102AD7BB5F91"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>With respect to a Department-wide succession plan for leadership and mission-critical occupations in the capital asset workforce of the Department—</text><subclause id="HB014889D201C4035B336373DA52DDCF9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if such a plan is not already developed, a timeline for the development of such a plan; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4C51CA128F7C48A78AC5603179437080"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if such a plan is already developed, the current implementation status of such plan.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H5E2FF1FEAFE7431E97CAF8DEEFADA432"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>An assessment of different regional challenges in rural, suburban, and urban areas to recruit and retain the necessary capital asset workforce of the Department and steps to be taken by the Department in response to such challenges.</text></clause><clause id="H73B37823F0DF4C59B9E7DF7751C4BD54"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>With respect to the report published by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine on December 24, 2019, entitled <quote>Facilities Staffing Requirement for VHA-Resource Planning and Methodology for the Future</quote>—</text><subclause id="H8B2F59EDB65844D98E45333CA726CF63"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a description of the recommendations from the report that have already implemented;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB5A2E7E74B39434398823A05617146B8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a plan and timeline to implement the recommendations from the report that have not already been implemented and the Secretary plans to implement; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4153ADB7880946EA8D4AB2F290FFFAA2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>for each recommendation from the report that has not already been implemented and the Secretary does not plan to implement, a description of the recommendation and a justification for the decision not to implement the recommendation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H107D1C6920E24DC2A05EC66DC42A36E8"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>A description of how the Department will leverage, where appropriate and relevant, contract support and partnerships with other Federal agencies, nonprofit organizations, and other entities to meet the short-, medium-, and long-term human capital needs for infrastructure to ensure that the Department has the experience and workforce needed to match the current and future projected infrastructure workload of the Department.</text></clause><clause id="H47CD44CA98FB49C5AA5411C0753CDDC2"><enum>(x)</enum><text>A description of any improvements to training or curriculum of the Department that are needed to enhance the education of the capital asset employees of the Department to ensure they are as proficient as possible in their jobs.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3531388E50B74E24AD7981E91D8E5B35"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>A description of the status of the implementation of the staffing model established under section 101(a)(4).</text></clause><clause id="HD9A9BE75717244B1BAB2ABD784961FEA"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>A description of such legislative or administrative action as the Secretary considers necessary to recruit, retain, and develop a strong capital asset management workforce.</text></clause><clause id="HF0FF70C83D14439786C6470E158135A5"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers necessary. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F454DCACD9D4E2BBBCE091684F3AAA3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Staff covered by strategic plan</header><text>Part One shall cover all relevant staff required for the effective management of the entire life-cycle of facilities, land, infrastructure, and other relevant capital assets of the Department, including the following: </text><clause id="HDD5D4D45888C479AA209AD28BFA4233C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Individuals who keep facilities clean, such as janitorial and housekeeping staff and housekeeping aids.</text></clause><clause id="HABB33165D4384D56BFA1213C6646263C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Individuals who maintain facilities, such as through repairs and preventative maintenance.</text></clause><clause id="H45B9B79C0D734744A30CA225F9F7125E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Groundskeepers.</text></clause><clause id="H8ABD67EF458F4BAABE093217C7136836"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Planners, engineers, and architects.</text></clause><clause id="HE20774584F2944718F88ECFFAAAFF977"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Project managers.</text></clause><clause id="H97051AD257EA4F40AAAFC91F523E1C06"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Individuals with expertise in real estate, acquisition, leasing, and easements. </text></clause><clause id="H2606F6DC29014A91B5F06F75FCF5E078"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Energy or utility experts, including experts with respect to energy efficiency and renewable energy.</text></clause><clause id="HFDC1CA84683244C9AE565C4F20B02BCA"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Individuals who work in—</text><subclause id="H286D4EBD21B9463CA5D86D6ADAC619DA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>capital asset management;</text></subclause><subclause id="HDC07CDC8F449445C8557CFE45FC04141"><enum>(II)</enum><text>healthcare architecture and engineering;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCC4C7683119A4EBEA6EB7BF7046306E1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>environmental management; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H99D7682D3A87490EAD320C1037705DE5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>occupational safety and health.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFE1321F2CE9E41D1BD767230058F409A"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Individuals who conduct contracting, including contracting officers, related to capital assets locally, regionally, or nationally for all various types of construction or infrastructure work, such as minor construction, major construction, nonrecurring maintenance, and leases.</text></clause><clause id="H6DDF5CE5560044049E786A852619FC90"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Individuals knowledgeable in relevant rules and procedures related to property disposal or transfer, environmental remediation, historic preservation, and other similar topics.</text></clause><clause id="HFF5ECE8653F94631A60B03FC20C6AA10"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Relevant legal counsel and staff of the Office of General Counsel needed to perform relevant duties that occur throughout the entire life-cycle of capital asset management activities. </text></clause><clause id="H2BF24C46F57D427D86DC578787DD852F"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Any other position that has a critical role, including supporting or enabling functions, in the planning, contracting, delivery, maintenance, upkeep, and disposal of capital assets.</text></clause><clause id="HF3A6E641038F4E09AA8390312C247F84"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Any other positions the Secretary determines relevant.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AE1D65F3A5142C08D5064F4C834F0A2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Part Two</header><subparagraph id="HD6985E27B0CE49BEB07DF4E88ABA0FF0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part two of the Plan shall cover the methods undertaken by the Department to accomplish changes to improve the planning, execution, and delivery of capital asset projects of the Department, such as maintenance, renovations, land acquisition, disposal, reuse, or new construction or leasing, including through better planning, project management, cost, and schedule performance (in this subsection referred to as <term>Part Two</term>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H328F8FDFA0B346BA8C9161D391DF0827"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Part Two shall include the following:</text><clause id="HA625ABF9899F4417861F4549483B4210"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A timeline for accomplishing the changes described in subparagraph (A). </text></clause><clause id="H6A71822C453440A884C7A9298AC833FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A description of the steps the Department is taking or plans to take to shorten the time it takes from project concept to completion while controlling costs and budget, and achieving established goals.</text></clause><clause id="HFB01EAB402FF4B39BB4CCD337EFCBD3E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of the steps the Department is taking or plans to take to increase the capacity and ability of the Department to complete a larger number of projects in a given year.</text></clause><clause id="H19DA39AE5532420282A20B240261F3E5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A description of what new or modified contracting or other services, arrangements, strategies, contract vehicles or mechanisms, innovations, pilots, and partnerships the Department is planning to use during the five-year period following the date of the Plan, including—</text><subclause id="H00BBB64A925D487396CD8D3886D5464E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a timeline of how and when the Department will test and implement those approaches; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H196DAD85FFF341A2AE6D51B4B2D22AF3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description of any limitations under current law (including regulations) that would prevent or are preventing the Department from using innovative contracting vehicles, services, arrangements, administrative action, or other agreements and strategies and what legislative changes are needed to facilitate use of those approaches, including a description of whether each limitation is a limitation for all Federal agencies or only for the Department.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H123D0C09B21D47A2B7A10B48E00F97A4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A description of the costs incurred or added to meet Federal or Department standards, including those for resiliency, accessibility, and other areas that are needed and may be greater or more stringent than private industry standards. </text></clause><clause id="HB51A1E8754BD46B4BD7D767957EC3E9D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>A description of the steps the Department is taking or plans to take to improve capital project delivery by standardizing facility design, modularizing facilities components, and taking other steps to accelerate project delivery while maintaining flexibility, agility, and quality, including a timeline for the completion of such steps.</text></clause><clause id="H9D8B4541870743A1B9F66336DEE1A43A"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>A description of steps the Department is taking or plans to take to make all of its relevant capital assets energy efficient.</text></clause><clause id="HCF57A3C0EDE24FF4B51B710708C483BC"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The steps the Secretary is taking or plans to take to ensure the Office of Information and Technology and the Office of Acquisition, Logistics, and Construction of the Department, or similar successor offices, are integrated into all relevant aspects of the capital asset planning and implementation process of the Department, including at the earliest stage of every relevant capital asset project in the field so as to improve communication, coordination, and project scope, cost, and schedule.</text></clause><clause id="H59F55F641DE546408AFEDF9AC6C1814B"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>A description of any other actions the Department is taking or plans to take to improve its delivery and management of capital assets. </text></clause><clause id="HCB465E3364D846B5BB4E20E74E183CC6"><enum>(x)</enum><text>A description of such legislative or administrative action as the Secretary considers necessary to more effectively manage and deliver needed capital assets of the Department.</text></clause><clause id="HF0B163A1DE6E40F187B62DAA4EBF2EE9"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers necessary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H33E0142C9D8041E2A3A052AB51988C3F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subsequent reports</header><text>Not later than three years after the date on which the strategic plan required by subsection (a) is submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) of such subsection, and once every three years thereafter for a period of six years, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report including—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H984B41C5152641D8BBAF937CBE895E0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of any changes with respect to the matters described in paragraphs (3) and (4) of subsection (a) since the strategic plan was submitted or the previous report was submitted under this subsection, whichever may have been more recent; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1A50C0020E6A40BB8489A1CB2EDE083B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an explanation of which plans, actions, and initiatives contained in the strategic plan or previous report, as the case may be, were carried out;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2DB28BD6578400B882AF751AF159B9D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of plans, actions, and initiatives from the strategic plan or previous report, as the case may be, that were not carried out and the reasons for such lack of action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CB1402E72F4E5FA1D54E43E00D50CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a discussion of the results and performance of the Department since the strategic plan or the previous report, as the case may be, including in cost savings, faster project delivery, increased capacity to complete an increased number of projects in a given year, and reduction in the number of unaddressed priority capital asset improvements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19B1644188EA46748E49A6C1A681F37E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such other matters as the Secretary considers necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H11313A50DFBD46218D25E8F90F1FC6DA"><enum>203.</enum><header>Centralized management of capital asset disposal and reuse and annual report on completion of disposal and reuse activities of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H565CA56E4900483FA35269D1314D09B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Centralized management</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H762CB264F09A42BBAFB0BCCC4DBDC4C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, to the greatest extent practicable, centralize and consolidate the management and oversight of all disposal and reuse activities of the Department of Veterans Affairs within one office or sub-office of the Department which shall have the sole focus of property disposal, including reuse, transfer, and demolition.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB05E0A00B63A44909457A408C1D4CA57"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Plans and goals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The office or sub-office described in paragraph (1) shall be focused on developing and implementing a measurable plan with yearly goals to dispose of, reuse, or transfer relevant capital assets.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3103008B5140441C9D93246D40DF6CE6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consolidation of functions and employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the greatest extent practical, the Secretary shall consolidate the functions and employees of the office or sub-office described in paragraph (1) within one organization element of the Department so as to improve effectiveness, efficiency, and accountability.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H133B84C220BC44CC8610AA6243967079"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disposal management report</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA01200E002E451C9B52CF828DA61DA1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate Committees of Congress a report on the actions of the Secretary to carry out this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A84604FB86746498C88CA389DD13EEC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted under subparagraph (A) shall include the following:</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7BA1956BAC7841EA9493ACFD812D0271"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of whether and how the consolidation has been carried out as required by this subsection.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76280171F2EB4EB09BB05CA08A5B6AD9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of the responsible single official with oversight over all capital asset disposals of the Department.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AD5A854F7324E9A8CF0B11A7058B9A6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Observations or conclusions regarding the challenges of managing capital asset disposals of the Department.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11F4B1DE5D2F4CFD9629AB94E736AC63"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such recommendations for administrative or legislative action as the Secretary may have to improve the organization and effectiveness of the capital asset disposal work of the Department.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H524B2A6C3A7F4C41A1C2EF5260B0853D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Initial disposal and reuse progress report</header><paragraph id="H010A08198DC04A2C8CC41B07612264F2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include with the budget justification materials that are submitted to Congress in support of the Department budget for the first fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act (as submitted with the budget of the President for such fiscal year under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code) a report containing a specific timeline to accomplish the disposal and reuse actions the Secretary included in the disposal and reuse reports included in the annual budget of the Department of Veterans Affairs submitted by the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, or similar future reports.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52AF0CEE3F8041ABBF2F9234066F0DE2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8F2AEA9F19DE4FB589C0904D6DC8114F"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6044DDF8A5784E7795B8A64F1DC78B03"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A description of a specific timeline and plan to sell, reuse, dispose of, demolish, transfer, or otherwise manage the capital assets, including individual structures and buildings, that the Secretary has identified in the reports described in such paragraph in the next fiscal year and over the next five fiscal years.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H651CF1D665D8419986BE037D232E60CD" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description under clause (i) shall—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A5FA3D58C454449905C2890D5F9A70C"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">indicate those disposal projects that the Secretary believes have a business case to conduct a disposal and those that the Secretary believes lack a business case; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0711A3AB4F424187A529DC32544A4D6C"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include an explanation for such reasoning. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91440E4F9EFE436281FD483143FFA3F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A list of any impediments or challenges, on a project-by-project basis and in the aggregate, to carrying out any action described in subparagraph (A), including funding constraints, environmental remediation and preservation mitigation and any need for administrative or legislative action to address those impediments or challenges.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EB919F924AF41859678117900E89641"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A discussion of whether disposal and reuse actions do not get completed or initiated because they may compete for resources with urgent health care delivery or other more time-sensitive infrastructure or other operational needs of the Department. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB967B15319D9482D9AD1D52F6C8D101B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A detailed cost estimate of the funding, including funding type, needed to accomplish all of the actions described in paragraph (1), including the number of fiscal years for which such funding is needed and an indication of what funding for capital asset disposal and reuse activities is included in the budget of the President with which the report under such paragraph is included.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2959A83AEBD14130A802B2951F1E9440"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A discussion of whether the Department would benefit from having a distinct and separate account within the budget of the Department dedicated to the management of the disposal and reuse of these assets.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE943616C43E04B8A91EA65E5A251B904"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The cost to maintain capital assets waiting to be processed for disposal or reuse for the preceding fiscal year, disaggregated by project.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D959B74A4AD494E88FA275BB29CE8F2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26BE475655694123B68AC9EA6D7F703C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Subsequent disposal and reuse progress reports</header><paragraph id="H51ED0636752344A49272E7EB98A3CFC0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Subsequent reports required</header><text>For the first fiscal year after the fiscal year referred to in subsection (b)(1) and each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary shall include with the budget justification materials that are submitted to Congress in support of the Department budget (as submitted with the budget of the President for such fiscal year under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code) a report on actions described in such subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4182C56F18EA48CDBB03749F1F6E3BFE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H0593CDF5B3454238B0E6FBD14483BBA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An update to the most recent report under subsection (b) or this subsection, as applicable, with respect to each of subparagraphs (A) through (G) of paragraph (2) of such subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EF0993533FB44E58CAF6A211FBE0957"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information on how many disposal and reuse actions from the previous year's report were accomplished or not accomplished.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03D09F61A45344B3B81565B3B0B3F641"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Information about what may have inhibited the accomplishment of those actions described in subparagraph (B) that were not accomplished.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H516A06045BD646ED89B639F4204275DC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of best practices or lessons learned with respect to actions described in subsection (b)(1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCAB0B36C88DF47099B577A8702FFFCF2"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate and relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="HE4725549ABD64505BA136FFBE3FE9AFC"><enum>204.</enum><header>Report on options to improve minor construction program of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9C4EE30155714A2F872B5DFCBA8A941D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on potential options and alternatives to improve, reform, and provide more flexibility to the minor construction activities of the Department of Veterans Affairs so as to increase effectiveness in commencing and delivering minor construction capital asset projects.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB65EDFC7384460ABDA4A044DD0DC44A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D27556DA4494B9EBC45955456033E13"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion regarding legislative or administrative action to define the term <quote>minor construction</quote> for purposes of Department budgeting and accounting by using an automatic adjustment of the threshold using—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H852D34F399634F4C9DC0E99D165D13F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an index to adjust for inflation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DD48DE73C9A493F8E050AB6A1E35FEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">another index to adjust for regional variations and trends in the cost of construction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H97DAC3DA199649A69CE6731AD4A7722E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion of whether the practice of the Department entering into multiple minor construction projects rather than one larger major construction project is an efficient best practice for delivery of capital asset projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73DF17E108814604AAE217B8080A84D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion of whether the Department should adopt any best practices of other Federal agencies or non-Federal entities for its minor construction capital asset projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD2BB97D9F70E48B484F7F3E4BF256555"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Such other suggestions for legislative or administrative action as the Secretary may have with respect to the management, including project thresholds, of minor construction capital asset projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDDEDD08EA834FD0950A1F2FCA213D96"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D15B23ADF734733B41D7E041CB6CFE9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H22A2C4AF165F41B38B65DE729F656A8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Major construction</header><text>The term <term>major construction</term> means capital project to construct, alter, extend, or improve any facility that involves a total expenditure of more than $20,000,000, including a major medical facility project (as defined in section 8104(a)(3) of title 38, United States Code).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBD8C5E21E3D46108669D2549B7E3AB5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minor construction</header><text>The term <term>minor construction</term> means a capital project to construct, alter, extend, or improve any facility that involves a total expenditure of $20,000,000 or less.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF670D1014BD94968920DDD18934D6231"><enum>205.</enum><header>Report on improvements to alignment of information technology funding and activation of medical and other space of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8E73BA65C5D4DED9C82516BA2AF61DA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on any potential improvements to the alignment of funding of the Department of Veterans Affairs for information technology so as to facilitate more effective and efficient activation of medical and other relevant space of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96EB64B0481B4256A005D66FA5DCE533"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following: </text><paragraph id="H1DDB9B6C12EC46A3971FB20ED8380564"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of any current limitations on funding mechanisms, including the timing and sequencing of information technology and health care resources that are needed to purchase, procure, and install information technology equipment and related information technology assets and services needed for the activation of medical and other relevant space of the Department, whether leased, owned, or otherwise under the jurisdiction of the Department. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1707BE8487C44AD842C12A4F4CD5420"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any proposed solutions the Secretary may have to address the limitations described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16D81840A35F4854879CAFEC68D6EC4F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any legislative or administrative action required to achieve the solutions described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD0A7F36FB29469B9A9AEFB791F2F187" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H345E330F9ABE4B03AAD13D4C96746C61"><enum>206.</enum><header>Reports on key capital asset investments, activities, and performance of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H1FA6BA7795B946FCAE3BA4426B032D99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 8120 of title 38, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10A92ADF16E94C979C738711875EED1F"><section id="HC905786920B84209B9007B9EB5281A11"><enum>8120.</enum><header>Reports on key capital asset investments, activities, and performance</header><subsection id="HADCB2015771B47EE8982C80B3300A603"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Capital asset investment, activities, and performance</header><paragraph id="H707D4FC01D51448A92CEEE09B6967CED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the end of each fiscal year, and every 60 days thereafter until the end of that fiscal year, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on key capital asset investments, activities, and performance of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89600D05B9464C0DA0620C38917E44E8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><subparagraph id="H8524219ECDFB46C785E3962BDD3ADB76"><enum>(A)</enum><header>First report in each fiscal year</header><text>The first report under paragraph (1) in each fiscal year shall include the following:</text><clause id="H112BDEE806D4497693F848768EFAA115"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A brief summary of each capital asset project that was completed in the previous fiscal year.</text></clause><clause id="H0904BB3675154A70BD16B666515D91C1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A brief summary of the accomplishments, impediments, and challenges experienced by the Department with respect to capital asset projects in the previous fiscal year and a description of efforts made to address any such impediments and challenges.</text></clause><clause id="H47EA6F82DEE54B65BEE270F26574E832"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>With respect to each capital asset project completed in such year, the following:</text><subclause id="H9A6B8936B24540B58DADF89D4F6A2909"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The type of project (major construction, minor construction, non-recurring maintenance, leases, or other category, including disposals).</text></subclause><subclause id="HEADC1BAC95704D4BAE32A895CD726D2B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The estimated total cost and the actual total cost of the project.</text></subclause><subclause id="HDF48AEE7B55741CBBB9B84076DDF9EF2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>A description of the project.</text></subclause><subclause id="H084034ACE8534B82B1927DEC688A06B2"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The location and facility with respect to which the project was carried out.</text></subclause><subclause id="H9DD39E7ACA3E4FF185F9DBCD523574B1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The fiscal quarter the project was expected to begin, the fiscal quarter the project began, the month and year the project was completed, and the fiscal quarter the facility in connection to such project was in use by veterans, employees of the Department, or other relevant users, as the case may be.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6A489E599FF24B63B7C1416F82875F68"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>In the case of any capital asset project completed during the previous fiscal year with respect to which the final cost of the project (or any increment of the project) was more than 10 percent greater than the estimated cost of the project (or increment) or the completion of such project (or increment) was more than 180 days later than the planned schedule for such project (or increment)—</text><subclause id="HD2ABA8ED36A546F2A95A367D887B7C8E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the reason for any such overage or delay; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H67D1E444C1BC4A01AC18EA5F0D1EBE1D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>actions being taken to prevent any such overage or delay in future projects. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H96D3C55925274209975AB493335F1EE4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A list of any capital asset projects cancelled during the previous fiscal year, including any projects in the design phase and including the reason for the cancellation.</text></clause><clause id="HDB5E3BC9E9E6428BBBFC0CB35C35A5EA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>A summary of total actual obligations for capital asset projects for the previous fiscal year, broken out by major construction, minor construction, non-recurring maintenance, and leases, from the medical facilities appropriation account of the Department.</text></clause><clause id="HA37F54409AAF4B85AA45358BEE12B216"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>A projected list of capital asset projects, broken out by type of project under subclause (I), that are expected to be initiated during the current fiscal year and those that are expected to be completed during the current fiscal year, which shall include the following:</text><subclause id="HEC3EA90BC8464BD08CB1F1905311DB45"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The type of project (major construction, minor construction, non-recurring maintenance, leases, or other category, including disposals).</text></subclause><subclause id="H10D6D900EF2C417791895097B7173E5C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The estimated total cost of the project.</text></subclause><subclause id="HBB85C316B1244A40AB13F12AB545F4AB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>A description of the project.</text></subclause><subclause id="H12BE9C2A42874AB7A142671083B29467"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The location and facility with respect to which the project was carried out or is expected to be carried out.</text></subclause><subclause id="H493004F292A24C01AE5AAAA652D5A0A9"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The fiscal quarter the project is expected to begin, the fiscal quarter the project is expected to be completed, and the fiscal quarter the facility in connection to such project is expected to be in use by veterans, employees of the Department, or other relevant users, as the case may be.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBB55CFCE82884F8796D3FA07E1585052"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Projected total obligations for capital asset projects for the current fiscal year, broken out by major construction, minor construction, non-recurring maintenance, and leases, from the medical facilities appropriation account of the Department. </text></clause><clause id="H1102BCF2A23A4FAE88A898C137D83164"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Such observations of best practices, impediments, and accomplishments related to the capital asset management and performance of the Department, including any legislative or administrative action, as the Secretary considers appropriate with respect to such practices, impediments, and accomplishments.</text></clause><clause id="H8BB08DAC597B47A58C0945F115915014"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Meaningful metrics that show the progress of the Department toward meeting relevant goals of the Department relating to capital asset management. </text></clause><clause id="H134FA6C325B247049F5AE8D15E93FCB5"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04D6D92969AC43F8A69C285775310E28"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent reports</header><text>Each report in a fiscal year after the first report shall include, at a minimum, relevant updates on any capital asset projects that are ongoing during that fiscal year, including any updates to information provided with respect to such projects under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E8CD508242D4A808F6D368C2D1F1C79"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text>Beginning not later than two years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>BUILD for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title>, the metrics described in subparagraph (A)(x) shall include the metrics developed under section 102(a)(1) of such Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04E3829D93FA407CA662E250A816E3A2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Matters relating to reporting costs</header><text>In each report under paragraph (1), when reporting on costs for capital asset projects, the Secretary may include information regarding Federal requirements, including those specific to the Department, that may not exist in the non-Federal construction sector that may increase costs for capital asset projects. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9445F1A7FE87499DB2D8100511ABD40B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Super construction projects</header><paragraph id="H1D5262838F114A9FBB60AFCBBBEC0EAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the end of each fiscal year, and every 60 days thereafter until the end of that fiscal year, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the super construction projects carried out by the appropriate non-Department Federal entity described in section 8103(e)(1) of this title during such year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA458C94042D4C79B09CF08B839D098C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required under paragraph (1) shall include, for each project described in such paragraph—</text><subparagraph id="H6BE458B35FE441C49EA941A59717AC87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the budgetary and scheduling status of the project, as of the last day of the most recent fiscal quarter ending before the date on which the report is required to be submitted; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6310C5A8749E479587EC955E66B5BCCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the actual cost and schedule variances of the project, as of such day, compared to the planned cost and schedules for the project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H61D56D8F77294C528B53F882877D21E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF93ABDCF5C8B499DA737E5FE1B4547FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC27B90601CC545C3B3863BE0A3648069"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD47DB849E8494A298FE309EDBC3EB3EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H941C6A5C92074A4EAC4CC0378C8F0477"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Capital asset project</header><text>The term <term>capital asset project</term> means a capital asset investment or activity of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54FF9B69AFAF483BBE27961499F536A5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Super construction project</header><text>The term <term>super construction project</term> has the meaning given such term in section 8103(e)(3) of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2DEC22B07C134AF3BA73DCE2C05E1412"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/81">chapter 81</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 8120 and inserting the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H7427A745AF214DFAB2101E284359AFA5"><toc><toc-entry level="section">8120. Reports on key capital asset investments, activities, and performance.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HB1960FE3203A4D919920552685298345"><enum>207.</enum><header>Reports on projected need for funding for infrastructure and capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H6CF1C62A64A242A0A1ACCFE56888D8C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report summarizing the projected amount of funding for infrastructure and capital assets that the Department of Veterans Affairs will need for the 10 fiscal years that begin immediately following such date. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE9C33BF2694245AD82FA074EE0C4C13B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subsequent reports</header><text>The Secretary shall include in the annual budget of the Department submitted by the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, for fiscal year 2025 and each fiscal year thereafter a report described in subsection (a) relating to the 10 fiscal years that begin immediately following the date on which such budget is submitted. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD51AD3FD165146BDA7B71E2D7C9AD578"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by this section shall include, for each fiscal year covered by the report and for the entire period covered by the report, the following:</text><paragraph id="HFE2CD8B18BA440C9B04301030447A86E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The projected funding needs of the Department disaggregated by funding purpose, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H74516A031CEE481C962B9F01205E241F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Land acquisition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2350E5CFA3CE456A8AD904C6CD8747F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Operations and maintenance of facilities of the existing capital asset portfolio of the Department to include the minimum level of funding below which facilities could not be appropriately maintained. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A85E73BF67646C1A46987DE51E04619"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Operations and maintenance of the planned future capital asset portfolio of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H863170A41BC7479084CF4F27E35F4D79"><enum>(D)</enum><text>New construction, by type, including major construction, minor construction, and nonrecurring maintenance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1CC8CFC9AB44B439CA3D8855F94D404"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Leasing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6499B94DA699489D864D926730D4B163"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Activation of space.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32325909A3C8412C826C3B4588DFFE37"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Disposal, reuse, and remediation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1378D03C6FE4BFEABD8F6E0850CF9E8"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Staffing to support the planning, delivery, management, and maintenance of the Department’s current and future capital asset portfolio.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H485B20C5D9A54C40AC06DF7F946624A7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Such other categories as the Secretary deems relevant. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H80C34234D52C4339BF5DD43FB8CCEEC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The projected funding needs under paragraph (1) disaggregated by—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE55EE0DA71D94DA1BA65D79D64153430"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not fewer than five major components of the Department that use infrastructure resources, including the Veterans Health Administration, the National Cemetery Administration, the Veterans Benefits Administration, the Office of Information and Technology, and all other staff offices of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H905A54A425594FE882B4ED0ED9C7EAF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">type of capital asset investment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1D208BCB42E44209D2D76BC82EF5416"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of the cost increases which may or have been incurred because of the delay in adequate, stable, and predictable funding and forward movement on capital asset projects. Such description may include a discussion of the negative effect of the lack of stable and predictable capital asset funding on the ability of the Department to plan, staff, and execute effective capital asset management.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A71BBB8B7E74C04A2F7FE9DF3E9638F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A complete list of capital asset projects (regardless of size or type) for which all relevant preparatory work has been conducted and whose key limiting factor in commencing is lack of sufficient funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D9F71F8820D4CB0ADDC4885D3D9FB26"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate, including matters relating to necessary legislative or administrative action. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDCEE9176CA2C4B8B8C7FE9037064C6DF"><enum>208.</enum><header>Inspector General of the Department of Veterans Affairs reports on Department infrastructure projects</header><subsection id="H9C8BA8AAA7724995B280B4ADF5212460"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, and at least twice during the six-year period beginning on the date that is three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Inspector General of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report examining the management and performance of relevant capital asset projects of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4B9D68C96CF34D1DA0691C3EB99EF1F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sample projects</header><text>The Inspector General shall select meaningful and representative samples of categories of projects and project management efforts for review, including those that were initiated before the date of the enactment of this Act and those that were initiated on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, such as major construction, minor construction, nonrecurring maintenance, major and minor leases, land acquisition, and disposals.</text></subsection><subsection id="H17E83F515DEF48A2AD6B8A5AEF2517CC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted under subsection (a) may include, at the discretion of the Inspector General, the following:</text><paragraph id="H5119D9EDAE7A406CB9DEA610C016837D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A comparison of planned versus actual cost, schedule, and scope metrics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0101AD86EBAA4DC4A901194A8B38036C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Improvements or lack thereof to capital asset project management, including staffing, at the local, regional, or national levels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BF464530A394E33847F9A2C39D4B03F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Observations on key characteristics inhibiting successful delivery of projects or allowing for successful delivery of projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C8CEA8E8E9942C6BB1664CA7EB41006"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Identification of areas of waste, fraud, and abuse, if any.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3B960CD42CC4D87B3B852A5334066C4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Inspector General considers appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0028D6F1EB4C426491CBA05FC414D726"><enum>209.</enum><header>Comptroller General reports on capital asset program management and execution by Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H95455D13661A4205877364B01A4BDFA9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act and not less frequently than once every three years thereafter until the date that is 9 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report reviewing the progress of the Department of Veterans Affairs toward meeting the goals, metrics, and other plans of the Department under this Act, particularly under sections 101, 102, and 202.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0D721BF23081435FB8168472CBBCB600"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) may include the following:</text><paragraph id="HCC5204DB15804851995609A0C851402D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A review of the performance of the Department related to planning, oversight, management of human capital, contracting, and execution of capital asset projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB42F3DDB50A74F47BAEC0989EA5249A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A review of how the Department is complying with the requirements of this Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9FE2B919F914AB4A860A084C2768030" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other topics as the Comptroller General considers appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H47BC5DBA2EC244E4B52288235F5CC826"><enum>210.</enum><header>Report on dental care physical infrastructure needs of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report, disaggregated by medical center or other relevant health care facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs, on—</text><paragraph id="H66A48F71BAA848C69E9E39C1BBE60873"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the physical infrastructure needed (such as new facilities, renovations, remodels, leases, or other infrastructure) to provide dental services to veterans eligible for such services under the laws administered by the Secretary; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2A8BCB3187B409ABC1CD6F228F5CC49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the project-by-project cost and total cost to establish the physical infrastructure specified under paragraph (1) and an estimated timeline to complete such projects upon receipt of appropriate funding. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H0622291FD72A417F99250FBAD74D3B19"><enum>211.</enum><header>Report on long-term care physical infrastructure needs of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H49FF1C6A6FE847C5B5AC8A88A3DF213B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report, disaggregated by medical center or other relevant health care facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs, identifying the physical infrastructure needs of the Department to support current and future anticipated long-term care needs and models of care for veterans, including—</text><paragraph id="HBC0D26BF8A0945A78AE8F3246FEC0FF8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>infrastructure needed to support the delivery of long-term care for women veterans, veterans with spinal cord injuries and diseases, veterans with traumatic brain injury, veterans with unique behavioral health needs, veterans with memory loss, and other population groups with unique needs or projected future needs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32E2B5FB976A4802874265CFA4BFDDAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information regarding the plans of the Department to provide such care as the Department builds internal capacity but space is not yet available to meet the demand for such care; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H941CF83829434CB886A14B4F951A785C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>with respect to any projects needed to provide the infrastructure specified under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H17B130F01AFC47B89F5B9429A521319F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the estimated individual project cost and total cost to accomplish those projects; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD235FBEF9FFC4FABA50C16EDDA50926B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the estimated individual project timeline to accomplish each such project upon receipt of appropriate funding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H529E6EEEBD95417F9D8F288E10F7ABEC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion of information regarding prioritization of certain projects</header><text>The Secretary shall include in the report required under subsection (a) information regarding how the infrastructure prioritization processes of the Department, such as the Strategic Capital Investment Planning process, or successor process, could be modified to include higher prioritization of projects that support the provision of a health care service that is not widely available, or is not available in compliance with appropriate quality or access standards, from non-Department providers.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFD803EE082CE40D68C0231AC0CE773AB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development of report</header><text>In developing the report required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with relevant regional and national program offices of the Veterans Health Administration with responsibility to manage the various health care services covered by the report, including long-term care and care relating to spinal cord injuries and diseases, to ensure that the report contains a holistic, comprehensive, and integrated plan to address the capital asset and other space needs for the population of veterans who require those services. </text></subsection><subsection id="H22B5BA4CF21D428DB81B12E94D4FE3CA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Indication of types of projects</header><text>In the report required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall indicate the projects that can be most efficiently and effectively accomplished through smaller individual infrastructure projects or through a larger medical facility replacement or new site of care, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection></section><section id="H729C848C8E4147BB87535CAFA242EFB9"><enum>212.</enum><header>Report on feasibility and advisability of using a dedicated budget account for maintenance of capital assets of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="HF7BB2ECB1DA64EB2B62FF7793577F0CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the feasibility and advisability of requesting that Congress create a dedicated budget account from which the Department of Veterans Affairs would request funds, based on relevant methodology, formulas and percentages tied to the existing and future capital asset needs of the Department, and if such funds are provided, draw upon to pay for maintenance, preventative maintenance, and repair of the capital assets of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBCDF39CCDB154896A58CFB880C8CDA28"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H60D64C07026E4B71BD8DAD7565A0DF91"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The best practices used by the Department, drawing from the Federal Government, State and local governments, nonprofit organizations, private industry, and other appropriate entities, relating to stable and consistent planning and budgeting for capital asset maintenance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H163E91E7A13C495BB0BD6270C63B1580" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Relevant formulas and percentages that the Department currently uses to identify the resources required for capital asset maintenance or could use to dedicate or segment off funds to pay for needed and expected maintenance costs based on the size, need, complexity, and other requirements of the capital asset portfolio of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78F5D29C505549CC9FCE33397B736C9F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other information as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H441D46BB88F245EAA408CB3E521BFBCA"><enum>213.</enum><header>Report on women veterans retrofit initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5102 of the Deborah Sampson Act of 2020 (title V of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/315">Public Law 116–315</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/8110">38 U.S.C. 8110</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5BCA6E81BE7A47DDA4836E08FF2F26FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BBE00B2239A483F85480B9502B8921E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection (c):</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H044C1D0B1CE84A50AECB9E25D1959662"><subsection id="H2FF8D67A97004FCA9AD1D1C39AEE07B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report on projects</header><paragraph id="HA6898A5FBE7A495189B80D66EBAE37A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>BUILD for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing—</text><subparagraph id="HCF95E927BADD4AABA9F56301594F899F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an identification of the funding requested and the funding provided to the Department for retrofitting prioritized under subsection (a) as of the date of the report;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEAD982F157B44688B974614F4B75E60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a list of projects conducted with such funding as of such date, including—</text><clause id="HA611DCC980CB47B984CD12259EC8E023"><enum>(i)</enum><text>amounts obligated for each such project;</text></clause><clause id="HCDF9C72ABAB14EF4A660622E9918B0E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the locations of each such project;</text></clause><clause id="H0A19C8DFEB16409E895A64CCE93DA41D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a short description of each such project; and</text></clause><clause id="H277EA4368224400B97137621A9A3DD14"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the status of each such project, including an estimated timeline to complete the project; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A16163307BC49DFAF8E931FDE9BBD51"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of projects for retrofitting prioritized under subsection (a) as of such date that remain unfunded as of such date, including—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2FC743745DBC4FA79E1E0E24061BF690"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the estimated funding required for those projects to be completed, on a project-by-project basis; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C7F9A27495A4FC79578056592A174DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an estimated timeline to complete each such project if necessary funding and other resources are provided.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H23694682E6DA4CFBA4B246A86EC66576"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Not later than one year after the submittal of the report under paragraph (1), and annually thereafter until the earlier of the date that is 10 years after the submittal of such report or the date on which all projects listed under subparagraphs (B) and (C) of such paragraph have been completed, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on—</text><subparagraph id="HB25E053071B140C9ACC618E1A302CEAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the progress made by the Secretary in completing such projects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3993DBF6FBFD4180BA8857A4E0F82601"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of the funding requested and the funding provided to the Department to complete such projects.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD8930C5EA6147D1915429D2222342C8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HEBE8939BEE12425F80BCABCF42E24EB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H742FFEDE49AD4525947CEBBCC5B42FBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H43ECF9A66E7847DA86413B8F2CD748FA"><enum>214.</enum><header>Report on capital asset and information technology needs of the research and development program of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H615856F4D7044D2F9CB6CC0604711ADD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to Congress a report on the capital asset and information technology needs of the research and development program of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE43732679A54476283AC59EE20CA2F0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEFFF8F8E1DAB49BE999A6FC9D13BA061"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H1551FD8849C94CB48AF291784EB2F624"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive summary of new facilities, renovations of existing facilities, leasing of facilities and any other such facilities or physical infrastructure the Department requires to effectively perform its research and development functions, including projected functions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB018F40C6C043C3920D52D98BBAF444"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Detailed information on the information technology resources, projects, equipment, and related information technology needs, disaggregated by type of information technology funding categories, such as development or operations and maintenance, the Department requires in order to make the research and development program and activities of the Department functional and high performing in the short, medium, and long term, and those needed to enable employees of the Department to perform their research and development in an effective and efficient manner.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F152AF5FDE24A6DA2D69659EB1D0FBE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such matters as the Secretary deems relevant to maintain and further improve and advance the research and development functions of the Department through improved capital asset and information technology support. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8838034A966495CBD5260430C3A927B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><subparagraph id="HC5E405CAD42E4906A25BB3554BEEDB0D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Facilities</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8ED9AC27E74F46808A64207EDED1004C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Summaries by project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In providing information under paragraph (1)(A), the Secretary shall provide estimated summaries for each project with cost data as well as a realistic multi-year plan to design and deliver the capital asset projects, assuming required funding is provided.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8B5ED67929F43309C07A6F042007A8F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Identification of projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each project shall be identified by its project type such as major construction, minor construction, nonrecurring maintenance, major lease, minor lease, or such other category as the Secretary determines may be appropriate. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H957C15E9FDEB4B1F86A3FE0D9EDF1769"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information technology</header><text>In providing information under paragraph (1)(B), the Secretary shall provide estimated summaries for each project or investment with individual and total cost data as well as a realistic multi-year plan to develop relevant requirements and acquire and deploy the relevant information technology services, projects, equipment, and related matters. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5E44E40FC9B46F3AC2D006D893BF4C1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>The scope of the report submitted under subsection (a) is on the capital asset, information technology, and other related critical support functions, excluding human capital related needs, needed for the Department to perform research and development in an effective and efficient manner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9AE611FEDC26464A856790F25EB79C12"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In preparing the report required by subsection (a), the Secretary may consider the following:</text><paragraph id="HB0A35372E14946C39E8E2C571165CAC0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The findings of the 2012 final report of the Research Infrastructure Program of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67DDF4569E4245ACB18197ABE025F98B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Current and updated data providing the most accurate and holistic presentation of the physical infrastructure, information technology, and other relevant support function needs of the research and development program of the Department. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B322CCB6C8B422299FC3AD086985CA8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5D00D3BCF9EE45CAAA6039EE4F2A43A3"><enum>215.</enum><header>Review and report on provisions of law relating to Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset management and oversight</header><subsection id="H706E1EDDCB0847F786F2546F90C29F18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall review all relevant authorities of the Department of Veterans Affairs, including those in section 312A of title 38, United States Code, and determine whether the provisions of such authorities are meaningful, relevant, and reflect the current operational needs, organization structure, and all other necessary requirements for the full life-cycle of effective and efficient management of capital assets.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC065413799FD4C17A25C651D61456154"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report regarding whether the authorities reviewed under subsection (a) should be revised to align more closely with current and future projected operational needs of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1C9942E7894B425F9BE14B817EE14DFF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (b) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H35D6C5F5F5384904978888114EF86F7E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of whether other offices, administrations, or entities of the Department should be directed to formally assume certain functions currently assigned to officials of the Department, including to the Deputy Secretary, the Director of Construction and Facilities Management, the Under Secretary for Health, the Assistant Secretary for Management, and the Chief Financial Officer, pursuant to statute or Departmental practice, so as to match operational realties and needs, directives, policies, and procedures of the Department, to improve efficiencies, streamline management and lines of authority, responsibility, and accountability or other reasons that would be beneficial to the capital asset management of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H191C61079C254255997634A5C42F2E0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of whether capital asset functions currently not clearly assumed or controlled by other entities of the Department should be more clearly assigned to relevant offices of the Department to match operational realities and needs, directives, policies, and procedures of the Department, to improve efficiencies, streamline management and lines of authority and responsibility, or other reasons that would be beneficial to the capital asset management of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25D3236EEC244BE680DB40B78A28D72D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of whether any new offices, structures, positions, or reporting lines should be created or modified in the Department to improve operational effectiveness, performance, and accountability for capital asset management.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DCBE512C608479A8B4F5625C8349AC6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of whether a modified Departmental organizational structure and changes to relevant statutory provisions could create a clearly identified single line of accountability and responsibility for the full life-cycle of capital asset management activities of the Department so as to improve effectiveness, efficiency, performance, and stability of Departmental capital asset management. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83B0B28BD7AE434DB9C2B8016A2AD8BF"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Specific reasons for the statutory or other changes that are recommended in the report or if no changes are necessary, a justification for not making any changes, including a statement providing the single responsible executive and office in charge of managing all capital asset management activities of the Department as of the date of the report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA52741150B943BABDDFBA8A1D6F734A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identification of such legislative or administrative action as the Secretary determines necessary to implement the changes necessary to improve capital asset management at the Department. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD061D988B5494D748280A865576B0FF5"><enum>216.</enum><header>Improving prevention, detection, and reporting of waste, fraud, and abuse in Department of Veterans Affairs capital asset projects and activities</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H595C0EBE8D444EE8BE06DAA6BEB321CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on actions the Department of Veterans Affairs is taking or plans to take to enhance the ability of the Department to prevent, detect, and report waste, fraud, and abuse occurring in capital asset projects of the Department, whether by employees, contractors, or other relevant persons or entities involved with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HAB1932BC03C749D98DE7583798A7867A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H0044AFF70DBA45B38FB3B32A79988A22"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of whether new training or enhancements to existing training should be undertaken to improve the prevention, detection, and reporting of waste, fraud, and abuse.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C432857970A4235ABA9CCE181A33B72"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recommendations for such legislative and administrative action as the Secretary determines appropriate to improve the prevention, detection, and reporting of waste, fraud, and abuse.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17954211C8424CF7B38F0476B9C1490A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other matters the Secretary considers appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H62690F45494A45B0ADC91F75A7AE6127"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57F2695AEB6E4086AC7AE2A92A66B500"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall consult with the Inspector General of the Department of Veterans Affairs and the Comptroller General of the United States on matters relating to best practices and strategies to improve detection and prevention by the Department of waste, fraud, and abuse in capital asset projects and management; and</text></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H505520F63AD2429F9BDA024117782D05"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may consult with such other persons and entities on such matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

