<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H736C13648A954B64AA506FC55092D4A5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6304 IH: Increased Cost of Compliance Modernization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6304</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase coverage under the National Flood Insurance Program for costs of compliance, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H40A4BAFC55734254AA050CFE51124C9D" style="OLC"><section id="H30F6909050B14725AB769AE45EA7CE56" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Increased Cost of Compliance Modernization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H557A1FA6CD5142C481A392A07E058FD1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increased cost of compliance coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1304(b) of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4011">42 U.S.C. 4011(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8FCFFD295B254F2B832F6BAA12D62ADA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (4), by redesignating subparagraphs (A) through (D) as clauses (i) through (iv), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B4F286DB9C7411F89E4BD2DB9EECCF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (4) as subparagraphs (A) through (D), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H272D8017A2924724A2EA408BC4A13142"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(b) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Additional coverage for compliance with land use and control measures</header-in-text>.—The national</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H43FEDA2E3CAD41248D03CBEE1AACFF7C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H2855E8DFC27D440CB6059BC0C7649B07"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional coverage for compliance with land use and control measures</header><paragraph id="H35482390157F41C8828EAB549B89A3E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The national</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H1606D470484E4232B88C67B3E61ED4C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking the last sentence (relating to surcharge); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DB4FDFF77C747F4863706D145488006"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42D349A6DD0E4AC990E9600D2251420E" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H50AF813C2EB54AC5AD1D430B9CBF0365" indent="up1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coverage amounts</header><subparagraph id="H0A718235A6B544E29AE7F2D0DCFBFD10"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Basic coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless a policyholder chooses additional coverage pursuant to subparagraph (B), the Administrator shall make available coverage provided under paragraph (1) in an amount equal to 20 percent of the maximum amount of flood insurance coverage allowable under section 1306(b)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4013">42 U.S.C. 4013(b)(2)</external-xref>) with respect to a residential building described in such section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D767C782EA44B1BAD8F9CA622983B39"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may offer, and a policyholder may choose to purchase for an additional premium, coverage provided under paragraph (1) in an amount greater than that offered pursuant to subparagraph (A), but not exceeding an amount equal to 40 percent of the maximum amount of flood insurance coverage allowable under section 1306(b)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4013">42 U.S.C. 4013(b)(2)</external-xref>) with respect to a residential building described in such section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE60F0DF529E14349852CF736ED1E41F6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Treatment of coverage limits</header><text>Any amount of coverage for a property provided pursuant to this subsection shall not be considered or counted for purposes of any limitation on coverage applicable to such property under section 1306(b) and any claim on such coverage shall not be considered a claim for purposes of identifying properties with multiple losses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA00CD6194F04AD3A4999705CB1FCF8D" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Premiums</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall charge risk premium rates for coverage made available pursuant to this subsection in accordance with section 1307(a)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H287F807595BC4BCF883718A0E477CCEB" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Assignment of coverage for mitigation grant cost share requirement</header><subparagraph id="H0F601905D65E45BD8482F32ACF11C1B2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A policyholder may assign the rights or benefits of the coverage made available under this subsection to a governmental entity for the purposes of using payments made for a claim against coverage made available under this subsection to satisfy a required non-Federal contribution for a flood-related mitigation project funded by a mitigation assistance program described in clause (i), (ii), or (iii) of paragraph (1)(D).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1053F08248AD45CE94B07A657692DD37"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a policyholder assigns rights or benefits of coverage pursuant to subparagraph (A), a required non-Federal contribution for a flood-related mitigation project funded by a mitigation assistance program described in clause (i), (ii), or (iii) of paragraph (1)(D) shall be an eligible expense for coverage made available under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BDD938AED0F4E378E1F5EA9F08171FC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header><text>The Administrator may adopt procedures for assigning rights or benefits of coverage pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9FACA02D0D540D1B9785EA8C563FF5E" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Administrator may implement this subsection by adopting one or more standard endorsements to the Standard Flood Insurance Policy by publication of such standards endorsement in the Federal Register or by comparable means.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

