<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB1890C4BB5394AEEBC3ACA2122FECDE2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5236 IH: Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe of North Carolina Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5236</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To extend the full measure of the Federal Government-to-government relationship between the United States and the Haliwa Saponi Tribe of North Carolina.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4FD0156A467E46D4947D61820EE006B7" style="OLC">
<section id="H2A5B64AF23CB442BAA5349B5488D7B5A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe of North Carolina Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HABA207E6A1EA426D8E72D6CB1DE81246"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HDC12CCA89791419A9A3853045F27F9B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe of North Carolina is a confederated Tribe that is a political successor to the historical Saponi Nation and to the Nansemond and affiliated Tribes that inhabited the Piedmont and coastal regions of what are now Virginia and North Carolina.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H512A53895A5740E78ED3B7BB47DA6BC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text><quote>Haliwa</quote> is a geographical designation that is derived from the physical location of the Tribe, which is primarily in Halifax and Warren Counties, North Carolina.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA72BE3E35464494D8679380A43B023D1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In North Carolina, in 1733, the Saponi Nation made peace with the Tuscarora and moved to a portion of the Tuscarora reservation in modern Bertie County, North Carolina, occupying a village known as Sapona Town.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H170F65E3098B4EE48489E50EDB368FEE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 1754, Captain William Hurst observed the residence of Saponi warriors and many women and children on Colonel William Eaton’s lands in the Granville District (modern Bertie, Granville, Warren, and Vance Counties, North Carolina).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE043B13F7D9145A79423F86A8D20381A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In 1761, the Saponi Indians were living on 10,000 acres of land in the Granville District on and near the Roanoke River along with the Meherrin and Tuscarora.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE7E928D14AAF4F83A2931B097A78F61B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In Virginia, as acknowledged by Congress in the Thomasina E. Jordan Indian Tribes of Virginia Federal Recognition Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/121">Public Law 115–121</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 59 et seq.), there were two sections of the Nansemond Tribe, one of which remained in Virginia and was accorded Federal recognition in 2018 concurrently with five other Tribes still resident in Virginia by that same statute.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF995CA24DD9641E5A510F8A8EEFADD9C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Another section of the Nansemond Tribe had migrated to North Carolina due to hostilities in Virginia, and today enrolled citizens of the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe include lineal descendants of those Nansemond.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE39682595A146869D5C03F60A583FF6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>After the American Revolution (1775–1783), the Nansemond and Saponi merged together for mutual protection and survival in Halifax, Warren, Nash, and Franklin Counties, in an area known as <quote>The Meadows</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA79E0023036246CEBB597FAD50F61B8A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Among the surrounding communities, the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe has often been referred to as the <quote>Meadows Indians</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1704F3E487B84FF785AD4107DA483F90"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In 1889, Warren County, North Carolina resident G.B. Alston wrote to the Smithsonian Institution anthropologist James Mooney and confirmed the residence of a Tribe of 300–600 Indians in the Meadows in Halifax and Warren Counties.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF0B05C6C1893433795F60069D272039B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The Tribe has continually existed as a separate community, with leaders exhibiting clear political authority.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5AC6E4FA8034B93BD59D981C32591F3"><enum>(12)</enum><text>While local non-Indians recognized the Indian and Tribal identity of the Haliwa Saponi, others insisted on classifying Tribal citizens as <quote>colored</quote> rather than Indian, due to segregation.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD591CB93B1C24D40837BD6FFC3037AA3"><enum>(13)</enum><text>During the era of school segregation, the Tribe opened its own school, the Haliwa Indian School, operated with the Tribe’s own funds.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3135CEB65EA46C8A2AE1CE527938337"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Since 1957 the State of North Carolina has had continuous dealings with the recognized political leaders of the Haliwa Saponi.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD84E4D86A5C546C9A57C5310A626573A"><enum>(15)</enum><text>In 1957, the Tribe opened the Haliwa Indian School.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61E90D0AABBA4133B252BDC85FEE5351"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Between 1960 and 1963, students from the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe attended Bacone College for Indians in Muscogee, Oklahoma.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E50F6BFC992412DA946569D622948D8"><enum>(17)</enum><text>In 1965, the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe won a lawsuit against the North Carolina Division of Vital Statistics to correct the race of Haliwa Saponi citizens on official records to read <quote>Indian</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H192D22D5026B4368B6C67F934A0EEF63"><enum>(18)</enum><text>In 1965 the State of North Carolina took formal legislative action recognizing the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7775F300F981477595035FBF6B4E9A67"><enum>(19)</enum><text>The United States has been providing Federal funding to the Tribe from the Department of Education’s Office of Indian Education for half a century.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF202B05C65C8488D9A4753C821A6EE87"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The United States has been providing Federal funding to the Tribe for housing and related infrastructure development from the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development pursuant to the Federal Native American Housing and Self-Determination Act for 25 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H67DE0A7FB5974C2697581219FF5138BE"><enum>(21)</enum><text>In 2000, the Tribe opened the Haliwa Saponi Tribal School, a charter school under the State of North Carolina, at the location of the original Haliwa Indian School, and the school currently receives Federal funds from the Department of Education, Office of Indian Education for Haliwa Saponi Indian students.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HF11C30D8F5884B0CB090A2B8AED74794"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H91FB5A56B5F14C17B86A3CD9E04F20D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Member</header><text>The term <quote>Member</quote> means a member of the Haliwa-Saponi Indian Tribe of North Carolina.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BB30DCCA65848EA924A7B08680F8C7F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8667D701A978442B9CE0D3C309F81ED2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tribe</header><text>The term <quote>Tribe</quote> means the Haliwa Saponi Tribe of North Carolina.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA1D6ED06F03D4C61932FF7E31AB304B7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Extension of full Federal Government-to-government relations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The United States hereby extends to the Haliwa Saponi Indian Tribe the full measure of the Federal Government-to-government relationship to make all laws (including regulations) of the United States of general applicability to Indians or nations, Indian Tribes, or bands of Indians (including the Act of June 18, 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5101">25 U.S.C. 5101 et seq.</external-xref>)) that are not inconsistent with this Act applicable to the Tribe and Tribal members.</text></section>
<section id="H586BB9F7C0934FAB8EB7F33AE18ABDA1"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal services and benefit</header>
<subsection id="HDD1B97D4D075486FA10D3B774BF25B7D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Tribe and its members shall be eligible for all services and benefits provided by the Federal Government to federally recognized Indian Tribes without regard to the existence of a reservation for the Tribe, including services and benefits under the Act of June 18, 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5101">25 U.S.C. 5101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE2C38ABA887D4F53B2C11A369C252243"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Service area</header><text>For the purpose of the delivery of Federal services and benefits to members, the service area of the Tribe shall include Halifax, Warren, Nash, Franklin, Vance, and Granville counties in the State of North Carolina.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDEEA45F17EB5437798CCBCB44296D0A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Service population</header><text>For purpose of the delivery of Federal services and benefits described in subsection (a), the Tribal roll in effect on the date of enactment of this Act shall, subject to verification by the Secretary, define the service population of the Tribe.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEBE282EDEA6848B4993DD3C641AFF061"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Roll; governing documents</header><text>The membership roll and government documents of the Tribe shall be the most recent membership roll and governing documents, respectively, submitted by the Tribe to the Secretary before the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H0C9D7F3F642747AF9C102EAF6D1D78C8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization to take land into trust</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary is authorized to take land into trust for the benefit of the Tribe and proclaim a reservation for the Tribe pursuant to the authorities granted to the Secretary in the Act of June 18, 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5101">25 U.S.C. 5101 et seq.</external-xref>), and lands acquired in trust for the Tribe and included in the first reservation proclamation for the Tribe shall be treated as an initial reservation that meets the requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/100/497">Public Law 100–497</external-xref>, section 20(b)(1)(B)(ii).</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

