<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4161E7E8D8B744748B2E4247D8883B05" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2677 IH: Harnessing Opportunities by Pursuing Expungement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2677</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Attorney General to make grants to States and units of local government to reduce the financial and administrative burden of expunging convictions for cannabis offenses, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC8101814496B4B98B8C86D8BF1BD086E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8FE1477AB3B54C39862E3EF1677187BF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Harnessing Opportunities by Pursuing Expungement Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HOPE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H89A6707BD0D54843A5B21FBC11049763"><enum>2.</enum><header>State Expungement Opportunity Grant Program</header> <subsection id="H37A4B64559B4452EA7466DFE67931C98"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Name of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The grant program established under this section shall be known as the <quote>State Expungement Opportunity Grant Program</quote>. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H284254E8533249A289865D096E075026"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General is authorized to make grants to States and units of local government to reduce the financial and administrative burden of expunging convictions for cannabis offenses that are available to individuals who have been convicted of such offenses under the laws of the State.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDFCE0D16EC284102B91A8D35C89F4768"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The chief executive of a State or unit of local government seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H9E8F98D302684ACDB8722C4DD4F95A4E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants under this section shall be used—</text> <paragraph id="H17C1DBF9EC7540D3B9F7448D33B4F6B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for technology to provide cost-effective legal relief at scale;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6DA42DCFAFBC49EE89841D863A914F86"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to automate the process of expunging convictions for cannabis offenses;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BAC2832F8734264905C0ADC2FE49571"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for clinics, including legal clinics, that assist individuals through the expungement process;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6244AA2ED3F94E14922B24FF9AF9655B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to implement the notice requirement described in subsection (e);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7A83A267DAD94A52A4A8C598EB615AE8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to seal records of conviction for cannabis offenses, if appropriate; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F37BF23F2C74837A682B83071DE1F30"><enum>(6)</enum><text>for other innovative partnerships to provide wide-scale relief to individuals who are eligible for the expungement of a conviction for a cannabis offense under the laws of the State.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H42CE569D5B79404A92CA60167BC99363"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Notice requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A jurisdiction that receives a grant under this section shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H8697117A87A14124BEB5396DBA3468F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>publish on a publicly accessible website information about the availability and process of expunging convictions for cannabis offenses, including information for individuals living in a different jurisdiction who were convicted of a cannabis offense in that jurisdiction; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66F8971A58C04C28B2A1FECE8DBFF049"><enum>(2)</enum><text>implement a process to notify each individual convicted of a cannabis offense when—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA1F7F334443243CAAEF8A0EAAD53F6EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the expungement process has begun; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D0B6B0B881648D883FBCC889EAF5FFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when the expungement is complete, which shall, if applicable, include an official certificate of expungement (including any other similar document used by the jurisdiction).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA1BF5514583441C0879BD8C85A0BB1FB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>A jurisdiction that receives a grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General a report describing the uses of such funds, and how many convictions for cannabis offenses have been expunged using such funds.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD10B7FB05A534802A76042261B377A51"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $2,000,000 to carry out this section for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2033. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="H7D095341D0834C4D99B43EDFB4A79E3A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study on the impact of criminal offenses related to cannabis</header>
<subsection id="HDBD6D246F0E8436F8443D04EAB6FDAD5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall conduct a study and submit to Congress and make publicly available on the website of the Department of Justice a report on—</text> <paragraph id="H127AFE12DFEB42339214F82A70150239"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the effects of the appearance on an individual’s criminal record report of a conviction for a criminal offense related to cannabis, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5302431215184DF29794739E80336AC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disqualifying him or her from future opportunities in housing and employment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5BEA8ECB4384FB7BD271986FD218887"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increasing the likelihood that the individual will have future involvement with the criminal justice system;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H61DF77C6083C437F8C8B965E04E25588"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how any such effects differ based on demographics, including race; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H68563D331DD6497D802AE20053B8BB17"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other matters determined appropriate by the Attorney General; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6496CE9021CA4C4D828B1A586738E957"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the costs incurred by States for incarcerating an individual convicted for a criminal offense related to cannabis. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6794D6B4669F4239809C72FDEF6CBAAA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under subsection (a) may not include any personally identifiable information. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="H0639FDB79C67467BA18FF6BC73FBC6EC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HF196369732C6485BA84F3DFBB1C37DCB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cannabis</term> means either marijuana or cannabis as defined under the State law authorizing the sale or use of cannabis in which the individual or entity is located.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2C7E905451E34E7B8849B9BDD31415F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cannabis offense</term> means a criminal offense related to cannabis that, under State law, is no longer an offense or that was designated a lesser offense or for which the penalty was reduced under State law pursuant to or following the adoption of a State law authorizing the sale or use of cannabis.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

