<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDA8EFF89D2CA48AEB9EA1E1BBBACBD29" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4490 IH: To amend the Controlled Substances Act to authorize pharmacies to deliver certain controlled substances to an administering practitioner in lieu of delivering such substances to the ultimate user, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4490</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Controlled Substances Act to authorize pharmacies to deliver certain controlled substances to an administering practitioner in lieu of delivering such substances to the ultimate user, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4101181409EF4D47821DED6DC43BB280" style="OLC">
<section id="H4F0A0F7DA1234E799EAEA206DF4DB20A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Delivery of certain substances by a pharmacy to an administering practitioner</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of section 309A(a) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/829a">21 U.S.C. 829a(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H44742C1DB53345B4969AEFC949AC3D86" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HF4F914426D1D4089BD50DCE24FBFC2DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the controlled substance is a drug in schedule III, IV, or V that is, pursuant to the approval or licensure of such drug under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, to be administered by, or under the supervision of, the practitioner;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


