<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H84A4FD3B24414954B6E9584B3826B037" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1157 IH: Countering the PRC Malign Influence Fund Authorization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1157</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the authorization of appropriations for the Countering the People&#8217;s Republic of China Malign Influence Fund, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3456F263B9184AA6887ED8D7FB9A0893" style="OLC">
<section id="H4365DA59B58D4EDCB66BBC29805F45BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Countering the PRC Malign Influence Fund Authorization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H275B90CBBF9F4C00834947E7E657FD7C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for Countering the People’s Republic of China Malign Influence Fund</header> <subsection id="H5B032B1BA7F6468BA679BF94D7AEEE19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Countering the People’s Republic of China Malign Influence Fund</header> <paragraph id="H2601A97300434B268BDD1BBEAA6222E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $325,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027 for the Countering the People’s Republic of China Malign Influence Fund to counter the malign influence of the Chinese Communist Party and the Government of the People’s Republic of China and entities acting on their behalf globally.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6B28C21B4314BD5B1E80FCF370B1C21"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability; amounts in addition to other amounts</header><text>Amounts appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H0D60A4E5E1954E828AB8D6D4FD148F5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are authorized to remain available until expended; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC3E2E3BFF9CF4E5689F154726FFE85CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall be in addition to amounts otherwise authorized to be appropriated for the purposes described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE5EEE8EFE36C480B85F243F8421D526C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The obligation of funds appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (a) or otherwise made available for the purposes described in subsection (a)(1) shall be subject to prior consultation with, and consistent with section 634A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2394-1">22 U.S.C. 2394–1</external-xref>), the regular notification procedures of—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA781EF4274AD4DFFA73E1E087AB3C225"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBEFCFBF2317047EAB2EF351C13A92D4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF5B0905875F049FEAC638E0DC67E5FAD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Policy guidance, coordination, and approval</header> 
<paragraph id="H8D2684A641984F1FB6C934DD143D2C20"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coordinator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall designate an existing senior official of the Department of State to provide policy guidance, coordination, and approval for the obligation of funds appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CC27804F8A44E288825F2D65C11225F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistant coordinator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall designate an existing senior official of the United States Agency for International Development to assist and consult with the senior official of the Department of State designated pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49E964F576704AC1871090BDCBF2BE8C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The senior official of the Department of State designated pursuant to paragraph (1) shall be responsible for—</text> <subparagraph id="HDDDA7A55BF0D4E4E8290FBB55992C160"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on an annual basis, the identification of specific strategic priorities for using funds appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (a), such as geographic areas of focus or functional categories of programming that funds are to be concentrated within, consistent with the national interests of the United States and the purposes of this section;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H040093DAA14046F8924372CE93D680EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the coordination and approval of all programming conducted using such funds, based on an assessment that such programming directly counters the malign influence of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China, including specific activities or policies advanced by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China and entities acting on their behalf globally, pursuant to the strategic objectives of the United States, as established in the 2017 National Security Strategy, the 2018 National Defense Strategy, and other relevant national and regional strategies as appropriate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H284BE2112A834FE8B9C6F5300546BDE2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring that all programming approved bears a sufficiently direct nexus to such activities of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China described in subsection (d) and adheres to the requirements outlined in subsection (e); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD92F22A5711E4EA6B618C656246E38BD"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting oversight, monitoring, and evaluation of the effectiveness of all programming conducted using such funds to ensure that it advances United States interests and degrades the ability of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China, to advance activities that align with subsection (d) of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H038F5DA8E8A9464B90D8BB9DE6BF125E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The senior official of the Department of State designated pursuant to paragraph (1) shall, in coordinating and approving programming pursuant to paragraph (2), seek—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8B4E973681F04536B546EBE8E4B1ADE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to conduct appropriate interagency consultation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB8516AD56194071B922B4BD628E0424"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to ensure, to the maximum extent practicable, that all approved programming functions in concert with other Federal activities to counter the malign influence of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4644EF4AF5A3408BB529D6F5D6F0A080"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Malign influence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>malign influence</quote>, with respect to the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China, shall be construed to include acts conducted by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China, or entities acting on their behalf that—</text> <paragraph id="H7A8EDEE8101F4FDF85F6E1F415EF5D7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>undermine a free and open international order;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE114FF5560A4485CB40461ACDED83EDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advance an alternative, repressive international order that bolsters the Chinese Communist Party’s or the Government of the People’s Republic of China’s hegemonic ambitions and is characterized by coercion and dependency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12679C6528A541A386DD7DEFB99F920D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>undermine the national security or sovereignty of the United States or other countries; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1D89D266BB3C4FE4943C37BC4B1728CB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>undermine the economic security of the United States or other countries, including by promoting corruption and advancing coercive economic practices.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3BB256DB30014341931EA0084D716E98"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Countering malign influence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, countering malign influence through the use of funds appropriated pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (a) shall include efforts—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8C4AD04CC860470F95D721899EEE5B63"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to promote transparency and accountability, and reduce corruption, including in governance structures targeted by the malign influence of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BBD5EB1C2164A2B9150D551639453B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to support civil society and independent media to raise awareness of and increase transparency regarding the negative impact of activities related to the Belt and Road Initiative, associated initiatives, other economic initiatives with strategic or political purposes, and coercive economic practices;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H851C011E3A774FE2A5E11E75E4DC3649"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to counter transnational criminal networks that benefit, or benefit from, the malign influence of the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFB75F2E58964EE2AF296A24B1A01B92"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to encourage economic development structures that help protect against predatory lending schemes, including support for market-based alternatives in key economic sectors, such as digital economy, energy, and infrastructure;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H212851DBD8F242488930F218A272B574"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to counter activities that provide undue influence to the security forces of the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H240789AC3AA44D03B28E6D67BBF2A791"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to expose misinformation and disinformation of the Chinese Communist Party’s or the Government of the People’s Republic of China’s propaganda, including through programs carried out by the Global Engagement Center; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEA6409273A124263924939D24CE6E0AE"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to counter efforts by the Chinese Communist Party or the Government of the People’s Republic of China to legitimize or promote authoritarian ideology and governance models.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H16BAC48FB0F042B9BB1E9A4AFA4BE490"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual summary</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2023, and annually thereafter for 5 years, the senior official of the Department of State designated pursuant to subsection (c)(1) shall submit to the congressional committees specified in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (b), a summary identifying each activity or program approved pursuant to subsection (c), and shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H95EF36881AEB46BDADE3EB3F4C0275BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for each program or activity, an identification of the country or regional location of the program or activity;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H018B692B6B064E7CAEDFA621576C9FB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each program or activity, whether the program or activity was ongoing prior to receiving support from funds from the Countering People’s Republic of China Malign Influence Fund, or any predecessor resource intended for the same or substantially similar purpose;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD0D6EEA2631C45148E5DA5B79CB03256"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for each program or activity, an identification of the acts described in subsection (d) that such program or activity is intended to counter; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01AAA7A5E066401EBB86F748CAD2E0A0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a table identifying the respective allocation of all programs or activities approved during that fiscal year across accounts and regional or functional bureaus.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

