<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H752BF0EB56BD45E58D96B5A8E2B278C7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1760 IH: To extend the admission to Guam or the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands for certain nonimmigrant H–2B workers.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1760</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To extend the admission to Guam or the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands for certain nonimmigrant H&#8211;2B workers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFB6C2B64D0E946E2892EBD98D752802F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD70979CCEF1D4A1CA344EABD7ABB6D22" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Extension of admission to Guam or the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands for certain nonimmigrant H–2B workers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(b)(1)(B) of the Joint Resolution entitled <quote>A Joint Resolution to approve the <quote>Covenant to Establish a Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands in Political Union with the United States of America</quote>, and for other purposes</quote>, approved March 24, 1976 (48 U.S.C. 11 1806(b)(1)(B)), is amended, in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>December 31, 2024</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2029</quote>.</text> </section> </legis-body></bill>

