<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HACF2B1417CA2495AA0659511B41D80F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6772 IH: Expanding Access to Retirement Savings for Caregivers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6772</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to reduce the age for making catch-up contributions to retirement accounts to take into account time out of the workforce to provide dependent care services.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEA8B150ED63F433AA4330973B56F5090" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H772DD19F55554DEDB02997FF8A860708" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Access to Retirement Savings for Caregivers Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF57683123CF5449EB25602614629CE24"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reduction of age for making catch-up contributions for individuals out of workforce to provide dependent care services</header> <subsection id="HEF501B4066DE49EDB4E0480CE13D84CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Individual retirement plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/219">Section 219(b)(5)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D79CC098E68459A8EAFD44F1297D7AE" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H953C516991FE42FC9E7A8342CFEC1FAB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Reduction of age for making catch-up contributions for individuals out of workforce to provide dependent care services</header> 
<clause id="H065D83DEFE97410CBEB9FC195E15EECA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible individual, subparagraph (B)(i) shall be applied by substituting <quote>the applicable age with respect to such individual</quote> for <quote>the age of 50</quote>.</text></clause> <clause id="H5E8C45A30FE44974B822F1BE969E2DF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Applicable age</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>applicable age</quote> means, with respect to any eligible individual for any taxable year, 50 reduced by the number of years which is equal to the duration of the aggregate qualified unemployment periods with respect to such individual (determined as of the beginning of such taxable year). For purposes of the preceding sentence any duration of aggregate qualified unemployment periods which is not a multiple of a whole number of years shall be rounded to the next lowest whole number of years.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7DD56B3618B74861A187B9D48DA64DD1"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>eligible individual</quote> means, with respect to any taxable year, any individual who has one or more qualified unemployment periods determined as of the beginning of such taxable year.</text></clause> <clause id="HFE23AA79DDA0493BA53B3D63E4AAEEA4"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Qualified unemployment period</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <quote>qualified unemployment period</quote> means, with respect to any individual, any uninterrupted period—</text> 
<subclause id="H0AD98916CFD046C0B68B66FB71807904"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which is not less than 1 year,</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC79364B0D80146CDA4138007759B2F26"><enum>(II)</enum><text>which begins after such individual attains age 18, and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HBD3F1C86344248D2BF917D983F6C8E86"><enum>(III)</enum><text>during which such individual has no earned income (as defined in section 32(c)(2)) on account of such individual’s provision of care to one or more qualifying individuals (as defined in section 21(b)(1)).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HF0F40C0710794846806C71B23F1F8A92"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Declaration requirement</header><text>A qualified unemployment period shall not be taken into account under this subparagraph with respect to any individual unless such individual has made a self attestation under the penalties of perjury that such period meets the requirements of clause (iv) with respect to such individual. The trustee may rely on such attestation unless the trustee knows, or has reason to know, that such attestation is false.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB54CFAE545AB4992970F86C086E0BC37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elective deferrals</header><text>Section 414(v) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE7F46532C8A84821893FB53CC796019E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H5051229D47084BD0869067C04577F3DD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Reduction of age for making catch-up contributions for individuals out of workforce to provide dependent care services</header> <subparagraph id="HDA467714B9744D45982457DC08A04BA0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible participant, paragraph (5)(A) shall be applied by substituting <quote>the applicable age with respect to such participant</quote> for <quote>age 50</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H498EEA89A5F0419C9312E963864C1D31"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application of definitions and rules</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, clauses (ii), (iii), (iv), and (v) of section 219(b)(5)(D) shall apply—</text> <clause id="HF438C00CCED642A5ACF0C79F1D053252"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by substituting <quote>participant</quote> for <quote>individual</quote> each place it appears in such clauses, and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H516FD0445CFB44F2A2B137A1410D2FDB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by substituting <quote>plan administrator</quote> for <quote>trustee</quote> in such clause (v).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H90378FDC90DE4098B7B8F8531E885A93"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Error correction</header><text>The Secretary shall issue regulations or other guidance under which an applicable employer plan may correct for an impermissible catch-up contribution by providing for a distribution of such contribution together with any earnings properly attributable thereto.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F33F2C56497408DA229EC42C2FF7113"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

