<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H857193C5557B4478ADD03CF1ECDA8B7C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>91 HR 3415 IH: Pilot Butte Power Plant Conveyance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3415</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior to convey to the Midvale Irrigation District the Pilot Butte Power Plant in the State of Wyoming, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCB9D98989F2340EE9F9D5469B462996C" style="OLC"><section id="H8B6155B3A96D4ADFAB63179C29966EBB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pilot Butte Power Plant Conveyance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H469BDD0D277E41E5832A22161BDBECF5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H2ED809A5344441189E62F3F5BF03370B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text>The term <term>Agreement</term> means the agreement entered into under section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H428755B9BDE144E6811994C19D80AD30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>District</header><text>The term <term>District</term> means the Midvale Irrigation District located in Pavillion, Wyoming.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F2A3964DC3C477FA210163ECC613347"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Power plant</header><text>The term <term>Power Plant</term> means the Pilot Butte Power Plant and other appurtenant facilities in the State of Wyoming authorized under the Act of March 2, 1917 (39 Stat. 969, chapter 146), transferred to the jurisdiction of the Bureau of Reclamation under the Act of June 5, 1920 (41 Stat. 874, chapter 235), and incorporated into the Riverton Unit of the Pick-Sloan Missouri Basin Program under <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/91/409">Public Law 91–409</external-xref> (84 Stat. 861), including the underlying land.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06AA73959E0E40C895BBA22443F57F45"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Commissioner of Reclamation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H71520E92D52247738D68D1E798A25C26"><enum>3.</enum><header> Agreement, conveyance, and report</header><subsection id="H83B2041C0D6B4F02A5EAE9E9F8C5FBA7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall enter into good faith negotiations with the District to enter into an agreement to determine the legal, institutional, and financial terms for the conveyance of the Power Plant from the Secretary to the District.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA785A14F27DF4CF48C9F2A40C7EEDD93"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conveyance</header><paragraph id="H5CEC6AA4815C42FE938D68CF62CDD48B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In consideration for the District assuming from the United States all liability for the administration, operation, maintenance, and replacement of the Power Plant, the Secretary shall offer to convey and assign to the District all right, title, and interest of the United States in and to the Power Plant—</text><subparagraph id="H14866645228B4ECD9B2546FC7736CF85"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to valid leases, permits, rights-of-way, easements, and other existing rights; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H288F84C2CE8C41FCA34EFFEEF6FF34C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in accordance with—</text><clause id="HC70D0B28F0D94D50B3D63839F29BFC12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the terms and conditions described in the Agreement; and </text></clause><clause id="HE878D7F9F8F94D1DA3B8B51870105368"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CFE549CE2E34CAC88205D26026C436E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Status of land</header><text>Effective on the date of the conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under paragraph (1), the Power Plant shall not be considered to be a part of a Federal reclamation project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF0B29BEBC26E4C39A9E29E92D50F5E54"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>If the conveyance authorized under subsection (b)(1) is not completed by the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives a report that describes—</text><paragraph id="H0C82E0E6DA434FE4BC8A5A0C76E9295E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the status of the conveyance under that subsection;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD881F6AD01B74704ABD177F1F9CAC6A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text> any obstacles to completing the conveyance under that subsection; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H662D31D6CB854F10A39198BD2EA4E141"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an anticipated date for the completion of the conveyance under that subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4233558A74744A5ABC47D21F895CD978"><enum>4.</enum><header>Liability</header><subsection id="H94726B29C01B4744810C7065ED5BEDD6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Damages</header><text>Except as otherwise provided by law and for damages caused by acts of negligence committed by the United States or by employees or agents of the United States, effective on the date of the conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under section 3(b)(1), the United States shall not be held liable by any court for damages of any kind arising out of any act, omission, or occurrence relating to the Power Plant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE07ED5143D054718B54214538DF2BBBD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Torts Claims</header><text>Nothing in this section increases the liability of the United States beyond that provided in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Federal Tort Claims Act</quote>).</text></subsection></section><section id="H9B90FD0CE672450BBC6828E856FD04B8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Compliance with other laws</header><subsection id="H15B6EAC53C484725BEB2431792AEEB8C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Compliance with Environmental and Historic Preservation Laws</header><text>Before making the conveyance authorized under section 3(b)(1), the Secretary shall complete all actions required under—</text><paragraph id="H2C7A6EE345EF4B389C21D1F184959275"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA175CB13FDDB4B98B32B0EF69921CA6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9451A0BF482C4AB4B850917C1256C4A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>subtitle III of title 54, United States Code; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1E67ACB101F4B0B9B58B5CB7571AAE8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other applicable laws.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43E3D5AF784F4C3892CACD9EB48892AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compliance by the District</header><text>Effective on the date of the conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under section 3(b)(1), the District shall comply with all applicable Federal, State, and local laws (including regulations) with respect to the operation of the Power Plant.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4B3BEE5F862B4236BBBE0C74608555A3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Payment of costs</header><subsection id="H912090AD743F4AC393EDD0A083035227"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Administrative Costs</header><text>Administrative costs for the conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under section 3(b)(1) shall be paid in equal shares by the Secretary and the District.</text></subsection><subsection id="H972517A0588B49239C60FBFC8F2A10CA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Real Estate Transfer Costs</header><text>The costs of all boundary surveys, title searches, cadastral surveys, appraisals, and other real estate transactions required for the conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under section 3(b)(1) shall be paid in equal shares by the Secretary and the District.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAF42F9B64752498884BE830BB14A8D6A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Costs of Compliance with Other Laws</header><text>The costs associated with any review required under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>), the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>), subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, or any other applicable laws for conveyance of the Power Plant to the District under section 3(b)(1) shall be paid in equal shares by the Secretary and the District. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

