<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02119144AB164813AF6C2658CD14E9BA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1519 IH: Compensation for the Victims of State Misrepresentations to the World Health Organization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1519</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide justice for victims of foreign state misrepresentation to the World Health Organization, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC41E7D6C8A574E93AC8D824FA2A037D0" style="OLC"><section id="H432A0927418D4B89B08B55B6790BF9D2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Compensation for the Victims of State Misrepresentations to the World Health Organization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD0E79EB6FD144B128887C5A6F54A5F7A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><subsection id="H66C8431D8FD547C1BA6AE8F57BF316E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HF2059432260A410D9436484649228CEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>There is a role for an international organization to help mitigate infectious diseases that respect no boundaries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA706E06A22147AE8028C936A6DF9803"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States depends on an effective World Health Organization (WHO) to make good, well informed, and transparent public health decisions to contain infectious diseases.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H509F736649894C818FA4F62C639BD591"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the past, the WHO played a critical role in addressing and mitigating infectious diseases, such as the 1979 eradication of smallpox, which eradication the WHO coordinated through a sustained global effort.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4CFBCC10E174710AFEA490C3AD1DF62"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Without accurate information, the WHO cannot advise Member States properly on the risks posed by infectious diseases.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44CFB349A47142199B85F8FC061480A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>There are credible reports that in 2006, 2009, and 2011 the Government of Ethiopia misrepresented the nature and seriousness of cholera epidemics in that country to the WHO with a view towards minimizing the potential damage to their economy.</text><subparagraph id="H3740032000EF4051B56E94B05E6BD269"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Those misrepresentations diminished the WHO’s effectiveness and the WHO transmitted inaccurate and misleading information regarding the presence of cholera to participating states.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H891E6BC31836488899EE57C78F7FD794"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Other Member States relied on the misleading and inaccurate information that the WHO communicated to them to formulate public health policy, resulting in loss of life, injury, and damage to property and commercial interests to citizens outside of Ethiopia as a consequence of that country’s misrepresentations to the WHO.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H352513CD3FBD4FFEBDF9C25ADC098D1D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>There are credible reports that WHO Member States misrepresented facts concerning the Ebola outbreak to that organization with a view towards minimizing the commercial impact that a widely disseminated understanding of the risks posed by the Ebola epidemic may have caused in their individual economies.</text><subparagraph id="H9007BBD254FE44B3B689D0711441EFB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Those misrepresentations diminished the WHO’s effectiveness, and the WHO transmitted inaccurate and misleading information regarding the communicability of Ebola to participating States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB78FBC5620C645ADBBA957300FE5B351"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Other Member States relied on the misleading and inaccurate information that the WHO communicated to them to formulate public health policy, resulting in loss of life, injury, and damage to property and commercial interests to citizens outside of the misrepresenting States as a consequence of those countries’ misrepresentations to the WHO.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC9409ED56FA435B89C2B645335E4020"><enum>(7)</enum><text>During the onset of the COVID–19 pandemic, China misrepresented the seriousness and nature of the novel coronavirus to the WHO, with a view towards minimizing the potential damage to their economy and international reputation.</text><subparagraph id="HD58B03AF1B6D45B8B2F47D3B42B82975"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Those misrepresentations diminished the WHO’s effectiveness and the WHO transmitted inaccurate and misleading information regarding the communicability of the novel coronavirus to participating States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF018D629205E40C9BEA7B56CE785FFE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Other Member States relied on the misleading and inaccurate information that the WHO communicated to them to formulate public health policy, resulting in loss of life, injury, and damage to property and commercial interests to citizens outside of China as a consequence of that country’s misrepresentations to the WHO.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H68A11B38EA924B2EA09380A7EF099BC0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In failing to relay accurate information to Member States particularly at the onset of the COVID–19 pandemic, Director-General Tedros relied on false information provided by the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party that the virus either could not be transmitted human-to-human or had a low rate of transmission, and based on such reliance, failed to thoroughly investigate the origins of the COVID–19 virus as well as contrary evidence of whistleblowers such as Li Wenliang regarding the virus’s transmissibility and lethality, thereby abetting the People’s Republic of China’s efforts to suppress information regarding a global health emergency. To date he has failed to hold the People’s Republic of China accountable to International Health Regulations, which apply to all WHO members, and mandate accurate reporting of disease outbreaks.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7EE420E3150F4489855B34816904C19F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Responsibility of foreign states for loss of life, injury, or other damages resulting from certain misrepresentations to the World Health Organization</header><subsection id="HB39802BA6CA74FDD892A23C624E5BCBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1605(a)(5) of title 28, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>in which money damages are sought against a foreign state for personal injury or death, or damage to or loss of property, occurring in the United States and caused by the tortious act or omission of that foreign state or of any official or employee of that foreign state while acting within the scope of his office or employment;</quote> and inserting <quote>in which money damages are sought against a foreign state, for personal injury or death, or damage to or loss of property, occurring in the United States as a result of a willful or grossly negligent misrepresentation of information to the World Health Organization of the nature, seriousness, or communicability of an infections disease or other tortious act or omission of that foreign state or of any official or employee of that foreign state while acting within the scope of his office or employment;</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H2EF310509EEF47E7ABC38DBB9EABE7F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1605(a)(5)(B) of title 28, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>misrepresentation, deceit,</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H687E149CE7A745C9B5607DBB9F241C1B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall take effect 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

