<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD38B833C502044A0835FBF9496A80901" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3180 IH: Bus Integration Dedicated to Improving Resilience, Eliminating Congestion, and Triggering Innovation Over Numerous Applications and Localities Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3180</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Energy to establish a program to encourage deployment of electric school buses and vehicle-to-grid technologies and applications, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF755C96D339C441C88D2283C3E7FFFA5" style="OLC"><section id="H50F8B5697EB24DA291F19397D69AE5F9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bus Integration Dedicated to Improving Resilience, Eliminating Congestion, and Triggering Innovation Over Numerous Applications and Localities Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BIDIRECTIONAL Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBBA62DA6AAE74DABA0BB6F2C9C573F9E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program to encourage deployment of electric school buses and vehicle-to-everything technologies and applications</header><subsection id="HF50B3A2032D947C59ABE3183F76107D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEC1A1141580A4341B237507BE4540EC0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Electric school bus</header><text>The term <term>electric school bus</term> means a school bus that is propelled—</text><subparagraph id="H3B2648B9607C441FB30AC6A85C02D0C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to a significant extent, as determined by the Secretary, by an electric motor that—</text><clause id="H206F5193B9094C91BDDC8851BF2D7AA7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>draws electricity from a battery; and</text></clause><clause id="H0DF872BC58774D11833CBC1779C212E5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is capable of being recharged from an external source of electricity; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC42F0BF6EB0B47FAA7D3795E48C6009C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by any necessary components or equipment required to facilitate electric-powered school bus operations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H904EEF82A2A540FBA268CA19BCB6A31C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H74C83A9831064A03B472D0041BC32F37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any person (including any company or other entity) or State, local, or Tribal entity that sells electric energy, including—</text><clause id="HC9C149DC02D44D34BCA8F825E917D35C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an electric utility, including—</text><subclause id="H55AB98650F02448E91E423CE7707F06B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a local distribution company or utility; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H81B7C25E62034EA6946FF329EBC55F17"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an electric cooperative;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFDB768199CC247A6974F0FD2A8AA9BA1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a municipality; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H70ACC66F5C0F48A38F957AFA4CD2971B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a retail marketer of electricity;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4ECAF273C0845F7A1E8AD1C7A766531"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State public utilities commission; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45ABAFEEF26B4F32904B840E298E3A31" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a third-party energy efficiency program administrator; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C23C34B977D40FD9529CEFB4783A337"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a school bus manufacturer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA787D6475A6E45AF8529DEED539D8B90"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a public or private school district;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39758314116A4F16B5C11764180EF580"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a supplier of charging infrastructure;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB2B2056FA004A249DAEEE9E9066BE5A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a developer, provider, owner, or operator of solar, wind, or other renewable or distributed energy resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26A76A0CDF214E948DB6D76512D8EA5E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a third-party school bus fleet or charging operator;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9E8B1CA1F5C400CB342DE6D5A3B3A69"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any other entity, including a partnership, that the Secretary determines to be appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F50D85370E04553BA4440A2DAFE8D3E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any partnership or consortium of entities described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (I).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AA51D95946742A5910DED1920AE9D93" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the <act-name parsable-cite="ISDA">Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H415DA69CE0D94A12AAA1E84DDAFD12A1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD613E0E4725948178B0489513565372A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the program established under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCE5915ABB334B4881138B9086921FE5" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Project partner</header><text>The term <term>project partner</term>, with respect to a project for which a grant is sought or provided under the Program, means an eligible entity that is a member of a partnership or consortium described in paragraph (2)(J) with respect to that project.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3C94F3DFEB04ADFA0CD9C82323B90B7" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Regional Transmission Organization</header><text>The term <term>Regional Transmission Organization</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/796">16 U.S.C. 796</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11AF058C01A54D899A6556BFF6FB8AC1"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H719C6177ED0641C9A948E04974475746"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program</header><paragraph id="HBCCDAFAF95BB44B9BB59BE29F0B5BCED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a program to encourage the deployment of vehicle-to-grid and vehicle-to-everything technologies and applications, as described in paragraph (2), including, at a minimum, a vehicle capable of discharging at least 10 kilowatts of power to bidirectional electric vehicle supply equipment that provides alternating current power to an electrical circuit, by providing grants to eligible entities for projects that include the use of not fewer than 1 electric school bus with bidirectional energy flow capabilities for an application described in that paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA1463DE584C4477972F9E34D3C392A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application described</header><text>An application referred to in paragraph (1) is—</text><subparagraph id="HF75C5AD65F824B6691070D486D461AB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a vehicle-to-grid application, such as—</text><clause id="H78615748CF10407DB45682DB0282307B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provision of a distribution-level service or participation in a distribution-level program;</text></clause><clause id="H58E24EEB70E049BA9748319B10074BC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provision of wholesale market services, such as capacity, energy, and ancillary services;</text></clause><clause id="HD0F41E10EA62418DA951C9FCE51DDA29"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provision of microgrid services; or</text></clause><clause id="H8D9A2A61F8D94DB4BEED99C540CBF1CB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>aggregations of vehicle-to-grid applications that provide distribution-level service, wholesale market services, or microgrid services;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EB952406DD14E96B84C4706D2A92BD0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a vehicle-to-building application; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DCE73F37B514AFA9DA2BC80B2746503"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other resilience or other application, as determined to be appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CAC5AD596BC45EBB1E30E0478C433EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority and diversity of projects</header><subparagraph id="H7047C86E45AA4419843B602DD3F8859D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In providing grants under the Program, the Secretary shall give priority to projects that, in the determination of the Secretary, are likely to be economically self-sustaining and replicable once established.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DE580030306456CB83783CE20CD6D97"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Secretary, to the maximum extent practicable in accordance with the priority required to be established under subparagraph (A), shall provide grants under the Program for projects across differing situations, including in a region that is experiencing congestion, shortages, transmission system constraints, or distribution system constraints that cause the cost of electricity to increase for consumers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE171DAF207C047EAB9CFDF61FB5455D8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applying for assistance</header><subparagraph id="H485014EA2C0743728CAE488C3C425AE5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under the Program shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, subject to this paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F5FF54520CC4F91B775A513A965D260"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><clause id="HB8AA0D3B029D4F82BADE5430337A655A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) shall demonstrate how the assistance requested under the Program would help the 1 or more eligible entities submitting the application to participate in economically justifiable opportunities that recognize bidirectional electric vehicle charging as a relevant technology, including existing electric utility or Regional Transmission Organization tariffs, programs, initiatives, policies, arrangements, or other opportunities that recognize bidirectional electric vehicle charging as a relevant technology. </text></clause><clause id="HC92B958817A2416E9FDB3F030B194973"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Interconnection rules</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) shall include a certification that any project described in the application and proposed to be carried out using a grant provided under the Program will comply with all applicable interconnection rules.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H683174FB4C8340FB9047BC7CDA68F88E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subparagraph id="H7D1BD130E1014642A4A15E2887FE6BB9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts provided to an eligible entity pursuant to a grant under the Program may be used for—</text><clause id="H39FC46BFEF5D47578CF9CE6B050445B3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>acquiring and installing bidirectional charging stations and interconnection upgrades necessary for bidirectional energy flow;</text></clause><clause id="H94F03B3D4DB340C48F33826508763F1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>retrofitting buildings, parking facilities, and school buses for bidirectional charging;</text></clause><clause id="HE5B035079FED4E4B8D3BE4CA57949683"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>acquiring and installing any necessary metering and telemetry equipment or systems;</text></clause><clause id="HAC0A8E6559934A6F98175060EC5DE00E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>acquiring technical assistance from the Department of Energy, National Laboratories, or other parties with relevant expertise for any participating project partners; and</text></clause><clause id="H2A31AAAAC9694C8EAC5AC07C178B8FC2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any application directly related to establishing, sustaining, and optimizing bidirectional energy flow, as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADD78EC835814AD4BFBC42DB271CFE8E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Amounts provided to an eligible entity pursuant to a grant under the Program shall be used in a manner that corresponds specifically to the incremental additional cost of implementing 1 or more applications described in paragraph (2) as compared to the costs associated with the acquisition, demonstration, or use of a typical electric school bus, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95747986E2084096B2CE56EEA637A991"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Community outreach</header><clause id="HBE890B1284B0418CBF4242065AF7A3D6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), an eligible entity receiving a grant under the Program shall use not less than 1 percent of the amounts received for outreach that is directed at the communities and bus users receiving or benefitting from those amounts, for the purpose of increasing awareness of the benefits of grid-integrated school buses and how grid-integrated school buses will be used.</text></clause><clause id="H382F6D30FF4B4BA385D64DB32894B521"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirement described in clause (i) if the Secretary determines that the outreach described in that clause is unnecessary or would be of minimal benefit to the overall goal of sustained technological deployment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F5F039258A1440A89F98DAFD5932011"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under the Program shall ensure that amounts derived from non-Federal sources are provided for the projects funded by the grant in a total amount that is equal to, or greater than, the amount of the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74D219CEB6CC45C58855F85EB19B5B46" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Outreach to potentially interested entities</header><text>Of the total amount appropriated to carry out the Program, the Secretary shall use not less than 1 percent for outreach to potentially interested eligible entities, including eligible entities participating in, or with a demonstrated interest in, the clean school bus program established under section 741 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16091">42 U.S.C. 16091</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD21E97E466EF45A590F4CA3F3CAFAEE3"><enum>(8)</enum><header>School district compensation</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under the Program shall demonstrate to the Secretary that any school district participating in the applicable project is appropriately compensated for that participation in a manner approved by the Secretary, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H517D75CBA7224D0DA645CDAA2073AC73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the provision of direct financial compensation to the school district;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC04890E7C4A041EC8A449682883F8481"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the provision or acquisition of electric school buses for the school district; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E5FDFBE61F14EBB821925D07A04C714"><enum>(C)</enum><text>savings resulting from the implementation of an application described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20D1ABA647884E5685FFD1377261B876"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Annual submission of data</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under the Program shall annually submit to the Secretary data from vehicles, chargers, and associated grid infrastructure necessary to determine operational and economic impacts, and additional data as determined to be necessary by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADF59BEC70804C13B8F37EDC8E4F9217"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Compatibility with EPA Clean School Bus Program</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may provide a grant under the Program for applicable projects, programs, or activities for which amounts are provided under the clean school bus program established under section 741 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/16091">42 U.S.C. 16091</external-xref>), and to eligible entities receiving amounts under that program, subject to all applicable requirements of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C3470A128A240E28A1CA641B499CCDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report summarizing any existing pilot programs, including State-funded and locally funded pilot programs, involving the use of school buses for the applications described in subsection (b)(2), including—</text><paragraph id="H830F4C43642F41CBA54D70FE4A1321B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any best practices, challenges, lessons learned, and promising future directions discernable from those pilot programs and applications;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52549EB3BB69406D8490CCCBB73DC6D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any challenges, opportunities, and strategies unique to the implementation of those applications in rural areas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4346E2E0410C47C9A6448D7F462DF2DD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any challenges to the commercial viability of those applications posed by State, Federal, or other regulatory barriers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89F79A26A1224B5580ED1BD9CA6A4711"><enum>(4)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2B5C9EC974964922839BF6103446095D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any challenges to the economic viability of projects involving those applications; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB5E4D80D03346A2A50505D85207A578" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any opportunities and strategies to make projects involving those applications economically viable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H984941DCC96F4E11A0C6611016EFE092"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $500,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC00C75DF3ABA4EAE9A68D149C7123451"><enum>3.</enum><header>Consideration of measures to promote vehicle-to-grid integration</header><subsection id="H50BA8FB6A337463AA3659ACBB3256A33"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 111(d) of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2621">16 U.S.C. 2621(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4CC633783C004A0A9DE18331339DF16E"><paragraph id="H56C64A9DE8E44E8EA933DE26C67DF6DE"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Vehicle-to-grid integration</header><subparagraph id="H48DDC09822434EDA814921D1628E74C8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State shall consider—</text><clause id="H2706B249F0E44CDEB1A935E4CA7DE343"><enum>(i)</enum><text>measures to promote vehicle-to-grid integration, including—</text><subclause id="H1E927D85C97C46BEB83AECCE7C66E747"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the establishment of rates, tariffs, measures, and standards that enable electric vehicles and electric vehicle charging infrastructure—</text><item id="H75D1C0F57E0746D589D5E583041BEDA6"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>to receive interconnection service as described in subparagraph (B); and </text></item><item id="HAB6240113919494ABA97AF4FD85D0AA4"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>to export power from the vehicle battery to the distribution system or the bulk power system;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H3D49811C26624B1BA896BF1C7AF86285"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the establishment of rates, tariffs, measures, and standards that enable electric vehicle charging station site hosts, charging station owners, aggregators, owners of electric vehicle fleets or individual fleet vehicles, or drivers of private light-duty electric vehicles to receive compensation for electricity exported from the vehicle battery to the distribution system or the bulk power system; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H42206EDF2C4A48EAA2872DF95FD033D5"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the establishment of rates, tariffs, measures, and standards that enable aggregation of electric vehicles for the purpose of participating in active load management programs, including customer demand-response programs and customer energy storage programs, and providing ancillary services that recognize the value that flexible electric vehicle charging can provide to the distribution system or the bulk power system; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HAAA3A0B32CAF4662AB6E6E5F9DAA5364"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the impacts of the rates, tariffs, measures, and standards described in subclauses (I) through (III) of clause (i), or similar rates, tariffs, measures, and standards, on all classes and types of vehicles, including, at a minimum, light-, medium-, and heavy-duty vehicles.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E71A2BD474B4B86BC3B4FD6299F89F7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Interconnection service described</header><text>The interconnection service referred to in subparagraph (A)(i)(I)(aa) is interconnection service that is offered based on—</text><clause id="HCCA7A148654349E2B9BBB1D8A9CDCE2B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the standards described in paragraph (15) (or successor standards); or</text></clause><clause id="H072059ECC4E140DD8BC8564BF568BC17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>as necessary and reasonable, standards that—</text><subclause id="H70EA3954E7F14FFA9B6ADD3D6D68C968"><enum>(I)</enum><text>are defined in electric vehicle-to-grid communications interfaces, protocols, or standards;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD97086DC7BFD4094924E55E77A1C8E1C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>are widely adopted; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H343D4A115D4C4CA58912F7810577F26D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to ensure the reliability and safety of the electric system, are—</text><item id="H885771F56AAB40EC8754483C1DF0217C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>consistent (or adjusted to be consistent) with the standards described in clause (i); and </text></item><item id="HA96F7274861E4DBEA9E60B7043F5C0D9"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>integrated, able to be integrated, or adjusted in a manner that facilitates integration with the standards described in that clause.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HEC53D2E2D88D4AD3BF88F04D5DAEF337"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compliance</header><paragraph id="HD103665F7CED403E822E3E808B56F61C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Time limitation</header><text>Section 112(b) of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2622">16 U.S.C. 2622(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD454AEE3D124E1CA01822D72E11D398"><paragraph id="HE94CFF85B1EC4361950D5F340394920D"><enum>(9)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF456CEFB631245B983E15192E331611B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, each State regulatory authority (with respect to each electric utility for which the State has ratemaking authority) and each nonregulated electric utility shall commence consideration under section 111, or set a hearing date for consideration, with respect to the standard established by paragraph (22) of section 111(d).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14312109FCBD46CFB5A14F12AE8BFF4A" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this paragraph, each State regulatory authority (with respect to each electric utility for which the State has ratemaking authority), and each nonregulated electric utility shall complete the consideration and make the determination under section 111 with respect to the standard established by paragraph (22) of section 111(d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E9BEC0DC5164684B012007D56AF6ED5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to comply</header><text>Section 112(c) of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2622">16 U.S.C. 2622(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>In the case of the standard established by paragraph (22) of section 111(d), the reference contained in this subsection to the date of enactment of this Act shall be deemed to be a reference to the date of enactment of that paragraph (22).</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H782618D852B44401B21EC65B70C38A04"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prior State actions</header><subparagraph id="H8D88EDB389754FF69AA89A034CE98DA0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 112 of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2622">16 U.S.C. 2622</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause id="HBDDD847AB21347589BB658EB33132060"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subclause id="HB97E9C18FA2D408DAAADD00868361463"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively, and indenting appropriately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB9B28D33DF474B1C8EFBA0175A32F090"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>Subsections</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF621E7B543D047759A4D27C7EEB92FF7"><paragraph id="H2B6A05FE3FE14ACF9D5B4306AF910572"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsections</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="HDA4D130DF9FD4F9D9B02C9EB64D6836B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text><subclause id="H9C503F5946B948AEACC12A738F7C39AD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively, and indenting appropriately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE93F925877F94F8282A3EBD4790FE1BC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through <quote>Subsections</quote> in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23B7DBC412334C75993A093233611236"><paragraph id="H7577738BD25A4C71AF4C6C548ECC952F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Time-based metering and communications</header><text>Subsections</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H4E899CEDAFAD4FD3A852D79F1DBD6441"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text><subclause id="H3120715FFC3C4FE7A1E18E1FE3C74BE0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively, and indenting appropriately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2FCD34CA760B465A87350FE708590E11"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through <quote>Subsections</quote> in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04AEACBF0DFD45DBB07BCE383AA214FA"><paragraph id="HF356E82C48E14634AB1D3DE3463413DA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interconnection</header><text>Subsections</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H53E21D5E65F149EF9314504256383AEE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subsection (g)—</text><subclause id="H787901B782414889B8FA1EA3A0D9960A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively, and indenting appropriately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H52766D6AB54F426182798AE274AE9676"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through <quote>Subsections</quote> in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H772503BD39F44C61BD66B8E0904723FD"><paragraph id="HE9841288F4DB4FEE84EB23DFA6D5661A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Demand-response practices</header><text>Subsections</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H342409C442024099A4A11116F1C9845C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subsection (h)—</text><subclause id="HE85459F2EF3042618E11274FFB2F88E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) through (C), respectively, and indenting appropriately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HEAC0FBE18DD0499395727AC119200471"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through <quote>Subsections</quote> in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H896D0FFD8F804E20904983D4430F6878"><paragraph id="H0284C9C737BE48308CA2395AB3EBACA6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Electric vehicle charging programs</header><text>Subsections</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H879423DAE6714F63A00C89DB1F65DAA4"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subsection (d) (as so amended) by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF1E4BF78152B4A40A48E45481367BBA3"><paragraph id="HBFEC452EAA2C4A0FA94C72EF7E62011F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Vehicle-to-grid integration</header><text>Subsections (b) and (c) shall not apply to the standard established by paragraph (22) of section 111(d) in the case of any electric utility in a State if, before the date of enactment of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HC1BA7F369AC94F248500015AC28C1BBF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State has implemented for the electric utility the standard (or a comparable standard);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC43025E4BD1642BC91F7BD690E8FFB18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State regulatory authority for the State or the relevant nonregulated electric utility has conducted a proceeding to consider implementation of the standard (or a comparable standard) for the electric utility; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A19C31070694E51910D97C59E0160E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the State legislature has voted on the implementation of the standard (or a comparable standard) for the electric utility during the 3-year period ending on that date of enactment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F061B4D7B6348368219D58DD6B4AC12" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Cross-Reference</header><text>Section 124 of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2634">16 U.S.C. 2634</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>In the case of the standard established by paragraph (22) of section 111(d), the reference contained in this section to the date of enactment of this Act shall be deemed to be a reference to the date of enactment of that paragraph (22).</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

