<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H75C063A1D08A4D048A2677377751861C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6605 IH: Stop Terrorism and Illicit Finance Location Exploitation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6605</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Treasury to study the threat of digital location obfuscation as it relates to national security and financial technology, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE9881E86906A470AA8890CB7903B5069" style="OLC"><section id="HA7C15D5A827F4F20A50873E9663D318E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header><subsection id="HC794B8DEEE7A4FB088F318BBE8E1C10C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Terrorism and Illicit Finance Location Exploitation Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STIFLE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87925E58F57D4754BBCA17A24C4060F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="HEFD687961CEF478096971D162D8FCAA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Financial sanctions are a primary national security tool for the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8E25EFE2C034C93A48D1D82480492CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Financial technology has created both new beneficial financial innovations and emerging illicit finance risks, including the evasion of sanctions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28AD110E419D48E893A8AED96A440024"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A financial technology platform must be able to determine the precise location of an active user of the platform to effectively implement location-based access controls for compliance with—</text><subparagraph id="H21B88E826CBE4FD3A149D428D3B29578"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sanctions programs administered by the Office of Foreign Assets Control;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H987E1F0287484EF186CA30F22D924788"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">obligations imposed by the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020, the Bank Secrecy Act, and regulations associated with such Acts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA14C39F8303B4CFEBFB5A7B4695CD70D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other regulatory obligation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H52D2E21D46984A28BF96B9B7118DD46B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Financial technology platforms generally use an Internet Protocol (in this Act referred to as <quote>IP</quote>) address as the primary or sole indicator of their users’ precise location.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C86375D320A449E8E55B51AF847C256"><enum>(5)</enum><text>IP addresses were first created in 1974 and standardized in 1983 as unique identification numbers attributed to devices on an interconnected computer network and are the foundation of the modern internet.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H204D47C2D3F14A2D9D927B2A4D545DB4"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">IP addresses are assigned by Internet Service Providers (in this Act referred to as <quote>ISPs</quote>) and have become a less accurate determinant of precise location as a result of the proliferation of mobile devices, dynamic IP addresses, globalized content delivery networks, and other innovations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F8B4D5C952E4DD585595C3AD004C8B5"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">IP addresses can be manipulated through the use of Virtual Private Networks (in this Act referred to as <quote>VPNs</quote>), proxy servers, anonymizing darknet website browsers, and other location obfuscation techniques for the purpose of—</text><subparagraph id="H083A48B4C48343C593DD58337BD740DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>illicit finance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AA8371604874F839E45EFC3D5FE36B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evading detection under existing sanctions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD0B5CAE3D584352AE0AD40EF7BF4CBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evading requirements set forth in the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020 and the Bank Secrecy Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H630B6E8777A04324B8C7FAD36D5CF491"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Global System for Mobiles triangulation, Wi-Fi triangulation, and GPS data provide substantially more accurate location information than IP addresses, but are individually susceptible to similar manipulation through device tampering, freely available downloadable software, and other obfuscation techniques. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C4A5568FAD54C2BA7AB5CE4C4734BD7"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Technology that combines enhanced data analytics with aggregated authentic sources of location data is widely used to effectively ensure compliance with United States sanctions, the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020, the Bank Secrecy Act, and other statutory and regulatory requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8488358C724E4F318FA92144D5EA6666"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on the threat of digital location obfuscation to national security and financial technology compliance obligations</header><subsection id="H3E6A768FABC3484183261352F5D3CA1F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury, acting through the Undersecretary of the Treasury for Terrorism and Financial Intelligence, and in consultation with technology experts, national security experts, and law enforcement, shall conduct a study to assess the following:</text><paragraph id="H03341BA2954E4D419E6BF1D89CEC9418"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The role that location obfuscation techniques, including VPNs, proxy servers, GPS location manipulation applications, and device tampering plays in money laundering, sanctions evasion, and other forms of illicit finance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40F18AA9A8254154B9CB2B9A69B21514"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The ease with which an illicit actor can manipulate and falsify location data relevant to compliance with sanctions, the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020, the Bank Secrecy Act, and any other statutory and regulatory obligation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5ECB61AF336A41888F1F680233481421"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The degree to which a financial technology platform relies upon an IP address as the primary or sole indicator of the precise location of a user of the platform.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H728C568BAF6044FC85BA1A03A928C000"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The ability of a financial technology platform to use multiple aggregated points of location data to indicate the precise location of a user of such platform if an illicit actor manipulates one or more of such data points.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H533F81392E84430E9E3105C77FA6AF6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, acting through the Undersecretary of the Treasury for Terrorism and Financial Intelligence, and in consultation with technology experts, national security experts, and law enforcement, shall submit to the Congress a report that contains the following:</text><paragraph id="H42E18506B1794160879F3C3186067ED6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each finding and determination made in the study required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DE716798E07468CAB561B800E218F79"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any insufficiency in or lack of available data inhibiting any finding and determination made in the study required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B70A11422B042A48C54737CFE026EF3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive analysis of any cost, benefit, and potential risk associated with the modernization of precise location standards used by a financial technology platform that relies on an IP address as the primary or sole indicator of the precise location of a user of the platform.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE56991B53DCA42EBB3D75B48A4858A30"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive analysis of the ways in which technology that combines enhanced data analytics with multiple aggregated and authenticated sources of location data may be used to reduce evasion of United States sanctions, requirements under the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020, the Bank Secrecy Act, and any other statutory and regulatory obligation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF26136629D864F54A542E222AB7B5E9C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HAEECB455AFF34400A4FBEB31537A2CB4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020</header><text>The term <term>Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020</term> means Division F of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1306B4CE8F404CACB8133EB8ED3EC507"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bank Secrecy Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Bank Secrecy Act</term> has the meaning given the term under section 6303 of the Anti-Money Laundering Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5301">31 U.S.C. 5301</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

