<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7321BE0B883F40FAB98D578B8E4A6BE5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5156 IH: First Responders’ Equipment Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5156</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to amend regulations relating to exemptions for engines and equipment for purposes of national security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H712DDC10867C45C3AE4003774DB1A24B" style="OLC"><section id="HB321FE3592574525B42755078469AFB5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>First Responders’ Equipment Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6D99C896A0004530BCC7F72273588EF5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendment to regulations exempting engines/equipment for national security</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall revise the regulations under section 1068.225(d) of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act)—</text><paragraph id="HD0357393D5E44182A9EE9DF4E7C07319"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to authorize—</text><subparagraph id="H0F346D0D10994EB38E0A572AB29ECBB1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">manufacturers and secondary engine manufacturers to request a national security exemption under such section 1068.225(d) for engines or equipment intended to be used by Federal, State, or local agencies for providing law enforcement, disaster relief, search and rescue, fire response, or emergency medical services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H669C20E849B14B8FAE1DF36D277A43D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an agency of the Federal Government responsible for national defense and the Department of Homeland Security (including the Federal Emergency Management Agency) to endorse a request described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7770E44263F140F6B235A9A879721032"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to specify that a request for a national security exemption described in paragraph (1)(A), and an endorsement of such a request described in paragraph (1)(B), is not required to specify a quantity of engines or equipment to be exempted in order to receive such an exemption. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

