<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB607DCCF9AF344AC83A16A67F68415BB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1359 IH: Modernizing Opioid Treatment Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1359</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand the take-home prescribing of methadone through pharmacies.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2A38F106BCB3451F9537D144AD0F4D70" style="OLC"><section id="H6943491D70C746D0813CD7EBDB548D6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Modernizing Opioid Treatment Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H087F57B8332B48019C4849C258D00687"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expansion of methadone for opioid use disorder through prescribing and pharmacies</header><subsection id="H6A14EA3E9FC54BABA52714DC22A11A69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Registration; other care by telehealth</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0A89270D39E45FEB8AABE2A7484D6CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB814FB36BBB94C9A82C70271EA4A6715"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Controlled substance; detoxification treatment; dispense; maintenance treatment; opioid</header><text>The terms <term>controlled substance</term>, <term>detoxification treatment</term>, <term>dispense</term>, <term>maintenance treatment</term>, and <term>opioid</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H81A90FB9EBAB494481A1C1F5280438F1"><enum>(B)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC18D773990746C68E79D54F01FF4882"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H315F468F9E464647BD955F51A1FE5D5E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of section 303(h) of Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823(h)</external-xref>) applicable to methadone medication for opioid use disorder are waived, and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall register persons described in subparagraph (B) to prescribe methadone for opioid use disorder to be dispensed through a pharmacy for individuals for unsupervised use.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFBD9F9B3D7C542EF812386A1FE3A502F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Persons described</header><text>Persons described in this subparagraph are persons who—</text><clause id="HFBF25F7E8405484E9FAA9A718309C65C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are licensed, registered, or otherwise permitted, by the United States or the jurisdiction in which they practice, to prescribe controlled substances in the course of professional practice; and</text></clause><clause id="HF106191BDDD041BF8F758C6F12E7EF66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are—</text><subclause id="H5C2808830E62410A821F3D4C533EBE28"><enum>(I)</enum><text>employees or contractors of an opioid treatment program; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HE80DF79D7CD94139B66C08E293C9D473"><enum>(II)</enum><text>addiction medicine physicians or addiction psychiatrists who hold a subspecialty board certification in addiction medicine from the American Board of Preventive Medicine, a board certification in addiction medicine from the American Board of Addiction Medicine, a subspecialty board certification in addiction psychiatry from the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, or a subspecialty board certification in addiction medicine from the American Osteopathic Association.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC761C9BE06B046EFA0A1FE6523412AF8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Requirements for prescribing methadone</header><text>The prescribing of methadone pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be—</text><clause id="HC2340E4A46584B40B239A91F2F5335EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>exclusively by electronic prescribing and dispensed to the patient treated pursuant to subparagraph (A);</text></clause><clause id="HF4381EE9C0BC46F1AD042EF1F4035952"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for a supply of not more than 30 days pursuant to each prescription; and</text></clause><clause id="H939B51F5E771482EAC236922E9B8FAB4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>subject to the restrictions listed in section 8.12(i)(3) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations, or successor regulation or guidance.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H260ABA7A84C74B77990A65E248FC824D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Requirements for dispensing methadone</header><text>The dispensing of methadone to an individual pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be in addition to the other care that the individual continues to have access to through an opioid treatment program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B955D3B326747388EAAA5B921F79C89"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Registration requirements</header><text>Persons registered in a State pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="H339C2F183CCB482ABE3BDE588C68E127"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensure and document, with respect to each patient treated pursuant to subparagraph (A), informed consent to treatment; and</text></clause><clause id="HF726739F778E40368CB4694C25119C5F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include in such informed consent, specific informed consent regarding differences in confidentiality protections applicable when dispensing through an opioid treatment program versus dispensing through a pharmacy pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C76D24B0EE7435A80DA7E6B86ED8711"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Cessation and withdrawal of registration</header><text>At the request of a State, the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary, shall—</text><clause id="H406A8DAE46D44FF888D198DF7B74C135"><enum>(i)</enum><text>cease registering persons in the State pursuant to subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H967F190404254304A1F76DE42E3CE8A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>withdraw any such registration in effect for a person in the State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21921461CEB141D78CAC00169F1F2E3E"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Maintenance and detoxification treatment</header><text>Maintenance treatment or detoxification treatment provided pursuant to subparagraph (A) and other care provided in conjunction with such treatment, such as counseling and other ancillary services, may be provided by means of telehealth, as determined jointly by the State and the Secretary to be feasible and appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A3CE7215B784B2890D65F83B62B97B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual reporting</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use and the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration shall jointly submit a report to Congress that includes—</text><paragraph id="H2E76CB0B38984F5F913F6EA028F86C04"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of persons registered pursuant to subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD1A89D264FA4BA6816693CEADDA7A64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of patients being prescribed methadone pursuant to subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC61F5C7C653C4649AF9A2FEBFDDC0796"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a list of the States in which persons are registered pursuant to such subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H34E20469CA584088A713B4CFD3F47AD9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on need to reduce barriers to patient care through opioid treatment programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HB76DF2F593B84A769CD5B4E06A6CADB0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>patients receiving services through opioid treatment programs face barriers to their care; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7411E9EB1A4AE6B67BB9F8E2F0EB21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>each State should align the regulation of opioid treatment programs in a manner that is consistent with the intent of this Act. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

