<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H90931367767645C19BD5D750A8B1C6A1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2965 IH: Autism Family Caregivers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2965</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, to award grants for providing evidence-based caregiver skills training to family caregivers of children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental disabilities or delays, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEEACE505F03D44098F381B21FE379857" style="OLC"><section id="HD854C4F54C814F78AC0C41E60B606E20" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Autism Family Caregivers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD0C8CA138A1E4002A35632F5BD021E46"><enum>2.</enum><header>Caregiver Skills Training Pilot Program</header><subsection id="H3C757B4D467F4811B057048815498F21"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, shall carry out a program, to be known as the Caregiver Skills Training Pilot Program, under which the Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to provide evidence-based caregiver skills training to family caregivers of children<italic></italic> with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental disabilities or delays, for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="H5A65C1E99859463B90C8CE5E6FFADE78"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improving the well-being of children and their caregivers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59FF78B85CFB419795CE4F981F3A931E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>teaching caregivers of such children evidenced-based intervention strategies to promote—</text><subparagraph id="HF67F9610D7B142A3BA35B4323607A637"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improvement in the well-being of such children and their caregivers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61739237E7D546EDB768B8E357F1E147"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the greater inclusion of such children in family and community life.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70A63C13CD334F74B78BD789183EB999"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive an award under subsection (a), an entity shall be—</text><paragraph id="HAA3BF602CA5D47E09E497E89E74F507A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a nonprofit or other community-based organization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C8545436577477EB6CE56E6282B5563"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a Federally qualified health center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0AABFC312FD4B5889F5BD438A8780E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an academic health center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A0FD537E21142B2843E37C6E75E3631"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a health system; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB19CE916D2AA4552A750E6277115D9AB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a collaboration or consortium of 2 or more entities listed in paragraphs (1) through (4).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H377754DE88FF411BBF299915F259D017"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To seek a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application that includes—</text><paragraph id="H7F6EFF7DB4CC440690DD3927F99BE742"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of—</text><subparagraph id="H14F73266A53F478794CD6E92595DCF1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the applicant’s experience delivering evidence-based caregiver skills training to family caregivers of children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental disabilities or delays;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29DF4508AA8D4C92B52CE490A697FE13"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the activities that the applicant proposes to carry out through the grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1BD59DAEA924444B90CCF8AC4B26691"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how such activities will achieve the purposes described in subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0280B58A60064849A3B5B461A5A3EC99"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a plan for—</text><subparagraph id="H6167273760CD468D80E796162415C50B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordination with community-based organizations, State and local early intervention providers, Medicaid systems, schools, and other providers of early intervening services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E4BE0499D5B4FC3A052ACA55C65B3DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>collaboration with health care payors (including public and private insurance), State departments of insurance, health plans, and other relevant payors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF852FE59C4E4AECAF502CEA990B971F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>expanding the skills training program proposed to be carried out through the grant; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D68C74B739F4C2ABF4DDE9FC0E8FEA5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>achieving sustainability of such program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5276A51944A74832A5BE2CF8CE5EDE60"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing and maintaining a stakeholder implementation committee under subsection (f).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D0F1CFF422649FDB3478420A634F5E3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of grantees</header><paragraph id="HD39CBF4199A346A8B6A7E2594E4EC63B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding a grant to an eligible entity or a collaboration or consortium of 2 or more entities described in subsection (b), the Secretary shall require at least one of the recipients to—</text><subparagraph id="HECCFE6ADF17949A19CC300E192B4CAEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have at least 3 years of demonstrated experience—</text><clause id="HFC8B563849DA41D495FF2112C4365BD3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">delivering culturally competent services for children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities, as well as collaborating directly with their families, including in medically underserved communities;</text></clause><clause id="H4D9D9B836077430AB3421C770AA3609E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing services to children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities, as well as collaborating directly with their families;</text></clause><clause id="H139A133F75944F6894ACA41493EC5B58"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing individual caregiver coaching to caregivers of children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities; and</text></clause><clause id="H921626F5519C49D6ACF386B6717B1363"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">working with self-advocates or adults with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56902A74071B4F7B9EECEAAF78F0B252"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstrate the ability to access resources from and collaborate with—</text><clause id="H4F7C75E93148456782C25A8272C98704"><enum>(i)</enum><text>health care providers;</text></clause><clause id="HF87A26713F5342F397EC249454074C08"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allied health professionals;</text></clause><clause id="HFAA35D89107A451685939EAA3EB6F867"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>educators;</text></clause><clause id="H3D5BE4AF10D94700826D9F90E72FFE54"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>social workers; and</text></clause><clause id="H605A37A9B5BF4C0CB1854572DBCC3C9D"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nonprofessional family caregivers who assist with daily living and developmental activities, including for children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF30AD18CF27F4F2A8D3371E6047CB878"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reducing disparities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary may consider, as appropriate, the extent to which an eligible entity can deliver evidence-based, culturally competent caregiver skills training programs for children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities from diverse racial, ethnic, geographic, or linguistic backgrounds.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17806ED9AC9F4312A5091C3366046E89"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recipient of a grant under this section shall use the grant—</text><paragraph id="H7B3920A9902141B6A9968880BC325304"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to provide, at no or minimal cost to participants—</text><subparagraph id="H9D730ED8A05D47ABB4AC738C13769D6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based caregiver skills training to family caregivers of children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16AB23948F2F4CF598D96CE03434F5F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such training in areas related to children’s learning and development, including—</text><clause id="H9FE538F64F6741C0A265B7A9E4FF98CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>communication skills;</text></clause><clause id="HB38A0C568AC04919A9F076BF9E4A66FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>social engagement;</text></clause><clause id="HEF6B4BA85A7C44B3A267964EE4C0448D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>daily living skills; and</text></clause><clause id="H2C209D085E304BCBAB046C0D6D626F3D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">caregiver response strategies to severe and challenging behaviors; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF96CDE3EDCA34BD1A9F7913B184E9B06"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to establish and maintain a stakeholder implementation committee under subsection (f).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD8F43AE97E1A48CA952C0807BD9737C5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Stakeholder implementation committee</header><paragraph id="H8C6263DC8EDC4D1CB4C51B9A1E407A3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As a condition on receipt of a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall agree to use the grant to establish and maintain a stakeholder implementation committee to advise on ensuring that the training provided pursuant to the grant is accessible and culturally relevant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4CC9EB28CDA4BD7A2E076FCEF173500"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The members of the stakeholder implementation committee shall all be from the local community served pursuant to the grant (or the relevant metropolitan statistical area) and shall include, at a minimum, the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3B3D625E321543BEB5EF7FA43209465E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Family caregivers of children with autism or other developmental disabilities, including autistic caregivers and other caregivers with disabilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H141CA8E44AF8478CBA2B08591A401A94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Pediatric health care and early intervention providers with experience providing services to children with autism or other developmental disabilities and delays.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC7EF25C90DD4559B4DA7432E3DC94C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Educators with experience working with children with autism or other developmental disabilities and delays.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D1CD27ECE3C4463A5C76D73521F2236"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Representatives of local organizations familiar with the cultural values and priorities of individuals in the local community.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA203CAA0504640DC804881DB4C225D22"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Local government officials.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H071816B4BD7040FCA71A464FF8E1AE88"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Requirements</header><paragraph id="H91BAD68E579F4E62B99F4D626B6D8378"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number of recipients and States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants under subsection (a) to not fewer than 25 eligible entities in not fewer than 15 States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AD5B84128324445BBD3A627F11CCA8C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The total amount of each grant awarded under subsection (a) shall be not less than $500,000 over a 5-year period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H031F8A1ABC2640ECA460D01AC57B28B4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Amounts received through a grant under this section shall be used to supplement, not supplant, other amounts received to provide—</text><paragraph id="HA3355CC8C527453EA5EEEC4D6D8CF7F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>behavioral, medical, habilitative, and other services covered by the Medicaid program or private health insurance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6745CF9DEB2E468E9B1A59F8734B4AD9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>services provided under the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1400">20 U.S.C. 1400 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D1924F822C94FB7AD3726ECB1F7F9E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>adaptations of a training program using evidence-based approaches to serve children of different ages, communities, and underrepresented groups.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H68795FA5569846F09FE6FAA81E74F425"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Activities of the Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, shall—</text><paragraph id="HF48B3CB5580240D58B90617376196CB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assist recipients of grants under subsection (a) in—</text><subparagraph id="HC542CF84548B4BE59CF6BDA81A57EB30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the implementation of caregiver skills training programs using lessons learned from other evidenced-based activities or caregiver programs conducted or supported by the Health Resources and Services Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C7311DE571F4A2DACD2CDA74F64C76D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring the programs of the recipients assist medically underserved communities, when possible; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89DF9664FB98453A8006BC0109EF7B40"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developing plans for achieving sustainability of the programs of the recipients;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H643903B270AD41FDBD5AC5C569F3D6E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct an annual evaluation of activities funded through grants under subsection (a), in consultation with the grant recipients, including evaluation of the effectiveness of such grants at improving health outcomes and quality of life for children with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental delays and disabilities and their family caregivers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAFEA329A5994AC1A43E254620B91137"><enum>(3)</enum><text>convene at least one national or regional meeting of such grant recipients to discuss best practices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H491BA00B87CC42549E72A03D0E064BEB"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HD4CE40C26BFD45E1BC2334672E4440B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after awarding the first grant under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and to other appropriate congressional committees, a report on the implementation of this section. Such report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H951C41FB3F02454D91E6C760FFC3BC8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how many grants have been awarded;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE57621F91864EC29595DD618BC6B7BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the name and location of the grant recipients;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FBD8821CABD4704BD59B9C8139A4007"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the communities impacted by the grants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE8E8E34A9A746FD996773A5BB202AE2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of the kind of activities to be carried out with the grants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C1A42DC98964E82B6C4CFB873BC8DAE"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis, conducted by the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, based on the evaluation under subsection (h)(2), of the effectiveness of such grants at improving health outcomes and quality of life for children with autism or other developmental disabilities or delays and their family caregivers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D5B5E7F4A9046D99B6F6FB42C3FB661"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">best practices to increase access to caregiver skills training programs described in subsection (a) in medically underserved communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H89216C973691474A8DD6EC6A0CB12535"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than the end of fiscal year 2027, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and to other appropriate congressional committees, a final report on the implementation of this section, including—</text><subparagraph id="H98B4C972B1EE4797A4CAAFAF7EACA5E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the information, analysis, and best practices listed in subparagraphs (A) through (F) of paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC60B645C1D0842338220E67A0B00D07F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations on how to expand and extend the program under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6097C3B31774477BAECADA84C7A67667"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD78E53F86FFD4A0AAD9AFB38D86B9416"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>family caregiver</term> means an adult family member or other individual who has a significant relationship with, and who provides a broad range of assistance to, a child between the ages of 0 and 9 diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder or other developmental disabilities or delays.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93108A71CBBB421F93F0CDE616CDC6A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federally qualified health center</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5579E5BC098B4E79AF6A304C67BB3872"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE1D594587DD44B8CB8F2C49FA89B4450"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

