<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H70A689EC8EF1499A83DAECFD0115C9A0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3296 IH: Wildfire Communications Resiliency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3296</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that construction, rebuilding, or hardening of communications facilities following a major disaster or an emergency related to a wildfire is not subject to requirements to prepare certain environmental or historical preservation reviews.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9EF427CED4AE49EDBBB447FFAC77E002" style="OLC"><section id="H1E9279AAD0A54E11B7E778FD68CA868C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wildfire Communications Resiliency Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HED1B65EC026747449F8EE6FA8FEEB4DE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Application of NEPA and NHPA to covered communications projects</header><subsection id="H9C0E577F1AF64C10A2173CB85890498F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>NEPA exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal authorization with respect to a covered project may not be considered a major Federal action under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9ED83344885B4152A8227D85942F87FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National historic preservation act exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered project may not be considered an undertaking under section 300320 of title 54, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA1EEECAE5D9A4F6A981AD89A6698AB94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H229F32CFD3724E01B037A13AFD774D92"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chief Executive</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Chief Executive</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5122">42 U.S.C. 5122</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DCBE9DAA8D24FB08928FD50BEA963FC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <term>communications facility</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>communications facility installation</quote> in section 6409(d) of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H038B134A350842E08A088EFC580F1A14"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered project</header><text>The term <term>covered project</term> means a project that—</text><subparagraph id="HD676BE0DF4DF4DA58F046C06B6EF38F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is to be carried out entirely within an area for which the President, the Governor of a State, or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government has declared a major disaster or an emergency related to a wildfire;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE63D3D4A87884D8C8378E47BDC393E07"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is to be carried out not later than 5 years after the date on which the President, Governor, or Chief Executive made such declaration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD716BD6CE50F439EBB73C29FBE30C1FA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>replaces a communications facility damaged by such disaster or emergency or makes improvements to a communications facility in such area that could reasonably be considered as necessary for recovery from such disaster or emergency or to prevent or mitigate any future disaster or emergency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2056DA4CADF44D3B64DC66B4FAE5583"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Emergency</header><text>The term <quote>emergency</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H591AB5A4FA6D46D4BB6C8F34D162A4C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an emergency declared by the President, an emergency declared by the President under section 501 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5191">42 U.S.C. 5191</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1ADD9FC69DF4684B984D4DD69ED459D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an emergency declared by the Governor of a State or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government, any occasion or instance with respect to which the Governor or Chief Executive declares that an emergency exists (or makes a similar declaration) under State or Tribal law (as the case may be).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20A2EDA1E33C4E88BF032A06487FED69"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federal authorization</header><text>The term <quote>Federal authorization</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HB155A605083841F8AB02190A4BDC06E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any authorization required under Federal law with respect to a covered project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD02C45DCB8534572BE077E7C3113724F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any permits, special use authorizations, certifications, opinions, or other approvals as may be required under Federal law with respect to a covered project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE28236CBE3374F9CA8F79327EB2796C8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Governor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Governor</quote> means the chief executive of any State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B0CC36A7DAB4F88BF4DE1A115E4546B"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Indian tribal government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Indian tribal government</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5122">42 U.S.C. 5122</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3349D2DD7334CB59CBADB40EA1CE19A"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Major disaster</header><text>The term <quote>major disaster</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HEB7367D157C049C599EDAC97D182E259"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a major disaster declared by the President, a major disaster declared by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDD044AF91CF42CABEACB322093B56F8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a major disaster declared by the Governor of a State or the Chief Executive of an Indian tribal government, any occasion or instance with respect to which the Governor or Chief Executive declares that a disaster exists (or makes a similar declaration) under State or Tribal law (as the case may be).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC80FBA200954C7BAE1C39F9AD9BEBC7"><enum>(9)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>State</quote> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, and each territory or possession of the United States. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

