<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB6E486952B984B6C8338DF06F5B57842" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1689 IH: Connecting Students with Mental Health Services Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1689</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230321">March 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Education, in coordination with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, to award grants to eligible entities to support the mental and behavioral health of elementary and secondary school students, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H42F5CF730A76482E8F92FA4896B73EF3" style="OLC"><section id="H677E867A90C4485E93E31E0CBDC23DBD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecting Students with Mental Health Services Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCF15799039E7481D996C788C8EF7C184"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants to support mental and behavioral health of elementary and secondary school students</header><subsection id="HCBBC746A8E304648BC10C4928D8275BC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Education, in coordination with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall carry out a program consisting of awarding grants to eligible entities to support the mental and behavioral health of students in elementary schools and secondary schools, especially such students who reside in rural areas or lack access to mental and behavioral health services.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF156A9F290A343709703D570873A604C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use the grant for resources to support the mental and behavioral health of students in elementary schools and secondary schools, which may include—</text><paragraph id="HD59EF71AABA9459DB90000056D06437D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">purchasing or upgrading equipment (which may include physical equipment and technology) to implement a telehealth program that includes mental and behavioral health care;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H825E4ACD1B5C44AD99D3D044278DC67F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensuring sufficient space and personnel to support such a telehealth program in one or more schools; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF2D162C6B7148A982E95F9975E80B60"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hiring, or providing additional compensation for, staff to help administer such a telehealth program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBDC72CDE51A4B819F0D91869ADE45F3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H8805A697E8544EB686ECF23308ABBE81"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>To seek a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary of Education at such time, in such manner, and containing such information and assurances as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B5F3EFB144848B78E31D0F48B0A2232"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each such application shall include a plan—</text><subparagraph id="HC53A75B454C649BEA68B60F848FBF14B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>detailing the applicant’s proposed telehealth program that includes mental and behavioral health care, to be supported through the plan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC93F8B717914478C82F2E6F74E16E19F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing assurances that any collection, maintenance, or use of student information through such telehealth program will be in accordance with applicable privacy laws.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H256766D39E144902822016F974291C61"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary of Education shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text><paragraph id="H71D29D5A3C974C9787B7F43224BC6ACC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit an application in accordance with subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8822A5449E644199DB873AAFA59453E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>serve—</text><subparagraph id="H9C846B26A742440DB0F2446F121DECE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>high-poverty elementary schools and secondary schools;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9290CE38903C4AA7B624083F0C31A72D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rural elementary schools and secondary schools; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB07689996DB6476CBA0022DA49A32F2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>elementary schools and secondary schools that are located in a health professional shortage area designated under section 332 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3224750810A84DBA8F72666F49D2CDE9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The Secretary of Education shall establish the program required by subsection (a) not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0B209569D3954A46BCC051D1FA7DA337"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Funds made available under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, and local funds provided for activities funded under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE5457367F8848D1824D604DAF0CCA35"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2025, the Secretary of Education and the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting jointly, shall submit to the Congress and make publicly available a report including—</text><paragraph id="H55C354547BF44FB4B389A4C7ECAFC9A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">analysis on the impact of the program under this section (in a manner that does not include information that would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual student)—</text><subparagraph id="HFEB50C1824E544AA9DDACBB3ED1BF974"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the number of students in elementary schools and secondary schools receiving health care (including behavioral and mental health services) through a telehealth program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9837C6F5A9344E1AA0E11FAD37D27025"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the number of such students receiving behavioral and mental health services through a telehealth program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C5770C9762048869E717BF8D76C82B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations for the reauthorization, expansion, and improvement of the program under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C47077DFC20479CA63DEAACB39C074E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H463979C598AB4017ACE48B67DC515AD8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>community health care provider</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HE950A73C43DF4F90AC73A1738FCB6191"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to subparagraph (B), includes a university health care system; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6967CD5A34824EB78EB7629518DDD09F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>excludes any provider that does not accept payment under a State plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8F7E3D492754C6EB08DD07F8A5D21A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <term>educational service agency</term>, <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given to those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EBAD43CD92F40D997AD1DD3321F9BF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a partnership between—</text><subparagraph id="HBD659DD48E654080B4AAE466B089150B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency or a consortium of any such agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31164711EABA43EFBD051ACDDFAB1A59"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a community health care provider or an educational service agency. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H061A8A34915443D388EAA140254CB9D7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>telehealth</term> means the use of electronic information and telecommunications technologies to support long-distance clinical health care, patient and professional health-related education, public health, and health administration.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD6E6345530C6434D8EFD9E6A16CA51CB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2027.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

