<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5D81CA876FE645B88942F856F99E4335" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3598 IH: To direct the Secretary of State to conduct a comprehensive study assessing the Chinese Communist Party’s role in the distribution of fentanyl in the United States.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3598</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230523">May 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to conduct a comprehensive study assessing the Chinese Communist Party’s role in the distribution of fentanyl in the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4E64C056427146978695ABF279D4CF48" style="OLC"><section id="H2416D8CB04E8409B8B40A56DE3288CB2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Comprehensive study assessing the Chinese Communist Party’s role in the distribution of fentanyl in the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall conduct a comprehensive study assessing the Chinese Communist Party’s role in the distribution of fentanyl in the United States, including its influence on the United States Government, specifically the Department of Justice, the United States economy, and United States public industries. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

