<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1CDB35DC791F4C82A45945245699BF1D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5321 IH: Strategic Defense Fellows Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5321</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the John S. McCain National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019 to improve the John S. McCain strategic defense fellows program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC4D8486622424E719DDA5A10FA3663D0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE112C6EA50424FF39CD9DA248AE7B08C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strategic Defense Fellows Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H3DDA065E3DD34B41AF9FFB9BCE5CD6A2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements to the John S. McCain strategic defense fellows program</header> <subsection id="H5018A8C76463447EB264DC0D1CFECB34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Selection of participants</header><text>Subsection (d)(2) of section 932 of the John S. McCain National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/232">Public Law 115–232</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1580">10 U.S.C. 1580</external-xref> note prec.) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HC681F96FF4824A49B17F07A81EB6D7B9" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H9C7B3D424E184604B30FBB6473B225A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Geographical representation</header><text>Out of the total number of individuals selected to participate in the fellows program in any year, no more than 20 percent may be from any of the following geographic regions:</text> <subparagraph id="H654A02E3D6744441B299C55F870A9FEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Northeast United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF5E34D718EFB44978D3392AC5C4FBBA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Southeast United States.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2BE6BBE2683423D97C32BDBC84D20C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Midwest United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAF77BE2D76274B4C9A0EBEC640092746"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Southwest United States.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDAE571C05F604214B2091C749FE15708"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Western United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86A5736B8A4B4F27921D8144A5A93492"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Alaska, Hawaii, United States territories, and areas outside the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0D94E02A2C354010B7DC6978DD1396EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appointment, placement, and conversion</header><text>Such section is further amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD17EA43E85A74D1C8377134D76E2C4F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(3)—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B99C7FE4C3E4BD4A0177590662A8294"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assigned</quote> and inserting <quote>appointed</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDBCE6CC371B9493D9B70D3B0B2048011"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assignment</quote> and inserting <quote>appointment</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H75E8F02F153D46BF865A4D762A80CB57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subsections (e) and (f) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H05FC995442464DA2A449678E5F05910C" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H93CCC40AD84D44258C5842AA05A5C866"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Appointment</header> 
<paragraph id="HC68AD7A23D4842FAA1BB8B3C1362F7B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An individual who participates in the fellows program shall be appointed into an excepted service position in the Department.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDD003F78628942D8ABC6F4C362DE001B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Position requirements</header><text>Each year, the head of each Department of Defense Component shall submit to the Secretary of Defense placement opportunities for participants in the fellows program. Such placement opportunities shall provide for leadership development and potential commencement of a career track toward a position of senior leadership in the Department. The Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the heads of Department of Defense Components, shall establish qualification requirements for the appointment of participants under paragraph (1) and subsection (f)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB3808E52FE9434BAEE9C099511B3384"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appointment to positions</header><text>Each year, the Secretary of Defense shall appoint participants in the fellows program to positions in the Department of Defense Components. In making such appointments, the Secretary shall seek to best match the qualifications and skills of the participants with the requirements for positions available for appointment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81B1DB4835B6435194962CBB1A2C3E45"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The term of each appointment under the fellows program shall be one year with the option to extend the appointment up to one additional year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDCB7DF05669042C684286C373A1AF7FE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Grade</header><text>An individual appointed to a position under the fellows program shall be appointed at a level between GS–10 and GS–12 of the General Schedule based on the directly-related qualifications, skills, and professional experience of the individual.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C054ECBB69C475ABDED2BD4EDFCB584"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Education loan repayment</header><text>To the extent that funds are provided in advance in appropriations Acts, the Secretary of Defense may repay a loan of a participant in the fellows program if the loan is described by subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of section 16301(a)(1) of title 10, United States Code. Any repayment of a loan under this paragraph may require a minimum service agreement, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD436D0B4E4694156A093D587A47CEEBD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Department of defense component defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>Department of Defense Component</quote> means a Department of Defense Component, as set forth in section 111 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1023D01720764A509B04B02A216F7116"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Career development</header> <paragraph id="H5EA3E01E6D504560A7C6524DB7A3E224"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that participants in the fellows program—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H36A64E6C3DCE4B51BC8B4B7B3BC62FF5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>receive career development opportunities and support appropriate for the commencement of a career track within the Department leading toward a future position of senior leadership within the Department, including ongoing mentorship support through appropriate personnel from entities within the Department; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA2998005137E48209BAE9CA4B5393E32"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are provided appropriate employment opportunities for competitive and excepted service positions in the Department upon successful completion of the fellows program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4CB9AFDF85E473E943C16DBAD4EC22F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Noncompetitive appointment or conversion</header><text>Upon a participant’s successful completion of the fellows program, the Secretary may, without regard to the provisions of subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, noncompetitively appoint or convert the participant into a vacant competitive or excepted service position in the Department, if the Secretary determines that such appointment or conversion will contribute to the development of highly qualified future senior leaders for the Department. The Secretary may appoint or convert the participant into a position up to the GS–13 level of the General Schedule or an equivalent position for which the participant is qualified without regard to any minimum time in grade requirements.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2D5B76279104D94BCF67D2505097EEA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appointment of former participants</header><text>The Secretary may utilize the authority in paragraph (2) for a participant—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC025E46D46D74921AFEF58FB78424137"><enum>(A)</enum><text>up to 2 years after the date of the participant’s successful completion of the fellows program; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4AF02703CF6842A8AA2D4E5676EB9470"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a participant who entered the fellows program before the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, up to 5 years after the date of the participant’s successful completion of the fellows program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44006C00A9D94EAD9CF597C1BC2953B9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Publication of selection</header><text>The Secretary shall publish, on an Internet website of the Department available to the public, the names of the individuals selected to participate in the fellows program.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

