<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1B8A667AC5AC4BD495C9672085731528" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4230 IH: The Fund Our Border Not The IRS Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4230</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To transfer the unobligated balances of amounts made available to the Internal Revenue Service under the Inflation Reduction Act to the Secretary of Homeland Security to secure the border.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE3589CE0967494A8A0B9784A57745DD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H432BB8AFD5F5408A8D6299A8FDC9B5C7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>The Fund Our Border Not The IRS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC03AC066EDF44BDE82A5D70FBD259922"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unobligated balances of the Internal Revenue Service made available to secure the border</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The unobligated balances of all amounts made available to the Internal Revenue Service under <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> shall be transferred to the Secretary of Homeland Security and be made available for the salaries and expenses of agents and officers of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, constructing and maintaining physical barriers along the southern international border of the United States, and other purposes relating to border security.</text> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

