<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBEC9796CE45C441A837705EB67CF6BF5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4222 IH: Executive Branch Conflict of Interest Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4222</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require executive branch agencies to prohibit conflicting financial interests through prohibited holdings regulations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0AC0EC3414464BE6BC1C6812BC432DD8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H33C6BC02023D4315BC07B8BD02089428" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Executive Branch Conflict of Interest Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9904283B94A84B5EB91CF2E2A6492708"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of prohibited holdings regulations</header> <subsection id="H32C21303418A4CBDAB4F22ADD811AFCC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H103DC2BDDBF84357B3D015674611FEA3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered government official</header><text>The term <term>covered government official</term> includes any officer or employee who occupies a position classified above GS–15 of the General Schedule or, in the case of positions not under the General Schedule—</text> <subparagraph id="H985739D0506848E29BAC5B026D73DA0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for which the rate of basic pay is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4C01989DC7224EB490CB8D954A34603F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each member of a uniformed service whose pay grade is at or in excess of O–7 under section 201 of title 37, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H775D963C1EF64C4183ABC05EB180774D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>each officer or employee in any other position determined by the Director of the Office of Government Ethics to be of equal classification.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E71A6E8C39F462CAD5B29E6795B86E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Diversified fund</header><text>The term <term>diversified fund</term> means a widely held investment fund described in section 13104(f)(8) of title 5, United States Code, that does not have a stated policy of concentrating its investments in any industry, business, or single country other than the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H68C2A9D350414D5B85CC65D6414F6ED2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to any exception for an interest held through a diversified fund or a qualified blind trust, no covered government official shall own any financial interest in a corporation, business, partnership, or other for-profit entity that is determined to be—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD5F79DC48DBE40E084A9724D21B5FF66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>substantially regulated by the agency or otherwise directly influenced by the action of the executive agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D0A6604FBEB404AA7708386F5A71353"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a major contractor of the agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA0FF228D9EC408E82A6DB917DB534C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an organization that has substantial lobbying contacts with the agency; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA697045783DE4F31846888EFD3227034"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an organization that otherwise poses the realistic potential for creating a substantial appearance of a conflict of interest.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H62C157DE931B4DA08B9982945A1C444E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall issue guidance to executive agencies regarding the meaning of the terms <term>substantially regulated</term>, <term>major contractor</term>, <term>substantial lobbying contacts</term>, and <term>substantial appearance of a conflict of interest</term> specifically in the context of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFF0577E6946B47BC93957B2883355958"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>If an agency head determines that no financial interest meets the criteria established in subsection (b), as defined by the Director of the Office of Government Ethics pursuant to subsection (c), and that issuance of a prohibited holdings regulation under this regulation is not possible, the head of the agency shall sign a report to Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6F4A06BC482541EBBB8B557A0CC30B99"><enum>(1)</enum><text>explains in detail why there is no realistic potential for any officer or employee described in subsection (a) to encounter a conflict of interest in the performance of official duties;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5C160BC7F1B4081B565151764B0844D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describes in detail all steps undertaken by the agency to evaluate the potential for conflicts of interest to arise at the agency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H39917C6960EB48A4810C4AB036E2CC34"><enum>(3)</enum><text>if any part of the agency is within the jurisdiction of an inspector general, shall include a written assessment by the Inspector General of the potential for conflicts of interest to arise in connection with the performance of official duties by officers and employees described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA0C66AB1021A42DBBDD05B2E729BC203"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>If an agency has issued a prohibited holdings regulation prior to the date of enactment of this Act, the agency head shall evaluate whether that regulation should cover any additional types of interests not currently covered. If the agency head determines that expansion of the regulation’s coverage is not currently warranted, the agency head shall so advise Congress in writing and shall not be required to issue a new regulation under this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2301309F51C947F2A913E920D69E9A18"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>Any regulation prohibiting potentially conflicting financial interests, whether issued pursuant to this Act or prior to the date of enactment of this Act, may, if deemed appropriate by both the agency head and the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, permit individual waivers in unusual circumstances, provided that the regulation requires the agency to submit the waiver to the Director for publication on the official website of the Office of Government Ethics, subject to applicable routine destruction requirements.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

