<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H117285C4F9294AC99A7B6BCD00EA98F2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 315 IH: No Taxpayer Funded Platform for Chinese Communists Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 315</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230112">January 12, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To prohibit certain funding made available to the United States Agency for Global Media relating to provision of an open platform for China, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H8BA19C6659954859B8CBE203543345F1" style="OLC">
<section id="H8274E5C6E1C84F5EAA157D94DF8123FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Taxpayer Funded Platform for Chinese Communists Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HEB51CDB3D9A34D7AABA38593A5C57C33"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on certain funding relating to provision of an open platform for China</header> <subsection id="HCD43BB850D3D4C5AA0FEFE583D3BCFE3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Funding prohibition</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no funding made available to the United States Agency for Global Media (USAGM) may be used to provide an open platform for representatives of the People’s Republic of China (PRC), members of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), or any entity owned or controlled by the PRC or CCP.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0D611347D9A946E382973CAF6E57966A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the USAGM shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report describing whether or not any of its broadcast entities, including its grantee organizations, has provided at any time during the five-year period immediately preceding such report an open platform for representatives of the PRC, members of the CCP, or any entity owned or controlled by the PRC or CCP. Such report shall be made available on a publicly available website by the Federal Government.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

