<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H93979AED44A34F4C9B1ABAB7A7C5E868" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2918 IH: Fair Housing for Survivors Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2918</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide protection for survivors of domestic violence, sexual violence, and sex trafficking under the Fair Housing Act.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB2F493135EF046CEB10C1131D039CD7E" style="OLC"><section id="HCFCE2BEACCFF4EFE98A8D905C70A9876" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Housing for Survivors Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC516747D31004149ACC834262402979C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HDB39071507DA41B7B5D8809988EB0532"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cities, towns, and rural communities in the United States continue to face enormous challenges regarding domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, dating violence, stalking, and other forms of intimate partner and gender-based violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC623CAD7AA143A4821A6A4906B09D57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>One in three women and one in ten men in the United States have experienced rape, physical violence, or stalking by an intimate partner in their lifetime.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5834790B78D641E7BE8A2CF2CCB0A449"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Intimate partner violence alone affects more than 12,000,000 people in the United States every year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H051F3F52A62448499D71CDC87412EC75"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Approximately 7,000,000 women are raped or physically assaulted by a current or former intimate partner each year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE208A4C83D4E45FEAE96290D48E47729"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Among women experiencing sex trafficking, many of their traffickers are also their intimate partners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DB961F8C1EE44A2A2269A06406952C5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Each day, an average of three women are killed by a current or former partner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91152780914640BBB410984108466332"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Researchers estimate that domestic violence costs employers up to $13,000,000,000 each year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34044C0B49794F10A4D9F240FF92F9E9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A fundamental component of ending domestic and sexual violence is securing safe and affordable housing for survivors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H186FFACDD00D401992CB1C0E911B9579"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Research indicates that: </text><subparagraph id="H6AF958F86A5D42A39C25238052B9822D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>As many as fifty-seven percent of homeless women report that domestic violence was the immediate cause of their homelessness. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35E39B54A99F4447B15118A9E904387A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Ninety-two percent of homeless women report having experienced severe physical or sexual violence at some point in their lives, including sexual exploitation and trafficking. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7A632AA25B640D8B25AD89EDEB234B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Eighty-four percent of survivors in domestic violence shelters reported that they needed help finding affordable housing. The National Network to End Domestic Violence’s DV Counts Report finds that the majority of survivors’ unmet needs are related to housing and shelter. In another nationwide study, more than half of the victims who identified a need for housing services did not receive them. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H742CAB24A9E34F84880AE990828CA920"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Survivors who become homeless as a result of sexual assault are vulnerable to further sexual victimization and exploitation including sex trafficking.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6691D6BFEA2F4515B2292C5CF83A3E26"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Women of color in the lowest income category experience six times the rate of nonfatal intimate partner violence compared to white women in the highest income category.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83F00BE41DFE48C2A3822F05E767FE6C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Poor women of color, domestic violence survivors, and women with children are among those at the highest risk of eviction.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FD1262FDBAF4826A2A81EFFDD881FBE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Housing insecurity can exacerbate survivors’ vulnerability. Women and men who experienced food or housing insecurity in a 12-month period had a significantly higher prevalence of rape, physical violence, or stalking by an intimate partner in that same time period, as compared to those who did not experience food or housing insecurity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABAE8957C6534A568645ADDD4F9E0B5A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Vulnerable women are also at risk of sex trafficking and exploitation by landlords who pressure them for sex in exchange for rent or a delay in rent payments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H486DB748A54D43A585A6F29B1BD85BAA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Approximately thirty-eight percent of all survivors of domestic violence become homeless at some point in their life.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H79442226AF5345AE80FEC06351B91C37"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Surveys show that a majority of survivors who experience a sexual assault in their home do not relocate to a safe environment because they do not have sufficient funds and are not aware of better options.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B49FF23BBDA4F4ABC940A4956F6321B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Domestic and sexual violence survivors often find themselves trapped in homes where they are further victimized by caregivers, parents, siblings, landlords, intimate partners, neighbors, or others in or near their home. Economic insecurity and the trauma that often follows sexual violence make it difficult, if not impossible, for many survivors to access safe, affordable housing options for themselves and their families.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F5B641AF3DB4BEAA2E25AC69C772BE8"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Domestic and sexual violence survivors continue to face discrimination in securing and maintaining housing based on their status as survivors and as a result of crimes committed against them.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85A9A2F0EB804822AC0F68ABA0F30EE3"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Research by the Attorney General of the State of New York found that sixty-seven percent of domestic violence survivors reported that discrimination by landlords is a significant obstacle in obtaining housing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06B38ABBFA0745198B8451E3D0CBB2AB"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Research also shows that survivors of domestic violence or sexual assault are commonly denied housing opportunities if a previous residence of the survivor was a domestic violence shelter, if the survivor has secured a protective order, or if there is other evidence that the survivor has experienced a previous domestic violence incident.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABE654A5A0704167A0825CACFC6166F9"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Studies show that survivors of domestic violence or sexual assault often face eviction based on a single domestic violence incident.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8AF0227FD984B3DB21FB0564DC54F9C"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Survivors of sex trafficking face additional challenges in obtaining and maintaining housing due to criminal records incurred as a direct result of their exploitation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4394B0A88DAB47A889AD622CB47095AF"><enum>(17)</enum><text>It is in the public interest to ensure that survivors of domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, dating violence, stalking, and other forms of intimate partner and gender-based violence are not discriminated against, particularly with respect to housing, based on their status as victims of the crimes committed against them.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF01476515EAB4FC4B736F2E7E09DB0AA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Survivors of domestic violence or sexual assault as protected class under the fair housing act</header><subsection id="H90E3D4496FB24639AAC1EEB38BB0BA92"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3601">42 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD6F2E74043F9489D83DE481DAA290A02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 802 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3602">42 U.S.C. 3602</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HB037CA2B81034290B392DC8833D4A89D" style="OLC"><subsection id="H06B350F8DD124CB290720645D6CBDE6E"><enum>(p)</enum><text><quote>Domestic violence</quote>—</text><paragraph id="HB309F5F813CD4F08ABC56A5E3A212EEB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB41C78D0FE343E9929D0EB20C78DFEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes—</text><subparagraph id="H0AA4DF681DB84127B53A4940BF606C96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>dating violence and stalking, as such terms are defined in such section 40002(a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD08AD0B2B81347FFA4FBFDD1276D6DB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">threatened domestic violence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15FF1D34739D4F47BE1CA5ACCF7DA6E3"><enum>(q)</enum><text><quote>Sexual assault</quote>—</text><paragraph id="H831CCE4ED01844A9BA9A37602052BB4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92B6DDBA960E4F49B724B014C52ED8C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes threatened sexual assault.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1BC1720E332C43E5A62290FAC948964C"><enum>(r)</enum><text><quote>Severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 103 of the Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7102">22 U.S.C. 7102</external-xref>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H56A898C653D14A10B6214F96A2CEAADA"><enum>(s)</enum><text><quote>Coercion</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 103 of the Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7102">22 U.S.C. 7102</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE95879C9FE0B4451B56042EDBE50E1B4"><enum>(t)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote> includes any person who experienced or is perceived to have experienced domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons.”.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9234A821876848D088413CAD03C4969A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 804 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3604">42 U.S.C. 3604</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="HAB28A5C530864C21B1A976A13E4DBC0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B498399E2E64212BA7A85B447F5833F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15AA4A6A2D9841A3BD6ACB426F3AF934"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13E00B45639845678B7FF4F613DBFD40"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H166C8C8690AC410593F62CF8E91F52A2"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (e), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H835470641851498296D9A9DF14A493BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 805 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3605">42 U.S.C. 3605</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H1598473F2BE64DB898A317DD3E3021F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF633BC41FDF842D783EDFFC46295A246"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>or familial status</quote> and inserting <quote>familial status, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H48548271EDCF442DA2995AA90D851946"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 806 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3606">42 U.S.C. 3606</external-xref>), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or whether a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA85E73DDB86644088BC0F06F8D60D2A7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 807 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3607">42 U.S.C. 3607</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H265F24EB633B431BB04DD0D09C686BAC" style="OLC"><subsection id="H247BEDF0919440B78EBD970D935B9AE4"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Nothing in this title shall prohibit a Federal, State, unit of local government, or other assistance or preference program from being designed to assist or benefit survivors of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons in seeking, securing, or maintaining dwellings, shelters, or any other form of housing for such survivors, including associated notices, statements, or advertisements of such dwelling.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H70097AE894CF4C7D91EF696C537F4F14"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 808(e)(6) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3608">42 U.S.C. 3608(e)(6)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>status as a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons,</quote> after <quote>handicap,</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F6FEA6BED4E48FEBCFD8B4F77D3DE46"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prevention of intimidation in fair housing cases</header><text>The Civil Rights Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1301">42 U.S.C. 1301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H802EE2715E5E4C12B11A4D8917548DD5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 901 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3631">42 U.S.C. 3631</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H203570F8783E43E49EB867F3EAC8EDB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph preceding subsection (a), by inserting <quote>or coercion</quote> after <quote>threat of force</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7FC06503128432F952718DE018E0ACC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or because the person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BEE1716B9E24E15B925F0B29ED49972"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(1), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or because a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB664CB5A7904C8C8A4447F0E22DD970"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by striking <quote>or national origin</quote> and inserting <quote>national origin, or because a person is a survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H85B29C5FC0E242699C2E199FCBEF53C0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 901 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H32D22FD78BAB456AA1B7673373965848" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H48C4DA92F2E349E69703E90F989A90E2" commented="no"><enum>902.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title, the terms <quote>domestic violence</quote>, <quote>sexual assault</quote>, <quote>severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote>, <quote>coercion</quote>, and <quote>survivor of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons</quote> shall have the meaning given such terms in section 802.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28F6199D712C4E40ACF8531CEA7195DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preservation of survivors’ ability To recover for other forms of discrimination</header><text>Nothing in this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, shall be interpreted to limit the ability of survivors of domestic violence, sexual assault, or severe forms of trafficking in persons to recover for any other claims of discrimination under the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3601">42 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.</external-xref>), including with respect to failure to conform to gender stereotypes or policies that disproportionately affect women. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

