<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6BFDC33802714C7E81185D8247904216" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3414 IH: Responsible Borrowing Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3414</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to authorize institutions of higher education to limit the amount of a Federal loan that an enrolled student may borrow.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7C14D8256996475DA84077463C294FAF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H65DB23A06C304AF5BBB602A1068068DB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Responsible Borrowing Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HC733141D92CE443181BD3581DD5AA07A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Institutional determined limits</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 455(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H4CACDC57280C4C4886558AB50EABE398" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HCC68113F4B784349BCC8D033F4B67D08"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institutional Determined Limits</header> 
<subparagraph id="HC027B7CD5B0F4018A85EEE366BEF136D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, an institution of higher education (at the discretion of a financial aid administrator at the institution) may prorate or limit the amount of a loan any student enrolled in a program of study at that institution may borrow under this part for an academic year or in the aggregate—</text> <clause id="H23CE8C9E4FFF4211A46DA7521A755496" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the institution can reasonably demonstrate that student debt levels are or would be excessive for such program, based on—</text> 
<subclause id="H155B3A939AB245FD8269E03B5CFAD759"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the most recently available data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics for the average or median starting salary in the region in which the institution is located for typical occupations pursued by graduates of such program; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA99B25840CA449778CC7D217A01F9C74"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the most recently available data from the College Scorecard (or successor website) on the median earnings of students who complete such program; </text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H9BD522BDE0BF47ADA6F40D1BF00CC16C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case in which the student is enrolled on a less than full-time basis or the student is enrolled for less than the period of enrollment to which the annual loan limit applies under this part, based on the student’s enrollment status;</text></clause> <clause id="HE000E3BC3B044D178C7E96D6D02D46ED"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the credential level (such as a degree, certificate, or other recognized educational credential) that the student would attain upon completion of such program; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H00E471F5035D43B6A035B6C1A0992EFE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the year of the program for which the student is seeking such loan.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H07F61C59380D4A619743E95314200180"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Increases for Individual Students</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the request of a student whose loan amount for an academic year has been prorated or limited under subparagraph (A), an eligible institution (at the discretion of the financial aid administrator at the institution) may increase such loan amount to an amount not exceeding the annual loan amount applicable to such student under this part for such academic year at the discretion of the financial aid administrator at the institution.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0E3A7FE7A4B64637B838A72655ED0737"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to authorize a proration or limiting of loan amounts by an institution of higher education because of a student’s race, color, religion, sex, marital status, age, disability, or national origin.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB88E0618EDCA4897B2F440728AAA4CEA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Exception for certain students</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This paragraph shall not apply to any student enrolled in a program of study at an eligible institution as of June 30, 2024, or any loans made under this part to such student for such enrollment, during the period required for the completion of such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

