<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H139637A1B7824CD8B58373E713A1527E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6204 IH: See the Board Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6204</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a grant program to support access to free eye care services for students attending public elementary schools and secondary schools.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD7A40ABF48764C1C9C729DC34E1D3349" style="OLC"><section id="H04285A4A99AF4BAEA4C97520845EF8C0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>See the Board Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2B0C66C03F3E496081B5319EAD237FFD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program to support access to free eye care services for students at public schools</header><subsection id="HAD2A03FB2069479E8EC12B0C77CC724C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall, subject to subsection (d), establish a grant program under which the Secretary awards grants to eligible entities that provide a qualifying eye care services program to purchase portable or mobile eye care equipment and to pay for appropriate operational costs, including for costs for qualified personal protective equipment, direct health care or service delivery costs, and any other relevant expense the Secretary determines necessary, for the provision of free eye care services through such program to students attending public elementary schools or secondary schools (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB6A805E8D1FF4944A87BEC78BA344F5B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, an eligible entity is a nonprofit organization.</text></subsection><subsection id="HED341CA7E27B476FBBD343458014EBBC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualifying eye care services program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>qualifying eye care services program</term> means a program under which such services are furnished free of charge to students attending public elementary schools or secondary schools (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) through the use of mobile eye clinics or mobile clinics that use portable equipment to bring screenings, exams, and an optical shop to such students. Such a program may use qualified health care providers at such schools or ophthalmic technicians for screening, optometrists or ophthalmologists for follow-up examinations, and an optician and dispensary for such students to be given glasses at such schools.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD2D7A0D28A224DC4B5A931DADD8E81F1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that eligible entities awarded grants under this section should, to the greatest extent possible, provide information to students described in subsection (a) and parents of such students about the importance of adhering to the medically recommended schedule for vision screenings and comprehensive eye exams.</text></subsection><subsection id="H18D515A2E0A14305A880CB6284FD4C61"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

