<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H595C8F73DC8F4249A97395CABC09A771" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4183 IH: Economic Inclusion Civil Rights Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4183</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend section 1977 of the Revised Statutes to protect equal rights under law.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HB9F575B437C44B78B1D8ABA4A6A1A4E7" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF695E93A35DF415098B8FC272A83FFB3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Economic Inclusion Civil Rights Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE3E246DE8A3B4E4C9B5872C60969B8A9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Equal rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1977 of the Revised Statutes (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1981">42 U.S.C. 1981</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB12C44AB351940CE9285C0BC352A941D"> 
<section id="H88447D44EFE14F1981FA67F589B7580A"><enum>1977.</enum><header>Equal rights under law</header> 
<subsection id="H5A40EEB2742E4D4080336CE6799FC578"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Finding</header><text>Congress finds that the decisions of the Supreme Court of the United States in Comcast Corp. v. National Ass’n of African American-Owned Media, 140 S. Ct. 1009 (2020), and General Building Contractors Ass’n v. Pennsylvania, 458 U.S. 375 (1982), have weakened the scope and effectiveness of Federal civil rights protections.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3CC4B6E0A64A46FDBFE8FE3161F1117F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose and authority</header> <paragraph id="HA7652F0C95774A7CAFE5427AE506EC47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>This section is an exercise of congressional authority under section 5 of the 14th Amendment, section 2 of the 13th Amendment, and the Commerce Clause of section 8 of article I, of the Constitution of the United States. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F58395224C2424096FEBB05070F85A8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to protect civil rights, including to enact into law key principles set forth in portions of the concurring opinion of Justice Ginsburg in Comcast Corp. v. National Ass’n of African<italic></italic> American-Owned Media, 140 S. Ct. 1009 (2020), and the dissenting opinion of Justice Marshall in General Building Contractors <italic></italic>Ass’n v. Pennsylvania, 458 U.S. 375 (1982). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB2BBF2DB469B482E969E9D2645773C97"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H832015056EE24AC48FB2D4431ACEAE5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Economic activity</header><text>The term <term>economic activity</term> shall have the broadest meaning permissible under the Constitution, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H71D0843049AC4372AD5E823F4BA15E82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>making, performing, and enforcing contracts;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6A0D00C2101848308ACF7AF278AAAF5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>producing, consuming, browsing for, shopping for, or waiting for goods or services; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H65E93DD7E74741FFA5B6C52A01FAED41"><enum>(C)</enum><text>soliciting, selecting, hiring, or dealing with a vendor, supplier, contractor, or subcontractor;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H18BD103D6EE24DC1A4B746E5AE48D6B1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>dealing with or serving (including refusing to serve) a shopper, patron, or customer;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H937D29A73B6446958F8CE9185536E726"><enum>(E)</enum><text>accessing, processing, or granting (including denying) access to loans, credit, bonding, or insurance; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H428C760C695A4C0A96B84119DADA019A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>purchasing, leasing, selling, holding, or conveying real or personal property, </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">whether the activities described in this paragraph occur on the internet, at a physical location, or through any other medium. </continuation-text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H721E4308D6154466BB7046BB1DF991AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Full and equal benefit and enjoyment of economic activity</header><text>The term <term>full and equal benefit and enjoyment of economic activity</term> means the benefit or enjoyment, respectively, of the same benefits, privileges, advantages, preferences, opportunities, terms, conditions, goods, services, facilities, accommodations, service and treatment, employment, and rights to make, enforce, perform, modify, and terminate contracts, and freedom from intimidation, harassment, and profiling as white citizens benefit from or enjoy, respectively.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF58CF0DB38D469B84396EA7B78C26ED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Security of person and property</header><text>The term <term>security</term>, used with respect to person and property, includes protection from physical harm and a threat of harm to one’s body or property, and protection against exposure to or a disproportionate burden from the negative human health and environmental impacts of pollution or an environmental hazard. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA49D1797DD8940569526825554FB1B13"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Statement of equal rights</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All persons within the jurisdiction of the United States shall have the same right in every State and territory as is enjoyed by white citizens to the full and equal benefit and enjoyment of economic activity, to security of their persons and property, to make and enforce contracts, including carrying out the contract formation process, and to sue, be parties, and give evidence, and to the full and equal benefit of all laws and proceedings, and shall be subject, in comparison to white citizens, to like punishment, pains, penalties, taxes, licenses, and exactions of every kind, and to no other.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H243972514A3C4A4DB4D8BB50AD8E1FD8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Discriminatory effects also prohibited</header> 
<paragraph id="H8357B8C1E2644405BA57BD3F89A39D75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No person shall use a criterion, method of administration, practice, or policy that has the effect of unjustifiably subjecting an individual to discrimination in violation of subsection (d).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5A81479C63A4A71B0BD59A5A78482CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Demonstration</header><text>A challenged criterion, method of administration, practice, or policy that has an effect described in paragraph (1) shall be unjustifiable unless its user demonstrates that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEF2CEB2972C94EE8BD25E9BBD58A3CC4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the use serves a legitimate purpose, which is both required by a substantial business necessity and not a pretext for discrimination; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H962E9E95EF904A1593D0E1D131EE1016"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the complaining party proffers an alternative, that that alternative is either inconsistent with substantial business necessity or would produce an equal or greater discriminatory effect on the basis of a classification protected by subsection (d). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE24ED2DA7534A109DF078E5DE1BA3C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on substantial business necessity defense</header><text>A demonstration that a criterion, method of administration, practice, or policy is required by a substantial business necessity may not be used as a defense against a claim of intentional discrimination under this section. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8AA6410AF9364651932E09C9664C67F4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Protection against impairment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All rights protected by this section are protected against impairment by nongovernmental discrimination and impairment under color of State law.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8919D270AF924565B2D961FB539C899E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Burden of proof for discriminatory treatment actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The equal rights guaranteed under subsection (d) shall be considered to be denied when the complaining party demonstrates that race was a motivating factor for the denial of such rights even though other factors also motivated the denial. A denial of equal rights guaranteed under subsection (d) may be established with comparator evidence or any other evidence that sufficiently demonstrates a denial of such rights, including evidence of conduct that a reasonable person would find racially hostile.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9076EF7A88BE48A9ACAF8D7FEC9B2E62"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Standing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person suffering injury in fact as a result of the alleged violation of this section may bring a cause of action for damages, or for equitable or for declaratory relief, under this section. Standing shall not be limited to victims who were parties to, or third-party beneficiaries of, a contract with the defendant. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H24309ABC008F4FB79F2B6EFEE9D54863"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Respondeat superior liability</header><text>Principals shall be liable for violations of this section by their agents, and local governments shall be liable for violations of this section by their employees, acting within the scope of their duties.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6D74C443B0624140A84717C18528DAA3"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Jury trial right</header><text>All persons within the jurisdiction of the United States shall have the right to enforce a right provided under this section in a court of law and before a jury of their peers, and no joint-action waiver or pre-dispute arbitration agreement shall be valid or enforceable with respect to any alleged violation of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC4A977BEBE1E4BB9A2B3FC8B062E663B"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Statute of limitations</header><text>All causes of action under this section shall be governed by the 4-year statute of limitations provided by section 1658(a) of title 28, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCCAC3587B1B94B1B95FBC9D4D6F4622F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Remediating past discrimination</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit or limit a lawful effort, under a provision other than this section, to remedy the effects of discrimination that has occurred or is occurring.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H698E7AA84B5C4914BFC51D65333DCD90"><enum>3.</enum><header>Application to pending actions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act, and the amendment made by this Act, shall apply to any cause of action for a violation of section 1977 of the Revised Statutes that is pending on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section> <section id="H651AAE20DF9345BC9EA186959D82BB74"><enum>4.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, the amendments made by this Act, and the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance shall not be affected thereby.</text></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


