<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9259F791B10F4F84842346FEAD751E15" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3715 IH: Affordability and Fairness for Mountain Communities Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3715</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To establish a waiver program to allow for ZIP Code localization area median income calculations, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H008CAD404FFA49D1B3123CD9AAEC4121" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF31DB2A327494654A9F30512445A6733" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Affordability and Fairness for Mountain Communities Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB9041A19CAE24A59B1D2D28B336AB91D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Waiver program for ZIP Code localization of area median income calculations</header> <subsection id="HD229115F2E1E45958500A74CD0FC0EB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall establish a waiver program to be known as the Area Median Income Localization Waiver (in this Act referred to as the <quote>waiver program</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H91DFCFEE2074479ABB1EBCFE8C1AEFB5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>The Waiver Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The waiver program established by the Secretary pursuant to subsection (a) shall allow a county government, or corresponding functional unit of government, to calculate area median income for covered programs using—</text> <paragraph id="HA74F37528AA7461CB5CECE4646729257"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a ZIP Code as the area for calculation; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EDAF892A8844CC7BAE0B56A3B88378C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a group of counties that each share a border with such county as the area for calculation. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H32564D71576D40958CCA12D0E9A0487B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A county government, or a corresponding functional unit of government, may apply to participate in the waiver program by submitting an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H09B8C4B547A147E78AC5563F7487CA35"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall grant a waiver to each county government, or corresponding functional unit of government, that submits an application pursuant to subsection (c).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8F52CDE7220B4AC5B08A9679DACAE246"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A county government, or corresponding functional unit of government, that receives a waiver under subsection (d) may, with respect to a covered program, calculate area median income using—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC543EBEB953A4DE68549EC1BC5560E8F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a ZIP Code as the area for calculation; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE4F86740C48346209C4919D3B347F3A8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a group of counties that each share a border with such county as the area for calculation; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H045006394C0942E09B3531935BDBEEC1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the original means for calculation provided by law for the program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE73A4C7FC3C74130B8F84A445BE48653"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Covered program defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered program</quote> means the following programs administered by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development or the Secretary of Agriculture:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB4B001D3337E4A79A7FCC5A1CCDCF128"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The public housing program under the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437">42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97CC4C1CAAD04A2F83DE32294F923868"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The program for rental assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H67BDB8EAB1F34EBDA2ACACCB57F74A4A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The HOME Investment Partnerships program under title II of the Cranton-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12721">42 U.S.C. 12721 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D8343C45BF04937B0607C360902A000"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The programs under Title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11360">42 U.S.C. 11360 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91FBA77400374058A1F8099CADEB53F8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Housing Trust Fund program under section 1338 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1992 (12 U.S.C 4568).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13070382DAB549BCB0E0D05D1F71175E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The program for supportive housing for the elderly under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEADA311CEF3C43FF988A722E738CECCE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The program for supportive housing for persons with disabilities under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1D64363122F498F8365357519A729EC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The AIDS Housing Opportunities program under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB659F6327FF544748F49A06BD4C33C04"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The program for Native American housing under the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4101">25 U.S.C. 4101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3994430DCB79439CB8444E23C95CF329"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The program for housing assistance for Native Hawaiians under title VIII of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4221">25 U.S.C. 4221 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE6297B049D14772A875D3A95FD9653C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The programs for assistance for rural rental housing under title V of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1471">42 U.S.C. 1471 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> <section id="HBA845D058E0D4345A727B5659D362A27"><enum>3.</enum><header>Assessment regarding optimizing use of area median income to support affordable housing in mountain communities</header> <subsection id="HBCE2CA7EBAF2414BA90702670498F516"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a study designed to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF2BA5066B0F547E3A3A0C2BC95AE7A23"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B492003513B43569F68E1DB999A3B46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>alternative methods for calculating area median income; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H31DB9719A0FC4FA3AB30E31071C11F63"><enum>(B)</enum><text>alternative metrics that would make housing more affordable for low-income families residing in mountain communities; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H815756E3EAB542C2A97D2C0593802E24"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluate how factoring roommates into area median income calculations for seasonal workers would impact housing assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE1880B9C0FFB4659ACA98528DC16EF67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H7501997F166142FAB71C2EBAEBFF79AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall, not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and make publicly available, a report that describes the findings of the study conducted pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61A6210E32084576980829CA5058ED08"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report contents</header><text>The report submitted pursuant to subparagraph (1) shall include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H37C88ABB70A046A5A9F888386F54CD7F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of all significant findings;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H81B246F3E4B343C18F37B439A812B8C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations found in any prior reports about the use of area median income;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86CF3B3237C44E8D80B3097E490CBCAA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment of the extent and impacts of the affordable housing crisis in mountain communities nationwide, particularly within jurisdictions for which the Secretary has applied a high housing cost adjustment, including a comparison of rent burdens for very low-income households and seasonal workers in jurisdictions with and without high housing cost adjustments;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46AD0178231C429A96856D74755E6DC8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an assessment of the effects that high housing cost adjustments have had on income limits and rent prices in mountain communities for which the Secretary has applied such an adjustment, including any effects on maximum rents allowed under sections 42 and 142 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 for tax-subsidized units;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F2C65F4F5AA42C49F6CFDA5AE6728A8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>recommendations for reforming or eliminating the use of area median income for the purposes of making housing more affordable for low-income and seasonal workers in mountain communities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34D3F357E9E64E5497C67AEDB1372510"><enum>(F)</enum><text>recommendations for using existing authorities of the Secretary to make housing more affordable for low-income and seasonal workers in mountain communities, particularly in areas for which the Secretary has applied a high housing cost adjustment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> </section> 
<section id="HA9C95E14F06740288BD34FB496F46590"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H3006B4B1296B43C2955DE8B24805F3F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Area median income</header><text>The term <term>area median income</term> means median income for an area, as such term is used in section 3(b) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437a">42 U.S.C. 1437a(b)</external-xref>), median family income, and any other substantively similar metric that the Secretary uses to refer to the median income level for a given area or jurisdiction for purposes of any program administered by the Secretary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H845B69457FB4466482660E2BCF4A76CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>High housing cost adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>high housing cost adjustment</term> an adjustment for high housing costs, high construction costs, or high costs of living, or any substantively similar adjustment that the Secretary may use to increase income limits for areas where the cost of housing is abnormally high compared to the median income for such area.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4284D0E9E4A0465CBBFE911F40F056DA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D787653B497466DA8A5D8E3CFF64644"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Mountain communities</header><text>The term <term>mountain communities</term> means any rural area, as defined in section 1490 of title 42, United States Code, located in the Mountain Division within the Census Bureau’s Western Region.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

