<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H242F595070754471BB2A48A3197B2B78" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5310 IH: Improving Contractor Cybersecurity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5310</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 41, United States Code, to require information technology contractors to maintain a vulnerability disclosure policy and program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H77555CAB2B5C44C3BA1297CBF33AA129" style="OLC"><section id="H2725642E0E5543B0B3197FC3BCC1E3B0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Contractor Cybersecurity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC4E86C5F32734AE1973F0B10E97278B0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Vulnerability disclosure policy and program required for information technology contractors</header><subsection id="H08EE130DD8434670B7B226D7F885BDCA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 47 of division C of subtitle I of title 41, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H5E2573912A7D48A8A9D48B92D52B1FF0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HDD53FDDFAA84470BABF8E20E7A91BE79"><enum>4715.</enum><header>Vulnerability disclosure policy and program required</header><subsection id="H3657295828344112A7A81B9C8E8FBD3C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements for information technology contractors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of an executive agency may not enter into a contract for information technology unless the contractor maintains or does the following:</text><paragraph id="H7FE7CD52CD734B7DB0ECE01D0A8A0770"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vulnerability disclosure policy for information technology that—</text><subparagraph id="H25669C33F919466E98FBDC3D231CA0D5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text> includes—</text><clause id="H5C42E735D8FE4E2B8E1A98EBC834B58A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of which systems are in scope;</text></clause><clause id="HBB7AB83AAC7A4D7688E146AF60A965EF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the type of information technology testing for each system that is allowed (or specifically not authorized);</text></clause><clause id="HE1EF0888CF184A7B8F2B04DA3719999B" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if a contractor includes systems that host sensitive information in the vulnerability disclosure policy, the contractor shall determine whether to impose restrictions on accessing, copying, transferring, storing, using, and retaining such information, including by—</text><subclause id="HD5BF3D8D307C43B686D4F5B383146803" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prohibiting sensitive information from being saved, stored, transferred, or otherwise accessed after initial discovery;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC9A979761B344D75B82194BBAE6EC89F" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>directing that sensitive information be viewed only to the extent required to identify a vulnerability and that the information not be retained; or </text></subclause><subclause id="H9EFDD7CC2B584A07B82086A54383569B" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>limiting use of information obtained from interacting with the systems or services to be explored by the researcher to activities directly related to reporting security vulnerabilities;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFA0B7B2E8EF1400CB907B51E3EEAC7CB" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a description of how an individual may submit a vulnerability report that includes—</text><subclause id="HF2AE31B2E39A4F97A3827104F34A8EB3" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the location of where to send the report, such as a web form or email address;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9B199DD7A17D482CB1E4BB715362A09A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the type of information necessary to find and analyze the vulnerability (such as a description, the location, and potential impact of the vulnerability, the technical information needed to reproduce the vulnerability, and any proof of concept); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H986138A4BF1542B79A131B87B2419995" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a clear statement—</text><item id="HEF88FA25954D4B0790ED160BEE203AAE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>that any individual that submits a vulnerability report may do so anonymously; and</text></item><item id="H741ECD01FE1246B0B1D0B16FC04F30F4"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>on how and whether any incomplete submission is evaluated;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HBCD62329D59C44E6AC26D2B3B668560A" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a commitment from the contractor that the contractor will not pursue civil action for any accidental, good faith violation of the vulnerability disclosure policy;</text></clause><clause id="H45BFAF8C541C4800A1A7D78DC5CDD8AA" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a commitment from the contractor that if an individual acting in accordance with the vulnerability disclosure policy of the contractor is sued by a third party, the contractor will inform the public or the court that the individual was acting in compliance with the vulnerability disclosure policy; </text></clause><clause id="H9B8E505EA4FA49E1B4324D3E49C0DB22" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>a statement that describes the time frame in which the individual that submits a report, if known, will receive a notification of receipt of the report and a description of what steps will be taken by the contractor during the remediation process; and</text></clause><clause id="H52217704AD2F4C01864CC476F26BBA66"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a set of guidelines that establishes what type of activity by a researcher are acceptable and unacceptable; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD02BED23BC44CD1B9955F2415691EE7" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not—</text><clause id="HD81D011B17254B48AF696672E49FDC08" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require the submission of personally identifiable information of a researcher; and</text></clause><clause id="H08B78FE2A9104C55909154FC5B3CA357" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>limit testing solely to entities approved by the contractor but rather authorizes the public to search for and report any vulnerability.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F91C17BE2AD4787895289D9FAAD7590" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of additional procedures that describe how the contractor will communicate with the researcher, and how and when any communication occurs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A0ED48B55F1444597A9CC5FB093730E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of the target timelines for and tracking of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H01E073B0B2734088B6DA30F968D1415E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text> Notification of receipt to the individual that submits the report, if known.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9A3EB4DE38047BC9D8869117F33714F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An initial assessment, such as determining whether any disclosed vulnerability is valid.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H632D2545043041739023D84C83A2958D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Resolution of a vulnerability, including notification of the outcome to the researcher.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA30793B62257464AB861D54C576827AB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A page on the website of the contractor that—</text><subparagraph id="HE31D86F7B8EA44F4898AF9F08D0CC6FE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allows for the submission of vulnerabilities by anyone relating to the information technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7921CF0EA884E4B99AB503A9D67FD2C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">lists the contact information, such as a phone number or email address for an individual or team responsible for reviewing any such submission under subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E78DFA250324D95BAD96773C98190E1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describes the process by which a review is conducted, including how long it will take for the contractor to respond to researcher and whether or not monetary rewards will be paid to the reporter for identifying a vulnerability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10C33881E6744853A3266D318F484218"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a discovered vulnerability that the contractor is not responsible for patching, the contractor shall submit the vulnerability to the responsible party or direct the researcher to the appropriate party.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF09BCB4B613245A0A5161F11D813A700" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirements and metrics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 7 days after the date on which the vulnerability disclosure policy described in subsection (a) is published, and on an ongoing basis as vulnerability reports are received, an information technology contractor shall report to the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security the following information:</text><paragraph id="H8EB002F3B4C14DB2BF816B376ED0CF37" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any valid or credible report of a not previously known public vulnerability (including any misconfiguration) on a system that uses commercial software or services that affect or are likely to affect other parties in government or industry once a patch or viable mitigation is available. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCBA017AABE24B96A4321638D3000309" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other situation where the contractor determines it would be helpful or necessary to involve the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C5BA4726A7F4B61976E0B8ACFBCD6EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>CISA submission of vulnerabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency shall communicate with and submit, as necessary, vulnerabilities to the MITRE Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures database and the National Institute of Standards and Technology National Vulnerability Database. </text></subsection><subsection id="H477D01A66F984E03AC8BC0944B8992F6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB42EBFA37F9F4CAEA7C9DAF902BC51C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>The term <term>executive agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 133.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H187B82D8656B47D7B57865B0EF79689A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Researcher</header><text>The term <term>researcher</term> means the individual who submits a vulnerability report. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC5E2096996E4483A954C37B3904CBC0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information technology</header><text>The term <term>information technology</term> has the meaning given that term in section 11101 of title 40.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA82AF66A255F4F0C908CE75B0A44EE0D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for chapter 47 of division C of subtitle I of title 41, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H00FAC1A5E0074835988AEBFD98DB4321" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="item">4715. Vulnerability disclosure policy and program required.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HE1BEBD75A66940B8B4190A651D4FADFE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this section and shall apply to any contract entered into on or after such effective date.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

