<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0AEFCDE77118404E883F2D8A34D85C7D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5912 IH: Preventing Underhanded and Nefarious Iranian Supported Homicides Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5912</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committees on Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To continue in effect certain Executive orders imposing sanctions with respect to Iran, to prevent the waiver of certain sanctions imposed by the United States with respect to Iran until the Government of Iran ceases to attempt to assassinate United States officials, other United States citizens, and Iranian nationals residing in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HAA564332EB484541B5E968CEFE78340F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H03185EC1F3604C03BD7B3FC02034E2A7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Underhanded and Nefarious Iranian Supported Homicides Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PUNISH Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFE12F88D9537426692768A8CEBE8E925"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD0011ED47D58408CA409871A1AD63A66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H7AD96C60D31E456D8E8508ECDF7DC267"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9268D54BBD704414AA2CE098D25E7DF3" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BC696C98B9D4748BB7995A17342448D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered Executive order</header><text>The term <term>covered Executive order</term> means any of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA21655303D004FECBD40439322327E5D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Executive Order 13871 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to imposing sanctions with respect to the iron, steel, aluminum, and copper sectors of Iran), as in effect on May 10, 2019. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H435549248FD44DC0A26819D6165261C1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Executive Order 13876 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to imposing sanctions with respect to Iran), as in effect on June 24, 2019.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE7D1C92790C84AE486B1A907AEEE88BD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Executive Order 13902 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to imposing sanctions with respect to additional sectors of Iran), as in effect on January 10, 2020.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1A5FB18CE8B846C7AE698400165340D6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Executive Order 13949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property of certain persons with respect to the conventional arms activities of Iran), as in effect on September 21, 2020. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6249A524C73045108B6891D341FA17D2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered provision of law</header><text>The term <term>covered provision of law</term> means any of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HA8CE7829ABC347899CA04D0F22E4A3B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>This Act. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC5C1D3F0C00E4842845FA8B838DE03DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each covered Executive order.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H769C1CD6AB1B448ABB08167A030EB17F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB97E25C2C7A54078871531AC29B60126"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8501">22 U.S.C. 8501 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F99DA75F2FB4B8494A489C6DAB23E59" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Section 1245 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H80C01DBE8CE24F3EB06C41861C415422"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Iran Threat Reduction and Syria Human Rights Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8701">22 U.S.C. 8701 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEFEF6BE6CE014A51BB7F5B603431B154"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8801">22 U.S.C. 8801 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCD4B5B53F99E4EAF923D2236D5EDFE62"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Title I of the Countering America's Adversaries Through Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9401">22 U.S.C. 9401 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H97C5B179DECA48D58410529CEBA7A8E8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HFC330C1EA8D74344B843A20E4F05DDD0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Government of Iran</header><text>The term <term>Government of Iran</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HEACC7C4F4AB84E9BAB34056011A49B83"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any agency or instrumentality of the Government of Iran; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HD0CD47F8EC4144938A0E6126CC9DAA0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any person owned or controlled by that Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H30BC721DF9E7485FBC8F0BFEDDD4EE91"><enum>3.</enum><header>Continuation in effect of certain Executive orders imposing sanctions with respect to Iran</header> <subsection id="H7AA03D8BCC4D495CB7EFF79956DC6168"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each covered Executive order shall remain in effect and continue to apply, and may not be modified, until the termination date described in section 10.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2D13F737DEC341CDA18AE9440A40638D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Continuation in effect of sanctions designations</header><text>With respect to each person designated for the imposition of sanctions pursuant to a covered Executive order before the date of the enactment of this Act, the designation of the person, and sanctions applicable to the person pursuant to the designation, shall remain in effect and continue to apply, and may not be modified, until the termination date described in section 10.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H737128F3DD6E4098BF5E0675A8CA1899"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>In publishing this Act in slip form and in the United States Statutes at Large pursuant to section 112 of title 1, United States Code, the Archivist of the United States shall include at the end an appendix setting forth the text of each covered Executive order. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB22BBFB857F748579995CF29693CD21E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Continuation in effect of national emergencies declared with respect to Iran</header> 
<subsection id="H37CB3C01908B4FCEB19F0A10FE6070B2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (a)(2) or (d) of section 202 of the National Emergencies Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1622">50 U.S.C. 1622</external-xref>), the national emergencies specified in subsection (b) shall remain in effect and continue to apply, and may not be modified, until the termination date described in section 10.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDB0F0551A25E4F5F9A6C6B51B220D8A0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National emergencies specified</header><text>The national emergencies specified in this subsection are the following national emergencies declared with respect to Iran:</text> 
<paragraph id="H643E845B7E8F4995B717AE7B99911BA5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The national emergency declared by Executive Order 12170 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking Iranian Government property) and most recently continued by the Notice of the President issued November 8, 2022 (87 Fed. Reg. 68,013).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC9DC70319864A74818CA298326AEEAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The national emergency declared by Executive Order 12957 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to prohibiting certain transactions with respect to the development of Iranian petroleum resources) and most recently continued by the Notice of the President issued March 10, 2023 (88 Fed. Reg. 15,595).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1B4781E1A32040EE98E7D5EB9B580C0A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Continuation in effect of sanctions with respect to the Central Bank of Iran, the National Development Fund of Iran, the Etemad Tejarte Pars Company, the National Iranian Oil Company, and the National Iranian Tanker Company under Executive Order 13224</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">With respect to each Iranian person designated on January 1, 2021, for the imposition of sanctions under Executive Order 13224 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and prohibiting transactions with persons who commit, threaten to commit, or support terrorism), as in effect on September 9, 2019, the designation of the person, and sanctions applicable to the person pursuant to the designation, shall remain in effect and continue to apply, and may not be modified, until the termination date described in section 10.</text></section> <section id="HB794E75E25AD44C08E2FB26555661306"><enum>6.</enum><header>Continuation in effect of foreign terrorist organization designation of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The designation of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>), and sanctions applicable to the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps pursuant to that designation, shall remain in effect and continue to apply, and may not be modified, until the termination date described in section 10. </text></section> 
<section id="HF1DBF2D2209C4A449638C1344EC1399A" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Prohibition on sanctions relief for Iranian financial institutions, including with respect to petroleum purchases from Iran</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1245(d) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a(d)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (4) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H390DF299E6074CF58C18E2E0EF572F16"> <paragraph id="H13CC263ED0E4461B823AA4928E432BEA" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on authority</header><text>The President may not exercise the authority under paragraph (5) to waive the imposition of sanctions under paragraph (1), or issue any license to authorize the purchase of petroleum or petroleum products from Iran, unless the determination set forth in the most recent report submitted under subsection (a) of section 9 of the <short-title>Preventing Underhanded and Nefarious Iranian Supported Homicides Act of 2023</short-title> was a determination that the Government of Iran has not engaged in any of activities described in subsection (b) of that section during the 5-year period preceding submission of the report.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H340E7091EF06412A9431DD8E6F85FBCC"><enum>8.</enum><header>Limitation on waiver, suspension, or reduction of sanctions with respect to Iran</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President may not waive, suspend, reduce, provide relief from, or otherwise limit the application of sanctions imposed pursuant to any covered provision of law unless, in addition to the requirements for a waiver under that provision of law, the determination set forth in the most recent report submitted under subsection (a) of section 9 was a determination that the Government of Iran has not engaged in any of activities described in subsection (b) of that section during the 5-year period preceding submission of the report.</text></section> <section id="HD95144D20747487F95CB36DBF5C0D5FA"><enum>9.</enum><header>Determination on the cessation of Iranian-sponsored assassinations or attempted assassinations of United States citizens and Iranian residents of the United States</header> <subsection id="H4B68DA46697D4011B3477FBA8381A03E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Determination required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, and the Secretary of the Treasury, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report setting forth a determination of whether the Government of Iran or any foreign person (including any foreign financial institution) has directly or indirectly ordered, controlled, directed, or otherwise supported (including through the use of Iranian agents or affiliates of the Government of Iran, including Hezbollah, Hamas, Kata’ib Hezbollah, Palestinian Islamic Jihad, or any other entity determined to be such an agent or affiliate) any of the activities described in subsection (b) during the 5-year period preceding submission of the report.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0DBF1B8357E4441E8B9DC5C453E133C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities described</header><text>The activities described in this subsection are—</text> <paragraph id="HFF0E3449A3FD40A694963B6FF57B6E7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the murder, attempted murder, assault, or other use or threat to use violence against—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDB6FEE7C7B774F47AA8D58327900B48D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any current or former official of the Government of the United States, wherever located;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA771BD3C61040049482A7081B055F66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any United States citizen or alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence in the United States, wherever located; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H728AD27E93DA49028F37751A33465462"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any Iranian national residing in the United States; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3B156E025084BC890EBA1A15CD5450B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the politically motivated intimidation, abuse, extortion, or detention or trial—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1389D7BC3C08475888AAEFEF3A52F5F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in Iran, of a United States citizen or alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence in the United States; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9C312B49F9D5492697B6C3F66BEE8C32"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outside of Iran, of an Iranian national or resident or individual of Iranian origin.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H3C6CE10E07A647E5B27A865E73370AE2"><enum>10.</enum><header>Termination date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The termination date described in this section is the date that is 30 days after the date on which the President submits to Congress the certification described in section 401(a) of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8551">22 U.S.C. 8551(a)</external-xref>).</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

