<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H13E4A6D9AB2F4868B03318B0D6F4041A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4714 IH: Pediatricians Accelerate Childhood Therapies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4714</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to authorize the Director of the National Institutes of Health to make awards to outstanding scientists, including physician-scientists, to support researchers focusing on pediatric research, including basic, clinical, translational, or pediatric pharmacological research, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6BA2D69469F749A895D543C4FD8C0161" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H04274165C8834E0A8B09BA09EB76E8FB"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pediatricians Accelerate Childhood Therapies Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H87060072D00D4404B8173CE2D8C0FE93"><enum>2.</enum><header>Trans-NIH Awards for Early-Career Pediatric Researchers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part G of title IV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/288">42 U.S.C. 288 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E160AE91D17477DAE69CE9A70048FAA">
<section id="H435369752A184FDC8EC8AF337DF42411"><enum>489A.</enum><header>Trans-NIH Awards for Early-Career Pediatric Researchers</header>
<subsection id="H64B6EC19C4F0487A936147C1BB26970A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the NIH shall make awards to public and nonprofit entities to support outstanding scientists, including physician-scientists, to support early-career researchers focusing on pediatric research, including basic, clinical, translational, or pediatric pharmacological research.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H898BB1037EDA438FAAF9FFB7B87DC9F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority research populations</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Director of NIH may prioritize the issuance of awards to—</text>
<paragraph id="H428FD5C048184D80A270045285A455F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>individual researchers at institutions described in subsection (a) presenting qualifying applications and representing populations that have been historically underrepresented in pediatric medical research, including women and underrepresented racial minorities; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13C3D8CA12C54C409A109E239E6DD4B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>institutions of higher education that are eligible to receive funds under part A or B of title III of the Higher Education Act of 1965, part A or B of title V of such Act, or subpart 4 of part A of title VII of such Act, or research institutions partnering with such institutions of higher education to offer programs to support early-career pediatric researchers. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H195C5FC3BE124EB6A5B40D0154BA63EF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority research topic areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a), the Director of NIH, in consultation with the Director of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development and the directors of other national research institutes and national centers that participate within the NIH Pediatric Research Consortium, shall—</text> <paragraph id="H6B46DE68665840DF915A97C77AEFF238"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish priority research topic areas, informed by external stakeholders, including research institutions, professional societies, patient advocacy organizations, and the private sector; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD72DA525A6314355A38E4A78DB0E58A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider opportunities to align such priority pediatric research topic areas with current and future priorities of the National Institutes of Health, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HCEED036C53064ECD8BD95A2B1D11662A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pediatric and adolescent mental and behavioral health, including addiction medicine;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBCC85A0E7AC94AEF8669724C5BC537D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>childhood cancer;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8EF3CB65A0AF44728B1CAE3D8C32F37F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>precision medicine, genetics, and genomics;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBD5A51770818455F9F6E3DD7FD5BB0B6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>rare diseases and disorders, such as sickle cell disease, and other diseases and disorders with significant unmet training needs; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H41A36A5F273040268E6817572167980E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>fetal, placental, and neonatal development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9FB8935131B94BE6858A7FB2BE649CC0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Director of NIH—</text> <paragraph id="H7EFBEA47BD324599B76ECAFA0EDB036C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall require recipients of awards under this section to use such awards to support pediatric research activities, including costs associated with laboratory staff and other costs associated with the conduct of research; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE77F0A7E9469417C957AF4C8A03FC801"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may allow recipients of awards under this section to use such awards for costs associated with receiving guidance and training from senior researchers and mentors, as necessary to help such recipients reach a state of research independence, including conferences and other meeting participation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H34A9BEF4ACDF4871883499E485EC22E1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Awards made under this section shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, other funding for pediatric research and pediatric training.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="HFE78BBFADAA1409FAF02F3EB309F9674"><enum>3.</enum><header>NIH Pediatric Research Consortium</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title IV of the Public Health Service is amended by inserting after section 409D (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/284h">42 U.S.C. 284h</external-xref>) the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H221B5E9C3C414AA1AFFB7C3045A7D10E"> <section id="H9D6E02F438C84AA3B30B126C66D4C12E"><enum>409D–1.</enum><header>NIH Pediatric Research Consortium</header> <subsection id="H30940523F7D44D16BB414AEFE5BD334C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of NIH shall establish and maintain a consortium to be known as the NIH Pediatric Research Consortium (in this section referred to as the <quote>Consortium</quote>) to coordinate pediatric research programs across the National Institutes of Health.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H3D7EC0FF334D4BF393F937C71710877A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The members of the Consortium shall consist of representatives of multiple national research institutes and national centers.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H60F5B53ABCBC46D0B19900FC4994C0D0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Chair of the Consortium shall be the Director of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (or the Director’s designee).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF7E26B8A189A437F98310BFC6E9399CE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In coordinating pediatric research programs across the National Institutes of Health, the Consortium shall—</text> <paragraph id="H9D01A8E1FD764429952902CE91693642"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish new or confirm existing National Institutes of Health pediatric research priorities, including priorities involving multiple national research institutes or centers;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F28863627374C17B2957BDE0A5FBFC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify gaps and opportunities for research collaborations involving multiple national research institutes and national centers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8721257B6E6D4CF9A3FDAA774A4709C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify opportunities to develop the next generation of pediatric researchers.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA0F9CD976F0B47E8883920A7F42916C7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Consortium shall consult regularly with external experts in the field of pediatric research, including children’s hospitals, children’s research institutions, patient organizations, and other stakeholders. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HA8831627B18B43E5BD1A29E194747894"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Beginning one year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Pediatricians Accelerate Childhood Therapies Act of 2023</short-title> and every 2 years thereafter, the Consortium shall submit to Congress, and make publicly available on the website of the National Institutes of Health, a report on—</text>
<paragraph id="HDB6BD9D3C49A4971BD6007FCA57F4541"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any research project involving pediatrics and involving more than one Institute or Center that was supported during the review period;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3CAD1CC21CA24B819F48A7BF936B4A3E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any strategic initiatives that include proposed research activities focused on pediatrics;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H83111A52C02143749432C661E2B69127"><enum>(3)</enum><text>career development awards supporting early-career researchers focused in pediatrics, including specific numbers of awards and amount of funding, made during the review period;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5E487E0F027D4D9EB0B36DECEF296133"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">details on the composition of awards supporting early-career researchers, including deidentified, aggregate demographic data indicating the proportion of early-career researchers supported by the awards who are from populations that have been underrepresented in pediatric medical research; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9AF7E6C33B684965B8DA595BBA1D5ED3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such other information as the Director of NIH determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

