<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1AD7DE144ACE43518800D9E193EFECC5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5117 IH: Securing American Classrooms Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5117</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To make certain amounts available for grants under the COPS program to be used for establishing school-based partnerships between local law enforcement agencies and local school systems by using school resource officers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF40EEA1E19534F13997B2F5F7688AB25" style="OLC"><section id="HF8781B67419140DE97AF029C158D4EEE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing American Classrooms Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H42A8770F7BE342C0A1523B89E57F93A3"><enum>2.</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any provision of section 9705 of title 31, United States Code, $1,000,000,000 of the funds available in the Department of the Treasury Forfeiture Fund established under that section shall be made available to the Attorney General, to remain available until expended. The Attorney General shall use such funds to make grants under part Q of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968, except that $750,000,000 of such grants may only be made to grantees who certify that they will use such funds for the purpose under section 1701(b)(12) of such part, and who will be hiring at least one veteran as a school resource officer.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

