<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H66070CF3088943549F77AA218E33E0C4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5885 IH: Honoring Police Officer and K9 Service Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5885</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a grant program to facilitate the veterinary care of former law enforcement canines, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H33A3F30549CB443DBC023D053765775D" style="OLC"><section id="HD6C10F71A6CF4320B6329901C307BCB7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Honoring Police Officer and K9 Service Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9D91CD67637B4ACE9E5991C1DA1AF014"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program to facilitate veterinary care for former law enforcement canines</header><subsection id="HC65DAF34520445D29C2E5CA210443DE4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall establish a grant program to facilitate the care of former law enforcement canines (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H59D2470A3C654F70A6E82E0F53F04B3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authority and eligible recipients</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program, the Attorney General may award a grant on a competitive basis to any entity that qualifies as a nonprofit organization under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and that the Attorney General determines has—</text><paragraph id="HEA8F0AC09A5644CEB3B523EDB01A3EDD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a demonstrated history of successfully assisting the owners of former law enforcement canines with costs associated with veterinary care, medication and antibiotics, or other medical expenses for the canine; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D7211BB5DC742B688098806AB3D78DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the capacity to record and provide a detailed accounting of the purposes for which grant amounts are expended. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BA72871E41A43E6BB569176601066E0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under the program may only use grant funds to cover the costs associated with veterinary care, medication and antibiotics, or other medical expenses determined necessary by a veterinarian for the former law enforcement canine.</text></subsection><subsection id="H48016BB44C9E4534BA52B6AD15E83DDC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under the Program, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Attorney General determines appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB4EC468C5ABC43CFB61C901EA6CF2BA4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HE1DD5D6B7DDB4369BA0151C298B5A324"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports to Attorney General</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under the program, a prospective recipient shall agree to submit to the Attorney General, on an annual basis for the duration of the project to be carried out using grant funds a report containing, with respect to the year covered by the report—</text><subparagraph id="H0AC0C1DE27254F5E875A4B07B8924BE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a detailed accounting of how grant funds were used; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4D55945E3244F429B2A9DDB22BB130F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a proposal for how activities carried out under the project may be improved in the future.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94F858EEAA7945CD90442F8F8113489F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text>Upon receiving a report under paragraph (1), the Attorney General shall submit a copy of the report to Congress.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28D7065561A5405EBD1862B7169A8CE3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $5,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4FC8784E88874EC28BE52060B32CB7F4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Former law enforcement canine defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>former law enforcement canine</quote> means a canine that has been used by a Federal, State, or local agency in the performance of law enforcement duties and that has been determined by such agency to be no longer needed for official purposes.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

