<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8D3627138B1E456CA9FA80E3AA362E80" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3061 IH: Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3061</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230502">May 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 49, United States Code, to establish an Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund in the Department of Homeland Security to fund investments in aviation security checkpoint technology, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H411D8A3738734A82B5C0533697A372D8" style="OLC"><section id="H38C2C9F9B44140BD873165C8837E61CD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAD11FF09E08D451C873EABE0E1FCEAC5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 44923 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H6EB33F2FCE1C4370B93AE605ACA65FCE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (i) as subsection (j); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA174A1E3F58D46DCAC17A4F96C562BBF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (h) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="H0FE685AD33694BE7BD01C447A7C4AF20"><subsection id="H44F6901E1FE04308BDB38BB77A261FBA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund</header><paragraph id="H1509B3E8DE3744D3B397D0174D3EC4EE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Department of Homeland Security a fund to be known as the Aviation Security Checkpoint Technology Fund (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>ASCT Fund</quote>). The second $250,000,000 from fees received under section 44940(a)(1) in each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 shall be available to be deposited in the ASCT Fund. The Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration shall impose the fee authorized by section 44940(a)(1) so as to collect not less than $250,000,000 in each of such fiscal years for deposit into the ASCT Fund. Amounts in the ASCT Fund shall be available until expended to the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration to fund the procurement, deployment, and sustainment of aviation security checkpoint technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D5C8E5520664D10A36D472C0FC5720A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>TSA briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection and quarterly thereafter for five years, the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration shall brief the Committee on Homeland Security and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate regarding planned procurement, nationwide deployment, and sustainment efforts of aviation security checkpoint technology at airport checkpoints through amounts made available from the ASCT Fund.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

