<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF72817B2CD684F2BBBCA3FA7AD91D653" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 4494 IH: Ensuring Faith in Our Elections Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4494</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000597">Ms. Lee of Florida</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote election integrity, voter confidence, and faith in elections by removing Federal impediments to, providing State tools for, and establishing voluntary considerations to support effective State administration of Federal elections and improving election administration in the District of Columbia, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H57DA5A0082284B1FB3A9E356864665FB" style="OLC"><section id="H07C093E30AF9454D93261A74124EC365" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Faith in Our Elections Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3C675007450149989E81039E52F6F847"><enum>2.</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H07C093E30AF9454D93261A74124EC365" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3C675007450149989E81039E52F6F847" level="section">Sec. 2. Table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8159674E7B99460B99A239F4F8A071B2" level="title">Title I—Findings Relating to Election Administration</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA3DAA18249D1463F832EFCB35A3EDA5F" level="section">Sec. 101. Findings Relating to Election Administration.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1C4B868A7D5F48E8A771ACBE13F23D50" level="title">Title II—Voluntary Considerations for State Administration of Federal Elections</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8EF7E4E76816441ABFA2346453866B17" level="section">Sec. 111. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8E476A4A8783409EB9BF760782E4D01B" level="section">Sec. 112. Election integrity voluntary considerations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC2AE9596D0A746EE94E671AFEA134CA8" level="title">Title III—Requirements to Promote Integrity in Election Administration</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCDD104242F174EF09F37802FC11B8BAC" level="section">Sec. 121. Ensuring only eligible American citizens may participate in Federal elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB90590EE1E9642528C8C1257BBA5A9CC" level="section">Sec. 122. State reporting requirements with respect to voter list maintenance.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H53163EF7DE5E41F7864B62C815F1B622" level="section">Sec. 123. Contents of State mail voter registration form.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HAD015A425F7C445D92F5ECDC3FA50D60" level="section">Sec. 124. Provision of photographic citizen voter identification tools for State use.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H12658F14CF674CA4A4F60B88C939B86A" level="section">Sec. 125. Confirming access for Congressional election observers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8018D04EC694CE7A1C6641D5C658AA6" level="section">Sec. 126. Use of requirements payments for post-election audits.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDBA34F69365C4674B0004E75D7F36546" level="section">Sec. 127. Certain tax benefits and simplification with respect to election workers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HED40D54708F64E8185A8D8B765B5653A" level="section">Sec. 128. Voluntary guidelines with respect to nonvoting election technology.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE3AB0012D5744FCC8D9E63646A7F4DD8" level="section">Sec. 129. Status reports by National Institute of Standards and Technology.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H386E189CCA274552971C61F7F841F8D6" level="section">Sec. 130. Requirements with respect to election mail.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H293DE62383CA44E18055FFC12C52F086" level="section">Sec. 131. Clarification of right of State to appeal decisions through duly authorized representative.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H11F30F13093A49B8B7C4FBBDDCB05258" level="section">Sec. 132. Federal agency involvement in voter registration activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H83F4D8D26DAD4B69980FC8C32D6F173C" level="section">Sec. 133. Prohibition on use of Federal funds for election administration in States that permit ballot harvesting.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H13F6C66D708341B7AA20100789AA7D6C" level="section">Sec. 134. Clarification with respect to Federal election record-keeping requirement.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H80C0DA9A2F994B989499B7D21D2B7391" level="section">Sec. 135. Clarification of rules with respect to hiring of election workers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4E284798AF92489D9CF2FEC4C9482787" level="section">Sec. 136. United States Postal Service coordination with States to ensure mailing addresses.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE06560FEBC5F4E17B1BC6119CDB98D32" level="section">Sec. 137. State defined.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H111BCA3DF70D4A35BE669E38599DB305" level="title">Title IV—District of Columbia Election Integrity and Voter Confidence</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2A87163AA4784F069C1CB5E0B9D349F7" level="section">Sec. 141. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDDD9C8B7A4BA4A78A2EAD93E6319E63A" level="section">Sec. 142. Requirements for elections in District of Columbia.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H775BC0FBCE7D49D58266FDF6B34FDC16" level="section">Sec. 143. Effective date.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H19D0F5D3DB834E428F47EB9357E80E4E" level="title">Title V—Administration of the Election Assistance Commission</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HADDAD1BABA4941DD99D4ADA48B4ADF62" level="section">Sec. 151. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFA07A00F3647447F90359CBFE92FE346" level="section">Sec. 152. Findings relating to the administration of the Election Assistance Commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H28A8C9B9FAB94B0A8FC6E2010E8E0301" level="section">Sec. 153. Requirements with respect to staff and funding of the Election Assistance Commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA0F7EBBC90C8434682C27F3AB270178D" level="section">Sec. 154. General requirements for payments made by Election Assistance Commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H31328DD6ED044DC4A1C0040C2F62FB43" level="section">Sec. 155. Executive Board of the Standards Board authority to enter into contracts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H46C92212764A4696A15D463A2CA4FD8F" level="section">Sec. 156. Election Assistance Commission primary role in election administration.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDE5924C6BB7D41D6AA93D28C08B2E79D" level="title">Title VI—Prohibition on Involvement in Elections by Foreign Nationals</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFA74F0F3A1D54BD690671F22F4ECB503" level="section">Sec. 161. Prohibition on contributions and donations by foreign nationals in connection with ballot initiatives and referenda.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8C30A59100C4B5F8629EBA8A1DE54AA" level="section">Sec. 162. Prohibiting providing assistance to foreign nationals in making contributions or donations in connection with elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDE4BA67924C047A78B3D06562C9B1FB9" level="title">Title VII—Constitutional Experts Panel with Respect to Presidential Elections</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE70377A998CA4ABA92AE0A823D39E7D0" level="section">Sec. 171. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB20B8E8AECDE4200BFD6572F497FACD2" level="section">Sec. 172. Establishment of panel of constitutional experts.</toc-entry></toc></section><title id="H8159674E7B99460B99A239F4F8A071B2"><enum>I</enum><header>Findings Relating to Election Administration</header><section id="HA3DAA18249D1463F832EFCB35A3EDA5F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>101.</enum><header>Findings Relating to Election Administration</header><subsection id="H80B78B83FD4945EC94DC9CF4AB7BC920"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that constitutional scholar Robert Natelson has done invaluable work with respect to the history and understanding of the Elections Clause.</text></subsection><subsection id="H77B4C42FF36E455389FE79BEB83E3D38" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="HFB9040EBAE1E4B30BA21CDACFE4A65DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Constitution reserves to the States the primary authority to set election legislation and administer elections—the <quote>times, places, and manner of holding of elections</quote>—and Congress’ power in this space is purely secondary to the States’ power and is to be employed only in the direst of circumstances. History, precedent, the Framers’ words, debates concerning ratification, the Supreme Court, and the Constitution itself make it exceedingly clear that Congress’ power over elections is not unfettered.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA205B36A81404FC1BDDA5AD52E62FD48"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Framing Generation grappled with the failure of the Articles of Confederation, which provided for only a weak national government incapable of preserving the Union. Under the Articles, the States had exclusive authority over Federal elections held within their territory; but, given the difficulties the national government had experienced with State cooperation (e.g., the failure of Rhode Island to send delegates to the Confederation Congress), the Federalists, including Alexander Hamilton, were concerned with the possibility that the States, in an effort to destroy the Federal Government, simply might not hold elections or that an emergency, such as an invasion or insurrection, might prevent the operation of a State’s government, leaving the Congress without Members and the Federal Government unable to respond.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFC31BF10E5B42208DB8ADD0D046E91E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Quite plainly, Alexander Hamilton, a leading Federalist and proponent of our Constitution, understood the Elections Clause as serving only as a sort of emergency fail-safe, not as a cudgel used to nationalize our elections process. Writing as Publius to the people of New York, Hamilton further expounds on the correct understanding of the Elections Clause: <quote>T[he] natural order of the subject leads us to consider, in this place, that provision of the Constitution which authorizes the national legislature to regulate, in the last resort, the election of its own members.</quote>. Alexander Hamilton (writing as Publius), Federalist no. 59, Concerning the Power of Congress to Regulate the Election of Members, N.Y. PACKET (Fri., Feb. 22, 1788).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B6C0A997F58475086D12F094365D7EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When questioned at the States’ constitutional ratifying conventions with respect to this provision, the Federalists confirmed this understanding of a constitutionally limited, secondary congressional power under article 1, section 4. (<quote>[C]onvention delegate James McHenry added that the risk to the Federal Government [without a fail-safe provision] might not arise from state malice: An insurrection or rebellion might prevent a state legislature from administering an election.</quote>); (<quote>An occasion may arise when the exercise of this ultimate power of Congress may be necessary . . . if a State should be involved in war, and its legislature could not assemble, (as was the case of South Carolina and occasionally of some other States, during the [Revolutionary] war).</quote>); (<quote>Sir, let it be remembered that this power can only operate in a case of necessity, after the factious or listless disposition of a particular state has rendered an interference essential to the salvation of the general government.</quote>). See Robert G. Natelson, The Original Scope of the Congressional Power to Regulate Elections, 13 U. PA. J. CONST. L. 1, 12–13 (Nov. 2010).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D3C43B70F224042A613559657C94AE2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">John Jay made similar claims in New York. And, as constitutional scholar Robert Natelson notes in his invaluable article, The Original Scope of the Congressional Power to Regulate Elections, <quote>Alexander Contee Hanson, a member of Congress whose pamphlet supporting the Constitution proved popular, stated flatly that Congress would exercise its times, places, and manner authority only in cases of invasion, legislative neglect or obstinate refusal to pass election laws [providing for the election of Members of Congress], or if a state crafted its election laws with a <quote>sinister purpose</quote> or to injure the general government.</quote> Cementing his point, Hanson goes further to decree, <quote>The exercise of this power must at all times be so very invidious, that congress will not venture upon it without some very cogent and substantial reason.</quote>. Alexander Contee Hanson (writing as Astrides), Remarks on the Proposed Plan: 31 January, reprinted in John P. Kaminski, Gaspare J. Saladino, and Richard Leffler (eds.), 3 Commentaries on the Constitution, public and private 18 December 1787 to 31 January 1788 522–26 (1984). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7477193BAF314A039B072A0DEFFE0CC8"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fact, had the alternate view of the Elections Clause been accepted at the time of the Constitution’s drafting—that is, that it offers Congress unfettered power over Federal elections—it is likely that the Constitution would not have been ratified or that an amendment to this language would have been required.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBA8FF02B1F648E7ADA1EB00AFCEE4A6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Indeed, at least seven of the original 13 States—over half and enough to prevent the Constitution from being ratified—expressed specific concerns with the language of the Elections Clause. See 1 Annals of Cong. 799 (1789), Joseph Gales (ed.) (1834). However, <quote>[l]eading Federalists …</quote> assured them <quote>… that, even without amendment, the [Elections] Clause should be construed as limited to emergencies</quote>. Three States, New York, North Carolina, and Rhode Island, specifically made their ratification contingent on this understanding being made express. Ratification of the Constitution by the State of New York (July 26, 1788) (<quote>Under these impressions and declaring that the rights aforesaid cannot be abridged or violated, and the Explanations aforesaid are consistent with the said Constitution, And in confidence that the Amendments which have been proposed to the said Constitution will receive early and mature Consideration: We the said Delegates, in the Name and in [sic] the behalf of the People of the State of New York Do by these presents Assent to and Ratify the said Constitution. In full Confidence . . . that the Congress will not make or alter any Regulation in this State respecting the times places and manner of holding Elections for Senators or Representatives unless the Legislature of this State shall neglect or refuse to make laws or regulations for the purpose, or from any circumstance be incapable of making the same, and that in those cases such power will only be exercised until the Legislature of this State shall make provision in the Premises</quote>); Ratification of the Constitution by the State of North Carolina (Nov. 21, 1789) (<quote>That Congress shall not alter, modify, or interfere in the times, places, or manner of holding elections for senators and representatives, or either of them, except when the legislature of any State shall neglect, refuse or be disabled by invasion or rebellion, to prescribe the same.</quote>); Ratification of the Constitution by the State of Rhode Island (May 29, 1790) (<quote>Under these impressions, and declaring, that the rights aforesaid cannot be abridged or violated, and that the explanations aforesaid, are consistent with the said constitution, and in confidence that the amendments hereafter mentioned, will receive an early and mature consideration, and conformably to the fifth article of said constitution, speedily become a part thereof; We the said delegates, in the name, and in [sic] the behalf of the People, of the State of Rhode-Island and Providence-Plantations, do by these Presents, assent to, and ratify the said Constitution. In full confidence . . . That the Congress will not make or alter any regulation in this State, respecting the times, places and manner of holding elections for senators and representatives, unless the legislature of this State shall neglect, or refuse to make laws or regulations for the purpose, or from any circumstance be incapable of making the same; and that [i]n those cases, such power will only be exercised, until the legislature of this State shall make provision in the Premises[.]</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45EBD4C01D894D61A3722CD554D99CDF"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds that the Framers designed and the ratifying States understood the Elections Clause to serve solely as a protective backstop to ensure the preservation of the Federal Government, not as a font of limitless power for Congress to wrest control of Federal elections from the States. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H974BC7FDA49242FFA89A990353B52E36"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This understanding was also reinforced by debate during the First Congress that convened under the Constitution where Representative Aedanus Burke proposed a constitutional amendment to limit the Times, Places and Manner Clause to emergencies. Although the amendment failed, those on both sides of the Burke amendment debate already understood the Elections Clause to limit Federal elections power to emergencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABB04C3BE0FC434E8A3B53A21B868C0D"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">History clearly shows that even in the first Congress that convened under the Constitution, it was acknowledged and understood through the debates that ensued over the Elections Clause provision that Congress’ control over elections is limited.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC63F9A5D33A040B9B25D1C95607DFADB"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Similarly, proponent Representative Smith of South Carolina also believed the original text of the Elections Clause already limited the Federal Government’s power over Federal elections to emergencies and so thought there would be no harm in supporting an amendment to make that language express. Annals of Congress 801 (1789) Joseph Gales Edition. A Century of Lawmaking for a New Nation: U.S. Congressional Documents and Debates, 1774–1875 (loc.gov). So, even the records of the First Congress reflect a recognition of the emergency nature of congressional power over Federal elections.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA228C54ED1E548C19B0B7A9E8270CC51"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Similarly, the Supreme Court has supported this understanding. In Smiley v. Holm, the Court held that Article 1, Section 4 of the Constitution reserved to the States the primary <quote>… authority to provide a complete code for congressional elections, not only as to times and places, but in relation to notices, registration, supervision of voting, protection of voters, prevention of fraud and corrupt practices, counting of votes, duties of inspectors and canvassers, and making and publication of election returns; in short, to enact the numerous requirements as to procedure and safeguards which experience shows are necessary in order to enforce the fundamental right involved. And these requirements would be nugatory if they did not have appropriate sanctions in the definition of offenses and punishments. All this is comprised in the subject of <quote>times, places and manner of holding elections</quote>, and involves lawmaking in its essential features and most important aspect.</quote>. Smiley v. Holm, 285 U.S. 355, 366 (1932).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46366196E221414688CD61401B7D369E"><enum>(13)</enum><text>This holding is consistent with the understanding of the Elections Clause since the framing of the Constitution. The Smiley Court also held that while Congress maintains the authority to <quote>. . . supplement these State regulations or [to] substitute its own[]</quote>, such authority remains merely <quote>a general supervisory power over the whole subject.</quote>. Id.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40B4626F28564CBB8D9A9AB057F3D7B7"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">More recently, the Court noted in Arizona v. Inter-Tribal Council of Ariz., Inc. that <quote>[t]his grant of congressional power [that is, the fail-safe provision in the Elections Clause] was the Framers’ insurance against the possibility that a State would refuse to provide for the election of representatives to the Federal Congress.</quote>. Arizona v. Inter-Tribal Council of Arizona, Inc., 570 U.S. 1, 7–9 (2013). The Court explained that the Elections Clause <quote>… imposes [upon the States] the duty . . . to prescribe the time, place, and manner of electing Representatives and Senators[.]</quote>. Id. at 8. And, while, as the Court noted, <quote>[t]he power of Congress over the <quote>Times, Places, and Manner</quote> of congressional elections is paramount, and may be exercised at any time, and to any extent which it deems expedient; and so far as it is exercised, and no farther, the regulations effected supersede those of the State which are inconsistent therewith[]</quote>, Id. at 9, the Inter-Tribal Court explained, quoting extensively from the Federalist no. 59, that it was clear that the congressional fail-safe included in the Elections Clause was intended for the sorts of governmental self-preservation discussed here: <quote>[E]very government ought to contain in itself the means of its own preservation[.]</quote>; <quote>[A]n exclusive power of regulating elections for the national government, in the hands of the State legislatures, would leave the existence of the Union entirely at their mercy. They could at any moment annihilate it by neglecting to provide for the choice of persons to administer its affairs.</quote>. Id. at 8.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AE97868FEB549D6828D1697149ABE84"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is clear in every respect that the congressional fail-safe described in the Elections Clause vests purely secondary authority over Federal elections in the Federal legislative branch and that the primary authority rests with the States. Congressional authority is intended to be, and as a matter of constitutional fact is, limited to addressing the worst imaginable issues, such as invasion or other matters that might lead to a State not electing representatives to constitute the two Houses of Congress. Congress’ authority has never extended to the day-to-day authority over the <quote>Times, Places and Manner of Election</quote> that the Constitution clearly reserves to the States. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB958FAB1A2C45C3BBE1F27710D4BB67"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress must act within the bounds of its constitutional authority when enacting legislation concerning the administration of our nation’s elections.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H1C4B868A7D5F48E8A771ACBE13F23D50"><enum>II</enum><header>Voluntary Considerations for State Administration of Federal Elections</header><section id="H8EF7E4E76816441ABFA2346453866B17"><enum>111.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Voluntarily Offered Tools for Election Reforms by States Act</quote> or the <quote>VOTERS Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="H8E476A4A8783409EB9BF760782E4D01B"><enum>112.</enum><header>Election integrity voluntary considerations</header><subsection id="H6E0DF62CA53F413D82A1C180A6AB41B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle C of title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20981">52 U.S.C. 20981 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H850AD78156744900A1A1117D48578AE5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 247 as section 248; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0ACD905B065942549CD4EB9AA9095E02"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 246 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H525E940A419D498E9C0E92DD67FD0914" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HCDB009BDC4D840D4986AFDC84B5D1794"><enum>247.</enum><header>Release of voluntary considerations by Standards Board with respect to election administration</header><subsection id="H71A874211A1746E0A3484999544921A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Standards Board shall draw from experiences in their home jurisdictions and information voluntarily provided by and between States on what has worked and not worked and release voluntary considerations with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9E439789889C4A14848CD8D6AAD5C873"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To consider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In releasing the voluntary considerations under subsection (a), the Standards Board shall examine and consolidate information provided by States and release considerations with respect to each of the following categories:</text><paragraph id="H0AE7840368CA4BB5BDFB60DAB5234477"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The process for the administration of ballots delivered by mail, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8EFCF395342549539532EC93D55767E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deadlines for the return and receipt of such ballots to the appropriate election official;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H474076496B354187BFB0D43E2438E0CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the design of such ballots, including the envelopes used to deliver the ballots;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46F8C3252B09425D8E64F11B256D359D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the process for requesting and tracking the return of such ballots; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDB4D58941F045F396E789F2664A79DD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the processing of such ballots upon receipt by the appropriate election official, including the schedule for counting the ballots and the reporting of the unofficial results of such counting. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAE7B2970EA64B4AA0FC3DA3D4B583A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The signature verification procedures used to verify the identity of voters in an election, which shall include an evaluation of human and machine methods of signature verification, an assessment of the training provided to individuals tasked to carry out such verification procedures, and the proposal of other less subjective methods of confirming the identity of a voter such as requiring the identification number of a valid government-issued photo identification or the last four digits of the voter’s social security number to be provided along with the voter’s signature. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H305998CC9D9846E2AA03465D29408B19"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The processes used to carry out maintenance of the official list of persons registered to vote in each State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDC45243F3BC4B3BB6A0636F9070C831"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Rules and requirements with respect to the access provided to election observers. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C9423A8D98A4084903BD9DCC738FBA1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The processes used to ensure the timely and accurate reporting of the unofficial results of ballot counting in each polling place in a State and the reporting of the unofficial results of such counting. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EB55863C4B3477B8DB3A79CA539BC4F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The methods used to recruit poll workers and designate the location of polling places during a pandemic, natural disaster, or other emergency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2539ED1A9B9E4D918337758809799054"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The education of the public with respect to the certification and testing of voting machines prior to the use of such machines in an election for Federal office, including education with respect to how such machines are tested for accuracy and logic.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE789EB851B5D4B2F87CD3032B9CC2CF9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The processes and procedures used to carry out a post-election audit.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5146B7B189AA4593A301650D051681EC"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The processes and procedures used to ensure a secure chain of custody with respect to ballots and election equipment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE033FFD03C6E4E72B3132ACE309653AD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Release of voluntary considerations</header><paragraph id="H7658947D2C4A4BA9BC6833047B819FBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline for release</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of the ACE Act, the Standards Board shall release voluntary considerations with respect to each of the categories described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A61DECFD85D4EB0AC21C240A43FD1E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transmission and notification requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the date the Standards Board releases voluntary considerations with respect to a category described in subsection (b), the Commission shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5CEDF1127D854AE4A90BC097A1F6FA58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transmit the considerations to the chief State election official of each State and the elected leadership of the legislature of each State, including the elected leadership of any committee of the legislature of a State with jurisdiction with respect to elections;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30C6C4A3FBBC4660A40B92A846D3CBBC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the considerations available on a publicly accessible Government website; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6F3B12F574A4EF5929890F11ABCB4C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notify and transmit the considerations to the chair and ranking minority member of the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking minority member of the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44DB02F96C734858B4B76404EA95DB8D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of requirements payments for implementation of voluntary considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State may use a requirements payment provided under this Act to implement any of the voluntary considerations released under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD39CF72F5E1345AC89BF0E439013D2FB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed—</text><paragraph id="H3B1756796EB747F699EE2960F4949EEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to require compliance with the voluntary considerations released under subsection (a), including as a condition of the receipt of Federal funds; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA7FDB0A52D743E3B57074149B6F9B70"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to treat the lack of compliance with such considerations as a violation of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 or to treat compliance with such considerations as a defense against an alleged violation of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H270BEE441F22498D8CCB50B7F38CF1F7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE94E90AA959E4C07A0B2189C958CFC22"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the item relating to section 247 as relating to section 248; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE605F12537AE4FB5A20DD12903F86327"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 246 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1C03E98D4BDE4C0D8C1CBC9513196B3E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 247. Release of voluntary considerations by Standards Board with respect to election administration.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HC2AE9596D0A746EE94E671AFEA134CA8"><enum>III</enum><header>Requirements to Promote Integrity in Election Administration</header><section id="HCDD104242F174EF09F37802FC11B8BAC"><enum>121.</enum><header>Ensuring only eligible American citizens may participate in Federal elections</header><subsection id="H93AFC387DCB8466BA7CC0D34C7CE509C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Non-Citizens: Outlawed from Voting in Our Trusted Elections Act of 2023</quote> or the <quote>NO VOTE for Non-Citizens Act of 2023</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H56991261A41E4BB48E0B078A16EE341F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings; Sense of Congress</header><paragraph id="H97EAC47D1F3D4426BA9320D4AD470A7F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><subparagraph id="H65D589F57E69462A9865DC6DB4C65AD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every eligible person who wishes to cast a ballot in a Federal election must be permitted to do so according to law, and their ballot must be examined according to law, and, if it meets all lawful requirements, counted.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C1D1E9FE1354DE4BDECC0A35ED770EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has long required States to maintain Federal voter registration lists in a manner that promotes voter confidence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H546199C6F9E94F819E81649F7EB096C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The changes included herein are not intended to be an expansion of Federal power but rather a clarification of State authority.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0BC0A382B47402CA8C926EE692EDEA4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fifteenth Amendment, the Nineteenth Amendment, the Twenty-Fourth Amendment, and the Twenty-Sixth Amendment, among other references, make clear that the Constitution prohibits voting by non-citizens in Federal elections.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD60A969710FE4E458E9195E5A6F57B1B"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has the constitutional authority, including under the aforementioned amendments, to pass statutes preventing non-citizens from voting in Federal elections, and did so with the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2E18A4F69DF4D7795C5EC730573C6DC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress may further exercise its constitutional authority to ensure the Constitution’s prohibition on non-citizen voting in Federal elections is upheld.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23140BFB3D9F4338B5D2835CF5F1C621"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since the Constitution prohibits non-citizens from voting in Federal elections, such ineligible persons must not be permitted to be placed on Federal voter registration lists.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B1815B96C754A07B1385B757BAC4214"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improper placement of an ineligible non-citizen on a Federal voter registration list leads to—</text><clause id="HBC2FCF16285C40FDB0E8B5B8B181855D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>confusion on the part of the ineligible person with respect to their ineligibility to cast a ballot; and</text></clause><clause id="HFF43713C09754E0A8B86BECDCC8CE65A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an increased likelihood that human error will permit ineligible persons to cast ballots in Federal elections.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H008669E7F0924ACAA173690D82B02D9C"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State officials have confirmed that poorly maintained voter registration lists lead to ineligible persons casting ballots in Federal elections.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H219DC9211F38486B986FF69208934CF7"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A former Broward County, Florida, elections supervisor has confirmed that ineligible non-voters were able to cast ballots in previous elections and that she was not able to locate as many as 2,040 ballots during the 2018 midterm recount.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5420B8EAB25A4B0C886370AE3A2B7065"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This clarification of State authority to maintain Federal voter registration lists to ensure non-citizens are not included on such lists will promote voter confidence in election processes and outcomes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5A7E7DDD1EF4FDE9D266D4750F4EA32"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has the authority to ensure that no Federal elections funding is used to support States that permit non-citizens to cast ballots in any election.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF2DA8392F9849978AD2A4FD8C9BF285"><enum>(M)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal courts and executive agencies have much of the information States may need to maintain their Federal voter registration lists, and those entities should make that information accessible to State election authorities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA36FE668D9394146AB2DE2FB639BDEDB"><enum>(N)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is important to clarify the penalty for any violation of law that allows a non-citizen to cast a ballot in a Federal election.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B3CA131A8A24970A37DA7B0BF6FF32F"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To protect the confidence of voters in Federal elections, it is important to implement the policy described herein.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE496699936F643FAB818D29B22DBA442"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="H5EEB05BFA5DD4A36801F2ED6ACF08725"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">many States have not adequately met the requirements concerning the removal of ineligible persons from State voter registration rolls pursuant to section 8 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507</external-xref>) and should strive to audit and update their voter registration rolls on a routine basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF3E91804F4B4A62A131E3C716BC769F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>allowing non-citizens to cast ballots in American elections weakens our electoral system and the value of citizenship and sows distrust in our elections system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DBC4F117D074AA0B4522776030AC57C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">even if a State has the sovereign authority, no State should permit non-citizens to cast ballots in State or local elections;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA41C4182CBF43F7915A7DF216C7F3B1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">States should use all information available to them to maintain Federal voter registration lists and should inform Congress if such data is insufficient; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D1622DB0CC94B72B8053372707CE96E"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress may take further action in the future to address this problem.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H77C3A46951B147D7AB1F78054EA3266D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clarifying authority of States To remove noncitizens from voting rolls</header><paragraph id="H825BA27D2F394B4899298FF1354AA2BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority under regular removal programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(a)(4) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H65E1193E1ACB42659E7B67B3BD39D340"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99F8674CEED649CAB97EDBD3F6D61DC3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (B) as subparagraph (C); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEBB8D80286F4D7785B57DFFA2A5C17F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3F2CECCD23EA4A92A0C55A444444CE2D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H0111B0A3889645A69F8AC820443480C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the registrant’s status as a noncitizen of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H47ADD4F055B8460495CA9701C9E023CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to ongoing removal</header><text>Section 8(c)(2)(B)(i) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(c)(2)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>(4)(A)</quote> and inserting <quote>(4)(A) or (B)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B76648835464BD9936C8174B7F1C12F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirement To maintain separate State voter registration list for noncitizens</header><text>Section 8(a) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H6B9506BE575644B59FDD3F1A0688DDF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H317548D313E44B5FBE7085CDBC724897"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE01577F7E2AC4F74A60CF61E25A3AF48"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HECF8F5BD1D9E41EF89DA096715A04111" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H20E758AD0C764B45B3F44A661EECC882"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a State that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or any local jurisdiction of the State, ensure that the name of any registrant who is not a citizen of the United States is maintained on a voter registration list that is separate from the official list of eligible voters with respect to registrants who are citizens of the United States. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7937F6DBA5094556916E32A48BBFA011"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirements for ballots for State or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 301(a)(1) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H176DFB05C2064A74AA80DE2EA57318F3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="HB3A106C785454D80B4B0E30D5FC7B304"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction, the ballot used for the casting of votes by a noncitizen in such State or local jurisdiction may only include the candidates for the elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction for which the noncitizen is permitted to vote.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H70EE15A2F1764F3281190CCDC38AA368" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reduction in payments for election administration to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header><paragraph id="HA7E762F74FCD45068F4964CA95FAB9BF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title IX of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21141">52 U.S.C. 21141 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H89CB0E472F774963BDDC7E1E82B70E23" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H64C6C921E3344D639FCC7322323D1E33"><enum>907.</enum><header>Reduction in payments to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting</header><subsection id="H8E912052843A4CC7BD5A448CADD292F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the amount of a payment under this Act to any State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction shall be reduced by 30 percent. </text></subsection><subsection id="H53EB5C86E41F4936AAFDEB88A05D7C6C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of funds for certain election administration activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds may be used to implement the requirements of section 8(a)(7) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(a)(7)</external-xref>) (as added by section 121(d) of the American Confidence in Elections Act) or section 301(a)(1)(D) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081(a)(1)(D)</external-xref>) (as added by section 121(e) of the American Confidence in Elections Act) in a State or local jurisdiction that allows individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in elections for public office in the State or local jurisdiction.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C734D98533744648FE22601616352F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBD365D2EB2CD4A1C922D88976E64BC81" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 907. Reduction in payments to States or local jurisdictions that allow noncitizen voting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E641890C76B4862B6BC1F461B72427F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Promoting provision of information by Federal entities</header><paragraph id="H936B6ED168D84430BD02FD3F5FE3B43C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each entity of the Federal Government which maintains information which is relevant to the status of an individual as a registered voter in elections for Federal office in a State shall, upon the request of an election official of the State, provide that information to the election official.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E8E30028F4F47CE85E764E27FD42345"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Policies and procedures</header><text>Consistent with section 3506(g) of title 44, United States Code, an entity of the Federal Government shall carry out this subsection in accordance with policies and procedures which will ensure that the information is provided securely, accurately, and in a timely basis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A6E3593FA564BF188A204DE3ACCFFE0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to coverage under Privacy Act</header><text>Section 552a(b) of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HB3B33F546D8D46DCA9E40C3901320821"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of paragraph (11);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA30A689609F4D09807B01C442EC7EFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (12) and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AD972591AEB42CDAA906E53DDD141B2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HD4C5A64279EA4B06923DD72A119F57D6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HAADC8AFE970D4245A8ED51375A5F5998"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to an election official of a State in accordance with section 121(h) of the American Confidence in Elections Act.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF5AD8C66008B4BF6A396579B5E5A7F91"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Ensuring provision of information to State election officials on individuals recused from jury service on grounds of noncitizenship</header><paragraph id="H8F0B18E69AC543DFAF20A77045879171"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement described</header><text>If a United States district court recuses an individual from serving on a jury on the grounds that the individual is not a citizen of the United States, the court shall transmit a notice of the individual’s recusal—</text><subparagraph id="H9BFA5138303E48C88034310C74FFADA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the chief State election official of the State in which the individual resides; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4A1D207AC8144E49693C92E1A5A050F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE581EDA1097548CAB0E0F37ED1E722AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H1F27F6D0FF4546B0B77905ABFD30A063"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <quote>chief State election official</quote> of a State is the individual designated by the State under section 10 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20509">52 U.S.C. 20509</external-xref>) to be responsible for coordination of the State’s responsibilities under such Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D56B936B9604BD2AE22179E37273F5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5C02C12E27449A3B331DCC88384BE2E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Prohibition on voting by noncitizens in Federal elections</header><paragraph id="HE8D22A0CD2CF4EC6B95B5EF220AF5CC8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 12 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20511">52 U.S.C. 20511</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HF2557641B0D04E8EA4AE5DF317E06A75" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A person</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In general.—</header-in-text>A person</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AB356071ACA4D67A1CF74144C2AEE0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC0BDDFE81DE042B5BB564CB802208DB3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H38F9C091D0ED4A72A9126716AB4D62F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on voting by aliens</header><paragraph id="H83E85FE6ECFA4B76B683677048DF9604"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any alien to vote in any election in violation of section 611 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65C3DEAA33664266B7051E79C933A4D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who violates this subsection shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned not more than 1 year, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6603467C28554FD289D1C672ADCD2369"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection and the amendments made by this subsection shall apply with respect to elections held on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB90590EE1E9642528C8C1257BBA5A9CC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>122.</enum><header>State reporting requirements with respect to voter list maintenance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC9DF6247F1A4411FBAE0B0A1395D1421"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (i), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H79E3224AF0F5423AB15AADB811462739" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HFE5BAF82EEE247EDB8F3C0B2A22EAD26" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The records maintained pursuant to paragraph (1) shall include lists of the names and addresses of all registrants in a State who were inactive according to the criteria described in subsection (d)(1)(B) and the length of time each such registrant has been inactive according to such criteria.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CAA392BC2D74901B57ADB767CB8B41A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (j) as subsection (k); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFC8D7A3E96547D19407414832B3973A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (i) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H076686B5F4164E8CA07CE70E599CBF3F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H646669F869E242B3AA22796E950F1759"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 30 of each odd-numbered year, each State shall submit to the Election Assistance Commission a report that includes, with respect to such State during the preceding 2-year period, the total number of—</text><paragraph id="H5FC443E940BD4A92A90082CACD93E978"><enum>(1)</enum><text>registrants who were inactive according to the criteria described in subsection (d)(1)(B) and the length of time each such registrant has been inactive according to such criteria;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18BBEC1E31CF47EA89362A257E3ADC9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">registrants who voted in at least one of the prior 2 consecutive general elections for Federal office;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E390586D0B14728B8A3C8E63FCC5329"><enum>(3)</enum><text>registrants removed from the list of official voters in the State pursuant to subsection (d)(1)(B);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD56316BA4F54E90A7A061B9C15374DB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notices sent to registrants pursuant to subsection (d)(2); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC79143BD90E249E2A24E1A391B02E4BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>registrants who received a notice described in paragraph (4) who responded to such notice. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H53163EF7DE5E41F7864B62C815F1B622" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>123.</enum><header>Contents of State mail voter registration form</header><subsection id="H6E8D7DAEBAC54B0BB6566F08642E27FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>State Instruction Inclusion Act</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCCD0A8A5D58D48EDAB83B53307E36987"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6(a) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20505">52 U.S.C. 20505(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H37DCFF165EB34205BD0E188F41D0EE69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, except that a State may, in addition to the criteria stated in section 9(b), require that an applicant provide proof that the applicant is a citizen of the United States</quote> after <quote>elections for Federal office</quote>; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2FD65C690D545B7B641293EF12F36E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>and such form may include a requirement that the applicant provide proof that the applicant is a citizen of the United States</quote> after <quote>elections for Federal office</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HAD015A425F7C445D92F5ECDC3FA50D60"><enum>124.</enum><header>Provision of photographic citizen voter identification tools for State use</header><subsection id="H74B7A0FC3D6340E0A2B66B889FF111FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Citizen Vote Protection Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD74E06AEDA504291AD06B230E5C43AE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings; Sense of Congress</header><paragraph id="H095795B07A604BC69ABEA172BC4398BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><subparagraph id="H89D3FFB87EB34AD5AE2888D347B5776E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Photo voter identification programs established by the States should be administered without unlawful discrimination and with an eye toward balancing appropriate access to the ballot box with election integrity and voter confidence goals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H791916B42F2942DC96A4CA08899D3335"><enum>(B)</enum><text>As confirmed by the bipartisan Commission on Federal Election Reform (commonly known as the Carter-Baker Commission), <quote>[v]oters in nearly 100 democracies use a photo identification card without fear of infringement of their rights</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD3A9ACD0F2744B0924023DAEC33128E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>As confirmed by the Carter-Baker Commission, “[t]he right to vote is a vital component of U.S. citizenship and all States should use their best efforts to obtain proof of citizenship before registering voters.”.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88E22511DEB64B3A82AD0755004F9566"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Carter-Baker Commission was correct in its 2005 report when it recommended that the REAL ID Act be <quote>modestly adapted for voting purposes to indicate on the front or back whether the individual is a U.S. citizen.</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H697D3560F4EE482081202BACA9563974"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress acknowledges the important work completed by the Carter-Baker Commission and, by amending the REAL ID Act, resolves the concerns in the Commission’s report that <quote>[t]he REAL ID Act does not require that the card indicates citizenship, but that would need to be done if the card is to be used for voting purposes</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7F8B06E6F8040CCA46A9A530D2F6E27"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Photographic voter identification is important for ensuring voter confidence in election processes and outcomes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H706BB7ECEC0143C7BB35BDFE362D373D"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Requiring photographic voter identification is well within States’ constitutional competence, including pursuant to the Qualifications Clause of the Constitution of the United States (article I, section 2, clause 2), the Presidential Electors Clause of the Constitution (article II, section 1, clause 2), and the Seventeenth Amendment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2F6515710A04E10A8A47E64023E0028"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fifteenth Amendment, the Nineteenth Amendment, the Twenty-Fourth Amendment, and the Twenty-Sixth Amendment, among other references, make clear that the Constitution prohibits voting by non-citizens in Federal elections.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83D9349DDA974082BE91565E86450B48"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress has the constitutional authority, including under the aforementioned amendments, to pass statutes preventing non-citizens from voting in Federal elections, and did so with the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FA1054122EB45AE974C967EFEA367C7"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress may further exercise its constitutional authority to ensure the Constitution’s prohibition on non-citizen voting in Federal elections is upheld.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H74451A0CF64444DAAAE86A3542361AF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the States should implement the substance of the recommendation of the Carter-Baker Commission that, <quote>[t]o ensure that persons presenting themselves at the polling place are the ones on the registration list, the Commission recommends that states [encourage] voters to use the REAL ID card, which was mandated in a law signed by the President in May 2005</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27F1BE8574B64457ADABD1C3AFCDD0F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>REAL ID Act Amendment</header><paragraph id="HD6A611F5116B431CB54A8F819BFB5BE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202(b) of the Real ID Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/30301">49 U.S.C. 30301</external-xref> note) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE4E8EC83D0EF4B65896DA90A6C5EE00A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H98199540882D41B3B2FE52BFF9535AD4"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the person is a citizen of the United States, an indication of that citizenship, except that no other information may be included with respect to the immigration status of the person.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7893892F0EE645699716F04793721E42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this subsection shall be effective January 1, 2026, and shall apply with respect to any driver’s license or identification card issued by a State on and after such date.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H624608981B444B8488CB9B3A74D626FE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section or in any amendment made by this section may be construed to establish or mandate the use of a national identification card or to authorize any office of the executive branch to establish or mandate the use of a national identification card.</text></subsection></section><section id="H12658F14CF674CA4A4F60B88C939B86A"><enum>125.</enum><header>Confirming access for Congressional election observers</header><subsection id="HBBA91D6F519B4529AC1CA217B93D2E9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Confirmation of Congressional Observer Access Act of 2023</quote> or the <quote>COCOA Act of 2023</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H97066812EB3547B0871240C42596CA0D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings relating to Congressional election observers</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HED2BAFB4730C49FAA0D4687F49CA05B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Constitution delegates to each of House of the Congress the authority to “be the Judge of the Elections, Returns and Qualifications of its own Members”.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6E46A30491A4D1AA576CE0AA2F9C652"><enum>(2)</enum><text>While, in general, Congress shall respect the determination of State authorities with respect to the election of members to each House, each House of Congress serves as the final arbiter over any contest to the seating of any putative Member-elect or Senator-elect.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46BFBDDB64954F648295ABF13871E22B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>These election contest procedures are contained in the precedents of each House of Congress. Further, for the House of Representatives the procedures exist under the Federal Contested Elections Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB095FFF0EAF142129B58DC242BC1A557"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the post-Civil War modern era, more than 100 election contests have been filed with the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D5ECE1E1E854D0DB1AA6CCC96F60B55"><enum>(5)</enum><text>For decades, Congress has appointed and sent out official congressional observers to watch the administration of congressional elections in the States and territories.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H775E6A6E8E5B42038AB207BCF437CE82"><enum>(6)</enum><text>These observers serve to permit Congress to develop its own factual record in preparation for eventual contests and for other reasons.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02E551D0978B4795B03F4196A60809E7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>This section and the amendments made by this section do not establish any new authorities or procedures but are provided simply to permit a convenient statutory reference for existing Congressional authority and activity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H14113CAFC4E54752A831D2D3B410DEA3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Confirming requirement that States provide access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H37482E6827A343B1B3D207656EF87010"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F5A554AC825491F8FDB10F15385BF9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDFAFC2342DE74F7ABD89FD0D273427AF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H14F7448E524A4329A0D9A93AE3A603B8"><enum>304.</enum><header>Confirming access for Congressional election observers</header><subsection id="H9F4DB318D525429C8C6F86BBC713451F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Finding of Constitutional authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds that it has the authority to require that States allow access to designated Congressional election observers to observe the election administration procedures in an election for Federal office because the authority granted to Congress under article I, section 5 of the Constitution of the United States gives each House of Congress the power to be the judge of the elections, returns and qualifications of its own Members.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE691E31F28904BB4BFB25D316ED1EE35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requiring States To provide access</header><text>A State shall provide each individual who is a designated Congressional election observer for an election with full access to clearly observe all of the elements of the administration procedures with respect to such election, including but not limited to in all areas of polling places and other facilities where ballots in the election are processed, tabulated, cast, canvassed, and certified, in all areas where voter registration activities occur before such election, and in any other such place where election administration procedures to prepare for the election or carry out any post-election recounts take place. No designated Congressional election observer may handle ballots, elections equipment (voting or non-voting), advocate for a position or candidate, take any action to reduce ballot secrecy, or otherwise interfere with the elections administration process.</text></subsection><subsection id="H42FBC98FC58046B2A8EB73ECC121E07A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Designated Congressional election observer described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, a <quote>designated Congressional election observer</quote> is an individual who is designated in writing by the chair or ranking minority member of the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives or the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate, or the successor committee in either House of Congress to gather information with respect to an election, including in the event that the election is contested in the House of Representatives or the Senate and for other purposes permitted by article 1, section 5 of the Constitution of the United States.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06AFF81F39594C5CBE4D8D1F52DDA8C0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HADD62505C18F44988488D9477F3CAA11"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5D5A4D4E79B84D44A53D67351358D20D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8262178C00464F24ACFC5E9041187A2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0D7AA64856034EC1B0F01C357873BB16" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Confirming access for Congressional election observers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC8018D04EC694CE7A1C6641D5C658AA6"><enum>126.</enum><header>Use of requirements payments for post-election audits</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 251(b)(1) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21001">52 U.S.C. 21001(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including to conduct and publish an audit of the effectiveness and accuracy of the voting systems, election procedures, and outcomes used to carry out an election for Federal office in the State and the performance of the State and local election officials who carried out the election</quote> after <quote>requirements of title III</quote>. </text></section><section id="HDBA34F69365C4674B0004E75D7F36546"><enum>127.</enum><header>Certain tax benefits and simplification with respect to election workers</header><subsection id="H920DC06D291F47739699DB87BFA65E6E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Election Worker Employer Participation Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0087A9DB57B54870AC75E33B8A4011C6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exclusion from gross income for certain election worker compensation</header><paragraph id="H8E3E980BA95148C2B417EF382882CE04"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part III of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after section 139H the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9213A923706B4038B331E339A63EB592" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H1DD9776AF7BA4D30970DE93679A81A12"><enum>139I.</enum><header>Certain compensation of election workers</header><subsection id="HC94126FE2B624929A5D563D5C2D374A8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Gross income shall not include qualified election worker compensation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H06C25A8797864A86B4C0421B3990D81A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The amount excludible from gross income under subsection (a) with respect to any taxpayer for any taxable year shall not exceed the dollar amount in effect under section 3121(b)(7)(F)(iv) for the calendar year in which such taxable year begins.</text></subsection><subsection id="H39EDC6B7AA014FB68680FBBD553433EE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualified election worker compensation</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>qualified election worker compensation</term> means amounts otherwise includible in gross income which are paid by a State, political subdivision of a State, or any instrumentality of a State or any political subdivision thereof, for the service of an individual as an election official or election worker (within the meaning of section 3121(b)(7)(F)(iv)). </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0150721212C4A47ABF4A9C41AB2AD04"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for part III of subchapter B of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 139H the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H930A633483CA47FC9D4EF4814D0F3CE6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H9213A923706B4038B331E339A63EB592" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H1DD9776AF7BA4D30970DE93679A81A12" level="section">Sec. 139I. Certain compensation of election workers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2637705FA4141EB9BE0A16E4ECA3052"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Information reporting not required by reason of certain amounts excludible from gross income</header><text>Section 6041 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFEA537CC22AC4C90B62C720238A80A4B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HEA90DA212C784CD0B3DFAA41FD521CA5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Treatment of certain excludible compensation of election workers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any payment by a State, political subdivision of a State, or any instrumentality of a State or any political subdivision thereof, for the service of an individual as an election official or election worker (within the meaning of section 3121(b)(7)(F)(iv)), the determination of whether the $600 threshold described in subsection (a) has been met with respect to such individual shall be determined by not taking into account—</text><paragraph id="H8210B40E931C4775B8C123C537B6DCB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any such payment which is qualified election worker compensation (as defined in section 139I(c)) which does not exceed the limitation described in section 139I(b), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C7764EE09984B1883C4C822A19D9766"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any such payment which is excludible from the gross income of such individual under section 127.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H121C2C653CE142A5A1884C666300DB2F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply to payments made after December 31, 2023, in taxable years ending after such date.</text></subsection></section><section id="HED40D54708F64E8185A8D8B765B5653A"><enum>128.</enum><header>Voluntary guidelines with respect to nonvoting election technology</header><subsection id="HC59B8F2234D34298946A42849C3BDF3F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Protect American Voters Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HDD02951FA7E54218A5C61CCFE901D4CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Election Assistance Commission</header><paragraph id="H2A3F397350C34CCDBD95A1D1944B1E5F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adoption of guidelines</header><text>Title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20921">52 U.S.C. 20921 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subtitle:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6D4F3155908649B8B3F0A6AC59DD0CD5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subtitle id="HC134556ECAE247269AD975686B38EBB7"><enum>E</enum><header>Voluntary Guidelines for Use of Nonvoting Election Technology</header><section id="H88B0AACAE77A443A9B2ACA855FA3B7BB"><enum>298.</enum><header>Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Commission</header><subsection id="HD40D6B60CB904109BC15EEF1A1636C48"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Adoption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall adopt voluntary guidelines for election officials on the use of nonvoting election technology, taking into account the recommendations of the Standards Board and the Local Leadership Council of the Commission under section 298A.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA9AB267BEA914052934CEA83CA213D03"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Commission shall review the guidelines adopted under this subtitle not less frequently than once every 4 years, and may adopt revisions to the guidelines as it considers appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9365D89BDABC4D4A9541BC3CEF75ACB9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Process for adoption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The adoption of the voluntary guidelines under this subtitle shall be carried out by the Commission in a manner that provides for each of the following:</text><paragraph id="H4EF2D78DFD264DC49E52C5FD13ABB0F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Publication of notice of the proposed guidelines in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE89D5414AB64CBFB8D9A004D026205B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An opportunity for public comment on the proposed guidelines.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H390B4D8D2D4944A4B97345095AEA2A4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An opportunity for a public hearing on the record.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAE2BC9D716F4A89AD0910F951747A99"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Publication of the final recommendations in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H36E03D4FAFE246A1A55F94EE52F1E253"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadline for initial set of guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall adopt the initial set of voluntary guidelines under this section not later than December 31, 2025.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5E17918249844110AD37833AD659DB8C"><enum>298A.</enum><header>Role of Standards Board and Local Leadership Council</header><subsection id="H4F43F3285B3C4A6FB9FEC6D5249A7AC1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Standards Board and the Local Leadership Council of the Commission shall assist the Commission in the adoption of voluntary guidelines under section 298, including by providing the Commission with recommendations on appropriate standards for the use of nonvoting election technology, including standards to ensure the security and accuracy, and promote the usability, of such technology, and by conducting a review of existing State programs with respect to the testing of nonvoting election technology.</text></subsection><subsection id="H90F96CCB9BA34CCF836FFF2879A395EB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sources of assistance</header><paragraph id="HCDE44C1DE7E14B80BF4AAB837E4BCAF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Certain members of Technical Guidelines Development Committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following members of the Technical Guidelines Development Committee under section 221 shall assist the Standards Board and the Local Leadership Council in carrying out their duties under this section:</text><subparagraph id="HEAF002020D544BBF8715401FC6713079"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD82413152F6741F5B368EE24AF96A118"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The representative of the American National Standards Institute.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA215AEABD7D4D9682ECB522C0EF7911"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The representative of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85F20517683F4C31B6BF8F8524096B35"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 4 members of the Technical Guidelines Development Committee appointed under subsection (c)(1)(E) of such section as the other individuals with technical and scientific expertise relating to voting systems and voting equipment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36644C0169A45AFA0C7A785325CDFBA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Detailee from CISA</header><text>The Executive Board of the Standards Board may request the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security to provide a detailee to assist the Standards Board in carrying out its duties under this section, so long as such detailee has no involvement in the drafting of any of the voluntary guidelines.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HBE4C9EBF54A343F59752F53DCA786B64"><enum>298B.</enum><header>Use of payments to obtain or upgrade technology</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State may use funds provided under any law for activities to improve the administration of elections for Federal office, including to enhance election technology and make election security improvements, to obtain nonvoting election technology which is in compliance with the voluntary guidelines adopted under section 298 or to upgrade nonvoting election technology so that the technology is in compliance with such guidelines, and may, notwithstanding any other provision of law, use any unobligated grant funding provided to the State by the Election Assistance Commission from amounts appropriated under the heading <quote>Independent Agencies—Election Assistance Commission—Election Security Grants</quote> in title V of division C of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/93">Public Law 116–93</external-xref>) for the purposes of enhancing election technology and making election security improvements until December 31, 2024.</text></section><section id="HF36B10562DCF4EF59BD2DDD9E8F5B67C"><enum>298C.</enum><header>Nonvoting election technology defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subtitle, the term <term>nonvoting election technology</term> means technology used in the administration of elections for Federal office which is not used directly in the casting, counting, tabulating, or collecting of ballots or votes, including each of the following:</text><paragraph id="HFD641E4E148A427FABE23ADCCEF4CF29"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Electronic pollbooks or other systems used to check in voters at a polling place or verify a voter’s identification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65EFDF8EA3844D46B1618E3A21BE2F46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Election result reporting systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3277F6812594DB3A1A360FB70CF64DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Electronic ballot delivery systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9C40AFBD2EE49509ACA1A114FCD3AE4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Online voter registration systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H713457AFFF5045969B2ED0D56D97A66D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Polling place location search systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18D1894334C14C4EB21E9FECACB97BB5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Sample ballot portals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1E91655E70541D39B4640B5B8CA69C1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Signature systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F329C568F234054962B92B09FC3DF1B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Such other technology as may be recommended for treatment as nonvoting election technology as the Standards Board may recommend.</text></paragraph></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H4938239CC1AC45D795840468A99C8C82"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the items relating to title II the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCE9A16880F644FD9BA97F71657FEF8C0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="subtitle">Subtitle E—Voluntary Guidelines for Use of Nonvoting Election Technology </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298. Adoption of voluntary guidelines by Commission. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298A. Role of Standards Board and Local Leadership Council. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298B. Use of payments to obtain or upgrade technology.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 298C. Nonvoting election technology defined.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CAA778C9A0A496295BA38BBC4168DDC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of technology used in most recent election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any nonvoting election technology, as defined in section 298C of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (as added by subsection (a)(1)), which a State used in the most recent election for Federal office held in the State prior to the date of the enactment of this Act shall be deemed to be in compliance with the voluntary guidelines on the use of such technology which are adopted by the Election Assistance Commission under section 298 of such Act (as added by subsection (a)(1)).</text></subsection></section><section id="HE3AB0012D5744FCC8D9E63646A7F4DD8" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>129.</enum><header>Status reports by National Institute of Standards and Technology</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 231 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20971">52 U.S.C. 20971</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6ECB0EC71ACC4065B13050E27554940D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HAD67E6741E2F4879A19B64DE8711E8A6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Status reports by National Institute of Standards and Technology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the end of each fiscal year (beginning with 2023), the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall submit to Congress a status report describing—</text><paragraph id="H5E45E6F5CF5842F1A170B5D317116F3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the extent to which the Director carried out the Director’s responsibilities under this Act during the fiscal year, including the responsibilities imposed under this section and the responsibilities imposed with respect to the Technical Guidelines Development Committee under section 222, together with the Director’s best estimate of when the Director will completely carry out any responsibility which was not carried out completely during the fiscal year; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1E9ADF9CCF148268194D3321B326626"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which the Director carried out any projects requested by the Commission during the fiscal year, together with the Director’s best estimate of when the Director will complete any such project which the Director did not complete during the fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H386E189CCA274552971C61F7F841F8D6"><enum>130.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to election mail</header><subsection id="HE46AB4771A6D4E978464C3D928971787"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Election Integrity Mail Reform Act of 2023</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H501C944DCB71489892386221AD62A10F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prioritizing election mail</header><text>Title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding after chapter 36 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H01DD46230C424A7782910549EF586D80" display-inline="no-display-inline"><chapter id="HA040C36263384CDEBF1B5947B3275E8E"><enum>37</enum><header>Election and Political Mail</header><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. </toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" idref="H57DA5A0082284B1FB3A9E356864665FB" level="section">3701. Prioritization of processing and delivery of election mail.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3702. Use of nonprofit permit for cooperative mailings.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3703. Marking or notice on election mail.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">3704. Application to Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act.</toc-entry></toc><section id="H84AAFF08D07640B59574013C48945E26"><enum>3701.</enum><header>Prioritization of processing and delivery of election mail</header><subsection id="H3CEB2E5F7F864AD98900993B8F42FE16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service shall give priority to the processing and delivery of election mail. In carrying out this subsection, the Postal Service shall at a minimum—</text><paragraph id="H19BB3658E46D41F480AD53C410674F6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>deliver any election mail regardless of the amount of postage paid;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60CCEC803FC64D0FA66D023671AA6FFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall, to the greatest extent practicable, process and clear election mail from any postal facility each day; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36D7CDB236904715A9DE7AECFEE42424"><enum>(3)</enum><text>carry and deliver election mail expeditiously.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDFEBAC76CA214E49849F4A3A533C4C7F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Election mail with insufficient postage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (a)(1), the Postal Service shall process and deliver election mail with insufficient postage in the same manner as election mail with sufficient postage, but may collect insufficient postage after delivery of any election mail with insufficient postage.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF05394A185E43BFA7DB4B43BCB6EB07"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Underfunded or overdrawn accounts</header><text>The Postal Service shall process and deliver election mail, under the standards in place under subsection (a), sent from a customer using an account registered with the Postal Service (including a corporate account or an advance deposit account) even if such account is underfunded or overdrawn. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit or otherwise prevent the Postal Service from seeking reimbursement from any person regarding unpaid postage.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0756BA7BC3594835956931C0879D1B7A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Election mail defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this chapter, the term <term>election mail</term> means any item mailed to or from an individual for purposes of the individual’s participation in an election for public office, including balloting materials, voter registration cards, absentee ballot applications, polling place notification and photographic voter identification materials.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4E74CB8A578D44C8A1E76B9492C30C58" commented="no"><enum>3702.</enum><header>Use of nonprofit permit for cooperative mailings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other law, rule, or regulation, a national, State, or local committee of a political party (as defined under the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971) which is eligible to mail at the nonprofit rate may conduct a cooperative mailing at that nonprofit rate with a candidate, a candidate’s committee, or another committee of a political party, and may seek reimbursement from such a candidate, candidate’s committee, or committee of a political party for the costs of such mailing.</text></section><section id="H8BDB19B7479D4172A8627E4EA35DF0E9"><enum>3703.</enum><header>Marking or notice on election mail</header><subsection id="HC89F10BD91684BA6B80DFB289E442754" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of assisting election officials in processing election mail, the Postal Service shall place a marking or notice indicating that a piece of mail is election mail. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6269971EAE324543AB5B019D70F113DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Postal Service may determine the appropriate manner in which subsection (a) is carried out, but at a minimum such marking or notice shall—</text><paragraph id="H5F498860A9884C869C54B637054CECFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be placed, as soon as practicable, at the time the election mail is received by the Postal Service, in a conspicuous and legible type or in a common machine-readable technology on the envelope or other cover in which the election mail is mailed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E696857AC8B4CF39DA406F1D2302632"><enum>(2)</enum><text>clearly demonstrate the date and time that such marking or noticed was so placed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD360A15D1344F5A98ABD0DB7666AF4C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed as requiring any change to the processes and procedures used by the Postal Service with respect to Postal Service barcodes on envelopes carried or delivered by the Postal Service. </text></subsection></section><section id="H692D91A7C36D408FA82994673C033942"><enum>3704.</enum><header>Application to Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This chapter shall not apply to balloting materials under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act and nothing in this chapter shall be construed to alter or otherwise affect the operation of such Act or section 3406 of this title.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H411284C448014C4AA94BCB30C80E3F25" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Postmarking stamps</header><text>Section 503 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H64160771ABE44AEB9390287DFDCCF794"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Whoever forges</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC"><enum-in-header>(a)</enum-in-header></header-in-text> Whoever forges</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9251459105B34F12AFCA0C974FAC7401"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or such impression thereof,</quote> and all that follows and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H96C46D61E86547A480499E2EAB0B4B51" display-inline="no-display-inline"><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="section">or such impression thereof—</quoted-block-continuation-text><paragraph id="H3F553844987342CE979F5DE14B6B33FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> shall be fined under this title or imprisoned not more than five years, or both; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E1FADF833214CEEAEB44DA41055D534"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the impression from a postmarking stamp or impression thereof forged, counterfeited, used, sold, or possessed in violation of this section is applied to a mailed ballot for an election for Federal, State, or local office, shall be fined under this title or imprisoned not more than 10 years, or both.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E0F3E365F5E45AD8A5A233DAD64FC89"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H43A7E54A946346BAB27DB8D0A9E4E5B6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H255835AF58184BF69095947C9313BCA7"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Whoever, with the intent to falsify the date on which a postmark was applied, applies to a mailed ballot described in subsection (a)(2) a genuine postmark that bears a date other than the date on which such postmark was applied, shall be subject to the penalties set forth in such subsection.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H293DE62383CA44E18055FFC12C52F086" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>131.</enum><header>Clarification of right of State to appeal decisions through duly authorized representative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1254 of title 28, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2DEB637A42B347B4B45768E69A67E957"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting a period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72BB1F34E8CD40A99AA3DBD7070FD181"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD2D6B39BCE0A48B79F88EA62772FCD6F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3297FC69A0224756BB976732E541F8F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">By appeal by a party (including the State as represented by any agent authorized as a party under State law) relying on a State statute held by a court of appeals to be invalid as repugnant to the Constitution, treaties or laws of the United States, but such appeal shall preclude review by writ of certiorari at the instance of such appellant, and the review on appeal shall be restricted to the Federal questions presented.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H11F30F13093A49B8B7C4FBBDDCB05258"><enum>132.</enum><header>Federal agency involvement in voter registration activities</header><subsection id="H414977C36A284B43BA35ABE7E0AAF8BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Free and Fair Elections Act</short-title> of 2023</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8C75108229864521BA0405451E5A0718"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification of Federal agency involvement in voter registration activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 14019 (86 Fed. Reg. 13623; relating to promoting access to voting) shall have no force or effect to the extent that it is inconsistent with section 7 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20506">52 U.S.C. 20506</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4C8B12A24AB4B16827155D9B456958E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibiting promotion of voter registration by agencies</header><paragraph id="H671B8D9A35BF46DA8E5EFFC303492E90"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agreements with nongovernmental organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds made available for the salaries and expenses of an agency may be used to solicit or enter into an agreement with a nongovernmental organization to conduct voter registration or voter mobilization activities, including registering voters or providing any person with voter registration materials, absentee or vote-by-mail ballot applications, voting instructions, or candidate-related information, on the property or website of the agency. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBA1E5E496A640A5B4FBBF9C2CB321BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities under Executive Order 14019</header><subparagraph id="H0A7EAFBB81FF43258C58102EB69CB745"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Delay in implementation</header><clause id="H8F50B503E11E4127BD1F9C746DBF55E8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Delay</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), none of the funds made available for the salaries and expenses of an agency may be used to implement activities directed under Executive Order 14019 (86 Fed. Reg. 13623) until—</text><subclause id="H865ED2DB68D64D388798ED7505D71EB3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of an agency that is required to submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees under subparagraph (B)(i), 180 days after the agency submits the report; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA229D03061AB41E989C0F33EAFD31B75"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of an agency that is required to submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees under subparagraph (B)(ii), the date on which the agency submits the report. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9F4DA1C4F4634A939D75D743D22EFB93"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply to any activity described in section 7(c) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20506">52 U.S.C. 20506(c)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66FB5A55163F42ACADA542A413630E72"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees—</text><clause id="H5F98AE27921F45CF85ADFDB07DBEF077"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a copy of the strategic plan of the agency for promoting voter registration and voter participation under section 3(b) of Executive Order 14019 (86 Fed. Reg. 13623) that the agency developed or submitted to the Assistant to the President for Domestic Policy; or</text></clause><clause id="HD79CFE3B15E24F738522430D4FD73798"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the agency did not develop or submit a plan described in clause (i) to the Assistant to the President for Domestic Policy, a certification signed by the head of the agency that the agency did not develop or submit such a plan.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4068A5BBF79C4E9B8044B66AABC8F775"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2)(B), this section shall apply with respect to fiscal year 2023 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE159EA9EC5C94A50A9DFF0A55923FAC4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional report on voter registration and mobilization</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report describing the activities carried out by the agency pursuant to sections 3 and 4 of Executive Order 14019 (86 Fed. Reg. 13623).</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F2C413ED08F46A39989944C9FB42FAD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibiting voter registration and mobilization in Federal work-Study programs</header><text>Section 443(b)(1) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087-53">20 U.S.C. 1087–53(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBABADF65DEDD45B9B3450EDE7BC5E668"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7561C003285D46F88E13BE2AC1AF3BDA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (D) as subparagraph (E); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4882919D68614645B9C4ACC2D46E3A84"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AF765505B53410A937C8B676F975257"><subparagraph id="H4B788BFB45D6411F80FB543BF8ECC53F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>does not involve registering or mobilizing voters on or off the campus of the institution; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D9E1AB2D00947C4BCB68200CC75D626"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD966288A3D4A4AF183034E627841DE1B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3502(1) of title 44, United States Code, except that for purposes of subsection (c)(2) such term does not include an independent regulatory agency as defined in section 3502(5) of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD13CA5204A404A39B6EFDDA31E9F6112"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H5FF97CFC7A7549C89BDA74D81B90DAF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B299D9CBE0E458A90A07115DF5F8C27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1B3C477997A4996A294F6E5B76AF2C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D6AF044C0BC42D6B695E1E25423ABAB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H83F4D8D26DAD4B69980FC8C32D6F173C"><enum>133.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of Federal funds for election administration in States that permit ballot harvesting</header><subsection id="H9DF30B8BCDEE428EAD11D31B253F5CB9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This section may be cited as the <quote>No Federal Funds for Ballot Harvesting Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6B735C3933734538B49B48569A943822"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="H05D2EEB792F547B2A3C1404944F4CFE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the right to vote is a fundamental right of citizens of the United States, as described by the Constitution of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB11C58807B2B4D37AE1E6C8127554B23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives, which is charged with investigating election irregularities, received reports through its official Election Observer Program for the 2018 general election and the 2020 general election, as well as from other stakeholders, that individuals other than voters themselves were depositing large amounts of absentee ballots at polling places throughout California and other States, a practice colloquially known as “ballot harvesting”;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87F7ED223A8B4C03AF0DAD198D8AB77D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the practice of ballot harvesting creates significant vulnerabilities in the chain-of-custody of ballots because individuals collecting ballots are not required to be registered voters and are not required to identify themselves at a voter’s home, and the State does not track how many ballots are harvested in an election;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCAFB76C8D224BE3865802CF0DECC2CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in North Carolina, a congressional election was invalidated due to fraud associated with ballot harvesting committed by a political operative, and it is unlikely such activity would have been detected were it not for the prohibition against ballot harvesting in the State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65C59D2F6F024882820A89269D5D5D4D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ballot harvesting invites electioneering activity at home and weakens States’ long-standing voter protection procedures, which remain in place at polling locations, creating the possibility of undue influence over voters by political operatives and other bad actors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44E649C142F945E9AD8C86A6E1FDEB28"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Supreme Court of the United States has affirmed State authority to restrict ballot harvesting (Brnovich v. Democratic National Committee, 141 S. Ct. 2321 (2021)).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBE09B84E81144DB0BF1AC376DB7C7510" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funds for election administration for States allowing collection and transmission of ballots by certain third parties</header><paragraph id="H7C0FD8FBB0534B0D975771439A01D7CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20901">52 U.S.C. 20901 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA1C1D417566F450E8745B72BD54CC3B2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H7E3F40B6542D407C9372A7EC089FB6F3"><enum>908.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funds for election administration for States allowing collection and transmission of ballots by certain third parties</header><subsection id="H13062FFA34474BE7B764FD6098DFCA09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds may be used to administer any election for Federal office in a State unless the State has in effect a law that prohibits an individual from the knowing collection and transmission of a ballot in an election for Federal office that was mailed to another person, other than an individual described as follows:</text><paragraph id="HCCACD59A6E824F7395BECA341C80BB7C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An election official while engaged in official duties as authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H571A48E933D94B43ADC225B255E7454C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee of the United States Postal Service or other commercial common carrier engaged in similar activities while engaged in duties authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H285F2C4A0FD844958BCF28711C2CD9F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any other individual who is allowed by law to collect and transmit United States mail, while engaged in official duties as authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H835131AAA47A4E35BE9AD2F595879307"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A family member, household member, or caregiver of the person to whom the ballot was mailed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5922D6FDD3FA4415B99B1F7A5356FE24" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, with respect to a person to whom the ballot was mailed:</text><paragraph id="H8F4759E6919C45A3A4E96ED2DCDBE8B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>caregiver</term> means an individual who provides medical or health care assistance to such person in a residence, nursing care institution, hospice facility, assisted living center, assisted living facility, assisted living home, residential care institution, adult day health care facility, or adult foster care home.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00CCEA3DD2174D28B5AE91EEB0B6AA4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>family member</term> means an individual who is related to such person by blood, marriage, adoption or legal guardianship.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA5576D3E0004172AA996DF6F15FB141"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>household member</term> means an individual who resides at the same residence as such person.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B15459FD03D4C24B9D94EBAA944D196"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5210548A97A843CFB783636F280A423F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 908. Prohibition on Federal funds for election administration for States allowing collection and transmission of ballots by certain third parties.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H13F6C66D708341B7AA20100789AA7D6C"><enum>134.</enum><header>Clarification with respect to Federal election record-keeping requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 301 of the Civil Rights Act of 1960 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20701">52 U.S.C. 20701</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote> including envelopes used to deliver voted ballots by mail (but excluding envelopes used to deliver blank ballots or absentee ballot requests or used for any purpose other than delivering voted ballots),</quote> after <quote>requisite to voting in such election,</quote>.</text></section><section id="H80C0DA9A2F994B989499B7D21D2B7391"><enum>135.</enum><header>Clarification of rules with respect to hiring of election workers</header><subsection id="H0FE52DB8CF434D3D958E95FC25FBC594"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Preferences for veterans and individuals with disabilities</header><paragraph id="H4D0E89B625034BAD9B50D0043693D827"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In hiring election workers to administer an election in a State or local jurisdiction, the State or local jurisdiction may give preference to individuals who are veterans or individuals with a disability.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3FD1376AA2C414DAB8F6D959AE55D08" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individual with a disability defined</header><text>In this subsection, an <quote>individual with a disability</quote> means an individual with an impairment that substantially limits any major life activities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEF107822D6944259B359C7B3C8F38A50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Preference and waiver of residency requirement for spouses and dependents of absent military voters</header><paragraph id="H1399A25253E845599E4ABE8BFFAFC0A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Preference and waivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In hiring election workers to administer an election in a State or local jurisdiction, the State or local jurisdiction—</text><subparagraph id="HF523B70F2856403794E564C66EFA0EB1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may give preference to an individual who is a nonresident military spouse or dependent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE81CA752721847EFAFF7006881B5F99C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may not refuse to hire such an individual as an election worker solely on the grounds that the individual does not maintain a place of residence in the State or local jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H61F81839877C46CDA031C3654786E0AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonresident military spouse or dependent defined</header><text>In this subsection, a <quote>nonresident military spouse or dependent</quote> means an individual who is an absent uniformed services voter under section 107(1)(C) of the Uniformed and Overseas Citizen Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20310">52 U.S.C. 20310(1)(C)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4E284798AF92489D9CF2FEC4C9482787"><enum>136.</enum><header>United States Postal Service coordination with States to ensure mailing addresses</header><subsection id="HFD51AEABA0BF4510B1CA356708A6DAF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Postmaster General shall, in coordination with the appropriate State executives of each State, carry out a program to identify and assign a mailing address to each home in each State that, as of the date of the enactment of this Act, does not have a mailing address assigned to such home, with a priority given to assigning mailing addresses to such homes located on Indian lands.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC96C3822500F41ACB3306E2707F62FC1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H713FC4B12EB945FFA500F1A8B9378025"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian</header><text>The term <term>Indian</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66D3DFB0900A4A32B034611452726BE0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian lands</header><text>The term <term>Indian lands</term> includes—</text><subparagraph id="H597B3255194B42ADBAC9FAEB0B15DE75"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any Indian country of an Indian Tribe, as defined under section 1151 of title 18, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF69FE19CB124C3E92E9EE14C079F4FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any land in Alaska owned, pursuant to the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1601">43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq.</external-xref>), by an Indian Tribe that is a Native village (as defined in section 3 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1602">43 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>)) or by a Village Corporation that is associated with an Indian Tribe (as defined in section 3 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1602">43 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D3B61D5ACC84BFF838622A94DAF49F4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any land on which the seat of the Tribal Government is located; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5C6258A56ED48ED93EF0D37E9807A6F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any land that is part or all of a Tribal designated statistical area associated with an Indian Tribe, or is part or all of an Alaska Native village statistical area associated with an Indian Tribe, as defined by the Census Bureau for the purposes of the most recent decennial census.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B12E564CFE740D59ED53FE4E43BD4AF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83FD17A23EFB4CAFA0518D3BAE11374C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given such term in section 901 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21141">52 U.S.C. 21141</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A555EF4A3FF4925BBBF156E66CE221B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal Government</term> means the recognized governing body of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6F1A087068BF4857876873CE19609A60"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE06560FEBC5F4E17B1BC6119CDB98D32"><enum>137.</enum><header>State defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 901 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21141">52 U.S.C. 21141</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and the United States Virgin Islands</quote> and inserting <quote>the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands</quote>. </text></section></title><title id="H111BCA3DF70D4A35BE669E38599DB305"><enum>IV</enum><header>District of Columbia Election Integrity and Voter Confidence</header><section id="H2A87163AA4784F069C1CB5E0B9D349F7"><enum>141.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Election Integrity and Voter Confidence Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="HDDD9C8B7A4BA4A78A2EAD93E6319E63A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>142.</enum><header>Requirements for elections in District of Columbia</header><subsection id="H99510176B3E94B7FA248439076283FAC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21801">52 U.S.C. 21801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subtitle:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF061B65C1BB24665BBFF970CA1C154C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subtitle id="H3F0E896D2F4941808067167672CA06E9"><enum>C</enum><header>Requirements for Elections in District of Columbia</header><section id="H484A435BFF064E0487BBA53CF9216CA9" commented="no"><enum>321.</enum><header>Statement of Congressional authority; findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that it has the authority to establish the terms and conditions for the administration of elections for public office in the District of Columbia—</text><paragraph id="H177398DB5D104ADEB087D4E4B31749D2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>under article I, section 8, clause 17 of the Constitution of the United States, which grants Congress the exclusive power to enact legislation with respect to the seat of the Government of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4293D3E7478C407FA434CF2FF4D2D038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>under other enumerated powers granted to Congress.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD937790E0CC148D08F4853A28179C040"><enum>322.</enum><header>Requirements for photo identification</header><subsection id="H506960EE1E694838BDE1B881F31D4108"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter Identification Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0E33CB50D17C49B9B274D7583960AA95"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requiring provision of identification To receive a ballot or vote</header><paragraph id="H852D3D8176C44AF5AF1525077AE99CB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Individuals voting in person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot for a District of Columbia election to an individual who desires to vote in person unless the individual presents to the official an identification described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36AB0F419C0C42238B084EE096D45326"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individuals voting other than in person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot for a District of Columbia election to an individual who desires to vote other than in person unless the individual submits with the application for the ballot a copy of an identification described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B2FC2FF1CC147198E20D79923BF3500"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Identification described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification described in this paragraph is, with respect to an individual, any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H14B367223B0F4F05847AD5654DEA2B09"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A current and valid motor vehicle license issued by the District of Columbia or any other current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by the District of Columbia or the identification number for such motor vehicle license or photo identification. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F2829E949274A559899A4B7379143E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A current and valid United States passport, a current and valid military photo identification, or any other current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H671E873CCAB04453899BC3949140DFEB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by a Tribal Government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBE750CDDF4541D8B2A9D8923EAC6FAB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A student photo identification issued by a secondary school (as such term is defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) or an institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84A8A021234947BBA7A6E9A36DE55CC6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The last 4 digits of the individual's social security number.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59A2B13EA1314E5B95391B1F32473035"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ensuring proof of residence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an individual presents or submits an identification described in paragraph (3) which does not include the address of the individual’s residence, the District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot to the individual unless the individual presents or submits a document or other written information from a third party which—</text><subparagraph id="HF7D10BD3914F41E3BB130DC17EE212F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides the address of the individual’s residence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBB431A3AD4148308C14D0C3EBB323CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such document or other written information is of sufficient validity such that the election official is reasonably certain as to the identity of the individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60CEE197D5C74AC8967288C6FE635365"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Provision of identification without cost to indigent individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the District of Columbia charges an individual a fee for an identification described in subsection (b)(3) and the individual provides an attestation that the individual is unable to afford the fee, the District of Columbia shall provide the identification to the individual at no cost.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1A93B68DBEA846E5B93E9D21522B6220"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rule with respect to sincerely held religious beliefs</header><text>In the case of an individual who is unable to comply with the requirements of subsection (b) due to sincerely held religious beliefs, the District of Columbia shall provide such individual with an alternative identification that shall be deemed to meet the requirements of an identification described in subsection (b)(3).</text></subsection><subsection id="H41FC74E3C94A49ECA0FCBEE06A8D90E0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Designation of District of Columbia agency To provide copies of identification</header><text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia shall designate an agency of the District of Columbia government to provide an individual with a copy of an identification described in subsection (b)(3) at no cost to the individual for the purposes of meeting the requirement under subsection (b)(2). </text></subsection><subsection id="H80665AB13D9446B5AD8ADBF352F267C7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inclusion of photos in poll books</header><paragraph id="HB2DB8AA0458449F5926E80EE9941C1A5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Methods for obtaining photos</header><subparagraph id="HF03B37ABE3794293A7517FC53E7316E6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Provision of photos by offices of District of Columbia government</header><text>If any office of the District of Columbia Government has a photograph or digital image of the likeness of an individual who is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election, the office, in consultation with the chief election official of the District of Columbia, shall provide access to the photograph or digital image to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E9351B8757D4AC4B28149D3DD4661C9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Taking of photos at polling place</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a photograph or digital image of an individual who votes in person at a polling place is not included in the poll book which contains the name of the individuals who are eligible to vote in the District of Columbia election and which is used by election officials to provide ballots to such eligible individuals, the appropriate election official shall take a photograph of the individual and provide access to the photograph to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDE01C9C1F2E46CE828D0B2CB7FA3AC2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Copies of photos provided by individuals not voting in person</header><text>The election official who receives a copy of an identification described in subsection (b)(3) which is submitted by an individual who desires to vote other than in person at a polling place shall provide access to the copy of the identification to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BC19D0DAA764633A1C41F453D5D202A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion in poll books</header><text>The chief election official of the District of Columbia shall ensure that a photograph, digital image, or copy of an identification for which access is provided under paragraph (1) is included in the poll book which contains the name of the individuals who are eligible to vote in the District of Columbia election and which is used by election officials to provide ballots to such eligible individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18C3A93F1C5740BBAC668E913782C315"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Protection of privacy of voters</header><text>The appropriate election officials of the District of Columbia shall ensure that any photograph, digital image, or copy of an identification which is included in a poll book under this subsection is not used for any purpose other than the administration of District of Columbia elections and is not provided or otherwise made available to any other person except as may be necessary to carry out that purpose.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC62583B42F9C43228832A30CBEE9E14B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section does not apply with respect to any individual who is—</text><paragraph id="HF35EB1CC49A145B09D181F01DAC34179"><enum>(1)</enum><text>entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H119EDC6445704FA386A5620E6B6F0EDE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provided the right to vote otherwise than in person under section 3(b)(2)(B)(ii) of the Voting Accessibility for the Elderly and Handicapped Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20102">52 U.S.C. 20102(b)(2)(B)(ii)</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81BD82120210486CB3DE696F9F795DBD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>entitled to vote otherwise than in person under any other Federal law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29E1FF84AB32494AADA048AF06F3F0EB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H2AA156A8F61F4CD09460620F05D6F0DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ED208D2973745AA9A9CD9017F3D04E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal Government</term> means the recognized governing body of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H180BCF07498F465E9A4DD1588DEBB855"><enum>323.</enum><header>Requirements for voter registration</header><subsection id="HBC68958FAD0648F582E4CE4C9E511A5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter List Maintenance Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H44FDD950354F49768B652730C38935A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual list maintenance</header><paragraph id="H5DEFACB658A642FFB2D4358EB2612F64"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><subparagraph id="H58DBE5417610468F9ECB9B30C4B25654"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The District of Columbia shall carry out annually a program to remove ineligible persons from the official list of persons registered to vote in the District of Columbia, as required by section 8 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507</external-xref>) and pursuant to the procedures described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1AB364787114CD7B98C316C9F1787C3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Removal from voter rolls</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a registrant from the official list of eligible voters in District of Columbia elections who has failed to vote in a District of Columbia election during a period of two consecutive years, the District of Columbia shall send to such registrant a notice described in section 8(d)(2) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(d)(2)</external-xref>) and shall remove the registrant from the official list of eligible voters in District of Columbia elections if—</text><clause id="HB4F30D29A58F48C182FB93A31CCB182D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the registrant fails to respond to such notice; and</text></clause><clause id="H05BA221750E548A4914ECF91F495A12B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the registrant has not voted or appeared to vote in a District of Columbia election during the period beginning the date such notice is sent and ending the later of 4 years after the date such notice is sent or after two consecutive District of Columbia general elections have been held. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A8B77E797844E4689DE9BE9F81811BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>In the case of a year during which a regularly scheduled District of Columbia election is held, the District of Columbia shall carry out the program described in paragraph (1) not later than 90 days prior to the date of the election.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H92736B352D2C4CBAAEBE9C0D1E1ED7F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibiting same-Day registration</header><text>The District of Columbia may not permit an individual to vote in a District of Columbia election unless, not later than 30 days prior to the date of the election, the individual is duly registered to vote in the election.</text></subsection></section><section id="H251F62478E9F44628659EFDA014664B2"><enum>324.</enum><header>Ban on collection and transmission of ballots by certain third parties</header><subsection id="H112B0BE72B184946BE99120F7EAC0875"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Election Fraud Prevention Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H416B7D8E7F044F039367571DE95C4E6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia may not permit an individual to knowingly collect and transmit a ballot in a District of Columbia election that was mailed to another person, other than an individual described as follows:</text><paragraph id="HAFBDE594576A481784F044E8AE0DC1CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An election official while engaged in official duties as authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8DBD6CC98AE4D428B8AA28E8995C673"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee of the United States Postal Service or other commercial common carrier engaged in similar activities while engaged in duties authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8CC2EA823AB43E98CD0A5C983632B2C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any other individual who is allowed by law to collect and transmit United States mail, while engaged in official duties as authorized by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E9782D1ED8146468432E39A6A3BC84F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A family member, household member, or caregiver of the person to whom the ballot was mailed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A2CEACD8DA646BBAEA93D39F349688F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, with respect to a person to whom the ballot was mailed:</text><paragraph id="H664FEA9A593F40C78FF5999CD34CF656"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>caregiver</term> means an individual who provides medical or health care assistance to such person in a residence, nursing care institution, hospice facility, assisted living center, assisted living facility, assisted living home, residential care institution, adult day health care facility, or adult foster care home.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0487E280A04413AB4F669EA71E654B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>family member</term> means an individual who is related to such person by blood, marriage, adoption or legal guardianship.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AA58F7C7A1B4049A65CE32D92223016"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>household member</term> means an individual who resides at the same residence as such person.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF13CFAF9289244C4A9881E897971BDA0"><enum>325.</enum><header>Timely processing and reporting of results</header><subsection id="H54EE1D5BF9C14A53BE20A616962946C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Timely Reporting of Election Results Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H1F9FDDF101874D86A379FEB9F8D00F17"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Time for processing ballots and reporting results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> The District of Columbia shall begin processing ballots received by mail in a District of Columbia election as soon as such ballots are received and shall ensure to the greatest extent practicable that the results of such District of Columbia election are reported to the public not later than 10:00 am on the date following the date of the election, but in no case shall such ballots be tabulated or such results be reported earlier than the closing of polls on the date of the election.</text></subsection><subsection id="H37105E6376DD429791976A71D66D5B48"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement To publish number of voted ballots on election day</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia shall, as soon as practicable after the closing of polls on the date of a District of Columbia election, make available on a publicly accessible website the total number of voted ballots in the possession of election officials in the District of Columbia as of the time of the closing of polls on the date of such election, which shall include, as of such time—</text><paragraph id="HA23A2C434A054CD38814F3AFA8AB0352"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of voted ballots delivered by mail;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2038E44FFCAB4DEE82A49C7BE1DE948E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of ballots requested for such election by individuals who are entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1F572E2B3944088A4F5887652424E6C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of voted ballots for such election received from individuals who are entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>), including from individuals who, under such Act, voted by absentee ballot without requesting such a ballot. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H33771F8CD97E4987A48C22985ABCCC8E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements To ensure bipartisan election administration activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a District of Columbia election, District of Columbia election officials shall ensure that all activities are carried out in a bipartisan manner, which shall include a requirement that, in the case of an election worker who enters a room which contains ballots, voting equipment, or non-voting equipment as any part of the election worker’s duties to carry out such election, the election worker is accompanied by an individual registered to vote with respect to a different political party than such election worker, as determined pursuant to the voting registration records of the District of Columbia. </text></subsection></section><section id="H412C3CA1652E41FBB281A3B1C6FDFD93"><enum>326.</enum><header>Ban on noncitizen voting</header><subsection id="HAE4F676F855843049F571C8B1AF1FC11"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Citizen Voter Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4C5E97FAFB1A4DA29F245D965F1D6278"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ban on noncitizen voting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No individual may vote in a District of Columbia election unless the individual is a citizen of the United States.</text></subsection></section><section id="HED92D72359854487A42AF201342C1D4E"><enum>327.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to provisional ballots</header><subsection id="H72CD4D1F1A5A43A3BFC6EEEA4D2008BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Provisional Ballot Reform Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H932CBD8CB1194E0FB3FE9AF07770ADCE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (c), the District of Columbia shall permit an individual to cast a provisional ballot pursuant to section 302 if—</text><paragraph id="HBB075BD17FA942A28364AE9E2280F3BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the individual declares that such individual is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election but the name of the individual does not appear on the official list of eligible voters for the polling place or an election official asserts that the individual is not eligible to vote; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62CC8C0DD04F463F8AAE6AB84218D417"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the individual declares that such individual is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election but does not provide an identification required under section 322, except that the individual’s provisional ballot shall not be counted in the election unless the individual provides such identification to the chief State election official of the District of Columbia not later than 5:00 pm on the second day which begins after the date of the election.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFAA71C2AA0F04E0190211945DABB17B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements with respect to counting provisional ballots in certain cases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the name of an individual who is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election appears on the official list of eligible voters for a polling place in the District of Columbia, such individual may cast a provisional ballot pursuant to section 302 for such election at a polling place other than the polling place with respect to which the name of the individual appears on the official list of eligible voters, except that the individual’s provisional ballot shall not be counted in the election unless the individual demonstrates pursuant to the requirements under section 302 that the individual is a registered voter in the jurisdiction of the polling place at which the individual cast such ballot. </text></subsection></section><section id="H43EC5720822540B3A999A486B7EAD5E8"><enum>328.</enum><header>Mandatory post-election audits</header><subsection id="H3E55F73C9F264F509495F3F5DB54BC6B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Mandatory Post-Election Audits Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB92A40B6A6BE4CD3B588CA83091716CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement for post-Election audits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after each District of Columbia election, the District of Columbia shall conduct and publish an audit of the effectiveness and accuracy of the voting systems used to carry out the election and the performance of the election officials who carried out the election, but in no case shall such audit be completed later than 2 business days before the deadline to file an election contest under the laws of the District of Columbia.</text></subsection></section><section id="H60B1C58ED97F463C9D8A9F23321F7CAB"><enum>329.</enum><header>Public observation of election procedures</header><subsection id="H8084B67541244BB8A5E0F647DAC3686A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Public Observation of Election Procedures Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H558698FFC65A4108BBFB9D83CC3414F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designated representatives of candidates, political parties, and committees affiliated with ballot initiatives</header><paragraph id="H0623B0F870674D01BEE442025158F1DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to observe procedures</header><text>An individual who is not a District of Columbia election official may observe election procedures carried out in a District of Columbia election, as described in paragraph (2), if the individual is designated to observe such procedures by a candidate in the election, a political party, or a committee affiliated with a ballot initiative or referendum in the election.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A02F70196C044258924A2B5AEDA76EC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority and procedures described</header><text>The authority of an individual to observe election procedures pursuant to this subsection is as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H4ADC5D27107A4B08895081D942D27C6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The individual may serve as a poll watcher to observe the casting and tabulation of ballots at a polling place on the date of the election or on any day prior to the date of the election on which ballots are cast at early voting sites, and may challenge the casting or tabulation of any such ballot.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E707DEB0D3C4CA8AC5CB4DBDC672A23"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual may serve as a poll watcher to observe the canvassing and processing of absentee or other mail-in ballots, including the procedures for verification of signed certificates of transmission under section 330(c)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64C86F4EB7AB42779C4A2B55ED8314F9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The individual may observe the recount of the results of the election at any location at which the recount is held, and may challenge the tabulation of any ballot tabulated pursuant to the recount.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB22ED56D3F7641C0A8BB1029900E8F72"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Provision of credentials</header><text>The chief State election official of the District of Columbia shall provide each individual who is authorized to observe election procedures under paragraph (1) with appropriate credentials to enable the individual to observe such procedures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74B1CB8A4465431F8ACBD842ED8AE245"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exception for candidates and law enforcement officers</header><text>An individual may not serve as a poll watcher under subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (2), and the chief State election official of the District of Columbia may not provide the individual with credentials to enable the individual to serve as a poll watcher under such subparagraph, if the individual is a candidate in the election or a law enforcement officer.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF31E21E863340AFA95F57057C17B63D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Other individuals</header><paragraph id="H7E8EA863453C48AFBB21778EDDDAFDBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Petition for observer credentials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the individuals described in subsection (b), any individual, including an individual representing or affiliated with a domestic or international organization, may petition the chief State election official of the District of Columbia to provide the individual with credentials to observe election procedures carried out in a District of Columbia election, as described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CA0DC2A5B9748AEA72C4CEEE2E3487C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority described</header><text>If the chief State election official provides an individual with credentials under paragraph (1), the individual shall have the same authority to observe election procedures carried out in the election as an individual described in subsection (b), except that the individual may not challenge the casting, tabulation, canvassing, or processing of any ballot in the election.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D30EBE9E06F4BDBAC49FE7102A2CEC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception for candidates and law enforcement officers</header><text>The chief State election official of the District of Columbia may not provide an individual who is a candidate in the election or a law enforcement officer with credentials to serve as a poll watcher, as described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEDCFEF0037D94001B639D3AD2F7CB831"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority of members of public To observe testing of equipment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the authority of individuals to observe procedures under subsections (b) and (c), any member of the public may observe the testing of election equipment by election officials prior to the date of the election. </text></subsection><subsection id="H5AFE21043ECB4EF09BDE729F2628E890"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibiting limits on ability To view procedures</header><text>An election official may not obstruct the ability of an individual who is authorized to observe an election procedure under this section to view the procedure as it is being carried out.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6F9A42E748754E408C02702561E681A8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Prohibition against certain restrictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An election official may not require that an individual who observes election procedures under this section stays more than 3 feet away from the procedure as it is being carried out.</text></subsection></section><section id="H84C29C8203F64C4AA237E657D34E9EE4"><enum>330.</enum><header>Requirements for voting by mail-in ballot</header><subsection id="H9F24D1486EB34372B86631D6C2BA7188"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Mail Balloting Reform Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFA2AD62B80094054A105BDEAB4B3C154"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibiting transmission of unsolicited ballots</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia may not transmit an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election to any individual who does not request the District of Columbia to transmit the ballot.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0F786FD90AD146DD9851BC7852FC09A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Signature verification</header><paragraph id="H7ECA12D061764C418CCD0FFC4C650D7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Inclusion of certificate with ballot</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia shall include with each absentee or other mail-in ballot transmitted for a District of Columbia election a certificate of transmission which may be signed by the individual for whom the ballot is transmitted.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A133C399D0340FEB36E0E0BD4ABC735"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requiring verification for ballot to be counted</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (d), the District of Columbia may not accept an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election unless—</text><subparagraph id="H678E59662BE045CDB41D58DDF3A671A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual for whom the ballot was transmitted—</text><clause id="HBABB098A09B4467D8187A437DC4129C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>signs and dates the certificate of transmission included with the ballot under paragraph (1); and</text></clause><clause id="H0F3465E4DDDC466DAB78411BAFFF8CE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes the signed certification with the ballot and the date on such certification is accurate and in no case later than the date of the election; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF82126B193794F2AA044425EAAE54FB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the individual’s signature on the ballot matches the signature of the individual on the official list of registered voters in the District of Columbia or other official record or document used by the District of Columbia to verify the signatures of voters. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA6EE17DF3C242F29B2EE27305483433" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity To cure</header><paragraph id="H31B683FE98754E2BB2E49D331913C8E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity to cure discrepancy in signatures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an individual submits an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election and the appropriate District of Columbia election official determines that a discrepancy exists between the signature on such ballot and the signature of such individual on the official list of registered voters in the District of Columbia or other official record or document used by the District of Columbia to verify the signatures of voters, such election official, prior to making a final determination as to the validity of such ballot, shall—</text><subparagraph id="HC032799C21CA49F4BDCEE099265F962D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>make a good faith effort to immediately notify the individual by mail, telephone, or (if available) text message and electronic mail that—</text><clause id="H0612B89741CA400AB21CB2C9465B3DFB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a discrepancy exists between the signature on such ballot and the signature of the individual on the official list of registered voters in the District of Columbia or other official record or document used by the District of Columbia to verify the signatures of voters; and</text></clause><clause id="H8CE79C81F2BB4F4E9C76AF3AD7B6AD34"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if such discrepancy is not cured prior to the expiration of the 48-hour period which begins on the date the official notifies the individual of the discrepancy, such ballot will not be counted; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H711748599339457F9B9DF07DD2FA4CA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cure such discrepancy and count the ballot if, prior to the expiration of the 48-hour period described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the individual provides the official with information to cure such discrepancy, either in person, by telephone, or by electronic methods.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H36933224EEE0492BACD0C92D1BEF1B3B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity to cure missing signature or other defect</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an individual submits an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election without a signature on the ballot or the certificate of transmission included with the ballot under subsection (c)(1) or submits an absentee ballot with another defect which, if left uncured, would cause the ballot to not be counted, the appropriate District of Columbia election official, prior to making a final determination as to the validity of the ballot, shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5FAB16A863AD4DB98358F2194219D228"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make a good faith effort to immediately notify the individual by mail, telephone, or (if available) text message and electronic mail that—</text><clause id="H177637C876AA440F988FBD34015476CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the ballot or certificate of transmission did not include a signature or has some other defect; and</text></clause><clause id="HD49A224705E641429A60CB9290367FCA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the individual does not provide the missing signature or cure the other defect prior to the expiration of the 48-hour period which begins on the date the official notifies the individual that the ballot or certificate of transmission did not include a signature or has some other defect, such ballot will not be counted; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4628422832E84794A123277C5183DA6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">count the ballot if, prior to the expiration of the 48-hour period described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the individual provides the official with the missing signature on a form proscribed by the District of Columbia or cures the other defect.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">This paragraph does not apply with respect to a defect consisting of the failure of a ballot to meet the applicable deadline for the acceptance of the ballot, as described in subsection (e). </continuation-text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H87A58805731941FDA06B69936BD09D71"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Deadline for acceptance</header><paragraph id="H9202BF76472D4AB484894ED97F85F4C5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the District of Columbia may not accept an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election which is received by the appropriate election official following the close of polls on Election Day.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5136C122A5FC4B95B9C4A82F364D9A46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception for absent military and overseas voters</header><text>Paragraph (1) does not apply to a ballot cast by an individual who is entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60F25D1EEE364439BB263E1077EA0922"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed as prohibiting the District of Columbia from accepting an absentee or other mail-in ballot for a District of Columbia election that is delivered in person by the voter to an election official at an appropriate polling place or the District of Columbia Board of Elections if such ballot is received by the election official by the deadline described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H09FB3AB1F3F1403494A868019B8A67D8"><enum>331.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to use of drop boxes</header><subsection id="H8A1B39128EF446139520D5BC79F099F0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Ballot Security Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H31ACB667A6B5405ABB6A23F9C4516A95"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a District of Columbia election, the District of Columbia may not use a drop box to accept a voted absentee or other mail-in ballot for any such election unless—</text><paragraph id="H2D5D504E5CF84585B959920944E0D86B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any such drop box is located inside a District of Columbia Government building or facility;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27054C6AE6794B4B89AE07ED26B9AE73"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the District of Columbia provides for the security of any such drop box through 24-hour remote or electronic surveillance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57DF4AEFCCD64A859623992AC89A80CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the District of Columbia Board of Elections collects any ballot deposited in any such drop box each day after 5:00 p.m. (local time) during the period of the election.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H87883CF418A3413E9048CCB495E90642" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>332.</enum><header>Special rule with respect to application of requirements to Federal elections</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">With respect to an election for Federal office in the District of Columbia, to the extent that there is any inconsistency with the requirements of this subtitle and the requirements of subtitle A, the requirements of this subtitle shall apply.</text></section><section id="H0792088478F940099B218DE425A1DF11"><enum>333.</enum><header>District of Columbia election defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subtitle, the term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H25087D383F75442587667655741CA828"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text>Section 401 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking the period at the end and inserting the following: <quote>, and the requirements of subtitle C with respect to the District of Columbia.</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H71DCA1F5FB8C4780A43ED668AE24C59F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the items relating to title III the following:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="yes-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-quoted-entry style="OLC"><toc-entry idref="H3F0E896D2F4941808067167672CA06E9" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Requirements for Elections in District of Columbia</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H484A435BFF064E0487BBA53CF9216CA9" level="section">Sec. 321. Statement of Congressional authority; findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD937790E0CC148D08F4853A28179C040" level="section">Sec. 322. Requirements for photo identification.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H180BCF07498F465E9A4DD1588DEBB855" level="section">Sec. 323. Requirements for voter registration.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H251F62478E9F44628659EFDA014664B2" level="section">Sec. 324. Ban on collection and transmission of ballots by certain third parties.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF13CFAF9289244C4A9881E897971BDA0" level="section">Sec. 325. Timely processing and reporting of results.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H412C3CA1652E41FBB281A3B1C6FDFD93" level="section">Sec. 326. Ban on noncitizen voting.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HED92D72359854487A42AF201342C1D4E" level="section">Sec. 327. Requirements with respect to provisional ballots.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H43EC5720822540B3A999A486B7EAD5E8" level="section">Sec. 328. Mandatory post-election audits.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 329. Public observation of election procedures.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 330. Requirements for voting by mail-in ballot.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 331. Requirements with respect to use of drop boxes.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 332. Special rule with respect to application of requirements to Federal elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 333. District of Columbia election defined. </toc-entry></toc-quoted-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H775BC0FBCE7D49D58266FDF6B34FDC16"><enum>143.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by this title shall apply with respect to District of Columbia elections held on or after January 1, 2024. For purposes of this section, the term <term>District of Columbia election</term> has the meaning given such term in section 333 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002, as added by section 143(a).</text></section></title><title id="H19D0F5D3DB834E428F47EB9357E80E4E"><enum>V</enum><header>Administration of the Election Assistance Commission</header><section id="HADDAD1BABA4941DD99D4ADA48B4ADF62"><enum>151.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Positioning the Election Assistance Commission for the Future Act of 2023</quote>. </text></section><section id="HFA07A00F3647447F90359CBFE92FE346"><enum>152.</enum><header>Findings relating to the administration of the Election Assistance Commission</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H06E0814CD51F401DA893B6680BE4ADAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Election Assistance Commission best serves the American people when operating within its core statutory functions, including serving as a clearinghouse for information on election administration, providing grants, and testing and certifying election equipment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11DED90622904FCBACD0D931BF223714"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The American people are best served when Federal agency election assistance is offered by a single agency with expertise in this space. The Election Assistance Commission, composed of four election experts from different political parties, is best situated among the Federal Government agencies to offer assistance services to citizens and to guide other Federal agencies that have responsibilities in the elections space. The Commission is also best suited to determine the timing of the issuance of any advisories and to disburse all appropriated election grant funding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB46479BA62D4FE5A3ACF01C07BF0FF1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To this end, Congress finds that the Election Assistance Commission should be viewed as the lead Federal Government agency on all election administration matters, and other Federal agencies operating in this space should look to the Commission for guidance, direction, and support on election administration-related issues.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H28A8C9B9FAB94B0A8FC6E2010E8E0301"><enum>153.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to staff and funding of the Election Assistance Commission</header><subsection id="H3FE4CDA32D3F45DBA338628C78E67CCF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 204(a)(5) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20924">52 U.S.C. 20924(a)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>of such additional personnel</quote> and inserting <quote>of not more than 55 full-time equivalent employees to carry out the duties and responsibilities under this Act and the additional duties and responsibilities required under the American Confidence in Elections Act</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H70C767F5FE88460F90334050B720774D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Section 210 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20930">52 U.S.C. 20930</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE994F2C8C2484A9BB403B1C197AC3736" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>for each of the fiscal years 2003 through 2005</quote> and inserting <quote>for each of the fiscal years 2023 through 2025</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF91C1A161714713A9D9D54137BAE6DF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>(but not to exceed $10,000,000 for each such year)</quote> and inserting <quote>(but not to exceed $25,000,000 for each such year)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F1BAD8E80E14DD9BD1493B552622C03"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on certain use of funds</header><paragraph id="HEE845329052540778D74B3E6E56E8DBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>None of the funds authorized to be appropriated or otherwise made available under subsection (b) may be obligated or expended for the operation of an advisory committee established by the Election Assistance Commission pursuant to and in accordance with the provisions of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/5/2">5 U.S.C. App. 2</external-xref>), except with respect to the operation of the Local Leadership Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D039AFBEF094255B3FE14900C8BFF22"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No effect on entities established by Help America Vote Act of 2002</header><text>Paragraph (1) does not apply with respect to the operation of any entity established by the Help America Vote Act of 2002, including the Election Assistance Commission Standards Board, the Election Assistance Commission Board of Advisors, and the Technical Guidelines Development Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5FA2FAD6921845E785104DEB4518A690"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements with respect to compensation of members of the Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 203(d) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20923">52 U.S.C. 20923(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H99673EC39DDB4F999B0F7668AB168E62"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>at the annual rate of basic pay prescribed for level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5, United States Code</quote> and inserting <quote>at an annual rate of basic pay equal to the amount of $186,300, as adjusted under section 5318 of title 5, United States Code, in the same manner as the annual rate of pay for positions at each level of the Executive Schedule</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFAE220E707E45B4B1B88F0A50EB60D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>No member appointed</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in paragraph (3), no member appointed</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2A287922F7A46AABF7FDD5D03BBB5E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H125B7CBB494241328BBBA7A1F2854461" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H5C62D062E81A4D6CB0B405B1A7F76673"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Supplemental employment and compensation</header><text>An individual serving a term of service on the Commission shall be permitted to hold a position at an institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>) if—</text><subparagraph id="HA91E577B304049F482A0540408345E6E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the General Counsel of the Election Assistance Commission determines that such position does not create a conflict of interest with the individual’s position as a sitting member of the Commission and grants the individual approval to hold the position; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EC79F89FAB4405D8087A24EB95FAC18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the annual rate of compensation received by the individual from such institution is not greater than the amount equal to 49.9% of the annual rate of basic pay paid to the individual under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E3670181D26495BBFBA24BBC7BD5F63" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Office of Inspector General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 204 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20924">52 U.S.C. 20924</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H51C7A2EFA396478F919721CB1C46DEED" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HA9877A57BAF64058B2A79826266CA5C0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Office of Inspector General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Inspector General of the Election Assistance Commission may appoint not more than 7 full-time equivalent employees to assist the Inspector General to carry out the duties and responsibilities under section 404 of title 5, United States Code, of whom 2 shall have primarily administrative duties and responsibilities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H31BF7F9BBC874F8BA82DCDB8CDBB016E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2022.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA0F7EBBC90C8434682C27F3AB270178D"><enum>154.</enum><header>General requirements for payments made by Election Assistance Commission</header><subsection id="H7A1E08F9C7EB40AD96A320AF8DFA9C6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exclusive authority of Election Assistance Commission To make election administration payments to States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No entity of the Federal Government other than the Election Assistance Commission may make any payment to a State for purposes of administering elections for Federal office, including obtaining election and voting equipment and infrastructure, enhancing election and voting technology, and making election and voting security improvements, including with respect to cybersecurity and infrastructure.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC59DE7E2365741D0B81A740D4880E40F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibiting use of payments for get-Out-the-Vote-Activity</header><text>Subtitle D of title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21001">52 U.S.C. 21001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new part:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB5E4B0CFEFD84E71B490E70C067BF253" display-inline="no-display-inline"><part id="H16AB6BB8315541BE8A63E6E046ED5567"><enum>7</enum><header>General Requirements for Payments</header><section id="H8D4C8A6AFAE3468F89A8C5C3A737E514"><enum>297.</enum><header>Prohibiting use of payments for get-out-the-vote-activity</header><subsection id="HF0CF95DD47B0494DB5AE1C451137E28E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No payment made to a State or unit of local government by the Commission may be used for get-out-the-vote activity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DDA35DA120E415895DD3394FC52C33D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>get-out-the-vote activity</term> means, with respect to a payment made to a State or unit of local government, any activity which, at the time the payment is made, is treated as get-out-the-vote-activity under the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 and the regulations promulgated by the Federal Election Commission to carry out such Act.</text></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HFCF16DEECA8F4C53A5A81C03E3C08256"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requiring disclaimer in communications</header><text>Part 7 of subtitle D of title II of such Act, as added by subsection (b), is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2BCA55EA49C94775BD05A9D84573B061" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H43C922060FB6446A9A714147D7DA01DD"><enum>297A.</enum><header>Requiring communications funded by payments to include disclaimer</header><subsection id="H9AFBCF5B712848CDA22E7E1F04069EFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State or unit of local government disseminates a public communication which was developed or disseminated in whole or in part with a payment made to the State or local government by the Commission, the State or unit of local government shall ensure that the communication includes, in a clear and conspicuous manner, the following statement: <quote>Paid for using Federal taxpayer funds pursuant to the Help America Vote Act</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC62019CB577C4851806486F795FC6346" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clear and conspicuous manner described</header><text>A statement required under subsection (a) shall be considered to be in a clear and conspicuous manner if the statement meets the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H5F9D263E46244849827589C4113575C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Text or graphic communications</header><text>In the case of a text or graphic communication, the statement—</text><subparagraph id="HD6E2AC2ECC794680BCE95BCB6AB73C21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appears in letters at least as large as the majority of the text in the communication</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB10309137B654D43ABAF800EB0AE1DA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is contained in a printed box set apart from the other contents of the communication; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFC7D5A53BA3A4B7FB6BAF191DFCF0781"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is printed with a reasonable degree of color contrast between the background and the printed statement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0E2BA68EE73442E9FD99D7B53F75A0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Audio communications</header><text>In the case of an audio communication, the statement is spoken in a clearly audible and intelligible manner at the beginning or end of the communication and lasts at least 3 seconds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H167314A33F834BE8B9D6C32B557F9480"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Video communications</header><text>In the case of a video communication which also includes audio, the statement—</text><subparagraph id="HCEA74C919F104FF0B08DB62225042CD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is included at either the beginning or the end of the communication; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5586395716DD4A15B043DF6828D4BD65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is made both in—</text><clause id="H619F4BB899AD499D9BBF153AD0F9E3B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a written format that meets the requirements of subparagraph (A) and appears for at least 4 seconds; and</text></clause><clause id="HD34AF934FA894E8DA86180F0D8D0B185"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an audible format that meets the requirements of subparagraph (B).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB713019D2224F3ABC66F862BAF9463F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other communications</header><text>In the case of any other type of communication, the statement is at least as clear and conspicuous as the statement specified in paragraph (1), (2), or (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9552AA5F5A8A423FB422CE1F7D208F58"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public communication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>public communication</term> means a communication by means of any broadcast, cable, or satellite communication, newspaper, magazine, outdoor advertising facility, mass mailing, or telephone bank to the general public, or any other form of general public advertising.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDA294F18209549D891CD218B05D86E14"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by inserting at the end of the items relating to subtitle D of title II the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H210E10799D3341A885C61EA2556BC4A7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="part">Part 7—General Requirements for Payments</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 297. Prohibiting use of payments for get-out-the-vote-activity.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 297A. Requiring communications funded by payments to include disclaimer.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H10504671F39641FF8785AEFFEA94CC17"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to payments made on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H31328DD6ED044DC4A1C0040C2F62FB43" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>155.</enum><header>Executive Board of the Standards Board authority to enter into contracts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 213(c) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20943">52 U.S.C. 20943(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H056E2C8770434C938CFC7D5ADC6DBE2D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H0EE6C3C7B9644568BCF4443808A52322"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Authority to enter into contracts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Board of the Standards Board may, using amounts already made available to the Commission, enter into contracts to employ and retain no more than 2 individuals to enable the Standards Board to discharge its duties with respect to the examination and release of voluntary considerations with respect to the administration of elections for Federal offices by the States under section 247, except that—</text><subparagraph id="H8241F4C11EB44A3DA8B4339C5C21AC46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>no more than 1 individual from the same political party may be employed under such contracts at the same time; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC40DBE8357BB4BB3A32549749D7EB21C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the authority to enter into such contracts shall end on the earlier of the date of the release of the considerations or December 31, 2023; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C71596E5BB6444B95967EA33A56445D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>no additional funds may be appropriated to the Commission for the purposes of carrying out this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H46C92212764A4696A15D463A2CA4FD8F"><enum>156.</enum><header>Election Assistance Commission primary role in election administration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as provided in any other provision of law, the Election Assistance Commission shall, with respect to any other entity of the Federal Government, have primary jurisdiction to address issues with respect to the administration of elections for Federal office. </text></section></title><title id="HDE5924C6BB7D41D6AA93D28C08B2E79D"><enum>VI</enum><header>Prohibition on Involvement in Elections by Foreign Nationals</header><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA74F0F3A1D54BD690671F22F4ECB503" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>161.</enum><header>Prohibition on contributions and donations by foreign nationals in connection with ballot initiatives and referenda</header><subsection id="H7311F4867B014A63ACE03610EA7E90DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section may be cited as the <quote>Keeping Foreign Money out of Ballot Measures Act of 2023</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6ECC661043D94087A4D6BFCB8A756271"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/29">Chapter 29</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98D42317688344F3AC6D5AC97FBAEB96" style="USC"><section id="HB56818A87B4E4E5CB48173763B0E497A"><enum>612.</enum><header>Foreign nationals making certain political contributions</header><subsection id="H50B6525263DD4F848A962DDF30C01C1C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for a foreign national, directly or indirectly, to make a contribution as such term is defined in section 301(8)(A) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101(8)(A)</external-xref>) or donation of money or other thing of value, or to make an express or implied promise to make a contribution or donation, in connection with a State or local ballot initiative or referendum.</text></subsection><subsection id="H630ED5DE23694C1CA13654004C8FDA40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who violates subsection (a) shall be fined not more than $250,000, imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both.</text></subsection><subsection id="H949C4F0B73B646448FAD4A73978C1E36"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Foreign national defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>foreign national</term> has the meaning given such term in section 319(b) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30121">52 U.S.C. 30121(b)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H187EB0CCD404407CB2C3851B4F9B8869"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/29">chapter 29</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFFA289C508744E9196937C2EE48A2E47" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">612. Foreign nationals making certain political contributions.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6FC267C372BE4E9ABEAFE3CA298F468C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply with respect to contributions and donations made on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC8C30A59100C4B5F8629EBA8A1DE54AA"><enum>162.</enum><header>Prohibiting providing assistance to foreign nationals in making contributions or donations in connection with elections</header><subsection id="H54DA27A225E448908165E4A2DCBF0065"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 319(a) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30121">52 U.S.C. 30121(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8E5FEA901D45498C88911D5BD291C0C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0B0DDC2FBC549E0B776D289B9DFC3C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (2) and inserting <quote>: or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37EBB2D667364C6D9FB51D0205825F52"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H91C7B5ED755D4B46B814FC6CEE1A9AEB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HDB21D965486A45C88E46B924E192945E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person to knowingly help or assist a foreign national in violating this subsection.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96FD32103F2E4F45822E17A129F9658C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply with respect to contributions and donations made on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HDE4BA67924C047A78B3D06562C9B1FB9"><enum>VII</enum><header>Constitutional Experts Panel with Respect to Presidential Elections</header><section id="HE70377A998CA4ABA92AE0A823D39E7D0"><enum>171.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Solving an Overlooked Loophole in Votes for Executives (SOLVE) Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB20B8E8AECDE4200BFD6572F497FACD2"><enum>172.</enum><header>Establishment of panel of constitutional experts</header><subsection id="H2A63B4E1B2AD4C60A812C0608E8A556C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established the <quote>Twentieth Amendment Section Four Panel</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Panel</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF3209E1EC4B4BA480D9A6076DB4458D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="H839DE8F8FB6D407994C9698D24DC5DB6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Panel shall be composed of 6 constitutional experts, of whom—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H44C5EC1C4B1948DDA1D4819FBF66E4F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed by the majority leader of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H15C72D7D24DB47E381272F344E95C5E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed by the minority leader of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3D585A84CC7541B38695F36DAE4EEE97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed jointly by the majority and minority leader of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4771A29D1268454F9B78823B9C48B156"><enum>(D)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HEE3D9798514C425EBEAE4B20DD3D0F85"><enum>(E)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed by minority leader of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF0B5AD79325E4C7C9FD566E68D3A1A3B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>1 shall be appointed jointly by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04D19D12E9044C27B90731B2F89B6402"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appointments of the members of the Panel shall be made not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB6D66D518AA4106A5603A32A8802523"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Vacancy</header><text>Any vacancy occurring in the membership of the Panel shall be filled in the same manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D69982DE09F49318BED9902FFE99A99"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chairperson and Vice Chairperson</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Panel shall select a Chairperson and Vice Chairperson from among the members of the Panel.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H67D52840715C4D149B8ED0FED4FF2CCB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the Panel shall be to recommend to Congress model legislation, which shall provide for an appropriate process, pursuant to section 4 of the Twentieth Amendment to the United States Constitution, to resolve any vacancy created by the death of a candidate in a contingent presidential or vice-presidential election. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE56DC5133770429CA50A6EBACD7B7504"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HCAE13295AEDD490783D34A3907ECE46B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which all of the appointments have been made under subsection (b)(2), the Panel shall submit to Congress an interim report containing the Panel’s findings, conclusions, and recommendations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0413AC22200D4428AB972192996C9039"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the submission of the interim report under paragraph (1), the Panel shall submit to Congress a final report containing the Panel’s findings, conclusions, and recommendations. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E924A9C23CD4739B52594FBEFA8DDFD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Meetings; information</header><paragraph id="H62245BE0740D41AC83684C674DAC859E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Meetings of the Panel shall be held at the Law Library of Congress. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACC9A3BC717E44248C824505976918E5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information</header><text>The Panel may secure from the Law Library of Congress such information as the Panel considers necessary to carry out the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCEA6AE7540DB4F5A851D15EB5B9A68E9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funds</header><paragraph id="HCAFE8226345B4675B201F40AAC8EFC4B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Compensation of members</header><text>Members of the Panel shall receive no compensation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BEB0762F99C4128BED41B67395F311B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other funding</header><text>No amounts shall be appropriated for the purposes of this section, except for any amounts strictly necessary for the Law Library of Congress to execute its responsibilities under subsection (e).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF09214D7B6134246ACE3A4169167EA6D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H30E8BB1F63AD498C924287321DA78D0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The panel established under subsection (a) shall terminate 90 days after the date on which the panel submits the final report required under subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5EABD693A2E483A8958CE8CA4093FEB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Records</header><text>Upon termination of the panel, all of its records shall become the records of the Secretary of the Senate and the Clerk of the House of Representatives. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

