<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB9C4CFC8D2434EDE92F86CCD1ED8C99B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5439 IH: National Risk Management Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5439</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230913">September 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to require the Secretary of Homeland Security to establish a national risk management process, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4AD4202FA22F49CF888E0080B55ABE01" style="OLC"><section id="H132B794E36F14FB6AF4E0523EDF2F658" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Risk Management Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H99F8BBE0F82243069F82470AD0E66A09"><enum>2.</enum><header>National risk management process</header><subsection id="HDB7AC54542FF45AB9DB9BB5A1175A9B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subtitle A of title XXII of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/651">6 U.S.C. 651 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H4D9E5AC644E44FA9BC77E2ABEC888A04" style="OLC"><section id="HC46D8C10994E448388003820188D1E74"><enum>2220F.</enum><header>National risk management process</header><subsection id="HAADC898E410C459686758A66A88E4A75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National critical functions defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>national critical functions</quote> means the functions of government and the private sector so vital to the United States that their disruption, corruption, or dysfunction would have a debilitating effect on security, national economic security, national public health or safety, or any combination thereof.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5EF30D5D3F0D40F38B184DD2954C2079"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National risk management process</header><paragraph id="H3B5115CDB9D34931883D683140429331"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Risk identification and assessment</header><subparagraph id="HB29BAE646E0A426585E5860384C17618" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, shall establish a recurring process to identify and assess risks to critical infrastructure, considering both cybersecurity threats and physical threats, the associated likelihoods of such threats, vulnerabilities within systems rendering such systems susceptible to such threats, and consequences of such threats to critical functions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H927CA920765948B5AEACDAAE7B46051F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In establishing the process required under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall consult the following:</text><clause id="HA75E48BC3CF24495811FECABD4D28B03"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Sector Risk Management Agencies.</text></clause><clause id="H74F79B73BBB94321812C23C67EFF7091"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Critical infrastructure owners and operators.</text></clause><clause id="HFD1F407023874EBAA79BE7251CFF7239"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs.</text></clause><clause id="H8B8E1C62ED984F2291E5D9CA1B757FEC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Assistant to the President for Homeland Security.</text></clause><clause id="HBF4F4B1D50794BBB83038E433CABDC3B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The National Cyber Director.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2487A2F80414138AEAFB0BD10A3B8C6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Process elements</header><text>The process established under subparagraph (A) shall include elements to—</text><clause id="HAD7109EABB854D92A0F3FED14ED66C95" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>collect relevant information, collected pursuant to section 2218, from Sector Risk Management Agencies relating to the threats, vulnerabilities, and consequences related to the particular sectors of those Sector Risk Management Agencies;</text></clause><clause id="H189068E2B8BC46E789F98169149300E3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allow critical infrastructure owners and operators to submit relevant information to the Secretary for consideration; and</text></clause><clause id="H49BFC7368F5E448489A2D6E0AC6E08C2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>outline how the Secretary will solicit input from other Federal departments and agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3932759F08604025A2B8BEB082A28900" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall publish in the Federal Register procedures for the process established under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BD199F0C32E4A6286E5CE3F5A3845F2" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the President, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate, and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives a report on the risks from cybersecurity threats and physical threats identified by the process established under subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HB207AE8935484E3591D744FCDEE038BE" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section; and</text></clause><clause id="H7FBF1D288494436AA57950DD761FF4D5" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary submits a periodic evaluation described in section 9002(b)(2) of title XC of division H of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/652a">6 U.S.C. 652a(b)(2)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3BD7707C2E1459A8629034158F3D717"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National critical infrastructure resilience strategy</header><subparagraph id="H6869EFE9569540E695924152CB88A213"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary submits each report required under paragraph (1), the President shall transmit to the majority and minority leaders of the Senate, the Speaker and minority leader of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate, and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives a national critical infrastructure resilience strategy to address the risks identified by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0579568FAD44D23A17FE19B7211C929"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each strategy under subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="HAFBE411405FA4AF99A6F3B05BD3475F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prioritize areas of risk to critical infrastructure that would compromise or disrupt national critical functions impacting national security, economic security, or public health and safety;</text></clause><clause id="H369B1C45328841AD80509319267B7929"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assess the implementation of the previous national critical infrastructure resilience strategy, as applicable;</text></clause><clause id="HABF723BC5A6E467EBA1B1ED14FC04761"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identify and outline current and proposed national-level actions, programs, and efforts, including resource requirements, to be taken to address the risks identified;</text></clause><clause id="HCE2BDCC425AA446D8804A67491341170"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identify the Federal departments or agencies responsible for leading each national-level action, program, or effort, and the relevant critical infrastructure sectors for each; and</text></clause><clause id="HEFEE96308E904AC7B82A26CEED84DD37"><enum>(v)</enum><text>request any additional authorities necessary to successfully execute the strategy.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1005E56A22941CFBF2B48E580CB7373"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each strategy under subparagraph (A) shall be unclassified but may contain a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3181CD2E7318445A89FF836656B8C1E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Congressional briefing</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the President transmits the first strategy required under paragraph (2)(A) and each year thereafter, the Secretary, in coordination with Sector Risk Management Agencies, shall brief the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives on—</text><subparagraph id="HCF5A7B6911B547A8BFFE19360B885830" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the national risk management process activities undertaken pursuant to the strategy transmitted in accordance with paragraph (2)(A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF4468CF36DE46C4B343EF737C1EA63B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amounts and timeline for funding that the Secretary has determined would be necessary to address risks of cybersecurity threats and physical threats and successfully execute the full range of activities proposed by such strategy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H59CD996E8C4D4C4EADDD789357AF5801" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 2220E the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC8D047D092E04A2DA5EF01EE95CE0FB5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 2220F. National risk management process.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

