<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H489E27409BC54C7A82E0D8F8071D3AFE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6876 IH: Customs Trade Partnership Against Terrorism Pilot Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6876</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000603">Mr. Luttrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a pilot program on the participation of third-party logistics providers in the Customs Trade Partnership Against Terrorism, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF5E17ECED5A64142A9258A76C61A3BD1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H974A3E5D11CE47349947F5957B34EABF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Customs Trade Partnership Against Terrorism Pilot Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CTPAT Pilot Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H740EE205809B4D9A84D51EECC55A5E1C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on participation of third-party logistics providers in CTPAT</header> <subsection id="H8F63B8486E5C41098D16134E01BF0578"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="HEB4674AB8CBB49AD932FD9F412D74EEB" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall carry out a pilot program to assess whether allowing entities described in subsection (b) to participate in CTPAT would enhance port security, combat terrorism, prevent United States supply chain security breaches, or otherwise satisfy the goals of CTPAT.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H22BA42D65B4C4337952392ED3B28D69B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal Register notice</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall publish in the Federal Register a notice for entities described in subsection (b) to apply to participate in the pilot program required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF4F9C652051C40F3B016D45EBEB0534B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>An entity described in this subsection is—</text> 
<paragraph id="H95B2549147A24B1DAD57947475CC9DD5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a non-asset-based third-party logistics provider that—</text> <subparagraph id="H1F40E8C288DB4D34914B9921ADD4B3FD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">arranges international transportation of freight and is licensed or bonded by the Federal Maritime Commission, the Transportation Security Administration, U.S. Customs and Border Protection, or the Department of Transportation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFDDB9DEFD47A44649DAADFA29FC25F68" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>satisfies such other requirements as the Secretary of Homeland Security specifies in the Federal Register notice required pursuant to subsection (a)(2); or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79F20243D8D54C89A8DA2D16C1103665"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an asset-based third-party logistics provider that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8AC1F12FF6734C8BAD40C2B8718F71BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>facilitates cross border activity and is licensed or bonded by the Federal Maritime Commission, the Transportation Security Administration, U.S. Customs and Border Protection, or the Department of Transportation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H863F3C18A1EA49F8BF84C72514CC1A07"><enum>(B)</enum><text>manages and executes logistics services using its own warehousing assets and resources on behalf of its customers; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H29BD1598044D460E8F81210A142B8E6D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>satisfies such other requirements as the Secretary of Homeland Security specifies in the Federal Register notice required pursuant to subsection (a)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H63BC139EC5794402A3AFD8032DB88918"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An entity that wants to participate in the pilot program under subsection (a)(1) shall submit to the Secretary of Homeland Security an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC384CA7A9F344A98A5058A08611DF85D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program under subsection (a)(1), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text> <paragraph id="H1D9731BF8C054E74BFC9C2BEB7CB973B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H76B734FC98C1453289363BA7A8E60467"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than ten entities described in paragraph (1) of subsection (b) participate in the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6EB33F84CA545D1BEA478E9E2F7D061"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than ten entities described in paragraph (2) of such subsection participate in the pilot program;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E633F3851824251B50EA8A1F6D2D95E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide for the participation of each of such categories of entities on a voluntary basis; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E845ECFDFDE40A4A6D44BE34042BDA1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>continue the pilot program for a period of not less than one and not more than five years after the date on which the Secretary publishes the Federal Register notice required pursuant to subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8B266B818A1F4F92B5E4DCBBB1B3E293"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the termination of the pilot program under subsection (d)(3), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the findings of, and any recommendations arising from, the pilot program relating to the participation in CTPAT of entities described in subsection (b), including an assessment of participation by such entities.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H847606B968ED41D5A233265BE843D74B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report on effectiveness of CTPAT</header> <paragraph id="H7E5E9145579B4C308A55A9AFF1CFB799"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report assessing the effectiveness of CTPAT.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE3B7357C40F545798FFEE55A2AAF2D18"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HD567E99393E74264B91A664BE378BEF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An analysis of—</text> 
<clause id="H46285D0C187146DCBE10D1DA003DA2F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>security incidents in the United States cargo supply chain during the five-year period preceding submission of the report that involved criminal activity, including drug trafficking, human smuggling, or terrorist activity; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCC04EC4F992F4BCB965AAB7A6AAF8BA8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether such incidents involved entities participating in CTPAT or entities not participating in CTPAT.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8FE8FDE80F3E40A6867A63795CB70490"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of causes for the suspension or removal of entities from participating in CTPAT as a result of security incidents during the five-year period referred to in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H07CF88DA7A59467DA5824743D2596CFD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An analysis of the number of active CTPAT participants involved in one or more security incidents while maintaining their status as participants.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDD7839C4D6C6408DA4911313381C455F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An analysis of CTPAT’s benefits for its participants.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D84003AD796414C9FED06E22D4A9E83" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations, as appropriate, to the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection for improvements to CTPAT, including with respect to preventing security incidents in the United States cargo supply chain and enhancing CTPAT benefits for participants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE9A39F1167C1449DBB67B4481F5FCC81"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HD5D68D163F6441B595AA760337916AA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBEA94A49BF4340AF8CE6380011598085"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs and the Committee on Finance of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1B69B5182299424EB26C863EEC62DE57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF869AD1020BF482898DFBB8A0C47DEE1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CTPAT</header><text>The term <term>CTPAT</term> means the Customs Trade Partnership Against Terrorism established under subtitle B of title II of the Security and Accountability for Every Port Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/961">6 U.S.C. 961 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

