<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB365B8FEC9954A4E8D723C623DE6B9FE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4627 IH: Afghan Adjustment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4627</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide support for nationals of Afghanistan who supported the United States mission in Afghanistan, adequate vetting for parolees from Afghanistan, adjustment of status for eligible individuals, and special immigrant status for at-risk Afghan allies and relatives of certain members of the Armed Forces, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H238FFB1DDAF645289627BDE44E0C7717" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF339C8A3C1D04777ABD87BA041E5B8D9"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Afghan Adjustment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCFEDCFDB0F1D47F1B3A450A85554D307"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H9CDDFF093C434472ACA04F7B564A89AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H83ACB5B89A1740E091DDD821E4B73A86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSJU00">Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB75A5EC943624BD9B2A0A378C836682F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFE7655115B2C4151BF7A8BA5D5B6D36E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H292720DC48C84C168DD2FB4D40455663"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="SSAP00">Committee on Appropriations of the Senate</committee-name>; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5DA5D26AEFD345E496171850BFF42E09"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H38CB873DA44248609C546E24DEB68B48"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3B1E8B11FCF74CA68E3D88D1B2DF6EB5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives</committee-name>; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H91412746E89D4C18A314C839787DAB6D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives</committee-name>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD4C03E3BAED24D209F27340B1142EB76"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Immigration laws</header><text>The term <term>immigration laws</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101(a)(17) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(17)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H32872348CC444520921C631DDC0C5E64"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Special immigrant status</header><text>The term <term>special immigrant status</term> means special immigrant status provided under—</text> <subparagraph id="H70CF2EE5484B45CC8A0826E6B8DAC4DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Afghan Allies Protection Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/8">Public Law 111–8</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H36E7D34E52FA442697BA3F0652C6B316"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 1059 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/163">Public Law 109–163</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H844DE11B416840188EF2D164F47F4F12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>section 7 or an amendment made by such section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0D675ACE2B324ADAB417873E95FC8AC6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Specified application</header><text>The term <term>specified application</term> means—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2C6665DCC2C249808258ED7E26ADF292"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a pending, documentarily complete application for special immigrant status; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H31E0155DE9264878A5BCC6CA50AECF93" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a case in processing in the United States Refugee Admissions Program for an individual who has received a Priority 1 or Priority 2 referral to such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67907A8E20D64B889CC46E6ACA410F0D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>United states refugee admissions program</header><text>The term <term>United States Refugee Admissions Program</term> means the program to resettle refugees in the United States pursuant to the authorities provided in sections 101(a)(42), 207, and 412 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(42)</external-xref>, 1157, and 1522).</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HBE82029620E24B7585C69E7435498B02"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HABA2D4596FE5413D865532E8E63C6F33"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nationals of Afghanistan residing outside the United States who meet the requirements for admission to the United States through a specified special immigrant visa application have demonstrably aided the United States mission in Afghanistan during the past 20 years; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H30C3F615CE514BECBBA9BDA07F895417"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States should increase support for such nationals of Afghanistan. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="HCCE32527630E4CF68490C836060FA7C9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Support for Afghan allies outside of the United States</header> <subsection id="H988B2B44C3B14E2F8B31AFF621D26379"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Response to congressional inquiries</header><text>The Secretary of State shall respond to inquiries by Members of Congress regarding the status of a specified application submitted by, or on behalf of, a national of Afghanistan, including any information that has been provided to the applicant, in accordance with section 222(f) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1202">8 U.S.C. 1202(f)</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H806C2A7608144FE1B6504406E3C96956"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office in lieu of embassy</header><text>During the period in which there is no operational United States embassy in Afghanistan, the Secretary of State shall designate an appropriate office within the Department of State—</text> <paragraph id="H50EAD6C1CF3A46E59B4C3C48CBF5F95E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to review specified applications submitted by nationals of Afghanistan residing in Afghanistan, including by conducting any required interviews;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC6A782F0E56D48DD84FBCBC6D35BBBD9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to issue visas or other travel documents to such nationals, in accordance with the immigration laws;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46EEF04FB6A848068A9DDD9C9F4964FA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to provide services to such nationals, to the greatest extent practicable, that would normally be provided by an embassy; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H406A4C8AAAE64B25B5518BC34F4D3D9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to carry out any other function that the Secretary considers necessary. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H7DEB0E83E97A4609A33AA19B2FF12569"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interagency Task Force on Afghan Ally Strategy</header> <subsection id="H6D0EDA4222F2497794514B724B57F127"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall establish an Interagency Task Force on Afghan Ally Strategy (referred to in this section as the <quote>Task Force</quote>)—</text>
<paragraph id="HCC9D6D0C3AD3486A8B47E8DE87270567"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to develop and oversee the implementation of the strategy and contingency plan described in subsection (d)(1)(A); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD4252F4E6FC247D0A881D62314E6464C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to submit the report, and provide a briefing on the report, as described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HCC4141EFFE034CFEBAF373E07F305E3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<paragraph id="H886C25AB028A42FD9D6E0F30192C7CFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HA92276F8FB664A4D827CEDF109955A24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1 or more representatives from each relevant Federal agency, as designated by the head of the applicable relevant Federal agency; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6E4A8E28ABF0439FB431EE2CB3F23046"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other Federal Government official designated by the President. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F0E6C3862F04AA9ACCF3CA48FC2F849"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Defined term</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>relevant Federal agency</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0B7F81DDDB08407ABAB4758C690070B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C81A7D5E9B447D4AFA20EEDA4746CE8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department Homeland Security;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB9B94B4B61E48EAACB1414EF192B954"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of Defense;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F17DECD61764F2C8B2039A936A4F0F4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9B902E9E52C3494DAB618EC6D8E6F2C8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Federal Bureau of Investigation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6977B2B9722D4217B4F2B86DD41B6673"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Office of the Director of National Intelligence. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5F0700A8CA234EA69A90B5649D70774E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Task Force shall be chaired by the Secretary of State.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0A8BFD58B5F941DDBEDB8D8031ED04E5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header> <paragraph id="H9559454427F84ECFB4C98B7C2CAA8271"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header> <subparagraph id="H7E3AAD78E2974175979442B7D4A5493B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the Task Force is established, the Task Force, acting through the chair of the Task Force, shall submit a report to the appropriate committees of Congress that includes—</text>
<clause id="H51ACD5512E3B4279B65F4890D7E80737"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a strategy for facilitating the resettlement of nationals of Afghanistan outside the United States who, during the period beginning on October 1, 2001, and ending on September 1, 2021, directly and personally supported the United States mission in Afghanistan, as determined by the Secretary of State in consultation with the Secretary of Defense; and</text></clause> <clause id="H5792DE661F7A4A30ABF2482EEE086678"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a contingency plan for future emergency operations in foreign countries involving foreign nationals who have worked directly with the United States Government, including the Armed Forces of the United States and United States intelligence agencies. </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3AF2A019789F4431BDAC1C7C2962143A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report required under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text> <clause id="H819E7F32301042F1B295DADAB69DC8DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of nationals of Afghanistan who have pending specified applications, disaggregated by—</text>
<subclause id="H2D0479368D28478A858FC7B1E61FF820"><enum>(I)</enum><text>such nationals in Afghanistan and such nationals in a third country; </text></subclause> <subclause id="H5E4423EBBA564A268667ABBC08B02020"><enum>(II)</enum><text>type of specified application; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H46255C7465604F40A0C5E41D30492AE9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>applications that are documentarily complete and applications that are not documentarily complete;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8213A62F66A341B8AB7FBE27469DC266"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an estimate of the number of nationals of Afghanistan who may be eligible for special immigrant status under section 7 or an amendment made by such section;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD93B11BAD50946BCA6ED529A592C3977"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to the strategy required under subparagraph (A)(i)—</text> <subclause id="H5FD9E2FF7533425486FA374737BB4283"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the estimated number of nationals of Afghanistan described in such subparagraph;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H43CCB812D40F4888B95231E5BF5846C7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description of the process for safely resettling such nationals; </text></subclause> <subclause id="H11A4D540850F448F992BC8B8F3EC99E0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a plan for processing such nationals of Afghanistan for admission to the United States, that—</text>
<item id="H2979A1A810A5429CB75663CF8AE0BD7E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>discusses the feasibility of remote processing for such nationals of Afghanistan residing in Afghanistan;</text></item> <item id="HD3EA2C79522A460D940FC23990336334"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>includes any strategy for facilitating refugee and consular processing for such nationals of Afghanistan in third countries, and the timelines for such processing;</text></item>
<item id="H793012C86A334660804676EFC2F20DEB"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>includes a plan for conducting rigorous and efficient vetting of all such nationals of Afghanistan for processing;</text></item> <item id="H7800AEA610484AFB95E013E88AD655DB"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>discusses the availability and capacity of sites in third countries to process applications and conduct any required vetting for such nationals of Afghanistan, including the potential to establish additional sites; and </text></item>
<item id="H7B7BECAC895E44AE9B11E92232FEA554"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>includes a plan for providing updates and necessary information to affected individuals and relevant nongovernmental organizations; </text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H8D87C4422DBA405E9770C22CBF55902A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a description of considerations, including resource constraints, security concerns, missing or inaccurate information, and diplomatic considerations, that limit the ability of the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Homeland Security to increase the number of such nationals of Afghanistan who can be safely processed or resettled; </text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCDBABDB65C1544998C729726B183B51B"><enum>(V)</enum><text>an identification of any resource or additional authority necessary to increase the number of such nationals of Afghanistan who can be processed or resettled; </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44B5D64030F24EAF9A8E5965E1F450F6"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an estimate of the cost to fully implement the strategy; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H94D4297E6A694D90ADC368DEE5A914B1"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>any other matter the Task Force considers relevant to the implementation of the strategy; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HACB5B2A21B37495A86084EB555AABE1A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>with respect to the contingency plan required by subparagraph (A)(ii)—</text>
<subclause id="HB39D21896607473D99AAFA9A8C906D91"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a description of the standard practices for screening and vetting foreign nationals considered to be eligible for resettlement in the United States, including a strategy for vetting, and maintaining the records of, such foreign nationals who are unable to provide identification documents or biographic details due to emergency circumstances;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HCE16D3F279E24699A26717486BEE5691"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a strategy for facilitating refugee or consular processing for such foreign nationals in third countries;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H127942CA4F6E42CE8444B87BA732A8A1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>clear guidance with respect to which Federal agency has the authority and responsibility to coordinate Federal resettlement efforts;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9364CC0B14974818A749FB84A9014FD9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a description of any resource or additional authority necessary to coordinate Federal resettlement efforts, including the need for a contingency fund; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HEF07875DFDE94A3D832CC9E86C5C217E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>any other matter the Task Force considers relevant to the implementation of the contingency plan. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H990805408E6246ECA3CF9C548F5C6CD3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under subparagraph (A) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H712D1919271F4720A9191E6FD0606384"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 60 days after submitting the report required by paragraph (1), the Task Force shall brief the appropriate committees of Congress on the contents of the report.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5106FA9B2299429CB9881189AF5A8D76"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Task Force shall remain in effect until the earlier of—</text>
<paragraph id="HD3C20FAAD2314524B011FAB0812FF010"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the strategy required under subsection (d)(1)(A)(i) has been fully implemented; or </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD52975AF5D6C45B4A4EABEC58D4AC689" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date that is 10 years after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H3FB459C931BD4CC9AC3F804982B91EEB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Adjustment of status for eligible individuals</header>
<subsection id="H00D47159BA0F4D1C8C7665B231D34872"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Defined term</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible individual</term> means an alien who—</text> <paragraph id="H1229DF8C26474A38B5691003800D04FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is present in the United States—</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H01AB65F894884826B2FE23D9612B55B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is a citizen or national of Afghanistan or, in the case of an alien having no nationality, is a person who last habitually resided in Afghanistan; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C036186789A48C18B31A247049118F0"><enum>(3)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFC3582B89A4C4037AB60AD87E1A66BCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>was inspected and admitted to the United States on or before the date of the enactment of this Act;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph indent="up1" id="H266F29019CA24B599D1386B0326D0A01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>was paroled into the United States during the period beginning on July 30, 2021, and ending on the date of the enactment of this Act, provided that such parole has not been terminated by the Secretary of Homeland Security upon written notice; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="H34B5DBD6290B4671A99CBE0326233B58"><enum>(C)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFE334314995A49BCB0EE8E34513D79C4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>was admitted or paroled into the United States after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></clause>
<clause indent="up1" id="H166FAA4A009C4455980CF4C7BCC3DE22"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security, in cooperation with the Secretary of Defense and other Federal agency partners, to have directly and personally supported the United States mission in Afghanistan, to an extent considered comparable to the support provided by individuals who have received Chief of Mission approval as part of their application for special immigrant status.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4E284527331441E9B2BF8458905B2B3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adjustment of status</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall adjust the status of an eligible individual to the status of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence if—</text>
<paragraph id="H8AB88749D39840A7874A598827860060"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the eligible individual—</text> <subparagraph id="HDD623FF47D7C49D4880EDF82B2848FDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submits an application for adjustment of status in accordance with procedures established by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA1C1AA0661E147FA95579F040D05B5DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>meets the requirements of this section; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76C991FD902B4D33B56E144A3629B88B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary determines, in the unreviewable discretion of the Secretary, that the adjustment of status of the eligible individual is not contrary to the national interest, public safety, or national security of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H952F73E1ABE34A3FBC875C8D1393C54F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Admissibility</header>
<paragraph id="H55FF4FBDD678425591E3A98A8C2C49F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the provisions of section 209(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1159">8 U.S.C. 1159(c)</external-xref>) (relating to the admissibility of refugees seeking adjustment of status) shall apply to applicants for adjustment of status under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D928B4264874DEBB9AECD635E81BEE4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional limitations on admissibility</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not waive under section 209(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1159">8 U.S.C. 1159(c)</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H70622A93F5A14458AB3FF7E55E5BA551"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any ground of inadmissibility under paragraph (3) of section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8686B7E20B7E416F956C9F7353E7ADB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any applicable ground of inadmissibility under paragraph (2) of that section that arises due to criminal conduct that was committed in the United States on or after July 30, 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5DB5B15AE974C24BE103FF749371563"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit any other waiver authority applicable under the immigration laws to an applicant for adjustment of status. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7E10EF95CD9A4DEA8586A21C3FDAA856"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interview and vetting requirements</header> <paragraph id="HD3C306A9456D4A41A96E72B1F161C0A5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements for in-person interview and vetting</header> <subparagraph id="HF9A9F9F4848A4977A0D2504EB561D194"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and, as appropriate, the Attorney General, shall establish vetting requirements for applicants seeking adjustment of status under this section that are equivalent in rigor to the vetting requirements for refugees admitted to the United States through the United States Refugee Admissions Program by conducting—</text>
<clause id="H32797BF3355449009DF57987903D062F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an in-person interview (except in the case of a child who was younger than 10 years of age at the time of admission or parole); </text></clause> <clause id="H458CCB19FB214F44A1829A5E7E5566D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>biometric and biographic screening to identify any derogatory information associated with applicants; </text></clause>
<clause id="H027A80F7A30B4437AC6BDC04DED5BAD5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a review and analysis of the data holdings of the Department of Defense, the Department of Homeland Security, and other cooperating interagency partners, including biographic and biometric records, iris scans, fingerprints, voice biometric information, hand geometry biometrics, and other identifiable information; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7C27BECBAFC449F28FE704D8E94D37E3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a review of the information required to be collected under paragraph (2).</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2430DA6E8CA44F77A854937DBE8D3851"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clearance of vetting requirements</header>
<clause id="H0D8C08D647394E96B8E4FEEB6178EF9A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not adjust the status of an eligible individual to that of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence under this section until—</text> <subclause id="HEC9B22FA8C3649CFA66BDD86213A57FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the vetting requirements described in subparagraph (A) have been implemented; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H7BAEA829D5A34CB6AD6D79E0F14F5B54"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the eligible individual clears the vetting requirements established under subparagraph (A). </text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA6DEED5432E641078CDA9CA7B61BB63D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall prioritize the vetting of applicants under this paragraph in a manner that best ensures national security.</text></clause>
<clause id="H9CDD02AC6452471989AC2784E1C01CE5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Previous vetting</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall conduct the vetting requirements established under subparagraph (A) with respect to each applicant for adjustment of status under this section regardless of whether the applicant has undergone previous vetting. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD78C3DD2D3414D769B1A06FD9730739E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Interview at port of entry</header><text>An interview of an individual by a U.S. Customs and Border Protection official at a port of entry shall not be considered to satisfy the in-person interview requirement under subparagraph (A)(i).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF77B6FD0316543FB97382A9A3EFF022C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph may be construed to require, as part of the vetting requirements under this subsection, that the Secretary of Homeland Security collect from an applicant any biometric information that the Department of Homeland Security already has on file.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F9422F8025B4C1E8F88CEB344ABAE1F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vetting database requirement</header> <subparagraph id="H8849FDFAAF9644AB8EA00A3002292102"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and, as appropriate, partners in the intelligence community (including officials of the Department of State, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and the National Counterterrorism Center), shall maintain records that contain, for each applicant under this section for the duration of the pendency of their application for adjustment of status—</text>
<clause id="H81CC32CDCA5C4CA9ADA557ED6F59EE15"><enum>(i)</enum><text>personal biographic information, including name and date of birth;</text></clause> <clause id="HCC6B973B282943FC85CA384190E8AF98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>biometric information, including, where available, iris scans, photographs, and fingerprints; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H60A3E7FD37D8497387E67AFA513E593F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the results of all vetting by the United States Government to which the applicant has submitted, including whether the individual has undergone an in-person vetting interview, and any recurrent vetting.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8F0EF7C96D44DD4A111816B36CADF79"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information sharing</header><text>In response to a request from the Secretary of Homeland Security, in accordance with subparagraph (A), Federal agencies shall share information to the extent authorized by law. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3A70275DBA47482D8FE23F2FD501E595"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary of Homeland Security to maintain records under any other law.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5004CCC77D6D4A4192282F08E85E823E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Record of admission</header> <paragraph id="H55D3612C40734C71B35F7E1C839D1971"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Priority for those who supported the United States mission in Afghanistan</header><text>Upon the approval of an application for adjustment of status under this section submitted by an applicant (and the spouse and child of an applicant, if otherwise eligible for adjustment of status under this section) who submits documentation establishing that the applicant has received Chief of Mission approval as part of their application for special immigrant status, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall create a record of the alien’s admission as a lawful permanent resident as of the date on which the alien was inspected and admitted or paroled into the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B91B5F69D774BFE9F3BBE8B87D2F435"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other applicants</header><text>Upon the approval of an application for adjustment of status under this section submitted by an applicant other than an applicant described in paragraph (1), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall create a record of the alien’s admission as a lawful permanent resident as of the date on which the alien’s application for adjustment of status under this section was approved. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H288FF8D51F89443DA04F95B0E0E33FA1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Deadline for application</header> <paragraph id="H2DCCF39D820E41B79D05EECD91D1BE07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), an individual described in subsection (a) may only adjust status under this section if the individual submits an application for adjustment of status not later than the later of—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEDF6FF4BA6D7481B97A74129EBFDF5AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date that is 2 years after the date on which final guidance described in subsection (i)(2) is published; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF73C1D33DE614BD0ADD58DFFAD026AF4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date that is 2 years after the date on which such individual becomes eligible to apply for adjustment of status under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H96DCEF14B5FA49AC9EF04C12B630657D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An application under this section may be considered after the applicable date described in paragraph (1), if the applicant demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Secretary of Homeland Security the existence of extraordinary circumstances relating to the delay in submission of the application. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD0378F5E687D40B3BBB3985EAF746622"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Prohibition on further authorization of parole</header><text>An individual described in subsection (a) who was paroled into the United States shall not be authorized for an additional period of parole if such individual fails to submit an application for adjustment of status by the deadline described in subsection (f).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA44C792699AB45519F083702440FE514"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Employment authorization</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security may extend the period of employment authorization provided to an individual described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (a)(2) to the extent that the individual has been granted any additional period of parole. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H375FFE1D244C430AA1BB81B2A24C8EC8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="H8E5D2EF9AA8449218AC22D3BA956A8BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim guidance</header> <subparagraph id="H3EB6AEAFBF8D4A81AE0A30F44CF952AA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall issue guidance implementing this section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFB0148A399134C3798CEE7BE68143F39"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Notwithstanding section 553 of title 5, United States Code, guidance issued pursuant to subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="H772CAF80874A43AE8927F877EE06831C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may be published on the internet website of the Department of Homeland Security; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H00A2476B8D5641F59AF1F831A9B47964"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall be effective on an interim basis immediately upon such publication, but may be subject to change and revision after notice and an opportunity for public comment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD588AAE9F7A34E678ABB08CC523804A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final guidance</header> <subparagraph id="HD0FC6CEDB64847ADBDD2C8BB8B59949B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall finalize the guidance implementing this section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA116667E4CB6482DAF2569DCACBE4955"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption from the administrative procedures act</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">Chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Administrative Procedures Act</quote>) shall not apply to the guidance issued under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H87A17792543F444A8226CFBBC996CE82"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Administrative review</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide applicants for adjustment of status under this section with the same right to, and procedures for, administrative review as are provided to applicants for adjustment of status under section 245 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1255">8 U.S.C. 1255</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HADC3BA842BAC410483B9E436E14A4831"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not charge a fee to any eligible individual in connection with—</text> <paragraph id="HFA6777FD32D642AD807132DDC9873CAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an application for adjustment of status or employment authorization under this section; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE5B0A9F746F24ECF851DB8C1876D2DC1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the initial issuance of a permanent resident card or an employment authorization document under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H74DDF964F6064A72A7E06077E6C60853"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Pending applications</header> <paragraph id="HE2C1D3C3BA814FF29344A5E4B8D1D020"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>During the period beginning on the date on which an alien files a bona fide application for adjustment of status under this section and ending on the date on which the Secretary of Homeland Security makes a final administrative decision regarding such application, an applicant included in such application who remains in compliance with all application requirements may not be—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4169DF019EF744F9BEBAC808317E88DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>removed from the United States unless the Secretary of Homeland Security makes a prima facie determination that the alien is, or has become, ineligible for adjustment of status under this section;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5BD696936DBE46EA941D3B9AC82CBBD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>considered unlawfully present under section 212(a)(9)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(9)(B)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF1299C04B2414A59AD171B280FA8A83A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>considered an unauthorized alien (as defined in section 274A(h)(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1324a">8 U.S.C. 1324a(h)(3)</external-xref>)) if the alien has applied for and has been issued an employment authorization document.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4F6A4A8B48DE43EC9BF56E6C4548E3A9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect on other applications</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, in the interest of efficiency, the Secretary of Homeland Security may pause consideration of any other application for immigration benefits pending adjudication so as to prioritize an application for adjustment of status pursuant to this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2275E27EFBFA446F97C6FEB60431D735"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Eligibility for benefits</header>
<paragraph id="H38A35A0790854E858282307744D7D34F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law—</text> <subparagraph id="HEFE42D2A312F4CEAA152859212F3C289"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual described in subsection (a) of section 2502 of the Afghanistan Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note, <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/43">Public Law 117–43</external-xref>) shall retain his or her eligibility for the benefits and services described in subsection (b) of such section if the individual has a pending application under this section or is granted adjustment of status under this section; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H05D1D02EC5E5457B9105AACF27D8AC48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such benefits and services shall remain available to the individual to the same extent and for the same periods of time as such benefits and services are otherwise available to refugees who acquire such status.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D4CB5CA35F842719C8B29CB2D390D37"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception from five-year limited eligibility for means-tested public benefits</header><text> Section 403(b)(1) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1613">8 U.S.C. 1613(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9C6B50B25FC04E97BD9CD63C910624D5">
<subparagraph id="H8295C8BC7039435EA069D1840F4ADE4E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>An alien who status is adjusted to that of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence under section 6 of the <short-title>Afghan Adjustment Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H37141E8F76744BA4B749F9831448FAA7"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Parents and legal guardians of unaccompanied children</header><text>A parent or legal guardian of an eligible individual shall be eligible for adjustment of status under this section if—</text>
<paragraph id="HE7EB403248034B4E874153298FA4C447"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the eligible individual was under 18 years of age on the date on which the eligible individual was admitted or paroled into the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9EDE9AFB81C344BDB0E4831E65B6DF9D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such parent or legal guardian was paroled into or admitted to the United States after the date referred to in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H710019D17E0744E2916211A10931C8C5"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Exemption from numerical limitations</header>
<paragraph id="HB87337A91C1C408E8E740B7522214FA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Aliens granted adjustment of status under this section shall not be subject to the numerical limitations under sections 201, 202, and 203 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151</external-xref>, 1152, and 1153). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CE7D00371814E8B935C1722F358B754"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Spouse and children beneficiaries</header><text>A spouse or child who is the beneficiary of an immigrant petition under section 204 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1154">8 U.S.C. 1154</external-xref>) filed by an alien who has been granted adjustment of status under this section, seeking classification of the spouse or child under section 203(a)(2)(A) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1153">8 U.S.C. 1153(a)(2)(A)</external-xref>) shall not be subject to the numerical limitations under sections 201, 202, and 203 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151</external-xref>, 1152, and 1153). </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H974EFC085A764E968E1A1023A707EAB6"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Notification of eligible individuals</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall make reasonable efforts to notify eligible individuals, including eligible individuals who independently departed United States Government facilities, with respect to—</text> <paragraph id="H8C4BAED645DD4058A6192AE42AA03857"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the requirements for applying to adjust status under this section;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H432F357D98F549DA87BFA80AB475DEF7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the deadline for submitting an application; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4F8FC42162040DCB10CDF40C3FEEF88"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the consequences under subsection (g) for failing to apply for adjustment of status.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEB98FA71471C46EDA264709ACED0B380"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header>
<paragraph id="HAAB15433A43D4378B37B901C934EB5D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report and consultation on vetting requirements</header>
<subparagraph id="H5CE950A1545D4569932210B83C604627"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial congressional consultation on vetting</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Secretary of Defense shall jointly inform and consult with the appropriate committees of Congress, in a classified or unclassified setting, with respect to the vetting requirements for applicants seeking adjustment of status under this section, including the nature of the interview and biometric and biographical screening processes required for such applicants and the amount of time needed by the agencies to set up the procedures and database required by this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D3B072E252D4F828534193E8A2E3036"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Second congressional consultation on vetting</header><text>Not later than the earlier of the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act or the date on which the Secretary of Homeland Security begins accepting applications for adjustment of status under this Act, the Secretary shall provide to the appropriate committees of Congress with a second consultation on—</text>
<clause id="H100F2AB61C974024B3EC3C272F9BC3C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the status of the vetting under this section, including the steps the Secretary has taken to respond to feedback provided during the initial consultation under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> <clause id="H0866DF6F28D940FDA785EE7F8E54C403"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the progress of the Secretary toward fully setting up the procedures and database required by this section. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8AA754AD1E2348BAA1A65FA0EBB20261"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header>
<subparagraph id="H5F75363F18BC4D60A0D1DEC9C7E9F50D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the application deadline under subsection (f)(1)(A), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide the appropriate committees of Congress with a briefing on the status of the vetting under this section of eligible individuals, including a plan for addressing any identified security concerns.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE8DDCDEC780144779F68B246B75BE56D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Element</header><text>The briefing required by subparagraph (A) shall include information on individuals who are eligible for adjustment of status under this section but did not—</text>
<clause id="H5FA2C6A37A054AB6995CE48615E7B29C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit an application for adjustment of status under this section; or </text></clause> <clause id="HAED58B1672794C11A817AD4AE7EB9DE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>meet the requirements of subsection (f)(2). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4DD622D32A044A79BBAF07F8A6EC1F32"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information request by Member of Congress</header><text>Upon request by a Member of Congress on behalf of an applicant or by any of the appropriate committees of Congress, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide, in a classified or an unclassified setting, as appropriate, the basis for an exercise of discretion under subsection (b)(2) that resulted in the denial of an application for adjustment of status. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H777D7D1C140E4DC88189E7B8CA76C27D"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to preclude an eligible individual from applying for or receiving any immigration benefit to which the eligible individual is otherwise entitled.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H82387CE70CC748FBAD6B541C549FD792"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Authorization for appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security $20,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2023 through 2027 to carry out this section. </text></subsection></section> <section id="HDFC4BA5D7F3343BC9FC5C01D5C184070"><enum>7.</enum><header>New category of special immigrant visas for at-risk Afghan allies and relatives of certain members of the Armed Forces</header> <subsection id="H2FCF26F32EBD455FB23C9C7EF79AFB09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>At-Risk Afghan allies</header> <paragraph id="HB309C8BC877F4E3781DC1ECF2EDB92C8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, or, notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of State may provide an alien described in paragraph (2) (and the spouse and children of the alien if accompanying or following to join the alien) with the status of a special immigrant under section 101(a)(27) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(27)</external-xref>) if—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7CD5F9D328E44773821281FB51BCC15A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the alien or an agent acting on behalf of the alien submits a request for a recommendation under paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC5CABCF9E08048FAAFFE2646FA8B4EE8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the alien is otherwise admissible to the United States and eligible for lawful permanent residence (excluding the grounds of inadmissibility under section 212(a)(4) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(4)</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF8AE1697714E42C9932699EE9B5B00AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to the alien, the Secretary of Defense has made a positive recommendation under paragraph (3). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDC427FD075149528646CF52C3226896"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alien described</header> <subparagraph id="H6D6274D23ED84AB498486D7F8FC074D2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An alien described in this paragraph is an alien who—</text>
<clause id="H940C19BBF617405B94068A0527B4B250"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a citizen or national of Afghanistan;</text></clause> <clause id="H3A6024D66BFF4318A0BE141E24AEBB95"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was—</text>
<subclause id="H44C35DA451A3490E8B20E0FD822541CA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a member of—</text> <item id="H5BECFBA7B50B4107BD562A36945BCF52"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the special operations forces of the Afghanistan National Defense and Security Forces;</text></item>
<item id="HE1EA1FAD4C1A4C56BD62D45F02399D91"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Afghanistan National Army Special Operations Command;</text></item> <item id="H474DCB5E5CAB46B4A11A373682D775E6"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the Afghan Air Force; or</text></item>
<item id="HC76F00B7B00944D9B190D27E0F865950"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>the Special Mission Wing of Afghanistan; </text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HCCD601A3044D40D9BCA19D893B5718BB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a female member of any other entity of the Afghanistan National Defense and Security Forces, including—</text>
<item id="H1EA958625B5C4F029E3CFBB2ED411203"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a cadet or instructor at the Afghanistan National Defense University; and</text></item> <item id="H91EDFDBD914144BA8AFEDB9ACAA70B38"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a civilian employee of the Ministry of Defense or the Ministry of Interior Affairs;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="HB201D7B9555A45C4B0E85A615D703681"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an individual associated with former Afghan military and police human intelligence activities, including operators and Department of Defense sources;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAC6452C38EAF4EA7B39339054B157E5A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an individual associated with former Afghan military counterintelligence;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC2558A75A03E4F73A95DBA325A98A5D7"><enum>(V)</enum><text>an individual associated with the former Afghan Ministry of Defense who was involved in the prosecution and detention of combatants; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2D1DDD6F5E2545A8A9BE41D0CBF60656" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a senior military officer, senior enlisted personnel, or civilian official who served on the staff of the former Ministry of Defense or the former Ministry of Interior Affairs of Afghanistan; </text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H9D71488C939144578EC8D7F05FBE39B9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provided service to an entity or organization described in clause (ii) for not less than 1 year during the period beginning on December 22, 2001, and ending on September 1, 2021, and did so in support of the United States mission in Afghanistan; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD5AD3F9001984028834D62FFE004FC38"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is recommended positively by the Secretary of Defense to the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Homeland Security, based on a consideration of the information described in paragraph (3)(A)(ii). </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8DE732B9DC6045F8B79B3E2E2665A47F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>For purposes of eligibility under this paragraph, the Afghanistan National Defense and Security Forces includes members of the security forces under the Ministry of Defense and the Ministry of Interior Affairs of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, including the Afghanistan National Army, the Afghan Air Force, the Afghanistan National Police, and any other entity designated by the Secretary of Defense as part of the Afghanistan National Defense and Security Forces during the relevant period of service of the applicant concerned. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1B4C681F0AC412EBC5B58464DB9ABF9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Department of Defense recommendation</header> <subparagraph id="H02AC42CBDEDE4BA8BDF6B30F29FBD563" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to each principal applicant under this section, as soon as practicable after receiving a request for a recommendation, the Secretary of Defense shall—</text>
<clause id="H3BAF0DC138E545EE8C7C412D46936C78" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>review—</text> <subclause id="H13740874022B4F01901AFDBF66458D0A" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEE7B1797F65D475693B497FEFCB32816"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the service record of the principal applicant, if available; or</text></item>
<item indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H514A0617C4714AE7AE486748B7E7A968"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>if the principal applicant provides a service record, any information that helps verify the service record concerned; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE31B6449C37B4E38825B5CF619D50A28"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the data holdings of the Department of Defense and other cooperating interagency partners, including biographic and biometric records, iris scans, fingerprints, voice biometric information, hand geometry biometrics, other identifiable information, and any other information related to the applicant, including relevant derogatory information;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H2411A83875C14A2695DE20A460EF30FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>submit a positive or negative recommendation to the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Homeland Security as to whether the principal applicant meets the requirements under paragraph (2) without significant derogatory information; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD475D937C0F64AF3916B93629416DF7C" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>submit with such recommendation—</text>
<subclause id="HF74404BF4F5D42F6860F916B285590E8" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum>
<item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6FA0AF5510E14997B30A4C85ED808996"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>any service record concerned, if available; or</text></item> <item id="H3309EC3A4B704A1196207FA0FAC10273" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>if the principal applicant provides a service record, any information that helps verify the service record concerned; and</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H403C182CC8D94EA59A876FCEE47925EF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any biometrics for the principal applicant that have been collected by the Department of Defense.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H381FCFA0F5C748D5A2B1E98DC8F8BBAB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of no available service records</header><text>If no service records are available for a principal applicant, the Secretary of Defense may review any referral from a former or current official of the Department of Defense who has knowledge of the principal applicant’s service as described in paragraph (2)(A)(ii). </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAC7AFEDCF4624D268C0DF07D3392C511"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Personnel to support recommendations</header><text>Any limitation in law on the number of personnel within the Office of the Secretary of Defense, the military departments, or the defense agencies shall not apply to personnel employed for the primary purpose of carrying out this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H92E4D446D8CD4999A7685B01AF22D851"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Review process for negative Department of Defense recommendation</header> <clause id="H7565783A41CD4529AEB1CE471EC703E7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An applicant who has a negative recommendation from the Department of Defense, as described in subparagraph (A)(ii), or with derogatory information shall—</text>
<subclause id="H516D2A71A4BB44529DAA52ACDAD71C16"><enum>(I)</enum><text>receive a written notice of negative recommendation from the Secretary of Defense that provides, to the maximum extent practicable, information describing the basis for the negative recommendation, including the facts and inferences, or evidentiary gaps, underlying the individual determination; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4FB1E295ABDD489DADD94939DB84CEC5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>be provided not more than 1 written appeal to the Secretary of Defense for each such negative recommendation.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HB948931C4A5F4051975098DF8D5F3483"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Deadline for appeal</header><text>An appeal under subclause (II) of clause (i) shall be submitted not more than 120 days after the date on which the applicant concerned receives a decision under subclause (I) of that clause, or thereafter at the discretion of the Secretary of Defense or the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></clause> <clause id="H3F64477F7BB04D06BFD3DDA69B403B17"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Request to reopen</header> <subclause id="H965D049D303945EDB7682E1265F15DA1"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An applicant who receives a negative recommendation under clause (i) may submit a request for a Department of Defense recommendation so that the applicant may provide additional information, clarify existing information, or explain any unfavorable information. </text></subclause>
<subclause id="H31FBEF34E9FE4582A6533A16A1E0C58B"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>After considering 1 such request to reopen from an applicant, the Secretary of Defense may deny subsequent requests to reopen submitted by the same applicant.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD3C96B796F574944A1EE17A4010D24A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special immigrant visas for certain relatives of certain members of the Armed Forces</header><text>Section 101(a)(27) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(27)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H2839A434507942A5B94D6946D2BD4A0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (L)(iii), by adding a semicolon at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H612C21C1F8334555A75AC185B50092E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (M), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC09B0ACA7FC74445AFE6C3F0A571DC55"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11A11B14EEE84E1AAEDCB23F3598307B"> <subparagraph id="H04797357772A4D6D97D56B7E7D378BAD"><enum>(N)</enum><text>a citizen or national of Afghanistan who is the parent or brother or sister of—</text>
<clause id="H3CBC0FCAEC484956BB6C10D8C72BE666"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a member of the armed forces (as defined in section 101(a) of title 10, United States Code); or</text></clause> <clause id="H17F29F4268CD41D099D1108BEB3E3FA7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran (as defined in section 101 of title 38, United States Code).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFB1BAEDE6EE0480293509C83339C2BED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>General provisions</header>
<paragraph id="H342F7F777ACD42D3898054603F5A0677"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Defense, or the Secretary of State may not charge any fee in connection with an application for, or issuance of, a special immigrant visa or special immigrant status under—</text> <subparagraph id="H0D78B468B1424475A748232C4110BE97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>this section or an amendment made by this section; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2B823FCADBD647FEA169E602C9963036"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 602 of the Afghan Allies Protection Act of 2009 ( <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/8">Public Law 111–8</external-xref>); or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C8C712D04B1454ABDDE5FB2268B4DDA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>section 1059 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/163">Public Law 109–163</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF6FD5F9ECF5442D9BCC5BC2F0FF5C19A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>An alien applying for admission to the United States under this section, or an amendment made by this section, may be represented during the application process, including at relevant interviews and examinations, by an attorney or other accredited representative. Such representation shall not be at the expense of the United States Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61CFA968CA604EC49FE5C3C1EB7D95CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Numerical limitations</header> <subparagraph id="HCFB84CBEF96B458EB2F2BEC7F0C4C13C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), the total number of principal aliens who may be provided special immigrant visas under this section may not exceed 11,500 each fiscal year.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFD74B7A2A89E4AD2B93FFDCE9D4FF2AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Carryover</header><text>If the numerical limitation specified in subparagraph (A) is not reached during a given fiscal year, the numerical limitation specified in such subparagraph for the following fiscal year shall be increased by a number equal to the difference between—</text> <clause id="H6D620266A14A4A86BDFD914E021FCC2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the numerical limitation specified in subparagraph (A) for the given fiscal year; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H53B1AEB340C744ADAB108356B0D1F0C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of principal aliens provided special immigrant visas under this section during the given fiscal year.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCECC8FC6EBBD49A6A16F9D61287006B7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Maximum number of visas</header><text>The total number of principal aliens who may be provided special immigrant visas under this section shall not exceed 34,500.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H966E80A540B54FE1A2B307B662D243A3"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Duration of authority</header><text>The authority to issue visas under this section shall—</text> <clause id="H3E398B60499146B2B96EC2DC30A08E3C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>commence on the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H4007D43FFD2A4D6185CDCC0B0FE6CAB5" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>terminate on the date on which all such visas are exhausted. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H430A0F1701D84A4BA677CD59910221F8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exclusion from numerical limitations</header><text>Aliens provided special immigrant visas under this section, or an amendment made by this section, shall not be counted against any numerical limitation under sections 201(d), 202(a), or 203(b)(4) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151(d)</external-xref>, 1152(a), and 1153(b)(4)) or section 602 of the Afghan Allies Protection Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/8">Public Law 111–8</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H78C1E0A222814A139F6BE0BDC4114548"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Order of consideration</header><text>Immigrant visas shall be made available under this section to eligible immigrants in the order in which the Secretary of Defense has issued a recommendation under subsection (a)(3), subject to the requirements of the adjudication process. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC39984CDA33649A09A895737BECA1B75"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Protection of aliens</header><text>The Secretary of State, in consultation with the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies, shall make a reasonable effort to provide an alien who is seeking status as a special immigrant under this section, or an amendment made by this section, protection or to immediately remove such alien from Afghanistan, if possible.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD3535BE0766A45DAADB717271F305FA6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Other eligibility for immigrant status</header><text>No alien shall be denied the opportunity to apply for admission under this section, or an amendment made by this section, solely because the alien qualifies as an immediate relative or is eligible for any other immigrant classification.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC2FADB3B596348ECA97CDC8EB5E66FDD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Resettlement support</header><text>A citizen or national of Afghanistan who is admitted to the United States as a special immigrant under this section or an amendment made by this section shall be eligible for resettlement assistance, entitlement programs, and other benefits available to refugees admitted under section 207 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>) to the same extent, and for the same periods of time, as such refugees.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H06C7AD8B19884E97AE476FC9EF54CAED"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Adjustment of status</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (2), (7), or (8) of subsection (c) of section 245 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1255">8 U.S.C. 1255</external-xref>), the Secretary of Homeland Security may adjust the status of an alien described in subparagraph (N) of section 101(a)(27) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(27)</external-xref>) or subsection (a)(2) of this section to that of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence under subsection (a) of such section 245 if the alien—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BFB34B4B75D47C3B20BA8E259C3A738"><enum>(A)</enum><text>was paroled or admitted as a nonimmigrant into the United States; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H57E41B86DC154BFF8BADC221ED989AA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is otherwise eligible for status as a special immigrant under—</text> <clause id="HA031695DC1124380A622E462249D745A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>this section; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HECCDF30632FC4F5E9FBA5CEBF2E807BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0C9FCED3A36403895E0EF5E6410C5AD"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Health and Human Services such sums as are necessary for each of the fiscal years 2023 through 2033 to carry out this section and the amendments made by this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HD22F6B570A6C429D9795281C3BAA1461"><enum>8.</enum><header>Support for allies seeking resettlement in the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during Operation Allies Welcome, Enduring Welcome, and any successor operation, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Secretary of State may waive any fee or surcharge or exempt individuals from the payment of any fee or surcharge collected by the Department of Homeland Security and the Department of State, respectively, in connection with a petition or application for, or issuance of, an immigrant visa to a national of Afghanistan under section 201(b)(2)(A)(i) or 203(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act, <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(b)(2)(A)(i)</external-xref> and 1153(a), respectively. </text></section> <section id="H5B3FA830B7D1460D8DA8FE6D5C57DB0D"><enum>9.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, and the application of the remaining provisions of this Act to any person or circumstance, shall not be affected.</text></section>
<section id="H6E213AE6261248D8886633F155C2FC33"><enum>10.</enum><header>Date limitation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security may not grant an application for adjustment of status under section 6 or an application for special immigrant status under section 7, or an amendment made by section 7, before the Secretary has implemented the vetting procedures required by this Act, and in no event before January 1, 2024.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

