<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF2BE962DFB5E49EAA5BA8871396606A5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6201 IH: Iranian Sanctions Enforcement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6201</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish and authorize funding for an Iranian Sanctions Enforcement Fund to enforce United States sanctions with respect to Iran and its proxies and pay off the United States public debt and to codify the Export Enforcement Coordination Center.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9BDC17C6C02346AA8FBE57558AFB2EB7" style="OLC"><section id="H54D7F2F30DDD4326BB365F8F5E70876F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iranian Sanctions Enforcement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7F84E7EAEC3F4E75A81605601C267F08"><enum>2.</enum><header>Iran Sanctions Enforcement Fund</header><subsection id="H9B6161EC4CC84B95B3C3BD3385CF6947"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 15 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, there shall be established in the Treasury of the United States a fund, to be known as the <quote>Iran Sanctions Enforcement Fund</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>), to pay expenses relating to seizures and forfeitures of property made with respect to violations by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H27DC22E1F6344F9C993AE04B084B3B65"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation of Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, shall appoint an administrator for the Fund (in this section referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H8CF1CFC6FC9F43F69AFC1724BB3899AA" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures from the Fund</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H084EFE859B5E4F6E84181A79EB868552"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may authorize amounts from the Fund to be used, without further appropriation or fiscal year limitation, for payment of all proper expenses relating to a covered seizure or forfeiture, including the following:</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC1F6794B69A476781A4345D287DB3F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Investigative costs incurred by a law enforcement agency of the Department of Homeland Security or the Department of Justice. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB8638D12EA445EF8E1E0D6042981FAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Expenses of detention, inventory, security, maintenance, advertisement, or disposal of the property seized or forfeited, and if condemned by a court and a bond for such costs was not given, the costs as taxed by the court.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H055AED828E7C42EDBDFD463BFE8EEB4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Costs of—</text><clause id="HF91BF2A924EC4BBE86AA623D65DCCFB5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>contract services relating to a covered seizure or forfeiture;</text></clause><clause id="H1CF2C84A47E14CFCAA246561E20C3385"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the employment of outside contractors to operate and manage properties seized or forfeited or to provide other specialized services necessary to dispose of such properties in an effort to maximize the return from such properties; and</text></clause><clause id="H4CE48F9A29A64EFABA75DB963B87E8F3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>reimbursing any Federal, State, or local agency for any expenditures made to perform the functions described in this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB9D7B0D834A425AA9E9E38CF06049F7" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Payments to reimburse any covered Federal agency for investigative costs incurred leading to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD315D743AAF34A38BA76020EBAE71372"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Payments for contracting for the services of experts and consultants needed by the Department of Homeland Security or the Department of Justice to assist in carrying out duties related to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD29DB5FD2BA43ACB8CE934F25692CFF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Awards of compensation to informers for assistance provided with respect to a violation by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States that leads to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AF458A705C44E9B9727B04A43CE005C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Equitable sharing payments made to other Federal agencies, State and local law enforcement agencies, and foreign governments for expenses incurred with respect to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93530A40AFE74840A7CB70BDEA9DD106"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Payment of overtime pay, salaries, travel, fuel, training, equipment, and other similar expenses of State or local law enforcement officers that are incurred in joint law enforcement operations with a covered Federal agency relating to covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC17676B5FCE4CE6BFEBC89A4E64B22A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of use of Fund for additional purposes</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may direct the Administrator to authorize the use of amounts in the Fund for the following:</text><subparagraph id="HB5F1C8A9B3014280ADE09AEEA4C48A7F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Payment of awards for information or assistance leading to a civil or criminal forfeiture made with respect to a violation by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States and involving any covered Federal agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAC99D1F5D0343789991EAB41D8F3035" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Purchases of evidence or information by a covered Federal agency with respect to a violation by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States that leads to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H584A6B5221B64BB8A7CB7821AAF224B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Payment for equipment for any vessel, vehicle, or aircraft available for official use by a covered Federal agency to enable the vessel, vehicle, or aircraft to assist in law enforcement functions relating to a covered seizure or forfeiture, and for other equipment directly related to a covered seizure or forfeiture, including laboratory equipment, protective equipment, communications equipment, and the operation and maintenance costs of such equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC834B76CD222424FB9B649E74274AC83"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Payment for equipment for any vessel, vehicle, or aircraft for official use by a State or local law enforcement agency to enable the vessel, vehicle, or aircraft to assist in law enforcement functions relating to a covered seizure or forfeiture if the vessel, vehicle, or aircraft will be used in joint law enforcement operations with a covered Federal agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB10D47B180A64204A800922646E35D29"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Reimbursement of individuals or organizations for expenses incurred by such individuals or organizations in cooperating with a covered Federal agency in investigations and undercover law enforcement operations relating to a covered seizure or forfeiture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H95566519414F43F5B849F6CA7200737B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prioritization of activities within the Fund</header><text>In allocating amounts from the Fund for the purposes described in paragraphs (1) and (2), the Administrator shall prioritize activities that result in the seizure and forfeiture of oil or petroleum products or other commodities or methods of exchange that fund the efforts of Iran or covered Iranian proxies to carry out acts of international terrorism or otherwise kill United States citizens. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H117D90FA5838470D87E18A22546605B7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Management of Fund</header><text>The Fund shall be managed and invested in the same manner as a trust fund is managed and invested under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/9602">section 9602</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1EFEB587C3A6482F93E1EFFF7A899DB0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20A9C82CEC7C4FDA9C8F6B8E343FE607"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Initial funding</header><subparagraph id="H0FB0688D96BE49F4A789A0765617A103"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Fund $150,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E44EBF7DD1C41FF90D304BFBF665F74"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Repayment of initial funding</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F70553A5E12472CBF256B68BBC6D1D1"><enum>(i)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2034, the Administrator shall transfer from the Fund into the general fund of the Treasury an amount equal to $150,000,000, as adjusted pursuant to paragraph (4).</text></clause><clause id="HB584B2B785534379866EE4A35F5981EC" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The repayment of amounts under clause (i) shall not be construed as a termination of the authority for operation of the Fund.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC86C0BD96B0419094A751C805F009E5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Continued operation and funding</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H579C97DAAC60468A914859A1DC286063"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the net proceeds from the sale of property, forfeited or paid to the United States, arising from a violation by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States, shall be deposited or transferred into the Fund.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A0CCD9D0CBC48D18F002431C872ADED" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Transfer of proceeds after deposits into the Justice for United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Act</header><text>The deposit or transfer of any net proceeds to the Fund under subparagraph (A) shall occur after the deposit or transfer of net proceeds into the United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Fund as required by subsection (e)(2)(A)(ii) of the Justice for United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20144">34 U.S.C. 20144</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96BEB5B1E79C4004A8ACC8CE45374AD5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maximum end-of-year balance</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H726479EF912E46E6AA3C7986E98FED12"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, at the end of a fiscal year, the amount in the Fund exceeds the amount specified in subparagraph (B), the Administrator shall transfer the amount in excess of the amount specified in subparagraph (B) to the general fund of the Treasury for the payment of the public debt of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9CE8A1FFD0A94C2BB70CA6011E1ED73F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount specified</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount specified in this subparagraph is—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67EF098B511B4AA88CD247E506C29E23"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in fiscal year 2024, $500,000,000; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE9C15D82CD24DCD8A40969F85AA882B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in any fiscal year thereafter, $500,000,000, as adjusted pursuant to paragraph (4).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E585F1C7D8B4B2F99D0A6B8B5AB38BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Adjustments for inflation</header><subparagraph id="HE9E6BEB72F8942F0A87BA8926925E91F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amounts described in paragraphs (1)(B)(i) and (3)(B)(ii) shall be adjusted, at the beginning of each of fiscal years 2025 through 2034, to reflect the percentage (if any) of the increase in the average of the Consumer Price Index for the preceding 12-month period compared to the Consumer Price Index for fiscal year 2023.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC1024D6717746FDA5950D689B4DE443"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consumer price index defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>Consumer Price Index</term> means the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A20826B5C8D46E6A381F184883D6365"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Prohibition on transfer of funds</header><paragraph id="H70AA143EC7DD41E1A06C73EEAFE0CBDA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any expenditure of amounts in the Fund, or transfer of amounts from the Fund, not authorized by this section is prohibited.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01352A6F49674ED4A91D9CDABFC104D5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Acts by Congress</header><text>Any Act of Congress to remove money from the Fund shall be reported in the Federal Register not later than 10 days after the enactment of the Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5AFD686C9E0445CE8A3C34514CD715C9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than September 1, 2024, and annually thereafter through September 1, 2034, the Secretary of Homeland Security, with the concurrence of the Secretary of the Treasury, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on—</text><paragraph id="H11C2EED5C3CA4E9AB1305D296EC8F55C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all activities supported by the Fund during the fiscal year during which the report is submitted and the preceding fiscal year;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6893F42AFBC042D098C5D2D98CAE8433"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a list of each covered seizure or forfeiture supported by the Fund during those fiscal years and, with respect to each such seizure or forfeiture—</text><subparagraph id="H968B5FC0F8A345BD990F7F8DE6D023EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the goods seized;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9D2BE397E2B4442B39682C0EF91BFC1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the current status of the forfeiture of the goods;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05F79E7ECE934C7F810BC863A618A9C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment of the impact on the national security of the United States of the seizure or forfeiture, including the estimated loss of revenue to the person from which the goods were seized; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0FBCB43CE4848FFBA22FA042083AEF0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any anticipated response or outcome of the seizure or forfeiture;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0A06AEB0BA74EF989D0BF8D88512B8F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the financial health and financial data of the Fund as of the date of the report;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF038489B39AB4F01BAFC445247C804CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the amount transferred to the general fund of the Treasury under subsection (e) or (h);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D31016A11EA404F97790AF2A0FF6A95"><enum>(5)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA9B06D47CB2443A5AED14D6AE4FB647A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount paid to informants for information or evidence under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51AB7E9137364E129EFAFE24CEBE3C61" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether the information or evidence led to a seizure; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76F0E284410F49CD95EFA45B9DE8B9F0" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if so, the cost of the goods seized; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1112E67FE1D4E19A9875C45C308F5D8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the amount remaining to be transferred under subsection (e)(3) and an estimated timeline for transferring the full amount required by that subsection; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E27F6AB6B7543BE9C56EFC79120190A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H68D526442AD9470FB9CE5BF99DD690F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any instances during the fiscal years covered by the report of a covered seizure or forfeiture if, after amounts were expended from the Fund to support the seizure or forfeiture, the seizure or forfeiture did not occur as a result of a policy decision made by the Secretary of Homeland Security, the President, or any other official of the United States; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H678510A06DF54C6AA5A09F4F912ECC5B" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the costs incurred and reasons the seizure or forfeiture did not occur.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB8700E8B24747E8A8CDD9B92A92B1C8"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Failure To report or utilize the Fund</header><paragraph id="H0C98F42B54124A11A1425B17829B4DAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effect of failure to submit report</header><text>If a report required by subsection (g) is not submitted to the appropriate congressional committees by the date that is 180 days after the report is due under subsection (g), the Administrator shall transfer an amount equal to 5 percent of the amounts in the Fund to the general fund of the Treasury for the payment of the public debt of the United States. For each 90-day period thereafter during which the report is not submitted, the Administrator shall transfer an additional amount, equal to 5 percent of the amounts in the Fund, to the general fund of the Treasury for that purpose.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CA64FE1608D4C58817ED5B225AD315B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of failure to use fund</header><text>If a report submitted under subsection (g) indicates that amounts in the Fund have not been used for any seizure or forfeiture activity during the fiscal years covered by the report, the Fund shall be terminated and any amounts in the Fund shall transferred to the general fund of the Treasury for the payment of the public debt of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD67F5A7CCCDF425096BF8DCC18CA8CA8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Waiver of termination of Fund for national security purposes</header><subparagraph id="HFE63DA846FC048BCB013634DABEBA6AE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the President determines that it is in the national security interests of the United States not to terminate the Fund as required by paragraph (2), the President may waive the requirement to terminate the Fund.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36CAC66056EE49D598277271AC828492"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>If the President exercises the waiver authority under subparagraph (A), the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report describing the factors considered in determining that it is in the national security interests of the United States not to terminate the Fund.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C2227F95FB94E85BFA49F0B328AAD5D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subparagraph (B) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H14C82C95BCA448218792732647D2EFB6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to affect the requirements of subsection (e) of the Justice for United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20144">34 U.S.C. 20144(e)</external-xref>) or the operation of the United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Fund under that subsection.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC31F4282A3494E1C8FE988B96D5E9237"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H10ACC330ACAF49389E573D23609A624C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB47E4647F09A4E4FB97BB57158815439"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H221EE75F23AE4089990A16C7EEF43037"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H47F5922E5691473AA3C655B2F3610779"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>covered Federal agency</term> means any Federal agency specified in section 3(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B41B87DADF2462BB84B1158C9C8374C"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covered Iranian proxy</header><text>The term <term>covered Iranian proxy</term> means a violent extremist organization or other organization that works on behalf of or receives financial or material support from Iran, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8E4CC9823B7E473C8D18655D3B31ADE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps–Quds Force;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA50726D30644709BF9A8956BC8134AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Hamas;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4718DB74A03B49C5B270C20EF4745EF9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Palestinian Islamic Jihad;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4A89D3C45C14CB7B9BFB23DF01E89CD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Hezbollah; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6409B8C696A40E3A4C3329C6C33B379"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Ansar Allah (the Houthis); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA240F2F5580C40AB9B4C1F76E1FC9802"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Iranian-sponsored militias in Iraq and Syria. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7FD197D7A99410D9B801AF1928D0181" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered seizure or forfeiture</header><text>The term <term>covered seizure or forfeiture</term> means a seizure or forfeiture of property made with respect to a violation by Iran or a covered Iranian proxy of sanctions imposed by the United States. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HBF4FC3ABAF1244B6A181AC08832BD5D7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Export Enforcement Coordination Center</header><subsection id="H834AE9A758434B95B133BAEE108E59B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall operate and maintain, within Homeland Security Investigations, the Export Enforcement Coordination Center, as established by Executive Order 13558 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4601">50 U.S.C. 4601</external-xref> note) (in this section referred to as the <quote>Center</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE8894AEE5F8D4760958B15080C14B8A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The Center shall serve as the primary center for Federal Government export enforcement efforts among the following agencies:</text><paragraph id="H8494EC93F8C1435BA2819C242096A677"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Department of State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F0D9F6EF79B4B60B64619CB8F5864B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46A23E0543C2487CB19FD0738F641281"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Department of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1095589D23144225B95F6385AA1838F5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Department of Justice.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H328A95A9FD1345D082E794669A42689D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Department of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DDB2FFA6A084A6B84C71E6F5B654D33"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2519A1518E34313A90FCD3C8A33EB91"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75428CAD748F4F09BF2FCBDADDB1E589"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Office of the Director of National Intelligence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1D89E4A7D074F76AE845C0FCF758C57"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Such other agencies as the President may designate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B29AD24A9EB4358A83535266FEB85E4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination authority</header><text>The Center shall—</text><paragraph id="HEA49B79E28474CC4AE1D118300E5F789"><enum>(1)</enum><text>serve as a conduit between Federal law enforcement agencies and the intelligence community (as defined in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>)) for the exchange of information related to potential violations of United States export controls;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC180F69A54474753B3EC6281786233B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>serve as a primary point of contact between enforcement authorities and agencies engaged in export licensing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB40CE7C98CAA47FBAD62B6CB7090F6DD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>coordinate law enforcement public outreach activities related to United States export controls; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4EC5363C9484562AFE42E2303D2A5A2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>serve as the primary deconfliction and support center to assist law enforcement agencies to coordinate and enhance investigations with respect to export control violations; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB172B1211C994668A2F1E0D5FB25AA4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>establish integrated, Government-wide statistical tracking and targeting capabilities to support export enforcement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3418403F9AA64089B9B1830DBE8B85DA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>carry out additional duties as assigned by the Secretary of Homeland Security regarding the enforcement of United States export control laws. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26FAA56297214274917FB3CD68B31221"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Executive Associate Director of Homeland Security Investigations shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1ED3DBF100749898F43DEE2EFDE3425"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve as the administrator of the Center; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDF7A134DB1274E8FA7F3A1D5F9F16C47"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintain documentation that describes the participants in, funding of, core functions of, and personnel assigned to, the Center. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A03ACB8C4C34D0AAC69DD6EEB5C884C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Director; Deputy Directors</header><paragraph id="HF0154DC72B454A78AE233542508CFE6E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center shall have a Director, who shall be—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H08952E33AF2D4730B77C2F9CA48C6D6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Senior Executive Service (as defined in section 2101a of title 5, United States Code) and a special agent within Homeland Security Investigations; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C90F9E72FF744EB977E9FA45DB48D60"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">designated by the Secretary of Homeland Security. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC89813691675472FBCF5CE6D4EDC2A8C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deputy Directors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center shall have 2 Deputy Directors, as follows:</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35ED0B64E14F491DB2140927F2A61BC8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One Deputy Director, who shall be—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H221D3B859FA14B92B0855ECFD7CA9CE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full-time employee of the Department of Commerce; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8670D62AED4A42E6AD5C46B6B445E331"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appointed by the Secretary of Commerce.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B27F01E22B8400DAA65C53017D17452"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One Deputy Director, who shall be—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H64B33A0F68C0416A823CA5C8DB2B0BEC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full-time employee of the Department of Justice; and</text></clause><clause id="HC9ABD04B8E544527ABD4224D53EC4A1A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appointed by the Attorney General.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBE3344F32124133AB3A39E2D3247849"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Liaisons from other agencies</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H69930039AC1D4DF59301C79428E23501"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Intelligence community liaison</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An intelligence community liaison shall be detailed to the Center. The liaison shall be—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8E013161E74548A49233AFC4022145BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full-time employee of an element of the intelligence community; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A8446278778445D926B5EFBDA3B96B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">designated by the Director of National Intelligence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6940057A9C648238C9ADD61C69DAE3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Liaisons from other agencies</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5E88E768D9E4441B66CAF6D322DA522"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A liaison shall be detailed to the Center by each agency specified in subparagraph (B). Such liaisons shall be special agents, officers, intelligence analysts, or intelligence officers, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97466BCAF1E64D71A1BBF3DF290171A9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agencies specified</header><text>The agencies specified in this subparagraph are the following:</text><clause id="HAFBD6B0D2DC842E0A1FDDCAC8F0C78D0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Homeland Security Investigations.</text></clause><clause id="H79C751C2AECD499B92AE8C90931D637A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></clause><clause id="H111F3A7DC5234FDDBA39A59C1E642E03"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Office of Export Enforcement of the Bureau of Industry and Security of the Department of Commerce.</text></clause><clause id="H5756F46A13A94B86941FCF6F6BB20348"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></clause><clause id="H8E59E7A30871433194B3E430C267BF8F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Defense Criminal Investigative Service.</text></clause><clause id="HB85ED1E20BDA4F25916EEBB304528FA8"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives.</text></clause><clause id="HFD43C682CFD14483BF67130AF8CDEC3C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The National Counterintelligence and Security Center of the Office of the Director of National Intelligence.</text></clause><clause id="HEFBA3491E29C46F4A8CDDDE812852D49"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></clause><clause id="H1F2B8C72195A429383A866606E7DB948"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>The Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text></clause><clause id="H979F7625900D4880A9C10FB0761CDB26"><enum>(x)</enum><text>The Directorate of Defense Trade Controls of the Department of State.</text></clause><clause id="H74D603F88462433CB37653D2FA7B8B9E"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>The Office of Export Administration of the Bureau of Industry and Security.</text></clause><clause id="H7E459949315E47799C1A45035BB87634"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>The Office of Enforcement Analysis of the Bureau of Industry and Security.</text></clause><clause id="H92198FD5DF734D8EB5135BB4185D2543"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>The Office of Special Investigations of the Air Force.</text></clause><clause id="HBDB74794D1B448E98EDA1D40DA000433"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>The Criminal Investigation Division of the Army.</text></clause><clause id="H1E3289747B8D4674B393193F2465887A"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>The Naval Criminal Investigative Service.</text></clause><clause id="H2F0EB78F264546C6A67A1148BF6752B8"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>The Defense Intelligence Agency.</text></clause><clause id="H2EAD96CE526043DBAA7E7A86DF3B74FD"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>The Defense Counterintelligence and Security Agency.</text></clause><clause id="HF9D128D0865F4DABA81E5B66E824A4B2"><enum>(xviii)</enum><text>Any other agency, at the request of the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

