<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA5B98AF2DEEB46249659BC2726CE8C49" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4515 IH: Performance, Resources, Inclusion, Matters, for Equity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4515</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230710">July 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to award grants to institutions of higher education with an endowment lower than $900,000,000 and an annual operating revenue for athletic programs that is less than $20,000,000 to strengthen existing sports and athletic facilities at such institutions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9B70202A38EE498384FBAC5006E451DF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFD8B5AC14DC34D2D84EEB7A45F440D83" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Performance, Resources, Inclusion, Matters, for Equity Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PRIME Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE40B1715F63842BCABCA04366C4138A6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program authorized</header> <subsection id="H9C94AEBEBFE74AB38648C8424B3E4041"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated to carry out this Act, the Secretary of Education shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to covered institutions to assist the institutions in developing, maintaining, or enhancing facilities, equipment, or infrastructure for any athletic program offered by the institutions.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3CCF02171C4D43EDAE4E90BDEEC333CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Minimum grant amount</header><text>The amount of any grant awarded under this Act shall be not less than $250,000.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H77BC6B4C52D84C3185F3949C87302D22"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this Act, a covered institution shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H1B30D0F0C177423A99B488245E28E9EE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text>A covered institution receiving a grant under this Act may use such grant to—</text> <paragraph id="H40C319A4E33A4F1F9712133DEB6BB4D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop, maintain, or enhance any facility, equipment, or infrastructure (including stadiums, gyms, or fields) for any athletic program offered by the institution; or </text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE4BC17A96405429BB69EAE9C94E4EA6B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">purchase and maintain materials, sporting equipment, and uniforms needed to conduct or produce a live sporting event in accordance with the most recent guidelines issued by the National Collegiate Athletic Association, the National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics, or the Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association. </text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBD578EED26A8418F96C0B77D1C5ACD14"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H603A1D6053724D8EA82CF55D0BA71DF5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual operating revenue</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>annual operating revenue for athletic programs</term>, when calculated with respect to a covered institution, means the total annual revenue for athletic programs offered by the covered institution, including those funds generated by the institution from ticket sales, student fees, and television receipts for such programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H38DFB08401DC4B9CABAB1B6D07E54B4F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered institution</term> means an institution of higher education—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFAB806466E5D4AE181B286C0DA8D3AFC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with an endowment fund that is less than $900,000,000; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H64F0B9BF78D14B00AA335929DF69767B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that has an athletic program, and an annual operating revenue for athletic programs that is less than $20,000,000.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H186865118A974B98A8A5B69778E93D7A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Endowment fund</header><text>The term <term>endowment fund</term> has the meaning given the term in section 312 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85748B858AE542CA95D4EC8C966ACBC9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 or 102(a)(1)(B) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>, 1002(a)(1)(B)). </text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

