<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2519F93055EB40B4AAB596BDB5A01CA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4869 IH: Migrant Child Safety Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4869</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 to establish additional requirements related to ensuring safe placements for unaccompanied alien children.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCFFFB794D3474129A54B62906ED25636" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2094938519784C26893861A537232B03" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Migrant Child Safety Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H82FD0D7B4F83471488E3FA3B9A580390"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring the safety of unaccompanied alien children</header> <subsection id="HAB7090B8D8FF41549E6BF5FFF75026BD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 235(c)(3) of the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1232">8 U.S.C. 1232(c)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HEF60CFB2C575410087A3DDCA5000CC3A" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H426A317008294A398BD4C204D67E83E2"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Information about individuals with whom children are placed</header> 
<clause id="H55BD396D01B142FE8C955F1C1B9196CA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Information to be collected by the Secretary of Health and Human Services and provided to the Secretary of Homeland Security</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before placing the child with an individual, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide to the Secretary of Homeland Security, regarding the individual with whom the child will be placed, the following information: </text> <subclause id="HEDE27466624446758E2546AE0E131EA4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The name of the individual.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4D4F332D8AA04AFD803227BFDEFEB7EE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The maiden name of the individual, if applicable.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H81E2BAADFB294B41956EC3D896B3F0AB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The social security number of the individual.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H789AA39CB8AB4341B418013240995287"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The date of birth of the individual.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H54EFCA9C0C3B47AB8AFA9CFF90A68C0E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The birthplace of the individual.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H737AAA765CA94AA2ABB812C89E4CCC8D"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>The location of the individual’s residence where the child will be placed, including proof of address.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5D4213268D4643909AAEC478B93A453A"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>The results of background checks of the individual and each additional adult household member of the residence where the child will be placed.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H373C662F13164A708CF1D0D7C3A27379"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>The immigration status of the individual, if known.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC5468CB95E4C4804878B8AFA43C82221"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Contact information for the individual, including a phone number.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1243A2D794DA4DF4A4C2DD69933C92F9"><enum>(X)</enum><text>Whether the individual is a relative or guardian of the child, and if so— </text> <item id="H7B39C785C59B4F2E989AA919BAB2E0AF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>documents to prove that the individual is a relative or guardian of the child;</text></item> 
<item id="HF625A6AE3CB04506B4B0F735B379F52B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the contact information of any witness willing to testify that the individual is a relative or guardian of the child; or </text></item> <item id="H68D8372A8B8143D88C87ABA65924FF04"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the results of a DNA test administered by the Secretary of Health and Human Services proving that the individual is a relative of the child.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H2D3C7E8A5ABD4CEF86A573A732EB69DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Activities of the secretary of homeland security</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after receiving the information listed in clause (i), the Secretary of Homeland Security, upon determining that an individual with whom a child is placed is unlawfully present in the United States and not in removal proceedings pursuant to chapter 4 of title II of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1221">8 U.S.C. 1221 et seq.</external-xref>), shall initiate such removal proceedings.</text></clause> <clause id="H815CBC784C894BE9B5408215E221B87D"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>No waiver</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services may not waive the requirements under clause (i). </text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB982BE444304138AECC8D4667E2592A"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Reports to NCMEC</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall report as missing to the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children the name (and any other information in the possession of the Secretary) of any unaccompanied alien child, with respect to whom, not later than 120 days after placing the child with the sponsor—</text> <subclause id="H6AAF48A70D3F431B9EFB4F245371121F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Secretary could not contact the sponsor for the purpose of a follow-up or well-being check; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6110D09419AF42D7A8AF96EFD2ECBD68"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the sponsor did not contact the Secretary for the purpose of a follow-up or well-being check.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H4E615C87714F4CF5B07044ED1A3AF64C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Information provided to State or local health or welfare agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after placing a child in a residence, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide to the appropriate State or local health or welfare agency the information provided to the Secretary of Homeland Security under clause (i) and any other information in the possession of the Secretary related to the child.</text></clause>
<clause id="H34BD5F6A28514069A0742AC4AFC0F97C"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Parental contact</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall attempt to contact the parents of each unaccompanied alien child, using any information in the possession of the Secretary. </text> </clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H6BE8F6C2B507411C8AC3F828C59BAE03"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to any unaccompanied alien child (as such term is defined in section 462(g) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/279">6 U.S.C. 279(g)</external-xref>)) apprehended on or after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

