<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56411812E3FE473AA4E150D5B16B16E0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3953 IH: Debt Ceiling Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3953</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000468">Mrs. Fletcher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000197">Ms. Pelosi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, to provide procedures for congressional disapproval of the issuance of additional debt.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7DF83CC9647041B9A96F6FAC0F05EA07" style="OLC"><section id="H39502637A4AF42B6B6642408867147C7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Debt Ceiling Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6EBEAF5B4ADD4821AE98B8C613EC7756"><enum>2.</enum><header>Procedures for congressional disapproval of issuance of additional debt</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3101 of title 31, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HE2FD18BDD9EB48E4B5D03AD9F06AC35B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H72651AAE67FB4AAB830EB0FDB07AE836"><enum>3101.</enum><header>Public debt limit</header><subsection id="H9B1DDC8B577C4226943D99F67D18256F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of joint resolution</header><text>In this section, the term <term>joint resolution</term> means a joint resolution—</text><paragraph id="HF90475E8889A4BAB9C7921AE5B0B505D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that is introduced during the period—</text><subparagraph id="H7DEFA392D0C04F0885454C476347CA01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>beginning on the date on which a certification under subsection (b)(1) is received; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H270C56DACD344A23AA8D843858743CB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ending on the date that is 3 calendar days after the date described in subparagraph (A) (or, if a House was not in session, the next calendar day on which that House is in session);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H261325DD8D2641E789C65996FF7A9639"><enum>(2)</enum><text>which does not have a preamble;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB253B667818346F8B9EDA19F40ED51EF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the title of which is only as follows: <quote>Joint resolution relating to the disapproval of the Secretary of the Treasury’s exercise of authority to issue additional debt, as submitted under section 3101 of title 31, United States Code, on ______</quote> (with the blank space being filled in with the date on which the applicable certification under subsection (b)(1) was received); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF12988DD0F734A649FB6B3C9AC4A29B8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the matter after the resolving clause of which is only as follows: <quote>That Congress disapproves of the Secretary of the Treasury’s exercise of the authority to issue additional debt, as exercised pursuant to the certification under section 3101(b) of title 31, United States Code.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDC902B6C65F146CDA782C6BD0B2F5463"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><paragraph id="HC0DF2DBEAEFD4DE89D3CD5310390A230"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to Congress a written certification whenever the Secretary of the Treasury determines that the debt is within $100,000,000,000 of a $1,000,000,000,000 increment and that further borrowing is required to meet existing commitments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3A865B1C60E4443B57A5E6A3928C01F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to issue debt after certification</header><text>Subject to the requirements of this section, the United States may issue additional debt as necessary to meet existing commitments on and after the date on which the Secretary of the Treasury submits a written certification to Congress under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72D12BD05CFF42BFA392620E2BC73997"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Resolution of disapproval</header><text>Congress may consider a joint resolution relating to each certification submitted by the Secretary of the Treasury under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F82D647F3E64DD5AE047B9AAEE63FE2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enactment of joint resolution</header><text>The United States may not issue additional debt if, not later than 30 calendar days after the date on which Congress receives a certification submitted under subsection (b)(1) (regardless of whether Congress is in session), there is enacted into law a joint resolution disapproving the Secretary of the Treasury’s exercise of authority to issue additional debt.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEEF2BC40E0E64373B40475FCE393BE91"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expedited consideration in the House of Representatives</header><paragraph id="H22A34CB7142F48F190E1879686AC10EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reconvening</header><text>Upon receipt of a certification submitted under subsection (b)(1), the Speaker, if the House of Representatives would otherwise be adjourned, shall notify the Members of the House of Representatives that, pursuant to this section, the House of Representatives shall convene not later than the second calendar day after receipt of such certification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B5C3B02E4B14828A78C922815938D92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting and discharge</header><text>Any committee of the House of Representatives to which a joint resolution is referred shall report it to the House of Representatives without amendment not later than 5 calendar days after the date of introduction of the joint resolution. If a committee fails to report the joint resolution within that period, the committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the joint resolution and the joint resolution shall be referred to the appropriate calendar.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66E398FFF9944C79AAACF94775F08674"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Proceeding to consideration</header><text>After each committee authorized to consider a joint resolution reports it to the House of Representatives or has been discharged from its consideration, it shall be in order, not later than the sixth day after introduction of the joint resolution, to move to proceed to consider the joint resolution in the House of Representatives. All points of order against the motion are waived. Such a motion shall not be in order with respect to a joint resolution relating to a certification after the House of Representatives has disposed of a motion to proceed that joint resolution. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on the motion to its adoption without intervening motion. The motion shall not be debatable. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is disposed of shall not be in order.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FFDC66CAF0D4C449E98E572A20143F2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>A joint resolution shall be considered as read. All points of order against a joint resolution and against its consideration are waived. An amendment to a joint resolution is not in order. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on a joint resolution to its passage without intervening motion except 2 hours of debate equally divided and controlled by the proponent and an opponent. A motion to reconsider the vote on passage of a joint resolution shall not be in order.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E00976EC785470B94F81CD02F52F670"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Expedited procedure in the Senate</header><paragraph id="H49D613A3F2E6447682FAFE7ACFE0F66B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reconvening</header><text>Upon receipt of a certification under subsection (b)(1), if the Senate has adjourned or recessed for more than 2 days, the majority leader of the Senate, after consultation with the minority leader of the Senate, shall notify the Members of the Senate that, pursuant to this section, the Senate shall convene not later than the second calendar day after receipt of such message.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED749A6E7AC54EA7B157E864CA7EF683"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Placement on calendar</header><text>Upon introduction in the Senate, a joint resolution shall be immediately placed on the calendar.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H874E9B001F7F41428A011D0464CDD1B9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Floor consideration</header><subparagraph id="HFBCDA65FD8E2421CB79459B2F50F67BE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding rule XXII of the Standing Rules of the Senate, it is in order at any time during the period beginning on the day after the date on which Congress receives a certification under subsection (b)(1) and ending on the 6th day after the date on which Congress receives the certification (even though a previous motion to the same effect has been disagreed to) to move to proceed to the consideration of a joint resolution relating to the certification, and all points of order against the joint resolution (and against consideration of the joint resolution) are waived. The motion to proceed is not debatable. The motion is not subject to a motion to postpone. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is agreed to or disagreed to shall not be in order. If a motion to proceed to the consideration of a joint resolution is agreed to, the joint resolution shall remain the unfinished business until disposed of.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC596D6776954502B98911860B6DDD69"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>Consideration of a joint resolution, and on all debatable motions and appeals in connection therewith, shall be limited to not more than 10 hours, which shall be divided equally between the majority and minority leaders or their designees. A motion further to limit debate is in order and not debatable. An amendment to a joint resolution, a motion to postpone, or a motion to proceed to the consideration of other business, or a motion to recommit a joint resolution is not in order.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B5DDA84D658463E8E32C3E1C0BC4A8B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Vote on passage</header><text>If the Senate has voted to proceed to a joint resolution, the vote on passage of the joint resolution shall occur immediately following the conclusion of consideration of the joint resolution, and a single quorum call at the conclusion of the debate if requested in accordance with the rules of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F7B89C333A6404C9F4D9B82A0D230CA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rulings of the chair on procedure</header><text>Appeals from the decisions of the Chair relating to the application of the rules of the Senate, as the case may be, to the procedure relating to a joint resolution shall be decided without debate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C215293E7054D71BB3E3AB690A18F6A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination with action by other House</header><paragraph id="H9F61E2F1332847AE850617B70C5E0D8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, before passing a joint resolution relating to a certification under subsection (b)(1), one House receives from the other a joint resolution relating to the same certification—</text><subparagraph id="HE3CE29CA441D4A88BBBDDF374C4A81A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the joint resolution of the other House shall not be referred to a committee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19E15AE714994408AE799E682C7CB130"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the procedure in the receiving House shall be the same as if no joint resolution had been received from the other House until the vote on passage, when the joint resolution received from the other House shall supplant the joint resolution of the receiving House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0C842012EB9474AA97547140573B43B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of joint resolution of other house</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Senate fails to introduce or consider a joint resolution under this section relating to a certification under subsection (b)(1), the joint resolution of the House relating to the same certification shall be entitled to expedited floor procedures under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F3F2BC589DE4ABF92D778CBA9DFD5B1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Treatment of companion measures</header><text>If, following passage of a joint resolution in the Senate, the Senate receives the companion measure from the House of Representatives, the companion measure shall not be debatable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E78CA199F6C42EDB75D3588ACCCE1D5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consideration after passage</header><subparagraph id="HA94D55F7F61C4AF79AD3897C3C83504F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If Congress passes a joint resolution, the period beginning on the date the President is presented with the joint resolution and ending on the date the President signs, allows to become law without his signature, or vetoes and returns the joint resolution (but excluding days when either House is not in session) shall be disregarded in computing the calendar day period described in subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF424B862DAA4A26A86BC540835A6094"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Veto message</header><text>Debate on a veto message in the Senate under this section shall be 1 hour equally divided between the majority and minority leaders or their designees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H096FC770FED645E5BA76E304E0C53794"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Veto override</header><text>If, within the calendar day period described in subsection (c), Congress overrides a veto of a joint resolution relating to a certification submitted under subsection (b)(1), the United States may not issue any additional debt under this chapter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44DA36EF73444F2FBB0F587F2C76765C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rules of House of Representatives and Senate</header><text>This subsection and subsections (a), (d), (e), and (f) are enacted by Congress—</text><paragraph id="HAD970D5F85034C06A6E8333B55A03AC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and House of Representatives, respectively, and as such are deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, but applicable only with respect to the procedure to be followed in that House in the case of a joint resolution, and they supersede other rules only to the extent that they are inconsistent with such rules; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H318CC463142E4C469BE9EFD996D2845B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H89DAAAD3C7044EA9997FF709DFA8FCF5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Debt defined</header><paragraph id="HBAF7E6E2F7994A8F89FB4622D8A81BCC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>debt</quote> means the face amount of obligations issued under this chapter and the face amount of obligations whose principal and interest are guaranteed by the United States Government (except guaranteed obligations held by the Secretary of the Treasury).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H836454B382C34F46BB25BBAAA33C4D3D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of face amount</header><subparagraph id="H95CBB09B2A5444BE8B5BE960D47573F2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the current redemption value of an obligation issued on a discount basis and redeemable before maturity at the option of its holder is deemed to be the face amount of the obligation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B3B986C02844221BEF7D06E1759E813"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain obligations not redeemable before maturity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the face amount, for any month, of any obligation issued on a discount basis that is not redeemable before maturity at the option of the holder of the obligation is an amount equal to the sum of—</text><clause id="HFBCFBE69E58446DD8F5F39129B38E237"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the original issue price of the obligation, plus</text></clause><clause id="HDC4726EB886344378F0BF795393F0D3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the portion of the discount on the obligation attributable to periods before the beginning of such month (as determined under the principles of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1272">section 1272(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 without regard to any exceptions contained in paragraph (2) of such section).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HBB58C707C2FC4B1F8505CEBDF6695858"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of expired provision</header><subsection id="H7D560B903864490BAD5EBB3F8A6201E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3101A of title 31, United States Code, is repealed.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6E6D5EBE8851498AABC08C48B6E125F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 3101A.</text></subsection></section><section id="H902EF339A70A486CA48A223D1D3EF2C7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><subsection id="H5ACA029B5BA74035A0EAC1E941177B70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H5AE212CE74A544CEB8F5E97E161F6961"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8348 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking subsections (j), (k), and (l). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA92FD4716C924750BBED26B358DB5C3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8438 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking subsections (g) and (h).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H161EF3AEADBA4F9599933E130380E3F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 14(d)(2)(A) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824(d)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended— </text><subparagraph id="HD2F6ACE2DB8943C6862AF44B78FA7B5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>in section 3101(b)</quote> and inserting <quote>under section 3101</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31BEF5E62DE64CDEBD819BC2141E2228"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an obligation to which such limit applies</quote> and inserting <quote>debt, as defined in subsection (h) of such section</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB23B2176FB294D7595709DC44952D5E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Savings provisions</header><text>Notwithstanding the amendments made by paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="H1FAAADC12C1F4EB58395FE2ADAD14250"><enum>(1)</enum><text>paragraphs (2), (3), and (4) of subsection (j) and subsection (l)(1) of section 8348 of title 5, United States Code, as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of this Act, shall apply to any debt issuance suspension period (as defined under section 8348(j)(5) of such title) that is in effect on the date of enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA81AECF15E0D40B7B97D8CBE0845A19E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>paragraphs (2), (3), and (4) of subsection (g) and subsection (h)(1) of section 8438 of title 5, United States Code, as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of this Act, shall apply to any debt issuance suspension period (as defined under section 8438(g)(6) of such title) that is in effect on the date of enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

