<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA6548374276744C7968904FF1B10E39A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3583 IH: Real Education and Access for Healthy Youth Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3583</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the overall health and well-being of young people, including the promotion and attainment of lifelong sexual health and healthy relationships, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3D01766B87544E61A12B21A12B507F67" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H17E9467B309F484BBB9AC9DCB48E03FD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Real Education and Access for Healthy Youth Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HED05147A435149A48609BFB7847EB251"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose and findings</header> <subsection id="HA1E39BE0C57A493290356E21A1A5B595"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this Act is to provide young people with sex education and sexual health services that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5392869B414F4A40B1A3A305E249124E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote and uphold the rights of young people to information and services that empower them to make decisions about their bodies, health, sexuality, families, and communities in all areas of life;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8834CB0E29D5441791DBEE641ACECDD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are evidence-informed, comprehensive in scope, confidential, equitable, accessible, medically accurate and complete, age and developmentally appropriate, culturally responsive, and trauma-informed and resilience-oriented, and align with the National Sex Education Standards of the Future of Sex Ed Initiative;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B3630E84AD44ED596827EE165E2647B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide information about the prevention, treatment, and care of pregnancy, sexually transmitted infections, and interpersonal violence;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07F6A257A11547ADBAB0F6E3736CB8D1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide information about the importance of consent as a basis for healthy relationships and for autonomy in health care;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCCE0BCF39324D56BFF055C645C57735"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide information on gender identity and gender expression;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36665D9332424B38A15A2C53591ADF7F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>provide information on the historical and current condition in which education and health systems, policies, programs, services, and practices have uniquely and adversely impacted Black, Indigenous, Latine, Asian American, Native Hawaiian, Pacific Islander, and other People of Color; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFC358AFF3026470A8255A0040BEAED40"><enum>(7)</enum><text>redress inequities in the delivery of sex education and sexual health services to marginalized young people.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7D5CC44DE9C84B5982738630D1390281"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCF2EEF0709504781982B5CA076191315"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Young people need and have the right to sex education and sexual health services that are evidence-informed, comprehensive in scope, confidential, equitable, accessible, medically accurate and complete, age and developmentally appropriate, culturally responsive, and trauma-informed and resilience-oriented.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02A15D3786D44A4CA5046CDDC9B05B30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Currently, there is a gap between the sex education that young people should be receiving based on expert standards and the sex education many actually receive.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9DA9978764C406281DF0C0995D3E6A8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Only 38 States and the District of Columbia mandate sex education or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) education in schools.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0961905122A44A918B69E5E8918BFE97"><enum>(4)</enum><text>When there is sex education or instruction regarding HIV or sexually transmitted infections (STI), 13 States do not require the content to be evidence-informed, medically accurate and complete, age and developmentally appropriate, or culturally responsive.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H444D5AAE44684934B83209D9C6D1D28F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Many sex education programs and sexual health services currently available were not designed to and do not currently meet the needs of marginalized young people. Some such programs and services actually harm marginalized young people.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF5713021153645779C6AC7E3EC86C242"><enum>(6)</enum><text>For marginalized young people, a lack of comprehensive in scope, confidential, equitable, and accessible sex education and sexual health services is not unfamiliar, but rather a longstanding manifestation of White supremacy, which has touched every aspect of our history, culture, and institutions, including the education and health care systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DB5A4A70E2042C39BBDE33CF7FF383A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The development and delivery of sexual health education and services in the United States historically has been rooted in the oppression of Black, Indigenous, Latine, Asian American, Native Hawaiian, Pacific Islander, and other People of Color.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68BF9CCD9125403D873209D1CB7BC333"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States has a long history of eugenics and forced sterilization. The sexual and reproductive rights and bodily autonomy of specific communities deemed <quote>undesirable</quote> or <quote>defective</quote> were targeted by our governments resulting in state-sanctioned violence and generations of trauma and oppression. These communities include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H53DA5AF50A7947CB86AA6873D10029B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>people with low incomes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3FD28222BBCF40319F58B9B8F7ABB2F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>immigrants;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H26EE5057179F4E8AA024629F4B1F70E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>people with disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC52D28FEEB174F23B48803CE389B1AEB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>people living with HIV;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00C58526C6294CD0BB9833E969B3DE61"><enum>(E)</enum><text>survivors of interpersonal violence;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8F50C21A6EA24375BA6FA79E5419784C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>people who are incarcerated, detained, or who otherwise have encountered the criminal-legal system;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6F7F6CE5CA3649C798336FEA71098C5C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, Latine, Asian American, and other People of Color;</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDCC8D8B82A534A0883702146E0991D4F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>people who are lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9333375E7DD74C9DAC76EAA475F5D784"><enum>(I)</enum><text>young people who are pregnant and parenting.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5B496B7F71AD420789C129AEE469B18D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Black young people are more likely to receive abstinence-only instruction. Research shows that abstinence-only instruction, also known as <quote>sexual risk avoidance</quote> instruction, is ineffective in comparison to sex education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H929D1E6DABC8433DA6EEAE7402B00E11"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, and Latine young people are disproportionately more likely to be diagnosed with an STI, have an unintended pregnancy, or experience sexual assault.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H87D7D254949347B189308B7A04AED033"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The framework of reproductive justice acknowledges and aims to address the legacy of White supremacy, systemic oppression, and the restrictions on sex education and sexual health services that disproportionately impact marginalized communities. Reproductive justice will be achieved when all people regardless of actual or perceived race, color, ethnicity, national origin, religion, immigration status, sex (including gender identity and sexual orientation), disability status, pregnancy or parenting status, or age have the power to make decisions about their bodies, health, sexuality, families, and communities in all areas of life.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF635AE17F17D4F4585DA3EDCC4878EC6"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Increased resources are required for sex education and sexual health services to reach all young people, redress inequities and their impacts on marginalized young people, and achieve reproductive justice for young people.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H683B984CA07543EE9ECF56AC23757FD2"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Such sex education and sexual health services should—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8C8C597005E64C2098E7A53A23A046A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote and uphold the rights of young people to information and services in order to make and exercise informed and responsible decisions about their sexual health;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7BB0B6E183884873BFD0A06E17AAB159"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be evidence-informed, comprehensive in scope, confidential, equitable, accessible, age and developmentally appropriate, culturally responsive, and trauma-informed and resilience-oriented;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEF390FF5774C4CD4B930752A1945AFB8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include instruction and materials that address—</text> <clause id="H2F996B51426A4840BE44EA1F83877751"><enum>(i)</enum><text>puberty and adolescent development;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H66271E0A401C49288E16AD15F4A69960"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sexual and reproductive anatomy and physiology;</text></clause> <clause id="HCF0B7FC666A74463BCC043D520C6020F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>sexual orientation, gender identity, and gender expression;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H958BF22962484366AA25757E80EE238A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>contraception, pregnancy, and reproduction;</text></clause> <clause id="H72FB7F68FA8043A1B5FCA80024FBC49D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>HIV and other STIs;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFDF0F3DA12614A6ABD898CC3208454BF"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>consent and healthy relationships; and </text></clause> <clause id="H8F103D58D7EC4319B361C8676F4A671A" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDE9E553EF84C489AAA2860E5DDFF4D74"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promote gender equity and be inclusive of young people with varying gender identities, gender expressions, and sexual orientations;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA90DED47410D431799A080A81BCED8F9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>promote safe and healthy relationships; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0C03532785E74FE7A5655061150A91E2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>promote racial equity and be responsive to the needs of young people who are Black, Indigenous, and other People of Color.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H07E834D86CA4489890FC538EDE96E4C5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HC050603EB724405482AFF4E8AB9EC6D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Age and developmentally appropriate</header><text>The term <term>age and developmentally appropriate</term> means topics, messages, and teaching methods suitable to particular ages, age groups, or developmental levels, based on cognitive, emotional, social, and behavioral capacity of most young people at that age level.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07DFAEBB0EA141128EF621ECA8B38153"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Characteristics of effective programs</header><text>The term <term>characteristics of effective programs</term> means the aspects of evidence-informed programs, including development, content, and implementation of such programs, that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDA7DD9897E634823913D82FAA5CBDCC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have been shown to be effective in terms of increasing knowledge, clarifying values and attitudes, increasing skills, and impacting behavior; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9714C740A96E4FE998D8A1E795244E81"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are widely recognized by leading medical and public health agencies to be effective in changing sexual behaviors that lead to sexually transmitted infections, unintended pregnancy, and interpersonal violence among young people.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40DA0A76006747C0B2E717818783F032"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consent</header><text>The term <term>consent</term> means affirmative, conscious, and voluntary agreement to engage in interpersonal, physical, or sexual activity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6870AF91D1D34ACA91AEA00F04491EA9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Culturally responsive</header><text>The term <term>culturally responsive</term> means education and services that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7AEA36268EB040EBA29C0CED3CCD1A4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>embrace and actively engage and adjust to young people and their various cultural identities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFC7927EC79CB4500B4D8753245345A26"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognize the ways in which many marginalized young people face unique barriers in our society that result in increased adverse health outcomes and associated stereotypes; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0D1DE1C31B55429C9A80DF7123D26D76"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may address the ways in which racism has shaped national health care policy, the lasting historical trauma associated with reproductive health experiments and forced sterilizations of Black, Latine, and Indigenous communities, or sexual stereotypes assigned to young People of Color or LGBTQ+ people.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA9ECB218A8B4DB1AB213F05091D534E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Evidence-informed</header><text>The term <term>evidence-informed</term> means incorporates characteristics, content, or skills that have been proven to be effective through evaluation in changing sexual behavior.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8A25BD7E516F4B2D85D7E36C241868AA"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gender expression</header><text>The term <term>gender expression</term> means the expression of one’s gender, such as through behavior, clothing, haircut, or voice, and which may or may not conform to socially defined behaviors and characteristics typically associated with being either masculine or feminine.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC699F55F33DF4A7794B65CDA91A77690"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Gender identity</header><text>The term <term>gender identity</term> means the gender-related identity, appearance, mannerisms, or other gender-related characteristics of an individual, regardless of the individual’s designated sex at birth.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40C7D055F90948898F91AA2A2E648615"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Inclusive</header><text>The term <term>inclusive</term> means content and skills that ensure marginalized young people are valued, respected, centered, and supported in sex education instruction and materials.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29A8AE6252904DB089EA2AB3AB766855"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA803A2F199754DB19DDC02B4DC0D8AB4"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Interpersonal violence</header><text>The term <term>interpersonal violence</term> means abuse, assault, bullying, dating violence, domestic violence, harassment, intimate partner violence, or stalking.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0F6E5B5D4E0E422DAE245F9462CF4AF2"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Marginalized young people</header><text>The term <term>marginalized young people</term> means young people who are disadvantaged by underlying structural barriers and social inequities, including young people who are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H48C50C26DA154FE28DDDA245E0C577FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, Latine, Asian American, Native Hawaiian, Pacific Islander, and other People of Color;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FB888DCCA6946DBB7D97532A9C9FD9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>immigrants;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD5D7E0FDC749440CA656E99BB842FC09"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in contact with the foster care system;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2C375CA43324E15A6F2891D759CD9B6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in contact with the juvenile justice system;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H83701AD5353C4EE6B0FA7908BD6D43F6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>experiencing homelessness;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE187DBCFCDD04EB2904366076867DD59"><enum>(F)</enum><text>pregnant or parenting;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08607B56374C4A2D96DBDBA924C6DB96"><enum>(G)</enum><text>lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, or queer;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFC202EA056B346C4994D30A6F35FF305"><enum>(H)</enum><text>living with HIV;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08337D0081BC43D5A71F30A36BCFEDD0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>living with disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DD632D27E0342BD82A261A9DD3BC1A7"><enum>(J)</enum><text>from families with low incomes; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEEADE7CF379441A59B5EBB808DC2162D"><enum>(K)</enum><text>living in rural areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04118383FF754CF691EEC25A5F38AD79"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Medically accurate and complete</header><text>The term <term>medically accurate and complete</term> means that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEF825060F42F4E14B355C54177D9328D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the information provided through the education is verified or supported by the weight of research conducted in compliance with accepted scientific methods and is published in peer-reviewed journals, where applicable; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9E9D2B4F8744ECCBBF2D28EA05ADCCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the education contains information that leading professional organizations and agencies with relevant expertise in the field recognize as accurate, objective, and complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7C5291224F104802B5D9950ECB075484"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Resilience</header><text>The term <term>resilience</term> means the ability to adapt to trauma and tragedy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA642B82E74F24B1CB418315914CD7403"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE93BE9347B424BF594978438DC8426AF"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Sex education</header><text>The term <term>sex education</term> means high quality teaching and learning that—</text> <subparagraph id="H468E774165CB436086A4D839EB332889"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is delivered, to the maximum extent practicable, following the National Sexuality Education Standards of the Future of Sex Ed Initiative;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB73694882AF94DBD812837CD65FA2AF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is about a broad variety of topics related to sex and sexuality, including—</text> <clause id="H5F9AA88FA2EE43E288C217899456DE25"><enum>(i)</enum><text>puberty and adolescent development;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE4253E63BBFD4D1EAD7473A9B0668053"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sexual and reproductive anatomy and physiology;</text></clause> <clause id="H98720D4F793F43F999E29B42AA4411F8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>sexual orientation, gender identity, and gender expression;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6BF2B86B848444A0B01911263A1060E4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>contraception, pregnancy, pregnancy options, and reproduction;</text> </clause> <clause id="H9F1ADABD26244C2FAD9DFB695E237D2C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>HIV and other STIs;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD44019C97D3446F6AADAC3295803FD00"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>consent and healthy relationships; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1896212897C34FF595EDACE705ABA486"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>interpersonal violence;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3675C8C715DE4CE5A42D9AB46EB0AAC6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>explores values and beliefs about such topics; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8AF7FC1B60945478640367EADE4A204"><enum>(D)</enum><text>helps young people in gaining the skills that are needed to navigate relationships and manage one’s own sexual health. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9589E7D1470041CB903F01D8E145BF6F"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Sexual development</header><text>The term <term>sexual development</term> means the lifelong process of physical, behavioral, cognitive, and emotional growth and change as it relates to an individual’s sexuality and sexual maturation, including puberty, identity development, sociocultural influences, and sexual behaviors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE460093A22D841DA98ED7FAD8EF882E2"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Sexual health services</header><text>The term <term>sexual health services</term> includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB745AC1765A04D7F80D1B0D6ACCB2E88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sexual health information, education, and counseling;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2FDC911A264A4018B842058CA4D0E961"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all methods of contraception approved by the Food and Drug Administration;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6232497B4C22402A836C5ACB0F89F880"><enum>(C)</enum><text>routine gynecological care, including human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccines and cancer screenings;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4340CA43473046B298319C81D4382BF8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>preexposure prophylaxis or post-exposure prophylaxis;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H38840756F42046C0952809428C73ACB1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>substance use and mental health services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3380EF6E7A4B443E8B247A2E90F2BC74"><enum>(F)</enum><text>interpersonal violence survivor services; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H504BF9F47D0B4F4B9F43F9DEB0AC9D6A"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other pregnancy and STI prevention, care, or treatment services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H215E4ED6C9A9461FAEEE4A9B138F4A21"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Sexual orientation</header><text>The term <term>sexual orientation</term> means an individual’s romantic, emotional, or sexual attraction to other people.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H116D1D1826BB4CBD8140E4293D9085E0"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Trauma</header><text>The term <term>trauma</term> means a response to an event, series of events, or set of circumstances that is experienced or witnessed by an individual or group of people as physically or emotionally harmful or life-threatening with lasting adverse effects on their functioning and mental, physical, social, emotional, or spiritual well-being.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA5E9BF8A7924441B8CD7DD3A03C6B02"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Trauma-informed and resilience-oriented</header><text>The term <term>trauma-informed and resilience-oriented</term> means an approach that realizes the prevalence of trauma, recognizes the various ways individuals, organizations, and communities may respond to trauma differently, recognizes that resilience can be built, and responds by putting this knowledge into practice.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4B4B337FD3941C183695865B9272329"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Young people</header><text>The term <term>young people</term> means individuals who are ages 10 through 29 at the time of commencement of participation in a project supported under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E7046B19CEB4A5487C572BEE0ED2549" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Youth-friendly sexual health services</header><text>The term <term>youth-friendly sexual health services</term> means sexual health services that are provided in a confidential, equitable, and accessible manner that makes it easy and comfortable for young people to seek out and receive services. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H297F261C94F442D19B624C053F1B1910"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants for sex education at elementary and secondary schools and youth-serving organizations</header> 
<subsection id="HD1BF2B6933DD450AAB0BC544DC425579"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Education, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to enable such eligible entities to carry out projects that provide young people with sex education.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8D261DD94F3E46508C36EAF45080610E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Grants awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5A73D9B2E29C4D638BF6EFE6E13F8F6A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a public or private entity that delivers health education to young people.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB12F461D49D44DA0A2A5DB3DBE840405"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA00B80F1CD0A44ECB83C0F358476AFA5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that are—</text> <paragraph id="H6AAD23A0CB9446F7B1F0C2FEAAE05017"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State educational agencies or local educational agencies; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D8D6D9183CA44969E7C68B0D14C1732"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations, as defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H66EC020B9B2D4F3E89BF5E30E9047C21"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out a project that provides young people with sex education.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1E32D00F7A964E189331082DA2178721"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grants for sex education at institutions of higher education</header> 
<subsection id="H60D6EB74F6FB459AA090E0A7EB0A2851"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Education, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to institutions of higher education or consortia of such institutions to enable such institutions to provide students with age and developmentally appropriate sex education.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H559EA07EDE484999ADDF9C487F27E682"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Grants awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H054201D303224658AC2000A8D81FF236"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An institution of higher education or consortium of such institutions desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H6F19C83ECF05488EA5DF42FD2009DE4E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to an institution of higher education that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFE786EC1734B47AD91038BCFE6676E25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has an enrollment of needy students, as defined in section 318(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059e">20 U.S.C. 1059e(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4150CED9634144D78CF8AA58C5F6D8AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is a Hispanic-serving institution, as defined in section 502(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101a">20 U.S.C. 1101a(a)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H50746653F5E1446990FB39A384568095"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is a Tribal College or University, as defined in section 316(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC68BE9CB72E44C47A77040658F7FFE8B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>is an Alaska Native-serving institution, as defined in section 317(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD37C2880323A43218AC8AA1F395E526E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>is a Native Hawaiian-serving institution, as defined in section 317(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H89F770DF7790454BBECB95FF47CF58F6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>is a Predominantly Black Institution, as defined in section 318(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059e">20 U.S.C. 1059e(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9AE379EA46D94B7EA98F0C84DD586A2C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>is a Native American-serving, nontribal institution, as defined in section 319(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059f">20 U.S.C. 1059f(b)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB792BDF0FCF4B3D989C5738241012CC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>is an Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution, as defined in section 320(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059g">20 U.S.C. 1059g(b)</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A9D2B9999BD4CDE935E130F01707EAF"><enum>(9)</enum><text>is a minority institution, as defined in section 365 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067k">20 U.S.C. 1067k</external-xref>), with an enrollment of needy students, as defined in section 312 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA780303A2B9F4B70A0EB8B2597B9C7A0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text>An institution of higher education or consortium of such institutions receiving a grant under this section shall use grant funds to develop and implement a project to integrate sex education into the institution of higher education in order to reach a large number of students, by carrying out 1 or more of the following activities:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE5056792368D44D3B09E37FF6694608A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Adopting and incorporating age and developmentally appropriate sex education into student orientation, general education, or courses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE4C5AE0FBD64635BAE0CE6B1FA4A3E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Developing or adopting and implementing educational programming outside of class that delivers age and developmentally appropriate sex education to students.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A2A048BB47C4592B5AD4C91965AC999"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Developing or adopting and implementing innovative, technology-based approaches to deliver age and developmentally appropriate sex education to students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCAE55A4B6C14391BFBBC9DEC2E7466D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Developing or adopting and implementing peer-led activities to generate discussion, educate, and raise awareness among students about age and developmentally appropriate sex education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2EE20C66525433DAB425AD3AB1F9204"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Developing or adopting and implementing policies and practices to link students to sexual health services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H8EC726827FAA4C4A805D1DA730FC9068"><enum>6.</enum><header>Grants for educator training</header> <subsection id="H0D78D76D4D1043C7A5873222BDB49364"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Education, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to enable such eligible entities to carry out the activities described in subsection (e).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC49FF55977FC4600ACAA63EF6C200B8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Grants awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3FCF6FF59F794997B6EA8D7C68EBA280"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H98C4C5AA00A2473EA9F6BE4121AE0DC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a State educational agency or local educational agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F76F5D33BD94BD8ADA460FB35E66CB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe or Tribal organization, as defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>); </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE30188650B94425A982FED2D32E1854"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a State or local department of health;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6FEA17821690453FA71D2CCF12D551CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an educational service agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF71875A9F9FB42CAAADE8B6D3427C5E0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a nonprofit institution of higher education or a consortium of such institutions; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H736A56870D16422490640B6CB055948E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a national or statewide nonprofit organization or consortium of nonprofit organizations that has as its primary purpose the improvement of provision of sex education through training and effective teaching of sex education.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6840757E8F0C4199BEB3AD94D7E95603"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H392283A0FB5D4FDF8A972F18F951D41B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header> <paragraph id="HEB39CC47392042858D79593850964FDC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Required activity</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use grant funds for professional development and training of relevant teachers, health educators, faculty, administrators, and staff, in order to increase effective teaching of sex education to young people.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3C31B0FC58924F628724BFD8AFF5DA68"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permissible activities</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section may use grant funds to—</text> <subparagraph id="H2B91B1EB1C034C3DADCF36D987B9C67A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide training and support for educators about the content, skills, and professional disposition needed to implement sex education effectively;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HED0617D955EC412386E73C4FE5DACD80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and provide training and support to educators on incorporating antiracist and gender inclusive policies and practices in sex education;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC38E1C99056E4B26ACF7757772C057E6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support the dissemination of information on effective practices and research findings concerning the teaching of sex education;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H351089DE60A34E87B2CB9833E0E93B2B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support research on—</text> <clause id="HDA2680A8D0D948C2A888531EF177726A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>effective sex education teaching practices; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC67F496E26674A09876202F3087466EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the development of assessment instruments and strategies to document—</text> <subclause id="HDC402F49F63E43E2B115C0DA4BA2BD77"><enum>(I)</enum><text>young people’s understanding of sex education; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCB3B75D03033438F9C5B8050664EA56C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the effects of sex education;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D4D13726D69450495B3B49D3A870B51"><enum>(E)</enum><text>convene conferences on sex education, in order to effectively train educators in the provision of sex education; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA81844C447704448AA0BACA97046DDB7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop and disseminate appropriate research-based materials to foster sex education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC55D30F12AFB4A839C8395917491E847"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section may award subgrants to nonprofit organizations that possess a demonstrated record of providing training to teachers, health educators, faculty, administrators, and staff on sex education to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF068276A779F4E78994298155EF60BB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>train educators in sex education;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9679BA77F384B22B841DC72B21B3457"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support internet or distance learning related to sex education;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC20D06E1E35F4C32B172D4D1F1185825"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promote rigorous academic standards and assessment techniques to guide and measure student performance in sex education;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5D2274DD872E494EB3D70D832E08181B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>encourage replication of best practices and model programs to promote sex education;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3762B15AB1914F7EB1B5A80C5467EF1B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>develop and disseminate effective, research-based sex education learning materials; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCB100CB17A60451292DE6872C2AF7C75"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop academic courses on the pedagogy of sex education at institutions of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H688E47487FF54F4AA468FEECF1E7FB03"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of grants to support the delivery of sexual health services to marginalized young people</header> 
<subsection id="HB135081919F447C8A641C883709BBA0C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to enable such entities to provide youth-friendly sexual health services to marginalized young people.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H106ACD09E3194F969AA851822916ED65"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Grants awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD7BA53619220444CB94925E1BB9657D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H475D1C1F3C014A768F6B5FB7AC6D0FE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a public or private youth-serving organization; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B09764DB9364335A9E70498B666284D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a covered entity, as defined in section 340B of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256b">42 U.S.C. 256b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8A344BB350984282BC8573B5630307C2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8026ACA928904271A798143C1633A197"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds to—</text> <paragraph id="HEB510B89482D4CA4BD84895903D566BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop and implement an evidence-informed project to deliver sexual health services to marginalized young people;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H462C3D2AAE1949CDA16396335147668F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish, alter, or modify staff positions, service delivery policies and practices, service delivery locations, service delivery environments, service delivery schedules, or other services components in order to increase youth-friendly sexual health services to marginalized young people;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B83C65B671B47F291BF050402EBC860"><enum>(3)</enum><text>conduct outreach to marginalized young people to invite them to participate in the eligible entity’s sexual health services and to provide feedback to inform improvements in the delivery of such services;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H349C13533A4C4B14800189A15B6732AA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establish and refine systems of referral to connect marginalized young people to other sexual health services and supportive services;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE93D95EC80C1428AAB887071C9EBB04D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>establish partnerships and collaborations with entities providing services to marginalized young people to link such young people to sexual health services, such as by delivering health services at locations where they congregate, providing transportation to locations where sexual health services are provided, or other linkages to services approaches;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC79CA1CEC3434AE7B2C120001F0DC410"><enum>(6)</enum><text>provide evidence-informed, comprehensive in scope, confidential, equitable, accessible, medically accurate and complete, age and developmentally appropriate, culturally responsive, and trauma-informed and resilience-oriented sexual health information to marginalized young people in the languages and cultural contexts that are most appropriate for the marginalized young people to be served by the eligible entity;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE88E415A6F974EA7A38CBAE25DA87E43"><enum>(7)</enum><text>promote effective communication regarding sexual health among marginalized young people; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2C68DFA8B4E46AFA791E2237FC882A0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>provide training and support for eligible entity personnel and community members who work with marginalized young people about the content, skills, and professional disposition needed to provide youth-friendly sex education and youth-friendly sexual health services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H53B3B572720746D6822542DF3AB47274"><enum>8.</enum><header>Reporting and impact evaluation</header> <subsection id="H9B2454C6FF2C40B3AA64014E5F137F27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grantee report to secretary</header><text>For each year an eligible entity receives grant funds under section 4, 5, 6, or 7, the eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary a report that includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC8FACA05724C4C818907EEE860480255"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the use of grant funds by the eligible entity;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H008C90423C2E4DEFB5BA84234262B542"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how the use of grant funds has increased the access of young people to sex education or sexual health services; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2798D803B77241CF985035B0A87CA1C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE2EBB20FD5454B7C8CCACED05A9C4FBE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Secretary’s report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for a period of 5 years, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress a report on the activities funded under this Act. The Secretary’s report to Congress shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8CF6906DECE34F148C15E55C9A107836"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a statement of how grants awarded by the Secretary meet the purposes described in section 2(a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1745DF5515E14488A5DA3A59B6611751"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information about—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H541CD69D802C4C078ACD6DDAD3608F77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of eligible entities that are receiving grant funds under sections 4, 5, 6, and 7;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H164FE14183CF4C02B854C042040556B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the specific activities supported by grant funds awarded under sections 4, 5, 6, and 7;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBEA62642606440939AF44537F7125339"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of young people served by projects funded under sections 4, 5, and 7, in the aggregate and disaggregated and cross-tabulated by grant program, race and ethnicity, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, and other characteristics determined by the Secretary (except that such disaggregation or cross-tabulation shall not be required in a case in which the results would reveal personally identifiable information about an individual young person);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8CBADA0714F43648542130286663FF3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the number of teachers, health educators, faculty, school administrators, and staff trained under section 6; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0195B95C6A29468C818AEB929C41E4BA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the status of the evaluation required under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H695B3B90FA5547A684D3733D72BBAED0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Multiyear evaluation</header> <paragraph id="H7A2F6E696F924994856610761E3C3EDC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall enter into a contract with a nonprofit organization with experience in conducting impact evaluations to conduct a multiyear evaluation on the impact of the projects funded under sections 4, 5, 6, and 7 and to report to Congress and the Secretary on the findings of such evaluation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA18347ED26E44A99965752415CF43919"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The evaluation conducted under this subsection shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H151C3336F59E41038D69BB89871968A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be conducted in a manner consistent with relevant, nationally recognized professional and technical evaluation standards;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5C22965DA50C43C2854919FDC2B78714"><enum>(B)</enum><text>use sound statistical methods and techniques relating to the behavioral sciences, including quasi-experimental designs, inferential statistics, and other methodologies and techniques that allow for conclusions to be reached;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE66B67DEDA484BACAA44BE2C9914ED52"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be carried out by an independent organization that has not received a grant under section 4, 5, 6, or 7; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFF8498C8E2C94B7ABF85BF8F4E0AA65C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>be designed to provide information on output measures and outcome measures to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3423AEABA03D4F6CB9C81B344E2C2435"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 6 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the organization conducting the evaluation under this subsection shall prepare and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress and the Secretary an evaluation report. Such report shall be made publicly available, including on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB5B13AB748E748148AF0983B22804E8B"><enum>9.</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Activities funded under this Act shall not discriminate on the basis of actual or perceived sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), age, parental status, race, color, ethnicity, national origin, disability, or religion. Nothing in this Act shall be construed to invalidate or limit rights, remedies, procedures, or legal standards available under any other Federal law or any law of a State or a political subdivision of a State, including the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000a">42 U.S.C. 2000a et seq.</external-xref>), title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>), and section 1557 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18116">42 U.S.C. 18116</external-xref>).</text></section> <section id="H88ED68C2CCD94A2AAC4532E89CA2734E"><enum>10.</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No Federal funds provided under this Act may be used for sex education or sexual health services that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3A381DCDF7D44014A18D39A38B31ACCD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>withhold health-promoting or life-saving information about sexuality-related topics, including HIV;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A5C756FA9EE4DAF8D4018BB57EF23BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are medically inaccurate or incomplete;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD96D498C03F48C48E56B2D8252DF237"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promote gender or racial stereotypes or are unresponsive to gender or racial inequities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEFE67226C764C3286DF7460C4266ACF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>fail to address the needs of sexually active young people;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H99E3050C12D54024B2EF28CE2E6ECA75"><enum>(5)</enum><text>fail to address the needs of pregnant or parenting young people;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H86ABE96C9CF243D78D3BB46E15A22000"><enum>(6)</enum><text>fail to address the needs of survivors of interpersonal violence;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB48B46866A8F4C9D921B8FDB6288708E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>fail to address the needs of young people of all physical, developmental, or mental abilities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC19F6C7D3FA145B98FCFD73C672C113F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>fail to be inclusive of individuals with varying gender identities, gender expressions, and sexual orientations; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65B1E195F7E743BFB78F6E2061B47360"><enum>(9)</enum><text>are inconsistent with the ethical imperatives of medicine and public health.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H669677702FF547EA88E432205B23A4D5"><enum>11.</enum><header>Amendments to other laws</header> <subsection id="HF6BF9804FB1648E99B9211096806BF04"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment to the Public Health Service Act</header><text>Section 2500 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300ee">42 U.S.C. 300ee</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsections (b) through (d) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1DC4E0D39FBC4B9E8B74FD4E1FABE4EB"> 
<subsection id="H5E02B78FA2874E5DA81AD624DC4D31AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of programs</header><text>All programs of education and information receiving funds under this title shall include information about the potential effects of intravenous substance use.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H08E23E76E52C426FA692AB843DAA8DC5" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</header><text>Section 8526 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7906">20 U.S.C. 7906</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2FD8B473646D4FAC9D983F571D9A5008" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (3), (5), and (6);</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H602E96BB27BA43FC9B8EB6B322B6540A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) and (7) as paragraphs (3) and (4), respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HF6A3950F3A0048A69E204DF82030D8D5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), as redesignated, by inserting <quote>or</quote> after the semicolon.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> <section id="H25BFF3D1C8DF49859D0BB47EF63D1451"><enum>12.</enum><header>Funding</header> <subsection id="HF55B3B2103C04C7E9461718DE7F4F58D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this Act, there is authorized to be appropriated $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029. Amounts appropriated under this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD2A4557C90B463BA088D5F365B816CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservations of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="H9A272FEAEBEA45AFAC3F03B5BC6D2CD5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="HED536705E45A434CBCC9960997981096"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall reserve not more than 30 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for the purposes of awarding grants for sex education at elementary and secondary schools and youth-serving organizations under section 4;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0821B98C4B3A4C36B9DC4DB2D5C1CE80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall reserve not more than 10 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for the purpose of awarding grants for sex education at institutions of higher education under section 5;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBE1FCA5096F34FBA9B307D9852FA9A6C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall reserve not more than 15 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for the purpose of awarding grants for educator training under section 6;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2966E09257204C00B0B6DBD6C6A6A414"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall reserve not more than 30 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for the purpose of awarding grants for sexual health services for marginalized youth under section 7; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H466A692592484846B15874D6BAD6A36C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>shall reserve not less than 5 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for the purpose of carrying out the reporting and impact evaluation required under section 8.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49942BBF7E5B4C9BB95DBCB55C4991AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Research, training, and technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall reserve not less than 10 percent of the amount authorized under subsection (a) for expenditures by the Secretary to provide, directly or through a competitive grant process, research, training, and technical assistance, including dissemination of research and information regarding effective and promising practices, providing consultation and resources, and developing resources and materials to support the activities of recipients of grants. In carrying out such functions, the Secretary shall collaborate with a variety of entities that have expertise in sex education and sexual health services standards setting, design, development, delivery, research, monitoring, and evaluation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7BB864FCF43E4CF08DD932C6273E15C7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reprogramming of abstinence only until marriage program funding</header><text>The unobligated balance of funds made available to carry out section 510 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/710">42 U.S.C. 710</external-xref>) (as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of this Act) are hereby transferred and shall be used by the Secretary to carry out this Act. The amounts transferred and made available to carry out this Act shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H42A0505A16F1431CBCF016ABF0D948D5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Repeal of abstinence only until marriage program</header><text>Section 510 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/710">42 U.S.C. 710 et seq.</external-xref>) is repealed. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

