<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9F368ACB76634040BBE22E6DDF91ED49" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2953 IH: Forced Arbitration Injustice Repeal Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2953</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. C&#225;rdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000273">Ms. Leger Fernandez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 9 of the United States Code with respect to arbitration.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7897C0E54E3A4307ABAE0BD08EF5C195" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE6DF3EB508D34F959A875F327CD0FEA8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Forced Arbitration Injustice Repeal Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAIR Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H422B151C27B0472692590C82C5E13E87"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4AAD7A8978C643499A5A9B9DC596EDCD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prohibit predispute arbitration agreements that force arbitration of future employment, consumer, antitrust, or civil rights disputes; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D7CD710989647D1A79BBBDAD39932FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit agreements and practices that interfere with the right of individuals, workers, and small businesses to participate in a joint, class, or collective action related to an employment, consumer, antitrust, or civil rights dispute.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H1F8366A80D8B4155AFB32EA1CCCE4F23"><enum>3.</enum><header>Arbitration of employment, consumer, antitrust, and civil rights disputes</header> 
<subsection id="H4E9A68F8C3724A6FA18980A35C6ED6BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 9 of the United States Code is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H56CBA9317DFD423DA3EF5440C92A4387" style="USC"> <chapter id="H2AB33795EA374B2B91B293F5F8C47DF0"><enum>5</enum><header>Arbitration of Employment, Consumer, Antitrust, and Civil Rights Disputes</header> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. </toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">501. Definitions. </toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">502. No validity or enforceability.</toc-entry></toc> <section id="H5F0908F8F1CF45E482EC55BFF5891C00"><enum>501.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this chapter—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF73A5C132A0946B5B61D9928A6341A68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>antitrust dispute</quote> means a dispute—</text> <subparagraph id="HC4DBCD9B7FCC4E2A919FAC36A5FCADAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>arising from an alleged violation of the antitrust laws (as defined in subsection (a) of the first section of the Clayton Act) or State antitrust laws; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE188B2D7F5A34594A5EF87282C02AD09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which the plaintiffs seek certification as a class under rule 23 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure or a comparable rule or provision of State law;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC31CF3BC9FA24DF19AFFE32228CFAF21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>civil rights dispute</quote> means a dispute—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8D270B9BEC994B5EAC66746D0A303D2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>arising from an alleged violation of—</text> <clause id="H3ED8B85807884B2E842F26527958607E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Constitution of the United States or the constitution of a State;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H94BBD07378644BBCB6FA48D24D04DBD0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any Federal, State, or local law that prohibits discrimination on the basis of race, sex, age, gender identity, sexual orientation, disability, religion, national origin, or any legally protected status in education, employment, credit, housing, public accommodations and facilities, voting, veterans or servicemembers, health care, or a program funded or conducted by the Federal Government or State government, including any law referred to or described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/62">section 62(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, including parts of such law not explicitly referenced in such section but that relate to protecting individuals on any such basis; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9568ED8B612E47AE9A6A567A46DDFF5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which at least one party alleging a violation described in subparagraph (A) is one or more individuals (or their authorized representative), including one or more individuals seeking certification as a class under rule 23 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure or a comparable rule or provision of State law;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38C2D49852C242B7A5F723C377DB3E12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>consumer dispute</quote> means a dispute between—</text> <subparagraph id="H8D9D2419FDD5415DB2C77DAB1CAE2623"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one or more individuals who seek or acquire real or personal property, services (including services related to digital technology), securities or other investments, money, or credit for personal, family, or household purposes including an individual or individuals who seek certification as a class under rule 23 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure or a comparable rule or provision of State law; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H20F2A79FD1EC4FDDB88CB76B88F63B57"><enum>(B)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE26EC292A86646AFA045250A15F7C656"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the seller or provider of such property, services, securities or other investments, money, or credit; or</text></clause> <clause id="HE7FF09D86F0C4F7F9AB2113ECCD71A3F" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a third party involved in the selling, providing of, payment for, receipt or use of information about, or other relationship to any such property, services, securities or other investments, money, or credit;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2C3000F596F54B50A54801496BFD179A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>employment dispute</quote> means a dispute between one or more individuals (or their authorized representative) and a person arising out of or related to the work relationship or prospective work relationship between them, including a dispute regarding the terms of or payment for, advertising of, recruiting for, referring of, arranging for, or discipline or discharge in connection with, such work, regardless of whether the individual is or would be classified as an employee or an independent contractor with respect to such work, and including a dispute arising under any law referred to or described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/62">section 62(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, including parts of such law not explicitly referenced in such section but that relate to protecting individuals on any such basis, and including a dispute in which an individual or individuals seek certification as a class under rule 23 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure or as a collective action under section 16(b) of the Fair Labor Standards Act, or a comparable rule or provision of State law;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0CB9B40DDE614F3DAA7621F0222EB22E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <quote>predispute arbitration agreement</quote> means an agreement to arbitrate a dispute that has not yet arisen at the time of the making of the agreement; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C3CFBD3CD4E42AA84E1C8FCB739C9B3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <quote>predispute joint-action waiver</quote> means an agreement, whether or not part of a predispute arbitration agreement, that would prohibit, or waive the right of, one of the parties to the agreement to participate in a joint, class, or collective action in a judicial, arbitral, administrative, or other forum, concerning a dispute that has not yet arisen at the time of the making of the agreement.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H3501E001F661498DBF7AFCB083E29874"><enum>502.</enum><header>No validity or enforceability</header> <subsection id="HB127A40019254C319432AFD49C132BC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, no predispute arbitration agreement or predispute joint-action waiver shall be valid or enforceable with respect to an employment dispute, consumer dispute, antitrust dispute, or civil rights dispute.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H171EB6756CEC417798913A88B2F082E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header> 
<paragraph id="HB64107413F7A4DB7AC7B8525D74698CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An issue as to whether this chapter applies with respect to a dispute shall be determined under Federal law. The applicability of this chapter to an agreement to arbitrate and the validity and enforceability of an agreement to which this chapter applies shall be determined by a court, rather than an arbitrator, irrespective of whether the party resisting arbitration challenges the arbitration agreement specifically or in conjunction with other terms of the contract containing such agreement, and irrespective of whether the agreement purports to delegate such determinations to an arbitrator.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H289AD4E98E4D41A99A66DBF4366FD92D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collective bargaining agreements</header><text>Nothing in this chapter shall apply to any arbitration provision in a contract between an employer and a labor organization or between labor organizations, except that no such arbitration provision shall have the effect of waiving the right of a worker to seek judicial enforcement of a right arising under a provision of the Constitution of the United States, a State constitution, or a Federal or State statute, or public policy arising therefrom.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4E03A715F4D14F32B4FB4874DC6E08B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H62B1E9A915544164AB400A86CFBB0BAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 9 of the United States Code is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HF32C66E185704219A8E31D970C029F5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 1 by striking <quote>of seamen,</quote> and all that follows through <quote>interstate commerce</quote> and inserting in its place <quote>of individuals, regardless of whether such individuals are designated as employees or independent contractors for other purposes</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC72E21A3A9D9470E93B7DA2911DFCE54"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2 by striking <quote>chapter 4</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 4 or 5</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4328A0EC665249F683B770AD8F70BDCC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 208 by striking <quote>chapter 4</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 4 or 5</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3E728B19C2644FDAD6288CF7C55476C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 307 by striking <quote>chapter 4</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 4 or 5</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2186D6B4668F4D49880DA6AFF663DE55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of chapters</header><text>The table of chapters of title 9 of the United States Code is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA490487BAB44B7FB9E5FABDAF6FF636" style="OLC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<multi-column-toc-entry level="chapter"><toc-enum>5.</toc-enum><level-header level="chapter">Arbitration of Employment, Consumer, Antitrust, and Civil Rights Disputes</level-header><target>501</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H21FD3C36DBB841E181165AC8493958D5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act, and the amendments made by this Act, shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act and shall apply with respect to any dispute or claim that arises or accrues on or after such date.</text></section> <section id="HF8748913E3D74EDBAAE622B627F9D53C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, shall be construed to prohibit the use of arbitration on a voluntary basis after the dispute arises.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

