<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD2F96AC95FD64A0E82AD3A31D23BFFCB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5230 IH: Basic Allowance for Housing Calculation Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5230</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to carry out a pilot program under which the Secretary enters into a contract for the calculation, using industry standard machine learning and artificial intelligence algorithms, of the monthly rates of basic allowance for housing for certain military housing areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB9B24836A29F45AC9AF40558116DBB10" style="OLC"><section id="H05345EE4431D482AAAD073FB0BED2809" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Basic Allowance for Housing Calculation Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H01AF97955E0A403FA68DD05A314CBBC2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Basic allowance for housing: pilot program to outsource rate calculation</header><subsection id="HA950B9D9EF7E411BBC3D47540DBEB5F5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2024, the Secretary of Defense shall seek to enter into an agreement with a covered entity pursuant to which the covered entity shall calculate, using industry standard machine learning and artificial intelligence algorithms, the monthly rates of BAH for not fewer than 15 MHAs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB68B4D60010745D2BC4D12EC0C95B54E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report containing the evaluation of the Secretary of the rates calculated by a covered entity pursuant to an agreement under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0906945F5054495EA4677FD62004008C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA08563BD9CB1419A95AE90E087C534B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>BAH</quote> means the basic allowance for housing for members of the uniformed services under section 403 of title 37, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABECE3DD2EF74CABBF8797D27B347C50"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means a nationally recognized entity in the field of single-family housing that has data on local rental rates in real estate markets across the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5F796396D774DF7B9344DC9F732F781"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>MHA</quote> means military housing area.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

