<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9DEC86CDF5754AD2B805DD6B178CF270" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4387 IH: Cybersecurity in Agriculture Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4387</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230627">June 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Agricultural Research, Extension, and Teaching Policy Act of 1977 to direct the Secretary of Agriculture to establish a program providing for the establishment of Agriculture Cybersecurity Centers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H52BCB3F0236E45FE974D8FB89CF03E3D" style="OLC"><section id="H2C3571406B9244BAA35641039B81F329" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cybersecurity in Agriculture Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H8B1750DEC8934308B99CAAEEFEE22951"><enum>2.</enum><header>Agriculture Cybersecurity Centers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle K of the National Agricultural Research, Extension, and Teaching Policy Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3319">7 U.S.C. 3319 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCD250BD9D3A74328AF8344C74337C8A9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HC025F4DD20DB459F83A15B677CA85CDF"><enum>1473I.</enum><header>Agriculture Cybersecurity Centers</header><subsection id="HF83B9407714E436BB6C5A22766C7450D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the National Institute of Food and Agriculture, and in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall establish a program under which the Secretary will—</text><paragraph id="HA77E936FE6544E3A8901CCA5176448E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>on a competitive basis, award grants to, or enter into cooperative agreements with, eligible entities to establish 5 Regional Agriculture Cybersecurity Centers to carry out research, development, and education on agriculture cybersecurity, with respect to seed agriculture, horticulture, animal agriculture, and the agriculture supply chain; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F44A940892540B5B0E8732C2E0E68C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a national network of such Regional Agricultural Cybersecurity Centers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H467915FC4E27419BACEE12C98B1682C7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">designate one college or university to coordinate the activities of such national network.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2AB2F18774A49D49FB97F4D6AE9C072"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Regional Agriculture Cybersecurity Center shall—</text><paragraph id="HDF5AA7BC79C64F36A4BF9CDD6CFC57AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct research on cybersecurity systems for the agriculture sector, including developing cybersecurity situational awareness systems to monitor cybersecurity threats, intrusions, and anomalies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AA7661F029247289CCBCED24FAD6113"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a security operations center for the agriculture sector to analyze cybersecurity threats, intrusions, and anomalies and to recommend mitigation actions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF62C301617374C569B8A4DD67F644C25"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop cybersecurity technologies and tools for the agricultural sector, including domain-specific intrusion and anomaly detection systems, domain-specific intrusion prevention systems, domain specific role-based access control and user authentication systems, lightweight device authentication protocols, and secure network architectures;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H299593DD197842D99B28211DB673B2EA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>build live cybersecurity testbeds to assess and refine cybersecurity technologies, tools, and systems developed for the agricultural sector;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BC458EBCEE24ED0B70C998027F47048"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conduct attack/defense exercises to validate and evaluate cybersecurity solutions for field deployment and agriculture industry adoption;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1FB4F27CFAA41FC911FF7F9BF80C700"><enum>(6)</enum><text>develop cybersecurity education and training programs for agricultural stakeholders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19B91246D78D4123B9718C8E2820B2B5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>conduct cybersecurity training using the testbeds referred to in paragraph (4); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0EC42F47E6445109DEA5B210EE7B8F7"><enum>(8)</enum><text>build a regional research and development collaboration network. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63FD9A6D6EAC4B378AF1AA48AE7501D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a college or university that has programs in food and agriculture sciences and cybersecurity that coordinates regional industry partners, cooperatives, government authorities and other stakeholders to strengthen security, privacy and resiliency, bolster the independent networks, and develop a skilled workforce.</text></subsection><subsection id="H673C996E959547F7AED6C4135B61D39A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

