<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD0935495C5A140B1B533B5320E207F82" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6045 IH: Curbing Illicit Drug Threats Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6045</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct a study and submit a report on the efficacy of Federal drug surveillance systems, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC48E2B4ED1D0469F9460DEDF5007355B" style="OLC"><section id="H5F3DED90C7EB4D9885A621FC3C07062E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Curbing Illicit Drug Threats Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HB238457412FD457C9E81E20C6B6D9457"><enum>2.</enum><header>GAO study and report on efficacy of Federal drug surveillance systems</header><subsection id="H28843922912642C59A7A60FDEEB6AE87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on—</text><paragraph id="HEABC37CD89F442C9999639126A73ABE0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the efficacy of Federal drug surveillance systems in providing up-to-date information on illicit drug use in the United States, including any limitations affecting such efficacy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04B4A8BBB0F34140A2296818CB5A40F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how such systems are used to address illicit drug use in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD15B0E85518D4C9A96241DCA9514C3A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall complete the study under subsection (a) and submit to Congress a report containing—</text><paragraph id="HD4BA7B41F697488CB3D6D622644C158F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the findings and conclusions of such study; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB994494051E49CFAA25B8E811A53BE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any recommendations for legislative or administrative actions to improve the efficacy of the Federal drug surveillance systems examined in such study, including any recommendations pertaining to interagency communication or data collection procedures.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7294BAF2A828411384F4975EF3E7FB05"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal drug surveillance systems defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Federal drug surveillance systems</term> includes—</text><paragraph id="H3B547F22D6184F3CBF82CC429EFDEDA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Drug Overdose Surveillance and Epidemiology System of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (commonly known as <quote>DOSE</quote>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22791725162D4BF9898FA74806C8F10D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the State Unintentional Drug Overdose Reporting System of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (commonly known as <quote>SUDORS</quote>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB962D592A56D49C881755C6126A541E5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the National Drug Early Warning System of the National Institute on Drug Abuse (commonly known as <quote>NDEWS</quote>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CFF4102793C4F048E3754619D7378EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Drug Abuse Warning Network of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (commonly known as <quote>DAWN</quote>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

