<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCEB9525C59144A6891E18B323B5AFCDE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1480 IH: Beagle Brigade Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1480</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the National Detector Dog Training Center, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB9A71B443C094FF7B608914B29578D68" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H802E93E77CC34AF99D08301D9F2A527A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Beagle Brigade Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H852F78C653224DC3B86D2FC630D577FC"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Detector Dog Training Center</header><subsection id="H57EEFAF82823468EAE4647EB818D3DBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established a National Detector Dog Training Center (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Center</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C4B3D9F24EE45F49C8FE6D966219690"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Center shall have the following duties:</text><paragraph id="H1BFED7D5A4D54AF4B09C3AB85466EB50"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Training dogs for the purpose of safeguarding domestic agricultural and natural resources from foreign and invasive pests and diseases.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C8F358A578B4D66BC5EDDEC3E200004"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Training human handlers to successfully select and train dogs for the purpose described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AF237C1252542279F5105CEDB54BEE7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaborating with relevant Federal agencies, including U.S. Customs and Border Protection, to safeguard domestic agricultural and natural resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A765DAC84FC471F9F8B9DF995010D1A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Collaborating with external stakeholders, including State departments of agriculture, local and county agricultural officials, private sector entities, and other relevant non-Federal partners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EDC30B2445B46B9A41254AADBB2FAAF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Ensuring the health and welfare of all dogs under the care of the Center, including by ensuring access to necessary veterinary care, adequate shelter, and proper nutrition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13EACA428EB04883BFB8B42D7D865AB7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Providing opportunities for private adoption of retirement-age trained dogs and dogs that do not complete training.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68E0DC701412410292370ECBA6FCEF54"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other duties necessary to safeguard domestic agricultural and natural resources from foreign and invasive pests and diseases, as determined by the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Administrator of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BA2D09CD051420D8D1CA35614C2FBBA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to any other amounts made available for the operation of the Center, there are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Administrator of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, such sums as are necessary for fiscal year 2024, and each fiscal year thereafter, for the operation of the Center.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5BF82BB067E448EFBDB67B7A395F46E2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Administrator of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, shall submit to Congress a report that contains—</text><paragraph id="HCD7B7C5EDE9F479188A79723C21AB968"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of current and emerging threats to domestic agricultural and natural resources from foreign pests and diseases within the purview of the operations of the Center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC269D90304E4D0A8A2F4E21A1FA964E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an examination of the role that the Center plays in the protection against foreign pests and diseases; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50D3B023CA824573ABE824398D7E3785"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of improvements needed in Federal programs to minimize threats from foreign pests and diseases within the purview of the operations of the Center, including strengthened coordination among the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, U.S. Customs and Border Protection, and other relevant Federal agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BA9B4D6955A43879243A39281E2F2B6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations to strengthen the capabilities of the Center in protecting against foreign pests and diseases; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F45769737C14ABEB31956906F0A3ABF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>recommendations to improve—</text><subparagraph id="HC8810CBED1874A248AF911324AB3219D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the dog procurement procedures of the Center; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A114436DED04C5589541A9132C2AFA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>private adoption opportunities for retirement-age trained dogs and dogs that do not complete training.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

