<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H13A595418C8C4A13BE5809D6368E2F44" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6219 IH: Accessing Satellite Data to Enable New Discoveries Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6219</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration to establish a program to identify, evaluate, acquire, and disseminate commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery in order to satisfy the scientific, operational, and educational requirements of the Administration, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H134050197314433E8FCFD7B50C95392B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H78EF2493AAB542F18E2FE16F93E13C60" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accessing Satellite Data to Enable New Discoveries Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ASCEND Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4C75B984CA3245839570DA766241CBD5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Commercial satellite data</header> <subsection id="HC3BBC824A663465BB1EB7591702013E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEB159A2269A54C918E17386B717C580C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 60501 of title 51, United States Code, states that the goal for the Earth Science program of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (referred to in this section as <quote>NASA</quote>) shall be to pursue a program of Earth observations, research, and applications activities to better understand the Earth, how it supports life, and how human activities affect its ability to do so in the future.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2DE723A526164D3FB7BDB625FEEB620F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 50115 of title 51, United States Code, states that the Administrator of NASA shall, to the extent possible and while satisfying the scientific or educational requirements of NASA, and where appropriate, of other Federal agencies and scientific researchers, acquire, where cost effective, space-based and airborne commercial Earth remote sensing data, services, distribution, and applications from a commercial provider.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1DDCBC13CAB04E74A983764BA3E815AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Administrator of NASA established the Commercial SmallSat Data Acquisition Pilot Program in 2019 to identify, validate, and acquire from commercial sources data that support the Earth science research and application goals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2FE771A7E6D04AC397088D50238F3A67"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of NASA has—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCB67969057D547C186D272BB78A35266"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determined that the pilot program described in paragraph (3) has been a success, as described in the final evaluation entitled <quote>Commercial SmallSat Data Acquisition Program Pilot Evaluation Report</quote> issued in 2020;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H63D59ED4DA0C4DBC85C5ADC3DEACDBEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>established a formal process for evaluating and onboarding new commercial vendors in such pilot program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8E73F83D112F48EFBBF023678F0D549C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increased the number of commercial vendors and commercial data products available through such pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H099F8180F94F4AB3ABC45DD0E49E2B02"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanded procurement arrangements with commercial vendors to broaden user access to provide commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery to federally funded researchers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6F4FA53C6B2343E489E26661950C558C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Commercial Satellite Data Acquisition Program</header> 
<paragraph id="H69E0D13D9282478EAF6F0C289944F2E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/51/603">Chapter 603</external-xref> of title 51, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HED2834D58BBA43668D840A2F215D99FD"> <section id="H59AC1321938B47788F2AC12010E8D4AC"><enum>60307.</enum><header>Commercial Satellite Data Acquisition Program </header> <subsection id="H4E470DC9EE09464DA1B61938C623FCFC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall establish within the Earth Science Division of the Science Mission Directorate a program to acquire and disseminate cost-effective and appropriate commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery in order to satisfy the scientific, operational, and educational requirements of the Administration, and where appropriate, of other Federal agencies and scientific researchers to augment or complement the suite of Earth observations acquired by the Administration, other United States Government agencies, and international partners.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H740F57921256452B8D2FE500C17338CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data publication and transparency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms and conditions of commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery acquisitions under the program described in subsection (a) shall not prevent—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H030096587C4148C1BFCD204B8F67D528"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the publication of commercial data or imagery for scientific purposes; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5312344C8DE4DBB92E42AF004575173"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the publication of information that is derived from, incorporates, or enhances the original commercial data or imagery of a vendor.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EB8926450AD4B3795B4B33A542D936F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>In carrying out the program under this section, the Administrator may—</text> 
<paragraph id="H785C63834A034C89AC2DA44DC38C91B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>procure the commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery from commercial vendors to advance scientific research and applications in accordance with subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7215AACFC3F4AC3BF7942C92DC4D46F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish or modify end-use license terms and conditions to allow for the use of procured commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery by individuals other than NASA-funded users, consistent with the goals of the program; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H071CA76D72BB437C8DA47724BE804496"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as practicable, procure commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery from commercial vendors to support—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB0DBAFAD6B6D4F329B27B3871B5A510D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nonscientific applications; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE5329B2BE2C44A4B9478836190F430E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nonmilitary activities of Federal agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4C0C7FFC1DD47F1B4A0CA2774E239A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section and annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report that includes the following:</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF0002B526FE044828365B8A43C9CF2AC"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H01A98D40D6EE4284BBA9EE12EE010C41"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of the initial report, a list of all agreements that are providing commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery to NASA as of the date of the report.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8041B90D0E5A427AB1275D6DF2C653ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each subsequent report, a list of all agreements that have provided commercial Earth remote sensing data and imagery to NASA during the reporting period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H72918E2B132C45E88176A602A74EE035"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of the end-use license terms and conditions for each such vendor.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33A73EBCA39240BB9E21776F28FB0DD6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the manner in which each such agreement is advancing scientific research and applications, including priorities recommended by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine decadal surveys.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5B8BEB868DA1449682EF7D6419593119"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Information specifying whether the Administrator has entered into an agreement with a commercial vendor or a Federal agency that permits the use of data and imagery by Federal Government employees, contractors, or non-Federal users.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0FBBAC7556BA4686B36AEA4F9D774EEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/51/603">chapter 603</external-xref> of title 51, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8BEC8E506264265932CAA9297E112B5"> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry level="section" bold="off">60307. Commercial Satellite Data Acquisition Program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


