<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H913354071CDE44A3A549D26B8CAC9727" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>95 HR 2839 IH: To amend the Siletz Reservation Act to address the hunting, fishing, trapping, and animal gathering rights of the Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2839</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Siletz Reservation Act to address the hunting, fishing, trapping, and animal gathering rights of the Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8C07CE7E24D54C679C0C56DFA262E8BB" style="OLC"><section id="H76CC3BE6CFD04476AE9C20ED513DE60D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Siletz Reservation Act amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/96/340">Public Law 96–340</external-xref> (commonly known as the <quote>Siletz Reservation Act</quote>) (94 Stat. 1074) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HFCEFBA5304E34185ABACAF5C68AA9F35" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"><section id="H6D49BF217E4A4F3C88DAE6C1DD1CDE5B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Hunting, fishing, trapping, and animal gathering</header><subsection id="H85E5565C880B495EB0EB677A97AB654D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H5D9FE3BE86D64CD29669FEE80AB45E2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consent decree</header><text>The term <term>Consent Decree</term> means the final judgment and decree of the United States District Court for the District of Oregon, in the action entitled <quote>Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians of Oregon against State of Oregon</quote>, entered on May 2, 1980. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30E9999A9FDB422D81B485863BE4F45B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1733659E809E4B428ACA35FFA669A3A4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Siletz Agreement</header><text>The term <term>Siletz Agreement</term> means the agreement entitled <quote>Agreement Among the State of Oregon, the United States of America and the Confederated Tribes of the Siletz Indians of Oregon to Permanently Define Tribal Hunting, Fishing, Trapping, and Gathering Rights of the Siletz Tribe and its Members</quote> and entered into by the United States on April 22, 1980. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H348F9DACCE2642EA9240A29E8872DE79"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Hunting, fishing, trapping, and animal gathering agreements</header><paragraph id="HC2AB4A0D05654F11A6330069AD3F96FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Siletz Agreement shall remain in effect until and unless replaced, amended, or otherwise modified by 1 or more successor government-to-government agreements between the Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians and the State of Oregon relating to the hunting, fishing, trapping, and animal gathering rights of the Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D1F08AFF68A42579EEFCEF5E98B0D0B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amendments</header><text>The Siletz Agreement or any successor agreement entered into under paragraph (1) may be amended from time to time by mutual consent of the Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians and the State of Oregon.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H009F1536269A4F679382423265503FEE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents of new agreement or amendments</header><text>The Siletz Agreement or any successor agreement entered into under paragraph (1) shall not provide for exclusive or primary Siletz take opportunity outside the exterior boundaries of the 1855 Executive Order Siletz Coast Reservation (as described in section 7(f)(1)(A) of the Siletz Tribe Indian Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/195">Public Law 95–195</external-xref>; 91 Stat. 1418; 130 Stat. 1364)) relative to any other federally recognized Indian Tribe, and shall not provide for new or expanded take of fishery resources in the Columbia River or in the Willamette River from its mouth to the top of Willamette Falls. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D949F24B4394302B47A07196E208851" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any action brought in the United States District Court for the District of Oregon to rescind, overturn, modify, or provide relief under Federal law from the Consent Decree, the United States District Court for the District of Oregon shall review the application of the parties on the merits without regard to the defense of res judicata or collateral estoppel. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7FB71DC95CC543FDB6816753072347FD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Nothing in this section enlarges, confirms, adjudicates, affects, or modifies any treaty or other right of an Indian Tribe.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

