<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE293C1BC3B6E4AF9AE4F6DC8F42C8E67" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3721 IH: United States Postal Service Shipping Equity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3721</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, and title 39, United States Code, to provide the United States Postal Service the authority to mail alcoholic beverages, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFD91EBAE4D534A07A92D026FD9966627" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H431363E3C6A14543ACBBE709E455D9A0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States Postal Service Shipping Equity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2774C4BBF8E442CF81DA5665C62D32C2" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Shipping of alcoholic beverages</header> <subsection id="H339D71BF6D5F403A959899E497CE73D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mailability</header> <paragraph id="HADCF394E204449EB995E7F68E27AB128"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nonmailable articles</header><text>Section 1716(f) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>mails</quote> and inserting <quote>mails, except to the extent that the mailing is allowable under section 3001(p) of title 39</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4D26E158158641DC99C2973A75DAED78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alcoholic beverages</header><text>Section 1154(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended, by inserting <quote>or, with respect to the mailing of alcoholic beverages to the extent allowed under section 3001(p) of title 39</quote> after <quote>mechanical purposes</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H29F4B17AB2A04B2688A2F350B2A7D7AA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Section 3001 of title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D6AB77D312F438FA3309EAB625EC56B" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H341096E9EEBE4C24B5B85E5032BE94C3"><enum>(p)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H582DB7B067E9413EA513EE66BE3031A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Alcoholic beverages shall be considered mailable if mailed—</text> <subparagraph id="HFE91477D65FF4F5598149FC87D8E77E0" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by a covered entity in accordance with applicable regulations under paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9DDD3C44A6264B1399503517F85CA442" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in accordance with the delivery requirements otherwise applicable to a privately carried shipment of an alcoholic beverage in the State, territory, or district of the United States where the addressee or duly authorized agent takes delivery.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H91FFFAF8232D410D9D5FDA59CB9A284D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Postal Service shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to carry out this subsection, including regulations providing that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5BB1819B0A6B46049876BA67938130EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the mailing shall be by a means established by the Postal Service to ensure direct delivery to the addressee or a duly authorized agent at a postal facility;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H48F8E239F49445E68681E36A96AA77C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the addressee (and any duly authorized agent) shall be an individual at least 21 years of age, and shall present a valid, Government-issued photo identification at the time of delivery;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA43A40293CF74D9B9BB922DF0AB14009"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the alcoholic beverage may not be for resale or other commercial purpose; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE87533598DF64115A3AB81324B4CE3BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the covered entity involved shall—</text>
<clause id="HBAED71B801E54042841A19AD3D4F26DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>certify in writing to the satisfaction of the Postal Service, through a registration process administered by the Postal Service, that the mailing is not in violation of any provision of this subsection or regulation prescribed under this subsection; and</text></clause> <clause id="H46DBC8F1DB6C4525A5A8E6E03926C65A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide any other information or affirmation that the Postal Service may require, including with respect to the prepayment of State alcohol beverage taxes.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA3EF4EAB91FE4946A43A270E33C9C3A2" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="HF582F6604FD74FF9A3CEF4D582EECB0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>alcoholic beverage</term> has the meaning given such term in section 203 of the Federal Alcohol Administration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/27/214">27 U.S.C. 214</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H12E9B99BE76F4DEF9B917F4022959FB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>covered entity</term> means an entity (including a winery, brewery, or beverage distilled spirits plant, or other wholesaler, distributer, importer, or retailer of alcoholic beverages) that has registered with, obtained a permit from, or obtained approval of a notice or an application from, the Secretary of the Treasury pursuant to—</text> <clause id="H6F1C8CAB25714A228FCF9C9868CD93F8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal Alcohol Administration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/27/201">27 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></clause>
<clause id="H245714F5AA074CB595532B78EE22F430"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/51">Chapter 51</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5001">26 U.S.C. 5001 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA955122855FD450CBD5C9CBA8CD2813C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the earlier of—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF725819F1A48475DB6F489F0518805BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the Postal Service issues regulations under section 3001(p) of title 39, United States Code, as amended by this section; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2ADF43CBA7004F4F9F58A1514DD47E00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>2 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD5C857BA07304314A4B6B56EB7862F57"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No Preemption of State, local, or Tribal laws prohibiting deliveries, shipments, or sales</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section, the amendments made by this section, or any regulation promulgated under this section or the amendments made by this section, shall be construed to preempt, supersede, or otherwise limit or restrict any State, local, or Tribal law that prohibits or regulates the delivery, shipment, or sale of alcoholic beverages.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1D0C870D202D428895C39C28C85C537F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Liability of the United States Postal Service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States District Courts shall have jurisdiction to render judgment upon any claim brought by a State, local, or Tribal government against the United States Postal Service of a violation of State, local, or Tribal law regarding the sale, mailing, transportation, or importation of alcoholic beverages into any State, territory, or district of the United States. The United States Postal Service shall be liable in the same manner and to the same extent as a private individual under like circumstances, but shall not be liable for interest prior to judgment or for punitive damages.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


