<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFB63ABEADF0E413D80067FB193F160F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 835 IH: Fair Investment Opportunities for Professional Experts Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 835</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Act of 1933 to codify certain qualifications of individuals as accredited investors for purposes of the securities laws.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2E254C5FF5F14DCB95762CBCD4AF5806" style="OLC"><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4078EA67457C49598386FAAF4AAD4677" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Investment Opportunities for Professional Experts Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H761DBFA30E64496D97D895689AE2E622" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition of accredited investor</header><subsection id="HB9C5DE15FBBD4362BBB28C76ED4875B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2(a)(15) of the Securities Act of 1933 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/77b">15 U.S.C. 77b(a)(15)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD2CD735CE674459E9037C9F8BCFF2E97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (i) and (ii) as subparagraphs (A) and (F), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCECF13509C21461E9203EB798092F241"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon, and inserting after such subparagraph the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF24FD1F151543DCA958040B6045A272" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H5CD671E612CD4876B1DF53449C82F6BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any natural person whose individual net worth, or joint net worth with that person’s spouse, exceeds $1,000,000 (which amount, along with the amounts set forth in subparagraph (C), shall be adjusted for inflation by the Commission every 5 years to the nearest $10,000 to reflect the change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics) where, for purposes of calculating net worth under this subparagraph—</text><clause id="HF4A023E12E5F4F4B803B1DCA59A6E402"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the person’s primary residence shall not be included as an asset;</text></clause><clause id="H4FB4841122D547D5B7FD6A57E72885A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>indebtedness that is secured by the person’s primary residence, up to the estimated fair market value of the primary residence at the time of the sale of securities, shall not be included as a liability (except that if the amount of such indebtedness outstanding at the time of sale of securities exceeds the amount outstanding 60 days before such time, other than as a result of the acquisition of the primary residence, the amount of such excess shall be included as a liability); and</text></clause><clause id="HFFBA619C584348109117CE4C1DF445EF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>indebtedness that is secured by the person's primary residence in excess of the estimated fair market value of the primary residence at the time of the sale of securities shall be included as a liability;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C44C5A2C00A4892BA50CC5AAEC6E806"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any natural person who had an individual income in excess of $200,000 in each of the 2 most recent years or joint income with that person’s spouse in excess of $300,000 in each of those years and has a reasonable expectation of reaching the same income level in the current year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AD143CBDB234B64B87C45B87FB7F34F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any natural person who is currently licensed or registered as a broker or investment adviser by the Commission, the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority, or an equivalent self-regulatory organization (as defined in section 3(a)(26) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934), or the securities division of a State or the equivalent State division responsible for licensing or registration of individuals in connection with securities activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA038E6F1F4E0440494432FD3DDAC3185"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any natural person the Commission determines, by regulation, to have demonstrable education or job experience to qualify such person as having professional knowledge of a subject related to a particular investment, and whose education or job experience is verified by the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority or an equivalent self-regulatory organization (as defined in section 3(a)(26) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934); or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8A6699D40B44A1EB5F85BF6723ECEF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>The Commission shall revise the definition of accredited investor under Regulation D (17 CFR 230.501 et seq.) to conform with the amendments made by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

