<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2E0E4DC0CF9C48EF98BDC176E2197588" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 796 IH: Supply Chain Mapping and Monitoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 796</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office in the Department of Commerce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6830A9AE92B544279EAB80CFC7E168EB" style="OLC"><section id="H9F822D82CB094245A06EA0E46678B9CC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supply Chain Mapping and Monitoring Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB3C043842C3A400383AB071232F28178"><enum>2.</enum><header>Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office</header><subsection id="H0526F206376741AAB3CC184B6E70F596"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC0370EBD81B04AF58049210FB1BCB3C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical good or service</header><text>The term <quote>critical good or service</quote> means any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including any mineral, metal, or advanced processed material), article, commodity, supply, product, or item of supply the absence of which would have a significant effect on—</text><subparagraph id="HB7D2FAEC640947F7A3921895A7FAB6E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the national security or economic security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9564FD6DED6F48B39029A50708D5968A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF72AFF469240444B85698E15953C801C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical industry</header><text>The term <quote>critical industry</quote> means an industry that is critical for the national security or economic security of the United States, considering key technology focus areas under this section and critical infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7AF86630D924789827A25DD91B57BB3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given to that term in the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AC32BDD70734333A45693CAE094CFB6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Domestic enterprise</header><text>The term <quote>domestic enterprise</quote> means an enterprise that conducts business in the United States and procures a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9E86317F4A044159243336D21438683" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Domestic manufacturer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>domestic manufacturer</quote> means a business that—</text><subparagraph id="HD36B1893598F43928248F7EE61747354" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducts in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA993831AA5FD4C1B88351D5B40837E7E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if provided financial assistance by the Federal Government, will conduct in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3AB95463FEA473093EF47423BD98598"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Economically distressed area</header><text>The term <quote>economically distressed area</quote> means an area that meets 1 or more of the requirements described in section 301(a) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3161">42 U.S.C. 3161(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE723D7AAB1974B40B02B074BA3FE1ECA"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <quote>Federal agency</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>agency</quote> in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA10032E3F20B4D979EE53ED7BAD16DD8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Industrial equipment</header><text>The term <quote>industrial equipment</quote> means any component, subsystem, system, equipment, tooling, accessory, part, or assembly necessary for the manufacturing of a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5D7899CF7BA49BEB86191B921BB5B0F"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Key technology focus areas</header><text>The term <quote>key technology focus areas</quote> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA378039C28904DE7B76DC5B72CCD672F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Artificial intelligence, machine learning, autonomy, and related advances.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD916AD4A19D440EFAD0B17CA8966F683"><enum>(B)</enum><text>High-performance computing, semiconductors, and advanced computer hardware and software.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03E8A24DD6D845BFA4D521A108110EC3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Quantum information science and technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DB5E097B091424AB0F604F6E4FD7933"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Robotics, automation, and advanced manufacturing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CC4ED8232104E488E489AD5B581EB86"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Natural and anthropogenic disaster prevention or mitigation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8B9F0E4E391422B863B2D0CE664DF7F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Advanced communications technology, including optical transmission components.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBB41AEBE29F4FA58B72C19B0CBDA6D1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Biotechnology, medical technology, genomics, and synthetic biology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BC9EB96A73346689C6CE195308FB67C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Data storage, data management, distributed ledger technologies, and cybersecurity, including biometrics.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB73727A89FC24AECAA801A0F01F12E7A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Advanced energy and industrial efficacy technologies, such as batteries, advanced nuclear technologies, and polysilicon for use in solar photovoltaics, including for the purposes of electric generation (consistent with section 15 of the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1874">42 U.S.C. 1874</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B62A183875F4183B5C90EA05FF903E2"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Advanced materials science, including composites and 2D materials and equipment, aerospace grade metals, and aerospace specific manufacturing enabling chemicals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84551F7E3F3D4EC6AF82E78B06D27E21"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Labor organization</header><text>The term <quote>labor organization</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 2(5) of the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/152">29 U.S.C. 152(5)</external-xref>), except that such term shall also include—</text><subparagraph id="H9A092F3FDBD545F7BE1EC009806FF9FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any organization composed of labor organizations, such as a labor union federation or a State or municipal labor body; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18BB88A3D7BA45A59BA921D162B6F9EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any organization which would be included in the definition for such term under such section 2(5) but for the fact that the organization represents—</text><clause id="HA35CF9B54964447AA5C3FB5C37D2DFE8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>individuals employed by the United States, any wholly owned Government corporation, any Federal Reserve Bank, or any State or political subdivision thereof;</text></clause><clause id="H2FC4A28C255F46178C177DEE130EBA77"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>individuals employed by persons subject to the Railway Labor Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/45/151">45 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="HB155919CBC2B4EA1AB030085BEBEB387"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>individuals employed as agricultural laborers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H957B7CA0340648E1B62C1651E7DBF794"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Manufacturing technology</header><text>The term <quote>manufacturing technology</quote> means technologies that are necessary or incidental to the manufacturing of a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CEC6F49D56645D99C91D9EDC7BA48B0"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <quote>Office</quote> means the Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C4EAFC4BBDD43EEB4E2FFF470CEC4FF"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Relevant committees of Congress</header><text>The term <quote>relevant committees of Congress</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC38D7D962FF948E697B8E8FD5D9FD4C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1D2FDDFB8714D5B8DD4DF18EFB80A51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9864CA2429D45BCB702B62A5CF6CDE4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Finance of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52FE0CDE4B8B4DADA5AAFEC77319C0EB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8442353ECCE24871B28F9E785810F1A5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC54021F6AD274279A9692F3061090D3D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3606763094143498C437AE80AA8C48E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H885BD3C5860B4D7BBA9BF214E3BD1C5E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7D22398E68B476F8CF9AC92B0B14E61"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51833B0FB9A3432BB5F7E7D286EC4995"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47E421A9FA6149858B30F19D56BE16F3"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EBFAD60F80C47CC993A19679B0E9571"><enum>(L)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD51CE244AD5141BBA5A7C3210CC8C287"><enum>(M)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC18AA57C04147CEB5AB14B0B4C003CB"><enum>(N)</enum><text>the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A04370D1F714F909A64C7B41375C08A"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Resilient supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>resilient supply chain</quote> means a supply chain that—</text><subparagraph id="H008CF0D6A5A744D9A06155814508EC39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures that the United States can sustain critical industry production, supply chains, services, and access to critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology during supply chain shocks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5CD1402E07145EF9F95748F5573EBBA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has key components of resilience that include—</text><clause id="HCB45F48C6A5D4251A39BF65E5272CF55"><enum>(i)</enum><text>effective private sector risk management and mitigation planning to sustain supply chains and supplier networks during a supply chain shock;</text></clause><clause id="H612B89612C344D218087D54E8916B8B2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>minimized or managed exposure to supply chain shocks; and</text></clause><clause id="H160FF660697B45F98551D8B89989295E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the financial and operational capacity to—</text><subclause id="H3D336A29F6474C82B3799EB4EBFB388D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>sustain supply chains during supply chain shocks; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0EB6E5A469BC41109B7FD234AEF7AD33"><enum>(II)</enum><text>recover from supply chain shocks.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C84D9CCE95D4EB1AA6D109A3A1C0A23"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C58A978FE7F4F50984D050C1BE56EE8"><enum>(16)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands of the United States, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0B8424F0DEA4060B90C45674F29E1B2"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain</quote> means a supply chain for a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BCD17E2C6E047449B7A8655E0348DF5"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Supply chain information</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain information</quote> means information that is not customarily in the public domain and relating to—</text><subparagraph id="HC6F1CAA9ECFE4F819963E931849357E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sustaining and adapting supply chains during a supply chain shock;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H655025438C98481EB02051B09074117B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supply chain risk mitigation and recovery planning with respect to a supply chain shock, including any planned or past assessment, projection, or estimate of a vulnerability within the supply chain, including testing, supplier network assessments, production flexibility, risk evaluations thereto, risk management planning, or risk audits; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H113F53AAADFE40D38038DC36375A73BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operational best practices, planning, and supplier partnerships that enable enhanced resilience of supply chains during a supply chain shock, including response, repair, recovery, reconstruction, insurance, or continuity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0CFFAD98D30419DB8679B3B1FDFFF0C"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Supply chain shock</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain shock</quote> includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="HAC845F5CB31B49C48900DDBD5B532AD6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A natural disaster or extreme weather event.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC898DA1C7D784AC2B4BD38CF79F2570C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An accidental or human-caused event.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00BC7324734F4EFB8011548ABEAAD99C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An economic disruption.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD3C05858D0A49459013826C14F157F6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A pandemic.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C983979D61146A0936D8829288B4520"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A biological threat.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE51A717B6F2448808178D0B6276E13E5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A cyberattack.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB576DC29143F4F3A845C388197402ACC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A great power conflict.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAC8EE17191449FB87C859D517F3DE78"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A terrorist or geopolitical attack.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF5D13B1F03D48D299BEBBE17BE13A20"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Any other supply chain disruption or threat that affects the national security or economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE205E7AA5D5E4CAFA3E6D01D7FEC9D74"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <quote>Tribal government</quote> means Indian Tribes, Alaska Native Tribal entities, and Native Hawaiian communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EE5702A123F406EAB35E3F916A3403E"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Under Secretary</quote> means the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response appointed pursuant to subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26B3B986F90D46AA94AD2696A61C28E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office to carry out the activities described in subsection (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H73CC88F345C94D9A89554B5C60C798BE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Office shall be the following:</text><paragraph id="H9F261A8FAD3B4F8885DCDD712B99D175"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Help to promote the leadership of the United States with respect to critical industries and supply chains that—</text><subparagraph id="H8408FC8F11034C92AB7F071FCEA481E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strengthen the national security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6987FD0CBF394DF595D36EF75A61575A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a significant effect on the economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18DBA68C29744B25847A272269056E6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Encourage partnerships and collaboration with the Federal Government and the private sector, labor organizations, the governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States, State governments and political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments in order to—</text><subparagraph id="H4BB706704A844EB9A18D31C627420B53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote the resilience of supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F690EB390524061B1EC54C7C1C6C17B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>respond to supply chain shocks to—</text><clause id="H4B5D9B30DBD74121BC1BBAB0FF6C8655"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical industries; and</text></clause><clause id="H7BC41930C23C4758A1A4AC4F685C938C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supply chains.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H37CA42CC3A79434598E0BA2F5B790DED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Monitor the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains and critical industries, including by—</text><subparagraph id="HE75177E69E1146C7BAE0D516AD08ECF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>monitoring the financial and operational conditions of domestic manufacturers and domestic enterprises;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5C8485ABBF3482F8374B43F5BAFC1EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>performing stress tests for critical industries, supply chains, domestic enterprises, and domestic manufacturers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H222260E804C541BDAE96C96F474CFDE3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>monitoring the demand and supply of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H471E48EB047F438CB2F3900AF6818134"><enum>(D)</enum><text>monitoring manufacturing, ware­hous­ing, transportation, and distribution; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FBEF4EDECD84ABBB20218FC49E86F23"><enum>(E)</enum><text>working in partnership with the coordination group established under subsection (g), as applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA0FDD2ADA3340B1AC02FBA7C6D7AA29"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Support the development, maintenance, improvement, competitiveness, restoration, and expansion of the productive capacities, efficiency, and workforce of critical industries and domestic manufacturers of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H724CD1E1FE9949B8A314DB56E53EF1C3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Prepare for and take appropriate steps to minimize the effects of supply chain shocks on critical industries and supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD519859E27044985B36EB032D833F586"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Support the creation of jobs with competitive wages in the manufacturing sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20E04401FABA4B93B0DADF06A015C82D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Encourage manufacturing growth and opportunities in economically distressed areas and communities of color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E5A7DCA4C984B0B8FACD04F62E58763"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Promote the health of the economy of the United States and the competitiveness of manufacturing in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1726715DAE94F38BEF171F02229708B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Coordinate executive branch actions necessary to carry out the functions described in paragraphs (1) through (8).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEBF23B7874EA4F7891773F4B0562E6C7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Under Secretary of the Office</header><paragraph id="H36DC9585A5644E15A88E8A99BD75D698"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment and term</header><text>The head of the Office shall be the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response, appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, for a term of not more than 5 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA7CC068564641138E2AF8F87BBAA14C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pay</header><text>The Under Secretary shall be compensated at the rate in effect for level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C39B8818D834787AB032A2274993270"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative authorities</header><text>The Under Secretary may appoint officers and employees in accordance with chapter 51 and subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H11480708B77E40EC95A004263F88BAC6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>The Under Secretary shall carry out the following activities:</text><paragraph id="H33D96B5EB3C14922A8D360924AC3622C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In collaboration with the coordination group established under subsection (g)—</text><subparagraph id="HFBAE5E8FE67740AE8EF18282744BC2EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>map, monitor, and model supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA148D3FC21E4B809E73B17D1C6F6A4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify high priority supply chain gaps and vulnerabilities in critical industries and supply chains that—</text><clause id="H8CEE24A28A97422D8B8491B777536982"><enum>(i)</enum><text>exist as of the date of the enactment of this section; or</text></clause><clause id="H7B7CD19D79394916BC97DE107937826C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are anticipated in the future.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H03F00119923247FD972556376665F607"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Identify and evaluate—</text><subparagraph id="HE5E103B5C7D24C08920DA962BA76194C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supply chain shocks that may disrupt, strain, compromise, or eliminate a supply chain;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D9500B910644575B08DE52017AE0500"><enum>(B)</enum><text>short-term, medium-term, and long-term manufacturing needs critical to the national security, economic security, public health, and the environment of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EB0A34A56674F319114BB6972463124"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the diversity, security, reliability, and strength of—</text><clause id="H767E8CA8F55F406A9C1FA2E5938556BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>supply chains, including single point of failure, single producer, or consolidated manufacturing; and</text></clause><clause id="HFE06398542594890B9037288A9AD2384"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sources of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, or manufacturing technology, including those obtained or purchased from a person outside of the United States or imported into the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H532451350FA4435E80677EA1744EF9A7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the demand and supply of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC865A10BED344929876D887E6F3979FA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the availability, capability, and capacity of domestic manufacturers or manufacturers in allied nations or other key international partners to serve as a source of a critical good or service, industrial equipment, or manufacturing technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD75631FCE0E8461381564618A0E33743"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the effect on the economic security of the United States, including jobs and wages, that may result from the disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of any supply chain;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BCAAEF7FA92435E9D2C18C09759A3B2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the state of the manufacturing workforce, including—</text><clause id="H9A97178C484C4B24935D9827AEF6BD2C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the needs of domestic manufacturers; and</text></clause><clause id="H026B71D548974B159620B9C9BCAFA1D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>opportunities to create high-quality manufacturing jobs; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93F0985177D1461CAEA9B497EF4FE52F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>investments in critical goods and services, industrial equipment, or manufacturing technology from non-Federal sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E40E52F201B45A0936E29110330930C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In collaboration with the coordination group established under subsection (g), State governments and political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments, and, as appropriate, in cooperation with the governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States—</text><subparagraph id="H69AC173D214446DFB3C6C73368985F1F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify opportunities to reduce supply chain gaps and vulnerabilities in critical industries and supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8798F66A6DC14FC1893717978A5BA7CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>encourage partnerships between the Federal Government and industry, labor organizations, State governments and political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments to better respond to supply chain shocks to critical industries and supply chains and coordinate response efforts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A35FD99454440DEBB00C31C5B92C8CB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>encourage partnerships between the Federal Government and the governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D93E96352164A8192406CBAB4EAA445"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop or identify opportunities to build the capacity of the United States in critical industries and supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05B1AB4E8B4847419B93E899D09AD74E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>develop or identify opportunities to build the capacity of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States in critical industries and supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FF104384C3B41D080956F172600E3D5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop contingency plans and coordination mechanisms to improve critical industry supply chain response to supply chain shocks.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H23F37CA64217440E976C4105F216B33B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In coordination with the Secretary of State and the United States Trade Representative—</text><subparagraph id="H8FABFE51B73441379A331FC779D722E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>work with governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States to promote diversified and resilient supply chains industries that ensure the supply of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology to both the United States and companies of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD594783A90B43CA81BDBB508081A527"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate with other offices and divisions of the Department of Commerce and other Federal agencies to use authorities, as of the date of the enactment of this section, to encourage the resilience of supply chains of critical industries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE74A0AEA55CB41809673221245718D15"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Develop strategies and plans to recover from supply chain shocks.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA5783E593684F6091BFD05764AABBA1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Continuous monitoring</header><text>The Under Secretary, in consultation with the head of any relevant Federal agency, including those with jurisdiction over supply chains, shall continuously monitor the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains.</text></subsection><subsection id="H11ABFD7005C849D6B121C5A41E2E18D1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Coordination group</header><paragraph id="HD799CF837606462BB66EADAFDAF0116E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (e), the Under Secretary shall establish a unified coordination group led by the Under Secretary which shall include private sector partners, labor organizations, and, as appropriate, Federally Funded Research and Development Centers, to serve as a method for coordinating between and among Federal agencies described under subsection (k) to plan for and respond to supply chain shocks and support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC2B305CDD264D08AF211FD58232F935"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Through the unified coordination group established under paragraph (1), the Under Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H0865BC9A4F0248D499AABFAA2EC5D376"><enum>(A)</enum><text>acquire on a voluntary basis technical, engineering, and operational supply chain information from the private sector in a manner that ensures any supply chain information provided by the private sector is kept confidential as required under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA047635589B249E0B9BC647EFE9E2C3F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>study the supply chain information acquired under subparagraph (A) to—</text><clause id="H3A8431034F604E6A8FF1036FC8565BE6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify supply chains; </text></clause><clause id="H51813CC5DEFF4A84B892D85AA6F510E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>assess the resilience of supply chains;</text></clause><clause id="HE484ED5F645F42DA9D8C313344FFA8F2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identify supply chains vulnerable to disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination; and</text></clause><clause id="H9D9DEBA7B9824BE7BCA7A2DF5535939C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">inform planning;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F071DEFC063418C971BD5B5A5D9B9A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>convene with relevant private sector entities to share best practices, planning, and capabilities to respond to potential supply chain shocks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C5197718144437E83F229DE4ED41A5E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop contingency plans and coordination mechanisms to ensure an effective and coordinated response to potential supply chain shocks.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2851CB79C3304592B7E264091897F443"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Subgroups</header><text>In carrying out the activities described in paragraph (2), the Under Secretary may establish subgroups of the unified coordination group established under paragraph (1) led by the head of an appropriate Federal agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD18CFBB8CFD841A9AA8DB09F8BDC3502"><enum>(4)</enum><header>International agreements</header><text>The Under Secretary, in consultation with the United States Trade Representative and any other relevant Federal agency, may enter into agreements with governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States relating to enhancing the security and resilience of supply chains in response to supply chain shocks.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B07713B34A04165B99F6D3A968EE58A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Designations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H8F3317A0ED844877B52EB2C51DBF930C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>designate—</text><subparagraph id="HB1C296D83E9943B5AA99AD1FCEE855C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>critical industries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4160C4CFB6524FD0A38B835E1914D76A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2110FE00994F4545A75DE657A8C29130"><enum>(C)</enum><text>critical goods and services;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D489FA089CE4DC3B298FA842EC6F2E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide for a period of public comment and review in carrying out paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C631C10ABA54ECB93DCB7B4DC35B0B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>update the designations made under paragraph (1) not less frequently than once every four years.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFC275742BDEE4CA49DCB8399E0F8E6EC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Quadrennial report on supply chain resiliency and domestic manufacturing</header><paragraph id="H08137DED8D174C5D841284CC893D637B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than four years after the date on which the final Sectoral Supply Chain Assessments report on supply chains required under section 4(a) of Executive Order 14017 (relating to America’s supply chains) is submitted, and not later than once every four years thereafter, the Under Secretary, in coordination with relevant Federal agencies and relevant private sector entities, labor organizations, State governments and political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments, shall submit to the relevant committees of Congress and post on the website of the Under Secretary a report on supply chain resilience and domestic manufacturing (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>report</quote>) to strengthen, improve, and preserve the diversity, security, reliability, and strength of supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3A28799EC694749A3FD31D9B3FD4AE6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Under Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H6BD324B7EBEF4A7C9FE3D1D07E3F3734"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify—</text><clause id="H1396B1403D8D40D0BE0F22C87DE6F673"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the critical industries, supply chains, and critical goods and services designated under subsection (h);</text></clause><clause id="H37817E75DA5846BAA1F49910294FD6CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supplies that are critical to the crisis preparedness of the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H02459428C097402D89261A905EA77406"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>substitutes for critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology; and</text></clause><clause id="H7657FAE2F4444B739D5217D357D9DBC0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the matters identified and evaluated pursuant to subsection (e)(3);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4FB50A213E54FF498196B2FF27F019E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide a description of—</text><clause id="HB149AA23DDC64B68B6C0529A03B02F4E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the manufacturing base and supply chains in the United States, including the manufacturing base and supply chains for—</text><subclause id="HD9D53A93A57D426A8626348FAF193DA9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>industrial equipment;</text></subclause><subclause id="H88FD9524083A4D379929EDE1BA6AA4D7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>critical goods and services, including raw materials and semiconductors, that are essential to the production of technologies and supplies for critical industries; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA77FFC651CC04C63B16189B7A7B2EA2A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>manufacturing technology; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0B9934230EA14F118DA2B53CE264CC46"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the ability of the United States to—</text><subclause id="H76F3CE80219E4BA0B27C7A452A6E902D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>maintain readiness with respect to preparing for and responding to supply chain shocks; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE14DBB15892D41748D26F18D5BCF689B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in response to a supply chain shock—</text><item id="H20DB1F3EDF2E4AC2950AF3C0916A79F6"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>surge production in critical industries;</text></item><item id="HC55D46F6F3564A92883860DFCBDCA76D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>surge production of critical goods and services and industrial equipment; and</text></item><item id="H4AEF9C468DA948A68C5B22F7237321BB"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>maintain access to critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A8E8CAF16CE4CC9BDCCD305BBC1A5FD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide an assessment and description of—</text><clause id="H3A0307A8EF69434294FC07DA33A57239"><enum>(i)</enum><text>demand and supply of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></clause><clause id="H4E7AD965D60B4C91AB4899E453BB78D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>production of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology by domestic manufacturers; and</text></clause><clause id="H5D67A384B64242C48068CCF0F57F0255"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the capability and capacity of domestic manufacturers and manufacturers in countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States to manufacture critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD599E3F2F5945C2AB1738DD6C4D015B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identify defense, intelligence, homeland, economic, domestic labor supply, natural, geopolitical, or other contingencies and other supply chain shocks that may disrupt, strain, compromise, or eliminate a supply chain;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B7DEEE452D543E98DACA6450B3A3E67"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provide an assessment of—</text><clause id="H38EEACA3CEF84C1E80820C3179B8EC95"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the resilience and capacity of the manufacturing base, supply chains, and workforce of the United States, the allies of the United States, and the key international partners of the United States that can sustain critical industries through a supply chain shock;</text></clause><clause id="HF7B17F27505341F28C2D0DD385878A92"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the flexible manufacturing capacity and capabilities available in the United States in the case of a supply chain shock; and</text></clause><clause id="HB5CD87C078ED4C528BAF47EAE09C172C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the effect innovation has on domestic manufacturing;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7193282824A747E48A1BBBEFEA8AD581"><enum>(F)</enum><text>provide specific recommendations to improve the security and resiliency of manufacturing capacity and supply chains through—</text><clause id="H4CD37D30B0A34B5E89287D5827475A6A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>developing long-term strategies;</text></clause><clause id="HD0FCFD754E5D490998660684FC68D20A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>increasing visibility into the networks and capabilities of suppliers and domestic manufacturers;</text></clause><clause id="H53FF4E0E6AF44A33B53C6EFFC6FE0DF2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifying industry best practices;</text></clause><clause id="H9F3EE826B65542BBA0496B8C99068C7A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>evaluating how diverse supplier networks, multi-platform and multi-region production capabilities and sources, and integrated global and regional supply chains can—</text><subclause id="HBFED7123FC7141329E8089787E1D97EB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>enhance the resilience of critical industries in the United States;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5828AEEF0E964B61A3C3E10F3AF8DD36"><enum>(II)</enum><text>support and create jobs in the United States;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC123D793B8474A3A872C2FBC35E76FBE"><enum>(III)</enum><text>enhance the resilience of manufacturing capabilities of the United States; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA2F2E33E82B94A1EB5294656471838A9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>support access of the United States to critical goods and services during a supply chain shock;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6F91EB73D8CF4073B9D8CCA0CB1D3D9F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>identifying and mitigating risks, including—</text><subclause id="HAA333BCC40A6437F816FE79B34AA3B2D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the financial and operational risks of a supply chain;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4DC3344C5B7C4152AD299EDA22F0A256"><enum>(II)</enum><text>significant vulnerabilities to supply chain shocks and other emergencies; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC0AF7E0D6A9948FA990A051A941E464C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>exposure to gaps and vulnerabilities in—</text><item id="HEDEB6CB8C2E847FD9A8882EE835A890B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>domestic capacity or capabilities; and</text></item><item id="H6E68DB58A5D74FEF89F6C7E0E1D7F9E5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>sources of imports needed to sustain critical industries and supply chains;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H073C9E35ACC6432688EE93A3CA042F4F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>identifying enterprise resource planning systems that are—</text><subclause id="HFAEE7AA5833A4EF3BCE6BF555102A893"><enum>(I)</enum><text>compatible across supply chain tiers; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HFFD890971FCC461A9321AEFC7F83CED6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>affordable for small- and medium-sized businesses;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD46B0E059C364D9D8A6940A5EC26BCDF"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>understanding the total cost of ownership, total value contribution, and other best practices that encourage strategic partnerships throughout supply chains;</text></clause><clause id="H7ECA8661FB8B4715963A081490F426AD"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>understanding Federal procurement opportunities to increase resiliency of supply chains and fill gaps in domestic purchasing of critical goods and services;</text></clause><clause id="H35430797E4524FD287A92167125ED8E6"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>identifying policies that maximize job retention and creation in the United States, including workforce development programs;</text></clause><clause id="H04ED24BF3A06457CB3BD2B48B2F1C37A"><enum>(x)</enum><text>identifying opportunities to work with allies or key international partners of the United States in building more resilient critical industry supply chains and mitigating risks;</text></clause><clause id="H87B2981DD3A349A398597C9C4C11948E"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>identifying areas requiring further investment in research and development or workforce education; and</text></clause><clause id="H058E9B16D85946EDBD3D1161093FCB80"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>identifying such other services as the Under Secretary determines necessary;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31E3DA75E8A24F0490DBD247BF70EA9F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>provide guidance to the Department of Commerce, the National Science Foundation, and other relevant Federal agencies with respect to critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technologies that should be prioritized;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA22013C7460A452AB908630C25B84C4E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>with respect to countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States—</text><clause id="HBF8D20B657814E20BCAD0771EC745DD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>review and, if appropriate, provide recommendations for expanding the sourcing of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology associated with critical industries from those countries; and</text></clause><clause id="H1226FB543DD54EA786EFBF67E0CBDCBD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>recommend coordination with those countries on—</text><subclause id="H94D647601D2347A8B89B9FCD53893F75"><enum>(I)</enum><text>sourcing critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H43076D0CD1F044C0A12E835B5922570D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>developing, sustaining, and expanding production and availability of supply chains, critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology during a supply chain shock;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E9B5551674C417DA5DEE815B3B39F51"><enum>(I)</enum><text>make recommendations for strengthening the financial and operational health of small- and medium-sized businesses in supply chains of the United States and countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States to mitigate risks and ensure diverse and competitive supplier markets that are less vulnerable to failure; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40971E38CE904AACB8007EACC7BE6BE8"><enum>(J)</enum><text>make an assessment of policies, rules, and regulations that impact domestic manufacturers’ operating costs and inhibit the ability for domestic manufacturing to compete with global competitors; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76429410DBFE404CB3138C542862C9FB"><enum>(K)</enum><text>make recommendations regarding freight and logistics necessary to support supply chains.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2C513D680BE4B1580B3D52418FFD590"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>The report may not include—</text><subparagraph id="HC83B4106BB8A4EB888409E82F6C9930E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supply chain information that is not aggregated; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA399DFEBEF194251828A71CAFF080305"><enum>(B)</enum><text>confidential business information of a private sector entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A81D02D11CE4382884E55A26494F70F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>The head of any Federal agency with jurisdiction over any supply chain shall collaborate with the Under Secretary and provide any information, data, or assistance that the Under Secretary determines to be necessary for developing the report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8810F2BD347B465C9CF213F756B297E0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report submitted under this subsection, and any update submitted thereafter, shall be submitted in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC03299DFE4F4D80B5C328714CC5FC1F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>The Under Secretary shall provide for a period of public comment and review in developing the report required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H694773AE6DAB481FA27F4E8638FEEAD0"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Concurrent with the annual submission by the President of the budget under section 1105 of title 31, United States Code, the Secretary shall submit to the relevant committees of Congress and post on the website of the Under Secretary a report that contains a summary of the activities required under subsection (e) carried out under this section during the fiscal year covered by the report. Such report shall be submitted in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD161BC4B08A34730BF1108D2F02BE866"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Coordination</header><paragraph id="HF4C80BD0B53949958AE01093AF2CD00D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In implementing the requirements under subsection (i), the Under Secretary shall, as appropriate coordinate with—</text><subparagraph id="H98018DD4165D44DFAE875A52D6372811"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the heads of appropriate Federal agencies, including—</text><clause id="H7BF798D650BA4D008E82DA35D4E0FA8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary of State; and</text></clause><clause id="HB4168527DACF449DB3A26F0211A24B4A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the United States Trade Representative; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A77D303474246A3A3B5364A31CB7DB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Attorney General and the Federal Trade Commission with respect to—</text><clause id="HBDAE03D346BC491382F21FE665165773"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advice on the design and activities of the unified coordination group described in subsection (g)(1); and</text></clause><clause id="HE36EB04723B14111997500EB5B7516F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensuring compliance with Federal antitrust law.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H577323F7427B4F64814BCF4DFA5F0C89"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specific coordination</header><text>In carrying out the requirements under this section, with respect to supply chains involving specific sectors, the Under Secretary shall, as appropriate, coordinate with—</text><subparagraph id="HEB9CA8EE62ED462A8CDA44E11CBE39B7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60853F37B657421C80DA31883A14333A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7A3F368CFE34D10A3EDC0ECC99B78B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23E854762AD3459F8A7A7E0835DB8A9B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13CAD177D6FE4A3BAD2949A41BFD3727"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Secretary of Transportation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB10998C599934BD2A280F6399627AF88"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83943F4E54414BCAAEA8B4FBF7F237E0"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Under Secretary of National Intelligence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2729482FAEA64AB79BA0F2FB9AA7F214"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A9F250101A345F698A28C0A104F9CE9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Small Business Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA92DCC2C9E3245E7957DB97BE3882A27"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the Secretary of Labor; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5876C221B0034F4EB6E2C29D7EA14D88"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the heads of other relevant Federal agencies, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF57FD287F0C24304B401C79795596EA7"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require any private entity—</text><paragraph id="H798F828D0CCA4984A3FB61C2DC053349"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to share information with the Secretary or Under Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF52B9EC307B42D8ADF438279F222E29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to request assistance from the Secretary or Under Secretary; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03BDE89885754F308A875C8F2E5BA399"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that requests assistance from the Secretary or Under Secretary to implement any measure or recommendation suggested by the Secretary or Under Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D2A0CAC4549492B9C9B9EB6F0D86C82"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Protections</header><paragraph id="H7402A6630D944A6E97295C9ED647E9CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Supply chain information that is voluntarily and lawfully submitted by a private entity and accompanied by an express statement described in paragraph (2) of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HA25185CB23004815B922ADAE26A07217"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be exempt from disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC00EAB4736774CA191CAE2D302C8CF5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be made available by any Federal, State, local, or Tribal authority pursuant to any Federal, State, local, or Tribal law requiring public disclosure of information or records; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF06D84CF2964E599FF7201F61554E5D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall not, without the written consent of the person or entity submitting such information, be used directly by the Under Secretary, or any other Federal, State, or local authority in any civil enforcement action brought by a Federal, State, or local authority.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A004CD039964A5399681DE05CDE3541"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Express statement</header><text>The express statement described in this paragraph, with respect to information or records, is—</text><subparagraph id="HFB5748BBF8F04431872068CFFC5B008F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of written information or records, a written marking on the information or records substantially similar to the following: <quote>This information is voluntarily submitted to the Federal Government in expectation of protection from disclosure as provided by the provisions of section 2(m) of the <short-title>Supply Chain Mapping and Monitoring Act</short-title>.</quote>; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC55A8E507BA6478D91C1AE3602D48C2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of oral information, a written statement similar to the statement described in subparagraph (A) submitted within a reasonable period following the oral communication.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0F9310028FE4909A1B636FA50E1001B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inapplicability to semiconductor incentive program</header><text>This subsection shall not apply to the voluntary submission of supply chain information by a private entity in an application for Federal financial assistance under section 9902 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD52B95589D804A3D84EB08580DF7146A"><enum>(n)</enum><header>No effect on discovery</header><text>Subject to subsection (m), nothing in this section, nor any rule, regulation, or amendment shall be construed to create a defense to a discovery request, or otherwise limit or affect the discovery of supply chain information from a private entity arising from a cause of action authorized under any under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF37584D624524575A940F1E62003F917"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Implementation report</header><paragraph id="HB63959D490384F68B3039D72F87D35F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the relevant committees of Congress and post on the website of the Under Secretary a report on the implementation of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD5F171357314B87B677C63EE632BD8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE10061D8289B47ACBF877DAC9FFD8AE7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify any office or bureau within the Department of Commerce that the Secretary determines has duties, responsibilities, resources, or expertise that support or duplicate the mission of the Office;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACB9F8E380F944D2A18EB85465051839"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describe the purposes of the offices or bureaus identified under subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56CD6D5DFB67415FB55DDE194C420193"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify if the Under Secretary is coordinating with the offices and bureaus identified under subparagraph (A) in implementing the requirements of this Act; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E15DC4B12584FB5942E074613F2EDE8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>if the Secretary makes a positive determination under subparagraph (C), evaluate the effectiveness and efficiency of the Under Secretary and the offices and bureaus identified under subparagraph (A) at implementing the requirements of this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBC9B367372D4DE4B1501CF4EB96428B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>identify if the Secretary will consolidate functions amongst the Office and the offices and bureaus identified under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1FCD852D347F40A498D6B7D598564CED"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Consistency with international agreements</header><text>This section shall be applied in a manner consistent with United States obligations under international agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4BB9AF17D0254AA3908E004B43165BAA"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Under Secretary $500,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, to carry out this section, of which not more than 2 percent per fiscal year may be used for administrative costs.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

