<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF38A0CE657BF42799C1DA306EB92D5EF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1228 IH: Combating Racist Training in the Military Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1228</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230228">February 28, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001184">Mr. Massie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To prohibit the United States Armed Forces from promoting anti-American and racist theories.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H16D6AF484D5146E080ECB47932D87A77" style="OLC">
<section id="H6D66AAF42D9A432E9AFD274C87948B03" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combating Racist Training in the Military Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8C1BC3197FDA4676B2D31A15B0648715"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
<paragraph id="HFF60F89B71D94C2DADFF98E3ED28B158"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The founding principles of the United States include the belief, enshrined in the Declaration of Independence, that <quote>all men are created equal</quote> and <quote>are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2A682098EE5C444D99FDFE668EB0D136"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States commitment to the equal dignity and natural rights of all mankind is the strongest possible defense against racism and oppression of all kinds.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB8BAD20A4A16435E9EAEF63387D31CD2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The mission of the United States Armed Forces is to <quote>support and defend the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic</quote> and <quote>bear true faith and allegiance to the same</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H288F8A17EDFD44CD92DA88938E058860"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To carry out this mission, the Armed Forces must train leaders who love the United States, its citizens, and the aforementioned founding principles.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H79C8017BF5B342558830ED27D13ABF4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Anti-American and racist theories, such as <quote>Critical Race Theory</quote>, teach that the United States is a fundamentally racist Nation, that the Constitution is a fundamentally racist document, and that certain races are fundamentally oppressive or oppressed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H34816D10424F434285A104F88AD0A850"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Such theories encourage people to judge and treat others differently on the basis of their race, rather than treating them as equal citizens and human beings with equal dignity and protection under the law.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H073538FCD6DB41589D3B3CC0047EC852"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Anti-American and racist theories, such as Critical Race Theory, teach students to distrust and even hate their country and fellow citizens.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DB177621C224D4D88ECCB82FDBB83F1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States Armed Forces should not promote or otherwise encourage anti-American and racist theories that demoralize and divide its members while undermining its mission to <quote>bear truth faith and allegiance</quote> to the Constitution.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H904B9C8EC82C4825963FA5A4BC5FF3E6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on promotion of anti-American and racist theories</header>
<subsection id="HA6FFC2B390334BF395B33B571F36A02F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The United States Armed Forces and academic institutions operated or controlled by the Department of Defense shall not promote the following anti-American and racist theories:</text> <paragraph id="H9FE31F6983414055ABCB447DCA03AD37"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any race is inherently superior or inferior to any other race.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H843DC1EE78C6424D9041F54F3776484F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States of America is a fundamentally racist country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H221C33913E784FBB882B35351B0F0D26"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Declaration of Independence or the United States Constitution are fundamentally racist documents.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9C5E64EF1CE94CF88A8A17363D3C9313"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An individual’s moral character or worth is determined by his or her race.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7A5AE70E6B94735A6DF72A2C93D73EB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An individual, by virtue of his or her race, is inherently racist or oppressive, whether consciously or unconsciously.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB9890C1047145F8B7E8C097AFDA0591"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An individual, because of his or her race, bears responsibility for the actions committed by other members of his or her race.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8E927DA67E594EF6AFDFA8790F0FFF37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Promote defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>promote</term> means the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H24CA2D3274B448BFA2CE8C71052A0D58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Including theories described under subsection (a) or materials that advocate such theories in curricula, reading lists, seminars, workshops, trainings, or other educational or professional settings in a manner that could reasonably give rise to the appearance of official sponsorship, approval, or endorsement.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0A3B76166A34259B55D9445577129C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Contracting with, hiring, or otherwise engaging speakers, consultants, diversity trainers, and other persons for the purpose of advocating theories described under subsection (a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H13BFB74B94D4449CA7203D9B20176212"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Compelling members of the Armed Forces to affirm or profess belief in theories described under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0F2CA7145FBD4E99ACAB7344F487270E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Segregating members of the Armed Forces or other individuals by race in any setting, including educational and training sessions.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H92612E9F1D3E46F9B1D5C807429BBBD9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header>
<paragraph id="HDC3CBB6DA2524160BB7BB15B793D7B5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Protected speech not restricted</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to restrict the protected speech of members of the Armed Forces or any individual. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H278B5FEC7E2A4627AACFE68D7C8054C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Access to materials for the purpose of research or independent study</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent individuals from accessing materials that advocate theories described under subsection (a) for the purpose of research or independent study.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDB91F0F9922F497DA582E25B24A6030D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contextual education</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent the United States Armed Forces and academic institutions operated or controlled by the Department of Defense from stating theories described under subsection (a) or assigning materials that advocate such theories for educational purposes in contexts that make clear the United States Armed Forces and Department of Defense does not sponsor, approve, or endorse such theories or works. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

