<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFE1774880D744264BBB4E92EB00BB5DF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1000 IH: Ordering Authentication in The House’s Swearing-in Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1000</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Clerk of the House of Representatives to provide Members-elect of the House with written copies of the oath of office prior to the first session of a Congress and to provide that a Member-elect who signs such copies shall be considered to have taken the oath of office.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H706602CDCF6D45A4834957AAEC452B09" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA75EF597B32042D5B71D65E8941CC5D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ordering Authentication in The House’s Swearing-in Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>OATHS Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HB590FC1A8EB04B2AA0DDBDDC0A9314D5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of signed written copy for taking oath of office by Members of House of Representatives</header> <subsection id="H30E36BC09A564E8095BB736F6902D513"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 30 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/25">2 U.S.C. 25</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE11D42000BA646488C1A46C47B1EC950"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the first undesignated paragraph; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56246E6992F44804AD2B4DAEEFD3599D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the remaining paragraph and inserting the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD677BA8BD18F437E9D14E22467166BD6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H7E23DC5A33DF44B5A80113DF89A0FF2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Provision of written oath of office by Clerk</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prior to the first session of Congress after every general election of Representatives, the Clerk of the House of Representatives shall cause the oath of office to be printed and shall furnish 2 copies to each Representative-elect, Delegate-elect, and Resident Commissioner-elect, who shall sign the copies and return them to the Clerk.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD60EE9982ECB4432BBF5703A6947F569"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Filing of signed copies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon receiving a signed copy of the oath of office under subsection (a), the Clerk shall file one copy in the records of the House of Representatives, and shall cause the other copy to be recorded in the Journal of the House and in the Congressional Record.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB0B65E3BFFF14638A4E04C3CF717BE7D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Legal effect of returning signed copies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The signed copy of the oath of office, or a certified copy thereof, or the copy filed or recorded under subsection (b), shall be admissible in evidence in any court of the United States, and shall be held conclusive proof of the fact that the individual who signed the copies duly took the oath of office in accordance with law, effective—</text> <paragraph id="HB08724DB2B814E1DA3CF9201BBBE0804"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at noon on the first day of the first session of Congress, in the case of an individual who returns the signed copies to the Clerk prior to noon on the first day of the first session of the Congress; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49998CCF123946828B4925CB2210590A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at the time the individual returns the signed copies to the Clerk, in the case of an individual who does not return the signed copies to the Clerk prior to noon on the first day of the first session of the Congress.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE2344F836F6C4BF8B9F0204DD6178CD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to the One Hundred Nineteenth Congress and each succeeding Congress.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


