<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H034E41F074554B0EBC021DA4436E9F52" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2781 IH: To provide for the withdrawal of the United States from the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2781</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the withdrawal of the United States from the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H42C45DC01B43492B9CA42AB5467CD4B2" style="OLC"><section id="HB232FE7ABEA54DE5B10C6AF8B878C5B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Withdrawal of the United States from the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President shall—</text><paragraph id="HAA1FBCD4035B44759FEBD2C0AC73E582"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 5 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, provide written notification to the Depository of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, done at Rio de Janeiro, June 3–14, 1992, of the withdrawal of the United States from the Convention effective on the date that it is 1 year after the date of receipt by the Depository of such notification of withdrawal in accordance with Article 25 of the Convention; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB18AEAE9F254938A9843E6EDD1F1C3E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the effective date described in this section, withdraw the United States from the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDB9E274C4E4E4289A39EA2E0F56160FF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No funds authorized or appropriated by any Act may be used to support, directly or indirectly, any efforts on the part of any United States Government official to take steps to carry out the obligations of the United States under the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change on or after the effective date described in section 1.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

