<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2EB42A27299041D194F377067C8D6A78" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 992 IH: Bicycles for Rural African Transport Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 992</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish within the Office of Gender Equality and Womens Empowerment of the United States Agency for International Development a rural mobility program to promote mobility in rural communities through access to affordable, fit-for-purpose bicycles, provide support to sustainably increase access to rural areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB4B8E9C6AB6B4D709D59454650210F7D" style="OLC"><section id="H73A951D6B89E4118B38EED707AA09ACF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bicycles for Rural African Transport Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H656C48D31FC04E528B076A3802DBCC30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Rural mobility program in sub-Saharan Africa</header><subsection id="HBF028155E43D4135B1FEDD423A193A5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="H6FE9B60E1CB84558B4CC9CC4F2E00E51"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) shall establish within the Office of Gender Equality and Women’s Empowerment of USAID a rural mobility program (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>) to carry out the purposes described in paragraph (2), including through grants made to eligible nongovernmental partner organizations, prioritizing those organizations with demonstrated success conducting rural mobility programs in the region to so carry out such purposes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFF6A1322F4745EB9B1CE3E0C9FA406E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The program shall focus on country-driven projects within sub-Saharan Africa to—</text><subparagraph id="HE38F8716A8F347629AB42DE272C455D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote rural communities’ access to critical services and opportunities, including education, health care, and livelihood opportunities, through access to affordable, fit-for-purpose bicycles; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08ABAD7494594843A7EE869E2DEEBAB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide support to sustainably increase access to critical services such as education, health care, and livelihood opportunities in rural areas, including through support for rural-based mechanics, access to spare parts, reduction of social and gender-based stigma, and community project management capacity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H29B27F6237374488B3007A4E55147DC2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>To the greatest extent practicable, the program shall partner with existing entities overseas that have successful models for providing access to affordable bicycles to achieve development objectives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C994B42172247C187BE8F776E320A2D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated—</text><subparagraph id="H082E5BD684EA458D824FC881A9E4467B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD202E2278E84F588C13A642F31FB294"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H189B77BDBDBC4A01B5B3E89193AADEF2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$6,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC47C9EF28C62479FABE5798163D3BBF4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$6,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0E3C80D378D403BAA72D5FBE7A9E159"><enum>(E)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2028 and each fiscal year thereafter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE236DF7E8D48486F904856E32DE28523"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H01673064FF074D139A9697E3C07E5BB6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prior projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of USAID shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report on projects carried out by USAID during each of fiscal years 2020, 2021, 2022, and 2023 relating to the purposes described in subsection (a)(2). The report shall—</text><subparagraph id="H1B00292298D44F5F945A3364562992CD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify in which countries USAID embedded rural bicycle mobility into strategies, programs, and projects of USAID;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97809352675F454B93074A22A7E37707" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describe the mechanisms by which rural bicycle mobility was so embedded;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41898992B9ED4DD1915E836636CC9947" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>specify the number of bicycles distributed each fiscal year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69927AE08DED4806BBF461C31DE0FA40" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>assess the outcomes for and impacts on participants in such projects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3148FFAE6D22467EA65A0C22C9A92F0A" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>assess USAID’s efforts to disseminate lessons learned from such projects.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E34633D4DB5492DABED62494D8BE236"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Current projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 30, 2025, and each December 30 thereafter, the Administrator of USAID shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report on projects carried out by USAID during the immediately preceding fiscal year. Each such report shall include information relating to the matters described in subparagraphs (A) through (E) of paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

