<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H95514F285621410AA0AC925B0D68C57B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3303 IH: Maternal Health for Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3303</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide support for programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs relating to the coordination of maternity health care, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3153CCF83C7F48AF9CDD43E0FF9C3CBE" style="OLC"><section id="H480D3A4AF9E244C3AB77ADEC5A9AF28E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maternal Health for Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5F219C026FF34E918CC15CD13989B929"><enum>2.</enum><header>Support for maternity health care coordination programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H33B2FAAC68024BA7B7B5711213BC2DFF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until September 30, 2028, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and make publicly available, a report that contains the following:</text><paragraph id="HDFFE1F1C38374D218F98A12AD3D4F980"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A summary of the activities carried out under the programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs relating to the coordination of maternity health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BCF03B7F08A4FB5A996D8E592D8D35D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data on the maternal health outcomes of veterans who receive medical care or services furnished at a medical facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs or by a non-Department of Veterans Affairs health care provider who provides such care or services to veterans under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, including pursuant to the programs specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C17D8A42EF5416A8454523283675B11"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Recommendations by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to improve the maternal health outcomes of veterans, with a particular focus on veterans from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8D1A97CCC5E24448966D14FB3B540890"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H85419262668A4A3FAD9D5E2C68162C56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024, 2025, 2026, 2027, and 2028, for the programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs relating to the coordination of maternity health care, including the maternity care coordination program described in Veterans Health Administration Directive 1330.03 (or any successor directive).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H984F6E0FB21C4D2293E9DB13EAFED016"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Amounts authorized under paragraph (1) are authorized in addition to any other amounts authorized for the coordination of maternity health care for the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

