<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H22E0D3C5BDC045E7B3328D9C36DA95BC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 759 IH: No Energy Revenues for Russian Hostilities Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 759</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To limit the authority of the Secretary of the Treasury to authorize United States financial institutions to engage in certain Russian-related energy transactions.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HADA883A0BBD0432C9D6EC0CE887B2774" style="OLC"><section id="H3D63F26E91EC468DA47E0BA8CB011E9A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Energy Revenues for Russian Hostilities Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HACC12EE5AD9A44D2B80518B6DABAD2B5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on authorizing certain Russian-related energy transactions</header><subsection id="HC285CD6BBAE04F18950867E9CCDB8356"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury may not authorize, or continue in effect any existing authorization for, a United States financial institution to engage in a transaction described under General License No. 8E, dated December 15, 2022, with respect to Executive Order 14024 of April 15, 2021.</text></subsection><subsection id="H688CC44D83094DDCBC9D5493A59AB9A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may waive subsection (a) for up to 90 days at a time for a United States financial institution upon certifying to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate that—</text><paragraph id="H0B53C4281377467FB07038097895DBC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the waiver is only applicable to transactions that involve funds owed to a Russian person; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB397E27C1EC467C8F6A60328A09AF3D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the funds, subject to approval by the Secretary, are to be used for the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H962A8584D0534955B1120196C6CC6CB2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Subsection (a) shall have no force or effect on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H8C0FC527E4E148D8A3A3EFD9485EDFBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD86CD163E7BE4261BB5D140B7D985D45"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">30 days after the date that the President reports to Congress that the Government of the Russian Federation has ceased its destabilizing activities with respect to the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

