<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF60971DEE7B541EE90BBE316C4E29B50" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4155 IH: Tribal HUD–VASH Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4155</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for rental assistance for homeless or at-risk Indian veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HA16268D4DD9048C4970B27932CE7C13C" style="OLC">
<section id="H8F7C07E4613B47FB8BCE0041F1FD699F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tribal HUD–VASH Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H444C6D5644C34544982AD68067B33745"><enum>2.</enum><header>Rental assistance for homeless or at-risk Indian veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o)(19) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(19)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H94B1E6B96F28423BB12B9AA301441F97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (D) as subparagraph (E); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H808E03A8175442C1A466726826AA15FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following new subparagraph (D):</text>
<quoted-block id="H97841C4FB963462AB9202AEE1EFADA5F" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H83AAE0A1C355479F8566937676B8E110"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Indian veterans housing rental assistance program</header>
<clause id="H0B4F2037A5564CF08D209A6FDF3C5141"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subparagraph:</text> <subclause id="H3063C8443E4C4B01AD9C4AD2D9EF4A0F"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Eligible indian veteran</header><text>The term <quote>eligible Indian veteran</quote> means an Indian veteran who is—</text>
<item id="HFBE84BDB00704A3D9F27580479F38B30"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>homeless or at risk of homelessness; and</text></item> <item id="H176154A2245F4F978C7CD186325F9572"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>living—</text>
<subitem id="HDBADA52171B143BF90836D892FA94782"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>on or near a reservation; or</text></subitem> <subitem id="H652CF8AB16B244A0B98087BB20EC0630"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>in or near any other Indian area.</text></subitem></item></subclause>
<subclause id="HDF16A7C9B02B495EAA27EE75AA5AF266"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Eligible recipient</header><text>The term <quote>eligible recipient</quote> means a recipient eligible to receive a grant under section 101 of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4111">25 U.S.C. 4111</external-xref>).</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4789E12FED1D4FBA93BA0027677920B0"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Indian; indian area</header><text>The terms <quote>Indian</quote> and <quote>Indian area</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 4 of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4103">25 U.S.C. 4103</external-xref>).</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCC6F2B6B5684487C9DA7CD763F5AB43F"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Indian veteran</header><text>The term <quote>Indian veteran</quote> means an Indian who is a veteran.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H32BF9FBAEEB84A8AB65F33F7F5EAF7C8"><enum>(V)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <quote>Program</quote> means the Tribal HUD–VASH program carried out under clause (ii).</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H967AC5C1A9C344B5AF73293134CF9D5F"><enum>(VI)</enum><header>Tribal organization</header><text>The term <quote>tribal organization</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA638E3F085D74F1A9E99F60744FB11C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Program specifications</header><text>The Secretary may use up to 5 percent of the amounts made available for rental assistance under this paragraph to carry out a rental assistance and supported housing program, to be known as the <quote>Tribal HUD–VASH program</quote>, in conjunction with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, by awarding grants for the benefit of eligible Indian veterans.</text></clause>
<clause id="H06FA3697BB0146D1908BCE61BDD9C805"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Model</header>
<subclause id="H91EEC0D81ACC49919FFA5A7FECB02D03"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subclause (II), the Secretary shall model the Program on the rental assistance and supported housing program authorized under subparagraph (A) and applicable appropriations Acts, including administration in conjunction with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H22A20C9CAEF948CB9175DA8EAE5BE644"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <item id="H4EEA8E0FCE1F4906AED3B6A84DA538EF"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Secretary of housing and urban development</header><text>After consultation with Indian tribes, eligible recipients, and any other appropriate tribal organizations, the Secretary may make necessary and appropriate modifications to facilitate the use of the Program by eligible recipients to serve eligible Indian veterans.</text></item>
<item id="H334AF4E5DC804B99A4ADA4956F55BEC6"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Secretary of veterans affairs</header><text>After consultation with Indian tribes, eligible recipients, and any other appropriate tribal organizations, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may make necessary and appropriate modifications to facilitate the use of the Program by eligible recipients to serve eligible Indian veterans.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H470FC178ED9D42ADB7E4BC60536BD5C4"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Eligible recipients</header><text>The Secretary shall make amounts for rental assistance and associated administrative costs under the Program available in the form of grants to eligible recipients.</text></clause>
<clause id="HFACAD16C3F474329B97AA5308D9BCE55"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Funding criteria</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants under the Program based on—</text> <subclause id="HA0DA2559CA7C440E869D2A37818583A1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>need;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1F4DE3CC810F479694FC0BB923397D73"><enum>(II)</enum><text>administrative capacity; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H63FBC54EBFB14E98AD01C3F624655523"><enum>(III)</enum><text>any other funding criteria established by the Secretary in a notice published in the Federal Register after consulting with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H625CD989D3B94B42A842295F077945AC"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>Grants awarded under the Program shall be administered in accordance with the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4101">25 U.S.C. 4101 et seq.</external-xref>), except that recipients shall—</text> <subclause id="HA3A2018CE7624AF38C16141AE1F4B245"><enum>(I)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary, in a manner prescribed by the Secretary, reports on the utilization of rental assistance provided under the Program; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1833B7682B6646BE8A3A85ED179354E5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary information specified by the Secretary to assess the effectiveness of the Program in serving eligible Indian veterans.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HE4C71FFDBA3E44668D8DD9E1B7FA34FE"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Consultation</header> <subclause id="HE597DDC3CE5B4C46A0E92A6DBBF561FA"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Grant recipients; tribal organizations</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall consult with eligible recipients and any other appropriate tribal organization on the design of the Program to ensure the effective delivery of rental assistance and supportive services to eligible Indian veterans under the Program.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HDC20FB5572DC4F1080B69A34BE927D6A"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Indian health service</header><text>The Director of the Indian Health Service shall provide any assistance requested by the Secretary or the Secretary of Veterans Affairs in carrying out the Program.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA402BA60C3A9413DABF59D250173AF57"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Waiver</header> <subclause id="HD91ABAFB5EF543249A99A9114156E8C8"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subclause (II), the Secretary may waive or specify alternative requirements for any provision of law (including regulations) that the Secretary administers in connection with the use of rental assistance made available under the Program if the Secretary finds that the waiver or alternative requirement is necessary for the effective delivery and administration of rental assistance under the Program to eligible Indian veterans.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H38423CE7AE8E4EEA9785F12982258C0E"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Secretary may not waive or specify alternative requirements under subclause (I) for any provision of law (including regulations) relating to labor standards or the environment.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HD1BF0C23FE83493E872D232F170A7B21"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Renewal grants</header><text>The Secretary may—</text>
<subclause id="H51D851453D6846C4B645AE9B5832104D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>set aside, from amounts made available for tenant-based rental assistance under this subsection and without regard to the amounts used for new grants under clause (ii), such amounts as may be necessary to award renewal grants to eligible recipients that received a grant under the Program in a previous year; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7EBAC23F5DD045A5B464288C05C3EDD8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>specify criteria that an eligible recipient must satisfy to receive a renewal grant under subclause (I), including providing data on how the eligible recipient used the amounts of any grant previously received under the Program.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H1B02B57A03014BCFBFEBDE5EB64182CE"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, and every 5 years thereafter, the Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Director of the Indian Health Service, shall—</text> <subclause id="H9BC6C3572492440E9E5822D44AACB690"><enum>(I)</enum><text>conduct a review of the implementation of the Program, including any factors that may have limited its success; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1038F084B25A4A30AFE58E4AAEBAD3DA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>submit a report describing the results of the review under subclause (II) to—</text> <item id="HE334D24560BA444E88D093E439D8BEC6"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Committee on Indian Affairs, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></item>
<item id="HCEF089F9C1674E739D0764788A2AF7CD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Subcommittee for Indian and Insular Affairs of the Committee on Natural Resources, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H478D3B702B534EFFB9230EC8F866E03B"><enum>(xi)</enum><header>Impact on formula current assisted stock</header><text>For a given fiscal year’s allocation formula of the Native American Housing Block Grants program, as authorized under title I of NAHASDA (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4111">25 U.S.C. 4111 et seq.</external-xref>), the number of qualifying low-income housing dwelling units under section 302(b)(1) of NAHASDA (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4152">25 U.S.C. 4152(b)(1)</external-xref>) shall not be reduced due to the placement of an eligible Indian veteran assisted with amounts provided under the Tribal HUD–VASH Program within such qualifying units.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


