<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2DCF00DE5D3C45009B777468698613AE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3521 IH: Saving America’s Future by Educating Kids Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3521</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to develop and disseminate an evidence-based curriculum for kindergarten through grade 12 on the dangers of vaping and misusing opioids, synthetic drugs, and related substances.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H035E2AF6E9C74E088E677C3C53E3D45B" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H65BD0589E4D242648A65A3A0F4199C1A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Saving America’s Future by Educating Kids Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8DDEE33D8AC249C893A87C83EE06147E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Evidence-based curriculum on substance use disorders</header><subsection id="H42AF37E2A4B4420C8FB24170DDF77D42"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H6291F70B7AEF4BFE8DAE4C20724C59A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Development and dissemination of curriculum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Education, in consultation with the partners described in paragraph (2), shall develop and disseminate an evidence-based curriculum for kindergarten through grade 12 on educating students at an age-appropriate level on the dangers and harmful impacts of substances that focuses on opioids, vaping, synthetic drugs, and other related substances of misuse.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC07CFB39B4C64AAE82C435B4E8A29CF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partners</header><text>The partners described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H483D6534B7284469BCDDD3C2C54D5680"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC9451CA48C446CB9F95A950F0EEC5C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FF0389F537C4DEEB421DA8762D3309D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary of the Administration for Children and Families.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF04EF21CC47041748722E3BCC983ABFE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Commissioner of Food and Drugs. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5979BEBB3F34B46BB5DF1BB1B4B8864"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Director of the National Institute on Drug Abuse or a designee of the Director from the National Institute on Drug Abuse.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFC207046D4441139018E1FAF551BC04"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Director of the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism or a designee of the Director from the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F756C7FD94448BD8D4C7FE29D9F2C69"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice or a designee of the Administrator from the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC20E89DB691A40C2BCA9B86DB6BBE599"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1346B05B7490466C9FB49EA7DA5D3458"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional consultation</header><text>The Secretary of Education may also consult with State educational agencies, local educational agencies, and single State agencies during the development of the evidence-based curriculum under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE168A45187A4D29882F7A0134B44E2A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Review and update</header><text>The Secretary of Education, in consultation with the partners described in paragraph (2), shall review and update the evidence-based curriculum developed under paragraph (1) every 2 years.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F5C638C1453471BB54CA6797A7E6D35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Competitive grant program</header><paragraph id="H5F737228586240F1BF86A1EB48343EC5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning the first fiscal year following the completion of the development of the evidence-based curriculum under subsection (a)(1), the Secretary of Education, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to State educational agencies to enable the State educational agencies to implement the evidence-based curriculum. The Secretary of Education shall award not less than 10 grants during each grant cycle. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD9F9A6912824065A7981852C51F585A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A State educational agency that desires to receive a grant under this subsection shall submit an application to the Secretary of Education at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61B16A4F0ED04F28B8D9489C2871F67D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary of Education shall give preference to States that have experienced the highest drug overdose death rates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A8E47D4C8D548AFAFBC8C3435C356E6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Subcontract</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this subsection may subcontract with community coalitions that are currently, as of the date of application, a recipient of a grant under section 1032 of the Anti-Drug Abuse Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1532">21 U.S.C. 1532</external-xref>), to implement the evidence-based curriculum, as needed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6005B7A02C82427D8E27D51CA16482F2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Each State educational agency that receives a grant under this subsection shall provide an annual report to the Secretary of Education and the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use on the State educational agency's curriculum implementation progress and program reach, in order to monitor the quality of implementation of the evidence-based curriculum.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2168701255444D1B03C0389F77487C1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2B6249D4A4634B18BCB9C8A012C0F1C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evidence-based</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AC6F380100A4337A9425E108B3B4387"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Single State agency</header><text>The term <term>single State agency</term> means the State agency responsible for administering the substance abuse prevention and treatment block grant under subpart II of part B of title XIX of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300x-21">42 U.S.C. 300x–21 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB6DE0712EEE4E6F88B432FE2E88BCA6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State educational agency</header><text>The term <term>State educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1731895FAEC64D809CE45154B1A45213"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2033. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

