<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC1373C62123D46FF9DAC9BD6195E051C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3881 IH: Credit Card Competition Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3881</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Electronic Fund Transfer Act to require the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve system to prescribe regulations relating to network competition in credit card transactions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5C41C499A0A648568A63E4692D3786F7" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HD689B17592FB4900BF95D54762E0B8A9"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Credit Card Competition Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB776191359154D00954D5A0477219607"><enum>2.</enum><header>Competition in credit card transactions</header> <subsection id="HE7C663A988924A98B9FEA4EC1646E90F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 921 of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-2">15 U.S.C. 1693o–2</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6235B99A3FEB4BC1AB1835AC93B78E36"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H5845CAEBF8E045CAB940BEF1BDCAF17B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2), (3), and (4) as paragraphs (3), (4), and (5), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAF331FC352345F4A1754CB4144822C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBFCA4493445449B3AB027DA09EB5A6ED" act-name=""> <paragraph id="H879B3CB3D06144CF860504BB482614CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Competition in credit card transactions</header> <subparagraph id="H4BE53D1DA4F44084B384DE92BC3909F8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>No exclusive network</header> <clause id="HF207D52382A544E7A46627BF4EC53B4C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Credit Card Competition Act of 2023</short-title>, the Board shall prescribe regulations providing that a covered card issuer or payment card network shall not directly or through any agent, processor, or licensed member of a payment card network, by contract, requirement, condition, penalty, technological specification, or otherwise, restrict the number of payment card networks on which an electronic credit transaction may be processed to—</text> 
<subclause id="H3EEA1835D48B44A5850DD2FA239FF8D4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>1 such network;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H483EAB503E4044F0AB9D7663C57DC365"><enum>(II)</enum><text>2 or more such networks, if— </text> 
<item id="H75802F2D3EC740398B7930A3BA0092DE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>each such network is owned, controlled, or otherwise operated by—</text> <subitem id="HE7D3E7BA0D95414DA249008009BED8F4"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>affiliated persons; or</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="H08CC34AD71EF4774BE4739A595C61A01"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>networks affiliated with such issuer; or</text></subitem></item> <item id="H22406EE7EE32452783548578FDC8B31A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>any such network is identified on the list established and updated under subparagraph (D); or</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H42E647AB5BC24E0CB9A3A061B0C3BC86"><enum>(III)</enum><text>subject to clause (ii), the 2 such networks that hold the 2 largest market shares with respect to the number of credit cards issued in the United States by licensed members of such networks (and enabled to be processed through such networks), as determined by the Board on the date on which the Board prescribes the regulations.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HF910A7EE538D401FA987F037CCEEDA13"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determinations by Board</header> <subclause id="H19575B35EC5645EF8B390EA47C845C43"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board, not later than 3 years after the date on which the regulations prescribed under clause (i) take effect, and not less frequently than once every 3 years thereafter, shall determine whether the 2 networks identified under clause (i)(III) have changed, as compared with the most recent such determination by the Board.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1F7255FB917A46EA94634DFE296D33E9"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Effect of determination</header><text>If the Board, under subclause (I), determines that the 2 networks described in clause (i)(III) have changed (as compared with the most recent such determination by the Board), clause (i)(III) shall no longer have any force or effect.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4439D9B4174945249DB33FB45381E304"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No routing restrictions</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Credit Card Competition Act of 2023</short-title>, the Board shall prescribe regulations providing that a covered card issuer or payment card network shall not— </text> 
<clause id="H10DF92F8E5914F46B60F8D238ADB3CA2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>directly or through any agent, processor, or licensed member of the network, by contract, requirement, condition, penalty, or otherwise—</text> <subclause id="H7B23BD08CCA740AEAA8FEF3F0D64D287"><enum>(I)</enum><text>inhibit the ability of any person who accepts credit cards for payments to direct the routing of electronic credit transactions for processing over any payment card network that— </text> 
<item id="HFFDCC3A30121451BADA23F8DF377E12B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may process such transactions; and </text></item> <item id="H84611FABF08947BD9F8A054F6674BAAF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is not on the list established and updated by the Board under subparagraph (D); </text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2B058B3CEB6C42C1B5104C138774DDB6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>require any person who accepts credit cards for payments to exclusively use, for transactions associated with a particular credit card, an authentication, tokenization, or other security technology that cannot be used by all of the payment card networks that may process electronic credit transactions for that particular credit card; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE8D97E8C7D5844DCB83E2AD5228AEBA1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>inhibit the ability of another payment card network to handle or process electronic credit transactions using an authentication, tokenization, or other security technology for the processing of those electronic credit transactions; or</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H8231FE8453F1499E892E715F8D9373D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>impose any penalty or disadvantage, financial or otherwise, on any person for— </text> <subclause id="H2A96E623B6764C609E3E0C33E6E87DE4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>choosing to direct the routing of an electronic credit transaction over any payment card network on which the electronic credit transaction may be processed; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H02A3AD38C4C84F70B750D06AA824BEBB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>failing to ensure that a certain number, or aggregate dollar amount, of electronic credit transactions are handled by a particular payment card network.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9BC8B2D1782141999E7F3964E5FC8270"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The regulations prescribed under subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall not apply to a credit card issued in a 3-party payment system model.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8C3CF5BBB35845A9A6FFF1486E7AC37B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Designation of national security risks</header> 
<clause id="H4978788597CD4CB6B7BD4D5C07B627E8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Credit Card Competition Act of 2023</short-title>, the Board, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, shall prescribe regulations to establish a public list of any payment card network— </text> <subclause id="H5119E3C862CD4E9D93D1FB1BD8E35A3C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the processing of electronic credit transactions by which is determined by the Board to pose a risk to the national security of the United States; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HFFC6D5FBFE944782AA6F3F91E277B262"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that is owned, operated, or sponsored by a foreign state entity.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HD5F669FE75644CA9B5A60089F4B1DCDC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Updating of list</header><text>Not less frequently than once every 2 years after the date on which the Board establishes the public list required under clause (i), the Board, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, shall update that list.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0BD40022DF5342C6AAD0A0EA57D9B799"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph—</text> <clause id="H4A7FE1024A174DDCA528D107637EF4F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the terms <term>card issuer</term> and <term>creditor</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 103 of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1602">15 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7F2CBF351D3A4745927B059727DBCC6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the term <term>covered card issuer</term> means a card issuer that, together with the affiliates of the card issuer, has assets of more than $100,000,000,000;</text></clause> <clause id="H2E5EDCFD959D4390B67550A2FDB599B6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the term <term>credit card issued in a 3-party payment system model</term> means a credit card issued by a card issuer that is—</text> 
<subclause id="H3DF11C2FF320474AB1B09DA60C00E854"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the payment card network with respect to the credit card; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB09403C9425A4D2B8BDB9967B50CBEE1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>under common ownership with the payment card network with respect to the credit card;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H7A3095978CD64316809D3F412F0CFCD8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the term <term>electronic credit transaction</term>— </text> <subclause id="H4630943F9D3F406997182F91F225C452"><enum>(I)</enum><text>means a transaction in which a person uses a credit card; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF24FCC3DD5A941EEBB04A4346D6AF0B2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>includes a transaction in which a person does not physically present a credit card for payment, including a transaction involving the entry of credit card information onto, or use of credit card information in conjunction with, a website interface or a mobile telephone application; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H64DD7E4BBE59465FA7B7BA3CAFA075F2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the term <term>licensed member</term> includes, with respect to a payment card network—</text> 
<subclause id="HC73003203FD7440DA0FA64D735AA10BD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a creditor or card issuer that is authorized to issue credit cards bearing any logo of the payment card network; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H1C853D9BB1CB4C77AEE843D49024596D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any person, including any financial institution and any person that may be referred to as an <quote>acquirer</quote>, that is authorized to—</text> 
<item id="H3D426426A7E5452FB8F652A41B5D5358"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>screen and accept any person into any program under which that person may accept, for payment for goods or services, a credit card bearing any logo of the payment card network;</text></item> <item id="H1922FAE548334E2AB5FB64F5D6ABC45A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>process transactions on behalf of any person who accepts credit cards for payments; and</text></item> 
<item id="HDCC6329A86924407A6FEFEFCB2B6B192"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>complete financial settlement of any transaction on behalf of a person who accepts credit cards for payments.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64C2DE0175024CB493800200BFF4B44F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1), by inserting <quote>, except that the Bureau shall not have authority to enforce the requirements of this section or any regulations prescribed by the Board under this section</quote> after <quote>section 918</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H328AF720F3F14773A440C294F33E7260"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Each set of regulations prescribed by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System under paragraph (2) of section 921(b) of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-2">15 U.S.C. 1693o–2(b)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a) of this section, shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date on which the Board prescribes the final version of that set of regulations.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

