<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H534992873C414B178388D94FCFF7325E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 5288 IH: SWIFT Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5288</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230825">August 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To make further improvements relating to women’s rights and protections, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1B7BBFF2ED44C4594640C13D3988BFC" style="OLC"><section id="HCADE64D7213D4DCA8D5B5DAED97DFCCD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Women’s Independence For Today Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote>SWIFT Act of 2023</quote>.</text></section><section id="H88D217E0F5754C2A9BA6F1CD7ECDBE14"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements to health education curriculum<editorial></editorial></header><subsection id="HD641E6E4FCE04AA49A10FECCB2F6A1E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Health education in high schools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Education shall encourage each public high school in each State to implement health education curriculum that includes information on the prevention of rape, sexual assault, and sexual harassment.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC84D693B2AF74F76AD99E9CD64012894"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Health education in institutions of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 487(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7D128507CFCB4C5CAEFACA2E697F6B9A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H649CBBA3F4FF4FF485ED61CD64852D50"><enum>(30)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The institution will—</text><subparagraph id="H9C6286C08B594225849B7E757BA26A71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>implement health education curriculum that includes information on the prevention of rape, sexual assault, and sexual harassment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEEBC309FDE943549C01EA3327ED8174"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require each student enrolled at such institution to complete such curriculum.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H41CD9773AE9F47739C39E7558073FEE3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2848317598F141698ED54841723C54B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>High school</header><text>The term <term>high school</term> has the meaning given such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BEA9E5B2ADC492D87351235B11C6E18"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H673C45D2B43841B19796E787D8047946"><enum>3.</enum><header>Comprehensive education program to improve healthcare system with respect to domestic violence and sexual assault</header><subsection id="H9D597762608A47688980AE0E5F34B2FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that there should be a national effort to educate first responders and healthcare workers on how to engage with victims of sexual assault and violence.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F8931D6B3D54C63B5AB0CA5B4BAE709"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of comprehensive education program described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the 13th of December after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Attorney General, in coordination and consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall implement a comprehensive education program to improve the healthcare system in the United States and ensure that responses to domestic violence and sexual assault continually improve. </text></subsection><subsection id="H523CAF07263B4BDA87280713C7C10A96"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Comprehensive education program described</header><paragraph id="HBCC5860DDA7148CA9B45FA0E54CF6719"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The comprehensive education program shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HCEAECA5F70134E189314BD8AA0050FB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enhanced training for covered employees, including—</text><clause id="H92E985F24C3E44EAAA5A3F2BB523B5C4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> training that considers mental health and encourages empathy;</text></clause><clause id="HF1363C6F14C649ACBBB932B32D5140DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>training on taking and maintaining diligent records;</text></clause><clause id="H7D028EC1E3ED49F5BD47869A9B72FB08"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>training on the proper handling of evidence; and </text></clause><clause id="H7804C5AED9B844C89C5C73C0F8DEE538"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other type of training relating to mental health that is recommended by the Secretary of Health and Human Services; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DD5A8E1CE294406A067483DFAF23059"><enum>(B)</enum><text>real world situational modules described in subsection (d). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H340FCF27A8964DAFAAFF7A7D31D22B47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement to participate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The comprehensive education program shall be available to any covered employee. A covered employee shall complete the comprehensive education program within the first three months of hire and again at least every two years. Such participation shall be managed and required by the executive of each covered entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDEA7EE3CA2443D4AE1B509728516E4A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>E-certification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covered employees who have completed the comprehensive education program shall be issued an e-certificate which qualifies such an employee to interact with victims of sexual assault, sexual violence, or domestic violence. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C49D978495A4F6D885D9FB052295149"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Real world situational modules described</header><text>The comprehensive education program described under subsection (c)(1) shall include at minimum the following 13 modules:</text><paragraph id="H0897870DF4D6416E860A79F6AD42EBA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A module detailing intake procedures for an individual documenting sexual assault.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC784BA5EA6804560B8D94E5BB16399D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A module detailing intake procedures for an individual documenting domestic violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CD94B0A8592491C997A79097CDD531B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A module detailing how to respond to a scene of domestic violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H668702885D7C4251894A5356EB422F9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A module detailing how to respond to a scene of sexual assault.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F2A5B32B4AA447FA33E5E2C399277A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A module on emotional support and empathy training.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94FF6D57728B4113B9F29DB20EF4C206"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A module on conflict de-escalation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H262B96E8262347D685B395B3B7824FE3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A module on reporting and associated procedures necessary for law enforcement efforts to investigate and prosecute perpetrators of sexual assault, sexual violence, or domestic violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB118E4D24F14781A0B6F7F7746C580A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A module on suicide prevention, de-escalation, and emergency response procedures, including how to interact with an individual dealing with suicidal thoughts or history.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB042976C9BD7436B8C9FFFAFA630FD0B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A module on how to provide services to and handle the needs of victims who are minors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB9D35F159E541C7B87A3423B3B47D2B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A module on Federal, State, and local laws and policies related to sexual assault and domestic violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CABCCB9D3194525952304193180CCD0"><enum>(11)</enum><text>A module on physical evidence collection and record taking procedures for law enforcement, including mandatory reporting requirements for information reported by a victim.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89B8ED52D481416F90F43EFDC4C7C788"><enum>(12)</enum><text>A module on social services references and resources for helping victims in an individualized context.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8F3C9A48F2741BA8830CECD96BBE014"><enum>(13)</enum><text>A module on costs a victim may expect to be associated with care and costs associated with mental health resources and care.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H303BF28603204916905A1A29D41BB024"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Loss of Federal funds</header><text>Any covered entity that does not comply with the requirements of this section shall not be eligible for any Federal funding for the following year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H850A8509CBE14B2ABBE70972DF0E5778" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Fine</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity found to have covered employees in violation of this section shall be fined $50,000 a month per employee who has not completed the requirements of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6A148B89174149FF9DA2A42B40478B79"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reducing national debt</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any fines collected pursuant to subsection (f) shall on December 13th of each year be deposited into the general fund of the Treasury for the sole purpose of reducing the national debt.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0791A2246C8946FC955E2F372C3B6D36"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is appropriated $13,000,000 per State for the Attorney General to carry out this section, to be derived from the unobligated balances of amounts previously appropriated as follows:</text><paragraph id="H67A2F29C3BF5434F94917F84DCD155AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The unobligated balance of all amounts made available to the Attorney General to prevent, prepare for, or respond to the coronavirus as of the date of the enactment of the <quote>Swift Act of 2023</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E1196DC2D74462EAA8D92A4C6378350"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent the unobligated balances described in paragraph (1) do not exceed $650,000,000, an additional amount representing the difference between the amount described in paragraph (1) and $650,000,000, derived from the unobligated balances of amounts appropriated by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> (commonly referred to as the Inflation Reduction Act of 2022) for the Internal Revenue Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB9C9648EA174982AC809AC251DD46C0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent the unobligated balances described in paragraphs (1) and (2) do not exceed $650,000,000, an additional amount representing the difference between the amount described in paragraphs (1) and (2) and $650,000,000, derived from the unobligated balances of amounts appropriated to pay any interest or debt owed by the United States to the People’s Republic of China, or from any amounts made available to provide United States assistance to the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7DAE8F4A183542E7A48290D15469CE3B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3F9512D0D4314DE88C0B53B148DC43AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered employee</header><text>The term <term>covered employee</term> includes any employee of any covered entity who directly, or has the potential to directly, interact with an individual who has been a victim of sexual assault, sexual violence, or domestic violence, including nurses, doctors, physician assistants, law enforcement officers, and first responders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA49A58D7DD66486291BB9DFFF15A9087"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term> includes any entity that employs a covered employee.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA3A5D8A3F90F433D8D25BA47EECA487D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on availability of funds for foreign countries that criminalize or discriminate based on gender</header><subsection id="H70CB1FEA6E724FD0B98D7898CC51DBD2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), no Federal funds may be obligated or expended to provide assistance, directly or indirectly, to a country described in subsection (c) for five calendar years. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8EBCB39065C0476FA95B54C7F554081F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><paragraph id="HD7BD85FE58174773BBF9E33452ED9C3D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may authorize an obligation or expenditure of Federal funds to assist a country described in subsection (c) only if the President determines, on a case-by-case basis, that such proposed obligation or expenditure is vital to the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC262B1F054E4D0CADB1424BD6F2B564"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Upon making a determination under paragraph (1), the President, acting through the Secretary of State, shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees and congressional leadership a briefing on such determination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A67FBFD02F84F1991F6E9F75E841CF8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Countries described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A country described in this subsection is a foreign country the government of which the President determines has enacted or established and is implementing any provision of law, or provision which has the force and effect of law, that criminalizes or discriminates on the basis of gender, including through such provisions that, on the basis of gender—</text><paragraph id="HD1F42BF9EA6D48F2A57CBCC4FF3858CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>limit or prohibit women from—</text><subparagraph id="HA21021AADDCA4D608F41E221031122D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enrolling in or attending any educational institution, school, or other program of instruction, or otherwise seeking or receiving education activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFCDA7CD892F4EEB813303C9ED8094C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operating a vehicle;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F1D8A221FC94ED6B1159235AD098C39"><enum>(C)</enum><text>freely exercising any religion; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H853ED4A0C7AF43048D6339DC1A6FC2D9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>walking or otherwise traveling without a male escort; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H702A219E0338417EB2FC9491FBB90B9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorize (including as a form of punishment) female genital mutilation, sexual abuse, beheading, or any other practice that targets the lives of women.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id23180f98ec844f00a0259f476a4c27b2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pay off the national debt</header><text>Any Federal funds not obligated or expended to provide assistance, directly or indirectly, to a country described in subsection (c) pursuant to subsection (a) or any Federal funds remaining for that fiscal year or previous years for such purpose shall be used to pay off the national debt. </text></subsection><subsection id="H29A537EAC7064199A2EBD017DD945821"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H50FD186B1CF74D4595C4E47D8D35FE30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE3912E12E2EE4D07A6E2D02C87A2E793"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDEC14A9B4B74CAEA15EA985E1BBEAC7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Foreign Relations and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H99A451A340294E70AE44C4B0B1E5F62E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Congressional leadership</header><text>The term <term>congressional leadership</term> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA6E16582B7FA45BEBE3D1E658B2D77C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F1611CE562245A9BCA401D59512115D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AA61771BFE043E5A1661554810B22B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The majority leader of the Senate. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE69604CBC0E04EFCB1DE714D5B82A698"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5C3AC7B7389451882248E0A376E1FA7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3DBC4745310C45968E19308ADBF64925"><enum>5.</enum><header>Funding for prevention and response to sexual violence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is appropriated $13,000,000 for the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to carry out the Rape Prevention and Education Program, to be derived from the unobligated balances of amounts previously appropriated as follows:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id16cdf6bf42484b5b95820a587bd10d88"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The unobligated balance of all amounts made available Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to prevent, prepare for, or respond to the coronavirus as of the date of the enactment of the <quote>Swift Act of 2023</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida88e0dd5e81a40eabe395b4e30fd6509"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent the unobligated balances described in paragraph (1) do not exceed $13,000,000, an additional amount representing the difference between the amount described in paragraph (1) and $13,000,000, derived from the unobligated balances of amounts appropriated by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> (commonly referred to as the Inflation Reduction Act of 2022) for the Internal Revenue Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida1d92f00544240febefd776cba51f8c4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent the unobligated balances described in paragraphs (1) and (2) do not exceed $13,000,000, an additional amount representing the difference between the amount described in paragraphs (1) and (2) and $13,000,000, derived from the unobligated balances of amounts appropriated to pay any interest or debt owed by the United States to the People’s Republic of China, or from any amounts made available to provide United States assistance to the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

