<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0C0A512AE2D14560B4DB5D9807734AB7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 565 IH: Land Restoration and Resiliency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 565</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service to enter into an agreement with the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation to establish the Community Resilience and Restoration Fund.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HECADD3769668471B881BB296C6D1FBC6" style="OLC"><section id="H2F3557F30E5741678D180B07B787D54C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Land Restoration and Resiliency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H8EA885191957457D83F6C18F1E2EBC06"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of Community Resilience and Restoration Fund</header><subsection id="HC1819344C65549EA888DFC8092020DB0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall enter into a cooperative agreement with the Foundation to establish the Community Resilience and Restoration Fund at the Foundation to—</text><paragraph id="HDD47AA30368640ABB5953D947974854B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improve community safety in the face of climactic extremes through conservation and protection of restoration and resilience lands;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H569A04B16583424BA1140798A5224F40"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to protect, conserve, and restore restoration and resilience lands in order to help communities respond and adapt to natural threats, including wildfire, drought, extreme heat, and other threats posed or exacerbated by the impacts of global climate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17B18C3B571B48F7B6A7A0AD89467546"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to build the resilience of restoration and resilience lands to adapt to, recover from, and withstand natural threats, including wildfire, drought, extreme heat, and other threats posed or exacerbated by the impacts of global climate change;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H279C2171B4464474BEE92E6D57FE5F09"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to protect and enhance the biodiversity of wildlife populations across restoration and resilience lands;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H281C4618BAAE4989940D8E759262C5BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to support the health of restoration and resilience lands for the benefit of present and future generations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FBB227C3A4D45EDBF0E76E705DC32BE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to foster innovative, nature-based solutions that help meet the goals of this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0BA457EC45249BCAB6FC9F37669D81C"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to enhance the Nation’s natural carbon sequestration capabilities and help communities strengthen natural carbon sequestration capacity where applicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7AE76203433340EF87BA9CF111277278"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Management of the Fund</header><text>The Foundation shall manage the Fund—</text><paragraph id="H48F3B060F703444BBE5B2F7AA1BD2830"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pursuant to the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation Establishment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3701">16 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32E148CDC3B04322824CAA4A0BFBD325"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in such a manner that, to the greatest extent practicable and consistent with the purposes for which the Fund is established—</text><subparagraph id="HC8516D54A14F4E66ADC2A893099B6128"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures that amounts made available through the Fund are accessible to historically underserved communities, including Tribal communities, communities of color, and rural communities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CCB2E018FCB4ADEA86043D7D0758324"><enum>(B)</enum><text>avoids project selection and funding overlap with those projects and activities that could otherwise receive funding under—</text><clause id="H8CF11CF314BA4BCABF571D7671433E77"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the National Oceans and Coastal Security Fund, established under the National Oceans and Coastal Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7501">16 U.S.C. 7501</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="H7A5E5E8F74F941D39984963519A37254"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other coastal management focused programs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB4397BABA7D442A96750C0250C560B9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Competitive grants</header><paragraph id="HE3EB362B6D91423E9212EF834E2666E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent amounts are available in the Fund, the Foundation shall award grants to eligible entities through a competitive grant process in accordance with procedures established pursuant to the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation Establishment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3701">16 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>) to carry out eligible projects and activities, including planning eligible projects and activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66126DCDBA5749E1A04FF0FF3F3D5C8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Proposals</header><text>The Foundation, in coordination with the Secretary, shall establish requirements for proposals for competitive grants under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27867E3867CF4ED2A3330184C82E1830" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of Amounts in the Fund</header><paragraph id="H0E4F1785A141414FBB340873BA80D8A9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Planning</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 8 percent of amounts appropriated annually to the Fund may be used to plan eligible projects and activities, including capacity building.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54EE5FADC6C04DFEAAD295D582234056" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not more than 4 percent of amounts appropriated annually to the Fund may be used by the Foundation for administrative expenses of the Fund or administration of competitive grants offered under the Fund.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41FAAF408AF04CB4B8A59578254CB47F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 10 percent of the funds appropriated in a fiscal year to the Fund or $10,000,000 (whichever is the lesser amount) shall be awarded in such fiscal year to support eligible projects and activities for Indian Tribes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEB887D7B4FE40489A1299A6B3CD3457"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary and Foundation shall ensure, to the greatest extent practicable and through meaningful consultation, that input from Indian Tribes, including traditional ecological knowledge, is incorporated in the planning and execution of eligible projects and activities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H768835D0FFBC408EB60BFF0E71580B2E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HBF35FE55BF094B33B1F9CC088DB0024C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning at the end the first full fiscal year after the date of enactment of this section, and not later than 60 days after the end of each fiscal year in which amounts are deposited into the Fund, the Foundation shall submit to the Secretary a report on the operation of the Fund including—</text><subparagraph id="H81273282ED274993BEC9A57BD4DE4D25"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an accounting of expenditures made under the Fund, including leverage and match where applicable;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DBED5FC66754289901954854F1CF10D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an accounting of any grants made under the Fund, including a list of recipients and a brief description of each project and its purposes and goals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72388381E71F45659BAC22806A7EB4E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">measures and metrics to track benefits created by grants administered under the Fund, including enhanced biodiversity, water quality, natural carbon sequestration, and resilience.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HECA038786A1A478E84B78EC1079CFD22"><enum>(2)</enum><header>5-Year Reports</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of the fifth full fiscal year after the date of enactment of this section, and not later than 90 days after the end every fifth fiscal year thereafter, the Foundation shall submit to the Secretary a report containing—</text><subparagraph id="H9F9081DE3268472C8C1D91F6C2CCD8CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any socioeconomic, biodiversity, community resilience, or climate resilience or mitigation (including natural carbon sequestration), impacts generated by projects funded by grants awarded by the Fund, including measures and metrics illustrating these impacts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46BF76222BD540EEA64AA21A21F6156C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of land health benefits derived from projects funded by grants awarded by the Fund, including an accounting of—</text><clause id="HE2ACC3629A8A4DBEBB4C3637A8EA9E8F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">lands treated for invasive species;</text></clause><clause id="H754197A0416544BEAC460DE9F0772196"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lands treated for wildfire threat reduction, including those treated with controlled burning or other natural fire-management techniques; and</text></clause><clause id="H58EDFBE793D94A25A8B4AEBB7F0C99C0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>lands restored either from wildfire or other forms or degradation, including over-grazing and sedimentation;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28B077DB14B34810A7BB8797AD1B0AC6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>key findings for Congress, including any recommended changes to the authorization or purposes of the Fund;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DDDBEF345B84FDA972CAF8344C5241F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>best practices for other Federal agencies in the administration of funds intended for land and habitat restoration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34BD9F55A8E546D7A1037492DAAB3FF6"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the use and outcome of funds specifically set aside for planning and capacity building pursuant to section 6; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7BA13530E10437A9F68CF3B43383314"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other information that the Foundation considers relevant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0E2B20AAD8042D3B34244ECB36C3638"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Submission of Reports to Congress</header><text>Not later than 10 days after receiving a report under this section, the Secretary shall submit the report to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE31E8DDD23544DEA5572C274D0ADCCE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There is hereby authorized to be appropriated to the Fund $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029 to carry out this section. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H188639397EA347ACBB156D6D985AE134"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="H20DD7583D4254DC3827D8BEA87BCC303"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a Federal agency, State, the District of Columbia, a territory of the United States, a unit of local government, an Indian Tribe, a nonprofit organization, or an accredited institution of higher education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5C5D62E191B48E2AD5CD9E3D9977413"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible projects and activities</term> means projects and activities carried out by an eligible entity on public lands, tribal lands, or private land, or any combination thereof, to further the purposes for which the Fund is established, including planning and capacity building and projects and activities carried out in coordination with Federal, State, or tribal departments or agencies, or any department or agency of a subdivision of a State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD18046021E6E41FA9AAED31E7D932F1B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Foundation</term> means the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation established under the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation Establishment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3701">16 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63498FE8134B415282F10AB076F72948"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>Fund</term> means the Community Resilience and Restoration Fund established under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB4F50E1C3FF43E6BF650C5A95E9D27F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> means the governing body of any individually identified and federally recognized Indian or Alaska Native Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, affiliated Tribal group, or component reservation in the list published pursuant to section 104(a) of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AD78CA2A8F9426A8DDECC1BCB82CEF6"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>restoration and resilience lands</term> means fish, wildlife, and plant habitats, and other important natural areas in the United States, on public lands, private land (after obtaining proper consent from the landowner), or land of Indian Tribes, including grasslands, shrublands, prairies, chapparal lands, forest lands, deserts, and riparian or wetland areas within or adjacent to these ecosystems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EBC638679CF4352A1839F499DD33D98" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public lands</term> means lands owned or controlled by the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F717DC455574AAEB96C26586F783556"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B32256A0DA5446C8ACA9FE170E73407"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means a State of the United States, the District of Columbia, any Indian Tribe, and any commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

