<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H45E3BA9771B341CF95C2DF2D5CF29AE2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 897 IH: Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary and Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 897</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the establishment of the Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H710F039A677A4B4583BC92FCA05BDCC9" style="OLC"><section id="H7EC2B1CCE1F0415B841A6ECB5C8EA4D3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary and Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5E0D9A20CEC143869B21B46B94DF6567"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H5CB63E7A30244623AE884203FB476B54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An ancient cypress forest dating back 50,000 to 70,000 years has been exposed in the Gulf of Mexico off the Alabama coastline.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67516A28FD8A49FE83C47150E1C1CB15"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The cypress trees, which were uncovered by massive waves associated with Hurricane Ivan, are still rooted in the mud they were growing in at least 50,000 years ago.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4673D15D255C46B39F1E2F26FD5E3F18"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Underwater Forest site is unique on a global scale, the only known site where trees between 50,000 and 70,000 years old have been preserved intact with the ecosystem they were growing in.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2C7248FF5AA46DC9CF393E28913BD12"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Exploration of the site continues to yield invaluable scientific insight in a variety of fields, though scientists have just begun to study the ancient forest.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDB238134DB0B44B39043F380EF19282F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Policy and purpose</header><subsection id="H56E7D934FA3F450ABC5F61D11A3B82CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States to protect and preserve the ancient cypress trees located off the coast of Alabama, known as the Alabama Underwater Forest.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5FE1D77741DC4BA68D387DB468A9A3F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this Act is to protect the resources of the area described in section 5(b), to educate and interpret for the public regarding the ancient Alabama Underwater Forest environment, and to manage human uses of the Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary consistent with this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H259468AB72CC4123B5AF17A9472E046E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act— </text><paragraph id="H1315A48F418949569D7DD4E62FA5E0AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sanctuary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Sanctuary</term> means the Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary designated under section 5(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58F094B994764A2387667EE4AF98DD73"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H015E36CF14B24F27BE535AB8F57A24AF"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sanctuary designation</header><subsection id="HD2002743CAC74FF293F463CA8D9D7C43"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The area described in subsection (b) is designated as the Alabama Underwater Forest National Marine Sanctuary pursuant to title III of the Marine Protection, Research, and Sanctuaries Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1431">16 U.S.C. 1431 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H52697C8D0B164E87818578F6315453B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Area included</header><paragraph id="HAAC8CAAD5AC54E4E9ECD5C6F6E3C4D70"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Sanctuary shall consist only of all waters and submerged lands within the boundary described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67B5BF091AD84B96A39CEBED6D0C1EF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Boundary</header><text>The boundary referred to in paragraph (1) shall encompass only the area within the following coordinates:</text><subparagraph id="HB87E3E6D409A4834A1B4DF050618DE8F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>30 degrees, 7 minutes, 20.2116 seconds north latitude; 87 degrees, 49 minutes, 15.7404 seconds west longitude.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H562AE6FD24364FE4A9C32ADF27F8F245"><enum>(B)</enum><text>30 degrees, 7 minutes, 20.2116 seconds north latitude; 87 degrees, 43 minutes, 44.8536 seconds west longitude.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB2FF9B027534899829BB73B48373994"><enum>(C)</enum><text>30 degrees, 5 minutes, 42.6552 seconds north latitude; 87 degrees, 49 minutes, 15.7404 seconds west longitude.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE287398383646EBA167FA842C7478F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>30 degrees, 5 minutes, 42.6552 seconds north latitude; 87 degrees, 43 minutes, 44.8536 seconds west longitude.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H674A5E4EA9344DF1B2D47C65AE56558D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>30 degrees, 7 minutes, 20.2116 seconds north latitude; 87 degrees, 49 minutes, 15.7404 seconds west longitude.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H37ADB10C916748519E722C096BFE5200"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Charts</header><text>The Sanctuary shall be generally identified and depicted on National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration charts that shall be maintained on file and kept available for public examination during regular business hours at the Office of Ocean and Coastal Resource Management of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and in online format and which shall be updated to reflect boundary modifications made pursuant to this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF35836FFE5504AE79A0D517047B85242"><enum>6.</enum><header>Prohibition of certain uses</header><subsection id="H9F2CBF6F67444D4CBADEF85CA095320B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibited activities</header><text>The following activities are prohibited and are unlawful for any person to conduct or to cause to be conducted within the Sanctuary:</text><paragraph id="H896967DC9E56458591DB0595E879CF11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Cutting, removing, or any kind of subsurface salvage of the cypress trees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58C9285E2BCF415B8CA72DBC76F0882D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Lowering below the surface of the water any grappling, suction, conveyor, dredging, or wrecking device.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6F158D5BF4344EEB9C394DA4BEE6868"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Detonating below the surface of the water any explosive or explosive mechanism.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93E653C8B7C14535B58C3838E0E39B69"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Drilling or coring the seabed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD62D84344BF946398F97B9C4B680CBF1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Lowering, laying, positioning, or raising any type of seabed cable or cable-laying device.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A974E067FE444C18286F70928CC558F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="HBF1AD3A9EEBD4B8F91F5A2E58A637F63"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The prohibitions in subsection (a) shall not apply to the following:</text><subparagraph id="H85C3A463077444C88876D720BA007C05"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fishing, diving, mooring, or similar recreational or commercial activities. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04E0E4C087C9434684C8E8187D50D75D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Necessary operations of public vessels, including operations essential for national defense, law enforcement, and responses to emergencies that threaten life, property, or the environment. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H137302ABC9DB42D585620EB16928A38B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Construction or placement of artificial reef structures for the purpose of enhancing fishery resources, fishing opportunities, or recreational diving opportunities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC01BEA9FA274D03AEB6958707A4378A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Exploration, development, or production of oil or gas pursuant to a lease, permit, or other authorization, provided such lease, permit, or authorization is issued on or before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFAAA8B4A035412693C733BF94566BCC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Office of National Marine Sanctuaries, may allow a person to conduct an activity that would otherwise be prohibited under subsection (a) if such activity meets the standards of Title III of the Marine Protection, Research, and Sanctuaries Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1431">16 U.S.C. 1431 et seq.</external-xref>), as determined by the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD72BE8FBE6614AFEBC4FF9C3BFB71259"><enum>7.</enum><header>Comprehensive management plan</header><subsection id="HE9C2442634724D01A3A6CD1ABAE06A97"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Preparation of plan</header><paragraph id="H8C1A876C8A984052A55EEECC38874163"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in consultation with appropriate Federal, State, and local government authorities and with the advisory council established under section 8, shall develop a comprehensive management plan and implement regulations to achieve the policy and purpose of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28EF73E3FDD646549D14D1B57B65B2EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text>In developing the comprehensive management plan and implementing regulations under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall follow the procedures described in sections 303 and 304 of the Marine Protection, Research, and Sanctuaries Act of 1972 (16 U.S.C. 1433 and 1434).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD7F5B2E3C7149C38F1334DB4185950D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Plan details</header><text>The comprehensive management plan required under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4DE016CC2C2F4A73BE06CE4C16A06CC8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitate all public and private uses of the Sanctuary compatible with the primary objective of Sanctuary resource protection, with a focus on facilitating—</text><clause id="H2F869F23A3474F2487B7EAE5E4978336"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fishing, diving, or similar recreational or commercial activities; and</text></clause><clause id="H87091E1F228B4AA4987002E6676F6A87"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">construction or placement of artificial reef structures for the purpose of enhancing fishery resources, fishing opportunities, or recreational diving opportunities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H253CF78AE9514BC682AC6A3B19643C17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider temporal and geographical zoning, to ensure protection of Sanctuary resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D872E620F744D8DA271FD9E40A718E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify needs for research and ecological monitoring; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B0202978D01415B8435FAF6EEB3F20F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure coordination and cooperation between Sanctuary managers and—</text><clause id="H40D55F29AC7C47DB97BBFFC26996527A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>other Federal, State, and local authorities with jurisdiction within or adjacent to the Sanctuary; and</text></clause><clause id="H1F7CD2440FB04ECEA9B4F8180333FC71"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>owners, operators, and stakeholders with respect to existing oil and gas operations within or adjacent to the Sanctuary. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H93531BB4159142B1B49F1B639A0F18A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for the participation of the general public in the development of the comprehensive management plan.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3615797208F34780A1A0B67580B9C564"><enum>8.</enum><header>Advisory council</header><subsection id="HFDCC42B731004F77800793708E77430E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish an advisory council pursuant to section 315 of the Marine Protection, Research, and Sanctuaries Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1445a">16 U.S.C. 1445a</external-xref>) to advise the Secretary with respect to the designation and management of the Sanctuary. </text></subsection><subsection id="H68257F56368D4449AB02051245E7070C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include a representative from the Alabama Department of Conservation and Natural Resources as a voting member of the advisory council. </text></subsection></section><section id="H15C2AB9528C04E6E95E0A4A99EFF7AF2"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $1,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out the provisions of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

