<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H632539ED427749FAA2C271B53470F90B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2603 IH: To require the Securities and Exchange Commission to revise certain thresholds related to smaller reporting companies, accelerated filers, and large accelerated filers, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2603</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Securities and Exchange Commission to revise certain thresholds related to smaller reporting companies, accelerated filers, and large accelerated filers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFD6B2415341048D8B72292BFA8B7357A" style="OLC"><section id="H73AEA14A87F04BE6811925DDCB6D9183" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Smaller reporting company, accelerated filer, and large accelerated filer thresholds</header><subsection id="H079732C5274C489889A3D65B50AD9A63"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Smaller reporting companies</header><paragraph id="HC2A25525D0B04FB2A9112BE4C5F63AC0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise the definition of a <quote>smaller reporting company</quote> under section 229.10(f)(1) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations—</text><subparagraph id="H5381BA645386404799CA0C919DCBBBF3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (i), by adjusting the public float threshold from $250,000,000 to $500,000,000; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F3AA2CDEBCF4232AFC5133F0367B54B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (ii)—</text><clause id="H74A6DBB821824AADBB2F74AE791667C6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by adjusting the annual revenue threshold from $100,000,000 to $250,000,000; and</text></clause><clause id="H08536E420C9D4F67B087780E3FCFB7EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (B), by adjusting the public float threshold from $700,000,000 to $900,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E679CF578FC4ED6B26727DFEF5CA49B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of three-year rolling average revenues</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise paragraphs (1)(ii) and (2)(iii)(B) under the definition of <quote>smaller reporting company</quote> under section 229.10(f)(1) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, by substituting <quote>three-year rolling average revenues</quote> for <quote>annual revenues</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8096D2042D44BDEB80760EB0B944096"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming changes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise the definition of a <quote>smaller reporting company</quote> under sections 230.405 and 240.12b–2 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, and any other rule of the Commission in the same manner as such definition is revised under paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H32751A70AE344CD98CB6BC5599A1212D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Accelerated filers and large accelerated filers</header><paragraph id="H19088251A3824E8F83E705BC605AD41E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Large accelerated filer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise the definition of a <quote>large accelerated filer</quote> under section 240.12b–2(2) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, to increase the threshold amount (for the aggregate worldwide market value of the voting and non-voting common equity held by non-affiliates of an issuer) from $700,000,000 to $750,000,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E61E5FAA456429BA09FC3691CB8A2F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Threshold to exit accelerated filer status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise section 240.12b–2(3)(ii) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, to increase the threshold amount (for the aggregate worldwide market value of the voting and non-voting common equity held by non-affiliates of an issuer) at which an issuer is no longer an accelerated filer from $60,000,000 to $75,000,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAFC5A037D10433496538ED2F541C721"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Threshold to exit large accelerated filer status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise section 240.12b–2(3)(iii) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, to increase the threshold amount (for the aggregate worldwide market value of the voting and non-voting common equity held by non-affiliates of an issuer) at which an issuer is no longer a large accelerated filer from $560,000,000 to $750,000,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H867C0094F14F45E9830863CE0D38FCF7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exclusion of smaller reporting companies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise the definitions of an <quote>accelerated filer</quote> and a <quote>large accelerated filer</quote> under paragraphs (1) and (2) of section 240.12b–2 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, respectively, to exclude any issuer that is a smaller reporting company, as defined under section 229.10(f)(1) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

