<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8AF39B5CDC744A989E8FB0A8FC84E7E7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4446 IH: Store On-Board Wheelchairs in Cabin Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4446</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require air carriers and foreign air carriers to provide on a publicly available website of the carrier information on requirements for on-board wheelchairs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H66F84BA1685F449689DAB35D1AA63336" style="OLC"><section id="HD1269430DA3A453FBF814C05DA764BAE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Store On-Board Wheelchairs in Cabin Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7BB5CACE878843B6BF4375297A29FF2C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>On-board wheelchairs</header><subsection id="HDBB4A4AF4EF24C9A923725C4D83946E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><paragraph id="H25D3A9CEFBA74983B26CEF8495FCEDE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case an aircraft that is required to be equipped with an on-board wheelchair in accordance with section 382.65 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, an air carrier and a foreign air carrier shall provide in a prominent place on a publicly available internet website of the carrier, and in any place where a passenger can make a reservation, information regarding the rights and responsibilities of both passengers on such aircraft and the air carrier or foreign air carrier, including—</text><subparagraph id="H235BF831533E41EBA5591E39C3A875F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that an air carrier or foreign air carrier is required to equip aircraft that have more than 60 passenger seats and that have an accessible lavatory (whether or not having such a lavatory is required by section 382.63 of such title 14) with an on-board wheelchair unless an exception described in such section 382.65 applies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4507DC9E67BC4BB981F9892FCDB7A9F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that a qualified individual with a disability may request an on-board wheelchair on aircraft with more than 60 passenger seats even if the lavatory is not accessible and that the basis of such request must be that the individual can use an inaccessible lavatory but cannot reach it from a seat without using an on-board wheelchair;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4229F861A22E4C9A9C1A872E77E8E38E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that the air carrier or foreign air carrier may require the qualified individual with a disability to provide the advance notice specified in section 382.27 of such title 14 in order for the individual to be provided with the on-board wheelchair; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H514F04B19EAE4C5DA6C9299D8A19E8A0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>if the air carrier or foreign air carrier requires the advance notice described in subparagraph (C), information on how a qualified individual with a disability can make such a request.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H80CC8BF8C38845A18238A44F82F56BFE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual training</header><text>An air carrier and a foreign air carriers shall require that all personnel who regularly interact with the traveling public, including contractors, complete annual training regarding assisting qualified individual with a disability, including regarding the availability of accessible lavatories and on-board wheelchairs and such individual’s right to request an on-board wheelchair.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C05615B64384B2A92C2DEE24BDFE4AB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public awareness campaign</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a public awareness campaign on the rights of qualified individuals with a disability, including with respect to accessible lavatories and such individual’s right to request an on-board wheelchair in accordance with section 382.65 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4D9FCE52EF142238D7227AE61152098"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified individual with a disability defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>qualified individual with a disability</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6297900CEED477B8F5DE9A3278AFA2C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The Secretary may assess a civil penalty in accordance with section 46301 of title 49, United States Code, to any air carrier or foreign air carrier who fails to meet the requirements under paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75BB7CCE3FC140BDA58B906CB43402AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Increased civil penalties</header><paragraph id="H55B4BE64E8404475882E2FAED2683316"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 46301(a)(7) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HA93D4FF0F82B4F2EB616A60D42708F51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">to harm</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA2E0037F4EC4E9C9E7C4F51370BA26D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HC37316CB00214D8B98A23F6516092942"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Bodily harm or damage to wheelchair or other mobility aid</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Damage to wheelchair or other mobility aid, bodily harm, or failure to equip aircraft with a wheelchair</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H0FF9562923D14D6B8DC5E800C6EFEC7F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or injury to a passenger with a disability</quote> and inserting <quote>, injury to a passenger with a disability, or a failure to equip an aircraft with an on-board wheelchair pursuant to section 382.65 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation)</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC741D44C68AE4500B5AE042C265BA8F2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by paragraph (1) shall apply to flights occurring on or after the effective date of the revision described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

