<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEE6FE10079024C6CB11302B712E236B9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 689 IH: No Support for Terror Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 689</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prevent allocations of Special Drawing Rights at the International Monetary Fund for countries that are perpetrators of genocide or state sponsors of terrorism, and to prevent United States tax dollars from directly going to the Taliban or other terrorists or terrorist-harboring nations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H472A812A2FFB407190FC75F750B7B8A4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3DD2DD3E697D40438808294740498957" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Support for Terror Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC9E68D19030B43079365F62199C37CD5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Preventing allocations of Special Drawing Rights at the International Monetary Fund for countries that are perpetrators of genocide or state sponsors of terrorism</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Bretton Woods Agreements Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/286">22 U.S.C. 286 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBB0FE143253545999F9E98F4EF2B2B64" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="HED9092DE00424CC2BD738952DE710378"><enum>74.</enum><header>Preventing allocations of Special Drawing Rights for countries that are perpetrators of genocide or state sponsors of terrorism</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall instruct the United States Executive Director at the Fund to use the voice and vote of the United States to—</text> <paragraph id="H8F708192A9674ABF813E66615FD9F36A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>oppose the allocation of Special Drawing Rights to any country that is a perpetrator of genocide or a state sponsor of terrorism, as determined by the Secretary of State; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H920AB23C3BAA4063B94BAA0642BFE351"><enum>(2)</enum><text>advocate that the Fund adopt a rule prohibiting such an allocation.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H5059AE10E4544BE48D8916D0FF61A35F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Preventing United States tax dollars from being provided to the Taliban or other terrorist organizations or countries that harbor terrorist organizations</header> <subsection id="H90E7969F774D4A1CAC486064BF08BD0B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header> <paragraph id="H19811A0CFAA74834A6EF7A810D7B8B5C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall jointly conduct a review of assistance provided to nongovernmental organizations and international organizations to ensure such assistance is not being further provided to the Taliban or other terrorist organizations or countries that harbor terrorist organizations in accordance with United States anti-terrorism financing laws.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H320D509913A945E98ADF7FB23CF15AD7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall jointly submit to Congress a report that contains the results of the review conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCB8D568BCE8E40D6B87B3523FE0DC70A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recipient requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall each require prime awardees of assistance to provide evidence that all sub-awardees of such assistance are complying with United States anti-terrorism financing laws.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

