<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8D477054F392460DAEB27BD77C885871" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3262 IH: To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to increase transparency of certain health-related ownership information.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3262</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to increase transparency of certain health-related ownership information.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE286FA25A17241859A4D395499D27CC0" style="OLC"><section id="HBD85A40CF65C4F51AEAE5B28C1E050CB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Mandatory reporting with respect to certain health-related ownership information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title XI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1301">42 U.S.C. 1301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H62FCA8129C204844B06EDA9473507AD0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5774C9B333564A2586B83906C2B6D945"><enum>1150D.</enum><header>Mandatory reporting with respect to certain health-related ownership information</header><subsection id="HCD03D98974F941D1857284D9CC3C0179"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory reporting with respect certain health-Related ownership information</header><paragraph id="H7D8A5D96AE564D9A872DA829CF98CBE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2025 (or in the case of a specified entity formed after January 1, 2025, within 60 days of becoming a specified entity), each specified entity (as defined in subsection (f)(5)) shall submit to the Secretary, in a form and manner specified by the Secretary, a report containing the following information:</text><subparagraph id="H4F405A893B944EF6BED289D3C37281AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data on mergers, acquisitions, and changes in ownership with respect to such specified entity for the previous 1-year period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9857DE3324614B4ABD1FD8DBEA2E7247"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that a specified entity is, or includes, a hospital, the additional information described in subsection (b).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF710667566140DF9E2B9130195998DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As applicable, the name, address, and business structure of the parent company of such specified entity (including the tax status of such parent company), as of the date of the submission of this report.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2914CFF60CE4A0490CC24AC0593C47B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other information with respect to ownership of a specified entity, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA333268E403C46DE9B30F93139BBCDDA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after submitting the report under paragraph (1), and annually thereafter, each specified entity shall submit to the Secretary an updated report, including—</text><subparagraph id="H2E32A88C46DB49A799EC1066C995DA03"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7F60654F227E48098FB397E9F2B0B9AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>data on mergers, acquisitions, and changes in ownership with respect to such entities for the previous 1-year period; and</text></clause><clause id="HFC778D3F6CD149039BBB4C473B0F2113" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other information with respect to ownership of a specified entity, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07EFDFDA5B3647D9B81323DD4AC99F90"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case that a specified entity is, or includes, a hospital, the additional information described in subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H01C904F5D36A40948217C8553B624669"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional information submitted by certain specified entities</header><text>For purposes of paragraphs (1)(B) and (2)(B) of subsection (a), with respect to a specified entity that is, or includes, a hospital, the information described in this subsection is the following information with respect to the previous 1-year period:</text><paragraph id="H1870FE9D7CA9469F830C58A6793071DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The business structure of the specified entity, including the business type and the tax status of such entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09FFAD619FD64D4B9D78089D7229B44B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The average debt-to-earnings ratio of the specified entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA67A3EC5E96D44FBB69B9E6F287D9A5E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The average amount of debt incurred—</text><subparagraph id="H18067A73EAD34A599FA5F2F5B84BE826"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by the hospital; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB182ED9FDC114DF7B110E839B892CF39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by the entire specified entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E130CCCEEA3436FBE0DBA4DEECE9C51"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Information with respect to real estate leases and purchases for property used, or intended to be used, to furnish or otherwise support the provision of health care services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8DC15015BDF4F1B836AA2841BAD1D4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In the case of a non-profit hospital, a subsidiary of a non-profit hospital, or a 501(c)(3) entity that shares common ownership with a non-profit hospital, capital gains investments (disaggregated by the type of investment) and any taxes paid on such gains from such investments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1503A2B3533643E9869E2E61EFCA07D9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>As applicable, information with respect to the parent company of such specified entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8AF9EB03F0744F84991E0FDE328D4F2A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2027, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall post on a publicly available website of the Department of Health and Human Services a report with respect to the previous 1-year period, including—</text><paragraph id="H695D7D29FF8E449D9F7339DB1AC8DD63"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of specified entities reporting for such year, disaggregated by the business structure of each specified entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C5D66BDA328440FA21B91F9B18E427B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of owners of each specified entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC221BCF905674FA79BE0459D018342EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any change in ownership for each specified entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACE9F66F026542CF8B45A38C22AB14F0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any change in the tax status of a specified entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC59361BCCD8E43CF9396149D891D5113"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an analysis of trends in horizontal and vertical consolidation, disaggregated by business structure and provider type; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H080D00557DA644FCA9155114C3E0A154"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, the name, address, and business structure of the parent company of such specified entity (including the business type and the tax status of such parent company).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E09B1B749254B08B54C864F3BADEC30"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Audits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct an annual audit consisting of a random sample of specified entities to verify compliance with the requirements of this section and the accuracy of information submitted pursuant to this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B9E54527FC04463924499DAB9547CC0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Penalty for failure To report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a specified entity fails to provide a complete report under subsection (a), or submits a report containing false information, such entity shall be subject to a civil monetary penalty of not more than $5,000,000 for each such report not provided or containing false information. Such penalty shall be imposed and collected in the same manner as civil money penalties under subsection (a) of section 1128A are imposed and collected under that section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H975AB17E55E8426999B47246997ED9B4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inapplicability of Paperwork Reduction Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/35">Chapter 35</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, shall not apply to collections of information made under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H46DF022BA03F432E84D23A4F4B4321F7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2558FA8EF7A140D2B4A7883D070E4D57" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Health plan</header><text>The term <quote>health plan</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1128C(c). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11796EE5A14643E8870FD289E2BAE5C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Hospital</header><text>The term <quote>hospital</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54A74D286BEC4A4686EE4EC488CE0EEE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Independent freestanding emergency department</header><text>The term <quote>independent freestanding emergency department</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2799A–1(a)(3)(D) of the Public Health Service Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7D6ED8A74E245ABBDE1C9BA44CED2CE" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Private equity company</header><text>The term <quote>private equity company</quote> means a publicly traded or non-publicly traded company that collects capital investments from individuals or entities and purchases an ownership share of a provider of services (as defined in section 1861(u)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H043AFC21129946CC8672904EBE4EBAD5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Specified entity</header><text>The term <quote>specified entity</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H9DF1AD7AD2D845EA8AEC4AA0BCA6BAB1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a hospital;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EE421B85416409394FC01244B611184"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a physician-owned physician practice with more than 25 physicians for a year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C69DF43D1B04052BF46CD12C4A7AED9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a physician practice owned by a hospital, a health plan, a private equity company, or a venture capital firm;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45945BB5B97C48538E2E30F18035A997"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an ambulatory surgical center meeting the standards specified under section 1832(a)(2)(F)(i); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9217197C0BA84EF1AEB00639AC4405FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an independent freestanding emergency department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H167E5F5301F04040936F73F56912E266" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Venture capital fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>venture capital fund</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 275.203(l)–1of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

