<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB7250EFEE57F4121A7AFBDF0EE057C83" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6617 IH: To require a report on payments provided to the Taliban and congressional review of agreements signed with the Taliban.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6617</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report on payments provided to the Taliban and congressional review of agreements signed with the Taliban.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF8E27023A92B4D9C8B38D1BB7E27F4A1" style="OLC"><section id="H978A8266E2FE49F38DC37B0CB6A876BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on payments provided to the Taliban</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the total amounts and types of payments, including payments of fees, taxes, rent, and other similar payments, provided by entities receiving United States-provided funds to the Taliban during the period beginning on August 1, 2021, and ending 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section><section id="H99B32F273EB1488A8BA7F91FC0FFF7A5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Congressional review of agreements signed with the Taliban</header><subsection id="H61495218074641CC845D7337DA0A8BFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the date on which an entity receiving United States-provided funds enters into an agreement with the Taliban, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a copy of the agreement. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0EE3E0ADACE74FAD8BEFA38BEA4738A0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on prior agreements with the Taliban</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes a copy of each agreement entered into between an entity receiving United States-provided funds and the Taliban from August 31, 2021, until such date of enactment. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC32289E0D3294BDE8087455F05DEDAA1" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Agreement defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>agreement</quote> includes memoranda of understanding and other manifestations of mutual assent.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4582092D0F1F4DB5B25C529965A04D74" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text><paragraph id="H1408EDF146B64C9A969533270894B3D0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term ‘‘appropriate congressional committees’’ means—</text><subparagraph id="H1B1F32EC6D014C0E9395E324D232A4FB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34AD3AAD65474764A12F30BA8DBF0FC6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0B7BF8B2BEB4676B18EBD226633DFD7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term ‘‘entity receiving United States-provided funds’’—</text><subparagraph id="H6CD0BAD396934E5DABCA92B68A7B355D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any agency, fund, program, or organization that—</text><clause id="H285E572F9B0B461CB88F831625F1966A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>carries out humanitarian or developmental assistance operations or other charitable activities in Afghanistan; and </text></clause><clause id="H1362BF9319F84D9DA46B369727E491F3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>receives funding from the United States Government; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF766E8F19564E78A87B945FD22C7C57" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any organization or other entity of the United Nations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

