<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0BD54AFD5BBB49CBBFE1666780191361" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4496 IH: American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter List Maintenance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4496</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to establish certain requirements for voter registration with respect to District of Columbia elections, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE4D6E09205354C10A1E32788D859C1E4" style="OLC"><section id="H0F98AC6458F34B8CBC5DDCC0A60258E4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter List Maintenance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7BF46116C75F4D8984A1370079A3D8A9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements for voter registration with respect to District of Columbia elections</header><subsection id="HEC0A4A1CD1BC4BDA83BA17071DF7C77D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H49683DBF0C074F7E9B2FFD7EF8C00441"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H344F2562B36C485187BD143F9A6CB534"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H14D20782C83A44ADBB58E0C5038B36BC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H7D2A9DAFC15340DAB82E487C1294E087"><enum>304.</enum><header>Requirements for voter registration in District of Columbia elections</header><subsection id="HC05DBD3EAA96425982152368F039682E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual list maintenance</header><paragraph id="H6D780E190BA548338CAAB1940DC04399"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><subparagraph id="HFFE2FA7EE6FB47F99AA5F958ABFDCDA2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The District of Columbia shall carry out annually a program to remove ineligible persons from the official list of persons registered to vote in the District of Columbia, as required by section 8 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507</external-xref>) and pursuant to the procedures described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7683112ADC1496FB08C5B1F319E15BD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Removal from voter rolls</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a registrant from the official list of eligible voters in District of Columbia elections who has failed to vote in a District of Columbia election during a period of two consecutive years, the District of Columbia shall send to such registrant a notice described in section 8(d)(2) of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20507">52 U.S.C. 20507(d)(2)</external-xref>) and shall remove the registrant from the official list of eligible voters in District of Columbia elections if—</text><clause id="HBEB75C1F5A5D469284938C76F20108F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the registrant fails to respond to such notice; and</text></clause><clause id="H6A8F940F79DE4F409B398F24B3CDBDF8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the registrant has not voted or appeared to vote in a District of Columbia election during the period beginning the date such notice is sent and ending the later of 4 years after the date such notice is sent or after two consecutive District of Columbia general elections have been held. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A6518FB5BA64EC1B8BB2E64FFAC15E3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>In the case of a year during which a regularly scheduled District of Columbia election is held, the District of Columbia shall carry out the program described in paragraph (1) not later than 90 days prior to the date of the election.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8346B2BA12B44A22BF217DBECFA21BBE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibiting same-Day registration</header><text>The District of Columbia may not permit an individual to vote in a District of Columbia election unless, not later than 30 days prior to the date of the election, the individual is duly registered to vote in the election.</text></subsection><subsection id="H892AF79DC65F4C7685A4C1DA5BC21C85"><enum>(c)</enum><header>District of Columbia election defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D746B663BFD4FEC95811EAB1F713BE2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1DD0039AFDB24A7199706C8BC7255D20"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="H04E8A81AFF004B44B8163D8E493A7BB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC911BE0296543759B715D431A3709BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H114C12BC8507455EAE352CA79AA5EA04" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Requirements for voter registration in District of Columbia elections.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

