<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H455D7FCAB7294559BCC6E8BA06B8D405" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6329 IH: Open Source Intelligence Availability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6329</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase the availability of open-source intelligence products in the Federal Government, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFE2147C18AA04966AA15812F95981884" style="OLC"><section id="H6B043250C3C146529CCEEE3E4DA29349" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Open Source Intelligence Availability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1282F75C20794B03A06B542CACDE02B7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Development of plan to make open-source intelligence products available to certain Federal employees</header><subsection id="HD38EB750E2EE4ABEACB30B39CE482281"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with such heads of the elements of the intelligence community as the Director considers appropriate, shall develop and submit to the congressional intelligence committees a plan to make available to covered individuals any covered open-source intelligence product.</text></subsection><subsection id="H06F1EE7F9C8745A689E1CD154D9AD05D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The plan required under <internal-xref idref="HD38EB750E2EE4ABEACB30B39CE482281" legis-path="__(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HB67A173B6C804452B36ECB0E5432B174"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Policies and procedures to make available to covered individuals any covered open-source intelligence product in a manner consistent with the protection of intelligence sources and methods. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H093EE03F09D04ED8B3F38929C9F86A16"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Policies and procedures to increase the availability and accessibility to covered individuals of publicly available foreign language material that is translated by or within the intelligence community. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H737E879C7C4044A78E94A6E01D9760A5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Policies and procedures to ensure that the head of each element of the intelligence community that produces any covered open-source intelligence product complies with all policies and procedures issued to implement the plan submitted under <internal-xref idref="HD38EB750E2EE4ABEACB30B39CE482281" legis-path="__(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6998B7A266F349D990E8541AD29548B1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Policies and procedures to ensure that any covered open-source intelligence product that is made available to covered individuals satisfies the requirements under any policy, procedure, or standard issued by the head of an element of the intelligence community relating to the production and dissemination of intelligence products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AA167CE12BA42F88BA7E08888B0F9D8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any obstacles to making available to covered individuals unclassified products derived from open-source intelligence produced by the intelligence community, including translated foreign language material described in <internal-xref idref="H093EE03F09D04ED8B3F38929C9F86A16" legis-path="__(b)(2)">paragraph (2)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5D0CFEB426144D5B2D7670A6EE2388D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>With respect to implementation of the plan, a discussion of the estimated timeline, any additional funding or other resources, and any new authorities that would be required for such implementation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FD479A5E9E045BA81FA25744A31297A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion of the feasibility and advisability of making unclassified products derived from open-source intelligence produced by the intelligence community available to State and local government officials who would derive value from such unclassified products.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D4BE6F75F4A4686886F7E03B24930A4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan required under <internal-xref idref="HD38EB750E2EE4ABEACB30B39CE482281" legis-path="__(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF9CDDC058284136AD1B9F4FB3DD74A5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Intelligence community directive with respect to open-Source intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence shall update Intelligence Community Directive 208, Maximizing the Utility of Analytic Products (or any successor directive) to specifically address—</text><paragraph id="H2C40AAD2C42544878621EE79FA59AE15"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the production and dissemination of unclassified intelligence products derived entirely from open-source intelligence, including from unclassified publicly available information, unclassified commercially available information, or any other type of unclassified information; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H952922A851644CA1B0D132653E3BA807"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the needs and requirements of covered individuals who do not hold a security clearance or have access to the classified systems on which such unclassified intelligence products reside.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52811772CD984EBCBC9281FC643FFF5F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC826D78FF2AA4F44B430D67AC396ABD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered individual</term> means an employee of the Federal Government—</text><subparagraph id="HAA4DA61A67DA4F97BB8902E90CC84D9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is not an employee or contractor of an element of the intelligence community; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCACD510080124EB9B5D887C133511AB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who would derive value from a covered open-source intelligence product.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8297FC4CB7984D7F82BD1DCF0D472095"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered open-source intelligence product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered open-source intelligence product</term> means an unclassified product derived from open-source intelligence that is produced by the intelligence community. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

