<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="HAD0CCD144E904B6B905E57A5D3F4B019"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4443 IH: Countering China’s Exploitation of Strategic Metals and Minerals and Child and Forced Labor in the Democratic Republic of the Congo Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4443</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that certain goods made with child labor or forced labor in the Democratic Republic of the Congo do not enter the United States market, to counter control of strategic metals and minerals by the People’s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA78B270F04414E3C9AFA4C51486BAE9F"><section id="HD71E69BE3A0D4823AD62F3E8F1CC9627" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Countering China’s Exploitation of Strategic Metals and Minerals and Child and Forced Labor in the Democratic Republic of the Congo Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF3AE8739F30347DCB368FBB690AAC310"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HED37DAEFB8514D1AB0582FDA1E538C21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Cobalt is an essential component of lithium-ion batteries, which are predominantly used for electric vehicles, smartphones, and laptops, among other electronic devices. According to the International Energy Agency, the world is expected to see a 40-fold increase in lithium demand and a 20-fold increase in cobalt demand by 2040, as the demand for electric vehicles is expected to grow significantly during this period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7031A6B4A9BC40B2BC46F1B9D6DD5CB7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 2021, global sales of electric vehicles doubled compared to 2020, reaching its new record of 6.6 million, and bringing the total number of electric vehicles in use to 16.5 million electric vehicles by the end of 2021. The People’s Republic of China (<quote>PRC</quote>) accounted for half of those sales, with over 150 percent growth in electric vehicle sales in that country compared to 2020. In the first quarter of 2022, an additional 2 million electric vehicles were sold worldwide, showing strong continued growth. While Europe and the United States saw increased sales, the PRC experienced an unprecedented tripling of electric vehicle sales of 3.3 million in 2022, accounting for approximately one-half of the global sales.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37FBD18AF8114FCB83D61BDA7230EF12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The concentration of global cobalt supply and production in the Democratic Republic of the Congo (<quote>DRC</quote>) as well as civil unrest and governmental corruption, heighten the vulnerabilities and risks of global supply chain disruptions. More than one-half of the world’s cobalt resources are in the DRC, which supplies approximately 70 percent of the global cobalt mine production in 2021. The DRC remains beset by conflicts and pervasive official corruption. Firms based in the PRC hold a dominant position in DRC’s cobalt sector, according to the White House. On the foundation of an unstable state, more than one-half of lithium and cobalt global supplies are processed and refined in the PRC, where more than 75 percent of all lithium-ion batteries are produced. About 50 percent of all batteries are for consumption in the PRC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D476D6A47740559B850A6CC357DC5C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Lithium deposits have been identified in the DRC, with exploration ongoing. It is estimated that the DRC can begin lithium production as early as 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE654729FC36A460FA3B9A525A2063BEF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Approximately 15 to 30 percent of cobalt produced in the DRC comes from artisanal and small-scale mining. An estimated 255,000 miners work in artisanal and small-scale mining in the DRC, of whom at least 40,000 are children.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H764E8208A56D4E84AA6982C0E8172B53"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The child miners in the DRC, some as young as 6 years of age, working in artisanal and small-scale mines, are subjected to the worst forms of forced manual labor. They work in harsh and life-threatening conditions, and are vulnerable to physical injuries, coercion, and abuse in addition to exposure to harmful toxins.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB94996EC808B4723BD9D7F514D602BAD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Amnesty International reported in 2016 that child miners in the DRC’s cobalt sector worked for up to 12 hours a day in the mines without the most basic protective gear, such as gloves and face masks which would protect them from lung and skin disease. Many children reportedly worked for prolonged periods underground, including at sites with inadequate ventilation and a high risk of fatal mineshaft collapse. Child miners interviewed by Amnesty International reported working for up to 12 hours a day in the mines, carrying heavy loads and being paid less than two dollars per day.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFAE1D50751646B3AA4DBD3C6EDE7C47"><enum>(8)</enum><text>According to a tally by Amnesty International, based on news reports, at least 80 underground miners working in artisanal and small-scale mining died in southeastern DRC between September 2014 and December 2015. Amnesty International assessed that the <quote>true figure is unknown as many accidents go unrecorded and bodies are left buried in the rubble</quote>. To this day, there is no official tally of the total number of such deaths.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC094FB91B88640E7B4D0E4D2EC1111C3"><enum>(9)</enum><text>As of 2020, 15 of the 19 cobalt mines in the DRC were owned or financed by PRC companies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CE4A67095614043B006743C7668DF0E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The 5 biggest PRC-owned mining companies in the DRC have lines of credit from PRC state-owned banks totaling $124 billion.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53BAC67CCE754EDF9BAC59A6691FB959"><enum>(11)</enum><text>China Molybdenum, a PRC mining and trading company, is the second-largest producer of cobalt worldwide. In 2016, it purchased Tenke Fungurume, which controlled one of the largest cobalt reserves in the world. More than $1.59 billion of the $2.65 billion came from loans from PRC state-owned banks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9445F4DF6F1F4B91926D72FE28F50E65"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Under PRC ownership of mining companies in the DRC, there has been reportedly a significant rise in serious injuries. There are questions regarding proper oversight of safety in the mines, as well as coverups of deaths and injuries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6A6C26739534A4EAB28A948A20D605B"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In July 2021, PRC mining company managers in Kolwezi ordered the brutal beating and whipping of miners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B70D4CDB210458D94C5FD6FE0CCCE69"><enum>(14)</enum><text>On July 14, 2022, the Tom Lantos Human Rights Commission, a bipartisan congressional commission, held a hearing on <quote>Child Labor and Human Rights Violations in the Mining Industry of the Democratic Republic of Congo</quote>. The hearing highlighted the concerns of child and forced labor in the DRC, the disregard of worker safety, and environmental degradation. It also highlighted PRC domination of strategic metals and minerals in the global supply chain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29FD9D2191874D3FB8806F940EAB4375"><enum>(15)</enum><text>In the 2022 Trafficking in Persons Report, the Department of State emphasized that <quote>In the <inline-comment>DRC,</inline-comment> artisanal and small-scale mining of cobalt has been associated with forced child labor and other abuses</quote>, noting further that <quote>Since 2015, the TIP Report narratives on the DRC have highlighted forced labor of children in artisanal cobalt mines.</quote>. The DRC is on the Tier 2 Watch List, and will be automatically downgraded to Tier 3, subjecting it to sanctions, if it does not substantively and consistently improve its record on trafficking.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37DC80B36BD548D586DD589630B8F116"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>) states that it is illegal to import into the United States <quote>goods, wares, articles, and merchandise mined, produced, or manufactured wholly or in part</quote> by forced labor, including forced or indentured child labor. Such merchandise is subject to exclusion or seizure and may lead to criminal investigation of the importer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H705437BBA95E4D6BAA92F84C57D88E7B"><enum>(17)</enum><text>On December 13, 2022, the Governments of the United States, DRC, and Zambia signed a memorandum of understanding with regard to United States support for the DRC and Zambia to develop jointly a supply chain for electric vehicle batteries, <quote>from the mine to the assembly line, while also committing to respect international standards to prevent, detect and take legal action to fight corruption throughout this process</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDDC6175875EF4E0494E005F7C36935D8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H6C40C413890647B492490A53C58942FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to prohibit the importation of covered DRC goods;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2361C96E1C204687ACA69F72EC56527F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to encourage the international community to prohibit the importation of covered DRC goods;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E0E28CC343D4E75BF1EF5DB04140038"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to enforce labor provisions under Chapter 23 of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement (USMCA) and coordinate with Mexico and Canada to effectively implement Article 23.6 of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement to prohibit the importation of covered DRC goods into the North American market;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21CE52D3C9E4479CB8A9F889225B0EDB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to mitigate and prevent gross violations of human rights in the DRC by—</text><subparagraph id="H3FA9388BA9E340DBB4DD80F6C0A0EA28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>utilizing bilateral diplomatic channels and multinational institutions where both the United States and the DRC are members; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BB2D4966AAD4E578D5143FF13D9F619"><enum>(B)</enum><text>using other applicable authorities available to the United States Government, including with regard to development assistance; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H58C531D9BE3B4675B39176230BE3AF92"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to combat PRC control of strategic metals and minerals in the global supply chain.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H3188A38759EE452BB75CFE19C4C04C21"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rebuttable presumption that import prohibition applies to covered DRC goods</header><subsection id="H89A0EF985C7B43AEB9563FA2FBEC6003"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), covered DRC goods shall be deemed to be goods, wares, articles, and merchandise described in section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>) and shall not be entitled to entry at any of the ports of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H733F4A75151345A080E68010A2EF34D5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The prohibition described in subsection (a) shall not apply if the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection—</text><paragraph id="H6EB8CB461480440485920DF775732133"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determines, based on clear and convincing evidence, including information produced by due diligence reviews by importers of their supply chains, that the covered DRC goods were not mined, produced or manufactured wholly or in part by child labor or forced labor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA742DAAB6E4A4FFDA53995293DB13D6E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submits to the appropriate congressional committees and makes available to the public a report that contains such determination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52C1D4051F6B43359685EF509C24A440"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect on the date that is 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3DE086178B41426899147C7F9E900DEE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Enforcement strategy to address child labor and forced labor in the DRC</header><subsection id="HA9D9C77530DD48E9B92F2741B47A4668"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Forced Labor Enforcement Task Force, established under section 741 of the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement Implementation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/4681">19 U.S.C. 4681</external-xref>), shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text><paragraph id="HE88C1ABA5AB9455AA84B2C4857E2FB84"><enum>(1)</enum><text>contains an enforcement strategy to effectively address child labor and forced labor in the mining, production, smelting, or processing of metals or minerals, in particular cobalt and lithium and their derivatives, in the DRC;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4176EC91CAD54002ACD3AE3D170764BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describes the specific strategy of the United States Government for enforcing section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>) to prevent the importation into the United States of covered DRC goods;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF43B782CFF684FBE98E100880AB7BF0F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>describes the perpetration of child labor and forced labor by mining companies in the DRC owned or controlled by PRC entities or financed by PRC state-owned banks or institutions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC415908AC4F4288B881411CDC11D771"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommends development and promotion of alternative sources of supply and production, including within the DRC and the United States domestically.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAFFF16D71FE1420AB67F7ECDE4EF418A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The strategy required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HE4343F29B8DB472EAF564E91DF3E8A37"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the actions taken by the United States Government, including what monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E) standards were utilized, to address child labor and forced labor in the DRC under section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>), including a description of all Withhold Release Orders issued, covered DRC goods detained, and fines issued.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7029C1451274212A1606678696542D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of—</text><subparagraph id="HDD458E9705AC4172AFC4F4C085F8E316"><enum>(A)</enum><text>covered DRC goods; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50F3C89571B24CF4A08E7A3374062199"><enum>(B)</enum><text>businesses that have sold covered DRC goods in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7140CD42764E49F9A4EBB09CA85A7B57"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A list of United States-based facilities and entities that source metals and minerals, in particular cobalt and lithium and their derivatives, from the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining sectors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD42CDA1C1624BFAB94EA209B7D84997"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A list of mining companies, including China Molybdenum, in the DRC owned or controlled by PRC entities, or financed by PRC state-owned banks or institutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1C605BFBB24265AFAFC8279E548DC7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A list of high-priority sectors for enforcement, which shall include electric vehicles production, with a sector-specific enforcement plan for each high-priority sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EC76AE6646D46E9845D9BA53A4F2487"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A description of the additional resources necessary for U.S. Customs and Border Protection and other Federal entities, including the Forced Labor Enforcement Task Force, to effectively implement the strategy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A5B249D1C8A4731BB97FDE23991482E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A strategy to coordinate and collaborate with appropriate nongovernmental organizations and private sector entities to implement the enforcement strategy for covered DRC goods.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H939A25FD561745A0AFD90D2300424404"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex, if necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEA61B0920B9D415796A7DE376284AF56"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>After the submission of the strategy required by subsection (a), the Forced Labor Enforcement Task Force shall provide briefings to the appropriate congressional committees on a quarterly basis and, as applicable, on any updates to the strategy required by subsection (a) or additional actions taken to address child labor or forced labor in the DRC, including actions described in this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H00E9325BDE0F4B3C88E305487DEE7147"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall cease to have effect on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="HD334004472624195B66930F1C30A3496"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 8 years after the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC96EF025E4FA4D52B8D0E20945AA2741"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the President submits to the appropriate congressional committees a determination that the DRC has ended child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4B31D9EDC12547068A1B9CB8BE51D077"><enum>6.</enum><header>Diplomatic strategy to address child labor and forced labor in the DRC</header><subsection id="H38CBC4D23AD34283BDB516FEE1CD2D6A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the heads of other appropriate Federal departments and agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that contains a United States strategy to promote initiatives to enhance international awareness of and to prevent and mitigate child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining.</text></subsection><subsection id="H168575A5CBB244CB8DFB184D935B90AA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H5F58FED5EFEF4FD6BD09091D6600D85D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan to enhance bilateral and multilateral coordination, including sustained engagement with the governments of United States allies and partners, to end child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H127B36EDA7FD40D3AC1B36901DFC6DE0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a strategic plan to enhance bilateral and multinational coordination, including sustained engagement with the governments of United States allies and partners, to counter child labor and forced labor by mining companies in the DRC owned or controlled by PRC entities, including China Molybdenum, or financed by PRC state-owned banks or institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA767FD69D8CB4806B7E4AA6301A5D500"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a plan based on proven strategies with monitoring and evaluation standards applied for public affairs, public diplomacy, and messaging efforts to promote awareness of child labor and forced labor in the DRC, with a special attention to the role of the mining companies owned or controlled by PRC entities, or financed by PRC state-owned banks or institutions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H854A2322E76A4901BD4BC7ADC90F8077"><enum>(4)</enum><text>opportunities to coordinate and collaborate with appropriate nongovernmental organizations, including, in particular, faith-based entities and private sector entities, to raise awareness about covered DRC goods.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4E2008F2F0B8404A8B01CCBF418E8435"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional matters To be included</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall also include—</text><paragraph id="HF8CB24E4F58A4B30B1D9A3BAF64147B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, a list of—</text><subparagraph id="HDFB98FAB3F7F4ED0920A099CE2E39D4F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>entities that directly or indirectly use child labor or forced labor in the production of covered DRC goods; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5624C0360EEF45F49AA422AFD78ED01A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>foreign persons that act as agents of the entities or affiliates of entities described in subparagraph (A) to import covered DRC goods into the United States; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7631DEA0B104FB894E99EE74976F438"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of actions taken by the United States Government to address child labor or forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining, including under—</text><subparagraph id="H7824C45048AA441697EC45E85BC49170"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/386">Public Law 106–386</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7101">22 U.S.C. 7101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C534846F88D4D2BAD490ED52399E0EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Elie Wiesel Genocide and Atrocities Prevention Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/441">Public Law 115–441</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09A7EE6FB87D42AAB52AE89C1E7CB9AC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D348DC1C42B475198F0166B30A20744"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex, if necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D4B0A0541524616ADA4CEA27E64D633"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary of State shall include any updates to the strategy required by subsection (a) in the annual Trafficking in Persons report required by section 110(b) of the Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7107">22 U.S.C. 7107(b)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H834C55C6EE8D475AA95038D51C7D4D82"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall cease to have effect the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H67E2BC81BC954B51AA64C2422BA3012C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 8 years after the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBED31DAE0BCB4DF187724C2890EC258E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the President submits to the appropriate congressional committees a determination that the Government of the DRC has ended child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1E49C386A9884D71B20D7A37679A9DA8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Impositions of sanctions relating to child labor and forced labor in the DRC</header><subsection id="H754AB36DD693487EBC90F8B5CA7E2CD9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><paragraph id="H9C9B18E53A4D4703BEFB5ED46DC2D6A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that identifies each foreign person, including any official of the Government of the DRC, that the President determines—</text><subparagraph id="H6595199BFB3B43E5AD4587B247CA862B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>knowingly engages in, is responsible for, or facilitates the child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F3FE4FD63DC4C3690E6F7A5A5FC5430"><enum>(B)</enum><text>knowingly engages in, contributes to, assists, or provides financial, material, or technological support for efforts to contravene United States law regarding the importation of covered DRC goods.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBA3D649B884410D88FB04F95BB5086D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H523688D21F6D4D5B8EBE2B29D0971C06"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><text>The President shall impose the sanctions described in subsection (c) with respect to each foreign person identified in the report required under subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6410C45189C44C56909FA58E317E55A3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H090C2633BDBC404E9B4D91BC8293BA6D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Asset blocking</header><text>The President shall exercise all of the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of a foreign person identified in the report required under subsection (a)(1) if such property and interests in property—</text><subparagraph id="H664EA3246DE94FFEA159AAEF1D1CF9C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01335B22C0EB4134B1BFDC50334A928E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>come within the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CF914AC94104AF39E5EF93EE6A2011E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6DBFDDDEE434C289638589AFA5DF0B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header><subparagraph id="H799E82F4005A4F08A9C03D14638DE516"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Visas, admission, or parole</header><text>An alien described in subsection (a)(1) is—</text><clause id="H51C4D0A6BEFD469D836E73D392DB91E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H85555ADDA7974C1DB06B5E6907AA0655"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="HC28A589B3C9D4DE398FA9FCAA134BE9B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE86791AE2CF4FECA7E8B479969B9948"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><clause id="H3B93EAE5B26240FA8D6EC779A8F258B7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An alien described in subsection (a)(1) is subject to revocation of any visa or other entry documentation regardless of when the visa or other entry documentation is or was issued.</text></clause><clause id="HBBF1D86C8DF240E1851D83EC40F83C4B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Immediate effect</header><text>A revocation under clause (i) shall—</text><subclause id="H6CE1EC6D00C34291B1D77F15E6F46142"><enum>(I)</enum><text>take effect immediately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H53B1F5695AA44557A0465428AE3E8498"><enum>(II)</enum><text>automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the alien’s possession.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF38E3BB464B439BB79E8CA1F04BA966"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header><paragraph id="HA9216C9E098D4263859C21271F534C76"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34930088E11442AAABE87F4E0357B23D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to a foreign person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of paragraph (1) to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of such section 206.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD778104CAC5453597650DA8070F419A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The President may waive the application of sanctions under subsection (b) with respect to a foreign person if the President determines and certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that such a waiver is in the national interest of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H717444A21EE549ED952D3F2EFECE11A8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="H7137500DA4FE48B3BD07F43F16F38D90"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exceptions for intelligence activities</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any authorized intelligence activities of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H763CDDDD77E8496C9603A73365EC2ED9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception to comply with international obligations and for law enforcement activities</header><text>Sanctions under subsection (c)(2) shall not apply with respect to an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary—</text><subparagraph id="H8CF0439A8E534450A311E3504AB5DE95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success on June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B84046870DA4FC59965F48F2A927B8C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to carry out or assist law enforcement activity in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H16F98DE6CB124F26A425137F92CB7437"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination of sanctions</header><text>The President may terminate the application of sanctions under this section with respect to a foreign person if the President determines and certifies to the appropriate congressional committees not less than 15 days before the termination takes effect that—</text><paragraph id="H470F3A270BEF44EA8C518D34139827BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>information exists that the person did not engage in the activity for which sanctions were imposed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE2D658A54C04F458A8A74882CBCC3B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the person has been prosecuted appropriately for the activity for which sanctions were imposed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA5478711D884ED9A8BDF83ABA6FC212"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the person has credibly demonstrated a significant change in behavior, has paid appropriate recompense for the activity for which sanctions were imposed, and has credibly committed to not engage in an activity described in subsection (a)(1) in the future; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B9C4BCD20794849AEEC39C677FB299F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the termination of the sanctions is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74248CF28573491CADDEDC8A7CBB4C45"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section, and any sanctions imposed under this section, shall terminate on the date that is 8 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA6737F37DA554A128D419DE61142D80A"><enum>8.</enum><header>Usaid efforts to prevent child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC</header><subsection id="HC880FF86BBF24AE68DB8ADAF5C42BF46"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development (<quote>USAID</quote>), in coordination with the Secretary of the Department of State and the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall increase efforts to prevent child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining, including by encouraging efforts—</text><paragraph id="H5D14956675A741ABB3104716E62CD1D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to expand citizens’ participation in local decision making;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE48ED84CF004410938F227E33EEF675"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to enhance transparency and accountability of governmental decisions on the local, provincial, and national levels in the DRC, on the expenditure of public funds, and the entry into contracts and other agreements in the mining industry of the DRC, in particular contracts or other agreements entered into with PRC entities, including China Molybdenum, or PRC state-owned banks or financial institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4618D369228A4CA9B9A052AC6B19836A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to strengthen social infrastructure to enhance oversight of the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C4D9F45EFE742AB8C9C25CBBC686606"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to provide basic protective equipment, including gloves, work-appropriate clothes, and masks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5B95F38CE4142A68D89ABFA6BCB791F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to develop the technical and business capacity of artisanal and small-scale miners, helping them comply with environmental, safety, and business regulations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H417FAC2DBDD74C1198716122EFCA9663"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to build entrepreneurial capacity in local communities in order to provide economically feasible alternatives to artisanal and small-scale mining; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8B7D66BF5E44C5BA39B363D48EFD08A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to support the ongoing development of country-specific policies and implementation of the national strategy to combat trafficking in persons in the DRC, especially to prevent child labor and forced labor in the DRC.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H93438BC20BC84B258816647E7D3C82A7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The USAID Administrator, in coordination with the Secretary of State and heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall coordinate with bilateral and multilateral donors; the International Monetary Fund; the government of the DRC at national, provincial, and local levels; United Nations agencies; civil society and nongovernmental organizations, including faith-based organizations; and the private sector to combat trafficking in persons in the DRC, including by—</text><paragraph id="HD64A41C2CC40440B805340416814885E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>supporting efforts by local and civil society organizations, including faith-based organizations, and the government of the DRC at national, provincial, and local levels to ensure the end of child labor and forced labor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62B5A6CFE9854972BBB1E81EFA2E7E14"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promoting transparency and accountability of national, provincial, or local level government decisions in the DRC with respect to public funds and contracts and other agreements related to the mining industry of the DRC, in particular contracts or other agreements entered into with PRC entities, including China Molybdenum, or PRC state-owned banks or financial institutions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03353342451E4902B8FFB7E2E89BC164"><enum>(3)</enum><text>undertaking efforts set forth in section 10(a) above.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0AD55663EC9843378DDF22C080277C0C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Intra-Agency efforts</header><text>In carrying out the activities described in this section, the USAID Administrator, in coordination with the Secretary of State and heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall seek to leverage additional private sector resources to end child labor and forced labor in the mining industry of the DRC, including artisanal and small-scale mining, by increasing cooperation between USAID and such other relevant Federal departments and agencies to better leverage the full spectrum of grants, technical assistance, and partnerships.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB3AFAEDB60CA44E690DF65E94A660B10"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD1673C7834DE4DA59C274229CFFED980"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2C416615BDA441E1903C1D591F54EDE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Financial Services, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H154C0754EB7B4DCDB6B449FA2F148BE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and the Committee on Finance of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F9DB817B4A541B9AA0FEB3A2C035A33"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artisanal and small-scale mining</header><text>The term <quote>artisanal and small-scale mining</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HEF294A18025647E0AC0846896257CFB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means mining with minimal to no mechanization; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26860BFD053E4634839F1A9FB4CCF910"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes the use of intensive hand tools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE608779635CF4F218DD03D2E511EC365"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Child labor</header><text>The term <quote>child labor</quote> means work that deprives children of their childhood, their potential, and their dignity, and that is harmful to physical and mental development, as such term is commonly used by the International Labour Organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E5F3E1D86FE4C7DB767D495AC6AABBF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered drc goods</header><text>The term <quote>covered DRC goods</quote> means goods, wares, articles, or merchandise containing metals or minerals, in particular cobalt and lithium and their derivatives, mined, produced, smelted or processed, wholly or in part, by child labor or forced labor in the DRC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF46A82D25F64255B13EA9E299930CFB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>DRC</header><text>The term <quote>DRC</quote> means the Democratic Republic of the Congo.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD268F85FB43B49F9B8578A7B7360BC27"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Forced labor</header><text>The term <quote>forced labor</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 307 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1307">19 U.S.C. 1307</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B4533E4B49D426484803F66AAC6F5AB"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term <quote>foreign person</quote> means a person that is not a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8C7D024066D4A3891B45498E1DACC75"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <quote>person</quote> means an individual or entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77F30CBE116643A79CFE7C95878D09B6"><enum>(9)</enum><header>PRC</header><text>The term <quote>PRC</quote> means the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C798884EE044DDEA4165DFF28A8DA5B"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Strategic metals and minerals</header><text>The term <quote>strategic metals and minerals</quote> means metals and minerals that—</text><subparagraph id="H8267C7E1D1694426AC8888FD04F48BB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are essential to national defense and national security,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9261103CD2F849769FA93FF04A96F9A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are used in weapons systems, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EB0F467F0924E42BC7B49B30E09C00A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>are the building blocks for modern technologies that are critical to economic prosperity for which the United States is dependent on imports from foreign countries,</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">the supply of which is susceptible to control by foreign powers such as the PRC or the Russian Federation whose interests are inimical to those of the United States.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57481E924DC642C8859B02C211F39BF0"><enum>(11)</enum><header>United states person</header><text>The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2E1E4EEF05A24F7E96C65C65F72F755C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F4B3C3597E04318A81CD486F3FF5699"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

