<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1DD32943C0E641BBAD3502944EB40705" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6311 IH: National Coordination on Adaptation and Resilience for Security Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6311</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Government to produce a national adaptation and resilience strategy, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H03B97CE405204B86BACF8EE9A4253211" style="OLC">
<section id="H63F0B1BC816F49FEBA9DA5EEA1A5A4BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Coordination on Adaptation and Resilience for Security Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H51A3ABD0554D4D92BCDB2CE6D239B840"><enum>2.</enum><header>National adaptation and resilience strategy</header> <subsection id="HDCFFFB8CDC0A424AB9D039F6292B571E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HC9356E8CF2624C22BEB594DEA5A871EA" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adaptation</header><text>The term <term>adaptation</term> means an adjustment in a natural or human system in response to a new or changing environmental condition, including such an adjustment associated with climate change, that exploits beneficial opportunities or moderates negative effects.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFA52C11573F49719DAC2A3BFA3BB156" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Climate change</header><text>The term <term>climate change</term> means changes in average atmospheric and oceanic conditions that persist over multiple decades or longer and are natural or anthropogenic in origin, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9282E2370A21403097C823A7EBAA85B0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increases and decreases in temperature;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA51AB67F41A44447A2F8C207FBF89EB9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shifts in precipitation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H44A522A911B6461481FD84094D682A71" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shifts in ecoregion or biome geography and phenology, as applicable;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE54D4EFBD7A346E6B4BB2B67CE5BA7EF" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>changing risk from certain types of rapid-onset climate hazards and slow-onset climate hazards; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4CD620DA5CE5478884F1C50002C331CC" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(E)</enum><text>changes to other features of the climate system. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1B8B6C43FF264152AF7D540B52C25DB4" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Council</header><text>The term <term>Council</term> means the Partners Council on Adaptation and Resilience established under subsection (c)(1). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H39E8A280CCF645AB8B261162397B4A26" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Executive agency</term> in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C4CEFB576014FC99E173436F06EFC78" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Freely associated state</header><text>The term <term>Freely Associated State</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5EEC59A3688541E7830671CA3AB04D88" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federated States of Micronesia;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDEAF8D1120054D0F8F310310DF9BFC00" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Republic of the Marshall Islands; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5E8D76A1363743A08839E6148D925013" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Republic of Palau.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCE58BEDAB4864D85B19AFC6763DFEC7C" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><text>The term <term>Implementation Plan</term> means the Implementation Plan jointly developed by the Chief Resilience Officer and the working groups under subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F4E563DCDAA41B5B40E0475B7A23A1B" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4BD8037980A4449B5C0F660A67728AF" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>National climate assessment</header><text>The term <term>National Climate Assessment</term> means the assessment delivered to Congress and the President pursuant to section 106 of the Global Change Research Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2936">15 U.S.C. 2936</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE50BF5C995EA445293F8DDE9766982E2" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Represented agency</header><text>The term <term>represented agency</term> means each Federal agency from which the Chief Resilience Officer appoints a member to a working group.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD14DABAB938A4A64BDB890193DEADBF1" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Resilience</header><text>The term <term>resilience</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>climate resilience</quote> in section 101 of title 10, United States Code. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2CBC8A480F5342E8A948BED5186C1896" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Slow-onset climate hazard</header>
<subparagraph id="HC001322FA88346AE925283EFF5518DFC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>slow-onset climate hazard</term> means an environmental hazard driven or exacerbated by climate change that evolves gradually through time due to incremental change or because of an increasing frequency or intensity of recurring climate impacts.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DF18E5A327C4337847533F1509C142A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The term <term>slow-onset climate hazard</term> includes—</text>
<clause id="HEC58A69E35584F96B3632FCA230B7D95" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sea level rise;</text></clause> <clause id="H27BBC47E7BFA4F51856BB5EF223E69A2" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>desertification;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD41D72DA67354E168890192981F26FCE" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>biodiversity loss or the alteration of or shift in habitat range of individual species or entire biomes;</text></clause> <clause id="H7990A7FC2E254A4693958E8E2BAA90CB" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>increasing temperatures;</text></clause>
<clause id="HDB378BD5EB9A4B54BE9097AB77E8189E" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>ocean acidification;</text></clause> <clause id="H8A8C4006406A439AACA7AFC29C5F1500" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>saltwater intrusion;</text></clause>
<clause id="H8F2E755C33F44D97A2E9614E82F8B0B0" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>soil salinization;</text></clause> <clause id="H90C2C78262C9441D8C48C2951E01B460" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>drought and water scarcity;</text></clause>
<clause id="H37931D30A1D0479F96765C85AF0014E4" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>reduced snow pack;</text></clause> <clause id="H59577B014E84417880E82D52CA793DFB" commented="no"><enum>(x)</enum><text>sea ice retreat;</text></clause>
<clause id="H7B5F9CDC5E8344D6A31E29D19E8C28ED" commented="no"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>glacial ice retreat;</text></clause> <clause id="H7035E29423EC4B35A672CAA8C5797B92" commented="no"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>permafrost thaw; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HBD0A302682564B789731D86D251F63B5" commented="no"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>coastal and river bank erosion.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA489329D70B4944B83D52AA8655C281" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Strategy</header><text>The term <term>Strategy</term> means the National Adaptation and Resilience Strategy required to be developed jointly by the Chief Resilience Officer and the working groups under subsection (d)(1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBCFFAC7EFF3349539FF78F6BFF9DF921" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Territorial government</header><text>The term <term>territorial government</term> means the government of a territory (as defined in section 602(g) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/802">42 U.S.C. 802(g)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CDD571E0994484A82C62B94B3E430CD"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Working group</header><text>The term <quote>working group</quote> means a working group established under subsection (b)(2)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7A266AC72FCE4DC781DDB92FB7231494"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chief resilience officer and national adaptation and resilience working groups</header>
<paragraph id="H803F808A92BF45C0B427A43548C739F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President shall appoint a Chief Resilience Officer of the United States to serve in the Executive Office of the President.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H957BCDFB5C0E48BCB6CDAEE107D59F15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H3210A77BB38B4213B06B462480D40FF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serve the President by directing a whole-of-government effort to build resilience to environmental vulnerabilities in the United States (as described in the National Climate Assessment or other relevant analyses identified by the Chief Resilience Officer) in collaboration with existing Federal initiatives and interagency adaptation efforts;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H061A0ED7A11141E6A4DCD92C43526156"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish any necessary interagency working groups to facilitate coordination with respect to resilience and adaptation and the development of the Strategy; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H83BF9C25171D4D01863FC8364F3AEFED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at the end of a presidential administration, delegate the duties of the Chief Resilience Officer to the Executive Secretary of the Working Groups designated under paragraph (5)(A) until a new Chief Resilience Officer is appointed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6E937B2D413D433EAC571CF6A215EA59" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall be paid at the rate of basic pay for level III of the Executive Schedule under section 5314 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H003A0DE7B5474F419B7F9C228C5511FB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Necessary assistance</header><text>To carry out the development of the Strategy and efforts of working groups, each represented agency shall furnish necessary assistance to that working group, such as—</text> <subparagraph id="H08C75BC23AC04874A936DDF7E35BF6F4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a detail of employees to the working group to perform such functions as the Chief Resilience Officer may assign, including support staff for the Executive Secretary designated under paragraph (5)(A); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB94540D63A84DE59E86AFD4D536D848" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on request of the Chief Resilience Officer, undertaking special studies for the working group as may be appropriate to carry out the functions of the working group.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6F7AB7AFDA554A78A2E36D608AF58FE5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Executive secretary</header> <subparagraph id="HCFBF3AB0BA6945EC90641D5F1F41B673"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall designate a permanent employee of a represented agency to serve as Executive Secretary of the Working Groups.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAC642E0FE8F34D78A7295236F37425C4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Employment</header><text>The employee designated as Executive Secretary under subparagraph (A) shall remain an employee of the agency, department, or program from which the employee was appointed. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3DE235A12D8744D1B4FCFBA74B585336"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Partners council on adaptation and resilience</header> <paragraph id="H522A23CE9EC44476A7F7B550DCBCC25B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a council, to be known as the <quote>Partners Council on Adaptation and Resilience</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H93132B28B8844DFA9C60EBC6568D28F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mission and function</header><text>The Council shall work to improve the adaptation and resilience operations of the Federal Government by providing recommendations through the Chief Resilience Officer, including those recommendations contained in the report required under paragraph (3), that identify how the Federal Government can better support non-Federal partners with equitable resources, technical assistance, improved policies, and other assistance to help communities build resilience to changing environmental conditions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H054F6C88E5C743F89B34180FB2CCD330"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 16 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 3 years thereafter, the Council, acting through the Chief Resilience Officer, shall submit to the President a report that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="HDA6ED17CF91242E1BF91D3452FEA1D9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an analysis of the deficiencies or gaps in the resilience operations of the Federal Government that reduce or fail to increase the capacity of non-Federal partners to adapt to changing environmental conditions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5F2BBAC16B84D808A7EA653183C70DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of the resources, including Federal funding, necessary for non-Federal partners to adequately adapt to changing environmental conditions; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC0F12173E1144FBEB317192DA5EC1E91"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations with respect to how the Federal Government could better support efforts by non-Federal partners to expeditiously address vulnerabilities associated with climate change and build resilience.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H82778C2EBAEE4677BD000F768AEAD26D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chair and vice chair</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H68668309C0514473A7DEAB9EFEA7EA5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve as chairperson of the Council; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE850006FD6B34380B97B653397FC583A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appoint a vice chairperson from among the members of the Council appointed pursuant to paragraph (5).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9B0A1DD8638B4539A698A0CE9CDFF1D6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<subparagraph id="H9C2D8805C7FB4A2FBD4D691AC42CB866"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the Chief Resilience Officer, the Council shall consist of not more than 23 members appointed by the Chief Resilience Officer.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69A399B8185C4C8A9C90713B41E18102"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointment</header> <clause id="H022C30EE4F9347D2AA3C89E851B11326"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall appoint members of the Council with relevant experiences to inform how the Federal Government can better support State governments, local governments, territorial governments, the governments of Indian Tribes, the governments of Freely Associated States, nonprofit organizations, or private sector entities to build resilience to changing environmental conditions.</text></clause>
<clause id="H79BABA3295114F8AB541DBD2A2A06A95"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Non-federal partner members</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall appoint 20 non-Federal partner members of the Council as follows:</text> <subclause id="H1C0F343537184B78A609E3102E29B42A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>12 members who are employees of State governments, local governments, territorial governments, the governments of Indian Tribes, or the governments of Freely Associated States, of which—</text>
<item id="H08BDA2AEC27D4CDC98CB235F585F4873"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>not fewer than 2 shall be employees of a State government;</text></item> <item id="H5388E69D4C9C42CBA46E5359EA54C1A6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>not fewer than 2 shall be employees of a unit of local government;</text></item>
<item id="HD510A01E4F3E47EDAE532E2905AE985C"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>not fewer than 2 shall be employees of the government of an Indian Tribe; and</text></item> <item id="HA2F9C5A7F73A4A5DB2995B6A7CD5485C"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>not fewer than 2 shall be employees of a territorial government or the government of a Freely Associated State; and</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H3A6E5246DE0244248E7C23ED5A99387A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>8 members who represent nongovernmental organizations and the private sector, of which—</text> <item id="HBD640F4ECF53419F9D68EE5786E1CA69"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>3 shall represent nongovernmental organizations;</text></item>
<item id="HAA946C93CC444F71A180E616BBF74051"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>3 shall represent the private sector; and</text></item> <item id="H5E61600C8B824418A19FC00B3D6D28C3"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>2 shall represent academic institutions.</text></item></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HEDFDB94D6BC0482CB524D7A9476587C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Represented agency members</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer may, with the consent of those representatives, appoint not more than 3 representatives of represented agencies to the Council that the Chief Resilience Officer determines would promote dialogue useful for implementation of the duties of the Council while keeping the size of the Council manageable.</text></clause> <clause id="HD5AF9BBFDC4C4D3CAB7256BEB263DB48"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, the Chief Resilience Officer shall seek to select members of the Council who—</text>
<subclause id="H463A236C73974931A418F461127C15A1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>possess first-hand, lived experience of environmental vulnerability in the United States, including direct experience working with, or as members of, communities that are highly vulnerable to changing environmental conditions; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3401AA9F6B9648D09302D913FFCE8132"><enum>(II)</enum><text>represent a diversity of—</text>
<item id="H5829455265EF4AC5B1BB90EEDA409C5B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>perspectives;</text></item> <item id="H97DE749BEF82411087B93DFCD1790E6D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>demographics;</text></item>
<item id="HA65C389E43174C1DBC28AF2E18684F27"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>geographies;</text></item> <item id="H04D8021D1B914A7AA0BB6C30E1DDCA31"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>political affiliations; and</text></item>
<item id="H270FD944876948DB85501D3FFBCAD869"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>institution sizes, including representatives of both small and large units of government and businesses.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HFC1443CF27294DB590608304820B0A00"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Term</header><text>Members appointed to the Council shall serve a single term of not more than 3 years, except that—</text>
<subclause id="H92DFB64BCD2D4AA3AB08F169F62FE3CC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>of the initial members appointed to the Council, the Chief Resilience Officer shall appoint—</text> <item id="HD2FA116CDD6C43769274D5D31D836389"><enum>(aa)</enum><text><fraction>1/2</fraction> of the members to serve for a term of 18 months; and</text></item>
<item id="H8BDC3633CC384275825A59A06117D58F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text><fraction>1/2</fraction> of the members to serve a term of 3 years; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HCA845F1517CE4CB3B2EFE8E200243BE4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Chief Resilience Officer may extend the term of any member of the Council by a period of not more than 1 year on a one-time basis, if the Chief Resilience Officer determines it necessary to support the work of the Council.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H26E4749A3BC24EBAB9EBF0A4D173A221"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Vacancies</header>
<subclause id="H664CBD7AAF3444DDAE089D7A363B7E75"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A vacancy in the Council shall be filled in the same manner in which the original selection was made.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC8F9B63FBFAD4C129EE0C244BF29972E"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Appointment of new members</header><text>After the expiration of the term for which a member of the Council is appointed, the member may continue to serve until a successor is appointed.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8451FD64ACA146F6A669C29B19781D02"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Applicability of faca</header><text>Section 1013 of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Council.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD8517D560537460ABF81BFEB1CE19616"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National adaptation and resilience strategy</header> <paragraph id="H9A425E3D66EE46D3AC638FFE7572958E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Strategy</header> <subparagraph id="H767158D4C81642F18189CB34D0EE50FB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Resilience Officer shall submit to the President and Congress a National Adaptation and Resilience Strategy.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H424DFA5CE3324A59B5436FED84056D9A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Not later than the date that is 3 years after the date on which the Chief Resilience Officer submits the Strategy to the President and Congress under subparagraph (A), and every 3 years thereafter, the Chief Resilience Officer shall submit an updated version of the Strategy to the President and Congress to account for—</text> <clause id="H51887C7C4B134B2F9A693FC23041FBB5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evolving science related to climate change, resilience, and adaptation;</text></clause>
<clause id="H219593D75F3D453C94970004CA79E68D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>relevant changes in Federal Government structure, congressional authorities, or appropriations; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD0662053697A44D081B1E03B04D30AA9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other necessary improvements or changes identified by the Chief Resilience Officer.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H353BED2FFAE347169CBB2010E0C87948"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Purpose and scope</header><text>The Strategy shall describe strategies for the Federal Government, in partnership with non-Federal partners, to address the vulnerabilities of the United States described in the National Climate Assessment or other relevant analyses identified by the Chief Resilience Officer to ensure that—</text> <clause id="H9E5230BE618D4823B2C60CBC8E6FE131"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the United States has an overarching strategic vision to respond to climate change that—</text>
<subclause id="H114AB6CAE45C4996B603BBBB5CC441B8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>identifies national resilience goals and guides national adaptation efforts;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H66465E44CC48462DAFA01215604F5351"><enum>(II)</enum><text>facilitates the incorporation of the resilience goals identified under subclause (I) into relevant national programs, operations, and strategies;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H39EC8015DE79467DA3C4D7F3E491EAFE"><enum>(III)</enum><text>develops proactive, long-term, scenario-based strategies to plan for and respond to current and future disasters or environmental condition changes to human communities, natural resources and public land, and infrastructure and other physical assets;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H121D53C515B5425D96DDF86ABE532AC0"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>emphasizes forward-thinking adaptation strategies, including predisaster mitigation, that seek to overcome repeated impacts to vulnerable systems and communities;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H704982016B264135A6E961A02D2C1D54"><enum>(V)</enum><text>prioritizes resilience efforts to support the most vulnerable human communities and the most urgent national resilience challenges, as determined by the Chief Resilience Officer in consultation with the working groups;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H8074CF8D6665479D9B2B5D380AB5E506"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>avoids unnecessary redundancies and inefficiencies in national adaptation and resilience planning and response; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HA306C122941643C7BF2721B57FA68F52"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>recognizes the vulnerability of natural systems to changing environmental conditions and underscores the importance of promoting ecosystem resilience to preserve the intrinsic value of nature and support ecosystem services relied on by human beings;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA11331E7BD1045D39FE68FE553185CE0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Federal investments in Federal and non-Federal infrastructure and assets promote resilience to the maximum extent practicable; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HE88DD21D84C24220BF67B6D495E18AB9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the adaptive capacity and resilience of State governments, local governments, territorial governments, the governments of Indian Tribes, and governments of Freely Associated States are maximized to the maximum extent practicable.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5A106C8743BF4FC2954E76E9420A8BC4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Council recommendations</header><text>In developing the Strategy, the Chief Resilience Officer and working groups shall consider the recommendations of the Council.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H63426D6ADE44474F8FFE43C602744D31"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The Strategy shall include the following:</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38279ED2D1C9481B8D54EA167A61ACCA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Information with respect to direct Federal Government adaptation and resilience response, including—</text>
<subclause id="HCBCC0F42558D40A3A793DE56135D9932" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>information on better preparing the United States for the adverse impacts experienced or anticipated to be experienced as a result of near-term and long-term climate hazards, including slow-onset hazards;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD47287DED78A4F6D964032654F5A4C9D" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>information on educating, engaging, or developing the skills of the workforce of the represented agencies with respect to topics related to environmental vulnerability and resilience to promote effective Federal resilience operations; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H0549D9F9C9644E4691F643CF593E1161" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an identification of opportunities and appropriate circumstances for represented agencies to better use natural infrastructure as an adaptation strategy.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H1E09257E970B414A827249F4344823E9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Information relating to the support of the adaptation of non-Federal partners and resilience groups, including—</text>
<subclause id="H1806B5130F714574B64161ED27651BDD" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>methods for represented agencies to better collaborate and work directly with non-Federal partners to increase the resilience and adaptive capacity of State governments, local governments, territorial governments, the governments of Indian Tribes, the governments of Freely Associated States, and other non-Federal partners;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB3739767273F4640A7BE6D39BE9F580B" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>clarifying, simplifying, and harmonizing the planning requirements and application processes for State governments, local governments, territorial governments, the governments of Indian Tribes, and the governments of Freely Associated States to access Federal funds for adaptation and resilience efforts across represented agencies;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H675C9C523AFC484F86CD5A4551F37990" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identifying under-resourced communities and communities with low adaptive capacity and resilience and to directly support those communities in applying for Federal funds for adaptation and resilience efforts; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6AA7C8BF9FE747E28FDD5BC99A397FC2" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>supporting the retreat or relocation of human communities in areas that are at increasing risk from climate change, in particular from slow-onset climate hazards, including strategies to better manage equitable property buyouts, managed retreat, or relocation options for communities in those areas.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HCB0C6AAEBCB9423A995F0168E98C483A" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>At the discretion of the Chief Resilience Officer, information relating to developing or improving resilience metrics and indicators to assist the Federal Government and non-Federal partners—</text> <subclause id="H065075F3C25440C591214322FB6FDF49" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, to consistently measure the resilience of human communities, natural systems, and physical assets to climate change;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H10840B7AC131424093A196CE5B8F75C6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to set baselines and targets to measurably increase resilience over time and measure progress towards goals outlined in the Strategy; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H77190700408B43D4A3DF5E60E0D90391" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to better monitor and assess the effectiveness of various resilience-building activities after implementation.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H9D4C7FC132554BCAB428F80FDDFD255E" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Information relating to funding adaptation, including—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C3206246E3A49E292B6CB31EA79E012"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strategies for—</text>
<item id="HDD3782EE961743D38EF91671548B407B" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>helping to prioritize Federal funding expenditures for adaptation and resilience in consideration of the greatest vulnerabilities; and</text></item> <item id="H41BC310B48B348348E8040712E314832" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>creating financial incentives for adaptation and resilience efforts;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="HBDB3431ED4384F1694E11E5EAB8C8A85" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a review of the cost-benefit analysis methodologies and discount rates used by represented agencies for all Federal investments, including a review of the implications of those methodologies and discount rates for adaptation and resilience; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H50219FA58B3248E4A8E3A6856777E3AD" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>recommendations to improve the methodologies described in subclause (II) to reflect—</text>
<item id="HF9A2C2CE24B44EE9B5D961E4E9B0F18C" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the added value of pre-disaster mitigation, resilience planning, and construction methodologies over the lifetime of a project or unit of infrastructure;</text></item> <item id="H16CEC8DC6D42471C82F96D10A28C08D4" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the benefits of natural infrastructure investments and nature-based solutions;</text></item>
<item id="H17E0FAE7A9244B28A342E64BEA0D748C" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the potential value of retreat and relocation as adaptation solutions; and</text></item> <item id="H097692ACEC1C44309CB96655E4F205BE" commented="no"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>to what extent existing cost-benefit analysis methodologies lead to inequitable outcomes or outcomes that increase climate vulnerability.</text></item></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H3C6E1D3744BD4A049E8162A5871E0003" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Information relating to community considerations, including strategies for—</text> <subclause id="H396D028CC7EA4C69B352735CC89D3E3E" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>ensuring that the costs, benefits, and risks resulting from resilience efforts, including funding allocations, the methodologies for determining funding allocations, and existing and future policies, are equitably distributed among sectors of society, types of communities, and geographies;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HEF5F3B44152A447DB27E7D1AE0AE1BE2" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensuring that federally supported resilience efforts are—</text> <item id="H2F502721F8A040E785A897D79AB0FD78" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>designed in consultation with the communities that will be affected by those efforts; and</text></item>
<item id="HD5B4C45874D446B1A579FD6D1403B920" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>centered on the needs of those communities; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HCDAFB0CEAC914EF6B8B1D7A402A2F846" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>to the greatest extent practicable, integrating equity considerations across all aspects of the Strategy.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H772C23CA75C9462AA8C25020D6A05070"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><text>Concurrently with the Strategy and each update of the Strategy, the Chief Resilience Officer shall submit to the President and Congress an Implementation Plan that describes how represented agencies intend to carry out the Strategy, which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H5691A4EEA42A433AB0913A68B22F1FD3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the roles and responsibilities of each represented agency in carrying out each element of the Strategy described in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF2FAB501DE3347F082A54E59626D0B84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a plan to enter into such interagency agreements between and among represented agencies, partnerships with non-Federal entities, and other agreements for coordination between and among the Federal Government and non-Federal partners as may be necessary to facilitate a unified national plan to build resilience; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF3FD3829A7BF46AC918C66916DF07C65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the use of any relevant metrics and indicators described in paragraph (1)(E)(iii); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H031EE8AE154847E4BB027BD47709D179"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations on leveraging or developing a national web-based approached to share resilience, adaptation, pre-disaster mitigation best practices, experiences, projects, technologies, and approaches.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64DC580194714B3BBEF475E051EDB8E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>National adaptation and resilience operations</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall include in the Strategy—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC3B4A9C496BD4D9A9C2935044E5F7BFB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of the existing resilience operations of each represented agency that includes—</text> <clause id="H91C497E356CF4CFAB08BD9363CCF38CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the roles and responsibilities of each represented agency in building national resilience to the vulnerabilities described in the National Climate Assessment or other analyses relevant to each represented agency;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD1CA84181823403EB46A3240C80287E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the major findings and conclusions from adaptation plans or risk or vulnerability assessments prepared by each represented agency;</text></clause> <clause id="HFE759A0324EB402F8AD2C7DC687B227A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the mechanisms by which each represented agency supports the resilience efforts of non-Federal partners, such as by providing funding, resources, and technical assistance; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HF207270315BB472EB0FE0E998F16F4F2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an assessment of how each represented agency is working to ensure equitable adaptation outcomes; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFD075E46B17D4E449AD0563DE627F01A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a cross-agency analysis of the resilience operations identified under subparagraph (A) that—</text>
<clause id="H0234BBE90B34425D9A24DA4EE934B1B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identifies—</text> <subclause id="H1BCF0DF1226243608DA5FB3325347ABB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the challenges, barriers, or disincentives for the Federal Government to build resilience in the United States;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1F7A03B1D7B0415F9B90FD34AA0E1515"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the inconsistencies in goals, priorities, or strategies underlying resilience operations and policy across represented agencies that may inhibit effective interagency coordination to support national resilience, including—</text> <item id="HAC82CF5CAE7F4D33871EE0DAD48D2E85"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the areas of necessary differences in those goals, priorities, or strategies; and</text></item>
<item id="H5928320286984C45A77C07D788DA3B3C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the justifications for those inconsistencies;</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HD6412C9E134B44EF8E8C2837009C9B4A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>areas of overlap or redundant use of resources between or among represented agencies, including recommendations to eliminate any unnecessary or unintentional redundancy;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCEED37FAB16A4ECE88A529FB0C1E9374"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>gaps or deficiencies in resilience operations and policy that need to be addressed in the context of the Strategy;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9E27E1841BF241E1B40F6C086187385F"><enum>(V)</enum><text>opportunities for greater collaboration between or among represented agencies to improve Federal Government resilience operations and policy; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HF445556619A64F7F934AAEDAD5E7F7CA"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>opportunities for greater collaboration between the Federal Government and non-Federal partners to build local-level adaptive capacity and resilience; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H32397F7B711945D9929C3E1250DF690E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a review and summary of all available Federal funding from represented agencies that is specifically allocated for adaptation activities to be undertaken by non-Federal partners, including—</text>
<subclause id="H88A6950F8F4749D8A9AEEA8B16FDF836"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a summary of Federal funding available in appropriations accounts and subaccounts;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE83A65B157E04C26AA1116C36E71308F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>disparities between the supply and demand for adaptation funding available to non-Federal partners; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H8D4D453C507B4CC29C667B33CCA1D4DD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(III)</enum><text>existing mechanisms to ensure Federal funding allocations are being directed to communities with the greatest level of vulnerability. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8E35510552B4B37ABB8DB6CA3FD3E88"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the completion of each Strategy and each Implementation Plan, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the President and Congress a report that assesses—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0C799303F44A4285858D1E04455DE487"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the extent to which the Strategy and Implementation Plan have been carried out by the Federal Government, which shall be judged, as appropriate, based on any metrics and indicators developed to track progress in increasing resilience under paragraph (1)(E)(iii);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49C96E32B22143FF98A67993B4901FD9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the actions taken under the Strategy and Implementation Plan and the resulting outcomes of those actions in building national adaptation and resilience planning and response; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H57B64AB4C46744769C034F9F27C5282D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the progress made towards the development of an effective whole-of-government effort to build resilience to the vulnerabilities described in the National Climate Assessment or other relevant analyses identified by the Chief Resilience Officer, including recommendations for additional steps necessary to reach this goal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED6834FD230A489F92262C356D891A54"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>The Chief Resilience Officer shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC214FAF682294E24B8B7BCF767901645"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish draft and final versions of the Strategy and Implementation Plan, and each update to the Strategy and Implementation Plan; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD50AD04D864F493CBF847F6C2934CC4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through publication in the Federal Register, solicit comments from the public on the draft versions of the documents published under subparagraph (A) for a period of 60 days, which the Chief Resilience Officer shall consider before submitting final versions of the Strategy and Implementation Plan, and updates to the Strategy and Implementation Plan, to the President and Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF59E6B76A5C14585910D62937065E476" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Adaptation and resilience clearinghouse</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Resilience Officer shall establish an adaptation and resilience clearinghouse that—</text> <paragraph id="H009F23B2D2E44652B8BA4686D8F9DFB9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increases the accessibility and utility of adaptation and resilience data and information produced, published, or hosted by the Federal Government; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7732FA505CC451CAED15ED2A52E24D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increases technical assistance to non-Federal partners on adaptation and resilience planning and response, including strategies to better collaborate across the represented agencies and work with non-Federal partners to—</text> <subparagraph id="H155DDBCEAD0145D98D6DE0A179C79BB0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide locally relevant resilience and adaptation information and, where practicable and useful, downscaled climate projections that are necessary to support local-level adaptation efforts;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8182B0D9147B417694CB59BC19B1F2B0" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish improved methods of communicating resilience and adaptation risk and other information;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8F014B998284794ACED5DAB123AD384" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>better educate non-Federal partners about the available resources;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEDA5C05EAE834B20B7CAA88C14E954E8" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>streamline information about Federal adaptation and resilience resources in a single centralized location if determined necessary by the Chief Resilience Officer;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5B954CA67A3747C18820619825BA892F" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>assist non-Federal partners in selecting and using appropriate information or related tools;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5DD0E1AA35284CD981963C2FA62CEF47" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>work with non-Federal partners to access existing Federal grant programs related to resilience and adaptation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9A330A7F40904E00A5589D6486F6FC5C" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><text>standardize procedures to synthesize, align, and update adaptation and resilience information produced, published, or hosted by the Federal Government to create standardized national, regional, and, where applicable, local climate information for adaptation planning.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8ACC450A63A449ADB6597A6BCD206E50"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall cease to be effective on the date that is the earlier of—</text> <paragraph id="HE82BE30485414044AE5F9EB0D3F74A0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the Comptroller General of the United States submits to the President and Congress the third assessment report under subsection (d)(4); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAF19D21FA1C541B78AD793E24325CA18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>September 30, 2033.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

