<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H15F94A2D1D704FFFAFB5D3FD1E555823" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4842</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To authorize efforts to counter the influence of the People’s Republic of China at the United Nations.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE92E076919704D61B2FD0D7D9502AA31" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H94FE5F65E3E047CFBB8C11DCFADDD1BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote>Strategy To Oppose Purposeful CCP Aggression at the United Nations Act of 2023</quote> or <quote>STOP CCP at UN Act of 2023</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HEE39B141136346B5B7F52331432CEFD9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H74EE166834F845FC8DF59E05B60DCD4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) wield increasing influence at the United Nations and other international and multinational organizations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D3CF22ED460477C89FA6EE88C9B88D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>This influence threatens the United States in its diplomatic engagement with countries at the United Nations and around the world.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94417C32D0394B9D898F324987879D8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>China uses its influence to sway vulnerable countries to vote in support of policies that support China and the goals of the CCP.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94A091227CBF4F8DB18D4DBDF4734ECF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>China uses its financial support and contributions to the United Nations and its agencies to influence the outcomes of policy debates and votes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD0E2CEA50216478A928D4A2ACD1A7A43"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From 2015 to 2021, China has grown its leadership role at the United Nations, where Chinese citizens have led four United Nations specialized agencies: the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO), the International Telecommunication Union (ITU), and the United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO). Three of the four Chinese citizen agency heads have departed due to term limits, however the FAO is still led by a Chinese citizen. Additionally, this year a Chinese citizen is one of seven candidates for election to the position of Secretary-General of the International Maritime Organization (IMO), a United Nations specialized agency responsible for improving the safety and security of international shipping and facilitation of international maritime traffic.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD0119D1DF9FF4FE1B3B234644F8163A7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Efforts to counter the influence of China at the United Nations</header> 
<subsection id="H9EE9AADBBC1444D4AAB5FC626894C084"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H93F905765DD94743A5DF2D3166DCB7A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for 9 years, the Secretary of State and the United States Permanent Representative to the United Nations shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the People’s Republic of China’s actions and attempts to place Chinese nationals in leadership positions at the United Nations and its affiliated agencies, including through coercion, intimidation, bribery and other illegitimate means, and to provide broader personnel representation of China at the United Nations, to influence the United Nations and its agencies generally.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD00C27257A764D5D820A69F4597EA7DF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters to be included</header><text>The report required by this subsection should include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H03336C26064A4D29BFB380A151D6C5F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of votes taken in the United Nations General Assembly, the United Nations Security Council, and United Nations specialized agencies that aligned with China’s interest and voting record.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3CFEBD1AEFE9431A9B29B6631AA3FD70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of financial contributions to the United Nations by China.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4E87BBED648446F4AA2A620E68CAD40B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of Chinese diplomatic personnel assigned to the United Nations.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEF9ED53D725A4DB49985AD8CB8B5D5E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of Chinese contributions, to include military personnel, to United Nations peacekeeping missions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86F754F4D7444C378AF685B866415675"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An identification of leadership positions at the United Nations, an identification of Chinese nationals in such positions, including Chinese nationals in supporting positions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6287203BDB764558A7DCF8635B6E5569"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The number and description of attempts by China to obtain such leadership positions at the United Nations.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H95B51489FC784D88B821C880CA18283E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A description of attempts and processes of China to co-opt third countries in order to align their votes at the United Nations with Chinese interests.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H481E0D809D364319823182FA98D74D1C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A list of not less than those 15 countries that are most aligned with Chinese interests at the United Nations, to include through voting record and lobbying efforts.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00CF7C59BEB449AFB59C0E5BCF1DECF0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>An explanation on how China views the United Nations as a vehicle to advance its interests.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BA099FDEF724F69864316D45E8A114A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by this subsection should be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H10D65CCED66B4C288490840755BE9AF5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H650D13598B94493489A93CFBA5C3D75F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Select Committee on the Strategic Competition between the United States and the Chinese Communist Party of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32C6D6A31E3D415C91A764E7411A2043"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD6158EB004B54DE4BFAD4DF750F96AE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office of Multilateral Strategy</header> 
<paragraph id="H49CB67585F9346CA9B8154DE43910F09"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall establish an office to develop and implement a strategy to counter China at the United Nations. The Secretary may designate the Office of Multilateral Strategy at the Department of State, as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, as the office required to be established by this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E5DE1AA936E43F48F2EB3FCE69C4620"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting and consultation</header><text>The office established pursuant to this subsection shall report to and consult with Congress with respect to the strategy described in this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H67EA333C9A7642F3B3622ECBAA62AF3F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should consider paying its contributions to the United Nations that are in arrears in order to strategically and financially expand its influence at the United Nations and counter China’s argument of insufficient United States financial engagement at the United Nations.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5CD4E56111834C7BBEDA695A6315E53E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sponsored junior professional officers</header><text>The Secretary of State shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2563DB2E3E2B4E6980F9F70555B89496"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require tracking and reporting on the number of Chinese sponsored junior professional officers at the United Nations; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9AF6DA95798946D08A8B8FE254067092"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increase the number of United States sponsored junior professional officers at the United Nations in order to match or exceed the number of Chinese sponsored junior professional officers at the United Nations.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 
