<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H666E9B0246834246827F8B5AD7D32394" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4343 IH: Organ Donation Clarification Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4343</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Organ Transplant Act to clarify the definition of valuable consideration, to clarify that pilot programs that honor and promote organ donation do not violate that Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA223B72083A747DAB9AD5790C25F469A" style="OLC"><section id="H5D8FEFC78EB94DA698A7973B889ABB15" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Organ Donation Clarification Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53F7AA52832640CBAA0801E577C4942E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HDBEF118D9CD04DBAB74B0A520E4AFEAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As of May 2023, 113,999 people await an organ transplant, with 95,957 of those people waiting for a kidney, and average wait times are approaching five years for a kidney, with over one-and-a-half times as many people being added to the waiting lists as getting a transplant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E9066BFF5AC4EDE9ED069AE36C5227F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Of the nearly three million Americans who die annually, under 30,000, representing about one percent of all deaths each year, possess major organs healthy enough for transplanting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCBEF6F134524109824C0052D9815693"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On average, 17 people a day died while waiting for an organ in 2020, with the majority of those people waiting for a kidney.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H545B5796BD954249A047FD8D848E0EC8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2022, approximately 4,498 people were removed from kidney waiting lists and approximately 1,500 from liver (1,123), heart (239), and lungs (145) waiting lists because they became permanently too sick to receive a transplant. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9153BEDC2A76485BA9CFA9775B1371F1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Over 75 percent of dialysis patients are not employed because dialysis requires multiple treatments per week which last several hours and leave patients drained, thus creating a huge financial burden on the patients, their families, and the government; moreover, lost tax revenue from these individuals is not included in the cost estimates above. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DF6ED298FF444A2A81AE7F1BE8FA8CA"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A patient receiving a kidney transplant, and thus no longer needing dialysis, can enjoy a much higher quality of life for another 10–15 years on average.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F533AF19389402DB8C9E2A1CFF1D483"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As medical advances extend people’s lives on dialysis, the number of patients on dialysis will increase significantly, as will the costs for individuals and the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AD6FB7A4ECC42CE85E7E6D33E222D99"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Roughly seven percent of the Medicare budget goes to the End Stage Renal Disease Program, with dialysis costing Medicare over $90,000 per patient per year, as Federal law dictates that Medicare will cover dialysis for everyone who has made minimal Social Security tax payments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52CE2F8C463C4E83B1727A9558FF0C25"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A kidney transplant pays for itself in less than two years, with each transplant saving an average of $136,000 in medical costs over a 10-year period, 75 percent of which is savings to the taxpayers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H467E3DE3C8CE48B2A28052DBF49545DB"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Experts project that if the supply of transplant kidneys could be increased to meet the demand, taxpayers would save more than $16,000,000,000 per year in medical costs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25C7EB2E80D945D8BAF8394A1E67264D"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The World Health Organization estimates that 10 percent of all transplants take place on the international black market, the last choice for desperate patients facing an alternative of death, however recipients often receive infected kidneys and suffer poor health outcomes and donors are often victimized.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56D8EB8F4CA84990A0B7B255C60880AD"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Present policy on domestic donation has never been subject to studies or pilots to determine effectiveness in increasing the availability of donated organs and the effectiveness of safeguards that prevent coercion or exploitation, precludes all but altruistic donation, prohibiting any form of incentive or benefit for donors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41064EA91E4B4AB0847D8974AA173DB8"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2010, Israel implemented sweeping changes to its national organ donation program including reducing financial burdens on donors, giving future transplantation priority to registered organ donors and their families, and promoting donation by reimbursing the donor’s medical costs, 40 days of lost wages, and five years of medical and life insurance costs, and as a result saw organ donation approximately triple over a 10-year period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCC2A9EB0A394743B8A17C079E09025C"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Experts are arriving at a consensus that trials are necessary to find new methods of promoting additional organ donation which will save lives and reduce organ trafficking.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H53E85DD3C6174A1FABCE8C45AFAF2466"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification of certain provisions of the National Organ Transplant Act</header><subsection id="H645CDBDAA4A5495D903D823F2B3C25AE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Valuable consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 301(c)(2) of the National Organ Transplant Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/274e">42 U.S.C. 274e(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA74A767BC2C247DAAAA365235C88D009" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HE465BF8C893B41A191F9FEF87A0AA346"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>valuable consideration</term> does not include the following: </text><subparagraph id="H04B2722E7F164621832FBC211EF73034"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reasonable payments associated with the removal, transportation, implantation, processing, preservation, quality control, and storage of a human organ. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFEC004176CF463EB43C57B5237EFE7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Advanced payments or reimbursement for travel, lodging, food during travel, and other logistical expenses related to donation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7E5C13FA841443BB5E73D6F5FAEEE5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Advanced payments or reimbursement for dependent care expenses related to donation before, during, or after the donation, but not later than the date that is 10 years after the date of the donation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95DD5DE80AB848668E6F99F33A2BB8AF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Advanced payments or reimbursement for lost wages related to donation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB92F3EEA39143FAA7A68DD0217FB8D2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Medical expenses related to donation and all related follow-up care including preventative follow-up care and medication for up to a 10-year period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H820068FC82A94DC8A4BD1368B64C475E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Paperwork or legal costs related to donation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1681C5D129CB42E49C9B43753AC761D2"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any term life insurance policy against the risk of death or disability as a result of donating an organ or the longer-term health effects of having donated an organ, that—</text><clause id="HD9734C0B11A64B4182534B89BD16D177"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a life insurance policy, provides for payments in amounts less than $2,000,000, adjusted annually for inflation; and</text></clause><clause id="H8D33376D36584F939076E5EFE9C5CD93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a disability insurance policy, provides for payments equal to or less than the reasonable earnings expectations of the donor.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H52C8DE0D1D7D4006B0B0B0BC465D8DB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered pilot program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 301 of the National Organ Transplant Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/274e">42 U.S.C. 274e</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6C59AA32A8814F4CACBBA5BE0181DF45" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HC70001DB4C954A718F25ED43CF639E61"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Covered pilot program encouraging organ donation</header><paragraph id="HBF5A71998D7C443293CD2FBD317E58C5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Approval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may approve covered pilot programs for purposes of applying the exception in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C10A3F710FC4EC19B4B326B258FE56B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception to prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) does not prohibit—</text><subparagraph id="HDCC40C20022B4212B0A789EC7882CE62"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">acquisition, receipt, or transfer of any noncash benefit provided pursuant to a covered pilot program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBA868A3ED3145A3A25382E1BF3B809A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other actions taken to carry out a covered pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H075C0150A01242B69FCB104055533613"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H17DC145EF9AF4AFC882C507D9C5270A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered pilot program</term> means a pilot program that—</text><clause id="H8BB6521B5BDB40BBAEA0B67FCC2D458E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is conducted by the Federal Government or any State, territory, Tribe, or local government;</text></clause><clause id="H68B932C09F854E75A62390DD1F1A5E1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is approved by the Secretary under paragraph (1);</text></clause><clause id="H392B86B9A8BD4E13AED632AC67C8C7A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is subject to an ethical review board process;</text></clause><clause id="HBB51E99AC3A74999AE18307C9A800046"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has a term of not more than 5 fiscal years;</text></clause><clause id="HAE7B14D15C574D729EDB2EA6C84557EC"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is for the purpose of providing, or allowing the provision of, noncash benefits for organ donation and organ donors, and measuring the effects of providing such noncash benefits;</text></clause><clause id="HFD4CB2F740DE4444B696CAD662E8AAD1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>measures the effects of providing such noncash benefits; and</text></clause><clause id="H38BF5DDFFC3847F29A179AF6BF76F9C5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">allows for the determination of the recipient of an organ donated pursuant to the covered pilot program—</text><subclause id="H9A8A227D12874D7A83792461DB4968E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of organs from deceased donors, only by the Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF1780BD2F4C24A1CBB6C4A77ABF55759"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of nondirected organs from living donors, only by a transplant center that is a member of, and abides by the rules and requirements of, the Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network established pursuant to section 372 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8D9F1363C8B4B739EBD8852ADF64BB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>noncash benefit</term> means any benefit or thing of value received by an organ donor that is impossible to sell, trade, or otherwise transfer to another individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8961DDEB8C114DBD9ACFE0B7AA0EEFA9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than three years after the Secretary first approves a covered pilot program, and every three years thereafter until there is no longer a covered pilot program in operation, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress on—</text><subparagraph id="H0FDD7637C8C34962B9DA74F7AE7A94C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the impact of covered pilot programs on the organ pool;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC20C23B356D4EEAB2357065BB7E4E54"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the demographics of the donors participating in covered pilot programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE30DD998F5A6470990AEFC0085F48D58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the demographics of the recipients of organs donated by participants in covered pilot programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C50C2AFB681443383E70B65C966FCD4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the effectiveness, fairness, and equitableness of the distribution of nondirected living donor organs that are donated by participants in covered pilot programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC105CAD13F4450CB39B004C98B10D56"><enum>(E)</enum><text>recommendations to Congress on—</text><clause id="H989274A6E7B1459B994D124F7499EBDE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improving covered pilot programs; and</text></clause><clause id="H969FF3B5CBF54684A92714A14DF73AAE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expanding the use of noncash benefits to incentivize organ donation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC5AD843E061E4E1DAA3F4372115BAA5D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relationship to payments by recipient of organ</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (d) of section 377 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/274f">42 U.S.C. 274f(d)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0C59A477FAC04D5C9EE82F9BD0F3671C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H89BD94A0621C4E74866E87EA5D3BB5F2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Relationship to payments under other programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An award may be made under subsection (a) only if the applicant involved agrees that the award will not be expended to pay the qualifying expenses of a donating individual to the extent that—</text><paragraph id="H68900FFCA1154214A23760747BA7C8E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>payment has been made, or can reasonably be expected to be made, with respect to such expenses—</text><subparagraph id="H3ACFA688F69F48F9911FB5475ADA92E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>under any State compensation program, under an insurance policy, or under any Federal or State health benefits program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H687CE5F9AD784EF08E8E2B50D0619D65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by an entity that provides health services on a prepaid basis; or </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB840120D55F347F485C062E859C12409"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the recipient of the organ has made payment, or had agreed to make payment, with respect to such expenses. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

