<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9BD386B92BD34447AB7B70B232E787EB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3886 IH: Government Unanimous Oversight Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3886</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require Federal judges and Federal prosecutors to submit quarterly financial disclosures to the Judicial Conference and the Attorney General.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3A5793FCFFF14B84813CF6B33BF36C55" style="OLC"><section id="HB38BB84DD25C4CE894615D039975DD69" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Government Unanimous Oversight Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GUO Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HA760118C9C6D4A8BA67DD2E614324A52"><enum>2.</enum><header>Quarterly financial disclosure requirement</header><subsection id="HC658AFFE2889466D926B22E7017C4621"><enum>(a)</enum><header> In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to any requirements under the Ethics in Government Act of 1978, on a quarterly basis, each Federal judge and each spouse thereof shall submit to the Judicial Conference, and each United States Attorney and Assistant United States Attorney, and each spouse thereof, shall submit to the Attorney General, a financial disclosure containing such information as the Judicial Conference or the Attorney General, as appropriate, may reasonably require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H878A7C3E1E45455EA7C6B3D8E47C6BB1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Judicial Conference reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Judicial Conference determines, based on a financial disclosure submitted under subsection (a), that a Federal judge or a spouse thereof has received compensation, reimbursement, or another payment from a foreign government, the Judicial Conference shall refer such matter to the Attorney General. </text></subsection><subsection id="H471312AEFDD047DDB18E766EC26617C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>If the Attorney General determines, based on a financial disclosure submitted under subsection (a) or a report received under subsection (b), that an individual has violated Federal law, the Attorney General shall take appropriate steps to enforce any such law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D48A97761F146F3B12CD06BE85F7912"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Upon making a determination that Federal law has been violated under subsection (c), the Attorney General shall submit a report to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate on such violation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F916AACDFC54771B916E4AD4EF08EDD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>An individual who fails to file a report required under subsection (a) shall be fined in an amount of $5,000 for each 30-day period that the individual fails to file such report. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

