<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAB51B8F7769B4BD39BEC21573D2A149B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 4898 IH: Global Press Freedom Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4898</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Office of Press Freedom, to create press freedom curriculum at the National Foreign Affairs Training Center, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H292F42A459D14951ACCA81A635132F17" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H44B649BD50424710B4FFF8255E431F4F"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Global Press Freedom Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H109BD59A1E34472282C3C0814EED020F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HBCB35330993943F2A237A82004F8A756"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Freedom of the press is fundamental to an open and free society and is foundational in the United States democratic system and enshrined in the First Amendment of the United States Constitution, which states (in part) <quote>Congress shall make no law . . . abridging the freedom of speech or of the press . . .</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5191217162224CE5AE967E2E5B85E13B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Historically, United States foreign policy has advanced freedom of the press as a central tenet, at home and abroad.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F0A9387288847E2A3B6FDAF1C9EA88D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States led the drafting of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, adopted in Paris on December 10, 1948, which enshrines the commitment of countries around the world to protect and promote universal human rights and values that are indispensable for human dignity, including freedom of expression.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F56E29B81A74316AC81496DB9145653"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Article 19 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights states, <quote>Everyone has the right to freedom of opinion and expression; this right includes freedom to hold opinions without interference and to seek, receive and impart information and ideas through any media and regardless of frontiers.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB002CD788824B779790145D0D8DA7AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A free and independent press has long been recognized as an important aspect of the United States’ national security and actions taken by foreign governments or organizations that weaken free press protections are a national security threat to the United States. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B17F1D9DB9A47708CFBA8D7614D0FAD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>International freedom of the press is under renewed and, in some cases, increasing assault, with rhetoric delegitimizing and discrediting the media or journalists, online harassment, physical attacks, gender-based violence, legal campaigns, censorship, and surveillance, all of which threaten the ability of journalists to do their jobs safely, freely, and without fear of reprisal.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F6CFC2EBD9544988563F2828DF3E09D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the past decade, the world has seen a significant deterioration of press freedoms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H505A8E31C57B4A069E37D7ED2F3A5F04"><enum>(8)</enum><text>According to Freedom House’s <quote>Freedom in the World</quote> and <quote>Freedom on the Net</quote> reports—</text><subparagraph id="H3E42196E1EB84635A60405E49606834A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of countries and territories scoring a zero for media freedom has ballooned from 14 countries to 33 countries since 2005; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2260271EC834BF385B2F21A3E40F465"><enum>(B)</enum><text>people in 53 countries faced arrest or imprisonment for expressing themselves online, including online journalists targeted for their reporting;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H052158C552C1440186DFBDD6B476A5DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">40 countries blocked websites featuring political, social, or religious content, including many news outlets; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03943D92F71941FFA7E3BB7F8A89FBE4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">journalists, bloggers, human rights activists, and other people experienced physical violence in retaliation for expressing themselves online in 40 countries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B1A41C9082840C1AF6BFDCA31D79E5C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>According to Reporters Without Borders’ 2022 World Press Freedom Index—</text><subparagraph id="HD3D509448AD94287A2B86FF652A48EA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>approximately 74 percent of the countries of the world are classified as <quote>problematic situation</quote> or worse with respect to journalistic freedom, with a record number of 28 countries receiving a <quote>very bad</quote> rating for press freedom situations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E8099FF87E74A20AE09BF46FC41AED3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>approximately 26 percent of the countries of the world have <quote>satisfactory</quote> or <quote>good</quote> press freedom environments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FD73BF50BB84D53A14D1D0F57186DA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>among the jurisdictions that have recently suffered the largest declines in press freedom are Hong Kong, Myanmar, Afghanistan, Russia, Ukraine (attributable to Russia’s invasion), Georgia, Greece, Nicaragua, the Palestinian Territories, Tunisia, and Mali; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F856F6B43EA467C96C71DFC8FDE9883"><enum>(D)</enum><text>democracies are being weakened by the asymmetry between open societies and despotic regimes that control their media and online platforms, while waging propaganda wars against democracies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6AA68B9334B469BBB57E207CD1C8339"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to the Committee to Protect Journalists, in 2022—</text><subparagraph id="HD5A9CD44724F482E9FDC46295AC55D8C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least 363 journalists worldwide were in prison, a new record high and a 20 percent increase from the 302 journalists in prison in 2021, with Iran, China, Myanmar, Turkey, and Belarus all ranking among the top 5 jailers of journalists;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49DAD1091F2E41949261A4FBEF3C842A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>of the journalists detained—</text><clause id="H89B80C10EBCD4B19AFAA9BF88D435B6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>131 journalists were detained without charge;</text></clause><clause id="H4B6850BC8E714A61B736C2FD9ADE0509"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>199 journalists were imprisoned on anti-state charges; and</text></clause><clause id="HC78A53EF792D4754838FBBEBC4F913E9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>354 detainees were local journalists covering events in their own countries;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H672FEF09562B4928A6CAB176BDD69730"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at least 67 journalists and media workers were killed, which is the highest number of journalist killings since 2018 and almost a 50 percent increase from the number of journalists killed during 2021;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3A9896323AD40BE909261F91EA25839"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 41 journalists and media workers were killed in direct connection with their work; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF58DDFF2F535461F92E43A1C3107A464"><enum>(E)</enum><text>there was complete impunity in nearly 80 percent of the 263 cases of journalists murdered in the last decade, with perpetrators facing no judicial consequences. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE392D2898244702BE3D5BAC10E26190"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Congress has recognized the importance of freedom of the press by enacting—</text><subparagraph id="H2CE49C817B4C4F31B6C5643F09F175F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Daniel Pearl Freedom of the Press Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/166">Public Law 111–166</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3E0D52EF40E4185B380503CE692AEF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (subtitle F of title XII of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5014454AF78B43F38D537725E852A46B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>S. Res. 501, 115th Congress (recognizing threats to freedom of the press and expression around the world and reaffirming freedom of the press as a priority in efforts of the Government of the United States to promote democracy and good governance).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H265D77B34E3A4649971D29E3D3BBF6A4"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The importance of freedom of the press has been recognized by numerous United States presidential administrations that span ideological and party lines, including—</text><subparagraph id="H17028F569B5544EB80F3D6972B0EAE56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a 1786 letter to James Currie, in which Secretary of State Thomas Jefferson wrote <quote>our liberty depends on the freedom of the press, and that cannot be limited without being lost.</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9AC553A116444BDAEC8BEDBE9B64392"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an address to Congress on February 6, 1986, in which President Ronald Reagan stated, <quote>Victories against poverty are greatest and peace most secure where people live by laws that ensure free press, free speech, and freedom to worship, vote, and create wealth</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8368F26EA8D4E46A21FBE8677542FDE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a statement by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice on April 11, 2007, stating that <quote>there is no more important pillar of democracy than a free and active press</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FF66A776F94457BA494000B266E8CB6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a statement by former Secretary of State Madeline Albright on May 31, 2018, reporting that <quote>Freedom of the press is a basic aspect of democracy, invented by Americans.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1DADC8A607D4C9993FAB0E1DEAFEA9C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a statement by Secretary of State Mike Pompeo on May 3, 2019, stating, <quote>A free and independent media is indispensable to a vibrant, functioning democracy. Despite some progress, journalists around the world continue to be persecuted, targeted with violence, or even killed—all too often with impunity.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9E3AB6B8C804B42801D8EFC193B6192"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Protection of a free and open press is not a partisan issue.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A8687C7006F4B52AED0E94F28CA53CA"><enum>(14)</enum><text>It is imperative that Congress further enshrine the Department of State’s role in protecting international press freedom and those engaged in journalism abroad.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H97C6E5E6BC114A5E92F0BCE6CDA9CFB5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It shall be the policy of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H468257FDC4DA41E5AA13A41B7F04CCCA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to condemn violations of, and attacks on, press freedoms, and threats to the safety of journalists;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D8DD8A507274B89B20D0CF9AEC78E4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to promote, and to assist other governments in the promotion of, the importance of a free and open press;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D97615762CF46FE9DED9E7A66FF7DEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to support press freedom abroad in all aspects of American foreign policy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4ED80D9AFF746BA98B3CD81937B7969"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to work with foreign governments that affirm and protect press freedom—</text><subparagraph id="HDC3D7674CB4F4418BBD5079FF3E7573A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to develop multilateral initiatives to combat suppression of the free and independent press; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE51A5CBDA41D447EB1B62954C331B72E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to promote accountability for individuals, governments, and other actors that violate and attack press freedoms and journalists.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H3EBA8F4B34234105A46156689EA1C345"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office of Press Freedom; Ambassador-at-Large for Press Freedom</header><subsection id="H147C10AF90144511B6611A7180D140E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established, within the Department of State, the Office of Press Freedom (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Office</quote>), which—</text><paragraph id="H913FDC74AF474A3AA8CFEB157457A14F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be situated in the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0B0AA584F52488090803CAF2C94366D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be headed by the Ambassador-at-Large for Press Freedom (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Ambassador</quote>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HABC1494CD6E94F72B84CFCCED25356E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The Ambassador shall be appointed by the President, by and with advice and consent of the Senate, and shall work with the Assistant Secretary of State for Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor to advise the Secretary of State regarding matters related to press freedom.</text></subsection><subsection id="H61372D40610845ECA3B6B9F19D9CFD18"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Ambassador shall have the following duties:</text><paragraph id="HCA36433CD04B43ACB073D42F988A24A9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General responsibilities</header><text>Notwithstanding the active role carried out by local United States Ambassadors in the monitoring of press freedom violations in their host countries, the Ambassador shall have the primary responsibility—</text><subparagraph id="HABFC01AE41084AD68AD1F046731455EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to advance the protection and well-being of members of the United States and foreign press abroad;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H958488BE221B4DC38AC65B4F2FFA2B6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to denounce violations of press freedom or freedom of expression by foreign governments or other actors; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F9913E750CB4558A16D033A1CF7F010"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to engage with foreign governments and press freedom organizations around the world concerning press freedom and freedom of expression. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB138D1853294A87A087F9CEED99F6B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specific tasks</header><text>The Ambassador, with the assistance of the Office and in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of State for Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor, and in fulfillment of the responsibilities described in paragraph (1), shall—</text><subparagraph id="H87D60B2F0B8840D99A1C61719A4E36DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate efforts between relevant United States embassy personnel and press organizations or threatened individuals in situations in which freedom of the press is threatened abroad;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33A3DB466EB447EABB64807B9A60D6D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publicly and privately denounce oppression of the press abroad;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B22C501F31545EB8886E7F1BED8F942"><enum>(C)</enum><text>represent the United States in issues concerning press freedom in diplomatic engagement with foreign governments, intergovernmental organizations, the United Nations, and other international organizations in which the United States is a member;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B8BCDA6691044E09F3C683EFFEE84F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommend appropriate responses by the United States Government when press freedoms are infringed upon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A380CA6C6534E829910F64B2A235A0A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provide Congress and the public with a regular report describing the successes and enduring challenges of the Office, based on metrics that the Office shall develop.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10ED7FB05EDD441198E54C18DBA63646"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advisory role</header><text>The Ambassador—</text><subparagraph id="H4523F01EEFE34E28A5366A76015FC3D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be a principal advisor to the President and to the Secretary of State regarding matters affecting press freedom abroad; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B25C46FC4CC46599A8B8CB00C4AC45C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall make recommendations regarding the policies of the United States Government towards governments or other organizations or individuals that—</text><clause id="H41BB0B0DC8DE4BFC9EADF716BC11BB0D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>violate press freedoms; or</text></clause><clause id="HE3175CCF2F4140A28022D0333A0CFD14"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fail to ensure the protection of members of the press.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE07FF470836D42CF874E9A7EE4CFA4B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reporting responsibilities</header><text>The Ambassador shall—</text><subparagraph id="H498FA9ABD7F14F5E88A826304775B3C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>work with the staff of the Office to ensure the success of the Office in carrying out its mission—</text><clause id="H11E3C32C0AAD4976AEE24E192BA9F281"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to promote press freedom abroad; and </text></clause><clause id="HD6387B4DBBEC4B2A8C8170872B1D244D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to protect members of the press in foreign countries;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED22B6A475884FC69DB34AC89C567C67"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after being appointed, ensure that there is a reasonable process for measuring the efficacy of the Office in carrying out the missions described in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA814F7E01CC43B1B0E967EECB3C0F59"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not later than 18 months after being appointed, and annually thereafter—</text><clause id="H54480AE88E324C349DBC7E49FC5EF40A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit a report to Congress that describes—</text><subclause id="HD5D81950290440DCB74B6AE7080756D9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the outcomes of the activities of the Office based on the process established pursuant to subparagraph (B); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7962312F3766427F9FA226A0D5AAC78B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the efforts of the National Foreign Affairs Training Center to train Foreign Service Officers about press freedom in accordance with section 5; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H505F1F81B8794AA7916FDF0C3F9E2A28"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>make a copy of the report submitted pursuant to clause (i) available to the public; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DE4EE1EF9C8401EABBA5A558F2728EE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>oversee the <quote>Freedom of Expression</quote> section of each country reviewed in the annual Country Report on Human Rights Practices. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF68347B21BAF4C2189B2E6DBAB6BDA74"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>The Secretary of State shall provide the Ambassador with sufficient funds—</text><subparagraph id="HB9DB92C76E8A4B2C9D8320989EC67F84"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to hire the staff for the Office to enable the Office to carry out the tasks and responsibilities described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H787CC58409B64EF08A0CC2AF3AFADEA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to comply with the reporting requirements described in paragraph (4); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76C2B7FBFA394135B6BF50BF0757C5FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for necessary travel to carry out this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDE7FBDA5AECD4C99A75EC20F288F22C5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Press freedom curriculum</header><subsection id="HF33E02F38F0C4AF2AA8595AE748535E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development</header><text>The Secretary of State shall ensure that there is a press freedom curriculum for the National Foreign Affairs Training Center that enables Foreign Service Officers to better understand issues of press freedom and the tools that are available to help protect journalists and promote freedom of the press norms, including—</text><paragraph id="H35CF7A70229442F588AD3F20E11F26C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the historic and current issues facing press freedom, including countries of specific concern;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H806CF06C19A840DA9661876F38742220"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Department of State’s role in promoting press freedom as an American value, a human rights issue, and a national security imperative;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55DAB541D37548D59DE2B2811641C157"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ways to incorporate press freedom promotion into other aspects of diplomacy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC96CF1D8FC254A19AC54732CF9FA1D33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>existing tools to assist journalists in distress and methods for engaging foreign governments and institutions on behalf of individuals engaged in journalistic activity who are at risk of harm. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BC27F23838E4C89844067163554FB1B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required study</header><text>Any Foreign Service Officer who is assigned to function as a Public Diplomacy Officer, a Political Officer, or a Consular Officer at an overseas mission shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF16900F987D445F297030DB4AD15A547"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complete the study of the curriculum described in subsection (a) not later than 90 days after the first day of such assignment; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0051982784EF4AC2A4D11706140B2A9B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">benefit from knowledge sharing by civil society actors who are at the forefront of the defense and promotion of the freedom of information.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H402174FE21424A6E9435F88333C78C4D"><enum>6.</enum><header>GAO study on the Daniel Pearl Freedom of the Press Act of 2009</header><subsection commented="no" id="HF87A10C9C47D4316A243055A64E88BEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall evaluate the implementation of the Daniel Pearl Freedom of the Press Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/166">Public Law 111–166</external-xref>) by reviewing the Department of State’s Country Reports on Human Rights Practices, prepared in select years and for select countries, to examine—</text><paragraph id="H9A94EADF2A23499D80D09EEEE8A52541"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the process used by the Department for preparing information regarding the freedom of the press for such reports and the extent to which such process changed after the date of the enactment of such Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06CAF7DCE6024B5DA4403753E4C70539"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which the Department of State followed the process referred to in paragraph (1) in preparing information regarding freedom of the press that was included in its most recently published Country Reports on Human Rights Practices;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCE0E750AE89470C8E2922E04C0AF2DC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any challenges encountered by the Department of State in collecting, corroborating, and reporting the information described in sections 116(d)(12) and 502B(i) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151n">22 U.S.C. 2151n(d)(12)</external-xref> and 2304(i)), as added by the Daniel Pearl Freedom of the Press Act of 2009; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88048CEB201E40CCA8FEA4EB8C67FC13"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the extent to which the Department of State measures the impact of its reports on freedom of the press on foreign governments’ behaviors or practices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE16F1F8132304789A53555F878CF6681"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit a report to Congress and to the Secretary of State that—</text><paragraph id="H95C9330DE7494D63BCE2857F9FA599ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>summarizes the results of the study required under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C9F443F13AA4AE4869CB1A278FAD779"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides recommendations for any legislative or regulatory action that would improve the efforts of the Department of State to report on issues of press freedom abroad. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

