<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6FB7B1D3B09D44F59ECA8FE6FF8311F8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6875 IH: United States-Uruguay Economic Partnership Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6875</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Caribbean Basin Economic Recovery Act to make Uruguay eligible for designation as a beneficiary country under that Act, to include Uruguay in the list of foreign states whose nationals are eligible for admission into the United States as E1 and E2 nonimmigrants if nationals of the United States are treated similarly by the Government of Uruguay, and to require a report on the eligibility of Uruguay for the visa waiver program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H64B45A4510DC442CA895AABF975387A0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H96BC5E16F3534902BBB2D81892311CF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Uruguay Economic Partnership Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H6F2DFA655B08409BBC60E9117704BAB5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eligibility of Uruguay for designation as a beneficiary country under Caribbean Basin Economic Recovery Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 212(b) of the Caribbean Basin Economic Recovery Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/2702">19 U.S.C. 2702(b)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>Turks and Caicos Islands</quote> the following new item: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9006753AA89E4B66B79BE2E0C493C932"> 
<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">Uruguay</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HD6F18EA278144205838BADE76574EFAA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Nonimmigrant traders and investors</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of clauses (i) and (ii) of section 101(a)(15)(E) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(15)(E)</external-xref>), Uruguay shall be considered to be a foreign state described in such section if the Government of Uruguay provides similar nonimmigrant status to nationals of the United States. </text></section> <section id="H7515F60B543742EC93D502A6919D8ADD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Visa waiver program eligibility</header> <subsection id="H786B07038E9B465AAF01C982F3DD9E66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Secretary of State, should conduct a review as to whether Uruguay meets the eligibility criteria for designation as a program country for purposes of the visa waiver program under section 217 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1187">8 U.S.C. 1187</external-xref>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE6645A6AACCF45F8A216222922DB59E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Visa waiver program eligibility</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall submit to Congress a report that includes—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A99AB0752A34636B0DCCDF82290C000"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment as to whether Uruguay meets the eligibility criteria for designation as a program country for purposes of the visa waiver program under section 217 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1187">8 U.S.C. 1187</external-xref>); and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB734CBC9B29D4885B8ABF40B3F2F94CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of such an assessment that Uruguay does not meet such eligibility criteria, a description of the actions required of Uruguay in order to meet such criteria. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

