<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H36286DF660E54062AADF5AB366CB7FA4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3759 IH: Barriers to Suicide Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3759</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. C&#225;rdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish a grant program to facilitate the installation, on bridges, of evidence-based suicide deterrents, including suicide prevention nets and barriers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H785F2320875A4BE08C1DEEB52448C727" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0CADF8219E714032A5FF95CF066D937F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Barriers to Suicide Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H56696CA0EF68426D9BA69A99DE438B0C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program</header> <subsection id="HFC324A6EE14D4BAD86EA7F3E2344A08E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall establish a program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to facilitate the installation of evidence-based suicide deterrents on bridges, including suicide prevention nets and barriers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6D552C96CF7E43CA81977B95021EED39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text>In carrying out the Program, the Secretary may make grants on a competitive basis in accordance with this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8E4A3EC0303E4C63897641272878F933"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible recipients</header><text>The Secretary may make a grant under the Program to a State or a political subdivision of a State.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF22C505BF1124B79B9F5E0B1E1DFF044"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under the Program, an entity described in subsection (c) shall submit to the Secretary an application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H223128966F984218A64E3F365E357318"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may make a grant under the Program only for a project that facilitates the installation on a bridge of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4BF02030543349FD99D4A17B40473220"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a suicide prevention net; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H488E5CB6B4A348B392A351E49700C7E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a suicide prevention barrier; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H08692899D41F4C66B5C661254D3787B1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other evidence-based suicide deterrent that is determined by the Secretary to be appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H560DCA35720849B08C958D25CD8E0C13"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making a grant under the Program, the Secretary shall give priority to a project located in an area with a high rate of suicide, taking into consideration the number of suicides and rate of suicides per capita in an area, or other priority characteristics, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1680F6DB016A4BEB80AF4C04B1A48209"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal share of the cost of a project assisted with a grant under the Program may not exceed 80 percent.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5B44A2DB0303409F9E5387F22FD8A58B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H14B5115AD9A7427F80EA103F43D72043"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD57146241AB44794942ECB5C9E44B015"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evidence-based suicide deterrent</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based suicide deterrent</term> means a suicide deterrent that demonstrates a rationale based on high-quality research findings or positive evaluation that such deterrent is likely to reduce or prevent suicide, and includes ongoing efforts to examine the effects of such deterrent. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD4F0DB79C37D437F942465BE5EE2396F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the Program $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H861F3E71235B4DDD99188B8E85CFAC72" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Title 23 amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 119(d)(2)(I) of title 23, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>Highway System.</quote> and adding <quote>Highway System, including installation of safety barriers and nets on bridges of the National Highway System.</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H0348C253D5DF4B2485B1634B75DA6DD7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Study on effectiveness of suicide prevention nets and barriers for structures other than bridges</header> 
<subsection id="H9BCCF3F1A9444ACB813ECA30B7A4AFE0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study to identify—</text> <paragraph id="HB07BC435BF254F418A77C41D34981B82"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the types of structures, other than bridges, that attract a high number of individuals attempting suicide-by-jumping;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9934D9A168AF4D87B0B84384AB4EC396"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the characteristics that distinguish structures identified under paragraph (1) from similar structures that do not attract a high number of individuals attempting suicide-by-jumping;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H88380B1B9F0C4BDBADAEE78E95F38005" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the types of nets or barriers that are effective at reducing suicide-by-jumping with respect to the structures identified under paragraph (1);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31BD9F9E8C244E47A98D8202E01D8303"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">methods of reducing suicide-by-jumping with respect to the structures identified under paragraph (1) other than nets and barriers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HACA50B7BD6464D26BD63EAC912D3C101"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">quantitative measures of the effectiveness of the nets and barriers identified under paragraph (3);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H432AEA3A07F24978A592FD88FBF44167"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">quantitative measures of the effectiveness of the additional methods identified under paragraph (4); </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C36518C96F34637A3078DAE947AF42A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the entities that typically install the nets and barriers identified under paragraph (3); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H16D8B96F16D1492694B4DE59B99A5FE8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the costs of the nets and barriers identified under paragraph (3). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBD0DA09FE73D49D48EAFF2B33CAF234A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the results of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

