<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H97F85796B11349F891417F89D6D422B5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3799 RH: Custom Health Option and Individual Care Expense Arrangement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 83</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3799</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–107]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230605">June 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on June 5, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide for health reimbursement arrangements integrated with individual health insurance coverage.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HWM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HF1543D4D3BB044D1910C4897102AF46B"><section id="H1C724D5B919D4E59940063696C128D02" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Custom Health Option and Individual Care Expense Arrangement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CHOICE Arrangement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H99A9ED270BD94BE0AC968AEC3B6EC2DE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of health reimbursement arrangements integrated with individual market coverage</header><subsection id="H6A35D8E06E994D8DAA24C99D28CB1887"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/9815">Section 9815(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8D9A1EC7DDBD4DDDBE1ED5CF492A430D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Exception.—</header-in-text>Notwithstanding subsection (a)</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE6B08A448E2A44C485594D490D7A5FAE" display-inline="yes-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><text><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Exceptions.—</header-in-text></text><paragraph id="H259E190C4F48463D8C9730D0D507890B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Self-insured group health plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (a)</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H313891695FD84B9288E355A9970F8211"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H47101A9CD5E24041B0BB2B1023DB75CC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><paragraph id="H0090098748BA41D7A910346EDD3F5AC7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Custom health option and individual care expense arrangements</header><subparagraph id="H4945B9704482492A80995384A4B26F57"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subchapter, a custom health option and individual care expense arrangement shall be treated as meeting the requirements of section 2711 and 2713 of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8F7BD3BA512494D82B56DAAE5D8278F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Custom health option and individual care expense arrangements defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>custom health option and individual care expense arrangement</quote> means a health reimbursement arrangement—</text><clause id="HD43D2476394F4EDEBC9BA6FB61AC928E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which is an employer-provided group health plan funded solely by employer contributions to provide payments or reimbursements for medical care subject to a maximum fixed dollar amount for a period,</text></clause><clause id="H76D81BA9962144C4A117FFB06938907F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under which such payments or reimbursements may only be made for medical care provided during periods during which the individual is covered—</text><subclause id="H2804ECD2E459418E9E40F3F7296E6413"><enum>(I)</enum><text>under individual health insurance coverage (other than coverage that consists solely of excepted benefits), or</text></subclause><subclause id="H609688E658AE43FC9893CFA7431769B7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>under part A and B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act or part C of such title,</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF743B07D46D34FA28F21EB8403F557EC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>which meets the nondiscrimination requirements of subparagraph (C),</text></clause><clause id="H8A9EEC9A86614A33BD5C22EF361A4C30" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>which meets the substantiation requirements of subparagraph (D), and</text></clause><clause id="HA3FF8BD2F6994549881BB806136A6437"><enum>(v)</enum><text>which meets the notice requirements of subparagraph (E).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8AAE6E2E3E747BC8B6D215D4EB60ABD"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><clause id="H3CBD791E8CC544888210B2B9E63421A7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An arrangement meets the requirements of this subparagraph if an employer offering such arrangement to an employee within a specified class of employee—</text><subclause id="HF254591D688F4ABD8137272A0D1CBD5C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>offers such arrangement to all employees within such specified class on the same terms, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6E21C07C5F9C47CDBA91736E18EE3AF6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>does not offer any other group health plan to any employees within such specified class.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8B64646AD56C4A6DB70938691D2B4418"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Specified class of employee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, any of the following may be designated as a specified class of employee:</text><subclause id="HDBB53271707E49B8B12E996095EF995D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Full-time employees.</text></subclause><subclause id="H8BBA876A80A946D18D52425CA84FB41B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Part-time employees.</text></subclause><subclause id="HE834FDA520234D24BFF0D8EFEC7926A3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Salaried employees.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC534FA89D3A145C298FD4A49BFE50138"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Non-salaried employees.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB3D7FF78FB544D7F831F5A1A8364B1D7"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Employees whose primary site of employment is in the same rating area.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6DB1788B37BB439B8E331776375DBEEC"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Employees who are included in a unit of employees covered under a collective bargaining agreement to which the employer is subject (determined under rules similar to the rules of section 105(h)).</text></subclause><subclause id="H791D93C8F57A4AE28879AC098B69CDA5"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Employees who have not met a group health plan, or health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage, waiting period requirement that satisfies the of section 2708 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subclause><subclause id="H44645E6B62F54F4A880A8DFD1C1286DE" commented="no"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Seasonal employees.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6738617BDF184A7F9A8D0344D2CE143D"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Employees who are nonresident aliens and who receive no earned income (within the meaning of section 911(d)(2)) from the employer which constitutes income from sources within the United States (within the meaning of section 861(a)(3)).</text></subclause><subclause id="H0C6A236127B1413D9597EBF086568150"><enum>(X)</enum><text>Such other classes of employees as the Secretary may designate.</text></subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">An employer may designate (in such manner as is prescribed by the Secretary) two or more of the classes described in the preceding subclauses as the specified class of employees to which the arrangement is offered for purposes of applying this subparagraph.</continuation-text></clause><clause id="HB0CD2C69EA8A4F5A9CD2B984F6EE2A44"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Special rule for new hires</header><text>An employer may designate prospectively so much of a specified class of employees as are hired after a date set by the employer. Such subclass of employees shall be treated as the specified class for purposes of applying clause (i).</text></clause><clause id="H7F922AD304B84AD3B58D7618ADC3A5A0" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Rules for determining type of employee</header><text>For purposes for clause (ii), any determination of full-time, part-time, or seasonal employment status shall be made under rules similar to the rules of section 105(h) or 4980H, whichever the employer elects for the plan year. Such election shall apply with respect to all employees of the employer for the plan year.</text></clause><clause id="H1CA47545309B4CD6A3B7C1FCB4BD4AE2"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Permitted variation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of clause (i)(I), an arrangement shall not fail to be treated as provided on the same terms within a specified class merely because the maximum dollar amount of payments and reimbursements which may be made under the terms of the arrangement for the year with respect to each employee within such class—</text><subclause id="H7058D42381B84B23AE47F8AB21A6A444"><enum>(I)</enum><text>increases as additional dependents of the employee are covered under the arrangement, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H613C7BB5EC374297B6577A06809C0607"><enum>(II)</enum><text>increases with respect to a participant as the age of the participant increases, but not in excess of an amount equal to 300 percent the lowest maximum dollar amount with respect to such a participant determined without regard to age.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90BD356BB0284A0DB2D69C632D4ACE61" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Substantiation requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An arrangement meets the requirements of this subparagraph if the arrangement has reasonable procedures to substantiate—</text><clause id="H7C62D56044894685AA89E7D0467E0655" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that the participant is, or will be, enrolled in coverage described in subparagraph (B)(ii) as of the beginning of the plan year of the arrangement (or as of the beginning of coverage under the arrangement in the case of an employee who first becomes eligible to participate in the arrangement after the date notice is given with respect to the plan under subparagraph (E) (determined without regard to clause (iii) thereof), and</text></clause><clause id="H74FBFAF56A4C47C9836B1E92B187EA7B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any requests made for payment or reimbursement of medical care under the arrangement and that the participant remains so enrolled.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92AB546575E04CEB80AC63B0276ACA77"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Notice</header><clause id="H745D7465DC4A4D9A8A57E62373264577"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in clause (iii), an arrangement meets the requirements of this subparagraph if, under the arrangement, each employee eligible to participate is, not later than 90 days before the beginning of the plan year, given written notice of the employee’s rights and obligations under the arrangement which—</text><subclause id="HEA3C914AF6554A41B1180A5612FB72F8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is sufficiently accurate and comprehensive to appraise the employee of such rights and obligations, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H5CE2B1A82A77411F81B513D386F2A7C1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is written in a manner calculated to be understood by the average employee eligible to participate.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA437DE44CD3E4BB3A204D3F547E1AF7D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notice requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such notice shall include such information as the Secretary may by regulation prescribe.</text></clause><clause id="HBBB5823A2367471A8FA76B9D45EE5C99"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Notice deadline for certain employees</header><text>In the case of an employee—</text><subclause id="HF8A4C846E13D466EAFC80B86ACAAB183"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who first becomes eligible to participate in the arrangement after the date notice is given with respect to the plan under clause (i) (determined without regard to this clause), or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA9593D76D1424266BD6AE781AE56322A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>whose employer is first established fewer than 120 days before the beginning of the first plan year of the arrangement,</text></subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">the requirements of this subparagraph shall be treated as met if the notice required under clause (i) is provided not later than the date the arrangement may take effect with respect to such employee.</continuation-text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA7FB60B8F9BC4EB382AD17AC541BFE30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No inference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent not inconsistent with the amendments made by this section—</text><paragraph id="HF0DDD620F7BB488B8EC18F81BD3106CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no inference shall be made from such amendments with respect to the rules prescribed in the Federal Register on June 20, 2019, (84 Fed. Reg. 28888) relating to health reimbursement arrangements and other account-based group health plans, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62AD3C0601774C49984242806539EEC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any reference to custom health option and individual care expense arrangements shall for purposes of such rules be treated as including a reference to individual coverage health reimbursement arrangements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD8E5E1A921FD422A945F6B5AE5EA4EE5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to plan years beginning after December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

