<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEF9A42B782C9458EA888CD07B4B58C1A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6346 IH: Advancing Nuclear Regulatory Oversight Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6346</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To update oversight and inspection practices of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H904A6C033EBF46EFAADFAFE1073AA827" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA43BB501FE6444DABE152A6DB1E3F101" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing Nuclear Regulatory Oversight Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDBADA17128C34BBBA01586F7DE4372C4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Implementing lessons learned from the COVID–19 health emergency</header> <subsection id="H89706F387E0A40C0AD24496F071115C3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on actions taken by the Commission during the public health emergency declared by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>) on January 31, 2020, with respect to COVID–19.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H06C869A74ED64B449FACC858F3E186F9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H67F520C7FEB24B188C4402B482853191"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify any processes, procedures, and other regulatory policies that the Commission revised or temporarily suspended during the public health emergency described in subsection (a);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A4ABC595B914BA99A47E9276FD9EAFE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">examine how any revision or temporary suspension of a process, procedure, or other regulatory policy identified under paragraph (1) affected the ability of the Commission to license and regulate the civilian use of radioactive materials in the United States to protect public health and safety, promote the common defense and security, and protect the environment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09B9C964ECD1449DB04BEEF3E7C43994"><enum>(3)</enum><text>discuss lessons learned from the matters described in paragraph (2);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72AAE16F6D0948F38FF5B05D61290981"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">list actions that the Commission has taken or will take to incorporate into the licensing and oversight activities of the Commission, without compromising the mission of the Commission, the lessons described in paragraph (3); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H159490A600994AAD8CC2CE7915F5E9CC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>describe when the actions listed under paragraph (4) were implemented or may be implemented.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4729227AD0AE4CCA89E05CD3F267155F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Advancing efficient, risk-informed oversight and inspections</header> 
<subsection id="H891488B7514D4E0897425B6A44AA6745" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall develop and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that identifies specific improvements to the nuclear reactor and materials oversight and inspection programs carried out pursuant to the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 that the Commission may implement to maximize the efficiency of such programs through, where appropriate, the use of risk-informed, performance-based procedures, expanded incorporation of information technologies, and staff training.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3020531083B44CF8AEC09B9FAAAA74E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Stakeholder input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the report under subsection (a), the Commission shall, as appropriate, seek input from—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE6D72540C0144CE39333C7547DF1000F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H769FC7EF668E4CE68A15F3E6C84C6EED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the National Laboratories;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F7C7276E1494071B48E939F96696DD4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the nuclear energy industry; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H96484070C96F4E1D8383E59988A4FE8B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>nongovernmental organizations that are related to nuclear energy.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H532FF73A1C9C4B9C8DCA9D9EE5756EA3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H41558760768E4F73BC6A1AF21B7E0212" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assess specific elements of oversight and inspections that may be modified by the use of technology, improved planning, and continually updated risk-informed, performance-based assessment, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5A5E0DA9E83A4549A5A54752DD9BBC6E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>use of travel resources;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA71E77A29B4E4771847710B83F09F13D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>planning and preparation for inspections, including entrance and exit meetings with licensees and consideration of whether inspection teams need to be onsite;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H468301B652794A1DB033753B5D4C6DB7" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>document collection and preparation, including consideration of whether nuclear reactor data are accessible without onsite visits or requests to the licensee and that document requests are timely and within the scope of inspections;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85078BB1F205433DB2485BEA9A252725"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the cross-cutting issues program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H69593EC1A24F4A8D8FA546E0CF2E26F4" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the scope of event reporting required by licensees to ensure decisions are risk-informed;</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HB03D602E20FB4419AEA04E3D10983253" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and assess measures to improve oversight and inspections, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H57D3483C13094311A6CEE1B4D733C53A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>elimination of areas of duplicative or otherwise unnecessary activities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H10EB7A7EEDD64A4D8C5020A12F6D7D71" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increased use of templates in documenting inspection results; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H610F6805C4E74707AAEA397FA1B0123F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>periodic training of Commission staff and leadership on the application of risk-informed criteria for—</text> <clause id="H4AABDEADED9643619FB8ADAECDEBCBD9" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inspection planning and assessments; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H78ED47FE03344C5F8E7123E4E39667F9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>agency decision making processes on the application of regulations and guidance; and</text></clause> <clause id="H8FAE9CC3383044CB83AD5878135FB4E6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the application of the Commission’s standard of reasonable assurance of adequate protection;</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H458F1EA24BF847788127E7BD582DB470" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess measures to advance risk-informed procedures, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HB69FA2CCB8AB46D7B0A148E95AAF107D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increased use of inspection approaches that balance the level of resources commensurate with safety significance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H65B4E1523C1D4D318E0AAEBAE9C42DE1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increased review of the use of inspection program resources based on licensee performance; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF06B13BEC954F88AC247E27052D4CA8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>expansion of modern information technology, including artificial intelligence and machine learning to risk inform oversight and inspection decisions; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF5F5FF7FB1D14F75AB71BF586181F34E" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">updating the Differing Professional Views or Opinions process to include—</text> <clause id="H950DBA0D3BD045B9BE624E7A37BC1AEA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>safety significance as a threshold for entering such process; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4085A2A9FEEB4DDE8C4E460684848E8C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>guidance for issue resolution to minimize the impact of such process on project schedules;</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3B716029E5745F58A261D4F839D75A0" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess the ability of the Commission, consistent with its obligations to provide reasonable assurance of adequate protection of health and safety pursuant to the Atomic Energy Act of 1954, to enable licensee innovations that may advance nuclear reactor operational efficiency and safety, including the criteria of the Commission for timely acceptance of licensee adoption of advanced technologies, including digital technologies;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE5A22BE10EE4B679F7E5A14484B95F0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify recommendations resulting from the assessments described in paragraphs (1) through (4);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C17E9E1D10B47748B996E1A2414FF2E" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify specific actions that the Commission will take to incorporate into the training, inspection, oversight, and licensing activities, and regulations of the Commission, without compromising the mission of the Commission, the recommendations identified under paragraph (5); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7D212AD5F204D129ED3392B7E6A5C0F"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe when the actions identified under paragraph (6) may be implemented.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H8B0BB5A39DB9483DB63EEFBAF571C536"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office and facility space review</header> <subsection id="H4DBC31129BE04FB3A607335797CEA5CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF01001A6419248F884A489990F64A399"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review office and other facility space requirements of the Commission; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67617C99AD6747C0BCFC81DB1AC6AEBB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report, with recommendations, on the results of such review.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDBD77AABDFC2422ABB03164853973CD5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report described in subsection (a) shall include—</text> <paragraph id="HC3AFDE45C89347C5846964EAA22FEB73"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an examination of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H37CCF02BB5444CFC9E70D9576B9479B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the costs associated with the headquarters, regional offices, and technical training center of the Commission, including examination of—</text> <clause id="H5619B8CF00CF47E7A20E4090D0C3617A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>costs that do not support the Commission’s mission, including rent subsidies for other Federal agencies; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H58ABEC6D24BD4FEE8234F6D6E85A7D82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>opportunities to reduce future costs through reduction in unnecessary office space, consolidation of offices, use of advanced information technology, or any other appropriate means; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDED183939AC8401FAFF34E60C7A3CA3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current and anticipated office and facility requirements to efficiently accomplish the mission of the Commission; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A56A868B2FB4CBD8EB8AB995D60C986"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations to Congress, the Commission, and the General Services Administration for actions that may assist in reducing office and facility costs to licensees and taxpayers.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HC019249CF0CC4F08A0BD4C87DFD4CE57"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFEF0DF7EE5284107AEB570D738A59AA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7D68A99C96D44CBA54A06FC62B7EC74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the Nuclear Regulatory Commission.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD4BA058CEE1A42A78CB23DA731B97A9E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Licensee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>licensee</term> means a person that holds a license issued under section 103 or section 104 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2133">42 U.S.C. 2133</external-xref>; 2134).</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

