<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD48906819314C5DBA9ED138A2E219DF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1616 IH: Comprehensive Access to Resources and Education for Long COVID Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1616</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To address research on, and improve access to, supportive services for individuals with Long COVID.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA94BED92F5854F6C83B472AD6296EA88" style="OLC"><section id="HB65A6987D5EC4E2E98418D4B4E9EDA86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Access to Resources and Education for Long COVID Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CARE for Long COVID Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9B0E8D8CFEC44CAC902786736C02260E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization to fund a patient registry for research on Long COVID and related conditions</header><subsection id="H099B9FF6986D4033B8A4EDA3293421C3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), acting in coordination with the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute established under section 1181 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320e">42 U.S.C. 1320e(b)</external-xref>), shall fund activities described in subsection (b) to improve treatment and outcomes for individuals with Long COVID and related conditions.</text></subsection><subsection id="H47258EF78E7D4E039F41F770CF0D093B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities described</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a), activities described in this subsection shall include—</text><paragraph id="HC7EBEE3E348B4250831DAD762B1106E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>creating or maintaining a regularly updated patient registry of individuals with suspected or confirmed Long COVID and related conditions, including information on—</text><subparagraph id="HF5AD4A1A3A5041CBBEC070F363392607"><enum>(A)</enum><text>symptoms that arise while an individual is initially infected with COVID–19 and that may resolve over time or extend beyond the resolution of the initial symptoms;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D4CE18A55544AFB8B53B9619A4B7436"><enum>(B)</enum><text>persistent symptoms that arise after an individual is initially infected with COVID–19 and that the clinician of such individual has reason to suspect were related to the COVID–19 diagnosis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC58F41A81AE243A78AB57CD5E02EFFEF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>symptoms that arise in an individual that may be related to COVID–19, but a diagnosis of COVID–19 was not obtained and cannot be identified due to a lack of antibodies, false negative test results, or lack of access to timely testing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE17E7C5B920546C1AD6971ACD77C1ADB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>treatments of individuals after primary diagnosis of COVID–19 and the effectiveness of such treatments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2481480D93B04A9C82487B0932B8CCB9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other relevant questions or issues related to individuals who experience a diagnosis of, treatment for, and management of care with COVID–19, Long COVID, and related conditions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E36F86DA3E8445E839C7CA1EA060EBB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>comorbidities, vaccination status, and demographics, including age, gender, race and ethnicity, geographic location, disability, and occupation of registry participants;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H906341E55B1B48D7B4226D55A4B6D5B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>synthesis of information relating to individuals experiencing Long COVID and related conditions and other information available through the patient registry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD908B7C59C53430B83F3C3E17C453D36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>dissemination of information to relevant Federal departments and agencies and patients participating in the registry to inform treatment and policy related to COVID–19, Long COVID, and related conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56E081B626944327B77949FB3DF890DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assurance that the registry utilizes common data elements and definitions for use in order to promote appropriate data sharing for ongoing and future research; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB05678E94924303A4DCD19CC97B85C4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>outreach to, and inclusion in the patient registry, as appropriate, of individuals, including children and older adults, from communities impacted by high COVID–19 and Long COVID rates, communities affected by health disparities and inequities (including Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations, urban Indian organizations, and people with disabilities), individuals with related conditions, health care providers, first responders, military service members, veterans, pregnant and lactating women, frontline workers who may be impacted by high COVID–19 and Long COVID rates, and health care providers from diverse disciplines that may treat individuals with COVID–19, Long COVID, and related conditions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H67F8073AFA57427295AA583DF97C60AB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Voluntary participation; privacy protections</header><paragraph id="H264537B11AF84567BAECF06B2A21FC62"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voluntary participation</header><text>Participation in the registry described in subsection (b)(1) shall be voluntary, and a person creating, assisting in the creation of, or maintaining the registry shall not include in the registry information about an individual unless the individual consents to the inclusion of such information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63632F234DB946C692A10BCD4A34D94B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privacy protections</header><text>Information about an individual that is included in the registry shall be subject to all applicable privacy protections under Federal and State law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1470D1073DC84DC4BA02F3F2A58B4952"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the establishment of the synthesized patient registry under subsection (b)(2), and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit a report that includes data, findings, and information with respect to the status of the patient registry (including progress, barriers, and issues) to Congress and the President.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAF535FE8D09D4C3691661AA1F9D43676"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $30,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE5F37B2197D840088EC4F86D4A871A76"><enum>3.</enum><header>Research on United States health care system’s response to Long COVID</header><subsection id="H5C30FFC4B5FF4BE2B348933EE0A105EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in coordination with the Director of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, the Director of the National Institutes of Health, and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall conduct or support research related to the United States health care system’s response to Long COVID, including with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H3D70040AC84849C38C88B353C13ED788"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the expansion and effectiveness of post-infectious disease treatment, including—</text><subparagraph id="HA7B76DC4DC9143B989D2285374F1F808"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying barriers to access for treatment of COVID–19, Long COVID, and related conditions for veterans, older adults, people with disabilities, children and young adults, communities of color, underserved and rural communities, and other groups impacted by high rates of COVID–19, as determined by the Secretary;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H795BE8290D524EE4A3BC4329BD880974"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evaluating and identifying potential gaps or other weaknesses that contribute to age, gender, geographic location, disability, occupation, and racial and ethnic disparities with respect to COVID–19 infection rates, severity and length of symptoms, associated diagnoses, and outcomes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H658B1980EC54448DABF2B4643A0600F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identifying trends associated with differences in diagnosis and treatment of Long COVID and related conditions by demographic factors such as age, gender, geographic location, disability, occupation, race, ethnicity, or other factors identified by the Secretary to promote health equity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7335E8641794DD9BEF45670D0257CF8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conducting and supporting research to—</text><subparagraph id="HC86A267CDC48496B87E98F163067E5C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify health care strategies that help mitigate age, gender, geographic location, disability, occupation, and racial and ethnic disparities in COVID–19 infection rates, hospitalizations, severity and length of symptoms, secondary illnesses, and outcomes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CB1342A6F28400291B8FC1249531AC7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify health care-related factors contributing to such disparities in COVID–19 infection rates, hospitalizations, severity and length of symptoms, secondary illnesses, and outcomes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42DBA0F68E91413AA404471F70EED940"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide recommendations on ensuring equity in diagnosis and access to quality post-infectious treatments that may be advanced to mitigate such disparities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB0B6BD037E646129A8EF779DC8A5FF6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><section id="H14425DA78BBA42FBB29B0E18A2C0A5D1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Education and dissemination of information on Long COVID</header><subsection id="HD2705CE150A64942A1416CBEC1855A62"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Long COVID public education program</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and disseminate to the public regularly updated information regarding Long COVID, in plain language and in a manner that is culturally and linguistically appropriate and easily accessible to people with disabilities and people with limited English proficiency, including information on—</text><paragraph id="H54EF88E8D61E48F5AD152EC28F0B6B8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the awareness, incidence, and short- and long-term health effects associated with COVID–19 infection, including Long COVID associated disability;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09E775AA869C4B2B8BF9D1787DADB058"><enum>(2)</enum><text>illnesses related and often comorbid with Long COVID, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H2F9BD8968594460DB87D749A0AA03809"><enum>(A)</enum><text>myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB175885A28444489A12FDBA697F5E8E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fibromyalgia;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4788F2BD051449E93F3E3D01AB7280E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome and other forms of dysautonomia;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H250E0F5B679F43B1B8BD51D5EF3AD2BF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>autoimmune diseases associated with viral triggers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC199FDF2BB5421AB8AD5B068F3AC4D2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>connective tissue diseases exacerbated or triggered by infections;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB14EC42BC36D424CB5FC40A35259991F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>mast cell activation syndrome;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67FABD1ECE344F5681666F08AF8F0E1A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>related conditions and illnesses that may affect adults, young adults, or children; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76C730DE707B4178B9FD107A5B0DEA20"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other conditions, as the Secretary determines appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H38EAFDAD365A4A89AA75A84AE167A0A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the availability, as medically appropriate, of treatment options for Long COVID and related conditions overlapping with Long COVID identified under paragraph (2); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01064C79E67449DCA3FD7C344E83BD8D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>strategies for reducing the likelihood of developing Long COVID.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B715A70FC03413E8C27B1682D2D9699"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Long COVID provider education program</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with representatives from impacted communities and health care providers who treat such communities or individuals, shall develop and disseminate to health care providers, including by developing or improving continuing medical education programs that advance the education of such providers, information on Long COVID, recommended assessment tools, including how to assess patients’ functional capacity to support applications for disability benefits, and management of Long COVID and related conditions for the purpose of ensuring that health care providers remain informed about current information on Long COVID and related conditions, including information on—</text><paragraph id="H6EAB2413435F4B5091D0B1D95B638ACB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Long COVID symptoms such as cognitive, neurological, psychiatric, gastrointestinal, respiratory, and cardiovascular symptoms;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7D2BEBF0CD54C378D9B9C680258B07D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome and fibromyalgia;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC6C093BCD1C411E8E67412DEE0C216A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome and other forms of dysautonomia;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32E843BAB3A7402BB1BCFB490C069235"><enum>(4)</enum><text>autoimmune diseases associated with viral triggers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H496F0DFEF04B41F8BCEEC593E888AD35"><enum>(5)</enum><text>connective tissue diseases exacerbated or triggered by infections;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BBD3EA671CD41D8999E21095A5F7C3C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>mast cell activation syndrome;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB383C2E5CD2746EF9504BE98167B300F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>related conditions and illnesses that may affect adults, young adults, or children; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE0D75CC56B446A7ADB005E372AF776B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>other conditions as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC153E5287526487ABECCAF669819DA81"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In developing and disseminating information in subsections (a) and (b), the Secretary shall ensure that—</text><paragraph id="HD5937B29F0B94B9CB07BE8814116C1DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>guidance on Long COVID diagnostics, treatments, and care include demographic factors such as age, gender, geographic location, disability, occupation, race and ethnicity, and other factors identified by the Secretary to promote health equity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC898B63A77034F2F94D6575F4836B2A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>individuals with Long COVID and related conditions, and entities representing such individuals, are empowered to participate in protocol development and outreach and education strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74A4536D42064F5A98201232C26B9493"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dissemination of information</header><text>The Secretary shall disseminate, in plain language and in a manner that is culturally and linguistically appropriate and easily accessible to people with disabilities and individuals with limited English proficiency, information under subsections (a) and (b), directly or through arrangements with intra-agency initiatives, nonprofit organizations, consumer groups, Federally qualified health centers, institutions of higher learning (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)), local educational agencies or State educational agencies (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)), or Federal, State, Tribal, or local public private partnerships.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0E1F52E78B2C4DD0A20CCEAB03557ED2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE9070C23BF3D47D79B3810725ACED75F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interagency coordination and information dissemination on rights associated with Long COVID</header><subsection id="HC1826A097F994DD9A1A956149229F525"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall convene relevant agencies to develop information and resources to make available to the public and for dissemination to individuals and communities impacted by Long COVID and related conditions to raise awareness and provide education on the impact Long COVID and related conditions may have on rights associated with employment, disability status, and education afforded under Federal and State law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H85E6C02C7C99459FBD1CCD8A3F8079F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Collaboration and consultation</header><text>In developing the information and resources under subsection (a), the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="HAD5C90E17E51447FABCC01A3EA132B20"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall collaborate with—</text><subparagraph id="H174C96E054E044DD9C58E6C59705D599"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Labor and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Disability Employment Policy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50B34D24AEE04FA98798CDA37265408E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4638FBA249624B0F9679E40AEE1AA420"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDE1C85FD78E4E7C8B3E75AE0F521974"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DF4342823BE47D5A513283CB9D2EC22"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the heads of relevant agencies within the Department of Health and Human Services, including—</text><clause id="HD5A695660B1E4DAF9584FF87C9AD7582"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></clause><clause id="HC98F798E90684C51947F7A5194634C59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Director of the National Institutes of Health;</text></clause><clause id="HFB883DA56A564923B2A7F3BD6A7964EC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services;</text></clause><clause id="HF882465ACD5343D28391DE0C978EBC03"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Administration for Children and Families; and</text></clause><clause id="H058916D56ABE4A4FBAD48F8C41AA3448"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Administration for Community Living; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5F9EB24DCC042C2B8760D0E60796569"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the heads of other Federal departments, agencies, or offices, as the Secretary determines appropriate to carry out the activities described in this section; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BD6855A83AA46CB9249825F86F47D7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may consult with—</text><subparagraph id="H2802AD656D684666978513BAC3DBBB35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>communities and professionals impacted by high COVID–19 rates;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93294E6FBC604797A0A557A89C76F1C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals with Long COVID and related conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88BC03EF6F464691B927CD5F6D9E1118"><enum>(C)</enum><text>caregivers of individuals with Long COVID and related conditions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5707387197BC4CCF85937030A960ED39"><enum>(D)</enum><text>organizations and experts that represent the rights and interests of the groups described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D7BFA4D6D3B4E91877EF6CBE8D6EC66"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Information and resources developed</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the entities described in subsection (b) shall develop information and resources to include—</text><paragraph id="H7CCEED1D8D4C44A38A2C80286F8F4E71"><enum>(1)</enum><text>educational materials to school administrators, counselors, educators, parents, coaches, school nurses, and other school staff about Long COVID and related conditions with clear guidance on appropriate academic, social, and emotional supports and services, and the rights of students with disabilities, available to students and families;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BF3962C49A041BF961ECD5821D59178"><enum>(2)</enum><text>guidance for employers on the rights of people with disabilities related to Long COVID and related conditions, including strategies for how employers can support such individuals in the workplace; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D5A61C4922748398B72234AA3319B34"><enum>(3)</enum><text>guidance on Long COVID and related conditions as a disability, including recommendations to streamline the process of applying for benefits through the Social Security Administration, including guidance on evaluating Long COVID and related conditions for individuals under the age of 18, continuing disability reviews, and the payment of benefits under part L of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10281">34 U.S.C. 10281 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17E5286214894DD8A33E94F2884DA970"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dissemination of information</header><text>The Secretary shall disseminate the information and resources developed under subsection (c) to—</text><paragraph id="HF967DD0AFDBD475980AECDB3A0A85AAB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States or State agencies implementing the State protection and advocacy system (as defined in section 102 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15002">42 U.S.C. 15002</external-xref>));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF271B3ABC8434EFB97B9D78BCF8A7FAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>State agencies on aging or area agencies on aging (as such terms are defined in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD783BF71D6F1486D984C81B81EF4C08D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>organizations and experts that represent workers’ rights and education; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A9388C9B6764B9AA3DA842D8FC5E7D8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other organizations and experts that represent the rights and interests of individuals with Long COVID and related conditions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFFB64D0E2C59401A881863EF01FFECC8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF4E303B301944345B0CF3D14DFCDEEE8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Program to support legal and social service assistance for individuals with Long COVID</header><subsection id="H20E44F96B4A7491CB5235753C387E007"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Administrator of the Administration for Community Living, shall award grants or contracts to eligible entities for purposes of establishing or expanding medical-legal partnerships, or increasing the availability of legal assistance or social supports necessary, to provide effective aid or support to individuals with Long COVID and related conditions, and their caregivers, who are seeking assistance in obtaining or maintaining access to, or in legal matters relating to, any of the following services, at minimal or no cost to the individuals:</text><paragraph id="H7BC6699287394E7FA62FE91C801224EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Social Security Disability Insurance program under section 223 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/423">42 U.S.C. 423</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27D4E12FDE4D4D248ED0768E861796BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The supplemental security income program under title XVI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1381">42 U.S.C. 1381 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H830BA2FD68324E01892CD3677D5A22A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Survivors benefits under title II of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/401">42 U.S.C. 401 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE61C799A08064EB49492C092297C8539"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Housing matters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37A78BBC73F2432084B4BA755EF1369D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Access to medical care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H421D70F8ECE745778BC4A27176A37546"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Access to vocational rehabilitation services under title I of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/720">29 U.S.C. 720 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F184E2E8FB746C08DE7D1104FAF6924"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Access to assistive technology under the Assistive Technology Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3001">29 U.S.C. 3001 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4474B1E345FD421AA59F20115947384A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Early intervention, specialized instruction, and related services and accommodations for children provided under parts B and C of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1411">20 U.S.C. 1411 et seq.</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1431">20 U.S.C. 1431 et seq.</external-xref>) and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4546B3F909D14E5E9FE487C107DAAD02"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The low-income home energy assistance program established under the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8621">42 U.S.C. 8621 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E2A36A437814F0EA8C4B64D5769A6A3"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Employment supports.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2D7FB057A5746FCAF4060C720299C7C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Nutrition assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7DDA28EB3124E6D9C205E0F5B398872"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Traumatic brain injury supports.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C04ECEE554C43FF878574E5662AF065"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Other support services for low-income individuals and people with disabilities (as defined in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C8EA659265740AE8B01B0B0468346F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility for awards</header><paragraph id="HD29AFF08B3A047649B382EC1BEB4D1B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive an award under this section, an entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD75115CAAF304A6285742D7C4209979F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be—</text><clause id="HF976F7B63D4148ECBE3DF60B72FD7FD7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a State, or an agency implementing the State protection and advocacy system (as defined in section 102 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15002">42 U.S.C. 15002</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="H96F6314452D34F94888D41CDB14E8E3F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State agency or area agency on aging (as such terms are defined in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="H3AA4224BCF824DE18EBC865D6AE1CE3B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a nonprofit entity or a publicly funded organization not acting in a governmental capacity, such as a law school;</text></clause><clause id="HD7221AF695D44A61B2E0C305FCECE9EE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe or Tribal organization;</text></clause><clause id="HF480BBAFBD3E474F8913AE5AE1E88B19"><enum>(v)</enum><text>an urban Indian organization;</text></clause><clause id="HF0F0BD7686AC4EE0B2854814C099D182"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a territory;</text></clause><clause id="H10950261C0704843BF932DC2AC6DB8C2"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>a health care provider with an existing multi-disciplinary clinic or other specialized program focused on serving individuals with Long COVID, underserved communities, or low-income patients, or with a demonstrated intent to create such a program;</text></clause><clause id="H287C3F36D8584B2C8147A0E31EF4280D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>an entity providing legal services; or</text></clause><clause id="H4820F0F30B3443DCB371C0B064F78666"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in clauses (i) through (viii);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A4160C0553549AE86F637420E9F3E5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agree to use the award for the purposes described in subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBE58A74A34B45A3BF84C5861722DF3F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>partner with at least one community-based organization with a demonstrated history of serving people with disabilities, including helping people with disabilities access supportive services, or a demonstrated history of serving impacted communities, including limited-English proficient communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1F2C7BA83D147F2A0571FA5A399713A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In making awards under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority to entities described in paragraph (1) that certify in writing that any person providing legal assistance through a program supported by the award—</text><subparagraph id="H6F08894AE11F4247B7C1DF5B563298E9"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9DF8CC8B4A6F4870A85AE9DD1268EE0C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has demonstrated expertise in providing legal assistance to people with disabilities; or</text></clause><clause id="H51721C43798247A1AEDEE5E80DEE879B" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is partnered with a person or organization that has demonstrated expertise described in clause (i); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H657BE969A34846C7A15F9D8DE3DE24BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has completed, or will complete, training in connection with disability-related legal issues.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3BBA5CCC63364AB18C5C20609EFD39B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity receiving an award under this section may use such award to—</text><paragraph id="HB21E5C153E17486C8600384F39743AB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish or expand medical-legal partnerships or other cooperative efforts between community-based organizations, medical and social service providers, and legal assistance providers to provide legal assistance and help accessing or maintaining social services for individuals with Long COVID;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D368592BC004A649031E076DCCE7E83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish or expand efforts and projects to provide legal assistance for individuals with Long COVID by organizations with a demonstrated history of providing direct legal or advocacy services on behalf of people with disabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6C17B6C54184C90B108A9A4941C0FBF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to organizations or agencies for educating individuals with Long COVID, caregivers, and parents, including foster parents, caring for children with Long COVID about rights related to accommodations in employment, education, or other matters as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAE532DC9A0F44E29EC9A966266E82D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>employ staff or educate current staff on assisting individuals with Long COVID in obtaining health care, social services, or legal services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H984474840CD24117B39AFEA81D04BA03"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Eligible entities receiving an award under this section shall collect data and report information to the Secretary of Health and Human Services in a manner prescribed by such Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7BF13DFFB58E4CF2BCF28908616B96AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit a report to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, which shall also be made publicly available, outlining the number of individuals who sought services offered by recipients of awards under this section and the services provided. Such report shall include a summary of activities conducted under the program under this section, and information broken down by award recipient.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA94685CE7B8445C2BD48C8DFF3D6D151"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="HD4FD792DDBD94AE5A3EBC8B5A1958157"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3DDFA134242465397ABAF99A3D0B8A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonsupplantation</header><text>Amounts made available under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, and local funds expended to further the purpose of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H11FB65EA2B834617A3930230B4FB5AD6"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H76FF7857F7D34981A13AC5D738A3DC5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The terms <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D9C734E2B4E4F25B99C9DE96579CA3A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Long COVID</header><text>The term <term>Long COVID</term> means health conditions that may result, directly or indirectly, from COVID–19. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC29B4B144294C5E822BA0BBBA4E249D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Urban Indian organization</header><text>The term <term>urban Indian organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC296078D52BA42DE91BED583A32CA794"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tribal organization</header><text>The term <term>Tribal organization</term> means the recognized governing body of any Indian Tribe; any legally established organization of Indians which is controlled, sanctioned, or chartered by such governing body or which is democratically elected by the adult members of the Indian community to be served by such organization and which includes the maximum participation of Indians in all phases of its activities: <italic>Provided,</italic> That in any case where a contract is let or grant made to an organization to perform services benefitting more than one Indian Tribe, the approval of each such Indian Tribe shall be a prerequisite to the letting or making of such contract or grant.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

