<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H96A73DA3C571427A922DF2A5FC2D0180" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6482 IH: Enhancing Geothermal Production on Federal Lands Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6482</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231128">November 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000469">Mr. Fulcher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Geothermal Steam Act of 1970 to promote timely exploration for geothermal resources under geothermal leases, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDB19817BC55C4879956884484E60799B" style="OLC"><section id="H9691E1C59B20477CB196AE12631D5120" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Enhancing Geothermal Production on Federal Lands Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6FA3B5D6A2D243FCB7D95F3CD9131E5D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Geothermal production on Federal lands</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Geothermal Steam Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/1001">30 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H48176A38B3F24ABA8DB6BDA093093C97" style="OLC"><section id="H8D856781E7D148DE8DC8FDD3AE1BFE3D"><enum>30.</enum><header>Geothermal exploration projects</header><subsection id="HB39D6734BD5C4F64B5AA624EFEF09DB1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6B6B10E08F5143B898ED1405F562FAD3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Geothermal exploration project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>geothermal exploration project</term> means the drilling of a temperature gradient well, monitoring well, calibration well, or another geothermal exploratory well, including construction or making improvements for such activities, on lands for which the Secretary has issued a geothermal lease—</text><subparagraph id="H965F11BACE9B4EE497D0240F592647B6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is carried out by the holder of the lease;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68C303DD01D9426AA5A3C4A65725C099" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which—</text><clause id="H9C9513D2969E484184474F7D3D224A67" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the last cemented casing string has an outer diameter of less than 13 inches; and</text></clause><clause id="HBD9CB791B78E48C9A385A59E8E569EB5" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total unreclaimed surface disturbance at any one time within the project area is less than 5 acres, not including the area of a permanent or temporary access road;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11AB8C9EFE744805849D69E7C0DA8AA9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that is completed in less than 120 days, including the removal of any surface infrastructure from the project area; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A79FF1D51CF4C6B9A553CDAA8974FB6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that requires the restoration of the project area within 3 years of the date of first exploration drilling to approximately the condition that existed at the time the project began, unless the project area is subsequently used as part of energy development under the lease.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFBF5CE296DD4F17BE8E2D6C6F0DD88F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered activity</term> includes, with respect to exploration, development, or production (including direct use) of geothermal resources—</text><subparagraph id="H27A4DF505D9B4D5D8A3A80C54E6286E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a geotechnical investigation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA309BAEE65D441DB92F5460384C06499"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">off-road travel in a right-of-way established by Congress, granted by a Federal agency, or included in a land use plan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98FC2A82380D427A9B57097CDD0A5192"><enum>(C)</enum><text>construction, maintenance, realignment, and repair of an existing permanent or temporary access road within a right-of-way established by Congress, granted by a Federal agency, or included in a land use plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB1458620140749D1BA858BBE08E9E365"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Non-Major Federal action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Geothermal exploration projects and covered activities shall not be considered major Federal actions under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H334002A8EF2C46FA98AE3A707F4CFE5E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement To provide notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The holder of a geothermal lease shall provide to the Secretary notice of their intent to carry out a geothermal exploration project at least 30 days before the start of drilling under the project.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HCD4C20C4E7EB4086AFBAD70C223D9198"><enum>3.</enum><header>Geothermal leasing priority areas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Geothermal Steam Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/1001">30 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H8C23DA70E1874DBD9A067A2ED4B0F99E" style="OLC"><section id="HB8422D7C1F58494D852EF8FC205273D7"><enum>31.</enum><header>Geothermal leasing priority areas</header><subsection id="H501EB9CAE66E44FAA6408C28D2A8754E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of covered land</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered land</term> means land that is—</text><paragraph id="H48FA95FD3E0B4BE28CEF8C2C6D264D00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Federal land; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF16A94DBE3094160B8BDCC4032DA399C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not excluded from the development of geothermal energy under—</text><subparagraph id="H6A9D7A4AF797427C91CA9FA26E599627"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a land use plan established under the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1701">43 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AA881D2548B438FB6B7DFE470B55F01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other Federal law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC61AA830948F48B6A6E1BBB569412AAB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation of geothermal leasing priority areas</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall designate portions of covered land as geothermal leasing priority areas as soon as practicable, but not later than 5 years, after the date of enactment of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF15F995E20F34481A95ADA34CF696B60"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria for selection</header><text>In determining which covered lands to designate as geothermal leasing priority areas under subsection (b), the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall consider if—</text><paragraph id="H2842319F5D594E2E8071284E8CDA9C79"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the covered land is preferable for geothermal leasing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB966BDD140AE4DFE9AFDB39880A60CA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>production of geothermal energy on such land is economically viable, including if such land has access to methods of energy transmission; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF38809E9763547378FF073D79BEC255F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the designation would be in compliance with section 202 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1712">43 U.S.C. 1712</external-xref>), including subsection (c)(9) of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H321195C7A3AB47BDBB2B46F30BBF352F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Review and modification</header><text>Not less frequently than once every 5 years, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H09F5EE0A4AA24282A1FD579CD276D6F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review covered land and, if appropriate, make additional designations of geothermal leasing priority areas; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BD9E14FFB2E44E2B54BC299E0F53D90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>review each area designated as a geothermal leasing priority area under this section, and, if appropriate, remove such designation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC4DDE6470A9415DB9EEE10FB9A1C344"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Programmatic environmental impact statement</header><paragraph id="HC5F954559AA640CC8567FFCBF39C2689"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial designations</header><text>Not later than one year after the initial designation of a geothermal leasing priority area, the Secretary shall prepare a supplement to any final programmatic environmental impact statement for geothermal leasing that is the most recently finalized such statement with respect to covered land designated as a geothermal leasing priority area under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0375092E71BE4D7FBA4FC0286B4B8E30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent designations</header><text>Each designation of a geothermal leasing priority area under subsection (b) shall be included in a programmatic environmental impact statement for geothermal leasing or in a supplement to such a statement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H410E38261CBD4D12BD8B20D378037BA2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>In developing any programmatic environmental impact statement for geothermal leasing or supplement to such a statement under this section, the Secretary shall consult, on an ongoing basis, with appropriate State, Tribal, and local governments, transmission infrastructure owners and operators, developers, and other appropriate entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6541F60084A54E9C8CBB8DC55982C2C3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The Secretary may not delay issuing a permit or holding a lease sale under this Act because the supplement required under paragraph (1) has not been finalized by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85378E279C4D40269DC11E106CB0C2F6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Compliance with NEPA</header><text>If the Secretary determines that the designation of a geothermal leasing priority area has been sufficiently analyzed by a programmatic environmental impact statement, the Secretary shall not prepare any additional analysis under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to geothermal lease sales for such geothermal leasing priority area.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

