<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA87E42548C2B49B781C6EF9D04814020" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5500 IH: Peer Learning for Agriculture Conservation Education Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5500</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food Security Act of 1985 to require the Secretary of Agriculture to establish an initiative to support peer learning relating to a wide range of agriculture conservation activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5F87341C519349839A4F323DDF660FD9" style="OLC"><section id="H83AD2875B5C34E26820B1224364F811E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Peer Learning for Agriculture Conservation Education Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PLACE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC3E3654A1EBC490EA1EFD9F73CC3C1A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Peer learning for agriculture conservation education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1271C of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3871c">16 U.S.C. 3871c</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0ED4116457BD4EDBB3986C10313A9EBC"><subsection id="HF5C244E07F894EBA9D9B2B69ED27BA82"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Peer learning initiative</header><paragraph id="H726F654230BB4E84B422F232CFCFD7F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of peer learning</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>peer learning</term> means an educational experience that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HA122D540C5E743E5A3295E159C1D6FDD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>farmer, rancher, or forester led information sharing, education, or training activities that support agricultural producers or foresters; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E69DBE58C1C49E793B9293CF195D5E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the provision of farmer, rancher, or forester led technical assistance to agricultural producers or foresters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F0DEC332F664747985052E47A0974BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment of initiative</header><text>Not later than 1 year after enactment, the Secretary shall establish an initiative to support projects that provide to agricultural producers peer learning opportunities relating to a wide range of agriculture conservation activities, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H2F077594A8C2431BB2E01DBF1784F99C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>activities or management systems, as determined by the Secretary, that directly contribute to improving soil health; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H819D0909CF0F423D8037B5E1479FCA1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other regional priority natural resource concerns, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0801804D6574C6DB5D758AFECE49523"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grants</header><subparagraph id="H97C090809F8144049CCC25DDFB4B04C7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the initiative established under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall enter into not fewer than 5 grant agreements each fiscal year to support peer learning projects in accordance with that paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02EE95F4719641078FDD8710FED2F93B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agreements</header><clause id="H12A173F6B64B4228A54288B61AD97F8D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may enter into a grant agreement under subparagraph (A) with 1 or more eligible partners that are engaged in providing peer learning to agricultural producers.</text></clause><clause id="HD5728A1F06774BEBA7EE324B4159F64C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Projects</header><text>A grant agreement under subparagraph (A) may support any of the following:</text><subclause id="HF2C3AC54B7A945C2994F70922BD4C081"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Projects within or sponsored by a State.</text></subclause><subclause id="H1D76B03BC4E040AA8E4F30458CAC6B80"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Multistate projects.</text></subclause><subclause id="H84AED32FB6F34CAEB1F45A4A0196B488"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Projects in a critical conservation area designated under section 1271F.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33C66C467C564A23A997DC186EEA156B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applications</header><clause id="H1DD4B2AFD749492287D14BF4B10A3C15"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An organization described in subparagraph (B)(i) desiring to enter into a grant agreement under subparagraph (A) shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></clause><clause id="HA034383673E443638607DD9A829A4DF4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Multiple applicants</header><text>An application under clause (i) may be submitted jointly by multiple organizations described in subparagraph (B)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC0C7EB081D64813BE94382A21B63466"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duties of the eligible partner</header><subparagraph id="H7D747898CCBF40C1BDF5235837BD6007"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Entities that enter into an agreement with the Secretary under paragraph (3)(B) shall use funding for purposes related to coordinating peer learning initiatives, such as—</text><clause id="H4BD982201467428D86F3B9A5D82E667C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>convening of stakeholders to achieve the goals of the contractual partnership with NRCS through the Program;</text></clause><clause id="H86512E4E027D4309910433F8B86E637B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>farmer outreach and education;</text></clause><clause id="HE9A82617EA154DC6AB80C2437C9DDA57"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>forester outreach and education;</text></clause><clause id="H293328A5CE1A418C992BC28DE64FF644"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>convening of the scientific community for the purposes of coordinating scientific research methodologies and data sets related to priority resource concerns identified in the agreement;</text></clause><clause id="H557AD090D25F46C58D3D771773ED2501"><enum>(v)</enum><text>coordination of municipal and State policies with on-farm practices;</text></clause><clause id="H7FBD120CBDA94D75BDF454C62B3DEB69"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>facilitating trainings; and</text></clause><clause id="HFE983799A1A04A6687780C903D6F1168"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>other activities as determined by the Secretary that facilitate peer learning oriented around priority resource concerns identified in the agreement.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25265AABFABE4848A21BF9E982AE0FA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Submit to the Secretary, in addition to any information that the Secretary requires to prepare the report under section 3871e(b) of this title, an annual report that describes the status of the project, including a description of—</text><clause id="H0F73313FACDB463FA73AEA4B8B0CA57A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the use of the funds awarded under paragraph (3);</text></clause><clause id="H34CF7F84C88246D9A35F7C80992E5280"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any subcontracts awarded;</text></clause><clause id="H0722201CB02F4D93A2888758DBC944AD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the producers receiving funding through the funding agreement under paragraph (3);</text></clause><clause id="H22CE1B469E14400583FFF40F526ED3EE"><enum>(iv)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4D6B37C1A0734FA2A45E4D4631CCA51C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the progress made by the project in addressing each natural resource concern defined in the funding agreement under paragraph (3), including in a quantified form to the extent practicable; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HFBFB975B7DFD4CBEB0C865E51A11C5A4" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>as appropriate, other outcomes of the project; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1E09A7CEBE4844EC8FFB0BC9B5B38F9A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any other reporting data the Secretary determines are necessary to ensure compliance with the program rules.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F74BEB24A9E4FC69718132CEBC8C61C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>With respect to a project funded under the initiative established under paragraph (2), the Secretary may waive any requirement under the program that limits the percentage of program funding that may be used for technical assistance, or requires a minimum percentage of program funding to be used for financial assistance, such that up to 100 percent of the funding provided for the project may be used for technical assistance, if the grant agreement entered into under paragraph (3)(B) with respect to that project includes a plan to promote the availability of covered programs to agricultural producers.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

