<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFC7A7069B9D4B6CA199DA9A313336B1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6850 IH: Safe Landings Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6850</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve technology and address human factors in aviation safety, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2ECBDFE0A3DC4CB68EF62347F3A13B9F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0D739BEAEC94490383FC0626576FA012" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Landings Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA986A8D30BEF4759B9B4DD0C60FF225C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE7B678B807974CC495B539D3EA9BC1E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Given that the United States enjoys an exceptionally safe aviation system with an exceedingly low frequency of airline accidents, efforts to improve aviation safety should examine nonaccident safety incidents for all possible insights.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDDAAFBC659F54B4F8804B3FD90607664"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aviation safety should not be taken for granted, and even with so few accidents, the U.S. Aerospace System should proactively address safety concerns that emerge from our dynamic and evolving economic conditions, technology, aviation industry, and other factors.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H76BE9E0074624B2487D732D25011E649"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Preventing accidents from occurring in the airport runway environment remains an objective requiring continued effort, and incidents of runway confusion, defined as the subset of runway incursions in which an aircraft unintentionally takes off or lands on a taxiway or incorrect runway, should be carefully monitored, reviewed, and studied for insights to improve safety.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF0BD06F2A4D44C8B5FBABE79768D6E8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>While technology continues to advance and new opportunities to use technology to address safety risks in aviation are examined and pursued, the evolving role of technology and the expanding use of automation should not be used as justification to diminish attention to and prioritization of the human contribution to aviation safety. The aviation industry and the Government must ensure that training programs for flight crews and other personnel are appropriately evolving, that training standards and expectations remain rigorous, and that risks and concerns associated with the interaction between humans, technology, and automated systems are identified, studied, and addressed in a timely manner.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H42FF35DCF45445B387DAA8001815AD8B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Implementation of NTSB recommendations</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HB949C00FA31742A3830BDB3BA634FB86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>NTSB recommendation</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H30AA001D457A48EE85DD8AC43347D5F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall implement the recommendation of the National Transportation Safety Board numbered as A–18–25 and issued on October 11, 2018, and, not later than 1 year after the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall issue to Congress a report on the status of the implementation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H33946B6C14014FA0BB0D80D230A001D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>In implementing this recommendation, the Administrator shall consider any relevant findings identified pursuant to section 334 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/254">Public Law 115–254</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB37ABFE1F6CE4C8F9AC23961B3DF831E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot alerts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall—</text> <paragraph id="HA6E86787AE214E1BAE974301FF578A39"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborate with aircraft and avionics manufacturers, labor organizations representing pilots operating under part 121 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, and software developers to develop the technology for a cockpit system that provides an alert to pilots when an airplane is not aligned with the intended runway surface;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEDAB93B0F063467DA1284E77674A5EEB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">once such technology described in paragraph (1) is available, establish a requirement for the technology to be installed on aircraft operating under part 121 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, landing at airports within Class B and Class C airspace and certified under part 139 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF186BC5D1E4444FE8DD53F6EC55B8C01"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in establishing the requirement as described in paragraph (2), consider any relevant findings identified pursuant to section 334 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/254">Public Law 115–254</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE67170D500064BC39BB1F38DC2D5AB74"><enum>(4)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, issue to Congress a report on the progress of the work described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> <section id="H9FDF92BF39DB4280A8234AAE7E1EBB7A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Investigations for covered events</header> <subsection id="H728E09C56A61499481605E76540EF5B2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Once implementation of section 3(a) of this Act is complete, the National Transportation Safety Board may initiate investigations of covered events to determine risk factors specific to the airport at which such an event occurred and other elements of the National Airspace System that may contribute to the cause of the event. The National Transportation Safety Board may also elect to consider multiple events in a single report as part of a special investigation or study to examine safety factors contributing to these events.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD7B4548EBD524ECE9BAE77095BF86954"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content</header><text>The review and analysis shall examine factors present at the time of any covered event at such airport, including—</text> <paragraph id="HE8BADB3E30F045E58902953BBF3FE2B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>challenges pilots perceive when flying into and out of the airport;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD05074BEDA1F4308AEC35486D9BFC567"><enum>(2)</enum><text>challenges that air traffic controllers face when working at the airport;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51726FA443BE40EAB6D39A600BE69B54"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">characteristics of the communications among and between groups of personnel whose work relates to the movement of aircraft into and out of the airport including pilots, air traffic controllers, maintenance workers, dispatchers, and airline airport operations personnel; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H83F86F26A6FF4D49858CEC9305C39A65"><enum>(4)</enum><text>physical characteristics of the airport and its facilities, such as the configuration of runways, taxiways, runway lighting, and construction activity.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD044EC63309948B9997072C5C9EBB5D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Protection of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Individuals involved in any manner in an investigation described in this section may request that the Board take such action as appropriate to protect from public disclosure any information that readily identifies such individual. The Board may withhold the information if the Board determines that the information may be withheld under an exemption under section 552 of title 5, United States Code, and the publication of such information is not in the public interest. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H67D5E65B9E5143C6BD2F42B0811AFFF5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Study on human factors and aviation safety</header> 
<subsection id="HF3D4C484A92A464D81891996A4C30A67"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine shall, in collaboration with other relevant Federal institutions and agencies, conduct a study on the role of human factors in high-risk professions, including aviation.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H631FE97957174F99A42A59A1DF719443"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the National Academies shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure and Committee on Education and Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions of the Senate a report on the results of the study required under subsection (a), including best practices that can be implemented across all high-risk professions, including within the aviation industry, to reduce risk involved with human factors. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H876C9ED587D54675B9BB34F8A4488D40"><enum>6.</enum><header>Task Force on Human Factors in Aviation Safety</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H13FA0E9512994F23808C0D5A4CC6A31D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall convene a task force on human factors in aviation safety (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF69DDFCF2FB64A3FACF8F925A6DEBA03"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall consist of members appointed by the Administrator and having expertise in an operational or academic discipline that is relevant to the analysis of human errors in aviation. The number of members shall be determined by the Administrator to ensure sufficient representation of relevant operational and academic disciplines.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB84CB7A3A8E495799237324CA1C83F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duration</header> 
<paragraph id="HAF02203725D94F6FB332B79F1D88C4B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Members of the Task Force shall be appointed for the length of the existence of the Task Force.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H937CE8ADAD64447D9CC48F565F061C12"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Length of existence</header> <subparagraph id="H5A2034F13AE743979350516CA93163B8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall have an initial length of existence of 2 years.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0AFEDCD819F84B87B7BC883CD2B52AB5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Option</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may exercise an option to lengthen the duration of the existence of the Task Force for a period of 2 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB6AF0B994AAF4C7D97AF7DA5C025757B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Disciplines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (b), disciplines may include air carrier operations, line pilot expertise, air traffic control, technical operations, aeronautical information, aircraft maintenance and mechanics psychology, linguistics, human-machine integration, general aviation operations, and organizational behavior and culture.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H90FE11EDB4DF47DAAECF163A32C9F37F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Expertise</header> 
<paragraph id="H36DE2E6D51F94C6EABCB584460E415C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No less than half of the members shall have expertise in aviation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21C025431F954BCCB1A527302D9F850D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional expertise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall include members with expertise on human factors but whose experience and training are not in aviation specifically and who have not previously been engaged in work related to the Federal Aviation Administration or the aviation industry. The Task Force shall also include pilot labor organizations, certificated mechanic labor organizations, and the exclusive bargaining representative of the air traffic controllers certified under section 7111 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2FC88ABFEFDE48DC877ED0D0473EDAFE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Federal Aviation Administration members</header> 
<paragraph id="H62D58A3C680C48008019F2DBB605FB64"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not more than 4 members may be employees of the Federal Aviation Administration and National Transportation Safety Board, excluding representatives of the labor representatives of employees of the air traffic control system. Not more than 2 members may be employees of the National Transportation Safety Board. The Federal Aviation Administration and the National Transportation Safety Board members shall be non-voting.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5FADF8B2FF248A1876BF8EA734F0A74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal Aviation Administration employees</header><text>Any member who is an Federal Aviation Administration employee shall have expertise in safety.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1536AD5180FB4811AC5709FCBA8CEAB6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In coordination with the Research, Engineering, and Development Advisory Committee established under section 44508 of title 49, United States Code, the Task Force shall—</text> <paragraph id="H1FE5B68EA08A43C58BC06133AEC1F784"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than the date on which the Task Force is no longer in existence, produce a written report that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF547A798F95849B5A06C87E428F3ABAF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the greatest extent possible, identifies the most significant human factors and the relative contribution of such factors to aviation safety risk;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7EE14DA5DADF434F9A3FD7C7287A9435"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifies new research priorities for research in human factors in aviation safety;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD9281B5DE3844138A122ACD9AAD73AF3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reviews existing products by other working groups related to human factors in aviation safety including the Commercial Aviation Safety Team (CAST)’s work pertaining to flight crew responses to abnormal events;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2D1870E55B55467C897131318886D25D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides recommendations on potential revisions to any Federal Aviation Administration regulations and guidance pertaining to the certification of aircraft under part 25 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, including sections related to presumed pilot response times and assumptions about the reliability of pilot performance during unexpected, stressful events;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H404DA9DF49774BDE81FCB8D7784F02FB"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviews rules, regulations, or standards regarding flight crew rest and fatigue, as well as maintenance personnel rest and fatigue, that are used by a sample of international air carriers, including those deemed to be more stringent and less stringent than the current standards pertaining to United States air carriers, and identify risks to the National Airspace System from any such variation in standards across countries;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H44513A0C5DAF461C9C46B93B7E33E4A6"><enum>(F)</enum><text>reviews pilot training requirements and recommend any revisions necessary to ensure adequate understanding of automated systems on aircraft; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF56C2BF20FC5407EB9B9E9B15FAF24D8"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviews approach and landing misalignment and make any recommendations for improving these events; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H166332D397C14B08B3D7F2858F67BE27"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies ways to enhance instrument landing system maintenance schedules as well as other relevant technology systems that facilitate safe landings that are jointly used by air traffic controllers, pilots, and Federal Aviation Administration technicians, determines how a real-time smart system should be developed that informs the Air Traffic Control System, Airlines, and Airports about any changes in the state of runway and taxiway lights, and identifies how this system could be connected to the Federal Aviation Administration’s maintenance system;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDE82603DC0C44850A659D2F916470E63"><enum>(I)</enum><text>analyzes, with respect to human errors related to aviation safety of part 121 air carriers—</text> <clause id="HDC7B394055CD474E912F26BF9B390E3A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>fatigue and distraction during critical phases of work among pilots or other aviation personnel;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H761366D64DB84273B47BD7782F78B977"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>tasks and workload;</text></clause> <clause id="HDE626F91A23941619F1AD59DC8E6FD3D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>organizational culture;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H08590AEFD8E8414CA1C680AF37D1C675"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>communication among personnel;</text></clause> <clause id="HF8066F8D991141C7805457ED4484DF65"><enum>(v)</enum><text>adherence to safety procedures;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBFF098780F7B4A1798D6EEE0F4C4F3BF"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>mental fitness of personnel; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD4564C55258441F58E29D9268D5847FD"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any other relevant factors that affect human performance or are the cause or potential cause of human error related to aviation safety;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9B0C2D8D1DA149559E6BC68C2A845A17"><enum>(J)</enum><text>includes a tabulation of the number of accidents, incidents, or aviation safety database entries received in which an item identified under subparagraph (I) was a cause or potential cause of human error related to aviation safety; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H955E7AE8ADC54FAC8AAF439C6F79B1E4"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a list of causes or potential causes of human error related to aviation safety about which the Administrator believes additional information is needed; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D8623FE751E47409CD4863233DB4362"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the Secretary exercises the option described in subsection (c)(2)(B), not later than the date that is 2 years after the date of establishment of the Task Force, produce an interim report containing the information described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEAC32A2DED3D4C1681656E5BEDAF5270"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Methodology</header> <paragraph id="H97456CBCC596436EA81B099BF45A067B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To complete the report under subparagraphs (I) through (K) of subsection (g)(1), the Task Force shall consult with the National Transportation Safety Board and use all available data compiled and analysis conducted on safety incidents and irregularities collected during the relevant fiscal years from the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7CE9FFE18CC14305808CBA05AE1A37F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Flight Operations Quality Assurance.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE974A0C708154922A3E6FD569F54CC51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Aviation Safety Action Program.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2E608ED293A4422BAEDFE6F7BD163805"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Aviation Safety Information Analysis and Sharing.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7B1E7FF56AB64D408FC6110D096151DF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Aviation Safety Reporting System.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF2ABEDC429D44ADFA832937DC0645867"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aviation safety recommendations and investigation findings of the National Transportation Safety Board.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1E683FBB19004642B5FE31E5C9750381"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Other relevant programs or sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B38FD1FE49044D1AB5396415B0382F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protection of information</header><text>The Task Force shall ensure that any data described in paragraph (1) has strong protections to protect employees from data being used to undertake punitive measures against the employee or personal liability. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCA6198A14C2B4B078CB6BE8788659032"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text>Section 1013 of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Task Force.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H11E4A6BF348F4127A1134846C3F15C84"><enum>7.</enum><header>Research and development program on new approaches to data analysis for aviation safety</header> 
<subsection id="H89DF2CD225134EFF9D5536761A90FA3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a new research and development program to be undertaken by the FAA’s Consortium in Aviation Operations Research (NEXTOR III) to investigate and develop new approaches to data analysis for understanding the factors in aviation safety incidents and identifying emerging risks of future safety incidents.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4E3DFFF9AF77416D8EACCF1476885DF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approaches</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The approaches described in subsection (a) include the use of new algorithms for analyzing the text and audio of communications between flight crews and air traffic controllers and the use of machine learning or artificial intelligence methods for analyzing a variety of data sets, including, data on weather, performance of communication, navigation and surveillance equipment and facilities, flight delays, safety incidents, flight crew work schedules, and air traffic and crew member communications for detecting anomalies in the National Airspace System.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE07B648286D84AEFAD902910AF94784F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In carrying out the research program established in this section, member institutions of the Consortium shall collaborate in the sharing of data for the purpose of testing and demonstrating the potential effectiveness of new approaches to analysis—</text> <paragraph id="H9D4B95F8DF464BB49D03EC0BD244FA55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with each other;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H466048CCEE0E4BE4B36895836939FBF7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with aviation industry partners;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D1AF83FDC0B4557BA20FEB79319BF5C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with units within the FAA including groups within the Air Traffic Organization, NextGen Office, Office of Airports, and Aviation Safety; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4C2FF56F44954E6589E091D8F88303B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s Aviation Safety Reporting System.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H87304DB01F1448D5BBD30F5CEF29F5AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Research</header> <paragraph id="H2F9EFBC739B7413EA3EB647706D0700C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The research undertaken pursuant to this section shall prioritize understanding the ways that various forms of human factors contribute to aviation safety risk.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H099AF5E22A454D3C8DA64F879434127E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors</header><text>The factors described in paragraph (1) may include fatigue and distraction during critical phases of work among pilots or other aviation personnel, tasks and workload, organizational structure and culture, communication among personnel, adherence to safety procedures, and any other relevant factors that are the cause or potential cause of human error in aviation operations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59B746EEDBE74E9D821A3AB8EBCFFDA6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Highly automated aircraft</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Research should seek ways to improve the design of highly automated aircraft to reduce instances of mode confusion and to combat problems of reduced awareness of basic flight parameters resulting from complacency about automated systems.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD1D030FF5A8545D588031683B12DA0B5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $20,000,000 for carrying out the program described in this section for each fiscal year from 2024 through 2029, including grants to participating research institutions, including the academic institutions that make up the FAA’s Consortium in Aviation Operations Research (NEXTOR III), the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the FAA’s Office of Safety, the NextGen office, and units within the FAA’s Air Traffic Organization that work on safety issues.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD3DA4F1277884C8290965CA0E1F69AC6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The program shall terminate on the date that is 6 years after the date on which the program is established.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEF703D96F63A47608E4E868C303C3AFA"><enum>8.</enum><header>Using instrument approach procedures as backups to visual approaches</header> 
<subsection id="H464388EA70884E88AAA1DB90D4A56E03"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall issue a report to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate that uses a representative sample of part 121 and part 129 air carriers to review the current range of air carrier practices in requiring the use of instrument approach procedures as a backup system for visual approaches and the extent to which operators require pilots to use approach procedures.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H42B2D734F1E64965966E5FB72E607E27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Issuance of guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall review and analyze the collected data from the report described in subsection (a) and issue guidance to air carriers on the most effective techniques and procedures to use instrument approach procedures as a backup system for visual approaches. Such guidance shall encourage the use of instruments to provide vertical and lateral guidance to mitigate the potential for a wrong surface alignment and to provide flight crews with more precise vertical and lateral deviation information.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H03A43D31ACA842D3B7155C88AE56093F"><enum>9.</enum><header>NOTAM Modernization Initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2(c) of the NOTAM improvement Act of 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H270589FE1A514F9BB00D4A606E559AE0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0E54DCD59BA4FF9A43E5435D36A0F3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB04D2F02F0DF4ED493675244BBD65FBC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE5F0C62B58A14D0D8C87AD619A652F27" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H62671F8961434B18A46EF13446D42BB1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborating with avionics manufacturers and software developers in considering hardware and software for sending, assessing, and displaying NOTAMs; and </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section> <section id="HE6EAEF19DA5847B1B2345289FDA1718B"><enum>10.</enum><header>GAO study on risks associated with the use of CVR data in foreign countries</header> <subsection id="HF40ECAA3F4B24136B6EABCE7508ACF89"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General shall take the lead in carrying out a study on the risks associated with the use of CVR data in investigations led by foreign governments or units of foreign governments.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H04215BD43BDC4AEF9C593A8CE7F767BF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At minimum, this study shall—</text> <paragraph id="HAEE5BAECDFFD48B6986F3034BB32E8D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review past incidents in which CVR data was used by foreign governments or units of foreign governments in such a way that the National Transportation Safety Board found to depart from the National Transportation Safety Board’s standards and procedures for a safety investigation, including the use or circulation of CVR data for purposes other than determining the causes of an accident or safety incident, inappropriate release of data contained on a CVR, or the dissemination of information or conclusions based on a misinterpretation of data contained on a CVR;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE959FB9E31DF4272918A928E48FF411A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">document the protections provided for cockpit voice recordings and transcripts by ICAO and other countries where United States-based air carriers operate;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H669B4F8DA8794B58A506DE50C4CFF51A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify and assess the risks to United States flight crews, air carriers, manufacturers, and other stakeholders in the aviation industry associated with CVRs capable of recording more than 2 hours of data; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE751E49533D14F8683BF0890A7B54CF6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide recommendations on measures to adopt to mitigate against such risks and ensure that any use of CVR data serves the sole purpose of a safety investigation, including recommendations for the United States to make to ICAO to mitigate these risks.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HB48B0FCDBF1D417FACB538C0E1F5B40D"><enum>11.</enum><header>Transparency in aircraft maintenance and repair work</header> <subsection id="HBFE3CDDF490843DDB8E68654F369757B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall update the guidelines of the FAA for part 121 certificate holders in implementing a Continuing Analysis and Surveillance System (CASS) for their air carrier maintenance programs to include reporting no less than once every 6 months by certificate holders to the FAA of any failure to follow procedures in aircraft maintenance as well as any major alteration, complete overhaul, or repair of mechanical irregularities of each airframe, engine, propeller, and appliance.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B435451F21146E7953F297905BD3ACD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Advisory</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall issue an advisory with formatting guidelines for air carriers to report information as required under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H02B934424B9C42D997B34810EF29D947"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each instance of a failure to follow procedures and for each major alteration, overhaul, or repair reported under the requirements of this section, the Administrator shall require certificate holders to include any name and any physical address where the work is carried out for each maintenance provider that performs work.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9BE4AE1B0F644C6C82464D919F708BFA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <quote>major alterations</quote>, <quote>airframe</quote>, <quote>propeller</quote>, and <quote>appliance</quote> have the meanings given such terms in part 1 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HFA22F2DED5904706A9A9539A7C100EDF"><enum>12.</enum><header>Review of FAA’s Aviation Safety Inspection Program</header> <subsection id="HF3C17AEB77094E4EB8CE87215881CCB1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Audit by the Department of Transportation Inspector General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Inspector General of the Department of Transportation shall initiate a review of the FAA’s August 2017 Flight Standards reorganization and its aviation safety inspection program.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7A5CD9BBBE284E36BF0C00631CB0320C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The review shall include an evaluation of—</text> <paragraph id="H640254075DA5458E8F7A26205CBE1C54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the FAA Flight Standards reorganization from a geographic-based system to a functional-based system;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7E7646446EC14224BC6B0B5401411E0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the implementation of the FAA’s Compliance Philosophy as it relates to safety inspections and enforcements;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFBB6AB40AB96411BA0C4A5FFFC6D1AEE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the FAA’s oversight system known as the Safety Assurance System (SAS);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D6DEBE13CDC4F4BAE9EBA61921376A1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>training for aviation safety inspector and operational research analysts on the Compliance Philosophy and SAS; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76927E9FCE34417796FD96DDC5E31E45"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the impact of the FAA’s reorganization and SAS on the FAA’s ability to produce reliable estimates of aviation safety inspector and operational research analyst staffing needs.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H01D8645E79E347CFBE05C739D920B158"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Inspector General shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the results of its review and any recommendations to improve the aviation safety inspection program of the FAA.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H6306766650454EAE9794DFF57E35263D"><enum>13.</enum><header>Review of ICAO best available technologies and standards</header> <subsection id="HF40B8DF1679643A9A3142790EF14E1FD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall conduct a study on the International Civil Aviation Organization’s best available technologies and standards.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H82170E12841D4116BC19F3FB2C79D605"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report containing the timeline for the Federal Aviation Administrator to adopt the best available technologies and standards studied under subsection (a) and, if the Administrator determines the Administrator will not adopt any such technologies or standards, a justification as to the reason for not adopting. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H7E02417B2B434ECEA166A93F6E57FD1D"><enum>14.</enum><header>Whistleblower protections audit</header> <subsection id="H79C4E58261DB4F78AAE4C7B8813A7955"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the inspector general of the Department of Transportation shall conduct an audit of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H35A742581A174FD3B09C2FC8AB9460AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>existing whistleblower protections and standards and practices in place for the aviation industry; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE099EBB8232146CF86B38E9918C56A5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the whistleblower program of the Federal Aviation Administration, including how such program has evolved since the most recent audit by the inspector general and whether there are any shortcomings or challenges for the program. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAED3534528BD46239E61643898418664"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the publication of the results of the audit under subsection (a), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall submit to the relevant committees of jurisdiction of Congress a report on the implementation plan for any recommendations from such audit and any reasons for not implementing any recommendation for which the Administrator will not implement. </text></subsection> </section> <section id="HDD1E9C86091F46448E0B25B17DFC8CC5"><enum>15.</enum><header>Two pilot rule</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall issue such regulations as are necessary to require that all part 121 air carriers providing air transportation of passengers or cargo require a minimum of 2 pilots in the cockpit for any flight carrying such passengers or cargo.</text></section> 
<section id="H6DA583FA1C8249009E393DC504829D8F"><enum>16.</enum><header>Flight safety information protection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 40123 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H7DDFFB22CD754F2FBEAF9897B06EF25B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="HF1FAFADC877042728B263846E2586530"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Flight safety information protection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may not disclose under this section flight safety information, including flight safety information voluntarily reported by Federal Aviation Administration employees, and data provided from flight data recorders, service difficulty recorders, accident and incident data systems, airline required crew narrative reports and summaries, ADS–B, aircraft communication addressing and reporting systems, and ATC voice communications and recorded radar data. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H70C39DCBFA7544A7B0A4A750CC884637"><enum>17.</enum><header>Knowledge safety experts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator shall take such actions as are necessary to ensure that any advisory committee of the Federal Aviation Administration that provides recommendations on topics that relate to or impact the safety of passengers, aircraft, crew members, ground crew, airports, or any other safety aspect have representation from knowledge safety experts in addition to representation from trade industry experts.</text></section> <section id="HAB8632D47B4249CE96C43BE27AB96A20"><enum>18.</enum><header>Transparency in aviation industry</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator shall take such actions as are necessary to ensure that air carriers and other persons providing air transportation are prohibited from hiding information determined to be important by the Administrator in any investigation regarding aircraft incidents, including incidents that result in death or injury. </text></section> 
<section id="H21E247E590504CE0A9AB1A508F121DAC"><enum>19.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H43CAAC71741F49BBBCD9468C2A081BBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0148EAEE54647D68EF66386E5DA05D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered event</header><text>The term <quote>covered event</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HA66FE653A66C4E4DBB853FD0002AAE1E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a category A or B runway incursion, as defined in Order 7050.1B of the Federal Aviation Administration (dated November 3, 2013);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H67E19FF5DE524EB787ACD76F3F7216DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a landing on a taxiway, incorrect runway, or other area not designed as a runway at a public-use airport on land;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H55006B3B6CBC4403A1A0ABF599E47D61"><enum>(C)</enum><text>descent by an aircraft below 300 feet above ground level on approach to a taxiway, incorrect runway, or other area not designed as a runway at a public-use airport on land; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F180D505A7E4F97BCC5B1EAE431F30F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a landing by an aircraft notwithstanding an instruction by air traffic control that the aircraft perform a missed approach or go-around.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47F04A465E9A4B67952E8651EB42BFD1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>FAA</header><text>The term <quote>FAA</quote> means the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H26F32FC82BF0481B883AEEAF8D0CC1D4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Part 121 air carrier</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>part 121 air carrier</quote> means an air carrier that holds a certificate issued under part 121 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B070E0CD28547ED983A3D6DF2D05C71"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Part 129 air carrier</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>part 129 air carrier</quote> means an air carrier that holds a certificate issued under part 129 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

