<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF47B78757A39411C9C9E97BF07C099C2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6470 IH: Restore Honor to Service Members Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6470</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231121">November 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for outreach to build awareness among former members of the Armed Forces of the process established pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 for the review of discharge characterizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB7DAE9798660423693CDB5262CC83908" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9F3149DE5CAD4C1AA8BDF56996D44B1F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restore Honor to Service Members Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HB6B3C33AE7214AE2AC47C5203E4F365D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tiger Team for outreach to former members</header> <subsection id="HD29C263A60BA428789926E35D35AEEAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Tiger Team</header> <paragraph id="H20A0CC0EA97643DD99F1437C7BF16578"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall establish a team (commonly known as a <quote>tiger team</quote> and referred to in this section as the <quote>Tiger Team</quote>) responsible for conducting outreach to build awareness among former members of the Armed Forces of the process established pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1552">10 U.S.C. 1552</external-xref> note) for the review of discharge characterizations by appropriate discharge boards. The Tiger Team shall consist of appropriate personnel of the Department of Defense assigned to the Tiger Team by the Secretary for purposes of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD3DDB4C4B97045C5A8F33E220FA64699"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tiger Team leader</header><text>One of the individuals assigned to the Tiger Team under paragraph (1) shall be a senior-level officer or employee of the Department who shall serve as the lead official of the Tiger Team (in this section referred to as the <quote>Tiger Team Leader</quote>) and who shall be accountable for the activities of the Tiger Team under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H290C423592EC4719B5763308B05AC523"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report on composition</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report setting forth the names of the personnel of the Department assigned to the Tiger Team pursuant to this subsection, including the positions to which such personnel are assigned. The report shall specify the name of the individual assigned as Tiger Team Leader.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H555BD3AD5DC5445996751E9375650DC2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header> 
<paragraph id="H36A332DA392E49FCA9D84FB95248F6D1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Tiger Team shall conduct outreach to build awareness among veterans of the process established pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 for the review of discharge characterizations by appropriate discharge boards.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74001CEE34414FA9A228418C69281868"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In conducting activities under this subsection, the Tiger Team Leader shall identify appropriate external stakeholders with whom the Tiger Team shall work to carry out such activities. Such stakeholders shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HADB444CC10714E238152770C4D24011B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H81F6C9CC23AB43E39DB89B78B7E93705"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Archivist of the United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H29501EA82D37493D81E402C0B7BCB05B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Representatives of veterans service organizations.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D282F84E59744A2A6989375BB4BEF06"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other stakeholders as the Tiger Team Leader considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB94D5E1A53C44DF8E7A3F7347DC2034"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 210 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to Congress the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HBBCFD388D77A4D74B23A9F2103D2755A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A plan setting forth the following:</text> 
<clause id="H07BA31D9334A455CA657B47EEBA3015F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A description of the manner in which the Secretary, working through the Tiger Team and in collaboration with external stakeholders described in paragraph (2), shall identify individuals who meet the criteria in section 527(b) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 for review of discharge characterization.</text></clause> <clause id="H2B45899AC3BC4AAEB4DE8B16A1837783"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A description of the manner in which the Secretary, working through the Tiger Team and in collaboration with the external stakeholders, shall improve outreach to individuals who meet the criteria in section 527(b) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 for review of discharge characterization, including through—</text> 
<subclause id="H50B6F77F0F404FFD81EA59B3C668B51B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>obtaining contact information on such individuals; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB8CC401E4441440B9C12F75A48029108"><enum>(II)</enum><text>contacting such individuals on the process established pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 for the review of discharge characterizations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HED7E8E54FD00455AB27918A0AF03F34E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the manner in which the work described in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (A) will be carried out, including an allocation of the work among the Tiger Team and the external stakeholders.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC0B594B1ACAC42F2888AE11D26E1AE26"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A schedule for the implementation, carrying out, and completion of the plan required under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H09EFF4125E8540AFA78E399CB728F6B1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of the additional funding, personnel, or other resources of the Department required to carry out the plan required under subparagraph (A), including any modification of applicable statutory or administrative authorities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H427D9A6852864B3FB2A2D6156284263A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Implementation of plan</header> <subparagraph id="H6B4461E4A22348418E8BB96E6F69B2A7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall implement and carry out the plan submitted under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (3) in accordance with the schedule submitted under subparagraph (C) of that paragraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA172FE2E6344A6E8E6F57B736BDD3DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Not less frequently than once every 90 days after the submittal of the report under paragraph (3), the Tiger Team shall submit to Congress an update on the carrying out of the plan submitted under subparagraph (A) of that paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H668D16EBDAF94E2DBAE242ACAE07F6AB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Tiger Team shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives a final report on the activities of the Tiger Team under this subsection. The report shall set forth the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFE056D3951CA46F1B0A9E4CDF4EA9265"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of individuals discharged under former section 654 or a similar policy prior to the enactment of former section 654.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35B07B6223414E789F0428A286BCEBA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of individuals described in subparagraph (A) who availed themselves of a review of discharge characterization (whether through discharge review or correction of military records) through a process established prior to the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DFE0563434B45769B9F9EF4CBA0B26C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of individuals contacted through outreach conducted pursuant to this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4CF42EDDDCC247DAB57C7A9B224E27B3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The number of individuals described in subparagraph (A) who availed themselves of a review of discharge characterization through the process established pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5021DAC687DB44428563D2FE5EF6C43B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The number of individuals described in subparagraph (D) whose review of discharge characterization resulted in a change of characterization to honorable discharge.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE913386C80764F699728F23241B9163F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The total number of individuals described in subparagraph (A), including individuals also covered by subparagraph (E), whose review of discharge characterization since September 20, 2011, resulted in a change of characterization to honorable discharge.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD72DC84F7AA546F4942C56B065CC4EE6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>On the date that is 60 days after the date on which the final report required by paragraph (5) is submitted, the Secretary shall terminate the Tiger Team.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE13E776B093E40D6BC28CD2961B888F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional reports</header> <paragraph id="HA12EB5234F1F42B2A5DEFB14D0B5BBA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall conduct a review of the consistency and uniformity of the reviews conducted pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H36D099BD551A45AA8F54C09967F87E71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and each year thereafter for a four-year period, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to Congress a report on the reviews under paragraph (1). Such reports shall include any comments or recommendations for continued actions.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H784B8CAFF72E4554848CB7D15752C3A2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Former section 654 defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>former section 654</term> means section 654 of title 10, United States Code, as in effect before such section was repealed pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/321">Public Law 111–321</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/654">10 U.S.C. 654</external-xref> note).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H3A0B38330FE948F79C20149A69EF7BCB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Relief for impacted former members</header> 
<subsection id="HD9037BCA2EE441CE9158F8ABA636A838"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review of discharge</header> 
<paragraph id="HA406280BEBCC46D0A9DA2C8A86F7593D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall review and update existing guidance to ensure that the appropriate discharge board for the military departments concerned shall review a discharge characterization of the covered member as required under section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 at the request of a covered member, or their representative, notwithstanding any requirements to provide documentation necessary to initiate a review of a discharge characterization. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H56A8614953734BD6AA0407E7716C595A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The appropriate discharge board for the military departments concerned shall not be required to initiate a request for a review of a discharge as described in paragraph (1) if there is evidence available to the discharge board that is unrelated to the material request of the covered member or the representative of the covered member but that would have reasonably substantiated the discharge decision of the military department. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H17D496E4293B4006B79FBC95BFE66265"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Veterans benefits</header> 
<paragraph id="H5E88DB35DC124E4F9EE76A3ECF1001BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date of change of characterization for veterans benefits</header><text>For purposes of the provision of benefits to which veterans are entitled under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to a covered member whose discharge characterization is changed pursuant to section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1552">10 U.S.C. 1552</external-xref> note), the date of discharge of the member from the Armed Forces shall be deemed to be the effective date of the change of discharge characterization under that section. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B1E4098DFB34212B9F12BC7951CC44A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize any benefit to a covered member in connection with the change of discharge characterization of the member under section 527 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1552">10 U.S.C. 1552</external-xref> note) for any period before the effective date of the change of discharge characterization. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

