<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAC4B0629255E4D79A5C6364031EBE804" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2405 IH: North Dakota Trust Lands Completion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2405</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000377">Mr. Armstrong</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To authorize the relinquishment and in lieu selection of land and minerals in the State of North Dakota, to restore land and minerals to Indian Tribes within the State of North Dakota, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HF4779E08EC08446FA6D619C524903473" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6357DC8FB6C64BDC9CDA952EA8135BA0"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>North Dakota Trust Lands Completion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1B9A019C8E1A4CA7B25D43BBE35C642E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2BE4B7A0A2B047B6ACF28B10DA2E5608"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in 1889, Congress enacted the North Dakota Enabling Act <quote>to provide for the division of Dakota into two States and to enable the people of North Dakota, South Dakota, Montana, and Washington to form constitutions and State governments and to be admitted into the Union on an equal footing with the original States, and to make donations of public lands to such States</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F2B6CC7522C4C6FAB15ADF46CBDB1EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 10 of the North Dakota Enabling Act (25 Stat. 679, chapter 180)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H672236BEF29E468DA42B2B07F373E320"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with certain exceptions, granted sections 16 and 36 in every township to the new States of North Dakota, South Dakota, Montana, and Washington <quote>for the support of common schools</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D14C89A40104BF0889EE8F6C2B19C5B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in cases where portions of sections 16 and 36 had been reserved, granted, or sold prior to those States attaining statehood, authorized indemnity or <quote>in lieu</quote> selections;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B05BD75E5BA46E3A331BC5E20B17E2E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the State of North Dakota was granted land and minerals totaling more than 2,500,000 acres under the North Dakota Enabling Act; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H24F914EBEF83490FACA78DA0F2F0E086"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the North Dakota Enabling Act provided further land grants to the State of North Dakota for the support of colleges, universities, the State capitol, and other public institutions;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF45C82B042D481DBF55B5E381543D52"><enum>(5)</enum><text>prior to the enactment of the North Dakota Enabling Act, the United States, through treaties and Executive orders, including the Treaty between the United States of America and the Mandan, Hidatsa, Arikara, and other Tribal Nations, made and concluded at Fort Laramie September 17, 1851 (11 Stat. 749), the Treaty between the United States of America and the Sisseton and Wahpeton Bands of Dakota or Sioux Indians, made and concluded at Washington February 19, 1867 (15 Stat. 505), the Treaty between the United States of America and different Tribes of Sioux Indians, made and concluded at Fort Laramie April 29, 1868 (15 Stat. 635), and the Executive order of April 12, 1870, established several reservations of land for multiple Indian Tribes located in the State of North Dakota; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD63028F22CE846B4838036106433335C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>authorizing the State to relinquish the State land grant parcels located within the reservations and to select other Federal land or minerals in lieu of the relinquished State land grant parcels will—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H1973532908FB4B2E8A317CDEB026BA03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fulfill the promise of land and minerals to the State; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC99AA894AA404E3FAAE045962BCACB27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide to Indian Tribes greater Tribal sovereignty and control of land and minerals within the reservations; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H050FDDFA247949BFAA408C04D89F7B13"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Congress should authorize the State—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC87EC12BAC7347B1B53E57C207E2E3C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to relinquish the land and minerals located within the reservations; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HA8A45B47B86540B082B43DE429A42C70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to select in lieu of the relinquished land other Federal land or minerals in the State of North Dakota of equal value.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H4AAFF0B78A0C49408B261BE636C479FB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H947AC0151FB048EB8A583D13309C516E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal land</header><text>The term <term>Federal land</term> means public land and minerals located within the State of North Dakota, including public land that is mineral in character.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CD721C7A8494E0A914574DEFEFF81FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>North Dakota Enabling Act</header><text>The term <term>North Dakota Enabling Act</term> means the Act of February 22, 1889 (25 Stat. 676, chapter 180).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF27D37D2A2B4437CB58FD2C986365818"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public land</header><text>The term <term>public land</term> has the meaning given the term <term>public lands</term> in section 103 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1702">43 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7F740941BE2347389825B8D50496FF4C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>The term <term>reservation</term> means any Indian reservation located wholly or partially within the State of North Dakota and recognized under United States treaty, Executive order, or Act of Congress. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58E8C3F25E774FDEA79ED809751D2538"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5CBFFDDAC38949DABBFD4E725A8DDD6A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means the State of North Dakota, acting through the North Dakota Board of University and School Lands and its agent, the Department of Trust Lands.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0974E2989D6C48D6AE3326802DC9D533"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State land grant parcel</header><text>The term <term>State land grant parcel</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H625794AD371B41ADA918CC569BEA6AA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a parcel of land granted to the State of North Dakota by Congress—</text> 
<clause id="HCAD9C048491C460C995D4E00B35D5358"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on statehood; or</text></clause> <clause id="H8217294EF5F44E0E94F87C896713F9A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through a grant pursuant to the North Dakota Enabling Act; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2B5B9C163B9548A0A1A8A5CF40B84276"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a section of land numbered 16 or 36 granted to the State of North Dakota by Congress for school purposes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEE0449A89E99482BA322F890C535CD68"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a parcel of land selected by the State of North Dakota as indemnity for any section of land numbered 16 or 36; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H386E4E03DE9348148A3BD1D19CB083B7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a parcel of land other than a parcel of land described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) obtained by the State after statehood.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA973687B68684E8C836EB687672F44F4"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Unappropriated Federal land</header> <subparagraph id="HEE30D145F2AB42D49F9D1D03A9E8AACD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>unappropriated Federal land</term> means Federal land under the management and control of the Bureau of Land Management and located within the State of North Dakota.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0CB57C5E512841C0A84D1E8D66A07D40"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>The term <term>unappropriated Federal land</term> does not include—</text> <clause id="HBE68ED646C21413B9EAB3AF56B21EF7F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>surface interests acquired by the Bureau of Land Management;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB18420E91F164A2693EFCE6819173196"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any area of critical environmental concern established pursuant to section 202(c)(3) of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1712">43 U.S.C. 1712(c)(3)</external-xref>); or</text></clause> <clause id="H2C7A184AACB84158B2D0157E7AA19379"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>land that is—</text> 
<subclause id="H1D20C734F3594DCFBF124CD0BB5A31A7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>withdrawn from public entry;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H661E7B799B7F472E9E7C67A7300C2DC4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>located within a unit of the National Park System;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H17DC3697A00048DCAD2DCBB9C49307C8"><enum>(III)</enum><text>located within any reservation;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB867C3C3C1154DFE8E20FD5C14B91A51"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>located within—</text> 
<item id="H5F7BB6DD67A34131937B16F2A03CAFEE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>T. 147 N., R. 95 W.;</text></item> <item id="H309D38656F3F4B7E915891CD586014BA"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>T. 148 N., R. 95 W.; </text></item> 
<item id="H43CEC3B3BFC2498CAC6D0A1126467B7D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>T. 148 N., R. 96 W.; or </text></item> <item id="H1EBFAAD4F4BD45EE95905324D8595E15"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>T. 149 N., R. 95 W.;</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0F03B394C7A84299A2103C283FCCF142"><enum>(V)</enum><text>located within a United States military reservation; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H99DB40F3E582413C9D04F365814DF2FB"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>designated by Congress or the President for conservation purposes. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HE451F6145C5E4E978697E64FAE12A8C6"><enum>4.</enum><header>Relinquishment and selection; conveyance</header> 
<subsection id="H6E883DCB7E964E5A8DB8FC803EC03EA0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Relinquishment and selection</header> 
<paragraph id="H8DDC4463998F43E98F87D5807082EF78"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to valid existing rights, if the State elects to relinquish all right, title, and interest of the State in and to a State land grant parcel located wholly or partially within the boundaries of any reservation, the Secretary shall authorize the State to select in accordance with this Act 1 or more parcels of unappropriated Federal land of substantially equivalent value within the State of North Dakota.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC620E89716424EA282801A2E5047E102"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Approval</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the State makes a selection under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall approve or reject, in whole or in part, the selection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H7AE96F8B220540B7B7C3EB134E8662B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conveyance</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HB5D6FE5840E14B2DB5653696014E1C95"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Conveyance by Secretary</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H10ADE1447BD746A8B8848A50335A7CEA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which the Secretary approves a State selection of unappropriated Federal land under subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall initiate the actions necessary to convey to the State the unappropriated Federal land.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4EE125837BD04360918D1428F78B6C8D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Conveyance of Federal land by the Secretary under this Act—</text> 
<clause id="HFB951BC369F14716AF0AF5DDE4CE13E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be by clear list, patent, or deed acceptable to the State; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H808304729074470DA2D6EBDFD32369C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be considered a sale, exchange, or conveyance under section 203, 205, 206, or 209 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1713">43 U.S.C. 1713</external-xref>, 1715, 1716, 1719). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9F80722AA3849E68B37DC016F7BEB85"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relinquishment and conveyance by State</header> 
<subparagraph id="H0BFBBD48121C4A5ABCBA13BECF6C9EAF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As consideration for the conveyance of Federal land under paragraph (1), on the date on which the Federal land is conveyed to the State, the State shall concurrently relinquish and convey to the Secretary all right, title, and interest of the State in and to the State land grant parcel identified for relinquishment under subsection (a)(1).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57BF3DC9525842758058E6715B154405"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Title</header><text>The State shall convey to the Secretary title, free of any financial claims, liabilities, or other financial encumbrances, to all parcels relinquished under subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD0844B7D10F4CE7951309E0EDD146D2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Relinquishment and conveyance by the State of a State land grant parcel under this Act shall not be considered an exchange or acquisition for purposes of section 205 or 206 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1715">43 U.S.C. 1715</external-xref>, 1716).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3D88B9E1DE36462D973BFADC56AFDA22"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Succession to rights and obligations</header><text>Each party to which land is conveyed under this Act shall, to the fullest extent allowable under Federal and State law, succeed to the rights and obligations of the conveying party with respect to any lease, right-of-way, permit, or other valid existing right to which the land is subject.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H09A15C6EE24847B49C9A5DEB049B5470"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Management after relinquishment</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H403FA6D382A141EAB5B10DDE3354A8AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>If a State land grant parcel relinquished by the State and conveyed to the Secretary under this Act is located wholly or partially within the boundaries of any reservation, on request of the applicable Indian Tribe, the portion of the State land grant parcel located within the boundaries of the reservation shall be—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H89A50181AC3A4ABCBBF6E022DF78CBDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>taken into trust by the Secretary on behalf of, and for the benefit of, the Indian Tribe on the date of the conveyance; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCCEBA2C552044EDCA2325DD791FEAE74"><enum>(B)</enum><text>considered to be a part of the reservation of the Indian Tribe.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB323D317700C4FCF893B27625AD9C534"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation required</header><text>Prior to the conveyance of a State land grant parcel located wholly or partially within the boundaries of any reservation, the State and the Secretary shall consult with the Indian Tribe the land of which is subject to conveyance in accordance with Executive Order 13175 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301</external-xref> note; relating to consultation and coordination with Indian tribal governments). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDA959862F77A40A18F28020316685570"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special rules for mineral land</header> 
<paragraph id="H82D44E55A8084FBBB117E3325F348296"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of unappropriated Federal land subject to a lease or permit</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>unappropriated Federal land subject to a lease or permit</term> means unappropriated Federal land subject to a mineral lease or permit that is—</text> <subparagraph id="HA807274BCC424DA59BF81706A40B8851"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issued under the <act-name parsable-cite="MLA">Mineral Leasing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/181">30 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H41C4629F98B945C996832140571CB675"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a producing or producible status during the 10-year period following the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7DDB9C108C924639A6E733DC1DB62C55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of mineral land</header><text>The State may select, and the Secretary may convey, unappropriated Federal land that is mineral in character under subsection (b) on the condition that, except as provided in paragraph (3)(A), if the selected land is unappropriated Federal land subject to a lease or permit—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF111B013DD0C4E51AF4F689E41301A00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary shall reserve an overriding interest in the portion of the mineral estate that is comprised of minerals subject to leasing under the <act-name parsable-cite="MLA">Mineral Leasing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/181">30 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H719A2CE4A0784D62B5CC0D932FCEFC29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such a selection shall not include any portion of the mineral lease or permit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H351A1EF3147E46F0B6D96EB8BD37E567"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conveyance of mineral estate</header> 
<subparagraph id="H7F25526526F34683A89C6DB3D6B8A5FE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the State selects unappropriated Federal land subject to a lease or permit under paragraph (2), on the option of the State—</text> <clause id="HCB9A02539CFE427F8C0986963C28ACC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary may convey with the surface interest in the land the interest in the mineral estate that is comprised of minerals subject to leasing under the <act-name parsable-cite="MLA">Mineral Leasing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/181">30 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6DCD38B079A04AF0B8E3D00F302BF42C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>all Federal mining claims over the land shall be converted to State leases in accordance with this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HCC2E9CCBFEAA44B4BF2AE865421D6A5C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Mining claims</header><text>To facilitate the conversion of Federal mining claims to State leases under subparagraph (A), a Federal mining claimant may file with the Secretary a voluntary relinquishment of the Federal mining claim conditioned on—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="HD4E4BC1C87FC42D5AC232685BE5A123D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conveyance of the land to the State; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HAB0E238A01614D268F1459A4A47E176B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the conversion of the Federal mining claim to a State lease.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H24B358E3530E492983AECDA4DB3BF7F6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Obligations under Federal law</header><text>Until the date on which the land is conveyed to the State under subparagraph (A), a Federal mining claimant shall be subject to any obligations relating to the land under Federal law.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF379385A0CC64B5085010E0ECEAA7F65"><enum>(D)</enum><header>No relinquishment</header><text>If the land previously encumbered by the relinquished Federal mining claim is not conveyed to the State under subparagraph (A), the relinquishment of land under subparagraph (B) shall have no effect.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H446D5FAB4B8641A3BEC50241CCD67E36"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rights-of-way; other interest</header><text>On conveyance to the State of land encumbered by a relinquished Federal mining claim under this paragraph, the State shall assume authority over any leases, licenses, permits, rights-of-way, operating plans, other land use authorizations, or reclamation obligations applicable to the relinquished Federal mining claim on the date of conveyance.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H798E7AEA56B74D3890E46CC408C72DEE"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Valuation</header><text>If a Federal mining claimant does not voluntarily relinquish under subparagraph (B) a Federal mining claim on land conveyed to the State, the Secretary shall take into account the encumbrance represented by the claim in determining the value of the land under section 5(b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF6B4C83C039A4CDCA1A532AB42B7FDCA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Withdrawal</header> 
<paragraph id="H599CBA7DA9F04F48806DB0A5A03EEEE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to valid rights in existence on the date of enactment of this Act, all Federal land selected by the State for conveyance under this Act, effective beginning on the date on which the State makes the selection and ending on the date described in paragraph (2), is withdrawn from all forms of—</text> <subparagraph id="HAC9FBA558B7C4C91BBA9A099BA83485F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>entry, appropriation, or disposal under the public land laws;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H10EF2939C89D40A3A308BD75E2D38BAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>location, entry, and patent under the mining laws; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF6C5998144274745ACADACFE8999CB68"><enum>(C)</enum><text>disposition under all laws pertaining to mineral and geothermal leasing or mineral materials.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A5933EF9CF043D7A3DCDC8740EBE8C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Date described</header><text>The date referred to in paragraph (1) is the date on which, as applicable—</text> <subparagraph id="HFE9EEEC00A6E430D9DCC78121CC9B36C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federal land is conveyed by the Secretary to the State;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7860BA0B402747288AEEB9BF031F3995"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary rejects the selection under subsection (a)(2); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H50F4A21881AC45F6B7C0424E9789A7ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the State withdraws the selection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H6DEF24B9A1D84D728136F2739171C4C8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Valuation</header> 
<subsection id="HFB128184DEA04F0393CC7911D69E59E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Equal value</header><text>With respect to a State land grant parcel conveyed under this Act in consideration for a parcel of Federal land selected in accordance with this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H55F58A92BCAC4233BC2F1EACEC0E9F9B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the overall value of the State land grant parcel and the overall value of the parcel of Federal land shall be substantially equal; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAFAEBCBBD14D4CD0BC500EC881AB75AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subject to subsection (c), if the overall value of the parcels is not equal, the party conveying the parcel of lesser value shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HA765353F02D54EDD8B496619BB5BAAA0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>equalize the value by the payment of funds to the other party; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7CDED41227DD48089E50F80DDEE13DB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enter the imbalance in value on a ledger account in accordance with subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC987878B00E74B83B5B34874B8DBEEA6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appraisal required</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (d), the Secretary shall determine the value of a State land grant parcel and a parcel of Federal land to be conveyed under this Act through an appraisal completed in accordance with—</text> 
<paragraph id="H24F93129CE644DD9841BB3F36F5BFAD0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Uniform Appraisal Standards for Federal Land Acquisitions; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB6D6459C07384D5FB934C46F74AB61F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subject to subsection (d)(1), the Uniform Standards for Professional Appraisal Practice.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF5DFAD2B8FEE42A3883E293F7BE7BFED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Equalization</header><text>With respect to a conveyance to the Secretary of a State land grant parcel of lesser value than the parcel of Federal land to be conveyed to the State under this Act, the total value of the equalization payment described in subsection (a)(2)(A) or the ledger entry described in subsection (e), as applicable, may not exceed 25 percent of the total value of the parcel of Federal land.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF87C3DF67E904921BC4767F80606B545"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Low value parcels</header> <paragraph id="HCD84C75F278843FFA91FD3B8E2BBF4DF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, with the consent of the State, may use mass appraisals, a summary appraisal, or a statement of value made by a qualified appraiser carried out in accordance with the Uniform Standards for Professional Appraisal Practice to determine the value of a State land grant parcel or a parcel of Federal land to be conveyed under this Act instead of an appraisal that complies with the Uniform Appraisal Standards for Federal Land Acquisitions if the State and the Secretary agree that market value of the State land grant parcel or parcel of Federal land, as applicable, is—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6E4F01AA5605434D8F5B0A09F7F017A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>less than $500,000; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC81F8EB0ECAE4A24A66EDD6BF19D50B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>less than $500 per acre.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDB077E7002DA4750B50A1478C35981D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Division</header><text>A State land grant parcel or a parcel of Federal land may not be artificially divided in order to qualify for a summary appraisal, mass appraisal, or statement of value under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H60A28A62DB9D4A228903A0C6628DA8F4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Ledger accounts</header> <paragraph id="H181C80055E0D43958C7F3126D478AEF7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to a State land grant parcel conveyed under this Act in consideration for a parcel of Federal land, if the overall value of the parcels is not equal, the Secretary and the State may agree to use a ledger account to make equal the value.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H404EA8CD02E44CC5B6A7007E6BC78343"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Imbalances</header><text>A ledger account described in paragraph (1) shall reflect imbalances in value to be reconciled in a subsequent transaction.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CCD8EA5F35245BF92BEC49BC914BE65"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Account balancing</header><text>Each ledger account described in paragraph (1) shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8FA0645D70964F3D8F2499EC44F3890F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>balanced not later than 3 years after the date on which the ledger account is established; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H47A6D1E7C4D6405EB01764F10BBE22CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>closed not later than 5 years after the date of the last conveyance of land under this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H04AE646AFFBE4F7DAAA4B0E1DA3238FA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Costs</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA9EE47ED5029455B88D4B52EC6400DB9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary or the State may assume costs or other responsibilities or requirements for conveying land under this Act that ordinarily are borne by the other party.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H147A41356EDB4446A436C1417760DEE2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Adjustment</header><text>If the Secretary or the State assume costs or other responsibilities under subparagraph (A), the Secretary or the State shall make adjustments to the value of the Federal land conveyed to the State to compensate the Secretary or the State, as applicable, for assuming the costs or other responsibilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4DC3CCB7D584D9EB11338DE258ED219"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Mineral land</header><text>If value is attributed to any parcel of Federal land that has been selected by the State because of the presence of minerals under a lease entered into under the Mineral Leasing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/181">30 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>) that is in a producing or producible status, and the lease is to be conveyed under this Act, the value of the parcel shall be reduced by the amount that represents the likely Federal revenue sharing obligation under the Mineral Leasing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/181">30 U.S.C. 181 et seq.</external-xref>) with the State, but the adjustment shall not be considered as reflecting a property right of the State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HCC886EB094C54352ADC5B713BC173527"><enum>6.</enum><header>Miscellaneous</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H250EA3776B684221A03DA40A75153B3B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Land or minerals conveyed under this Act shall be subject to all applicable Federal, State, and Tribal law.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5264D511553B46D28DD8454953FA7052"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Protection of Indian rights</header> 
<paragraph id="HA0BDF39BE94D448FA5FBD4387DE4F9EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Treaty rights</header><text>Nothing in this Act modifies, limits, expands, or otherwise affects any treaty-reserved right or other right of any Indian Tribe recognized by any other means, including treaties or agreements with the United States, Executive orders, statutes, regulations, or case law.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DF23F85953643B2A00CE591F28D0EFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Land or minerals held in trust</header><text>Nothing in this Act affects—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3E38F34634D94F33B22E8CEF904DDA7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>land or minerals held in trust by the United States as of the date of enactment of this Act on behalf of, and for the benefit of, any Indian Tribe; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC58916FC3E3645F7AEC78BB541B5FB0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any individual Indian allotment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB344DDDCF7854CFCB572E1435C6A86E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Hazardous materials</header> 
<paragraph id="H687EBB5055A94C5A9D23E7BA978F32F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the State shall make available for review and inspection any record relating to hazardous materials on land to be conveyed under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H77EC41F482B546A8B46C958EE53D36CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification</header> <subparagraph id="H29CB4E989B6C4DEF9F4B7F9335A97811"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Prior to completing a conveyance of Federal land under this Act, the Secretary shall complete an inspection and a hazardous materials certification of the land to be conveyed. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17818247956A46FDB5310267CDBA3B4D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State land grant parcels</header><text>Prior to completing a conveyance of a State land grant parcel under this Act, the State shall complete an inspection and a hazardous materials certification of the land to be conveyed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2166C088F2A44EFFB444F8DA4D2E382C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grazing permits</header> <paragraph id="H2DC5AF014FD14BFFB780C7A1F0ED3534"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If land conveyed under this Act is subject to a lease, permit, or contract for the grazing of domestic livestock in effect on the date of the conveyance, the Secretary or the State, as applicable, shall allow the grazing to continue for the remainder of the term of the lease, permit, or contract, subject to the related terms and conditions of the user agreements, including permitted stocking rates, grazing fee levels, access, and ownership and use of range improvements.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H42DE581F288C4F82B3A9FF905D6DDB39"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cancellation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3E8CD718CC434C55A8B0EA12FE2E0BDA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this Act prevents the Secretary or the State from canceling or modifying a grazing permit, lease, or contract if the land subject to the permit, lease, or contract is sold, conveyed, transferred, or leased for nongrazing purposes.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4F8FBD19EA149EC846DD90044277E66"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Base properties</header><text>If land conveyed by the State under this Act is used by a grazing permittee or lessee to meet the base property requirements for a Federal grazing permit or lease, the land shall continue to qualify as a base property for the remaining term of the lease or permit and the term of any renewal or extension of the lease or permit.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H93E26E4CF8594AC1AEEBDB13B65007A5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Range improvements</header><text>Nothing in this Act prohibits a holder of a grazing lease, permit, or contract from being compensated for range improvements pursuant to the terms of the lease, permit, or contract under existing Federal or State laws. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HB9800B70438E480E83F19CA04BCC9F0D"><enum>7.</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act applies to or impacts the ownership of any land or mineral resources.</text></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


