<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA18B41680B3046CC83CE513EB984C81E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5396 IH: Coverage Determination Clarity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5396</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to prohibit Medicare local coverage determinations from restricting access to care, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H551D84A5045B4E33BFB9D7C048C479FD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H286C87BD08A94AB780D62EF1525BC6FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Coverage Determination Clarity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9ED5A5E974EA4995B692834FB1FF0FB6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving access to items and services under medicare local coverage determinations</header> <subsection id="H2297927DF8F6450A833BE5ACE0BE0CEF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1862(l)(5) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(l)(5)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H70F439622A804E79947067D56398DAA6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>The Secretary</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subparagraph (E), the Secretary</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3D61AE2B7AD40ACA7F6CC34DDCDD490"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9383C6B7D2AD4C05967A3E02F76AF7F9" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H65B864D5A1AE45E5B4D7BFFB6B5114DF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Prohibition on limiting access items and services</header> 
<clause id="H8A0C266BC3FF4DC0957AAC405B819157"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Review of local coverage determinations</header><text>Beginning in 2024, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall review each local coverage determination in effect as of the date of such review to determine whether such local coverage determination denies, limits, or conditions the coverage or provision of items or services beyond that provided by a national coverage determination that has determined that such items or services be covered nationally under this title.</text></clause> <clause id="H88F1E63F6CA145A6955BA74CE379AB36"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Conflict between a national coverage determination and a local coverage determination</header><text>A local coverage determination denies, limits, or conditions the coverage or provision of items or services for purposes of clause (i) to the extent that such local coverage determination limits access to such items or services by imposing restrictions that do not directly interpret provisions of a national coverage determination that has determined that such items or services be covered nationally under this title.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF56B3409AABA4F8FA8E0B21C263D7478"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Revision of local coverage determinations</header> 
<subclause id="H38383C2A3DDC4685A6303A1B9123D843"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the review conducted by the Secretary under clause (i) determines that a local coverage determination denies, limits, or conditions the coverage or provision of items or services that are approved, cleared, authorized, or licensed under section 505, 510(k), 513, or 515 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act, the Secretary shall direct the appropriate Medicare administrative contractor to expeditiously revise such local coverage determination to eliminate the limitation.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5389A8AFF3EC43E5A8B22CEAC9763707"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>A Medicare administrative contractor shall publish a revised local determination no later than the date that is 180 days after the date on which the Secretary directs such contractor to revise a local coverage determination under subclause (I).</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H73E2268AB105458DBA572EA8EDBCF348"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>New local coverage determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require each Medicare administrative contractor that develops a local coverage determination to ensure that any such local coverage determination does not deny, limit, or condition the coverage or provision of items or services pursuant to clause (ii) beyond that provided by a national coverage determination that has determined that such items or services be covered nationally under this title.</text></clause> <clause id="HE3FAAAAD25B543BC883A560DA621C2F9"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Error verification and corrective actions</header><text>In verifying any potential errors and taking corrective actions, Medicare administrative contractors, comprehensive error rate testing recovery auditors, and unified program integrity contractors and independent review agencies—</text> 
<subclause id="HE2F84BFF2AFF4027A124BE409BE6F178"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall not deviate from local coverage determination provisions applicable in the region in which such verification or corrective action occurs; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HFEC774EC78A643F5B659D77822C0AB66"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall provide transparent review by publishing the names of the reviewers and their qualifications in a place and format available to providers.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H982243C595354333B901438314B93255"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header><text>Beginning in 2025 and each year thereafter, the Secretary shall submit a report to the appropriate committees of Congress on the findings of the review conducted under clause (i) and any local coverage determinations revised pursuant to clause (iii) during the preceding year.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H94457BE824054AEB9FE7DD876C59CE19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to proposed and final local coverage determinations posted on Medicare administrative contractor websites on and after January 1, 2023.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

