<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7A821D7485324D3FAF6963BB4F7ADC19" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 643 IH: Equal Voices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 643</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the total number of Representatives at a number that provides that the average number of constituents represented by a Member from any State is equivalent to the number of constituents represented by the Member from the least populous State and to apportion Representatives among the States accordingly, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAD575EC2A1CE407A8DC4661F85B5C64F" style="OLC"><section id="HA385FF254D0D4BA1BE8F3F4CCD624304" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header><subsection id="H7C25000BD9DD46599B158DA214BB268D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Equal Voices Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H16B7E95EDFA14E1492F1B2E110105DDE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HC51D39E188AF4A4F9ECB8906EC38BBC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Our Nation’s founders intended the House of Representatives to be the chamber closest to the American people: <quote>the People’s House</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08D57CB2358A4E478F8DA11F4D8E00D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of Representatives in Congress has been 435 since 1911 when the U.S. population was 92,228,531 (1910 U.S. Census). The U.S. population has grown to more than three times that size to 331,449,281 in 2020 (2020 U.S. Census) while the size of the House has remained the same.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8B2DB98560542B4A5BE4661FAEC20F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Our electorate has changed significantly since the size of the House last grew in 1911. Prior to the passage of the 19th Amendment in 1920, the Civil Rights Act in 1957, and the Voting Rights Act in 1965, women and people of color faced barriers and in some cases, legal prohibitions, to voting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE64437C471CA4CADA80937186F5AA3C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>When the cap on the size of the House was statutorily set in 1929, the average Member of the House represented approximately 280,000 people, compared to approximately 762,000 people in 2020.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H433A577187864D83A348DB52EF2D0CE9"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based on the 2020 Census, individuals in the State with the smallest population, Wyoming, had 1.3x more relative representation compared to the national average district size.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4038F18A54E4880B7833E0E5128570B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Each Member of the House represents far more people on average than legislators in nearly all developed and developing democracies, and is an outlier among other member countries of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), with nearly 3 times the citizen to representative ratio as Japan, the country with next largest district size.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3A73515E7974B129C1E084C6AE6AED6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Representatives who serve fewer people are more likely to have contact with their constituents, receive higher marks for their constituent service, and better reflect the views of their districts.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HECA07FA5A3D042AA9BCD18BC00123C63" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of number of Members of House of Representatives on basis of number of constituents of least-populous State</header><subsection id="HEBDF36D88EF348A78016B8963E754980"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Method for determination of number</header><text>Section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="H90A19AFBE38C4EA1B0B9663344FD5C94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(a) On the first day</quote> and inserting <quote>(a)(1) On the first day</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A6B646F8F134FBD9B95B97AC5DB263C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the then existing number of Representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>the number of Representatives determined under paragraph (2)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C9F2021C7CF4153B725B6383F8A2F10"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" id="HB01600D0CC354D7EB204D980B4172070" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H56BE0E2305F64C8F948BF466D6FF0A5C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of Representatives determined under this paragraph is, with respect to a regular decennial census of the population of the United States, a number equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H93674171A93E44579359C076A5D7DA34"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the whole number of persons in all States (as shown in the statement under paragraph (1)); divided by</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A5CC3D30DB14A428F13615E1EC7D72B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the whole number of persons in the State with the smallest whole number of persons (as shown in such statement),</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">rounded to the nearest whole odd number.</continuation-text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA665C49A90D54A3A98BC564B0B252A90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>The first section and section 2 of the Act entitled <quote>An Act For the apportionment of Representatives in Congress among the several States under the Thirteenth Census</quote>, approved August 8, 1911 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2">2 U.S.C. 2</external-xref> note), are repealed.</text></subsection><subsection id="H92DB40F8EC5F4C54B443DB0DF033A5FE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to the first regular decennial census conducted after the date of the enactment of this Act and each subsequent decennial census.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF288092BD0AD4E85B92329E655A15802"><enum>3.</enum><header>Commission to recommend number of Members of House of Representatives in event of significant population change</header><subsection id="HAB569ADF7F5F41179B1B173D307EE714"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, with respect to a regular decennial census of the population of the United States, the number of Representatives determined under section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2(a), is 15 percent greater or lesser than the number of Representatives determined under such section with respect to the previous regular decennial census, there shall be established in Congress a commission to carry out the duties described in subsection (d) with respect to the apportionment of Representatives resulting from that census.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4FE4E72C942044D68EEDD010B0D57C74"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="H70D87E41CC0848DD8D713EEC430AF762"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A commission established under this section shall consist of 15 members appointed as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H8D06695543824F45B9BEC10DBD989FBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">5 members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C19513BAAB5437793EDF35F486FE34C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>5 members appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E39773B02D14FE99C350F872DAE9255"><enum>(C)</enum><text>2 members appointed by the majority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AAB8A9F973E4BEFA3AD9D0BEDB22916"><enum>(D)</enum><text>2 members appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44F19F88E818493B8C01C7FB15DAEC6C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>One member who shall serve as the Chair of the Commission, who shall be appointed by the vote of a majority of the other members, of whom—</text><clause id="H16EDF0B539234AE796314EDFE24EA80A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 2 shall be members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives;</text></clause><clause id="HF0F9E11C5D044F01B9C32D8C22790084"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at least 2 shall be members appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives;</text></clause><clause id="H1D8CEEB3638F40E2A9CA94B5CEF6C776"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at least one shall be one of the members appointed by the majority leader of the Senate; and</text></clause><clause id="H3085842D38C24F1DA12407F36C0CC223"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>at least one shall be one of the members appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C220E16CDA94B4EBC69DF2F3F7A0BF5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appointing authorities under paragraph (1) shall appoint the members of the commission not later than 30 days after the President transmits to Congress the statement showing the number of Representatives to which each State is entitled under section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB53543439B44FC0A64C40632C4D5F6C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>In appointing members of the commission, the appointing authorities under paragraph (1) shall prioritize the appointment of individuals who are qualified to assess the appropriate number of Members of the House of Representatives because of their expertise or study of politics, government, and related fields, and their demonstrated ability to work in a nonpartisan manner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C850D24D55B4BB6BB10CB9629A83594"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Vacancy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vacancy in the commission shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment was made.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0A71012ACA148A1BF1A9CA688963F89"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the commission—</text><subparagraph id="H1E51E685F892478CA63BBA5F5E13710A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be paid the daily equivalent of the annual rate of basic pay payable for level V of the Executive Schedule for each day (including travel time) during which the member is engaged in the actual performance of duties vested in the commission; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75C06EB646484D39927F9B94E7E80235"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02CB2B22A65147DD9AC1C5E952D55DBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staff</header><paragraph id="H8A29D296AFD947E5BB64CF1DCA04809D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to appoint staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The chair of the commission may appoint, prescribe the duties and responsibilities of, and fix the pay of such staff as the chair considers appropriate to assist the commission in carrying out its duties, without regard to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service, and without regard to the provisions of chapter 51 and subchapter III of chapter 53 of such title relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates, except that no rate of pay fixed under this paragraph may exceed the rate of pay for a member of the commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92789A24174E45468081F8D3985B2E3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Experts and consultants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202(i) of the Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/4301">2 U.S.C. 4301(i)</external-xref>) shall apply with respect to the commission in the same manner as such section applies with respect to a standing committee of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C1481500C1D4A059E78E5E5EFEF8C06"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>With respect to a regular decennial census, the commission shall carry out the following duties:</text><paragraph id="H9DC90F76F6B548B6908A54564F7C86A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Analyzing the shifts in population among the States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE500FD2B5534495A9E9160EB1B34630"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analyzing how the application of section 22(a)(2) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)(2)</external-xref>), as added by section 2(a), will affect the ability of the House of Representatives to carry out its responsibilities in an effective manner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17AB2ED5388146B4898A992A79788AE2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Recommending the optimal number of Members of the House and the optimal apportionment of Members among the States, taking into account—</text><subparagraph id="H771F5239A5EB47109ED42739003295CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shifts in population among the States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCA885BD46CB4819992D610C7288F105"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the need to reduce disparities in the size of congressional districts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22DFEFD33C5A470AB432C3696B5047FD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the need to ensure that historically under represented populations are not disenfranchised.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDEAE016E1504843BD2CE4179A4C4678" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Powers</header><paragraph id="H7015597E84F74EF48454BE2874A80570"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hearings and other activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of carrying out its duties, the commission may hold such hearings and undertake such other activities as the commission determines to be necessary to carry out its duties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D91A121717B4766AACE3AEEF32DFB14"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to use subpoenas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The commission may require by subpoena the attendance of such witnesses and the production of such books, papers, and documents, as it considers appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD282926C63E34A149B30BFCEE1B5FA8C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Access to legislative branch services</header><text>The commission shall have access to the services of the Architect of the Capitol, the Government Accountability Office, the Congressional Budget Office, and the Congressional Research Service in the same manner and under the same terms and conditions as any standing committee of the House of Representatives or Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F53AF0084654917B1FB951A19C65C26"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The commission shall submit a report to Congress containing its recommendations under subsection (d)(3) not later than 6 months after the publication of the regular decennial census of the population of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H226F827E8BE944F1A0BFFBCF57F5B664"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>A commission established under this section shall terminate 30 days after submitting the report under subsection (f).</text></subsection><subsection id="H29DD2F9CA51A4F1DB99F1992C19AE726"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall apply with respect to the second regular decennial census conducted after the date of the enactment of this Act and each subsequent decennial census.</text></subsection></section><section id="H14D903B3DD5E4A94A984B1ECDBBEC8C9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for provision of additional space, facilities, personnel, and resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the House of Representatives and the Architect of the Capitol for the fiscal year in which this Act is enacted and each succeeding fiscal year such sums as may be necessary to provide for any additional space, facilities, personnel, and other resources for the House which may be required as the result of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

