<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59BBD47DE77B482FA76DDC60D6A4B12F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2883 IH: Domestic Reinvestment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2883</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the Secretary of Homeland Security, or any other person, from requiring repayment, recoupment, or offset of certain antidumping duties and countervailing duties paid under section 754 of the Tariff Act of 1930, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFAD950AC3F66489F9A2B917865067204" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1F4F70C642A44C449C0247786F28704A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Domestic Reinvestment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFBAFD1EB4BAC4E55B079EAB012B62557"><enum>2.</enum><header>Termination of all efforts to clawback payments of certain antidumping duties and countervailing duties</header> <subsection id="H9567388A14134370AAFA40F0BB8D382D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, neither the Secretary of Homeland Security nor any other person may—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2B651CDBD7BB4F40BB300785FB8B5779"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require repayment of, or attempt in any other way to recoup, any payment described in subsection (b); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E38E4461E9747F1A4CB3630F83D5A4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>offset any past, current, or future distributions of antidumping duties or countervailing duties assessed on any imports in an attempt to recoup any payment described in subsection (b). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFA5E1447BC234077B8B2C2F4FED2788A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payments described</header><text>Payments described in this subsection are payments of antidumping duties or countervailing duties made pursuant to section 754 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (19 U.S.C. 1675c (repealed by subtitle F of title VII of the Deficit Reduction Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/171">Public Law 109–171</external-xref>; 120 Stat. 154))) that were— </text> <paragraph id="H8690AD907E1E4EE491DD8DBF146D951E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assessed and paid with respect to imports of goods from any country; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE3D052391A5F4F2E91E9036A41A7B9B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>distributed on or after January 1, 2001.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAB179E52840547C7AA48A6E4B269E3CC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payment of certain funds collected or withheld</header><text>Except with respect to payments described in subsection (d), not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall— </text> 
<paragraph id="HF81A82D3B0EE4C98B53D1DD9418D9BF0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>refund any repayment or other recoupment of any payment described in subsection (b) that was collected by the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection after January 1, 2017; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2685E86314AD450CB7E3583E58185BAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fully distribute any antidumping duties or countervailing duties that the Commissioner is withholding as an offset as described in subsection (a)(2). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HED5DF772639B416B9602581BAFD14ED5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent the Secretary of Homeland Security, or any other person, from retaining, offsetting, requiring repayment of, or attempting to otherwise recoup, any payment described in subsection (b) as a result of—</text> <paragraph id="H27327680717840018502CD7820FB227F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a finding of false statements, other misconduct, or insufficient verification of a certification by a recipient of such a payment; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H631EB8EBCED64B12AB08AA5CE3D059CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the issuance of a refund to an importer or surety pursuant to a settlement, court order, or reliquidation of an entry with respect to which such a payment was made. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

