<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H95F2E28B4B6E4881A94AEC9F6718CD87" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4642 IH: International Regulatory Transparency and Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4642</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require transparency from the Federal financial regulators with respect to international meetings, negotiations, and agreements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H75E7B59309F3431185AEB5A0A4B0A9D5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6180C3C524C24C67830A60346EA4B15C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>International Regulatory Transparency and Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAE8FA2864A13445F8BE2D267DCE867DB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transparency for international meetings, negotiations, and agreements</header> <subsection id="HF1F276F29A9642FA9F789E3E114EA3A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification of international negotiations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal financial regulator shall, prior to entering into any international negotiation (other than an enforcement cooperation agreement), provide written notification to Congress and the public containing information on the purpose, scope, and anticipated impact of the negotiations.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H829592485F2D4D3FB1EB4E9278DAB11D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting on formulation of American positions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal financial regulator shall report to Congress on the formulation of American positions regarding matters before international regulatory bodies, including the rationale, objectives, and potential impacts of the proposed positions.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBE70EB63254749E38551A820285D4696"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transparency for agreements in connection with covered international financial organizations</header> <paragraph id="HB8A0BABE56A84B0CB4A203AFB3AE53CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Summaries of meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal financial regulator that participates in a meeting of a covered international financial organization, or that meets with the staff of a covered international financial organization, shall post a summary of the meeting, including information on the topics discussed and the key outcomes of the meetings, on the homepage of the Federal financial regulator.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBEC23034614846FF914700AE3E1B1910"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public comment period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal financial regulator may not enter into an international agreement in connection with a meeting of a covered international financial organization unless the Federal financial regulator first notifies the public of the proposed agreement and provides for a public comment period of 60 days or more.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4E98B9467AD341DF80813FAE62966BFA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication of final agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal financial regulator that enters into an international agreement described under paragraph (1) shall make the text of the agreement available to the public.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H47E994AADCE545BB8EEA237AB66A3FF0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Congressional briefings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal financial regulator shall provide periodic briefings to members of Congress on the status and progress of international regulatory negotiations.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2DBE084DCCB64FE69DFCC51451B5D197"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HAC376A9232EC4C9196AA9D980010E1E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered international financial organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered international financial organization</quote> means the Financial Stability Board, the Basel Committee on Banking Supervision, the International Organization of Securities Commissions, and the International Association of Insurance Supervisors.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEB1D201988D45A98A490692FB54E6DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal financial regulator</header><text>The term <quote>Federal financial regulator</quote> means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the National Credit Union Administration, the Department of State, the Department of the Treasury (including the Federal Insurance Office), and the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

