<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F69CA6DCC9C4BD0B83D3060C1F05B1D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4985 IH: Expanding Medical Education Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4985</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a grant program to support schools of medicine and schools of osteopathic medicine in underserved areas.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD4065746F61F41DDA00DA53BABDDA703" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HCC7170563FB14E229D51E447697E0A38"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Medical Education Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9932249BC7BE41B1A92C1AD0D5625865"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants for schools of medicine and schools of osteopathic medicine in underserved areas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart II of part C of title VII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/293m">42 U.S.C. 293m et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E1E2538846F433C84F26D610994542F"><section id="HCF669BA4AE754B098CDC22E95DECEDD6"><enum>749C.</enum><header>Grants for schools of medicine and schools of osteopathic medicine in underserved areas</header><subsection id="H44AA06D4E3D04328AA657C8E363C0320"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may award grants to institutions of higher education (including consortiums of such institutions) for the establishment, improvement, or expansion of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4EDB8558700E4165B612D7C677D2B150"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting grant recipients under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to any institution of higher education (or consortium of such institutions) that—</text><paragraph id="H5D2EB0A79C4A464C933C887341FAA8AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>proposes to use the grant for the establishment of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, in an area—</text><subparagraph id="H08CAC7B2DF294C149882A47E43745B73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in which—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H241901DF1D2B497284BA2146E91EA5EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no other such school is based; or </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2C3AC1B0142495185AEC09118793E07"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case in which the school of medicine or osteopathic medicine proposed to be established would be a minority-serving institution, no other minority-serving institution that includes a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine is based; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A547BEB95AD4F9E9AD0E019F7FA1363"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is a medically underserved community or a health professional shortage area; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H08640B041AC047A99BF1DF59EA85A195"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is a minority-serving institution described in section 371(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 or an institution or program described in section 326(e) of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H121C0A3BBB7447E9BDED15533AC38700"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary, to the extent practicable, may ensure equitable distribution of awards among the geographical regions of the United States. </text></subsection><subsection id="H98633D8A83B44427BC1C28E912AA0A4A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An institution of higher education (or a consortium of such institutions)—</text><paragraph id="HC14F2EC1541741B79A1C2E52BC027DB0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall use grant amounts received under this section to—</text><subparagraph id="H0BA5C070708743F987FB768D8A8D3F2D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recruit, enroll, and retain medical students who are pursuing a degree of doctor of medicine or doctor of osteopathy, including individuals who are from disadvantaged backgrounds (including racial and ethnic groups underrepresented among medical students and health professions), individuals from rural and underserved areas, low-income individuals, and first generation college students, at a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine or branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BC3A816EFFE49D5A2B114511BA07625"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop, implement, and expand curriculum that emphasizes care for rural and underserved populations, including accessible and culturally and linguistically appropriate care and services, at such school or branch campus; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H814B6A414A4D43D58B4AAE52925494B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may use grant amounts received under this section to—</text><subparagraph id="HDDA6EFD00AED4F358E8711436530779B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>plan and construct—</text><clause id="HFA20122043934F519B865F1F20C9A3AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, in an area in which no other such school is based; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FC2862F8AD54C4B9C75D0EDB2136456"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, that will be a minority-serving institution, in an area in which no other such school that is a minority-serving institution is based;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CF81C12FFC5451AA6D4A0B9EFBF269E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>plan, develop, and meet criteria for accreditation for a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine or branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F8A2D354F5F485E938458B5360B76DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hire faculty, including faculty from racial and ethnic groups who are underrepresented among the medical and other health professions, and other staff to serve at such a school or branch campus;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD18D3B87BA7347CB809958694E2B6FE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support educational programs at such a school or branch campus;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FEF56C43B004077BC087F95C23EAF37"><enum>(E)</enum><text>modernize and expand infrastructure at such a school or branch campus; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38096B830AB0427DA31299E452B752BF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>support other activities that the Secretary determines further the establishment, improvement, or expansion of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine or branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFAABF30787E94C229BFB75FE04F7218D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (a), an institution of higher education (or a consortium of such institutions), shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a description of the institution’s or consortium's planned activities described in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE0A98361419346439B608A1A114EA926"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reporting</header><paragraph id="H5EA3D6C9C0624DBC8480A1503F1A275D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports from entities</header><text>Each institution of higher education, or consortium of such institutions, awarded a grant under this section shall submit an annual report to the Secretary on the activities conducted under such grant, and other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC55F63CC42440F4BD1D22054F96D2F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this section and every 5 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that provides a summary of the activities and outcomes associated with grants made under this section. Such reports shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HB9A9995011FE455B8550B1CCE9A64097"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of awardees, including their primary geographic location, and location of any school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of school of medicine or osteopathic medicine that was established, improved, or expanded under this program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9381492D4F244D69AC9FC74C59C8868"><enum>(B)</enum><text> the total number of students (including the number of students from racial and ethnic groups underrepresented among medical students and health professions, low-income students, and first generation college students) who—</text><clause id="H0CE11443499A4CBA9E38CD4A6548C0C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are enrolled at or who have graduated from any school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, that was established, improved, or expanded under this program, deidentified and disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, sex, geographic region, disability status, and other relevant factors, to the extent such information is available; and</text></clause><clause id="HAB85D779E1BC49D2AB29C0757E0DAD0B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who subsequently participate in an accredited internship or medical residency program upon graduation from any school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, that was established, improved, or expanded under this program, deidentified and disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, sex, geographic region, disability status, medical specialty pursued, and other relevant factors, to the extent such information is available; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2898874013A40DBB1AC7B1AC5E1881C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the effects of such program on the health care provider workforce, including any impact on demographic representation disaggregated by race, ethnicity, and sex, and the fields or specialties pursued by students who have graduated from any school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, or a branch campus of school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, that was established, improved, or expanded under this program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEA705691F81461BBB687793546986DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the effects of such program on health care access in underserved areas, including medically underserved communities and health professional shortage areas; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD85657AC7144380894FEE7314925397"><enum>(E)</enum><text>recommendations for improving the program described in this section, and any other considerations as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF135BFBC8A744D0DA99A6693B9CDE8AB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make reports submitted under paragraph (2) publicly available on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E2CA2B494FD4E71A3D99399355179A6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD822784D6FF84DD99DA4D980C53E54B7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Branch campus</header><subparagraph id="HA3D142EB9E044B019808C0442C06CD34"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>branch campus</term>, with respect to a school of medicine or osteopathic medicine, means an additional location of such school that is geographically apart and independent of the main campus, at which the school offers at least 50 percent of the program leading to a degree of doctor of medicine or doctor of osteopathy that is offered at the main campus. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17B29338BCC64FE18D921C5F0A2BBB1D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Independence from main campus</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the location of a school described in such subparagraph shall be considered to be independent of the main campus described in such subparagraph if the location—</text><clause id="H98F377F6AF7D4797AE19FF91E6B82429"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is permanent in nature;</text></clause><clause id="HCDF207261C0C419690DE81C797BFFCD0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>offers courses in educational programs leading to a degree, certificate, or other recognized educational credential;</text></clause><clause id="HBA6BF19D2DA34A5D97DAC5DB779D6C98"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has its own faculty and administrative or supervisory organization; and</text></clause><clause id="H1ABF163BD391499BB49B62AF7BD90710"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has its own budgetary and hiring authority. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H23176A6763CB4060B52DB2DECCE4889A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>First generation college student</header><text>The term <term>first generation college student</term> has the meaning given such term in section 402A(h)(3) of the Higher Education Act of 1965. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC77907FD04D94300BA73F4BE80D0166C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Health professional shortage area</header><text>The term <term>health professional shortage area</term> has the meaning given such term in section 332(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50BAB285F4B144B3941FC07F3B30DF13"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFA2C26A491F4B298CD07C8970E313C1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Medically underserved community</header><text>The term <term>medically underserved community</term> has the meaning given such term in section 799B(6).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF28237502CF4AE8AA39DBA770FE7A53"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

