<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAE5C41FD039A439595E4C0FEC282AEC7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6137 IH: GIS Emergency Response Technology Sustainment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6137</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize annual appropriations to the Geospatial Management Office of the Department of Homeland Security for the sustainment of innovative GIS technologies to improve emergency response capabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEDC9A29491C349E296C7D9BB061677E3" style="OLC"><section id="H83EB0F7520024841993E668AF929BFD5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>GIS Emergency Response Technology Sustainment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H830AEB7EE3794E52953C61FE16E1A8BA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual authorization for GIS emergency response technology sustainment</header><subsection id="HB0228370C28441EF8F94F0D5AF53C79D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of search and rescue common operations program</header><text>There is established within the Geospatial Management Office of the Department of Homeland Security a program for the sustainment of innovative GIS technologies to improve emergency response capabilities, such as urban search and rescue geospatial software platforms in emergency and disaster response.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA1474C243D2D479FA9601BB102715FE6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Geospatial Management Office $3,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2030 to carry out the program established pursuant to subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H10BB4C3626854E1EA7E588229E5C740D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Funds made available pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (b) shall be used for the following:</text><paragraph id="HFE0C03DB285F4C7D91B552B4399523C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinated on-the-ground and remote geospatial urban search and rescue training, planning, and response through ongoing collaboration with appropriate nonprofit entities focused on enhancing public safety through geospatial technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H513CD46AF36E4FCE917D162BE0ADBFCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Sustainment and expansion of search and rescue geospatial support technology solutions in preparation for emergency events and disaster responses.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H061BD56286D34744AB01B2C88E02F5ED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>To carry out subsection (c), the Geospatial Management Office shall collaborate with appropriate nonprofit entities in the field of geospatial technology, particularly such entities with experience in developing and deploying emergency response platforms.</text></subsection><subsection id="H09C8025C71AE442ABCE49879C2866E97"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting Requirement</header><text>Not later than April 1, 2025, and every April 1 thereafter through 2031, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report detailing the following:</text><paragraph id="HDDB3928AE6C647BB984B44150B3FC6DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The obligation and expenditure of funds made available pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (b) for the immediately preceding fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3015FA40F0814ADB9CF18B5FE8002397"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The progress and effectiveness of activities carried out pursuant to subsection (c) during such immediately preceding fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

