<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6A43222CFFD9417683DB02016A1B5294" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3695 IH: Vehicle Rental Order Obligation Mandate Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3695</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To protect consumers from overbooking by rental car companies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H710249749F6B4129A23F7FFAB92068D6" style="OLC"><section id="H489F1D799F45430B9CC3FB22291708E0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Vehicle Rental Order Obligation Mandate Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>VROOM Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H26F8198E849B4C11B99C9FAE6A8E3E0B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protection from overbooking by rental car companies</header><subsection id="HC558A7F3310E4B65872F55408EB63447"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Protection from overbooking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A rental car company that fails to honor a reservation of a consumer shall offer the consumer, and allow the consumer to choose from between, each of the following:</text><paragraph id="H6D562C8EFE1648339684CFEDE2DCD4ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If such a vehicle is available, fulfillment of the reservation, at no additional cost to the consumer, through a covered rental vehicle of a class that is more expensive to rent than the vehicle initially reserved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H797E413D63E546A2908C437A80692BAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>If such a vehicle is available, both—</text><subparagraph id="H3D4945D088E14C2F8A4C6A2D26F62C49"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fulfillment of the reservation through a covered rental vehicle of a class that is less expensive to rent than the vehicle initially reserved; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6186202ED0B647D6B89B1A3F87217C21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an amount equal to the difference in price between—</text><clause id="H449662C40C83465697B8C949F4454742"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reservation as initially reserved; and</text></clause><clause id="HC209DF1FCC164226ADFD5A7513476CD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the reservation as fulfilled pursuant to subparagraph (A), as determined by using the lesser of—</text><subclause id="H56EC792D54A740A6A69BBB61B905A89B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the lowest available price of such reservation as fulfilled had such reservation as fulfilled been made on the date on which the initial reservation described in clause (i) was made; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H94918587549344E3B737B208C34BBC6E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the lowest available price of such reservation as fulfilled had such reservation as fulfilled been made on the date of fulfillment.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1300047641ED468AA40D035FDFCA6C82"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An amount equal to 200 percent of the total rental price of the reservation of the consumer, except that in no case may the amount exceed $500 per day of the reservation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB1E88237428F4DD3A44425C64385CAD5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Commission may promulgate, under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, regulations to implement this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5BDD8DCE0B6645A689EA0AF121E81B1A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement by Commission</header><paragraph id="H568D40CA1F414835A6860991BA5FE198"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFA54E1AAA8F4D029687C96BB4A3D461"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall enforce this section and the regulations promulgated under this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this Act. Any person who violates this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE85049B3B4D4E0D8280BB720A78B410"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effect on other laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3EEBB0A20AE4ACF96E93F484D9C9695" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Actions by States</header><paragraph id="H37A03C1F33504663AAF77619F2CAE99A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which the attorney general of a State, or an official or agency of a State, has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of such State has been or is threatened or adversely affected by an act or practice in violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section, the State, as parens patriae, may bring a civil action on behalf of the residents of the State in an appropriate district court of the United States to—</text><subparagraph id="HBF55423B44B74F5A9BF320DCE06B47D5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enjoin such act or practice;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AE242B42E9A4B498722F27115339E7F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enforce compliance with such section or regulation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE7CAFFD2C624C319AB9CACC15FEFF3B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81B12C8E9ABC465FAF6B1A5BDEB5B05F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>obtain such other legal and equitable relief as the court may consider to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C6978D6F4D94062A2F409177477EFAB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Before filing an action under this subsection, the attorney general, official, or agency of the State involved shall provide to the Commission a written notice of such action and a copy of the complaint for such action. If the attorney general, official, or agency determines that it is not feasible to provide the notice described in this paragraph before the filing of the action, the attorney general, official, or agency shall provide written notice of the action and a copy of the complaint to the Commission immediately upon the filing of the action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA30B1E461DF34A8A93D72C3C7B8154F5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority of Commission</header><subparagraph id="HAB85B7A49CFC4CC7A452ADE562E9C2F4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receiving notice under paragraph (2) of an action under this subsection, the Commission shall have the right—</text><clause id="H44C5BD05390A4814B9C775E4BF5127F7" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to intervene in the action;</text></clause><clause id="H381DDDD1D7034D64BD4A90A6FB063DA5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>upon so intervening, to be heard on all matters arising therein; and</text></clause><clause id="H2E25887F91AA4CE9A5976F43E242D6E0" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to file petitions for appeal.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE8D8DDAD6C64E8A965DB0A081E6E212" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation on State action while Federal action is pending</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Commission or the Attorney General of the United States has instituted a civil action for violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section (referred to in this subparagraph as the <quote>Federal action</quote>), no State attorney general, official, or agency may bring an action under this subsection during the pendency of the Federal action against any defendant named in the complaint in the Federal action for any violation of such section or regulation alleged in such complaint.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3AE65E574974652A90D7C90BC2C0675" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>For purposes of bringing a civil action under this subsection, nothing in this Act shall be construed to prevent an attorney general, official, or agency of a State from exercising the powers conferred on the attorney general, official, or agency by the laws of such State to conduct investigations, administer oaths and affirmations, or compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and other evidence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE058D1892B7E49038DC447CC6673168F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person injured by an act or practice in violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section may bring in an appropriate district court of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H1F2E54807E5340AA8F3CAA5415E46872"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an action to enjoin the violation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE07789360AAC4F5C98E7A3BCC6278C2C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an action to recover damages for actual monetary loss from the violation, or to receive up to $1500 in damages for each such violation, whichever is greater; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BB708F976414DF3BF4E4B222BB7F2DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>both such actions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H382B2DBD66FE477B92A30FBCA2BE6852"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6034F8F789054CDD918D7DA775BD2209"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A3753FFFEB44C8C8B18094258601A55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered rental vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered rental vehicle</term> means a motor vehicle that—</text><subparagraph id="HC02957F63B3840799F5EB0912597FB88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a gross vehicle weight rating of 10,000 pounds or less;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64B8C7AE2A9A4292B7FC97B81DC16779"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is rented to a consumer for a term of less than 4 months;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B801D576DC2493F9718A37A74A02755"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is rented without a driver provided as part of the rental; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC68166FEC79948BA8C871B7E05DDFBE3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is part of a motor vehicle fleet of 35 or more motor vehicles that are used for rental purposes by a rental company.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HADBD04009750457BADE5D106E9005B54"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fails to honor a reservation</header><text>The term <term>fails to honor a reservation</term> means, with respect to a rental car company, that the company does not provide a consumer, who has a confirmed reservation for a covered rental vehicle (without regard to whether the reservation was paid for in advance), a vehicle of the class reserved by the consumer at the time for fulfillment associated with the reservation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB265D69B351443CE9F1D4250EB9912F4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Motor vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>motor vehicle</term> means a vehicle driven or drawn by mechanical power and manufactured primarily for use on public streets, roads, and highways, but does not include a vehicle operated only on a rail line.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H430E380557644A2493F0FF7FE1EE6463"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rental car company</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>rental car company</term> means a person who—</text><subparagraph id="H9EF897755FE64F54A739215E4AA08F21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is engaged in the business of renting covered rental vehicles; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80B03970E36E483481C85EFAFF62D5DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>uses for rental purposes a motor vehicle fleet of 35 or more covered rental vehicles, on average, during the calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

