<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H947671BF5F544F8BAAB2CE1EFC6465C3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3541 IH: Accounting STEM Pursuit Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3541</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Student Support and Academic Enrichment Grant program to promote career awareness in accounting as part of a well-rounded STEM educational experience.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE0959FAEDE84BE08818DA639BB045DE" style="OLC"><section id="HB88889EF8A624FDB8190DBB4C31AE947" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accounting STEM Pursuit Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H76AB3B12F42D454FB02891C2BF326328"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H79747415E529422AAAEAF179A1519E99"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The accounting profession is working to ensure that it meets the needs of the public, businesses, governments, and not-for-profit organizations in a technology-driven marketplace.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2168FCC0E8784242A043B9BD2045CB66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Promoting diversity, equity, and inclusion within the accounting profession fosters a field that is reflective of the local, regional, and global communities it serves, and is better positioned to innovate around the complex issues facing organizations of all kinds and the evolving public interest.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B277D404D7C46D0ACC988064A102C36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Early exposure to the accounting profession through family, friends, and other community interactions, or relevant elementary and secondary course offerings, increases opportunity for students to recognize the limitless possibilities of a career in accounting, and therefore inspires that professional trajectory.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17C610245C5A4CAFAFA837D01495178E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>This Act seeks to build on existing financial literacy initiatives by establishing the significance of early course offerings in accounting education as drivers for improving career opportunity and diversity within this STEM profession.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D32F2B8722D494AA173FB6C04BD4972"><enum>(5)</enum><text>There is a clear and logical integration between accounting and technology: as the profession continues to advance its use of technology to serve the public interest, accounting professionals, including CPAs, are technological leaders who manage and analyze big data, ensure data security, manage cybersecurity risk, and work alongside Information Technology professionals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3241371A698400A8C796E05DC92D2DB"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pipeline of accounting majors in higher education, and accounting as a profession, will be expanded through exposure to STEM-designated accounting programs particularly in middle and secondary education curricula.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HAD643F4C8774431F8036889546989B1C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Accounting as part of a well-rounded educational experience</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart 1 of part A of title IV of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7111">20 U.S.C. 7111 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4DA343C8D4E44E099BA8AFD5103E874E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 4104(b)(3)(A)(i)—</text><subparagraph id="H7AEFE90E96DB437F9FCEC772FFA5C2BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (VI), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77CD43B3A5174FCE8771D88F3ACBC65D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subclause (VII) as subclause (VIII); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0D01D9765974CC2A948C895B87900D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subclause (VI) the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6D91C38494C64ADBA6EEB7F6176A9433" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="H34CA107D00E14CE180D5BA4168621053"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">accounting education, including accounting career awareness; or</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H48709796B2964F348D22D69A64856E6A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 4107(a)(3)—</text><subparagraph id="H4B62C69F01D04AC8B3006863C93DBA90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF5FDE3C6D8A4C7D9A5D5828DA68714B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (J) as subparagraph (K); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16A62B8B9BD24305B31901352A4C627D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (I) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H303336623A8E4AA0930F952647361467" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H5E49A88E821B4374B465B8DF65F7F9C1"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">activities to promote the development, implementation, and strengthening of programs to teach accounting, including increasing access to high-quality accounting courses for students through grade 12 who are members of groups underrepresented in accounting careers; or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

