<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H8BC8794935B4413CA1658828FBA29991"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4731 IH: Access to Infertility Treatment and Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4731</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require health insurance coverage for the treatment of infertility.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause"><section section-type="section-one" id="S1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access to Infertility Treatment and Care Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id0D24A08752D5408B99DF03169CB1A92C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="id1d2fcd68caa54bc8aaa4ca5aa700d92e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Infertility is a medical disease recognized by the World Health Organization, the American Society for Reproductive Medicine, and the American Medical Association that affects men and women equally.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddfe335029d28472c932415f38256e408"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1 in 8 couples have difficulty getting pregnant or sustaining a pregnancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id18df913dc46d4de3a64a2e8c04231d69"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Infertility affects a broad spectrum of prospective parents. No matter what race, religion, sexual orientation, or economic status one is, infertility does not discriminate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id611207edfa2a4a0fa55abca30f62546e"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 11 percent of women in the United States between the ages of 15 and 44 have difficulty getting pregnant or staying pregnant. Similarly, 9 percent of men in the United States between the ages of 15 and 44 experience infertility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida2fcf2a4dd19421a934ee8ba9257ba32"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Infertility disproportionately affects individuals with particular health complications. For cancer patients and others who must undergo treatments such as chemotherapy, radiation therapy, hormone therapy, or surgery that are likely to harm the reproductive system and organs, fertility preservation becomes necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfb208c9a29a0482cb55231702011e79f"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Leading causes of infertility include chronic conditions and diseases of the endocrine or metabolic systems, such as primary ovarian insufficiency, polycystic ovarian syndrome, endometriosis, thyroid disorders, menstrual cycle defects, autoimmune disorders, hormonal imbalances, testicular disorders, and urological health issues. Other causes include structural problems or blockages within the reproductive system, exposure to infectious diseases, occupational or environmental hazards, or genetic influences.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd53af1298ef74793a7ece3b62ad5347e"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Recent improvements in therapy and cryopreservation make pregnancy possible for more people than in past years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9553ad1da95940f080b2f6ddf523a5d6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Like all other diseases, infertility and its treatments should be covered by health insurance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7734b4387eba4e3d9f88b897212681a5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A 2017 national survey of employer-sponsored health plans found that 44 percent of employers with at least 500 employees did not cover infertility services, and 25 percent of companies with 20,000 or more employees did not cover infertility services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id48653a1fefa040549dc73e88644f89b8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Coverage for infertility services under State Medicaid programs is limited. The Medicaid programs of only 5 States provide diagnostic testing for women and men in all of their program eligibility pathways; the Medicaid program of only one State provides coverage for certain medications for women experiencing infertility; and no State Medicaid programs cover intrauterine insemination or in vitro fertilization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1be6b4839ebc4850a09cadddf38abfc6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>States that do not require private insurance coverage of assisted reproductive technology have higher rates of multiple births.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb82ba2163ec648ab996199c0547888ea"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The ability to have a family should not be denied to anyone on account of a lack of insurance coverage for medically necessary treatment.</text></paragraph></section><section id="idD6091FD0E9CF41A8A93BBA33985E8CE8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><subsection id="id13603DA07A114BD981BD017B504FB35D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8dac2caa803c4cbabab9498528d0ca88"><enum>(1)</enum><header>PHSA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part D of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-111">42 U.S.C. 300gg–111 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0a242182972041fd8a8ef7744227164c"><section id="idA6F696C95541466EA480ED15B5A679C0"><enum>2799A–11.</enum><header>Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><subsection id="idc170c9b70f804fa196e8e4fd1cfa2f71"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A group health plan or a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall ensure that such plan or coverage provides coverage for—</text><paragraph id="id9F21486B6D3A4836A5955337C86899D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the treatment of infertility, including nonexperimental assisted reproductive technology procedures, if such plan or coverage provides coverage for obstetrical services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6274ee1ac2f64438acb94f77782995a1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>standard fertility preservation services when a medically necessary treatment may directly or indirectly cause iatrogenic infertility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id89A3899FA71D4FD994D82D03B2F46FD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id870F05A3525C400687A488AB9082D520"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>assisted reproductive technology</term> means treatments or procedures that involve the handling of human egg, sperm, and embryo outside of the body with the intent of facilitating a pregnancy, including in vitro fertilization, egg, embryo, or sperm cryopreservation, egg or embryo donation, and gestational surrogacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id53451EE7544949688BD94BA3FF43BE8F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>infertility</term> means a disease, characterized by the failure to establish a clinical pregnancy—</text><subparagraph id="id3FFB1455E7204C6D94A3CEC650D9FC31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>after 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3C973544B93E4DA0A4407678DA06C896"><enum>(B)</enum><text>due to a person's incapacity for reproduction either as an individual or with his or her partner, which may be determined after a period of less than 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse, or based on medical, sexual and reproductive history, age, physical findings, or diagnostic testing; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id003B10542EA94287AB806A3633E55590"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>iatrogenic infertility</term> means an impairment of fertility due to surgery, radiation, chemotherapy, or other medical treatment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="iddabce247df9f4dab89c5bb21f8e81c2e"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required coverage</header><paragraph id="idc6f39190a00f4fb881eb087b146c1c56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coverage for infertility</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), a group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage that includes coverage for obstetrical services shall provide coverage for treatment of infertility determined appropriate by the treating provider, including, as appropriate, ovulation induction, egg retrieval, sperm retrieval, artificial insemination, in vitro fertilization, genetic screening, intracytoplasmic sperm injection, and any other non-experimental treatment, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with appropriate professional and patient organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6279fcb23f1e4a4a91ec3dbb89f5dd9b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coverage for iatrogenic infertility</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall provide coverage of fertility preservation services for individuals who undergo medically necessary treatment that may cause iatrogenic infertility, as determined by the treating provider, including cryopreservation of gametes and other procedures, as determined by the Secretary, consistent with established medical practices and professional guidelines published by professional medical organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1ed7580bfcf74d48b51ff09055b7f2f1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on coverage of assisted reproductive technology</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall provide coverage for assisted reproductive technology as required under paragraph (1) if—</text><subparagraph id="id48959ea84a5248f2bdc95cdfe118afac"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual is unable to bring a pregnancy to a live birth through minimally invasive infertility treatments, as determined appropriate by the treating provider, with consideration given to participant's, beneficiary's, or enrollee's specific diagnoses or condition for which coverage is available under the plan or coverage; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id629ed4bc5ae5401db3fdda9b64be2733"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the treatment is performed at a medical facility that is in compliance with any standards set by an appropriate Federal agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd98a50bbce574041b8bf4cf6dc6c857b"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Cost-sharing, including deductibles and coinsurance, or other limitations for infertility and services to prevent iatrogenic infertility may not be imposed with respect to the services required to be covered under subsection (c) to the extent that such cost-sharing exceeds the cost-sharing applied to similar services under the group health plan or health insurance coverage or such other limitations are different from limitations imposed with respect to such similar services.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc042bafaaa5b401883e013061b6d3ec1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage may not—</text><paragraph id="idf8cc619ceebb4087810e4f159c7bcec0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide incentives (monetary or otherwise) to a participant, beneficiary, or enrollee to encourage such participant, beneficiary, or enrollee not to be provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to which such participant, beneficiary, or enrollee is entitled under this section or to providers to induce such providers not to provide such treatments to qualified participants, beneficiaries, or enrollees;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide1253f80ea5d41b9ab5fc33728885cf1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit a provider from discussing with a participant, beneficiary, or enrollee infertility treatments or fertility preservation technology or medical treatment options relating to this section; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id44b89dfd6205439d8ef85e45a3397c66"><enum>(3)</enum><text>penalize or otherwise reduce or limit the reimbursement of a provider because such provider provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to a qualified participant, beneficiary, or enrollee in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id87c261abac544887a37ac04b5cdf2c7a"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a participant, beneficiary, or enrollee to undergo infertility treatments or fertility preservation services.</text></subsection><subsection id="idd1ceafb0695e44f98cc5de0c523fc941"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall provide notice to each participant, beneficiary, and enrollee under such plan or coverage regarding the coverage required by this section in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary. Such notice shall be in writing and prominently positioned in any literature or correspondence made available or distributed by the plan or issuer and shall be transmitted—</text><paragraph id="idCB6C70851BE54FEBAD0AE4E2C39EF491"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the next mailing made by the plan or issuer to the participant, beneficiary, or enrollee;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4FB43F82ABAF41DBBFFB5D0DCA3AB773"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as part of any yearly informational packet sent to the participant, beneficiary, or enrollee; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id659C8D1F56814F878B1EBCE73A471291"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than January 1, 2024,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">whichever is earlier.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="idc75d0c5389a44aecb542f96a1026bfee"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Level and type of reimbursements</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a group health plan or a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage from negotiating the level and type of reimbursement with a provider for care provided in accordance with this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id20056a7e688d4273bcdd785e20f67c49"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ERISA</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc2d7bcc0208643bb8f2eb2aecdd343d3"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Subpart B of part 7 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1185">29 U.S.C. 1185 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idF2972DB84FFA4087AB54B6F44281FC29"><section id="id85FE369C3E35427E94B0118F7B76AA7E"><enum>726.</enum><header>Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><subsection id="id87619FD7979946AA8276DEBBCAE8BF70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A group health plan or a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage shall ensure that such plan or coverage provides coverage for—</text><paragraph id="id10B40AEAD7A74AF3888FDFD0DCA123E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the treatment of infertility, including nonexperimental assisted reproductive technology procedures, if such plan or coverage provides coverage for obstetrical services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idE842A7332EC7428399C0EBDB12473902"><enum>(2)</enum><text>standard fertility preservation services when a medically necessary treatment may directly or indirectly cause iatrogenic infertility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idA3C28EAB530F42498C914ACD3112BE6B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="idC6566A7D7A154A6BA61232846985BE45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>assisted reproductive technology</term> means treatments or procedures that involve the handling of human egg, sperm, and embryo outside of the body with the intent of facilitating a pregnancy, including in vitro fertilization, egg, embryo, or sperm cryopreservation, egg or embryo donation, and gestational surrogacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id48634F1A694E41E6946001B8E59B1724"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>infertility</term> means a disease, characterized by the failure to establish a clinical pregnancy—</text><subparagraph id="id62EA2DEFF3E34B8FB45CABE07B6A1CBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>after 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4DCCD40A47EA45FCB4725DFD70E9A4A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>due to a person's incapacity for reproduction either as an individual or with his or her partner, which may be determined after a period of less than 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse, or based on medical, sexual and reproductive history, age, physical findings, or diagnostic testing; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7F6403765FEB41C3A13C30A33BE9FF21"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>iatrogenic infertility</term> means an impairment of fertility due to surgery, radiation, chemotherapy, or other medical treatment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id3449876A03F24122B7CFDCF6738834FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required coverage</header><paragraph id="id310A3FB825B040CABE56992A46A8C7E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coverage for infertility</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), a group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage that includes coverage for obstetrical services shall provide coverage for treatment of infertility determined appropriate by the treating provider, including, as appropriate, ovulation induction, egg retrieval, sperm retrieval, artificial insemination, in vitro fertilization, genetic screening, intracytoplasmic sperm injection, and any other non-experimental treatment, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with appropriate professional and patient organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id480E66740B4248218DF02D047E45E0FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coverage for iatrogenic infertility</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage shall provide coverage of fertility preservation services for individuals who undergo medically necessary treatment that may cause iatrogenic infertility, as determined by the treating provider, including cryopreservation of gametes and other procedures, as determined by the Secretary, consistent with established medical practices and professional guidelines published by professional medical organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idF2F25F26707448ADB2111EA23187BB16"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on coverage of assisted reproductive technology</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage shall provide coverage for assisted reproductive technology as required under paragraph (1) if—</text><subparagraph id="idAF350C22E02940F48AA5CE908775EA76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual is unable to bring a pregnancy to a live birth through minimally invasive infertility treatments, as determined appropriate by the treating provider, with consideration given to participant's or beneficiary's specific diagnoses or condition for which coverage is available under the plan or coverage; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7221472220ED4D57967426A7AF7BC5BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the treatment is performed at a medical facility that is in compliance with any standards set by an appropriate Federal agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id210CAAEAB0C3455B883A5C8B16DFEE25"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Cost-sharing, including deductibles and coinsurance, or other limitations for infertility and services to prevent iatrogenic infertility may not be imposed with respect to the services required to be covered under subsection (c) to the extent that such cost-sharing exceeds the cost-sharing applied to similar services under the group health plan or health insurance coverage or such other limitations are different from limitations imposed with respect to such similar services.</text></subsection><subsection id="idF2A121D286CF42678980A2490A816E97"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage may not—</text><paragraph id="idBD54E69B3E1E4BBAB493D9946DB70426"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide incentives (monetary or otherwise) to a participant or beneficiary to encourage such participant or beneficiary not to be provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to which such participant or beneficiary is entitled under this section or to providers to induce such providers not to provide such treatments to qualified participants or beneficiaries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6CCA5E6D073244B2838D3370EA81084C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit a provider from discussing with a participant or beneficiary infertility treatments or fertility preservation technology or medical treatment options relating to this section; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id78B5604FE6354B418A53A5592D5C1855"><enum>(3)</enum><text>penalize or otherwise reduce or limit the reimbursement of a provider because such provider provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to a qualified participant or beneficiary in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idBDEB37E1A0B04043A79D2A184937F437"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a participant or beneficiary to undergo infertility treatments or fertility preservation services.</text></subsection><subsection id="idAC312CF1FE3E4CAD9D4B6FF6DE2292CD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage shall provide notice to each participant and beneficiary under such plan or coverage regarding the coverage required by this section in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary. Such notice shall be in writing and prominently positioned in any literature or correspondence made available or distributed by the plan or issuer and shall be transmitted—</text><paragraph id="idEFA466B67E7E4D03B0DA9E942E8BA32F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the next mailing made by the plan or issuer to the participant or beneficiary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5713171398624A358C91FA9D5490CD37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as part of any yearly informational packet sent to the participant or beneficiary; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD1C2B1ADB9464B0D84B2B2BE50D6A913"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than January 1, 2024,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">whichever is earlier.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="id0836448E98744B45A2C84EC5D4E7C928"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Level and type of reimbursements</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a group health plan or a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage from negotiating the level and type of reimbursement with a provider for care provided in accordance with this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46771E2285AB4140A9359A1CE846D29D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1001">29 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 725 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H053F5617657842F88BA8358AD19C41C6"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 726. Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb2e1e7d99e0e441baf87f2d7b40bdf95"><enum>(3)</enum><header>IRC</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id083df52a59204bdb853c0a3db9d1f868"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/100">chapter 100</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idBE1BD5BC34904B74BA0469F3BBB57DF4"><section id="idF26A7D5CCCB4495FAD59C245BA6FBEC9"><enum>9826.</enum><header>Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><subsection id="id50531086020442A1AEB84FA13E3A4217"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A group health plan shall ensure that such plan provides coverage for—</text><paragraph id="id96B9DBA60AC740D593D027B126111E19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the treatment of infertility, including nonexperimental assisted reproductive technology procedures, if such plan provides coverage for obstetrical services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idB63A3E72F24D4644A0C742AFB39D3785"><enum>(2)</enum><text>standard fertility preservation services when a medically necessary treatment may directly or indirectly cause iatrogenic infertility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idB2FDA931F58F477BA908077E85245552"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id2A15528361F747B29E8859C24D385DA8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>assisted reproductive technology</term> means treatments or procedures that involve the handling of human egg, sperm, and embryo outside of the body with the intent of facilitating a pregnancy, including in vitro fertilization, egg, embryo, or sperm cryopreservation, egg or embryo donation, and gestational surrogacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idC6E7EACD08774938B7D65B40723CC221"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>infertility</term> means a disease, characterized by the failure to establish a clinical pregnancy—</text><subparagraph id="id7C330123021A49D980DFB3F0668E7368"><enum>(A)</enum><text>after 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idA7E644DC2C78454B9C0266CBD7F038A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>due to a person's incapacity for reproduction either as an individual or with his or her partner, which may be determined after a period of less than 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse, or based on medical, sexual and reproductive history, age, physical findings, or diagnostic testing; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idF18FE86879D2442FA3DDE9235ACDFFA8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>iatrogenic infertility</term> means an impairment of fertility due to surgery, radiation, chemotherapy, or other medical treatment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idAD66C329DAC94DADA273A621450FBF1D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required coverage</header><paragraph id="idD456B72FC3D640D4A92957CE1354F774"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coverage for infertility</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), a group health plan that includes coverage for obstetrical services shall provide coverage for treatment of infertility determined appropriate by the treating provider, including, as appropriate, ovulation induction, egg retrieval, sperm retrieval, artificial insemination, in vitro fertilization, genetic screening, intracytoplasmic sperm injection, and any other non-experimental treatment, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with appropriate professional and patient organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idD135876A1CC244ABBE12A893EE6928BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coverage for iatrogenic infertility</header><text>A group health plan shall provide coverage of fertility preservation services for individuals who undergo medically necessary treatment that may cause iatrogenic infertility, as determined by the treating provider, including cryopreservation of gametes and other procedures, as determined by the Secretary, consistent with established medical practices and professional guidelines published by professional medical organizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id88265E54811B407397F49C2A7AEAEBE0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on coverage of assisted reproductive technology</header><text>A group health plan shall provide coverage for assisted reproductive technology as required under paragraph (1) if—</text><subparagraph id="id9541BBF5FC054C0FB8A0A2B03CD55BC5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual is unable to bring a pregnancy to a live birth through minimally invasive infertility treatments, as determined appropriate by the treating provider, with consideration given to participant's or beneficiary's specific diagnoses or condition for which coverage is available under the plan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idE6C27EDDD2634E0C872C9916C0677F1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the treatment is performed at a medical facility that is in compliance with any standards set by an appropriate Federal agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id164BF5785DD94050A10B43FBD8B46450"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Cost-sharing, including deductibles and coinsurance, or other limitations for infertility and services to prevent iatrogenic infertility may not be imposed with respect to the services required to be covered under subsection (c) to the extent that such cost-sharing exceeds the cost-sharing applied to similar services under the group health plan or such other limitations are different from limitations imposed with respect to such similar services.</text></subsection><subsection id="id460355FE3BA6412CAFACBCC76C1C52F5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text>A group health plan may not—</text><paragraph id="id498D0566107C4304BFCCC0EA5975DBB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide incentives (monetary or otherwise) to a participant or beneficiary to encourage such participant or beneficiary not to be provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to which such participant or beneficiary is entitled under this section or to providers to induce such providers not to provide such treatments to qualified participants or beneficiaries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idC6D5324057C743E6936372EF31519AE0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit a provider from discussing with a participant or beneficiary infertility treatments or fertility preservation technology or medical treatment options relating to this section; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id90661830DD4641EA895250CB1CFB6C35"><enum>(3)</enum><text>penalize or otherwise reduce or limit the reimbursement of a provider because such provider provided infertility treatments or fertility preservation services to a qualified participant or beneficiary in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id1312D5ABB7524083B04A8B09229C8DBA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a participant or beneficiary to undergo infertility treatments or fertility preservation services.</text></subsection><subsection id="id445BAF8EA71A4B52A5FD778AFC64C339"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>A group health plan shall provide notice to each participant and beneficiary under such plan regarding the coverage required by this section in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary. Such notice shall be in writing and prominently positioned in any literature or correspondence made available or distributed by the plan and shall be transmitted—</text><paragraph id="id01A7C00DF9AC4DD4A3999D046AAF264C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the next mailing made by the plan to the participant or beneficiary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idC40BE878AFEC4981847B5A41A3A26086"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as part of any yearly informational packet sent to the participant or beneficiary; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3B3618DC89B242DE90F2915D792E446F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than January 1, 2024,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">whichever is earlier.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="idAB5795D4FDDB49B9A3E22364F9ADB677"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Level and type of reimbursements</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a group health plan from negotiating the level and type of reimbursement with a provider for care provided in accordance with this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H795D6ABC87B348E6929E1F920294D18D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/100">chapter 100</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new item: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FE8C986AF3C462E85B8CB7982D5ED76"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 9826. Standards relating to benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id94BB887C75CA4C5288D442F6E3EDDEB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 2724(c) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-23">42 U.S.C. 300gg–23(c)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 2704</quote> and inserting <quote>sections 2704 and 2708</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="id068a8eccc82545369dc5b40bf706e265"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><paragraph id="id4B2E8417F39E41E9805BAB2D85B2A1B1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall apply for plan years beginning on or after the date that is 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6ba326ea843f4e09b6029f44df4696a4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collective bargaining exception</header><subparagraph id="id8E3EB3D3CC3243ACBEC0BF4F3622227A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a group health plan maintained pursuant to one or more collective bargaining agreements between employee representatives and one or more employers ratified before the date of enactment of this Act, the amendments made by subsection (a) shall not apply to plan years beginning before the later of—</text><clause id="id0ec8cee7001e43c3bfa72615c59fe5f7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which the last collective bargaining agreements relating to the plan terminates (determined without regard to any extension thereof agreed to after the date of enactment of this Act), or</text></clause><clause id="id9a2e3dfe7f1b477e864af8ca15a1c139"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date occurring 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id515fbdd38950497f83c54fa798a13ed6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), any plan amendment made pursuant to a collective bargaining agreement relating to the plan which amends the plan solely to conform to any requirement added by subsection (a) shall not be treated as a termination of such collective bargaining agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id5003cf5eb0364e3f968597fdefd760c4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Federal Employees Health Benefits Program</header><subsection id="idEEE2577C8AF14D31A8F1F12FFC1C1A3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 8902 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3df7812342074b519c8aa1273ba5a80e"><subsection id="idf0443d054a934c7fb452657678babc77"><enum>(q)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="idFDE8C05CEC714845A503CBF897310AC6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>infertility</term> and <term>iatrogenic infertility</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="id1B7F940695B04F389FD381DBB2979730"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A contract under this chapter shall provide, in a manner consistent with section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act, coverage for—</text><subparagraph id="id766AAD3E64674B8CAB42AE4F1B2A4860"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the diagnosis and treatment of infertility, including nonexperimental assisted reproductive technology procedures, if that contract covers obstetrical benefits; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idB5E49E2C4D4840C0A8056CF11BC5A556"><enum>(B)</enum><text>standard fertility preservation services when a medically necessary treatment may directly or indirectly cause iatrogenic infertility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="id9773146D5FD84641AD6C7944B994B311"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Coverage for the diagnosis or treatment of infertility and fertility preservation services under a health benefits plan described in section 8903 or 8903a may not be subject to any copayment or deductible greater than the copayment or deductible, respectively, applicable to obstetrical benefits under the plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="idD6AA72A7055D4D7EBF0A22DBA0F10126"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Subsection (m)(1) shall not, with respect to a contract under this chapter, prevent the inclusion of any terms that, under paragraph (2) of this subsection, are required by reason of section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfb95043901434c4db593da0ce94ce205"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to— </text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idCCAF1D1F51B64CB0BBBBEC75CCA2449A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any contract entered into or renewed for a contract year beginning on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8FE9751F66C94C0EA54E3D2EB1563119"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any health benefits plan offered under a contract described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id8a5115b46860485c9adb2d23b3b2d17f"><enum>5.</enum><header>Benefits for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility under the TRICARE program</header><subsection id="idDB850D02D1654D1B952C9FBB940C6DA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/55">Chapter 55</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idBEB2705267FF4408BEF66C35CA9CCE78"><section id="idead8f2a141f445059a4875d6c3795050"><enum>1110c.</enum><header>Obstetrical and infertility benefits</header><subsection id="id8859ec796f8b414ab9cd661808bc38f6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any health care plan under this chapter shall provide, in a manner consistent with section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act—</text><paragraph id="id39ABC61C308F48A1BC2B466C7A21A67D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coverage for the diagnosis and treatment of infertility, including nonexperimental assisted reproductive technology procedures, if such plan covers obstetrical benefits; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd66b14b21d7e423cb5d5cc01d528aa0b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coverage for standard fertility preservation services when a medically necessary treatment may directly or indirectly cause iatrogenic infertility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id2bdb8e39f6ad414fb13b21e1bafe18d0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Copayment</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish cost-sharing requirements for the coverage of diagnosis and treatment of infertility and fertility preservation services described in subsection (a) that are consistent with the cost-sharing requirements applicable to health plans and health insurance coverage under section 2799A–11(d) of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="id928b0b5a17904afcb6ba49e8fa34eadd"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall prescribe any regulations necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id2200126144774B4FA685897047C17E0C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <term>assisted reproductive technology</term>, <term>iatrogenic infertility</term>, and <term>infertility</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="idd02e929d436346cd9ada7da77dd1efdf"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 55 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="idbb6098d9-7b2e-4188-93b5-58cbced0bd7c"><toc><toc-entry idref="idead8f2a141f445059a4875d6c3795050" level="section">1110c. Obstetrical and infertility benefits.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="id9c9278481aa84cd0a2ecda85c26c9d35"><enum>6.</enum><header>Treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility for veterans and spouses or partners of veterans</header><subsection id="id0d55f69ea38945e98c5ca6793368af9e"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idD65FA90035C94BC78BDE50D59B8E460F"><section id="idd6ffb097c76b40a38dbe49c055d5721d"><enum>1720K.</enum><header>Infertility treatment for veterans and spouses or partners of veterans.</header><subsection id="id8B0E3D5A3EC842CE8B289054FDEA6B95"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall furnish treatment for infertility and fertility preservation services, including through the use of assisted reproductive technology, to a veteran or a spouse or partner of a veteran if the veteran, and the spouse or partner of the veteran, as applicable, apply jointly for such treatment through a process prescribed by the Secretary for purposes of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="id89CF3752A4514947A7B94ED963553063"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <term>assisted reproductive technology</term> and <term>infertility</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 2799A–11 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id94AAA02B42EA43E3B8B9B0369860DD5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of subchapter II of chapter 17 of such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1720J the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="idc2400c7b-4dcc-43f3-a448-4e42efd33042"><toc><toc-entry idref="idd6ffb097c76b40a38dbe49c055d5721d" level="section">1720K. Infertility treatment for veterans and spouses or partners of veterans.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id704FE1F2ED0F44C3A03F4D2F893BDDF1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall prescribe regulations to carry out section 1720K of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="id819B6B436DE249BAB326934DC4D87959"><enum>7.</enum><header>Requirement for State Medicaid plans to provide medical assistance for treatment of infertility and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><subsection id="id0C74AA42F52D458495E9AFFBA3F57E6E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="idC147EE10AFDB4BAA99D5D1F0CA1DC7BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a)(4)—</text><subparagraph id="id06196F2EF4DA42568707CC159EA44442"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>; and (D)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (D)</quote>; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5C871D657EEF447CAD8667C3233B3458"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>; and (E)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (E)</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idFA881DCFA775477F808F9EF4306B98C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>; and (F)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (F)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3E0C1EF52A9A4E0AA0EC260C3095C057"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>; and (G) services and supplies to treat infertility and prevent iatrogenic infertility (as such terms are defined in section 2799A–11(b) of the Public Health Service Act) in accordance with subsection (jj)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id1D6F6941AA3E430FABE72ED6275152EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc0bfa1c658ee4ee88eedbd1acef39397"><subsection id="idb40afe0faf4b40e7974b4fcc01fe7890"><enum>(jj)</enum><header>Requirements for coverage of infertility treatment and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a)(4)(G), a State shall ensure that the medical assistance provided under the State plan (or waiver of such plan) for treatment of infertility and fertility preservation services complies with the requirements and limitations of section 2799A–11(c) of the Public Health Service Act in the same manner as such requirements and limitations apply to health insurance coverage offered by a group health plan or health insurance issuer.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idDC2FA3E091A64F578A856553B476ADC4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No cost sharing for infertility treatment</header><paragraph id="idaf6711cd8882412f9e055f48f7b772f2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsections (a)(2)(D) and (b)(2)(D) of section 1916 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o">42 U.S.C. 1396o(a)(2)(D)</external-xref>) are amended by inserting <quote>, services and supplies to treat infertility and provide fertility preservation services described in section 1905(a)(4)(G)</quote> after <quote>1905(a)(4)(C)</quote> each place it appears.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id94472a5e053a4d4b87e86a7d6cf1048c"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application to alternative cost sharing</header><text>Section 1916A(b)(3)(B)(vii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o-1">42 U.S.C. 1396o–1(b)(3)(B)(vii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote> and services and supplies to treat infertility and provide fertility preservation described in section 1905(a)(4)(G)</quote> before the period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id2DE26D9C9F21428C8AD67B173974FA94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Presumptive eligibility for infertility treatment</header><text>Section 1920C of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-1c">42 U.S.C. 1396r–1c</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="id4C31B88261EB43D1B34C29B001F258EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">and infertility treatment</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">family planning services</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id09F1A6E822C34A31B6CA6BF3C8DBEAB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="id842FE8A6E2C345B5BBD7D9C0E931AD2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>State plan</quote> and inserting <quote>A State plan</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id623A2C8CB0B54A64AE2302DA6FFA49B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>1905(a)(4)(C)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 1905(a)(4)(C), services and supplies to treat infertility and prevent iatrogenic infertility described in section 1905(a)(4)(G),</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idB6D46B0D7524402ABE871A5BBD0E5B38"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or in conjunction with an infertility treatment service in an infertility treatment setting</quote> before the period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idA05A08CBAA1346D28CC29CAAFD5EA50A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Inclusion in benchmark coverage</header><text>Section 1937(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396u-7">42 U.S.C. 1396u–7(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="idA5D9BA317AD547818A1600A9BF85AB62"><paragraph id="idFE2B9AC1743046C3BDEC52F51F8D73F8"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Coverage of infertility treatment and prevention of iatrogenic infertility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the previous provisions of this section, a State may not provide for medical assistance through enrollment of an individual with benchmark coverage or benchmark-equivalent coverage under this section unless such coverage includes medical assistance for services and supplies to treat infertility and provide fertility preservation described in section 1905(a)(4)(G) in accordance with such section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id2AB571A0F49446DFAF645233FED89A08"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="id045B9A08633743118AC7FD09D88126B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idac18e3c9e9b9443991af7ade70485211"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Delay permitted if State legislation required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State plan approved under title XIX of the Social Security Act which the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines requires State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) in order for the plan to meet the additional requirement imposed by this section, the State plan shall not be regarded as failing to comply with the requirements of such title solely on the basis of the failure of the plan to meet such additional requirement before the first day of the first calendar quarter beginning after the close of the first regular session of the State legislature that ends after the 1-year period beginning with the date of the enactment of this section. For purposes of the preceding sentence, in the case of a State that has a 2-year legislative session, each year of the session is deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

