<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB03CA6B31D7146239638BB619AE29D82" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1820 IH: To require the Secretary of the Army to renew the lease of land for operations of the Corona Municipal Airport, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1820</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230328">March 28, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Army to renew the lease of land for operations of the Corona Municipal Airport, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H390F4E05EE9B41279664850A3F19454A" style="OLC">
<section id="H16E18A159EC141C19AFD5EE852DB9170" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H890D96F22FED475EA84F955085846B6F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1960, Corona established the Corona Municipal Airport to provide recreational opportunities for aviators throughout southern California.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAE58158BBC2948F0B757A7BA36BC7EA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The City of Corona initially entered into a lease agreement with the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers on December 24, 1959.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE29B04EE60D470FA353E9A8B7122DEE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The City’s lease with the Corps of Engineers enabled the construction of the airport into its current configuration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBC9F9F7A196E43E292BB885885ECEF35"><enum>(4)</enum><text>For over 60 years, the Corona Municipal Airport has supported local businesses, tourism, and recreation for local residents and the region.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4525717827846F88E49D6970558E1BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Corona Municipal Airport maintains the capability to assist in public safety efforts to protect life and property where aviation assets may be necessary.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B830215B3524AE59239975D28E9CDC7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Corona Municipal Airport supports approximately one dozen local, small businesses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBD21F913B1D495DBC3EE7ED3E28BE59"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Corona Municipal Airport continues to drive business development and local tourism for the City of Corona and connect people throughout southern California to those opportunities.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF5901F1C8D9B4BDDB94A008D8F3268A9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The City of Corona’s lease with the Corps of Engineers is set to expire on January 30, 2037, without an opportunity to grandfather the facility under existing policies.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE10228174493423E953F850D4B008E5D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The closure of the Corona Municipal Airport would deprive aviators of significant opportunities to enjoy this recreation pastime as fewer small, recreational airports in the region remain open and accessible.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE1F689A56E62412EBD55D839FF4FBF5D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Extending the City’s lease with the Corps of Engineers would allow this culturally and economically significant facility to continue serving aviators in the region.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H3C42E9E3707B4256B5141A122AF295AE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Corona Airport Lease Renewal, Prado Dam, CA</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of the Army, acting through the Chief of Engineers, shall not apply chapter 16 of the Corps of Engineers Operation and Maintenance Policy ER 1130–2–550 (March 30, 2009) to the lease of land and water areas within the Prado Flood Control Basin Project Area between the Department of the Army and the City of Corona, California, for the operation of the Corona Municipal Airport (Recreation Lease No. DACW09–1–67–60) and shall renew such lease.</text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


