<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBC66FDA2EA384DB9AF10FC4A51B73C85" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4922 IH: Lacey Act Amendments of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4922</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to enhance protections against the importation, and transport between States, of injurious species, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB153C53D0E3D40E4A4472FA316745F3A" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HD52CC0FE0EDC4EF58A7E85ADF456BFE4"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Lacey Act Amendments of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAA4D3262DC364F8CB908F7E58612008E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments</header> <subsection id="HA3EE466640B74BF683F983D45BFF202B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 42 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H86118DEDE6ED4166BFF597B25E04060D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H25268E587E2F4C04BA8A89DCA63CF8C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the first sentence, by striking <quote>shipment between the continental United States</quote> and inserting <quote>transport between the States</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE3DADE6158E747F8A48648508B0BC58B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after the first sentence the following: <quote>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of the Interior may prescribe by regulation an emergency designation prohibiting the importation of any species of wild mammals, wild birds, fish (including mollusks and crustacea), amphibians, or reptiles, or the offspring or eggs of any such species, as injurious to human beings, to the interests of agriculture, horticulture, or forestry, or to wildlife or the wildlife resources of the United States, for not more than 3 years, under this subsection, if the Secretary of the Interior determines that such regulation is necessary to address an imminent threat to human beings, to the interests of agriculture, horticulture, or forestry, or to wildlife or the wildlife resources of the United States. An emergency designation prescribed under this subsection shall take effect immediately upon publication in the Federal Register, unless the Secretary of the Interior prescribes an effective date that is not later than 60 days after the date of publication. During the period during which an emergency designation prescribed under this subsection for a species is in effect, the Secretary of the Interior shall evaluate whether the species should be designated as an injurious wildlife species under the first sentence of this paragraph.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H219B54C1F85D41AD89050E500E208E87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B65AA8BCC4C4E29854904DB6A6323F7">
<subsection id="HB66238CA5443483B9751B0F79870F541"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Presumptive prohibition on importation</header>
<paragraph id="H77014960646141B4BCD5BCEDF9530010"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Importation into the United States of any species of wild mammals, wild birds, fish (including mollusks and crustacea), amphibians, or reptiles, or the offspring or eggs of any such species, that is not native to the United States and, as of the date of enactment of the <short-title>Lacey Act Amendments of 2023</short-title>, is not prohibited under subsection (a)(1), is prohibited, unless—</text> <subparagraph id="H658087499C924430BB28D0797048784D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during the 1-year period preceding the date of enactment of the <short-title>Lacey Act Amendments of 2023</short-title>, the species was, in more than minimal quantities—</text>
<clause id="H5518A223C9344235821CAF7A2B0B2607"><enum>(i)</enum><text>imported into the United States; or</text></clause> <clause id="HC36EDA283027437A8008AFC9533323EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>transported between the States, any territory of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, or any possession of the United States; or</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H39DCE2506DF244219B051E7EC1120A9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior determines, after an opportunity for public comment, that the species does not pose a significant risk of invasiveness to the United States and publishes a notice in the Federal Register of the determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H31077192B37F44F9BE38C8526B5E5A1E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) shall be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary of the Interior under subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4A91034B4196409AB38617341E4C224E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 42(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H303BFE3056164054831674823E4C3CF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>and subsection (d)</quote> after <quote>this subsection</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H67AB9B922FAC423E9B59F027DF2714EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <subparagraph id="H585241B6151B4BBA9F8DA364983B3BFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the foregoing</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (1) or subsection (d)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC92DBED2AAD34EDD93E2F87147F78F2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>this Act</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>this section</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04BACC50626C4644A5D209C5CBFAA90A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting <quote>or subsection (d)</quote> after <quote>this subsection</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H82C5061D848840718863A7064C2A634C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text> <subparagraph id="HA724BD2D1ABD4257923AEB54C1088BB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and subsection (d)</quote> after <quote>this subsection</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4F09943CA928444ABF59980327BF67FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>hereunder</quote> and inserting <quote>under such provisions</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0495A86594F1448DB6A5CB50F121EF1F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations; effective date</header> <paragraph id="HC9FC7B3AD194495B9B481ED07F8B8C60"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Interior shall promulgate regulations to define the term <term>minimal quantities</term> for purposes of subsection (d)(1)(A) of section 42 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H50B3F62E37714162A484E12B600B285A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Subsection (d) of section 42 of title 18, United States Code, as added by subsection (a)(2), shall take effect on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

