<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H417330007DE14751BBC6AA9123513368" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4527 RH: Health Data Access, Transparency, and Affordability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 210</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4527</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–260]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on July 11, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 to ensure plan fiduciaries may access de-identified information relating to health claims, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HED00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H4BD6A055381F47549812E8DEDA1E7380"><section id="H4C0F23AFC8EB419CBF689F5DC86EF99F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Health Data Access, Transparency, and Affordability Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Health DATA Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H29797AFF468149EC94D75DE9F07A8148"><enum>2.</enum><header>Plan fiduciary access to information</header><subsection id="HB57ED858D34F4601B28A5921ECDDC492"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of section 408(b) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1108">29 U.S.C. 1108(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBFD221F5993444ED94F688A6C53F0277" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><subparagraph id="H8C3F0AD7ECEC437BB80A4D02CFB6FBB6" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No contract or arrangement for services between a group health plan and any other entity, such as a health care provider, network or association of providers, third-party administrator, or pharmacy benefit manager, is reasonable within the meaning of this paragraph unless such contract or agreement—</text><clause id="H704DFD7AA0E6403A918A34A08BEED090"><enum>(i)</enum><text>allows the responsible plan fiduciary to audit all de-identified claims and encounter information or data described in section 724(a)(1)(B) to—</text><subclause id="H53247984D9FD46328FD475289D25465D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>ensure that such entity complies with the terms of the plan and any applicable law; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA0029C01CF754D198396E97040EA7330"><enum>(II)</enum><text>determine the reasonableness of compensation paid by the plan; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE65BB860BEDC40A2AE322C21693E8374"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not—</text><subclause id="H5F4BB166D5B943A48B965879B2DE2AB0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>unreasonably limit the number of audits permitted during a given period of time;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF56A3DF1BC8840A784D198835A61B4A1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>limit the number of de-identified claims and encounter information or data that the responsible plan fiduciary may access during an audit;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB007950EDE2D40F7BB6489408CC47982"><enum>(III)</enum><text>limit the disclosure of pricing terms for value based payment arrangements, including—</text><item id="H788B53E503464230BF974EA979A5AC3F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>payment calculations and formulas;</text></item><item id="HF5054D23F76044ADA17769806DE3C690"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>quality measures;</text></item><item id="H983776E7612F40A8B51503DE8E4185F8"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>contract terms;</text></item><item id="H64DBD8C34A5B455684916640CBEB8DAB"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>payment amounts;</text></item><item id="H96FED780F32F455BA0F990CEA3AC846B"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>measurement periods for all incentives; and</text></item><item id="H1F06E9EEA50F4E42984A9C3F94390B21"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>other payment methodologies furnished by a health care provider, network or association of providers, third-party administrator, or pharmacy benefit manager;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H63BE43DFAD2448F197A911C73A9A4267"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>limit the disclosure of overpayments and overpayment recovery terms;</text></subclause><subclause id="H976AE78597C8482489EF12B283FD6470"><enum>(V)</enum><text>limit the right of the responsible plan fiduciary to select an auditor;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D153129CFB8436A8C4BBBDCE7268C13"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">otherwise limit or unduly delay by greater than 60 days the responsible plan fiduciary from auditing such information or data; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H8BFCB1B64B914FF28D36E8193E221E78"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">charge a fee beyond the reasonable direct costs to administer the operation of conducting such audits.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H1C0A05C28890484298BDD0A55EA15539" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Civil enforcement</header><paragraph id="HDDB6E5BA3FDF4D038105B2C372636F7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (c) of section 502 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1132">29 U.S.C. 1132</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1CFABE6D32D14DE19126DD623ABBE686" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><paragraph id="HBDC6F4D7A989405385386D4FF2602230" indent="up1"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an agreement between a group health plan and a health care provider, network or association of providers, third-party administrator, pharmacy benefit manager, or other service provider that violates the provisions of section 724, the Secretary may assess a civil penalty against such provider, network or association, third-party administrator, pharmacy benefit manager, or other service provider in the amount of $10,000 for each day during which such violation continues. Such penalty shall be in addition to other penalties as may be prescribed by law.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C8B8F797C7542549183660309A9C90F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Paragraph (6) of section 502(a) of such Act is amended by striking <quote>or (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), or (13)</quote>; and</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7609736BD7BA4DF487E565B1CA7C0986"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Existing provisions void</header><text>Section 410 of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2510F57C6D6D40DEB2D5022DA013B871" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><subsection id="H715A0DE1EBD749DDB0E7AE759C53B3D0"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any provision in an agreement or instrument shall be void as against public policy if such provision—</text><paragraph id="HA4C1D6021BE94873AF48DA882C58F394"><enum>(1)</enum><text>unduly delays or limits a plan fiduciary from accessing the de-identified claims and encounter information or data described in section 724(a)(1)(B); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H872EACE61E1C47F1B6E772D13882390F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>violates the requirements of section 408(b)(2)(C).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAF974D8132CB44479F5BF9DB6B6CA1AB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clause (i) of section 408(b)(2)(B) of such Act is amended by striking <quote>this clause</quote> and inserting <quote>this paragraph</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC4D190779C4648549B9362C9CF1E4175" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Updated attestation for price and quality information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 724(a)(3) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1185m">29 U.S.C. 1185m(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4BEB910C5C4A4CC6A93B796640E0E0AC" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HED00"><paragraph id="H5A23F9328050435C9C1D8554B1BD08F3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Attestation</header><subparagraph id="HA8A6A2667CFA436C996C462EC46A6CE2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), the fiduciary of a group health plan or issuer offering group health insurance coverage shall annually submit to the Secretary an attestation that such plan or issuer of such coverage is in compliance with the requirements of this subsection. Such attestation shall also include a statement verifying that—</text><clause id="H8AD9099B4247453C8B95BC2997F699EE" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the information or data described under subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1) is available upon request and provided to the plan fiduciary, the plan administrator, or the issuer in a timely manner; and</text></clause><clause id="H11211A3B1F894392ABB2CB6BEC2B2E68" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>there are no terms in the agreement under such paragraph (1) that directly or indirectly restrict or unduly delay a plan fiduciary, the plan administrator, or the issuer from auditing, reviewing, or otherwise accessing such information.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42C8CBC4840943FF845404897AA31D65"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation on submission</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), a group health plan or issuer offering group health insurance coverage may not enter into an agreement with a third-party administrator or other service provider to submit the attestation required under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35105D53384A411B8D121044DD09F01D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>In the case of a group health plan or issuer offering group health insurance coverage that is unable to obtain the information or data needed to submit the attestation required under subparagraph (A), such plan or issuer may submit a written statement in lieu of such attestation that includes—</text><clause id="H180B32DCE33E4D5CBF58C0F6E6D36174"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an explanation of why such plan or issuer was unsuccessful in obtaining such information or data, including whether such plan or issuer was limited or prevented from auditing, reviewing, or otherwise accessing such information or data;</text></clause><clause id="HCC551331EF9C4DD0B71B7E3FCD980136"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the efforts made by the plan fiduciary to remove any gag clause provisions from the agreement under paragraph (1); and</text></clause><clause id="H0A612AD563E4474EACB1C550E6A2A55A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a description of any response by the third-party administrator or other service provider with respect to efforts to comply with the attestation requirement under subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3D3D8FF18BB342828990A9CA22F991BD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Study on plan assets</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a report on the status of de-identified claims and encounter information or data described in section 724(a)(1)(B) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1185m">29 U.S.C. 1185m</external-xref>), including information on the following:</text><paragraph id="H19F95CC5747D4DC5B0A53C3A2FC22531"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Circumstances under current law where such information or data could be deemed a group health plan asset (as defined under section 3(42) of such Act).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A91366467C04FDD9754B8E7E8A5CB69"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether restrictions on the ability of a plan fiduciary to access such information or data violates a requirement of current law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDABF88BAE644899B78AE5C4CF114354"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The existing regulatory authority of the Secretary to clarify whether such information or data belongs to a group health plan, rather than a service provider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9A66AB812064D12BAE0E7A75C5B5DC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Legislative actions that may be taken to establish that such information or data related to a plan belongs to a group health plan and is handled in the best interests of plan participants and beneficiaries.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

