<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H35A30DAD971B41D5BD0BC384D2DC68CE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2689 IH: Trust in Government Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2689</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Small Business</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the service delivery of agencies and public perception of agency interactions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4B7642FF1884482C98229FD83E9C93E7" style="OLC"><section id="H3DCDB3F44B0045ACA8764D0FF230F7C1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Trust in Government Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE87F3FBE837042249C87744E3B5C6CCD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvement of service delivery of agencies and public perception of agency interactions</header><subsection id="H2D91A2F8BB9048D68ABC2B6DBDF88C0C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H835ED4AD81F4479F9FB78C1CBC38A454"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the agencies subject to the requirements of this Act should—</text><subparagraph id="H2D82561EE718488A8BA7DF53B06933A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve their understanding of customers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91240DD4B603403DA95D48838262D175"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduce administrative hurdles and paperwork burdens to minimize the time it takes to process benefits, enhance transparency, and create greater efficiencies across Government;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC10F6AFAF8A44EACB07FCAFD77301032"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improve public perception of agency interactions by systematically identifying and resolving the root causes of any challenge experienced by the public with respect to such interactions, regardless of whether the source of any such challenge is statutory, regulatory, budgetary, technological, or process-based; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE86E13A0CD4846299938C9997B27F170"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to engender public trust, ensure that the efforts of the agency appropriately maintain or enhance protections afforded under law and the policies of the agency, including protections related to civil rights, civil liberties, privacy, confidentiality, and information security; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H958638C5C8C24A78944CF24C471743C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Federal Government should—</text><subparagraph id="H9F290587E60646CEB90D31C2C30F6A28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>make improving service deliveries and public perception of agency interactions fundamental priorities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FC3AF83D01243E2A164199F9700FC0F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>measure performance empirically and by on-the-ground results for the people of the United States, especially for experiences of the people of the United States with services delivered by agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95FB422500D448439F147A523B16BD4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reforms To improve agency service delivery and customer experience</header><paragraph id="H2A18D3435E1C4C4B8584B564C5E1D7F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reforms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to improve the overall economy, efficiency, and management of government operations and activities, reduce the paperwork of agencies, and provide high-quality services to the public—</text><subparagraph id="HD2B26E877CB9433A9DA5CC07471AB33C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of State shall redesign the passport renewal process to allow for a fully online renewal application that does not require any physical documents to be mailed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09CEB5FA6B2A42C8BA655D9461781654"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury shall design and deliver new online tools and services of the Internal Revenue Service to—</text><clause id="HE5E06DD6363F4CDFA23BAA0E53DD9190"><enum>(i)</enum><text>expand electronic filing options for taxpayers;</text></clause><clause id="H47BFA5ACA43F405C924CC3D7FC52034A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide the option for taxpayers to receive customer support via secure email; and</text></clause><clause id="HB5C8F01C3FD84B72BD4F8B78E50D5A22"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide the option for taxpayers to schedule customer support telephone call-backs;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95E9145A5D9A4EAAAA7248285159BD33" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior shall design and deliver a centralized, modernized electronic permitting system to accept and process applications for permits; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H333D99A597B44BCEAC90121EA17CB924"><enum>(D)</enum><text> the Secretary of Agriculture shall design and deliver new online tools and services—</text><clause id="HC61B3EAE1C3A4D54B804914A4F25328C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for online purchasing under the special supplemental nutrition program for women, infants, and children under section 17 of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1786">42 U.S.C. 1786</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="HCB70A21A03924BC4A50D5B2A548AE0D0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to simplify enrollment and recertification for nutrition assistance programs such as the supplemental nutrition assistance program (commonly known as SNAP) and the program described in clause (i), including expanding the use of direct certification; and</text></clause><clause id="HCF1200F2233A4638958F2C4B121CCA70"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for a simplified process for applying for direct loans under subtitle A or B of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC30344B6A92F413B9A2F8649BB52D5CF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Secretary of Labor shall—</text><clause id="HB5AACAE74DDC43D68D28AEA4386B0FDA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>update existing rules and policies, consistent with applicable law and to the extent practicable, to allow individuals entitled to medical treatment under any Federal workers’ compensation program to conduct their routine medical treatment appointments using telehealth platforms; and</text></clause><clause id="H4604F509F1604E3188291D1E7067DFFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>update rules, policies, and procedures to eliminate, consistent with applicable law and to the extent practicable, requirements for workers’ compensation claimants to submit physical documents, but to retain the option for physical submission for claimants who cannot otherwise submit them;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6756815503304B7DAC50AEE7132140DB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><clause id="H4375FDFF71904CD3B300D9BA53B6D701"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">continue to design and deliver new, personalized online tools and expanded customer support options for individuals entitled to benefits under part A of title XVIII of the Social Security Act or enrolled under part B of such title;</text></clause><clause id="H5F72DAD6C4CF4274B77741F15B73CE0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>strengthen requirements for maternal health quality measurement, including—</text><subclause id="H2EA1D49610674605B3CD3B1649B9247A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>measuring perinatal quality and patient care experiences; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H42A68558AC8D4E7B9848EB65DF960AD5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>evaluating the measurements by race and ethnicity to better identify inequities in maternal health care delivery and outcomes;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H81CB372933CE442FBF19C974C46C86A4" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the maximum extent permitted by law, support coordination between the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>), the Medicaid program under title XIX of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>), the Children’s Health Insurance Program under title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H9D47781F2C8740D8AE74192475793EDC" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to the maximum extent permitted by law, propose ways to streamline State benefit program enrollment and renewal processes in order to reduce administrative burden on customers and remove barriers to enrollment and renewal, including by eliminating face-to-face interview requirements and requiring prepopulated electronic renewal forms, to ensure eligible individuals are automatically enrolled in and retain access to such benefit programs; </text></clause><clause id="H817A82AF14894121B067FF1494373552"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop guidance for covered entities and business associates of such entities as such terms are defined in section 160.103 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations, on providing telehealth in compliance with HIPAA privacy regulation (as defined in section 1180(b)(3) of the Social Security Act) to improve patient experience and convenience following the end of the COVID–19 public health emergency; and</text></clause><clause id="HADA5E6FFEA444FE2947A8A5D9FC9F8A2"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>test methods to automate patient access to electronic prenatal, birth, and postpartum health records (including laboratory results, genetic tests, ultrasound images, and clinical notes) to improve patient experiences in maternity care and health outcomes;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAACCDF0C343F47F5A818E434AFDC1FAD"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Secretary of Education shall—</text><clause id="H1718924091714E7AA504A216203A2D58"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress a plan for providing eligible recipients of Federal financial aid under title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>), with the option to receive information about relevant recommendations for benefits and services provided by the Federal Government that such recipients may qualify for (including healthcare subsidies, broadband support, and food assistance) to connect such recipients with support to lower additional economic barriers to postsecondary education completion; and</text></clause><clause id="H145DDB317A064CAB91CAD821DE597A9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">design and make available to the public a centralized loan repayment portal through the website of the Department of Education that enables a borrower of any loan made under part D of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087a">20 U.S.C. 1087a et seq.</external-xref>), regardless of loan servicer, to make payments on such loan;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E8FF7BDA52F4E33BB5BBCF6125CE255"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall provide digital services through a single, integrated, and equitable digital platform on VA.gov and an appropriate mobile application of the Department of Veterans Affairs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0BD75997BE1439C9FFF44D09AC7DEEB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security shall design and deliver—</text><clause id="H9CCD4F4CD8DF42CFB0A87F6F1C9AF968"><enum>(i)</enum><text>innovative technologies at airport security checkpoints to reduce passenger wait times;</text></clause><clause id="H88B9E000B1634D65A6B862ADEA0AC928"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>new opportunities for customers to connect with the Transportation Security Administration, including as appropriate, through—</text><subclause id="HAE1B87E98F714549A165397D103361F1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>online chat;</text></subclause><subclause id="H988B41A560C3411E9C6BDC729844281F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>improved communications during additional screenings; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB5E25B88ECDA45DEA866C937969A422C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>additional mechanisms to provide customer feedback; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H243EE3B071EC43348257FE5452CA2EAB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a streamlined, online disaster assistance application;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H350F0037127B4FEFA09C77BAA6404854"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator of the Small Business Administration shall develop and implement a streamlined, online disaster assistance application;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7DF6ECB1F2445A0A2373AD93129BD8A"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the Commissioner of Social Security shall—</text><clause id="HBE1DF150955448BC833F9C896475661C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop a mobile-accessible, online process so that any individual applying for or receiving services from the Social Security Administration can upload forms, documentation, evidence, or correspondence associated with their transaction without the need for service-specific tools or traveling to a field office;</text></clause><clause id="H1E38B01020D64860BDA3CB6A6115D25A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>consistent with applicable law and to the extent practicable, maintain a public policy of technology neutrality with respect to acceptable forms of electronic signatures;</text></clause><clause id="H529773D7815840C18F634997A1371B3D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>consistent with applicable law and to the extent practicable, revise any necessary regulations, forms, instructions, or other sources of guidance (to include the Program Operations Manual System of the Social Security Administration) to remove requirements that members of the public provide physical signatures; and</text></clause><clause id="H51CBFF924E02478B8D68915E9080896B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to the maximum extent permitted by law, support applicants and beneficiaries to identify other benefits for which they may be eligible and integrate Social Security Administration data and processes with those of other Federal and State entities whenever possible;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11CAB1C374DB4A4CACACF5FAE9C7C383"><enum>(L)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Administrator of General Services shall collaborate to provide seamless integration of Login.gov accounts to allow customers to access any websites and applications of the Department, and other customer-facing digital products and to eliminate outdated and duplicate customer sign-in options;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79D2B1C523AB4283948CA312CF2C2B0A"><enum>(M)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Education, and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall collaborate to enable a more streamlined Public Service Loan Forgiveness process for eligible borrowers, including those who serve in the United States Armed Forces or as civil servants, or who work for eligible nonprofit organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36F00502E23A4AD5B801C0FC8099F7A0"><enum>(N)</enum><text>the Director of OMB, acting through the Administrator of the United States Digital Service, shall collaborate with agencies in the executive branch and Tribal governments to conduct research and document challenges related to accessing grant programs to which the Tribal governments are entitled, and shall propose ways to streamline processes and reduce administrative burdens for Tribal government customers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA4CD662CFAD4C19A7CA8A7275D1763A" commented="no"><enum>(O)</enum><text>the Director of OMB, acting through the Administrator of the United States Digital Service, the Administrator of General Services, and the Postmaster General, shall develop ways to update mailing address records across Government so that members of the public may change their respective mailing addresses for purposes of all Government services only once, through the United States Postal Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H331060817EAB44A08105DA14628B3919"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ongoing accountability for improving Federal service delivery and improving trust in government</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 90 days thereafter—</text><subparagraph id="H66236F2E44494111AC5169A36BC30476"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the head of each agency subject to a requirement under subsection (a) shall certify in writing to the Director of OMB that the requirement has been satisfied; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB08B1394BE1F462C8649AD4ADB15B8CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Director of OMB shall—</text><clause id="HF9B4E62D05FF4BE2885F0878BF00D2DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in coordination with each head of an agency identified under paragraph (1), submit in writing to Congress, reports on the status of the progress of agencies in satisfying the requirements required by subsection (a), until such time as those requirements have been satisfied; and</text></clause><clause id="HA9C87973445C4EBFAACEC2CB04E3C4B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to each agency subject to a requirement under subsection (a), certify in writing to Congress that the head of each agency has satisfied the requirement.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8D70C6EC16E24413879DA20AC9575324" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>OMB guidance</header><paragraph id="H779D32679CF44BFA81C2D975EFEA936E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency customer experience initiatives</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of OMB shall designate a team of individuals within the Office of Management and Budget to lead and support agencies initiatives to improve public perception of agency interactions, including by facilitating the decision-making processes of such agencies that are needed to—</text><subparagraph id="H2F732EBCD5614E3CAD13BBA40B01104F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>achieve the purposes of this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H368B422F47F54B2A9BBF857F06A881E2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate the activities of high impact service providers as described in this Act; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2183494FA1549D7B2C8CDB1D2785BE9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop strategies for the integration of services and development of products involving multiple agencies as described in this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB578EC87A78490CA6B708C4E3527071" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance of OMB</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the enactment of this Act, the Director of OMB shall update guidance issued by the Director and supporting processes (such as information collection reviews or data sharing approvals) as necessary and applicable, to implement the provisions of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC47EE607CD36401A9EAC7090A9569761"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H34DE1C87B8544FF78687481EEE03EC59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Customer</header><text>The term <term>customer</term> means any person or governmental entity that interacts with an agency of the executive branch, either directly or through a federally funded program administered by a contractor, nonprofit, State or local government, or other entity of the Federal Government/executive branch.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H392283A6A47B4EB696B8FC8EC9D1C23B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public perception of agency interactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public perception of agency interactions</term> means the perception of the public regarding interactions with the agency, including interactions with the agency through a contractor, non-profit, or other Federal entity, and the overall satisfaction of the public regarding such interactions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9AB5554592A422A891E453F23249196"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director of OMB</header><text>The term <term>Director of OMB</term> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE6DDD87D66D4498B58C1993133015EF" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Service delivery</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>service delivery</term> means, with respect to all points of the agency-to-customer delivery process, an action of the agency related to providing a benefit or service to a customer of such entity, including providing a benefit or service to a customer that is related to an application for a benefit or loan, health care or small business counseling, requests for documents, such as a passport or Social Security card, filing taxes or declaring a good, using resources such as a park or historical site, or seeking information such as notices about public health or consumer protection. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

