<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4A4C7D041BB2435385953EA0C902F6AA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5398 IH: Advancing Tech Startups Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5398</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Commerce to conduct a study on tech startups, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF4FB31EEEDEC4508A3BB3932E24FDDFE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H88141A6446624A8EB721EA7FB2188DA0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing Tech Startups Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5DEA0550594D4D15837EF480FBD5B4F9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technology startup companies study</header> <subsection id="H995DC81E67D7401494D48E46282019E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="H4B37D3CDF56245E8B4E1C90E4679D7EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce, in coordination with the head of any other appropriate Federal agency, shall conduct a study on the impact of technology startup companies on the United States economy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0F03DC22D1E4447F8541B75617201031"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for study</header><text>In conducting the study, the Secretary shall do the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HA75FF675788948B2AE5FC9E3A6D1A2FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop and conduct a survey on technology startup companies in the United States through outreach to participating entities, as appropriate, to—</text> 
<clause id="H6A971D4E28C34DD68DDF6C3EB16AAE2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish a list of locations, including any State, city, or geographic area, dedicated to the creation, development, and growth of technology startup companies;</text></clause> <clause id="H00A66A559E6147ADA43A85F88976316E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide a description of the activities of such locations with respect to the creation, development, and growth of technology startup companies, including any incubators, accelerators, or other activity dedicated to such creation, development, and growth;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H70DC70D6D7584A2B84260A7E3B157E83"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>establish a list of public-private partnerships focused on promoting the creation, development, and growth of technology startup companies; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA590142376034B76B1363EE103C282BC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>provide a description of the activities of such public-private partnerships to create, develop, and grow technology startup companies.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9C34C95C7654C798439C734BC8B6014"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Develop a comprehensive list of Federal agencies asserting jurisdiction over entities and industry sectors dedicated to the creation, development, and growth of technology startup companies.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0737C5D9ACE448FAB844244D181A52FE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identify all interagency activities taking place among the Federal agencies listed under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A4A64A5E51D42288006F5399FB01CFA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Develop a brief description of the jurisdiction and expertise of the Federal agencies listed under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H11BD3C98A2544C71BDF7CCFCBEE3E742"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identify each Federal rule, regulation, guideline, policy, and other Federal activity implemented by each Federal agency listed under subparagraph (B) as it relates to any State, city, or geographic area dedicated to the creation, development, and growth of technology startup companies.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H978B837AFBF34A0DAFB1A37804A163C9"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conduct a survey of relevant marketplaces and supply chains impacting the creation, growth, and development of technology startup companies in the United States to—</text> <clause id="HE631400C9BF94188911E6E538C170C84"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assess the severity of risks posed to such marketplaces and supply chains; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8B3908CB0D4543E390FD96A7D728FDC2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify emerging risks and long-term trends in such marketplaces and supply chains.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0B88C840F543445D9D6F2EC31AB7ED3D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the completion of the study conducted under subsection (a), the Secretary, in coordination with the head of any other appropriate Federal agency, shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, and make publicly available on the website of the Department of Commerce, a report that contains—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3F9F6B78E91E4E688631C07A24BE8708"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the study conducted under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C13EA68F9FA490B9C04FB75F17FBFF0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations for legislation to provide for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5F24471D047D408AB529461F11326E7D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development and implementation of a comprehensive plan to promote the creation and growth of technology startup companies in the United States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA946070013C245A1B73326B7F7F978CA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the development of policies that States can adopt to encourage the creation and growth of technology startup companies in the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H903535564D94476392D0B9D79D688285" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the development of strategies to mitigate current and emerging risks to relevant marketplaces and supply chains impacting the creation and growth of technology startup companies in the United States.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

