<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDE57D870D20E48FEAA14D51A1C6E3297" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4193 IH: Fly Together Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4193</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Transportation to establish a policy with respect to family seating on air transportation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H534D76AFB6034FD8A4AF1E118D028815" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBE6CE70AB5BE4A9CB06A1AE58F463DBD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fly Together Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA7B671D26D7F477CA48BD1A5AC1E34DC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Family seating</header> <subsection id="H4BB24A0F38674B82B36409976D435AB2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall issue a notice of proposed rulemaking to establish a policy directing air carriers that assign seats, or allow individuals to select seats in advance of the date of departure of a flight, to sit each young child adjacent to an accompanying adult, to the greatest extent practicable, if adjacent seat assignments are available at any time after the ticket is issued for each young child and before the first passenger boards the flight.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2120D8023BF147DB9294E40D465BD7C5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees</header><text>The notice of proposed rulemaking described in subsection (a) shall include a provision that prohibits an air carrier from charging a fee, or imposing an additional cost beyond the ticket price of the additional seat, to seat each young child adjacent to an accompanying adult within the same class of service.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC487A90DFA744B07A470DB30D87A3D20"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Notwithstanding the requirement in subsection (a), nothing in this section may be construed to allow the Secretary to impose a change in the overall seating or boarding policy of an air carrier that has an open or flexible seating policy in place that generally allows adjacent family seating as described under this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H149D64BAEA4443A5B90E6265649253B0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Young child</header><text>In this section, the term <term>young child</term> means an individual who has not attained 14 years of age.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

