<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H26E02FCFB2E34577BD164FBE3EC8F8D8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 613 IH: Wayne Ford Racial Impact Statement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 613</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish a process for the creation of minority impact assessments to determine whether pending bills, if enacted, are likely to create or exacerbate disparate outcomes among racial or ethnic minority groups, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H351D72F8CCCD400CBBEC03998F7932BA" style="OLC">
<section id="H504861026FAD490FBCD5CF55F1A86FA7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wayne Ford Racial Impact Statement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H372D9F21E11448AB95E7B48CA4A7BF94" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header> <subsection id="H27C39D09F9FF400483AA22683D263EF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HA4EAA242BE2144FD93B3CDCAD32AC17F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Minority impact assessments are a tool for lawmakers to evaluate potential disparities of proposed legislation prior to adoption and implementation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0123C39E3C2649E5B9F832D19476DCD8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>There are 5,000 criminal penalties in Federal law and the number of Federal statutes carrying a criminal penalty has increased by 50 percent since the 1980s.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC1B9DF04753C467F9672874F2E497DFD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The enactment of criminal laws and penalties is a serious matter and the legislative process should reflect the gravity of this process.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5B913F9EED294E8E98863A02C71662BC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United States Sentencing Commission was created to reduce sentencing disparities, which provides a strong foundation for equity action in this branch of Government.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA21565AFF4244D28B7F265F27D066499"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Criminal laws conceived and voted on in haste can lead to the enactment of unnecessary, duplicative, ineffective, or prejudicial criminal penalties.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H541A6C41CB7040B194356E27D0414B79"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2008, Iowa was the first State to enact minority impact assessment legislation, authored by former State Representative Wayne Ford, requiring that criminal justice legislation be evaluated with respect to whether it will disproportionately impact specified minority groups.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDC57FD00F47A4688A3186A27B49C3856"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Iowa law created a measurable decline in Black incarceration rates from 13.6 per 1 White resident to 9 to 1 White residents, demonstrating that minority impact assessments can effectively address disparities in lawmaking and sentencing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4F83492AF4EC44CB970BE45EA6FBED69"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Similar legislation has since been considered or enacted in New York, Arizona, Arkansas, California, Florida, Hawaii, Illinois, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maryland, Michigan, Minnesota, Mississippi, Missouri, Nebraska, New Mexico, Ohio, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Texas, Utah, Vermont, Washington, Wisconsin, Connecticut, Oregon, New Jersey, Colorado, Maine, and Virginia.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9EEB8A4B54BD4B3C830FABA0E68654A4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The NAACP and the National Black Caucus of State Legislators have adopted resolutions in support of Federal legislation providing for the use of minority impact assessments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0534008095A24223BC2A2B9665C2911F"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Precedent for adopting procedural measures that increase critical deliberation and require independent analysis at the Federal level of racial disparities in criminal justice already exists in the form of scores from the Congressional Budget Office.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4DBF90240B624EEC8F39E1CE9D6BB23F"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Deeply rooted discriminatory policies and practices in our legal system fuel systemic inequalities and cycles of poverty and hardship, stigmatize and exclude people with criminal records, and impede community integration.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE8E74022AE514A5995B1993CBE09E63B"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Requiring an independent assessment with sobering information on the impact of legislation that adds or increases criminal penalties is one way to level the inequities that disproportionately impact people of color, LGBTQ individuals, individuals with disabilities, and other vulnerable groups in sentencing.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB7D620E40807439CACFD8D30E1F2960F"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Congress must institutionalize a more deliberate and evidence-based process prior to voting to criminalize conduct and impose harsh sentences.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB0E7B1BF2B9243BCB791260E96A42367"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to provide a tool for lawmakers and Federal agencies to determine whether pending bills and proposed rules, if enacted, are likely to create or exacerbate disparate outcomes among racial or ethnic minority groups. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="HBC839166A8F54B6CA7EA6D8431291085"><enum>3.</enum><header>Minority impact assessment requirements</header>
<subsection id="HA29CA063B9F14DC0BAE8D63C9094B73F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Minority impact assessments on legislation</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States, in consultation with the Sentencing Commission and the Administrative Office of the United States Courts, shall prepare and submit a minority impact assessment to Congress on a covered bill or joint resolution prior to the consideration of such a bill or joint resolution on the floor of the House of Representatives or of the Senate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1E82F88005C0489288BFE5D8F37580D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Minority impact assessments on rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States, in consultation with the Sentencing Commission and the Administrative Office of the United States Courts, shall prepare and publish in the Federal Register along with the general notice of proposed rulemaking required under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, a minority impact assessment to Congress on a covered rule. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HADB4C88D6EB64598AECCF816E7583B71"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minority impact assessment prepared upon request</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of Congress may request from the Comptroller General of the United States a minority impact assessment on a covered bill or joint resolution. The Comptroller General of the United States shall prepare and submit to Congress such a minority impact assessment not later than 21 days after receiving such a request. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H714AB19EB8204EB7893F0849735E4F6E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Minority impact assessment</header><text>A minority impact assessment shall include— </text>
<paragraph id="H0C6BF7BC2DCB4C3A9F678E7FD85A4E76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>detailed projections of the impact of the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule on pretrial, prison, probation, and post-prison supervision populations, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HD2CE3507EE024FF9906852BFF36AC2C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule would have a negative impact, no impact, a positive impact, a minimal impact, or an unknown impact on such populations; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H70DF31A59FF848FD8FD06FA1D2445289"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule on correctional facilities and services, including any changes to the operation costs for correctional facilities, and any decrease or increase in the populations of individuals incarcerated in correctional facilities; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H12352DF6F5194B4B9E64799DFBA4F31D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a statistical analysis of how the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule would impact pretrial, prison, probation, and post-prison supervision populations, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, disability, gender, and sexual orientation; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H236A140402D9433D8923A881C96CAB20"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an estimate of the fiscal impact of the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule on Federal expenditures, including expenditures on construction and operation of correctional facilities for the current fiscal year and 5 succeeding fiscal years;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3300C4BE98A1416190B82BFF132E5B64"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of any other significant factor affecting the cost of the covered bill or joint resolution or covered rule and its impact on the operations of components of the criminal justice system; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAFEF01E1BE3E44A7B4E8220027CBA2CD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a detailed and comprehensive statement of the methodologies and assumptions utilized in preparing the minority impact assessment.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE93F806BA75A4F1E87F705E79CD08DDB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall prepare and transmit to the Congress, by March 1 of each year, a minority impact assessment reflecting the cumulative effect of all relevant changes in the law taking effect during the preceding calendar year.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA25AE61C27B149799AA4B75ECBF34C9C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after preparing a minority impact statement under subsection (a) or (c)—</text> <paragraph id="HEDD12E81710E4DDE9276E461BAA50A13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Comptroller General of the United States shall publish such minority impact statement on the website of the Government Accountability Office; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB664A27E70F24AE2BB2D43322B79F53E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the sponsor of such covered bill or joint resolution shall submit such minority impact statement for publication in the Congressional Record. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3E2F170104124E3F81ACDB64CC5E371C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HAB382D0208DE4BCBA1E870445287B51C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered bill or joint resolution</header>
<subparagraph id="H9003871BBAD9499C80BE6FA25A3F7D85"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>covered bill or joint resolution</term> means a bill or joint resolution that is referred to the Subcommittee on Crime, Terrorism, and Homeland Security of the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives or the Subcommittee on Criminal Justice and Counterterrorism of the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate and that—</text> <clause id="HC99C9967E2714FEEA92FF5DAF6A57661" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establishes a new crime or offense;</text></clause>
<clause id="H468D16710AB3475B8C9FEE558C4F1002"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">could increase or decrease the number of persons incarcerated in Federal penal institutions;</text></clause> <clause id="H723BE169BFB548A783DAC173BE6E2E2B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>modifies a crime or offense or the penalties associated with a crime or offense established under current law; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HEFBB7582FCC740F5824BBA2EFCF9065E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>modifies procedures under current law for pretrial detention, sentencing, probation, and post-prison supervision.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Such term includes a bill or joint resolution that applies to youth or juveniles.</continuation-text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95E7379DFB834F5BABBF717C9C5EFBAC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of certain bills considered under rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A bill or joint resolution which, upon introduction in the House of Representatives, is not referred to the Subcommittee on Crime, Terrorism, and Homeland Security of the Committee on the Judiciary shall be treated as a covered bill or joint resolution under this Act if—</text>
<clause id="H02689E67DAA34796A2AB3A664FA0AD73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the bill or joint resolution is considered in the House of Representatives pursuant to a rule reported by the Committee on Rules; and</text></clause> <clause id="HCC227101A3C64E5A9340765C74E9D87F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the bill or joint resolution would have been referred to such subcommittee upon introduction if the text of the bill or joint resolution as introduced in the House were identical to the text of the bill or joint resolution as considered in the House pursuant to the rule.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA67BB9DD0334423597E62EFCEA065BBE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered rule</header><text>The term <term>covered rule</term> means a rule (as such term is defined in section 551 of title 5, United States Code) that—</text> <subparagraph id="HA676FF6CD40D4942A0B01694BE2D5DE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">could increase or decrease the number of persons incarcerated in Federal penal institutions; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H28E460E752F941F4AB67D4E153844B41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>modifies a crime or offense or the penalties associated with a crime or offense established under current law; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H043100C710DC4479B4EF87C72AAA3559"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">modifies procedures under current law for pretrial detention, sentencing, probation, and post-prison supervision. </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such term includes a rule that applies to youth or juveniles. </continuation-text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


