<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8389447DCBE445C6A94606F703FC7B25" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>105 HR 4779 IH: Breast Cancer Patient Equity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4779</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide coverage for custom fabricated breast prostheses following a mastectomy.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA754EF0BBF884EE0B4343C14E5438684" style="OLC"><section id="HA9C41CD0CE0140EA9ABE5F239472AB86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header><subsection id="H25325EE6E04543EAA13A0412CFB8BB05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Breast Cancer Patient Equity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1734A0D62BAD43AABAE612E33A7DDC20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H82E15467B32F4D3DAFB52D79BF74C9C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>There are currently more than 4,000,000 women with a history of breast cancer in the United States, many of whom experience unreconstructed breast loss.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29B799C31C1E45CCB0D21A72B9336778"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2023, an estimated 297,790 women will be diagnosed with invasive breast cancer that required surgery, with many having to undergo surgical breast removal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83220401ADEC4EFD805D0DB64FD3C5A0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2023, an estimated 43,100 women in the United States are expected to die from breast cancer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1096205C4EA4958AC4D58AD5FEB3723"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Annually, there are more than 100,000 women in the United States who undergo mastectomies, a surgical removal of the breast.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9F45BEE5C1F44188F875FBA4099E237"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of breast mastectomies in the United States has increased among younger women, ages 18 to 34 years old, at a rate of 30 percent and at a rate of 15 percent for women ages 35 to 44 years old.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB93865A046444DDBBE1C8BBDCAAA9B4E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The results of breast reconstruction surgery can vary and, as with any surgical procedure, there are inherent risks associated with such surgery. Additionally, reconstruction of the breast using implants requires lifelong follow up to ensure the health of the patient.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60FA984234844D7DB5F0D8E187A8550B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>While the number of women choosing to undergo surgical breast reconstruction continues to increase, many women continue to lack the viable option of custom fabricated prosthetic breasts to restore the lost breast.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD601F28B046A44EF8EC6F8B847D73CB3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Both older women and minority women are less likely to be offered or undergo surgical breast reconstruction and are disproportionately disadvantaged by a lack of access to the option of custom fabricated prosthetic breasts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFF562D7B79A42BD88691CFADAF72511"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Currently, the Medicare program provides coverage and reimbursement for custom fabricated prostheses for any body part, with the exception of breasts, that has been lost.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5AF445FB7334C2A97B6A690F4B06758"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Following passage of the Women's Health and Cancer Rights Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/277">Public Law 105–277</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/201">42 U.S.C. 201</external-xref> note), many private insurers and group health plans began to provide coverage for custom fabricated breast prostheses as an alternative to surgical breast reconstruction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40CCFAB0457E45BD8C18C1EA56ABC76A"><enum>(11)</enum><text>While the Medicare program recognizes custom fabricated breast prostheses as a discrete device and valid treatment option, having assigned a billing code for such option under the Healthcare Common Procedure Coding System (<term>HCPCS</term>) and setting a maximum allowable fee, Medicare does not provide reimbursement and denies claims as ‘not medically necessary’. Medicare does provide reimbursement, however, for more costly surgical breast reconstruction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H033E83BEBBEA47FBBC6D67A1A20CD12D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Due to the fact that the Medicare program does not provide reimbursement for custom fabricated breast prostheses, many private insurance companies have also begun to limit their reimbursement for them.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBE5A993315D47A79524C6B699F42EDA"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs does provide the option of a custom fabricated prosthetic breast for women post-mastectomy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10BBD018A8464BB9AC51D86F51C654C0"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Providing coverage for custom fabricated prosthetic breast devices and components will not increase the incidence of breast mastectomies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA8D9337BBF2E48DF938F402D0C8F6D4F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Coverage</header><subsection id="HF0BEC1CC4547436CA5AA200C4819E096"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1861(s)(8) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(s)(8)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4A06EA62EDC549F9AB78EEB9E9EDEA87"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE630B9361B2A4B37886A77F8A788861C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>(A)</quote> after <quote>(8)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6C32EB1E7444C85B790F9A080C13FF1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF78C3A033962434F98E8568AC8263C3E" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HBAB9843DD0CF4E8DBD0A7F54257FEDF7" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">custom fabricated breast prostheses following surgical removal of the breast, including replacement of such prostheses;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9FDBCF902D64677810C635B6ACE8046"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1862(a)(7) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(a)(7)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>1861(s)(8)</quote> and inserting <quote>1861(s)(8)(A)</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCEE7BF7F11A44DD4B9FF2237F2034E38"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to items and services furnished on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

