<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE7F2063332514404A24EF93006AFFBBA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 405 IH: Essential Medicines Strategic Stockpile Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 405</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230120">January 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to provide for stockpiles to ensure that all Americans have access to generic drugs at risk of shortage, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H15817681AF504F348FD158AFB4206071" style="OLC"><section id="HC734ADF56C844D998BAFE4A8362373D4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Essential Medicines Strategic Stockpile Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H024BDC7BB94C4776914221AF18F9AFE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on ensuring medication supply stability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subpart:</text><quoted-block id="HFB8887E856E44411A8B7D56E8C153187" style="OLC"><subpart id="HF7661CF1F89246F68C11CD75CD663D86"><enum>XIII</enum><header>Ensuring Medication Supply Stability</header><section id="H597883665B4C46D58ED7D5E054D8958C"><enum>340J.</enum><header>Ensuring medication supply stability</header><subsection id="H537BA6CBD5574D2DB6E6EF2C5EB193C0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Award of contracts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than January 1, 2024, the Secretary shall award contracts to eligible entities to each implement and test the effectiveness of acquiring, maintaining, managing, and distributing a stockpile that—</text><paragraph id="HB6700B7C22DA4C7090CA723C43B68071"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consists of generic drugs at risk of shortage; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F823442785A43B99F11481150EA35F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is of sufficient quantity to ensure that customers in the United States have access to such drugs for at least 6 months (as specified by the Secretary based on the historic demand for those drugs).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3633365274EF460D88B2EC2B2337B9B3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection of drugs</header><paragraph id="H1FAC9D5F03264362B69D1358E3F74F55"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H3E703A17FABA46E39ECD7D3062083F11"><enum>(A)</enum><text>select not more than 50 drugs that may be included by eligible entities in a stockpile pursuant to a contract under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD00A3B9A3154E5C8825AE21088AD22D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>maintain an up-to-date list of such drugs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H734FF25554D740F7B4C13F61B3EC13CA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make such list publicly available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0642CA964C4245D3939C65C644C5BD28"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Choice of eligible entities</header><text>A contract awarded to an eligible entity under this section need not require the stockpile of the eligible entity to include all 50 drugs listed pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2EED9B1A5EF542A3A60397AEFEC74DAD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sufficient quantity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each generic drug listed pursuant to subsection (b)(1), the Secretary shall specify the quantity of such drug that is sufficient to ensure that consumers in the United States have access to such drug for at least 6 months.</text></subsection><subsection id="H24384A23B4454811AE9B778895DB188A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration; liquidation of inventory</header><paragraph id="H5324D6BDEC7E423AA1C9466BD9140132"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>A contract awarded under this section shall be for a term of no more than 3 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F8845D614CF4B04A78D5DC7231548AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Liquidation of inventory</header><text>A drug held in a stockpile pursuant to a contract under this section may be liquidated by the eligible entity at the end of the period of the contract.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF837C6A17C2941508CA6058164FCCE35"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Stockpile requirements</header><paragraph id="HB32760E9643944DA931865825C6B49FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ensuring availability of unexpired products</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity with a contract under this section for a stockpile of generic drugs at risk of shortage shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5938C6B13ED24B5880E97F55D433077D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that each drug maintained in the stockpile has an expiration date at least 1 year beyond the current date; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93C7E06609DF464BBCA35BF8A8224D76"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to comply with subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H39A6FE0215084492904FBD722633A533"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sell drugs in the stockpile through normal commercial channels and replace those drugs; or</text></clause><clause id="H9E79C60C482F4F119D9AAA008D2FA502"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if there is no commercial market for a drug in the stockpile, dispose of the drug and report such disposal to the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H63B083D46F1B4B34B2AD0638062752DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management of stockpile</header><subparagraph id="HE4318E4FFADB400399B18C9F0F2D2D6A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that—</text><clause id="HB14A5022BFF74067826C553820173052" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collectively, the eligible entities with contracts under this section for a stockpile of generic drugs at risk of shortage acquire, not later than 6 months following the date set in such contracts, and maintain thereafter, a 6-month supply of such drugs; and</text></clause><clause id="HB2E34FAEFE674F46B1241BAF08681C7F" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the 6-month supply required by clause (i) is in addition to the average levels of inventory held by eligible entities over the previous year for the respective drugs.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8B061D9C2004A83BBDAC5E2C24F6ECF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inventory management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity with a contract under this section for a stockpile of generic drugs at risk of shortage shall manage inventory to ensure that drugs in the stockpile are efficiently cycled to the commercial market.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBAACD44A5024C4A8B8ED9165DA682AE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Annual audits</header><text>Not more than annually, the Secretary may request a physical audit count of the inventories of all eligible entities with a contract under this section to validate that each such entity is maintaining the appropriate amount of stockpiled inventory.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAF98DC1BF5B415B84CE8046DDA78DE6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Each eligible entity with a contract under this section shall submit reports at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require regarding—</text><subparagraph id="H12FB63DEF0C24D448A1F6E47460AD959"><enum>(A)</enum><text>current inventory levels of stockpiled drugs at a drug level; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H407E99F2614D42FD9A2E7B49AB5F8621"><enum>(B)</enum><text>indicators of current inventory levels of stockpiled drugs relative to acceptable minimums; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2BA6EF0FCC14CD8B30BED2D7D8F742D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such other matters as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8A9D21E1E604DA28E7C61DA83392E0F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Contract terms</header><paragraph id="H6F317FCF4B8B4769BFBC8E95E433F00A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payment of monthly fees for management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary shall pay to each eligible entity with a contract under this section for a stockpile of generic drugs at risk of shortage appropriate monthly fees for the management of the stockpile.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05BB3F7DA2D440CD89253DAFC954B285"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment conditioned on stockpile adequacy</header><subparagraph id="H10D9B3D65BDE4AB4AFFEB5972B365772"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), each contract with an eligible entity under this section shall provide that no payment under the contract may be made until the entity demonstrates to the Secretary that the entity has stockpiled such portion of the total quantity of drugs to be stockpiled under the contract as the Secretary determines to be acceptable for payment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DCF44E706174CAB8B8E319EE2B533F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions for advance payments</header><clause id="HAD91EDF07C9B4E83B8C093874FE9FC28"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A contract under this section may provide that, if the Secretary determines (in the Secretary’s discretion) that an advance payment, partial payment for significant milestones, or payment to increase capacity is necessary to ensure success of the terms of the contract, the Secretary shall pay, in advance of delivery, an amount not to exceed 10 percent of the total contract amount to be paid to the eligible entity by the Secretary pursuant to the contract over the full period of the contract.</text></clause><clause id="H2506E594ED7546CF803A5141F350CA27"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Cost of capital</header><text>A contract under this section may provide for payments to compensate the contracting eligible entity for additional capital requirements related to the additional inventory to be maintained.</text></clause><clause id="H71959D1FE75B4BA1A9EFECA550883F27"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, make any determination under clause (i) to make an advance payment at the same time as the issuance of a solicitation.</text></clause><clause id="HF8436AD444CA44EF8A1770630EA45116"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Repayment</header><text>If the Secretary makes an advance payment pursuant to clause (i), the Secretary shall require the eligible entity receiving such advance payment to repay it if there is a failure to perform by the eligible entity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB40B05E0F724A528216A78021B2EDD3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as affecting the rights of eligible entities under provisions of statute or regulation (including the Federal Acquisition Regulation) relating to the termination of contracts for the convenience of the Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H78CF5EE765994919A7FCEE3FA9C5ACFD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Congressional oversight</header><paragraph id="H5FE2E91D3DCC4349B79871B36AE7691A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Independent evaluation and report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section and annually thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct an independent evaluation, and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report, concerning the program under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6ECE0C5A13F4516A66A05E6D707C8A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall review, assess, and provide recommendations, as appropriate, on the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5E8260FC496D4059938DCBC23B07E553"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Details on likely costs and resultant savings as compared to a stockpiling method that does not incorporate perpetual inventory cycling.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BFFF4B597E64F6395A1A490FD5F10E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Identification of drawdowns from the stockpile, as evidence of market shortage avoidance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A4A85F525634F79BF16A02FF44B1F22"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The allocation of drugs included in the stockpiles funded pursuant to this section to the customers of the eligible entities with contracts under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H546BF8F1FCBE48DEA45CD869A3F75076"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The degree to which eligible entities with contracts under this section fulfilled their obligations under such contracts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94C848FEEB1C4F6FA5C4FC027088FFE4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6A9D92393C284398955DB1A9F06DAD92" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity that meets each of the following criteria:</text><subparagraph id="H5E941B4A35844D0D95EBA7DCF288230C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The entity is licensed or registered in accordance with applicable Federal and State law and in good standing with respect to such licensure or registration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D8C607925CD4B53875E19711B163ACF" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If the entity is not a manufacturer, the entity agrees—</text><clause id="H5B7E5FFDAD4E4EEF9F43649932243165"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to purchase all drugs to be maintained in its stockpile funded under this section directly from the manufacturers of the drugs or the exclusive distributors of such manufacturers; or</text></clause><clause id="H7C4991DDFAE24812B5E8A40F39797044"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an entity that is a co-op or chain pharmacy warehouse—</text><subclause id="H273837CBFDC44165BF2BA0FF789EEE9C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to purchase drugs to be maintained in its stockpile funded under this section from an authorized distributor; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3D94B765054547F9AC3203756F192B4D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>distribute those drugs only to its member pharmacies.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DB754A249914459B0872A9872673C5D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The entity sells more than 90 percent of its drugs to dispensers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43338087D46944CD9D77FF311424FD60" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The entity agrees to distribute inventory from its stockpile funded under this section only to wholesale distributors or dispensers that are customers of the entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H257CCA0A99E34E1698719EB97B3AE720"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>generic drug at risk of shortage</term> means a drug (as defined in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act) that—</text><subparagraph id="H5E0EE61CCDE54DFC8EF89BCAA3C746C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is approved pursuant to section 505(j) of such Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H133646A3838F45BDB34D8AD3B0292380"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is included in the list of essential medicines published by the Food and Drug Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BFC7680AA7147AD97C0FEF9B297731F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is included, at any point during the preceding 36 months, on the drug shortage list in effect under section 506E of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H463B8F9B95BB4DF186C25B0D85C45EEC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is manufactured by 3 or fewer persons that are registered under section 510 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act for purposes of such manufacture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D64BC5FE2D3445C8F0BEE384F319BD8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $120,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2026, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

