<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5F69C3113F8E40C1A3918D201582B1A8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6693 IH: Lung Cancer Screening and Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6693</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to authorize the coverage of additional lung cancer screening tests under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H325C7A1CCB79431BB48E7DE12FE4AD7E" style="OLC"><section id="H3FCCC519FEE24B8CB38AA091353DD759" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Lung Cancer Screening and Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7B8BC7AED5954519B8393515FD23F634"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority to expand coverage of tests for lung cancer screening under the medicare program</header><subsection id="H4FB6F7B8D07140F0B52B954F9519CEFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1834(n) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(n)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H94D6722F379948F4A9D0869ECDAF1230"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively, with appropriate indentation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA72A9E43A924948AFB8EEA2E5CF9052"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, with appropriate indentation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32C6F2B3D46B4F7997601345D52D7818"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>Notwithstanding any other provision of this title</quote> and inserting: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H729D4DA1BCA74ADA954007675F96B7E8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H652AAD232C0D4EE2962B38390991D347"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this title and subject to paragraph (2)</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0637C97F31C4E669B9EA3D34D858A60"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H5EBFA231CB794CD9A0A871D6A992276D" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H4372D54521A94E1EA4BBC8F63A85598D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to cover new lung cancer screening tests as preventive services</header><subparagraph id="H377E0555F5E74986AA1F4203245C9E4E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), in addition to preventive services consisting of screening tests for the early detection of lung cancer covered under this part pursuant to national coverage determination 210.14, the Secretary may provide for coverage under this part of other lung cancer screening tests that are cleared or approved by the Food and Drug Administration as preventive services when furnished to appropriate individuals (as determined by the Secretary), with such frequency and payment limits as the Secretary determines appropriate in consultation with appropriate organizations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFFAAB1A23FB47D5A50FA8B25782C507"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of national coverage determination process</header><clause id="H6ECDFD516E754874806F797F6FA09EB8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Coverage of other lung cancer screening tests under subparagraph (A) shall be determined using the process for making national coverage determinations (as defined in section 1869(f)(1)(B)), except that there shall be no requirement for a determination under section 1861(ddd)(3)(B) with respect to such test under such process.</text></clause><clause id="HA5B0BF33F296480C88B4F6A7825B2FD9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in clause (i) shall be construed as preventing the Secretary from considering recommendations made by entities with expertise in preventive services, including entities convened by the Secretary or the Director of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, with respect to other lung cancer screening tests described in subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H244422E474334B29B71F0F697D93D0FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act, and apply with respect to coverage of preventive services under Part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j et seq.</external-xref>) on or after such date.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

