<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC09C0322810349039F3FC762B2EBA93D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4072 IH: Methane Emissions Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4072</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230613">June 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to conduct a measurement-based national methane research pilot study to quantify methane emissions from certain oil and gas infrastructure, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA499E2EB61D543FAA6C596DC5C3D5066" style="OLC"><section id="HA565A3E5D2DE41A7B68F9FE21E39E032" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Methane Emissions Research Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4F6536D28605427EB3ADAC9E05037A55"><enum>2.</enum><header>National methane research pilot study</header><subsection id="H308BF68EF6C04847A6C74DA61D2DA5C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator, in collaboration with the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the Administrator of the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and the heads of other Federal agencies as appropriate, shall conduct a measurement-based national methane research pilot study (in this section referred to as the <quote>pilot study</quote>) to quantify methane emissions from covered oil and gas infrastructure. The Administrator shall employ a technology or suite of technologies for methane emissions measurement, research, and analysis. To the extent practicable, the Administrator shall consider utilizing innovative technologies for methane emissions measurement and quantification.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDE78209FBE454FA496A47ECED59D5C7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The pilot study shall—</text><paragraph id="H3E07D74594AF40E8B448E1577DE3BC16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encompass two regions, which shall be determined by the Administrator;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5854193B71C147578DCF25012657B955"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify areas consisting primarily of covered oil and gas infrastructure within each such region;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3EA03D50FDA456390D1BA64F1D44AE1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and implement methodologies and procedures for a measurement-based evaluation of methane emissions from such infrastructure;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H355AEF23F64F4B66BF407DEA60E36D48"><enum>(4)</enum><text>assess diverse approaches to the characterization of methane emissions from such infrastructure; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF0D227C233F4851B722E0C0DCA1F6F2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>consult with Federal, State, local, academic, nonprofit, and private sector entities, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E60B457F40746D39FB7B6DD84D137D1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress, and make publicly available, a report assessing the results of the pilot study. The report shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H4615A6E3DB90424AAB2A8D4C203A1CEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An overview of the findings of the pilot study pertaining to the quantification and characterization of methane emissions from covered oil and gas infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47CDCB96FF85492B9C5CB90B0FDDA0BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An analysis of how the pilot study could support and inform the development and implementation of a national methane census study (in this section referred to as the <quote>methane census</quote>), to be undertaken on a recurring basis and encompass all seven regions. Such analysis shall also examine the following:</text><subparagraph id="HD457D02713284303BD82F729F0FB1A23"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The feasibility of evaluating the amount of methane emissions from covered oil and gas infrastructure by region, industry segment, type of emission source, or any other criterion, as a component of the methane census.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77B1C1D260E44FBFB369722DBCDDC225" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The necessary scope of measurement-based activities within regions in order to carry out the methane census.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H644F22F7F49E4E4483B5608AF2089391" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any onshore or offshore gaps within the scope of the pilot study that could merit inclusion as a part of the methane census.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4DA9F951CD340ABB620A4068FFB2223"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The estimated budget that would be required to oversee the methane census.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F3020A86B4A40DCB40396B94603D288"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any other relevant topic, as determined by the Administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H876E4FCF0B6C4041A9C78EED212725A9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of how the measurement-based evaluation of methane emissions from covered oil and gas infrastructure, as completed by the pilot study or contemplated for the methane census, could support efforts to reconcile data generated by top-down methods and bottom-up methods with respect to the Environmental Protection Agency’s Inventory of U.S. Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Sinks. Such analysis shall also examine the following:</text><subparagraph id="HC3EAD95ED3D7459EBEC11B4B5ED56C91" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>How methane emissions data from the pilot study or methane census could be utilized as a part of a reconciliation process to better understand and improve data estimates from both top-down methods and bottom-up methods.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC20E9AC8AE754D17ACA92E1B120D889E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>How methane emissions data from the pilot study or methane census could identify and help to explore any significant discrepancies between top-down methods and bottom-up methods for methane emissions from covered oil and gas infrastructure.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H097A054CA31741F889C44566B538A849" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any other relevant topic, as determined by the Administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BE7476EEA684B299537ADCE8F3CCA9E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of any research or technology gaps that were identified during the course of the pilot study and could merit additional study to support the improvement of methane emissions measurement and quantification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF39FBB0601964141A9DC0099F09D733C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of the methodology of the pilot study, which, to the greatest extent possible and consistent with appropriate protections for confidential business information and intellectual property, shall include a discussion of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF72A9F60AF2D40128B4FEC564EA657C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Study design.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B5071D5C60E4C1CAFCEF8572D9A6755"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Measurement techniques.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3848877972849A5B8AEBC555ADB5526"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Efforts to account for additional significant sources of methane emissions within a region.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6E6F685A2C64B368E500C66647AF2F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Assumptions and uncertainties in the results of the pilot study.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70962FB323F342F9A7993A17782E0079" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Methane emissions data interoperability</header><text>The Administrator, to the greatest extent possible, shall ensure that all data collected as part of the pilot study adheres to data and metadata standards to support the public findability, accessibility, interoperability, and reusability of such data. The Administrator shall consult with the heads of other Federal agencies, as appropriate, to—</text><paragraph id="HBFD7A62A58BC4DD1A2BD744862637B3A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>facilitate effective data sharing regarding methane emissions measurement and quantification data; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4927803B12C45138F6CF9757F690816" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that methane emissions measurement and quantification data gathered by such other Federal agencies can be converted to a format that is consistent with the methodologies and procedures of the pilot study.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06247A699D7F41E2B6CA9CEA6A3AED6B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $20,000,000, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0626AD2A9B324DE792F10744DAD787CE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDEB34BE7C5A7456B8F37913C0A61614A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71884494DA88454EB3BDE4032C9C6AC2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D60074560684F06A5AF5FE42B50B868"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered oil and gas infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>covered oil and gas infrastructure</quote> means the infrastructure used for the production, gathering and boosting, processing, transmission, and storage of oil and natural gas in the United States. Such term does not include oil and gas distribution infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FFD171DFAB5445699296018B3049A12"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Region</header><text>The term <quote>region</quote> means any of the seven oil and gas regions evaluated by the U.S. Energy Information Administration in its May 2023 Drilling Productivity Report.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

