<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Received-in-Senate" dms-id="H3F9B031E3EE644E780E74F3AF4B54F53" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1734 : Testing, Rapid Analysis, and Narcotic Quality Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1734</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received</action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require coordinated National Institute of Standards and Technology science and research activities regarding illicit drugs containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other substances of concern, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H195967E1EB01451E97292E377FFA8468" style="OLC"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="HFD34206D58574130A8EFE869FF02D3B1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Testing, Rapid Analysis, and Narcotic Quality Research Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRANQ Research Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HD20A3B097FEA4655BB3FA550176AA96C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Xylazine detection and analysis</header><subsection id="H5CB0C20A8375482A88114400A3BD25C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall—</text><paragraph id="H40E79ADE3AA747CF9EFACD291D413EBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support NIST intramural basic measurement science and research to advance—</text><subparagraph id="H5646D6120A5A46FAAB866F33B8646353" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>analytical methods to identify, understand, differentiate, and categorize illicit drugs containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other emerging substances of concern;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56103D3581DD46229AD1DD9C8BB27A2A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>measurement technologies to shorten analysis timelines and enhance narcotic and opioid detection and analysis capabilities in illicit drugs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD73249B4E56446C2877F629F6944D391" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>new data tools, techniques, and processes to identify and publicly disclose relevant information concerning illicit drugs containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other emerging substances of concern; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5603C34B4B3455CA41981D095C6453E" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>all other areas determined by the Director to be critical to the development and deployment of technologies to measure and analyze the presence of xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other emerging substances of concern in illicit drugs;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE813C7F68DDD41CFAF742390F922A44C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support activities to inform and expand the development of near-real time spectrometry capabilities regarding xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other emerging compounds in illicit drugs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA323541552D34B15811576E76003CA34" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>convene the private sector, institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, Federal laboratories, and other Federal agencies engaged in the analysis of illicit drugs to develop coordinated strategies and voluntary best practices for the safe handling, transport, and analysis of illicit drugs containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other emerging substances of concern;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD0A122E278747B8B7767D14DFC96956" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establish or expand collaborative partnerships or consortia with other government agencies engaged in counternarcotic research and development, institutions of higher education, Federal laboratories, and the private sector to enhance narcotic and opioid detection and analysis capabilities regarding xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other emerging substances of concern in illicit drugs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H866DF2D6B6DD47799B3D0D5763C05097" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide opportunities for graduate and postgraduate research on the detection and identification of xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other emerging substances of concern in illicit drugs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2B4D4BFF89247E190E485A7DF80DBF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Controls</header><text>In carrying out activities authorized under this section, the Director shall ensure proper security controls are implemented to protect sensitive information, as appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC39C37BC255E42DEB8D1F9BF9AF39550"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H87BF5E21F1744FF0B99895F70C1121D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F261255B2014DEA9C46B98FD3D8FC07"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal laboratory</header><text>The term <quote>Federal laboratory</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3703">15 U.S.C. 3703</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40A1E6A00F2B4C9298E2EF6024A1FA62"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1001">19 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H666CCD89AA16492489125F84409A3E83"><enum>(4)</enum><header>NIST</header><text>The term <quote>NIST</quote> means the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90178D7020124C0BBAB188EBDBDA5FA0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <quote>nonprofit organization</quote> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F06D8842CBC40E1AEA13F6C2341FA08"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Xylazine</header><text>The term <quote>xylazine</quote> means the nonopioid tranquilizer methyl benzene compound frequently used in veterinary medicine as an emetic and sedative with analgesic and muscle relaxant properties.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCB4A4E87197F442E9FE78ED48BE67159"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later that 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the implementation of this Act. Such report may include legislative recommendations to improve the Director’s ability to carry out section 2.</text></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230511" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives May 11, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

