<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF4347A969E3C4E5394D6C5923DF66D76" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5174 IH: United States-Moldova Defense Partnership Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5174</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230808">August 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for increased defense cooperation between the United States and Moldova.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H268B61268DF040F2A67B8AC72B218D9A" style="OLC"><section id="HB69FBCF43C7B4C46B4EC28B525B98766" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Moldova Defense Partnership Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3E75621D7CB74CB5B1F55AE6DD2E7AAC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H3A2ED36C4BC54FA6A1599DFE303ADF52"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Moldova is a close partner in the European region and the United States should remain committed to supporting its security and prosperity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BBA13A7A29F4B98AB8974A9B9E3968E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Moldova’s military relies on outdated Soviet era equipment that needs to be replaced;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7F55532EE9B42649EE0CD11442F8AB2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>senior Moldovan defense officials have stated they need $275 million to modernize Moldova’s Armed Forces;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16F77EF41717427AA0E4F46E100F5858"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the United States should increase and deepen efforts to partner with and support the modernization of the Moldovan military;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7C8FD3CD620470D8486AE76EC37ADFE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>it is in the interest of the United States that Moldova continues to transition its military equipment away from Russian-produced platforms and weapons systems through the European Recapitalization Incentive Program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE89A70C190D34356AD640276EB2DFF31"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the strategic partnership that the United States and Moldova have established over 30 years is mutually beneficial to the national security of both countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AA4E6A0C13347D19EE877CFAC23D1CC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the United States needs to support Moldova’s reform process consisting of a transition from conscription to an all-volunteer/professional force, modernizing equipment from Soviet to Western systems, creating a “mobile, modular, flexible and function army,” according to the 2022 statement by Defense Minister Antolie Nosatii, and emphasizing air defense capabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44CFD354B2684AEEAF8EBFB6B704AFC8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the United States should continue to invest in International Military Education and Training programs in Moldova.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0FC1310D13BC45B8BDC829E33B1016D7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Funding for the European Recapitalization Incentive Program</header><subsection id="H712ED4F7F38B4FEFBDBE6E1838AFA6A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the maximum extent feasible, amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the European Recapitalization Incentive Program should be considered for Moldova as appropriate to assist the country in meeting its defense needs and transitioning away from Russian-produced military equipment.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3AA5146FD83146D3BE900BFFBACAB397"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that provides a full accounting of all funds distributed under the European Recapitalization Incentive Program, including—</text><paragraph id="H466E8713889D482C8366D2F14224AC0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of how the funds were used in Moldova; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FD3A95A25FA4AF5A646A22F620761AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an accounting of remaining equipment in Moldova that was provided by the then-Soviet Union or Russian Federation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9FB32D018FEE41D7A1154350817FED2F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>For purposes of subsection (b), the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H29CB23BB77CA4AF49DDE3FB8C82726A5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86E6540441424BD9BCE38EF517BE8125"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H13D2D5ADC3194E2AB1B60DA296C7739B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on loan program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that, as appropriate, the United States Government should provide direct loans to Moldova for the procurement of defense articles, defense services, and design and construction services pursuant to the authority of section 23 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2763">22 U.S.C. 2763</external-xref>) to support the further development of Moldova’s military forces.</text></section><section id="H10F93F461B954641AF68B3503E576BDE"><enum>5.</enum><header>IMET cooperation with Moldova</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, there is authorized $1,000,000 for International Military Education and Training assistance for Moldova, which may be made available for the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H7332F610170A4D1DB21FD64810D53A23"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Training of future leaders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDBE782AC6034B70B4DC27A2DB54AF3C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Fostering a better understanding of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B69215C3A994FCB9D17A99598A7AE31"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Establishing a rapport between the United States Armed Forces and Moldova’s military to build partnerships for the future.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2BEB3E2997E44A68828E96CDEDA76F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Enhancement of interoperability and capabilities for joint operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2864E8DBA794CD290634AF83FD3D049"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Focusing on professional military education, civilian control of the military, and protection of human rights.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

