<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H644110BEFC844080B53C95DF8D8D4C4B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6592 IH: Fight Book Bans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6592</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Education to provide grants to local educational agencies to cover the costs of challenges to determinations not to discontinue the use of specific instructional materials, or the availability of specific school library materials, in public elementary and secondary schools, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4DC51849FE4643F08AF1BC6C59B12656" style="OLC"><section id="HE1814911F01245ED8E87C3C1881BB413" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fight Book Bans Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2DCC51FFBBAD4590B594FDDD24D0DF03"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants to reimburse certain costs of challenges to continued use of instructional and library materials</header><subsection id="H6F7463F1C66140079AF23070504DF05B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="HD5390247A9BE4DA6B1B7BADB5B0AAA34"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable program</header><text>The term <quote>applicable program</quote> means any program for which the Secretary of Education has administrative responsibility as provided by law or by delegation of authority pursuant to law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B254B8E40EF4BD7A2B52EACBF888948"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered local educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered local educational agency</quote> means a local educational agency that has the duty and responsibility under law—</text><subparagraph id="HFEC908EE41404FDCA0C8B3B8DDE1193F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to select and provide instructional materials and school library materials for students attending public elementary schools or public secondary schools under the jurisdiction of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1124B45872B4F8E8E2948720C325085"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide, or participate in, a process—</text><clause id="HFAAD8A33CDF84D21B197950D15032A13" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to provide for resolution of an objection by a parent or other person to—</text><subclause id="HEA6F1ECE2D704BE2935FE798B5923BDB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the use of a specific instructional material; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H062A30FDAD5C47529AA8D75AA9E23507"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the availability of a specific school library material; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2D356F620420475B9B0D453C7C2ADF5A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to discontinue the use of the instructional material, or the availability of the school library material, for any grade level or age group if the local educational agency determines that the material is inappropriate or unsuitable; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1290C506AA2644CFA86C4F757B1B5D5E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide, or participate in, a process (including any administrative proceeding or court case) under which a parent or other person who disagrees with a determination made by the covered local educational agency pursuant to subparagraph (B)(ii) to discontinue or not to discontinue the use of an instructional material, or the availability of a school library material, may appeal, or otherwise request reconsideration of, the determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA48937A10E7246B9A5685AD5A4EF450B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>elementary school</quote>, <quote>parent</quote>, <quote>secondary school</quote>, and <quote>Secretary</quote> have the meaning given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4A38FD79D844DD0B4DE6D1A23A21EC3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Instructional material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>instructional material</quote> means instructional content that is provided to a student, regardless of its format, including printed or representational materials, audio-visual materials, and materials in electronic or digital formats (such as materials accessible through the Internet). The term does not include academic tests or academic assessments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3EC4E7DCEC04370B79243C83E6326E7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>local educational agency</quote> means a public elementary school, public secondary school, school district, or local board of education that is the recipient of funds under an applicable program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F0691E96E8C437BBD3C62B6C9C9A93A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>School library material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>school library material</quote> means any material available to a student via the student’s school library, regardless of its format, including printed or representational materials, audio-visual materials, and materials in electronic or digital formats (such as materials accessible through the Internet).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72E441042187406285B1961CBA901E2B"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Student</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>student</quote> means any public elementary school or public secondary school student.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9B7ED38B26344F56A5DEDBDA45C82B41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header><paragraph id="HBA5A8E88A231409DB32813DD9B8E0CE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Education is authorized to make grants to covered local educational agencies to reimburse such agencies for the costs (including costs such as attorneys’ fees and court costs) incurred in connection with a process described in subsection (a)(2)(C), if—</text><subparagraph id="H0E79413246A541FC9924AFB995FCD949"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such costs are not reimbursed by the State or any other person; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13E38D2EC28F41A9A6BAB8FB9271FC2C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such process was initiated due to a determination by the covered local educational agency not to discontinue the use of an instructional material or the availability of a school library material.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50B2CDEEA3AE45AEB6F5CD4107473FF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered local educational agency desiring to receive an award under paragraph (1) shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary shall require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C6C57CA228B4C6DA683F0FF791D06BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The maximum amount that a covered local educational agency is eligible to receive under this subsection is $100,000 for each determination described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24D9D171AA794658A9E2001EF5F3474E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Award process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall ensure that the award process is based on content-neutral and viewpoint-neutral criteria and does not take into account the content of the instructional material or school library material concerned.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF588394399294907B6508CD7BDE887A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated a total of $15,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

