<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H993BD5762D024362B508C4E93ED9B56B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4711 IH: Protecting Taxpayers from Student Loan Bailouts Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4711</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To limit the authority of the Secretary of Education to propose or issue regulations and executive actions.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE5C25CAE755446578E55ABB8ABD81297" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6364A80DF5154762A3EA1939C322F956" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Taxpayers from Student Loan Bailouts Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2D046D49CF764134ADE5964579BF637A" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on authority of Secretary of Education to propose or issue regulations and executive actions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part G of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1088">20 U.S.C. 1088 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 492 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1098a">20 U.S.C. 1098a</external-xref>) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5CC9C0362AA405C9C76B9F1131F72B8"> 
<section id="H55C3BA278EF2441090B15A236ECFA35F" commented="no"><enum>492A.</enum><header>Limitation on authority of the Secretary to propose or issue regulations and executive actions</header> 
<subsection id="H3F1703D5B1C34718B61D0527BA71BA62" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Draft regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning after the date of enactment of this section, a draft regulation implementing this title (as described in section 492(b)(1)) that is determined by the Secretary to be economically significant shall be subject to the following requirements (regardless of whether negotiated rulemaking occurs): </text> <paragraph id="H1B47877FEEE44E588B9E762F9245466B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall determine whether the draft regulation, if implemented, would result in an increase in a subsidy cost. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9DD091775E164C5A9C1B30D0F2BD3D94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>If the Secretary determines under paragraph (1) that the draft regulation would result in an increase in a subsidy cost, then the Secretary may take no further action with respect to such regulation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC48938A91F944AD58181C70F94661F20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proposed or final regulations and executive actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary may not issue a proposed rule, final regulation, or executive action implementing this title if the Secretary determines that the rule, regulation, or executive action—</text> 
<paragraph id="H71BD84B18BEC41ACBA8BD70BEBCC4C52" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is economically significant; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1AA27FFB20CB4C1F9CE14757EA158DCA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>would result in an increase in a subsidy cost.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB223D5C55B148FC94A72F0035539B88" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relationship to other requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The analyses required under subsections (a) and (b) shall be in addition to any other cost analysis required under law for a regulation implementing this title, including any cost analysis that may be required pursuant to Executive Order 12866 (58 Fed. Reg. 51735; relating to regulatory planning and review), Executive Order 13563 (76 Fed. Reg. 3821; relating to improving regulation and regulatory review), or any related or successor orders.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAE169A03DCA64FAF822D0EB352F85930" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>economically significant</term>, when used with respect to a draft, proposed, or final regulation or executive action, means that the regulation or executive action is likely, as determined by the Secretary—</text> 
<paragraph id="H63DEBBA673464F5BA6F1FBE76FD02CD5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to have an annual effect on the economy of $100,000,000 or more; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H739FA6A1F80B4A2EAF6309258E2CCD49" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>adversely to affect in a material way the economy, a sector of the economy, productivity, competition, jobs, the environment, public health or safety, or State, local, or tribal governments or communities.<italic></italic></text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

