<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFDEA4AC8460546C58235863D06D088BE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4529 IH: Public Health Guidance Transparency and Accountability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4529</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act regarding guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A5233C05EA2423E9A1CD18B0D4195EB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBD0B6C62A720448CA0E74A1DE7AA25E1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Public Health Guidance Transparency and Accountability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H755894D371BE4C39B50DF0745CD3BE72"><enum>2.</enum><header>CDC guidance documents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/201">42 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 317V of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-24">42 U.S.C. 247b–24</external-xref>) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H945945C443BF4FA1B35CAA8FA2E5DC1D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H1863BA129EC6414BBE6F14E946CC5184"><enum>317W.</enum><header>CDC guidance documents</header> 
<subsection id="H7997F42C6FBD4B36A25311CD48CBCB5A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Good guidance practices</header> 
<paragraph id="HD9A836A70FC54D2EA587DFD6114B849A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall, by regulation, develop, establish, and maintain good guidance practices setting forth the policies and procedures of the Centers for the development, issuance, dissemination, and use of guidance documents.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H707D013EACE44B4FAF3F48D440E49D40"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulation required by paragraph (1) shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCA443EAFC8F8450F9BC7446F100F6B70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>incorporate each requirement of subsections (b) through (k); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6028784375A44771A6C42918CBCD839E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require guidance documents to be developed with public participation.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31DEA81CD77F46FA8842E337DEC3EC50"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Initial regulation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H04A0D77A8E8446F6B6B31E5152628A2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Public Health Guidance Transparency and Accountability Act of 2023</short-title>, initiate the rulemaking process for the initial regulation under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H288D3AC6B0F746299E2D8DFE60AA1F93"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Public Health Guidance Transparency and Accountability Act of 2023</short-title>, finalize such regulation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2266F289B8A54C898D7B5B6004B1B712"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No creation, conferring, restricting, or revoking of rights, responsibilities, or liabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention may present views on matters under the jurisdiction of the Centers, but shall not—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1A6F433BFABA430CBEC72053452BFE02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create, confer, restrict, or revoke any rights, responsibilities, or liabilities for or on any person;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2078D2F1B644CFA865E93176E22A51E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be treated (including in any civil or criminal proceeding) as having the force and effect of law; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8FC2D28936B455A82204CEC97163E89"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include any provision that—</text> <subparagraph id="HC97657BDCD404DADAE7B133335AAF274"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is binding on the public or a State, local, Tribal, or Territorial government; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68B1E99D50474A429BE1BBA6384E42DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>requires an individual to take or refrain from an action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H90E24CB3E90A44A5A7DD4AD4792FF574"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect on CDC employees and contractors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Although guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall not be binding on the Secretary or the Director of the Centers, the Secretary shall ensure that employees and contractors of the Centers do not deviate from such guidance documents without appropriate justification and supervisory concurrence.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H932D52EB94D348A7AF4B74BD043E5A5E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H2714CDD5402E40EB97861E781F6201AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide training to employees of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in how to develop, issue, disseminate, and use guidance documents in accordance with the regulation under subsection (a)(1); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAFD9B894B7374787868CF8FA9DD7E8AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">monitor the development, issuance, dissemination, and use of such documents to ensure compliance with the regulation under subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5C8E78AC12E345E69A2214823B5697A4" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public participation in process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"></text> 
<paragraph id="H2DF6F4A2504C4B24A19FB8D331B78A0E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary shall ensure that public participation required by subsection (a)(2)(B) occurs prior to finalization and implementation of any guidance document, including any guidance document that sets forth—</text> <subparagraph id="H6BE600B5DD9D429888DE9670FFC8E131" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>initial interpretations of a statute, a regulation, or an emerging public health situation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF95C9F2753C84F19951D64C6073AADB1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>changes or updates in interpretation or policy that are of more than a minor nature;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C2A985E83CE4748BFA861488E927CB0" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>complex scientific issues; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85A59C10655A42BD972227DB01D5F87D" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>highly controversial issues.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC41557F6DD374AE7AF66F94D5AE07C61" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide for public participation required by subsection (a)(2)(B) to occur after the guidance document has been finalized and after implementation of the guidance document has begun if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2F25FF499145426BA2D923739D9A29B9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that commencing public participation sooner is not feasible or appropriate; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H424909FC01014977BC5576E1E5964781" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the guidance document sets forth only existing practices or minor changes in policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD43B9B080F264E38A137E368C4613AD2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>In finalizing, implementing, and revising a guidance document, the Secretary shall take into account public comments received during public participation on the guidance document.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4D7B3782102B405182CCD44104170F69"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Uniform nomenclature</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> In developing guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Secretary shall ensure uniform nomenclature for such documents and uniform internal procedures for approval of such documents.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE165F19ABAB04F048AB7F0709226EAB0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Indication of nonbinding nature</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and revisions of such documents are properly dated and indicate the nonbinding nature of the documents.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB52397626A2E4D5A8B256E7D979BAE16"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Periodic review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall periodically review all guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and, where appropriate, revise such documents. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H63F9097337A14590A3DE21BCA29CA81F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>List of documents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall maintain electronically and update and publish periodically in the Federal Register a list of all guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H232006A3142F40C8B33409644AAD0DA1"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make available to the public the list under subsection (i) and all guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, including by posting on the public website of the Centers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF90031D8C7A44156869757A32586D5FE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Appeals mechanism</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that an effective appeals mechanism is in place to address complaints that guidance documents of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention are not being developed, issued, disseminated, or used in accordance with this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill>

