<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H61E5B78B009E4F1A860A544D43905129" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 550 IH: Fire Information and Reaction Enhancement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 550</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to maintain a program that improves wildfire forecasting and detection, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HACF5BBCF349844D58FB6B3AE66CA94F6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCC2F2798B768473BAF68EF34AAE25B7B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fire Information and Reaction Enhancement Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FIRE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF4CC46B922E748F98BA2DA9D455F1547"><enum>2.</enum><header>Wildfire forecasting and detection</header> <subsection id="H5F271543781343DDA5E1608F8A7F6244"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="H816679794B5546A9AB66B19B1D334D56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in collaboration with the United States weather industry and such academic entities as the Administrator considers appropriate, shall establish a program within such Administration to improve wildfire forecasting and detection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E964A21E4FA49F68476399E7D57277D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the program under paragraph (1) shall be to develop and extend accurate wildfire forecasts and warnings in order to reduce loss of life, injury, property, and damage to the economy, with a focus on improving the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H60D948FD3A2544EFBF82E4FC9BEE590C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The prediction of intensification and spread of wildfires.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6253AE9341914E0AA052F40C7A3458EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The forecast and communication of smoke dispersion from wildfires.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H41B0911086DA4E48ABFC793ABDD5574B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Information dissemination and risk communication to create more effective watch and warning products.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6714E8B0F9BD4B9BA084D03F359F111D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The early detection of wildfires to contain their growth and mitigate damages.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H580E9454F36B41C88F668D5AAF43BF14"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to meet the goals specified in paragraph (2), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration is authorized to conduct development, testing, and deployment activities related to the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0C860FBF39474ED59D2E6DFC5A704040"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Advanced satellite detection products.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DD4DBFCDD6948EBBA7B96B67B4B60BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Grid-based assessments and outlooks of fuel moisture and danger levels.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3DA174C93B84426E9C99930537991C79"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Coupled atmosphere and fire modeling systems.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5AEC00DA112E4BFF990629F73F432F4E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Systems to link climate predictions to achievable land management decisions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F9590155D58495684944507B1A02ABE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Improved spatial and temporal resolution observations in high latitudes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCE21FF1C64D3439F87E95E618F1A13F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Construction authorization</header> <paragraph id="HB200372733D94A768007B2AEDFF5518A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Administrator for the Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research, in partnership with industry and academic partners, shall establish a program to create one or more weather research testbeds to develop improved detection of and forecast capabilities for wildfire events and their impacts.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9EA724F9DB9C49D5A7B47A7742980615"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under paragraph (1), the Assistant Administrator for the Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research may not utilize resources for such testbeds from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration cooperative institutes in existence as of the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68D0582151EA4FCFB65E20D9D1B15D03" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out the program under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

