<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02B7A6F362384148A4F60DFF2A8802B3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5394 IH: Expanding Remote Monitoring Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5394</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure appropriate access to remote monitoring services furnished under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H117865F224DC4162AC0F568F51F139B0" style="OLC"><section id="HBE5B4E3DEADB428995B35333A46D8172" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Remote Monitoring Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFCABFBB78CF146E484869EE845EFAF72"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H0298AB0CA47D42E3A3E29C22D6886554"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Remote monitoring is an option that can help patients manage their health conditions from their homes with oversight from their health care providers, which can improve patient health outcomes, reduce long-term health costs, and increase care options for patients.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB181C32C320D4A60BF6F15B809B6461D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) saw such results in a 2019 report. Veterans enrolled in remote patient monitoring had a 53 percent decrease in VA bed days of care and a 33 percent decrease in VA hospital admissions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE66FDF696FFE443691A0CD84F7881252"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providers are currently required by Medicare to collect 16 days of patient data over a 30-day period in order to bill Medicare for remote monitoring services, even in cases where this full duration is not medically necessary to ensure the health and safety of the patient. This can limit the use of remote monitoring in instances where it can promote patient health and safety and where it can reduce the overall cost on the health system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61F0B6586CBA4DDDB7C637A8966C03A8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the 2021 Physician Fee Schedule, the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) issued an interim policy to lower the duration required by Medicare to bill for remote monitoring services from 16 days to 2 days within a 30-day period, but only for individuals who had been diagnosed with, or were suspected of having, COVID–19. This short-term flexibility called attention to the long-term need to reassess the minimum duration required for providers to bill for remote monitoring.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC87DC4773AD42F2B2596F6DE9492D6B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>As part of issuing the 2021 Physician Fee Schedule, CMS studied comments in support of permanently lowering the minimum required duration of remote monitoring for all patients, not just those with COVID–19.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B602A85379941C19957C107507DC61C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>CMS concluded that <quote>we agree that a full 16 days of monitoring may not always be reasonable and necessary</quote> but did not revise the 16 day per 30-day period minimum duration for all patients because CMS did not believe they had received <quote>specific clinical examples</quote> to allow for <quote>understanding under what clinical circumstances fewer days of monitoring would be medically reasonable and necessary and allow a practitioner to establish clinically meaningful care</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7939D5E0307549549385E84C0099D47F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Clinical evidence shows numerous instances in which fewer than sixteen days of monitoring within a 30-day period establishes clinically meaningful care. These include:</text><subparagraph id="H1A9FE29277E944158F2C9996FFBD07B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Sixteen days of monitoring per 30-day period may not be required to establish that a patient has sleep apnea.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF0B8D97D0D5428B8B3FD07CF2BDDDEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A patient prescribed a narcotic for pain may require their breathing to be monitored only while on the medication.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAEB2256D9DE744C7B8E46B96847D4ED7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A patient with a chronic condition like diabetes, congestive heart failure, or obesity may have their weight monitored over a longer period of time, but it is not clinically appropriate to have such patient step on a scale 16 or more times in each 30-day period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29C7DBFDA59D45148D842A763B175E5E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A patient whose blood pressure or oxygen levels are monitored during physical therapy may not necessitate 16 days of monitoring in each 30-day period given physical therapy is often ordered twice weekly.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71EBB05AC5434A4B8FD95791200B40AA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A patient who wears a heart monitor to measure palpitations may wear the monitor continuously, but the data only needs to be collected when the individual is experiencing symptoms.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28481AE0379D4F88B0E7C76F2DC954E2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A patient with hypertension is often monitored for long-term management of this condition on more of a weekly basis, only needing more frequent data collection for active monitoring with changes in medication or dosages.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19C4B4925B3D4C758AF892AF35B3601E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A patient who suffers from Muscular Sclerosis or Muscular Dystrophy may benefit from a provider tracking the patient’s exercise between visits to monitor certain physiologic parameters such as muscle movement but may not produce 16 days of data in a 30-day period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA0CD1ED55774D8BB2F8ABBB05B6A92B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>A patient who needs a total joint replacement may simply need pre-testing for surgery baselines, including to establish gait, force, activity, heart rate and other factors and then compare pre-surgery and post-surgery function.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1E8EBED2A274C37A762EE175BA4E0B4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>For a patient with urologic dysfunction, male urine flow data obtained from the patient can be collected in two to four consecutive days.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59F086FFB0A64A0EAEBD9901540FEE24"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Remote monitoring may allow a provider to assess a patient’s adherence, range of motion, and response to physical therapy and occupational therapy regimens even though many such regimens are less than 16 days per month.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6E077A1A4924039A37217C8105232F1"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Monitoring cognitive behavioral therapy for less than 16 days in a 30-day period may provide clinically meaningful care while moderating a patient’s anxiety and other symptoms.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H638685A7670F4BB593ADD5635B1EA19D"><enum>(L)</enum><text>A patient with respiratory issues may not require a full 16 days of monitoring of inhaler usage to get clinical benefits from remote monitoring.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD784CC03A68B474B8927B453B00A915C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A two-day minimum duration would permit Medicare coverage of the full range of remote monitoring services that can be beneficial to a patient without precluding the differential reimbursement of individual remote monitoring services based on patient acuity and cost.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE9E2C596E2594589807492CA686DD7D5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ensuring appropriate access to remote monitoring services furnished under the medicare program</header><subsection id="H39365B38CEBF42848451220676864509"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall ensure that remote monitoring services furnished under title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>) during the period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act and ending on the date that is 2 years after such date of enactment are payable for a minimum of 2 days of data collection over a 30-day period, regardless of whether the individual receiving such services has been diagnosed with, or is suspected of having, COVID–19.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4A08BDF92A2E42078A1C063503395D4A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H92E8C045E1FB41C5906ED33F74463667"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, after consulting with entities specified in paragraph (2), submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="H266129D2B9A347C9BFCD25A2DF740C16"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A summary and analysis of previous experience with such remote monitoring services being payable under such title for a minimum of 2 days of data collection over a 30-day period.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2D16DA31519491D884FEB2FAAB6F53B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations for implementing a reimbursement model that takes into account patient acuity and cost of providing remote monitoring services, including potentially creating differential reimbursements for periods with different durations, such as fewer than and more than 16 days.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H332459A384D74B2098AFF935579F6BBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis and justification for the appropriate place of service and supervision requirements for non-clinical staff reviewing and escalating patient data and provide recommendations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB64D5F5B75442B1A0F03A577751F459"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the estimated savings resulting from earlier interventions and fewer days of hospitalizations among patients furnished remote monitoring services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9BD9A10B4E8415EB13192C41E2D15D0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specified entities</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the entities specified in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H26AB1C7EF35C49D7BC211F676F08F115"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Relevant agencies within the Department of Health and Human Services (including, with respect to issues relating to waste, fraud, or abuse, the Inspector General of such Department).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA8794DC9E064838BD042E77028D68FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs (including the Office of Connected Care of such Department).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61F42BA748DC49D18D45DD3FBFBAD8E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Licensed and practicing osteopathic and allopathic physicians, anesthesiologists, physician assistants, and nurse practitioners.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0ADF753D996A4770B716741BD2A7FF54"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Hospitals, health systems, academic medical centers, and other medical facilities, such as acute care hospitals, cancer hospitals, psychiatric hospitals, hospital emergency departments, facilities furnishing urgent care services, ambulatory surgical centers, Federally qualified health centers, rural health clinics, and post-acute care and long-term care facilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E03E33B0ED046D09F71AEB9C2282E09"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Medical professional organizations and medical specialty organizations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA75BE79B41614E50B17E0C58A4C21565"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Organizations with expertise in the development of or operation of innovative remote physiologic monitoring services technologies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H293DF6E2F06B4A74954B5FD68BA0BCDD"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Beneficiary advocacy organizations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86630AA885824C8B8EE6FA604B3E48A0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The American Medical Association Current Procedural Terminology Editorial Panel.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA02D8329B8CC45E6AF68A41D3F1FDC7D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Commercial payers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FEEE492E5E64F49877FE27548904E40"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Any other entity determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDDDCAB84AC6342C5871D3A7124A75BD4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H876EBF5B224C4B5685DA6FB5F060AFAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Remote monitoring</header><text>The term <quote>remote monitoring</quote> means remote physiologic monitoring and remote therapeutic monitoring.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF7CB85768F6422B9736DDCC0E613417"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Remote physiologic monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>remote physiologic monitoring</quote> means non-face-to-face monitoring and analysis of physiologic factors used to understand a patient’s health status, including the collection and analysis of patient physiologic data that are used to develop and manage a treatment plan related to chronic or acute conditions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33A1B51330D944D0863E10F0898F0772"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Remote therapeutic monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>remote therapeutic monitoring</quote> means the use of medical devices to monitor a patient’s health or response to treatment using non-physiological data. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

