<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H155B9ABDE1DE4A19ADB5BA457D871175" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3907 IH: United States-Israel International Development Cooperation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3907</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 to authorize appropriations for certain cooperative projects among the United States, Israel, and developing countries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H414D7C28163543CE9DB775B48FEA851B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3BFD8F681F714572A9EB52C1B4F35FE5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Israel International Development Cooperation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H37EFDB1613674803AD266E253F0B817D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9CAD11916DBE449381A5A453062A61F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shared international development cooperation between the United States and Israel benefits the development efforts of the United States through the sharing of Israel’s unique expertise as seen in the work done by Israel’s Agency for International Development Cooperation (MASHAV) as well as Israel’s humanitarian programs and robust civil society sector;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2C8FC6D6EDF4B68B81889F85DFF4667"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">since the signing of a memorandum of understanding for global development cooperation between the United States Agency for International Development and MASHAV on August 21, 2019, the United States and Israel have collaborated on a number of initiatives in Africa, Eastern Europe, and Latin America across such sectors as water technology, agriculture, and education;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEB36B71212AA4FC58A748C60F018DE3D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>this ongoing cooperation harnesses the strengths of the United States and Israel in carrying out projects in developing countries and demonstrates the shared commitment of both the United States and Israel to international development, thereby furthering the policy of the United States to expand prospects for engagement and normalization between Israel and other countries; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FF6C38B39084B3DB7D4673E5A1986B8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the United States should continue to partner with Israel to advance common goals on energy, agriculture, food security, democracy, human rights, governance, economic growth, trade, education, environment, global health, water, and sanitation, with a focus on strengthening mutual ties and cooperation with other countries throughout the world.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD8F03D8007CC46C0AC386418C1F38261"><enum>3.</enum><header>Cooperative projects among the United States, Israel, and developing countries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 106(e) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151d">22 U.S.C. 2151d(e)</external-xref>) is amended in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text> <paragraph id="H375C0A83C6904BC39F68B27EF265CA5C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>$2,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$4,000,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4217C1A93D02457D954BC72A61E152CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2021 through 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2024 through 2026</quote>.</text></paragraph> </section> <section id="H526F785F51764B7282B8A6BA18FE8925"><enum>4.</enum><header>USAID report to Congress on expanding development cooperation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall prepare and submit, to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate, a written report on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4DCF3E1C19A44AF0ACB66C02E371FD3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the feasibility and advisability of expanding development projects under section 106(e) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 to include multilateral cooperation among the United States, Israel, and regional Arab partners that promote new development projects, including in Africa; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC410D00B9C0B453E865C89AE94B0694B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the need for additional resources to do so.</text> </paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

