<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEDB9AC0C47F74C95A2BAD23CE5F5B216" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6196 IH: Israel-Hamas War Crimes Deterrence and Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6196</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a comprehensive report on the Federal Government’s efforts to collect, analyze, and preserve evidence of atrocities committed during Hamas’s attack on Israel, public dissemination campaigns to ensure those responsible for the attacks are identified and prosecuted, and efforts to leverage international cooperation and best practices regarding current Israeli-Hamas war.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6DFF057D9E404E9399D905CCC06A884F" style="OLC"><section id="H29CFDE4AF65E44EEBF07AE06E42A57FA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Israel-Hamas War Crimes Deterrence and Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H168F220DBC1E4AA89AD4CFACA1E0D7F1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H1EDF6481418F4CA291B6882B462EDADD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in its premeditated, unjustified, and deadly assault on Israel in years on October 7, 2023, Hamas militants crossing the border with a heavy barrage of rockets and gunmen, resulting in the deaths of at least 1,400 Israelis and 32 United States citizens, crimes that include but are not limited to—</text><subparagraph id="HCC52FA336B784904AEE334C178A4DC0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the deliberate killing of civilians in their homes, including men, women, and children;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64B10833C76C40C0BE62863D65137951"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the taking hostages that include Israeli and United States citizens; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F07FEA58D4647F5AF691EC814EE214A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the wanton destruction of property and civilian infrastructure; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAE0D4891D6A408C8F0ED45D14EE4D41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>and other international human rights violations.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4C12E493895D494ABF05E914FE0F8CF2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H15E92CD9099D4E6CBF279EE11C48B5EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to collect, analyze, and preserve evidence and information related to war crimes and other atrocities committed during Hamas’s attack on Israel that began on October 7, 2023, for use in appropriate domestic, foreign, and international courts and tribunals prosecuting those responsible for such crimes consistent with applicable law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE3D9BD966604943A28FEADEF5F8EC36"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to help deter the commission of war crimes and other atrocities in Israel and surrounding areas by publicizing to the maximum possible extent, efforts to identify and prosecute those responsible for the commission of war crimes during the full-scale attack of Israel that began on October 7, 2023; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H881D1BE777F9456881CDC9B92AFE7737"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to continue efforts to identify, deter, and pursue accountability for war crimes and other atrocities committed around the world and by other perpetrators, and to leverage international cooperation and best practices in this regard with respect to the current situation in Israel.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBE27ED6FC6D44A0BA78B387EFAA8F695" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report on United States efforts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and consistent with the protection of intelligence sources and methods, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report, which may include a classified annex, describing in detail the following—</text><paragraph id="H6082475451A5407ABACB38A403345F8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>United States Government efforts to collect, analyze, and preserve evidence and information related to war crimes and other atrocities committed during the full-scale attack of Israel by Hamas, including a description of—</text><subparagraph id="HF38C6DEB3E7C430C89C7B45A97A897BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the respective roles of various agencies, departments, and offices, and the interagency mechanism established for the coordination of such efforts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9748C55920904C6EAF1C895E0657493D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the types of information and evidence that are being collected, analyzed, and preserved to help identify those responsible for the commission of war crimes or other atrocities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H554CD243BDF9436B91BA0CBBE27A79F0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>steps taken to coordinate with, and support the work of, allies, partners, international institutions and organizations, and nongovernmental organizations in such efforts;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0E692658CA844D98234FF8C23106507"><enum>(2)</enum><text>media, public diplomacy, and information operations to the world aware of efforts to identify and prosecute those responsible for the commission of war crimes or other atrocities during this conflict, and of the types of acts that may be prosecutable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01514CA79A1A4AB1BC20959583202310"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the process for a domestic, foreign, or international court or tribunal to request and obtain from the United States Government information related to war crimes or other atrocities committed during this attack.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

