<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H34A89D3C3A0C4AF89C113F0AAC594703" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4727 IH: No Obamacare for Illegal Aliens Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4727</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To exclude certain individuals subject to certain deferred action from eligibility for health plans offered on the Exchanges, advance payments of the premium tax credit, cost-sharing reductions, a Basic Health Program, and for Medicaid and the Children’s Health Insurance Programs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H507BC20905D9457A92909CD1EF67BCBB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H22CCA7CD7A054888AC81B33131095442" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Obamacare for Illegal Aliens Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H238C5921008E45669627F95A102BEE0C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of individuals subject to certain deferred action for purposes of enrollment in health plans offered on the Exchanges</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H397461C7C817468DB623594E8B536B9F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enrollment ineligibility</header><text>Section 1312(f)(3) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18032">42 U.S.C. 18032(f)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, shall not be treated as lawfully present for purposes of the preceding sentence.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H201989481787432D8026CB093F3DAD3A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ineligibility for credit for coverage under a qualified health plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">section 36B(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, shall not be treated as lawfully present for purposes of the preceding sentence.</quote>.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H497F50412E7C45AA9704AD5D5ED94A8F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ensuring that taxpayer funds for health insurance coverage are available only to authorized individuals</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84CD35C2AC4848C89AC041E9CF79F873"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Basic health programs</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1D0E7430AA142D7997AD4B54787C7F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1331(e)) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18051">42 U.S.C. 18051(e)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A13709FDB334223970F7E9548A2898F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC449EA6A09FD45E095DFEC7FBC02781E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking the second sentence; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE281C168AB04C20A2A61052FF5D8FD1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1), the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H97EF783F687C4C65807C70CBFC87A299"> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD2A347C4532409582480522E74C1CEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>Such term shall not include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03A612107645441DB2288B7252A09E04"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any individual who is not a qualified individual under section 1312 who is eligible to be covered by a qualified health plan offered through an Exchange.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H71D24D062E2A4414804DFCF5F5A21CED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any individual who is neither a citizen or national of the United States nor an alien lawfully present in the United States. Any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, shall not be treated as lawfully present for purposes of the preceding sentence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47C677BB6BE74A1EBDD09BC60487B3E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text>Section 1331(d) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18051">42 U.S.C. 18051(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C73CEB321EB40E689C081314E43FE7D"> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H839A7893E64A43CFA072FF7117A57064"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of pass-Through funding for certain individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No amounts transferred to a State under this section may be used to offset the cost of health insurance coverage (including through premium or cost sharing reductions) or to provide any other benefit with respect to an individual who is not an eligible individual (as defined in subsection (e)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAEDAE5DC869A4E1D89E09238F00794D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State innovation waivers</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE83FEB1E0FF4867BA233C8D338D6E0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1332(a)(2)(B) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18052">42 U.S.C. 18052(a)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(other than the requirement described in section 1312(f)(3))</quote> before the period.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EEBB7FF0CC44A318F77539DC5C441D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of pass-Through funding for certain individuals</header><text>Section 1332(a)(3) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18052">42 U.S.C. 18052(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>No amounts paid to a State under this paragraph may be used to offset the cost of health insurance coverage (including through premium or cost sharing reductions) or to provide any other benefit with respect to an individual who is not a citizen or national of the United States or an alien lawfully present in the United States. Any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, shall not be treated as lawfully present for purposes of the preceding sentence.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H556677A00D074876B4753D1A12B2CC61"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Medicaid and CHIP</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAB54140E4ED4AE5ACFCF36B7F17781D"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Exclusion from definition of qualified alien under PRWORA</header><text>Section 431 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1641">8 U.S.C. 1641</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H537D98B485CE4771BA602C53AFCF2B84"> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H692FA5A5822641F8BAEF1A84111AC880"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Treatment of certain deferred action under Medicaid and CHIP</header><text>For purposes of this title, the term <term>qualified alien</term> shall not include any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, but only with respect to the designated Federal program defined in section 402(b)(3)(C) (relating to the Medicaid program) and the State Children's Health Insurance Program established under title XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>). An individual granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum described in the preceding sentence shall not be treated as lawfully present or lawfully residing for purposes of the designated Federal program defined in section 402(b)(3)(C) (relating to the Medicaid program) or the State Children's Health Insurance Program established under title XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE20A2C0D115488D84F163E1B2277768"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion from CHIPRA coverage option</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83E196919876410BA3449005BDB72489"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1903(v)(4) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(v)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35B8712FD9F14FE189448FE87664CBF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>A State may</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subparagraph (D), a State may</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H017CBF466B974F90B1A6AE21BD64F778"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F18E6EB39A148D0AA84B70AB78EC8EA"> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93984333777B417397D5250E77206FBE" indent="up2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any alien who is lawfully present in the United States solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, shall not be treated as lawfully present or lawfully residing for purposes of an election by a State to provide medical assistance to a category of aliens under subparagraph (A) and shall not be considered to be described within either or both of the eligibility categories described in such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H159E6619B63341E9B6930CCB94F8B8E3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>Section 2107(e)(1)(O) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397gg">42 U.S.C. 1397gg(e)(1)(O)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, and subject to subparagraph (D) of such paragraph</quote> after <quote>title XIX</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H421433F6D6184BB5AC2150CB3AE054ED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusion from other pregnancy-related coverage options under CHIP</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCF22B56FB09244D189630DBB2879352E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definition of child</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2110(c)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397jj">42 U.S.C. 1397jj(c)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>Such term, including as applied under section 457.10 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this sentence), shall not include any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, and any such individual shall not be treated as lawfully present or lawfully residing in the United States for purposes of eligibility for child health assistance under a State plan under this title.</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C00183A69F64EC8BB5F1A9FF9B98215"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Targeted low-income pregnant women</header><text>Section 2112 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397ll">42 U.S.C. 1397ll</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D332A1C976F41E3B8D6D83FB8C22B0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(2), by inserting after and below subparagraph (C), the following new flush sentence:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E942E283B3B4E8B828B71AF617C46EC"> 
<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such term shall not include any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, and any such individual shall not be treated as lawfully present or lawfully residing in the United States for purposes of eligibility for pregnancy-related assistance or child health assistance under a State plan under this title.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> 
<clause id="H285C71C1173C4C45B5602EABEFFCCEB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (f), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE1AAE2B8A7F499682DD7BA951E71474"> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6A87299E2C37452C9B2CC5BCACB2562D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (3), a State shall not provide child health assistance under any authority described in paragraph (1)(A) or pregnancy-related services under a waiver specified in paragraph (1)(B) to any alien who is lawfully present solely because such individual was granted deferred action pursuant to the memorandum of the Department of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote> issued on June 15, 2012, and any such individual shall not be treated as lawfully present or lawfully residing in the United States for purposes of eligibility for pregnancy-related assistance or child health assistance under a State plan under this title.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H00BB6089C0E142B88C434C6062B444AF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rescission of certain waivers</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall rescind any waiver approved under section 1331 or 1332 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18051">42 U.S.C. 18051</external-xref>, 18052) or under title XIX or XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>, 1397aa et seq.) before such date that would not have been so approved had the amendments made by this section been in effect at the time of such approval. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

