<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H807A9CA8CDE5405D88CC684A7A4F0D04" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3246 IH: Sanction Russian Nuclear Safety Violators Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3246</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the imposition of sanctions with respect to any foreign person endangering the integrity or safety of the Zaporzhzhia nuclear power plant.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H22CAC5323B54444CBE7639A57ADEC409" style="OLC"><section id="H5EF296E5B396442EBD1B25092CC65BE7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sanction Russian Nuclear Safety Violators Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD698973B079A4144A3D919468BF8DDB3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HB4AF99DA7D0C4CA1B900A3C79AA837F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On February 24, 2022, the Government of the Russian Federation, led by Vladimir Putin, launched an unprovoked, full-scale invasion of Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F00F80A71D54480BE455A728CC9F407"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Russian forces have illegally occupied the Zaporzhzhia nuclear power plant, the largest nuclear power plant in Europe, and have placed Russian military equipment within the power plant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5508592DD5AA491C81B74AB535975328"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Officials from the Russian Federations State Atomic Energy Corporation <quote>Rosatom</quote> have been present at the plant since March 2022 and have requested information on confidential issues regarding the plant’s operations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E450CF4277346B295D0401855007499"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The International Atomic Energy Association <quote>IAEA</quote> has stated that the presence of Rosatom officials is a significant safety concern and could lead to technical interference in the plant’s operations, and has found that the power plant has structural damage in places due to shelling caused by Russia’s invasion of Ukraine. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67FCEDD72D5945DFA55BEBC90E2FA715"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Director General has stated that failing to demilitarize the Zaporzhzhia nuclear power plant is <quote>playing with fire</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88D6B4971B6745A1B5A3667C67D8D7B1"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In May 2023, Russia evacuated citizens from the region around Zaporizhzhia, including personnel who operate the plant, further exacerbating concerns about the plant’s stability and safety.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7D25664DA12E400E989FADE0E18A95D8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sanctions</header><subsection id="H49B3C72E20DB4E0F8192F31EFD85542C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall impose sanctions described in subsection (b) with respect to any foreign person has endangered the integrity, safety, or undermined Ukrainian operational control of the Zaporzhzhia Nuclear Power Station located in southeastern Ukraine since the Russian Federation launched an unprovoked, full-scale invasion of Ukraine.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD481045D8E7044E5BEC4EF5527E9AC0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="HE7A2AFA145184AC8AA45A1FD4338CCC1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Asset blocking</header><text>Notwithstanding the requirements of section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>), the President may exercise of all powers granted to the President by that Act to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of the foreign person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F75D158B1EC4D08884461E1C384CE34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Visas, admission, or parole</header><subparagraph id="H9FE1C9DDE1D54A26A126448B433E3149"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An alien who the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Homeland Security (or a designee of one of such Secretaries) knows, or has reason to believe, is described in subsection (a) is—</text><clause id="HC554412F0EA64F829FDBD9E9B0550A03"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause><clause id="HB1D75744941F4F008D5AF490B964313C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible for a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="HED9A7931AE884ABC9CA7031828ECBA28"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H695320A4FC154FFF9F1F3533BBB6D39F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><clause id="H7228935374824C7DB8399E52E0CA19FE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The issuing consular officer, the Secretary of State, or the Secretary of Homeland Security (or a designee of one of such Secretaries) shall, in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1201">8 U.S.C. 1201(i)</external-xref>), revoke any visa or other entry documentation issued to an alien described in subparagraph (A) regardless of when the visa or other entry documentation is issued.</text></clause><clause id="H044EA9A1C7C94C368C97F7E5AF009977"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Effect of revocation</header><text>A revocation under clause (i)—</text><subclause id="H3CC643501CEF4DE88220570825812D93"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall take effect immediately; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3429EBF726884FAC82A664B71CD9B656"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the alien’s possession.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5AC5DCC34719465D931EBE39B102290C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="H4C48DF215FFA47A4B33C61D228CFA76B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exception to comply with international obligations</header><text>Sanctions under subsection (b)(2) shall not apply with respect to the admission of an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BD3E7D457244ECBB84ABA8F2723076D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception relating to the provision of humanitarian assistance</header><text>Sanctions under this section may not be imposed with respect to transactions or the facilitation of transactions for—</text><subparagraph id="H17A64F4DB3D944089E3CDA0DFB887C86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE9AE76068734BA193752392D0BB8E98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the provision of humanitarian assistance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB12CB3DAB4E64138A33F14A26D1552F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>financial transactions relating to humanitarian assistance; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BA9E4AD8CD5411DAF0DB7276D448638"><enum>(D)</enum><text>transporting goods or services that are necessary to carry out operations relating to humanitarian assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5E4008DCB344417BAA31FF24885176D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception related to ukrainian operational control</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions under this section shall not apply to any foreign person seeking to reestablish Ukrainian operational control of the Zaporizhzhia Nuclear Power Station or the surrounding region.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82897068AD3E4B749A94B8FFD7729617"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header><paragraph id="H0056C2911EBB4D718D32015A7343EB51"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided to the President under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this subtitle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA533A07179245A5B76C0CEC33216CF6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to a person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of regulations promulgated under section 403(b) to carry out paragraph (1)(A) to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of that Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H576C34B0A2DE46AA9EE79671F50CDADF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The President may waive the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this section if the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees not later than 15 days before such waiver is to take effect that the waiver is vital to the national security interests of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB0114C84EEF44D890E5053E82BCA8CA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HED708F9E2E624BA380E0BE424B4DB53B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61FF419D78C8490FA1FF4F711F7EFD93"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>foreign person</quote> means an individual or entity that is not a United States person;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A39F813528945139F0A47D67E763F90"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H80CAA3A7CA624345B5BF355C397DFE8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a United States citizen; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FC9A022C82341ABB4AC7E86E1B30DE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a permanent resident alien of the United States; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC3A6131EF3C4BA7BB5D2486F9F9836C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1031C45CD59F4F98A25787EDFCAE24D7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

