<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8697B4B13D0B4471BDAE8AD9493581F1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 2645 IH: Keeping Families Fed Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2645</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230417">April 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend section 2202 of the Families First Coronavirus Response Act to extend for 1 year the availability of certain flexible benefits under the supplemental nutrition assistance program (SNAP).</official-title></form><legis-body id="H71CA01FF38444BA7ADE5A7AAD9B8FC3F" style="OLC"><section id="H3B8A4D6C84254577AA07D32584783410" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Keeping Families Fed Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF43F1334A7664C73A722051F185DDC23"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HA87BE0726D3D4960A711AFC28F9A500F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>After February 2023 the emergency nutrition assistance benefits provided under the supplemental nutrition assistance program (SNAP) authorized by the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 ended, resulting in a benefit cut for every SNAP recipient household in the 32 States then providing the emergency benefits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BB6A46B17A24FACB09D3BB8A2F46538"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, every recipient household in those States now receives at least $95 reduction in SNAP benefits a month, and some households see reductions of $250 a month or more. The average household receives $90 a month less in emergency SNAP benefits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55B5A11E6BA741C2BF19C72F5CA0E120"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The ending of emergency allotments after February 2023 was required by an Act enacted in December 2022 that provided only 2 months for State agencies that administer SNAP and for SNAP recipients to prepare for a stark reduction in benefits. More resources and guidance for the end of the emergency SNAP benefits would have allowed the State agencies and SNAP recipients to better prepare for a benefit reduction and better prevent the hunger cliff caused by benefit reductions.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC4342EC814E44D33AB1D267B150772C5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2302(d) of the Families First Coronavirus Response Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2011">7 U.S.C. 2011</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/127">Public Law 116–127</external-xref>) is amended by inserting before the period at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBDCAD7BA018D443798DA97B6CF591889" display-inline="no-display-inline"><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">, but such authority shall be in effect during the 1-year period that begins on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Keeping Families Fed Act of 2023</short-title></quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H2E82EC9FED8041D0B7E306EF3B53BCEC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Strategy plan</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall develop, and submit to the Congress, a strategy plan for State agencies that administer the supplemental nutrition assistance program under the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 to provided resources and guidance for public awareness, and preparation for the end, of the extended emergency program benefits authorized by the amendment made by section 3.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

