<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H178D2E1DE3E348308D288F0F0A5FCC1A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5632 IH: TRAIN Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5632</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development to make available to government officials of nonadversarial countries in South and Central Asia training in analyzing, assessing, and mitigating any risk of accepting investment or lending from China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF532EB33871B4478A7E737CE5ACD8122" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H977C28F973FF46719CFD9EA4FF51E38C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Thwarting Regional Adversary Investments Now Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>TRAIN Act</quote>. </text></section> <section id="H7269396726734730A6C8770B32CF6886"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H4CF1029F67D44765A0CE9C244B82EC9C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2015, Chinese President Xi Jinping issued an official outline of the principles, framework, priorities, and cooperation mechanisms of the Belt and Road Initiative (referred to in this section as the <quote>BRI</quote>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H90F3E8EB38BD49F7940A7D77E402DC72"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since its inception, more than 140 countries and 32 international organizations have signed BRI cooperation documents with China, including 40 countries in sub-Saharan Africa, 34 countries in Europe and Central Asia, and 24 countries in East Asia and the Pacific.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7CE1923AC1749B5AAAD5199FBDC26FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Many developing countries do not possess the legal, technological, or intelligence capabilities necessary to properly evaluate the national security, debt sustainability, and other risks posed by related agreements with Chinese entities or the Chinese Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76C819A625BF41B8A83C4A75D5ACE9FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Due to the expanding investments by foreign adversaries in the economic and infrastructure sectors of allied and partner countries, the United States should provide technical training, assistance, and support to evaluate the risks these investments pose, and provide a formal review of the future impact these investments would have, on partner economies.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H135D667198BE4E2099BF4ADD9E029EA1"><enum>3.</enum><header>USAID training for foreign government officials</header> 
<subsection id="H8B252C3E55BC4F3FB76018904FAB010A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development (referred to in this section as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) shall make available to appropriate government officials of nonadversarial countries in South and Central Asia training in analyzing, assessing, and mitigating any legal or financial risk of accepting investment or lending from a foreign adversary that is in the region.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HE53C010F422040C4AD7D29A81FE2C75A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="H90B96F6584AE403F8B0E5E9EBFE9E623"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement and elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act and on an annual basis thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7B05D6C69470456D980E85273164D770"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an overview of the training provided under subsection (a) during the prior fiscal year; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3A4ECCF64004F7FA937DCFEA8987DCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an overview of each lending or legal agreement entered into during the prior fiscal year between a nonadversarial country in South and Central Asia and a foreign adversary that is in the region, including an analysis of any risk posed to the United States by such agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2F310783DBB41108AF18BCEF8CFB070"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H61F2125481394B3B908A3366238632E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the requirements of subsections (a) and (b), the Administrator shall consult with—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2EA4ABFA05F9494692D6FA6EADCA60BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Chief Executive Officer of the United States International Development Finance Corporation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07E09B6B917A4AC79675D74497116F58"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7801E5BC76C64AC68542392394E45992"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States Trade Representative;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EF860AE38F3483B90AA9C7C3E439183"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the President of the Export–Import Bank of the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF5574514C5C44158F0DFB038DE8B8C4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary of State for South and Central Asian Affairs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B67259BFAC54EA4B96E014F625D9DDE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1D10EA21E4EF414BBC2CF834E9F22F14"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H7F05CC13CA464A5095A42C8C43C80F57"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H39B1BD9E95FC42FDAEA1E4F5DC86D610"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5FC89E04FC9A41AAA5DCD0D8B801CDD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2213727DED7442A48056D9AA9452A312"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6321F188BA1A4782A7AAE72D67391C4C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H649FF2D13A7E4E84982C742BBA2EA042"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign adversary</term> means a foreign government or individual engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or its allies or to the security and safety of United States citizens.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3194060B4BBB4D1B99B5BB10B6EA509B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>nonadversarial country</term> means a country that is not engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or its allies or to the security and safety of United States citizens.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

