<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H38741176194B4665999942F13B56067E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2743 IH: Fair Access to Banking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2743</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000369">Mr. Amodei</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000612">Mr. Rose</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000294">Mr. Emmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001116">Mr. Clyde</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Reserve Act to prohibit certain financial service providers who deny fair access to financial services from using taxpayer funded discount window lending programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H95820D40FE014267B03CB2241840F450" style="OLC"><section id="HB7BC0A685CBC4A4791C4F37C7086B929" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Access to Banking Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H65438971E5A64CAD81A3C0E717710737"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="HF25F588C5538474FB87E141039C87CCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>article I of the Constitution of the United States guarantees the people of the United States the right to enact public policy through the free and fair election of representatives and through the actions of State legislatures and Congress;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6F5FE274F3D4D97AF0247D96C3A7ED5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>financial institutions rightly objected to the Operation Choke Point initiative through which certain government agencies pressured financial institutions to cut off access to financial services to lawful sectors of the economy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13F8846609E247F3985A526BD39527E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in response to pressure from advocates whose policy objectives are served when financial institutions deny certain customers access to financial services, financial institutions are now, however, increasingly employing subjective, category-based evaluations to deny certain persons access to financial services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47E29917AC284996B1476A69926C6E5D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>this privatization of the discriminatory practices underlying Operation Choke Point by financial institutions represents as great a threat to the national economy, national security, and the soundness of banking and financial markets in the United States as Operation Choke Point itself;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C8D41B9B15B426BBB02BF9664ED2057"><enum>(5)</enum><text>financial institutions are supported by the United States taxpayers and enjoy significant privileges in the financial system of the United States and should not be permitted to act as de facto regulators or unelected legislators by withholding financial services to otherwise credit worthy businesses based on subjective political reasons, bias or prejudices;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4AB20F477034E9AAABBD6A5DB01A447"><enum>(6)</enum><text>financial institutions are not well-equipped to balance risks unrelated to financial exposures and the operations required to deliver financial services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A409D62DF7F486BA0DA1BC09A5A5027"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the United States taxpayers came to the aid for large financial institutions during the great recession of 2008 because they were deemed too important to the national economy to be permitted to fail;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10BC8AC177D34F0D841D3261A7C7846E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>when a financial institution predicates the access to financial services of a person on factors or information (such as the lawful products a customer manufactures or sells or the services the customer provides) other than quantitative, impartial risk-based standards, the financial institution has failed to act consistent with basic principles of sound risk management and failed to provide fair access to financial services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H232421EC82B847ACBB3AE49C7DB16B8D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>financial institutions have a responsibility to make decisions about whether to provide a person with financial services on the basis of impartial criteria free from prejudice or favoritism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC130817A2EAD48C7920EA8CC184221B5"><enum>(10)</enum><text>while fair access to financial services does not obligate a financial institution to offer any particular financial service to the public, or to operate in any particular geographic area, or to provide a service the financial institution offers to any particular person, it is necessary that—</text><subparagraph id="H26AA83D6B61B4E6AACF92F8E5C535145"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the financial services a financial institution chooses to offer in the geographic areas in which the financial institution operates be made available to all customers based on the quantitative, impartial risk-based standards of the financial institution, and not based on whether the customer is in a particular category of customers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FA27F2040CE481EB5DDA981855E6545"><enum>(B)</enum><text>financial institutions assess the risks posed by individual customers on a case-by-case basis, rather than category-based assessment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA6E7BD1DEA247F8945EC34B3AA959FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>financial institutions implement controls to manage relationships commensurate with these risks associated with each customer, not a strategy of total avoidance of particular industries or categories of customers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2AAF4DF0AE14DC8AB1FA1DAA8673C7D"><enum>(11)</enum><text>financial institutions are free to provide or deny financial services to any individual customer, but first, the financial institutions must rely on empirical data that are evaluated consistent with the established, impartial risk-management standards of the financial institution; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H171B31606FDC4367BCC4059B53502BAC"><enum>(12)</enum><text>anything less is not prudent risk management and may result in unsafe or unsound practices, denial of fair access to financial services, cancelling, or eliminating certain businesses in society, and have a deleterious effect on national security and the national economy.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF9FFA054E00644E18F6EE3044A0988F2" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are to—</text><paragraph id="H2EEDCCE4933549F2B6A67930D8AEFC37"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure fair access to financial services and fair treatment of customers by financial service providers, including national and State banks, Federal savings associations, and State and Federal credit unions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F1C72C1D8AA4598B6E798FEDD049899"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure financial institutions conduct themselves in a safe and sound manner, comply with laws and regulations, treat their customers fairly, and provide fair access to financial services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20515A14892C43F1992AB8CB7822D294"><enum>(3)</enum><text>protect against financial institutions being able to impede otherwise lawful commerce and thereby achieve certain public policy goals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03341E85BC4F411DBDC78A36449124C3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure that persons involved in politically unpopular businesses but that are lawful under Federal law receive fair access to financial services under the law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9A2858704AD4A4EB14D838D65561B47"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensure financial institutions operate in a safe and sound manner by making judgments and decisions about whether to provide a customer with financial services on an impartial, individualized risk-based analysis using empirical data evaluated under quantifiable standards.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H693C87E3DB9B4269A4CEBEC4D4E7A4C7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Advances to individual member banks</header><subsection id="H6FB7EF94B5DB4A1C979280378A051A33"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Member banks</header><text>Section 10B of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/347b">12 U.S.C. 347b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE21F0FE96FA44778EC396F10270056D"><subsection id="H710891C2274544B495889CF4F3C106A1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of discount window lending programs</header><text>No member bank with more than $100,000,000,000 in total consolidated assets, or subsidiary of the member bank, may use a discount window lending program if the member bank or subsidiary refuses to do business with any person who is in compliance with the law, including section 8 of the <short-title>Fair Access to Banking Act</short-title>.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDBE813C0E64F49548DAA482D4C9F74B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Insured depository institutions</header><text>Section 8(a)(2)(A) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818(a)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3325A5F595D640BF8A3CFCEBE5817AE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EDA04062F404AC8BC33A4FFCCE3AFB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the comma at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H831B3AE779F64F948C19EAD0AC7A0CB3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D5802DDE0634BACA866678245AD4B24"><clause id="H4FC611B5A9F0433A91DB82077092B8F8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an insured depository institution with more than $100,000,000,000 in total consolidated assets, or subsidiary of the insured depository institution, that refuses to do business with any person who is in compliance with the law, including section 8 of the <short-title></short-title><short-title>Fair Access to Banking Act</short-title>.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD811A431293F48DEA9C802E2B0D63AB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Nonmember banks, trust companies, and other depository institutions</header><text>Section 13 of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/342">12 U.S.C. 342</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote><italic>Provided further</italic>, That no such nonmember bank or trust company or other depository institution with more than $100,000,000,000 in total consolidated assets, or subsidiary of such nonmember bank or trust company or other depository institution, may refuse to do business with any person who is in compliance with the law, including, including section 8 of the <short-title>Fair Access to Banking Act</short-title>:</quote> after <quote>appropriate:</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9199D5F4549049AEA2ED73F97EFFC9A9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Payment card networks</header><subsection id="H61C09ABCE05B4094A276DAAE64095063"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>payment card network</term> has the meaning given the term in section 921(c) of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-2">15 U.S.C. 1693o–2(c)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1DB05BA89E714F069BAABD8B256D96C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>No payment card network, including a subsidiary of a payment card network, may, directly or through any agent, processor, or licensed member of the network, by contract, requirement, condition, penalty, or otherwise, prohibit or inhibit the ability of any person who is in compliance with the law, including section 8 of this Act, to obtain access to services or products of the payment card network because of political or reputational risk considerations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE1DD805A0504D828BC5E5EC06021B4A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Civil penalty</header><text>Any payment card network that violates subsection (b) shall be assessed a civil penalty by the Comptroller of the Currency of not more than 10 percent of the value of the services or products described in that subsection, not to exceed $10,000 per violation.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF1925D974EDE4D849EC425FD716E792B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Credit unions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 206(b)(1) of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1786">12 U.S.C. 1786</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>or is refusing or has refused, or has a subsidiary that is refusing or has refused, to do business with any person who is in compliance with the law, including section 8 of the <short-title>Fair Access to Banking Act</short-title>,</quote> after <quote>as an insured credit union,</quote>.</text></section><section id="HCE23047FBB1246569133F81EC6263E0B"><enum>7.</enum><header>Use of automated clearing house network</header><subsection id="H5BDFB40C3B0B4892810D9A3C39A66DF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB362E4A9951449C8A08FB812BA1164A8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered credit union</header><text>The term <term>covered credit union</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HDC4392F43A3B43FEBBD4FB0E2C095BB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any insured credit union, as defined in section 101 of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1752">12 U.S.C. 1752</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4A7891F295B4A87BE4825F99DF5A18E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any credit union that is eligible to make application to become an insured credit union under section 201 of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1781">12 U.S.C. 1781</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5220315A5726470CBAB6A2ED3435D315"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Member bank</header><text>The term <term>member bank</term> has the meaning given the term in the third undesignated paragraph of the first section of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/221">12 U.S.C. 221</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E5EF31E7AB1406083677B7426474EAE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No covered credit union, member bank, or State-chartered non-member bank with more than $100,000,000,000 in total consolidated assets, or a subsidiary of the covered credit union, member bank, or State-chartered non-member bank, may use the Automated Clearing House Network if that member bank, credit union, or subsidiary of the member bank or credit union, refuses to do business with any person who is in compliance with the law, including section 8 of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H8CBB13BE5568449F81B329FD9D27D7E4"><enum>8.</enum><header>Fair access to financial services</header><subsection id="H27FA84CF78BC49BC99763EFE0058287D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H26E9EAD9E3034A3699186D8DA1978A68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bank</header><text>The term <term>bank</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HE8EA35D0E2364B12B091F7C966FEB49B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an entity for which the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency is the appropriate Federal banking agency, as defined in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8C233C52A7644208D81440C2BFB5DFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="HCD6AFE4188B64D6B818691EC5D89898F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>member banks;</text></clause><clause id="HD77CAC2D702F4C01B1F2DF981F90C076" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>non-member banks;</text></clause><clause id="H71D0221CF41B48BDB9FB59E4EC09C818"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>covered credit unions;</text></clause><clause id="H4FDB6744224C41DFB4F195E7BF33B6FB" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>State-chartered non-member banks; and</text></clause><clause id="HB46CF640B4854978A75400AC02A3C90E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>trust companies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF535097799D0473BBAEBAE30FC94C4E8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered bank</header><subparagraph id="HC6A2B8BAB20B4248BD2E5BBB7602A06A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>covered bank</term> means a bank that has the ability to—</text><clause id="H864BFD514E3545DABD055309F2D56579"><enum>(i)</enum><text>raise the price a person has to pay to obtain an offered financial service from the bank or from a competitor; or</text></clause><clause id="H2C40AA6B29454E4F9142EB30A1493575"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>significantly impede a person, or the business activities of a person, in favor of or to the advantage of another person.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1DACEC692DE4E26A5182076290D83A4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Presumption</header><clause id="H5C5DC4D58785453A8E282FDDE001C053"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A bank shall not be presumed to be a covered bank if the bank has less than $100,000,000,000 in total assets.</text></clause><clause id="H3EB956ACF1D5488CA6B52C08F4517486"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rebuttable presumption</header><subclause id="H394B8645970240BFBCD8B2F07126EBE9"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A bank is presumed to be a covered bank if the bank has $100,000,000,000 or more in total assets.</text></subclause><subclause id="HAD69B4E51D1442658E18F8E0C91A9D9F"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Rebuttal</header><text>A bank that meets the criteria under subclause (I) can seek to rebut this presumption by submitting to the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency written materials that, in the judgement of the agency, demonstrate the bank does not meet the definition of covered bank.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD57726129B8C4426BD5D033B78F496F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered credit union</header><text>The term <term>covered credit union</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H66486ACED8694380BD2161993562D17F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any insured credit union, as defined in section 101 of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1752">12 U.S.C. 1752</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6256BEB4A0FC4CF19F48A3A8E3B78B9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any credit union that is eligible to make application to become an insured credit union under section 201 of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1781">12 U.S.C. 1781</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49B456B8B53749198446F0AD034AF95E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deny</header><text>The term <term>deny</term> means to deny or refuse to enter into or terminate an existing financial services relationship with a person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H277DFE824C234C9092E5260AA43B1473"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fair access to financial services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fair access to financial services</term> means persons engaged in activities lawful under Federal law are able to obtain financial services at banks without impediments caused by a prejudice against or dislike for a person or the business of the customer, products or services sold by the person, or favoritism for market alternatives to the business of the person. Refusing to provide or continue to provide financial services to a person because the person engaged in rude or harassing conduct toward an employee of a bank is not a violation of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD1EA4B0AC0C46359E8344C208BAB881"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Financial service</header><text>The term <term>financial service</term> means a financial product or service, including—</text><subparagraph id="HCE288B05C79341A1B21634578B10BA2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>commercial and merchant banking;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE49B537DF3AE4D7EB6C5BCC9B337D7E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>lending;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16D8237FB8FE44698B8191B273BBCDE1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>financing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22C005D4E3414A42A17625BF1682232C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>leasing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9B0EF5B9D4D43D8B584111D6B0C99C1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>cash, asset and investment management and advisory services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7E5CC6C2C8F463E96E7DEF9AC51F74C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>credit card services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD83CC0A672064A7C805B408766F8322F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>payment processing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H729474D6343844D78630F66A6B744478"><enum>(H)</enum><text>security and foreign exchange trading and brokerage services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE09696538316456E80B03FDBC64AD42F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>insurance products.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF54CE4902FEF440A894E6F4F8B9746AF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Member bank</header><text>The term <term>member bank</term> has the meaning given the term in the third undesignated paragraph of the first section of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/221">12 U.S.C. 221</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HADFAB97100D741BDB685CDC0726B27F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><paragraph id="H19E481B3348A465E98E393DE74FC8241"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To provide fair access to financial services, a covered bank (including a subsidiary of a covered bank), except as necessary to comply with another provision of law—</text><subparagraph id="HB78A1363B613452F8D914A8A5D1660B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall make each financial service it offers available to all persons in the geographic market served by the covered bank on proportionally equal terms;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFE2C42DA1F74362B6FAFC0EC073133C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may not deny any person a financial service the covered bank offers unless the denial is justified by such quantified and documented failure of the person to meet quantitative, impartial risk-based standards established in advance by the covered bank;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H964EC6D7BD4B4FC6B2DC0BA751A0AD95"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may not deny, in coordination with or at the request of others, any person a financial service the covered bank offers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88AE8E79AF0A42E79866A0E249EF7A82"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall, when denying any person financial services the covered bank offers, provide written justification to the person explaining the basis for the denial, including any specific laws or regulations the covered bank believes are being violated by the person or customer, if any.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE3FB54BA9EB4FC9A28AAEFE0DC755EA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Justification requirement</header><text>A justification described in paragraph (1)(D) may not be based solely on the reputational risk to the covered bank.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9F8022745924CC398D3443D6E98CFBA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cause of action for violations of this section</header><paragraph id="H54DC9D6DB71E4992B613545CCD165EA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a person may commence a civil action in the appropriate district court of the United States against any covered bank that violates or fails to comply with the requirements under this Act, for harm that person suffered as a result of such violation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE62D9F805CFB4EF59397A867E4D2CEB4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No exhaustion</header><text>It shall not be necessary for a person to exhaust its administrative remedies before commencing a civil action under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BFE464DBEB34430A003FE675ED67585"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Damages</header><text>If a person prevails in a civil action under this Act, a court shall award the person—</text><subparagraph id="HB53AE66AF3C14F7F91BC084653AD6D1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reasonable attorney’s fees and costs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H444F30019769437E9851D479911ED2EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>treble damages.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

