<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0CDE824921A84A1481AAAE969A74AAD9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 649 IH: To establish the National Commission on Domestic Terrorist Attacks on the United States by Antifa, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 649</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the National Commission on Domestic Terrorist Attacks on the United States by Antifa, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1FDCC3D0DEA4BE4A66FC2ECA434462F" style="OLC"><section id="H6572BB7D2FBB4F8D85E0161C5F5A29B8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of Commission</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is established the National Commission on Domestic Terrorist Attacks on the United States by Antifa (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>).</text></section><section id="HAE2F00EAB15D4EC6BA6EB49412000332"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The purposes of the Commission are to—</text><paragraph id="H9AE072E71B57470D85161935016C3C17"><enum>(1)</enum><text>examine and report upon the facts and causes relating to the involvement of Antifa in the 2020 riots, including the costly and deadly riots in—</text><subparagraph id="H04A044FBAB59424D8DD1CC0097695838"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Minneapolis, Minnesota;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BAFD553DC5841B985DA5A51B342E13D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Rochester, New York;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AD892D1061E41AB98DFB63DFF4C54A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Los Angeles, California;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D86263BA833488AA683A06A72035021"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Washington, DC; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A5DC0B858754539B4826A9E8263570E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Miami, Florida;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9551FB40425C43569B13F5464AE95D3B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Portland, Oregon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19D825B9516C464AB1A019ED4D433A71"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Seattle, Washington;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDCA35BB07B34581B2E3A39091217EE2"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Atlanta, Georgia;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2323A816F6D948BE95CFCA49A8070ACD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Chicago, Illinois; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4844A23F746E4338A7759A689DBBC93F"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DC0F2434A0141258C8ACE2B1B9AD835"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ascertain, evaluate, and report on the evidence developed by all relevant governmental agencies regarding the facts and circumstances surrounding the involvement of Antifa in the 2020 riots; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01CCF2932F0442039972A2E668EDFD02"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make a full and complete accounting of the circumstances surrounding involvement of Antifa in the 2020 riots, and the extent of the United States preparedness for, and response to, such riots and the Antifa organization; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2947E38362DB4109AE4D75D62D307030"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">investigate and report to the President and Congress on its findings, conclusions, and recommendations for corrective measures that can be taken to prevent further attacks and violent riots perpetrated by Antifa.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDEC8236120954C7C924164A446900087"><enum>3.</enum><header>Composition of the Commission</header><subsection id="HF91ADD82F0B04B2CA44C9670B80C03A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the requirements of subsection (b), the Commission shall be composed of 10 members, of whom—</text><paragraph id="HEDDF00734B3E4BFFA0E9C6D5C67708BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>3 members shall be appointed by the majority leader of the Senate; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H641772EAA1124B52BAD2E9472DBE5CE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>2 members shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE973426C5E5F44AFA375F79548F6AE43"><enum>(3)</enum><text>3 members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the Senate; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2E32AAD9CF342B99A1C1B104E43D6C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>2 members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CFE1B1D7A9A4FCF9541E52E7FDB3595"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><paragraph id="H78B0699EC6A14403AB0BE666F30773D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Political party affiliation</header><text>Not more than 5 members of the Commission shall be from the same political party. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1DFA527555B4411B7F140EBF59174D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nongovernmental appointees</header><text>No member of the Commission shall be an officer or employee of the Federal Government or any State or local government, or a Member of Congress. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CA0C8BFDE7344E5877810BCEAAFBC40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Other qualifications</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that individuals appointed to the Commission should be prominent United States citizens, with national recognition and significant depth of experience in such professions as governmental service, law enforcement, the armed services, legal practice, public administration, intelligence gathering, commerce, including domestic terrorism, and foreign affairs. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1FCA91F2B08841FD81F1E86F4BCC7961"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chairperson; Vice Chairperson</header><paragraph id="HD8F1B2A3FF83405EA463B3F797E552E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the requirement of paragraph (2), the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson of the Commission shall be elected by the members. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DB522D6E7374A11807C89EE495339DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Political party affiliation</header><text>The Chairperson and Vice Chairperson shall not be from the same political party.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C837F06A4BE47849C46C3FD6B19F4D1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Initial Meeting</header><text>If 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, 6 or more members of the Commission have been appointed, those members who have been appointed may meet and, if necessary, select a temporary Chairperson and Vice Chairperson, who may begin the operations of the Commission, including the hiring of staff. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE1CEE4F691074D90BC3781EB50846EE5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Quorum; Vacancies</header><text>After its initial meeting, the Commission shall meet upon the call of the Chairperson or a majority of its members. Six members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum. Any vacancy in the Commission shall not affect its powers, but shall be filled in the same manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subsection></section><section id="HAE24F057E3114BB1ADFEE85731099788"><enum>4.</enum><header>Functions of the Commission</header><subsection id="HD479148A9D54454B8F3BA2396543BE5B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The functions of the Commission are to—</text><paragraph id="H93B6BC8BE86A4FDB990623B450BD0285"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">investigate the relevant facts and circumstances relating to the involvement of Antifa in the 2020 riots, including any relevant legislation, Executive order, regulation, plan, policy, practice, or procedure; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36953F0F4EB1433B9A4A174147D1F86D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify, review, and evaluate the lessons learned from such riots, regarding the structure, coordination, management policies, and procedures of the Federal Government, and, if appropriate, State and local governments and nongovernmental entities, relative to detecting, preventing, and responding to Antifa; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62392A0784DF4F2CAA020B6759634842"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit to the President and Congress such reports as are required by this Act containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations as the Commission shall determine, including proposing organization, coordination, planning, management arrangements, procedures, rules, and regulations. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD877C1C7A0F14D028FFE41CB816FFC62"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope of Investigation</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a)(1), the term <term>facts and circumstances</term> includes facts and circumstances relating to—</text><paragraph id="HDB00DDFF77284AE8BE4A9755AA0CDC82"><enum>(1)</enum><text>intelligence agencies; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E534EABB23E47EF866A38942DE65BB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>law enforcement agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H848DD7BD1EE6417CBB76A19CDEA3B982"><enum>(3)</enum><text>diplomacy; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC65A9AF6E7B46E9A66CD4F30DF34150"><enum>(4)</enum><text>immigration, nonimmigrant visas, and border control; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FDFCD4A6C4F459CBF225F56DC2CCF41"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the flow of assets to terrorist organizations, including Antifa; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EE6734F6BA443ADB33029784599F529"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other areas of the public and private sectors determined relevant by the Commission for its inquiry.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H33DD3EE3349547F5BF12C87463A66200"><enum>5.</enum><header>Power of the Commission</header><subsection id="H747B7AB2F84748B4A2B77608AAA74AA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Hearings and Evidence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may, for purposes of carrying out this Act—</text><paragraph id="HC304ACFEF67E4DA3A80B3DF14ED246B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hold hearings, sit and act at times and places, take testimony, receive evidence, and administer oaths; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEB21351891F4253AEB3930D5283067D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require, by subpoena or otherwise, the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of books, records, correspondence, memoranda, papers, and documents. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20FFB0684911478CADFA5402995D6E95"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subpoenas</header><paragraph id="H69A6779A472A47CFA282FB9DF4672686"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Service</header><text>Subpoenas issued under subsection (a)(2) may be served by any person designated by the Commission. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED9D5C01BBD941C58CAE53C358BCB22D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subparagraph id="HB8257695A9E54FD6BD14D937C29EF64F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of contumacy or failure to obey a subpoena issued under subsection (a)(2), the United States district court for the judicial district in which the subpoenaed person resides, is served, or may be found, or where the subpoena is returnable, may issue an order requiring such person to appear at any designated place to testify or to produce documentary or other evidence. Any failure to obey the order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt of that court. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4338CF12FCE143EBA387A73A61E06B52"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional enforcement</header><text>Sections 102 through 104 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (2 U.S.C. 192 through 194) shall apply in the case of any failure of any witness to comply with any subpoena or to testify when summoned under authority of this section. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD02FD299BF84DF2A034F59B7E8AA7D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Closed Meetings</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law which would require meetings of the Commission to be open to the public, any portion of a meeting of the Commission may be closed to the public if the President determines that such portion is likely to disclose matters that could endanger national security. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB62B7B6EE7274D789DBEE716820425E0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Contracting</header><text>The Commission may, to such extent and in such amounts as are provided in appropriation Acts, enter into contracts to enable the Commission to discharge its duties under this Act. </text></subsection><subsection id="H19307C3EB5B94771942C36C74D41A5F2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Information from Federal agencies</header><text>The Commission may secure directly from any department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States any information related to any inquiry of the Commission conducted under this Act. Each such department, agency, or instrumentality shall, to the extent authorized by law, furnish such information directly to the Commission upon request. </text></subsection><subsection id="H35CAD80302A44C69826400B51DF28ED0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assistance From Federal Agencies</header><paragraph id="H21A71908314F4DB6808BF80F8EC29FF1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General services administration</header><text>The Administrator of General Services shall provide to the Commission on a reimbursable basis administrative support and other services for the performance of the Commission's functions. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87492651259E439BA4A01E3644F9CAE6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other departments and agencies</header><text>In addition to the assistance prescribed in paragraph (1), departments and agencies of the United States are authorized to provide to the Commission such services, funds, facilities, staff, and other support services as they may determine advisable and as may be authorized by law. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0964770AF9024A69AD79908F32A8B1A8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Gifts</header><text>The Commission may, to such extent and in such amounts as are provided in appropriation Acts, accept, use, and dispose of gifts or donations of services or property. </text></subsection><subsection id="H18D1A8C69CE747F08A9FF89B3D8DFBFD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Postal services</header><text>The Commission may use the United States mails in the same manner and under the same conditions as departments and agencies of the United States. </text></subsection><subsection id="H66E8B1A82C554532875731541854E36C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Powers of Subcommittees, Members, and Agents</header><text>Any subcommittee, member, or agent of the Commission may, if authorized by the Commission, take any action which the Commission is authorized to take by this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H740AAE8C21864BEDBFF6E256B112F921"><enum>6.</enum><header>Staff of the Commission</header><subsection id="H66A60689636243F4899E9E0324575FCB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall have a Director who shall be appointed by the Chairperson and the Vice Chairperson, acting jointly. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0677A33FAF774D4C99E284411A4EAD33"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The Chairperson, in consultation with the Vice Chairperson, may appoint additional personnel as may be necessary to enable the Commission to carry out its functions. </text></subsection><subsection id="H12455C39941847EDB424D352066CE798"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of Certain Civil Service Laws</header><text>The Director and staff of the Commission may be appointed without regard to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service, and may be paid without regard to the provisions of chapter 51 and subchapter III of chapter 53 of such title relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates, except that no rate of pay fixed under this subsection may exceed the equivalent of that payable for a position at level V of the Executive Schedule under section 5316 of title 5, United States Code. Any individual appointed under subsection (a) or (b) shall be treated as an employee for purposes of chapters 63, 81, 83, 84, 85, 87, 89, and 90 of that title. </text></subsection><subsection id="HAC476D264ABD47409006F58B986878A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Detailees</header><text>Any Federal Government employee may be detailed to the Commission without reimbursement from the Commission, and such detailee shall retain the rights, status, and privileges of his or her regular employment without interruption. </text></subsection><subsection id="H65B372A2CD6842E7ABF2102022D6F8FF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultant Services</header><text>The Commission is authorized to procure the services of experts and consultants in accordance with section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, but at rates not to exceed the daily rate paid a person occupying a position at level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC7D8537F1AA542188F019B346C1B46D7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Compensation and travel expenses</header><subsection id="H10C774CF040D4BDDAF31E0E272524682"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member of the Commission may be compensated at not to exceed the daily equivalent of the annual rate of basic pay in effect for a position at level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5, United States Code, for each day during which that member is engaged in the actual performance of the duties of the Commission. </text></subsection><subsection id="H09314D690D3F4689AAB89D3D0F55B959"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>While away from their homes or regular places of business in the performance of services for the Commission, members of the Commission shall be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in the same manner as persons employed intermittently in the Government service are allowed expenses under section 5703(b) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection></section><section id="H77E1439AD1F84555A8441ADEE1B6DC88"><enum>8.</enum><header>Security clearances for Commission members and staff</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The appropriate executive departments and agencies shall cooperate with the Commission in expeditiously providing to the Commission members and staff appropriate security clearances in a manner consistent with existing procedures and requirements, except that no person shall be provided with access to classified information under this section who would not otherwise qualify for such security clearance.</text></section><section id="HAD617952B48844E192777F7C40ABF166"><enum>9.</enum><header>Reports of the Commission; termination</header><subsection id="H061D5F4781414F2397463D916488B2CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the first meeting of the Commission, the Commission shall submit to the President and Congress an initial report containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations for corrective measures as have been agreed to by a majority of Commission members. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9B1205B1418447F5A306B1631B315643"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the submission of the initial report of the Commission, the Commission shall submit to the President and Congress a final report containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations for corrective measures as have been agreed to by a majority of Commission members. </text></subsection><subsection id="H1128C1A43B32490BA00FA34DFE49C49F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H23929CDE415D431084DC89DC8D9B2677"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission, and all the authorities of this Act, shall terminate 60 days after the date on which the final report is submitted under subsection (b). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82E2717758EB4D95850F2B2B72ABEAF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative activities before termination</header><text>The Commission may use the 60-day period referred to in paragraph (1) for the purpose of concluding its activities, including providing testimony to committees of Congress concerning its reports and disseminating the second report.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7E6B70F4CB5845A4AD4DDF2E1CEA5E94"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission to carry out this Act $3,000,000, to remain available until expended.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

