<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDE9DE31510C84145AE4150236E667F8B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4161 IH: Pre-Pilot Pathway Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4161</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230615">June 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish an apprenticeship program for students at flight schools, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4D210866D3FE4516B2A02B2382A69C2F" style="OLC"><section id="H00BA9F68C8A64FDF92789D95340A3994" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pre-Pilot Pathway Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD5F9F3F449CD4511B80C3811D3A5A1CE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Apprenticeship program for pilots</header><subsection id="H0B1EB2BA965C4BAD9A81287A30FA8825"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H432910417BA44783BCE242140CDD20AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprentice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprentice</term> means a student enrolled at a flight school. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21F44A9E8A324C1D8743CA83985B3347" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Flight school</header><text>The term <quote>flight school</quote> means a flight academy certified under part 141 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DDE2BA4B327497EBF95F50E8936B8F4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D8A7FE94E3D4EE9A8F41E9D77C0EEC2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with flight schools and other industry stakeholders, shall establish an apprenticeship program with flight schools to establish a pipeline of qualified and interested individuals to become commercial pilots.</text></subsection><subsection id="H530068923C1D41CCBFA3A4AD8FE0C7ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the apprenticeship program established under subsection (b), each flight school participating in the apprenticeship program established under subsection (b) may select up to 8 applicants to flight school to serve as apprentices each academic year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4CB7BB4CFAE343DDAFE0E6FD2891ABC7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Curriculum and requirements</header><paragraph id="H2636270782B24F8BB70B38845E2B9BA1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To graduate from an apprenticeship program established under subsection (b), an apprentice shall satisfy any relevant requirements and minimum curriculum under part 141 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), including all curriculum under subpart C of such part. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29202CA0BBB6400AB360418D8C8A1398"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum requirements</header><text>Nothing in this Act prevents a flight school from imposing additional requirements, such as modifying the terms of service of the apprenticeship program, on an apprentice taking part in an apprenticeship program established pursuant to this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H38D360B87FFE46799892C6CD9F1D8220"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Optional program</header><text>A flight school may choose not to participate in an apprenticeship program established under this section. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFE6B7AFC816942DC99639128E1892226"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue such regulations as are necessary to implement this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD561C6D62A864AC585AA0820349F7229"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Incentivizing retired pilots</header><text>The Secretary shall take such actions as may be appropriate to develop methods to incentivize pilots, including retired military pilots, retiring airline pilots, and graduates of the apprenticeship program established under this section, to become instructors at flight schools, including through the development of pathway programs for such pilots to gain initial qualification or concurrent qualification as certified flight instructors under part 61 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

