<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF4CF7DB7BB3E4F62A420E31458D91639" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3911 IH: Ukrainian Adjustment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3911</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for adjustment of status of nationals of Ukraine, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H45F74DAC316046739E955D202D9C62ED" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8E241A8F29224402B11955E2228536C9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ukrainian Adjustment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H544D470465FE4C97B1192F47B3A3B5A0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Adjustment of status for eligible Ukrainian nationals</header> <subsection id="HC66ADFAA51BC45F1A8CE5C61749AAEDF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Streamlined adjustment of status for eligible Ukrainian nationals</header> <paragraph id="H534308CDF66741C28CA30739631241A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall adjust the status of an eligible Ukrainian national described in subsection (b) to the status of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence if the eligible Ukrainian national—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF61491E5BA9647F688DD818D012D4DF6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submits an application for adjustment of status in accordance with procedures established by the Secretary of Homeland Security;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6DFB1229F2F24F15A3DC1F350610F21B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to subsection (c), is otherwise admissible to the United States as an immigrant, except that the grounds of inadmissibility under paragraphs (4), (5), and (7)(A) of section 212(a) the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>) shall not apply; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2EDFB64158B744AABA7B707212680585" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has complied with the vetting requirements under paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (d) to the satisfaction of the Secretary of Homeland Security; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E47D2A288E045F3B2F50EAAA5F04EA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that the adjustment of status of the eligible Ukrainian national is not contrary to the national welfare, safety, or security of the United States.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFEE9932747F94977B8D12ABE57F054DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of refugee admissibility requirements</header><text>The provisions relating to admissibility for a refugee seeking adjustment of status under section 209(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1159">8 U.S.C. 1159(c)</external-xref>) shall apply to an applicant for adjustment of status under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFF08F02422BA4A41BA421565D1CB5F3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible Ukrainian national</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an eligible Ukrainian national for the purpose of this section is a citizen or national of Ukraine (or a person who last habitually resided in Ukraine) who—</text> 
<paragraph id="H248E9DA74D2F458BB4A25887377FEB84"><enum>(1)</enum><text>completed security and law enforcement background checks to the satisfaction of the Secretary of Homeland Security and was subsequently—</text> <subparagraph id="HE4FDDC736335427F80B997E9ECB91738"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paroled into the United States after February 20, 2014; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H90CD43062DF64BBE9CB1B5D5F4AE1FCD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">paroled into the United States for the purpose of accompanying or following to join as—</text> <clause id="HC20BBC1745734BB4BC163AB2E03F0D19"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the spouse or child (as defined in section 101(b)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(b)(1)</external-xref>)) of an individual described in subparagraph (A); or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBC2220048ED04E2B9805078C3A1BE83D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the parent, legal guardian, or primary caregiver of an individual described in subparagraph (A) who is determined to be an unaccompanied child under section 462(g)(2) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/279">6 U.S.C. 279(g)(2)</external-xref>) or section 412(d)(2)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1522">8 U.S.C. 1522(d)(2)(B)</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8CAC0BF3BAB4600A2DFD66CEC352F5D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has not had such parole terminated by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text> </paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H9E6F122AE5F44045AC198709E5554E4F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver</header> 
<paragraph id="HC2342CB7074C40098E90EF748C778926"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to an applicant for adjustment of status under this section, subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary of Homeland Security may waive any applicable ground of inadmissibility under section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>) (other than paragraphs 2(C) or (3) of such section) for humanitarian purposes, to ensure family unity, or if a waiver is otherwise in the public interest.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D667A6528CF46FF97E6629CCEE20D66"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not waive under this subsection any applicable ground of inadmissibility under section 212(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(2)</external-xref>) that arises due to criminal conduct that was committed—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H861887B0A0904BB39D70750F413D74C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on or after February 20, 2014;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H877A83A9530F477B8C95828641951B9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>within the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73A0DEE796BB4CDFA625D98C65B8E3B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by an applicant for adjustment of status under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64435CCAA8424A368F746DC98D3610F4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit any other waiver authority.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCA2F55B20B6D46ADBCD4E907881ED803"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interview and vetting requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H4CF4411F61484D7BA9AB34814E6A636E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish vetting requirements for applicants seeking adjustment of status under this section that are equivalent to the vetting requirements for refugees admitted to the United States through the United States Refugee Admissions Program, including an interview.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H36CC8BA52815444D875AEA70509271D1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary of Homeland Security to maintain records under any other law.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF394D523AC314B3DA093EF862AEB70AA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Protection for battered spouses</header> 
<paragraph id="HC2D46C7BCA6F4FC189F0F09C1684ED11"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An alien whose marriage to an eligible Ukrainian national described in paragraph (1)(A) of subsection (b) has been terminated shall be eligible for adjustment of status under this section as an alien described in paragraph (1)(B) of that subsection for not more than 2 years after the date on which such marriage is terminated if there is a demonstrated connection between the termination of the marriage and battering or extreme cruelty perpetrated by the principal applicant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07EC78907A124ED6A7FAA7190269EB75"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of other law</header><text>In reviewing an application for adjustment of status under this section with respect to spouses and children who have been battered or subjected to extreme cruelty, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall apply section 204(a)(1)(J) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1154">8 U.S.C. 1154(a)(1)(J)</external-xref>) and section 384 of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1367">8 U.S.C. 1367</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD24313AB444D442FA152B34C9D5E3AD9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Date of approval</header><text>Upon the approval of an application for adjustment of status under this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall create a record of the alien’s admission as a lawful permanent resident as of the date on which the alien was inspected and admitted or paroled into the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H91358E8E8C7B49F4919CC3F04B6D7DB7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Prohibition on further authorization of parole</header> <paragraph id="HEBCE974EA3B94EE498583F98E945E01F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), an individual who is a national of Ukraine shall not be authorized for an additional period of parole if such individual—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD38ECFAF0F0048D69522E38F5D2AA44A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is eligible to apply for adjustment of status under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA54E22BBE6D44A6283399E73BE28E262"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fails to submit an application for adjustment of status by the later of—</text> 
<clause id="H19FF868A71424811A37E3508FE5C9826"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date that is 1 year after the date on which final guidance described in subsection (h)(2) is published; or</text></clause> <clause id="H0A9380560A4741CEBF02F65AA2CC6744"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date that is 1 year after the date on which such individual becomes eligible to apply for adjustment of status under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H334F29C685AD402FA5D9B4A859E60A3E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An individual described in paragraph (1)(A) may be authorized for an additional period of parole if such individual—</text> <subparagraph id="H67303778418B4FA2B1EE9894FE2C6804"><enum>(A)</enum><text>within the period described in paragraph (1)(B), seeks an extension to file an application for adjustment of status under this section; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC96323A2408B442F8DF57EAB4D745156"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has previously submitted to a vetting equivalent of the vetting required under subsection (d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98B701C1858C4AE4B8AA8575E8D8E6B1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline for application</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), a national of Ukraine who does not submit an application for adjustment of status within the timeline provided in paragraph (1)(B) may not later adjust status under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H643DEF75823142BC95DCCCE9BCD5A268"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Implementation</header> 
<paragraph id="H925F3388566446789B6A6B49C63CE988"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim guidance</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9C81C2D19091478BBCD4C58BB8C918CB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall issue guidance implementing this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC1EF619BEAC4DCCB6C5E8F8C7FA86BF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Notwithstanding section 553 of title 5, United States Code, such guidance—</text> 
<clause id="H3DCA007F861F4C9A962F58D6ACB6F497"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may be published on the internet website of the Department of Homeland Security; and</text></clause> <clause id="HAB8C94CDA4054EEAA427AB95D10F3679"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall be effective on an interim basis immediately upon such publication but may be subject to change and revision after notice and an opportunity for public comment.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H02265A243D7E45428B272EBA5ECD9996"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final guidance</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall finalize guidance implementing this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HECD301BBFCDD4D14B36DAB4EC02780E9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Administrative review</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide applicants for adjustment of status under this section with the same right to, and procedures for, administrative review as are provided to applicants for adjustment of status under section 245 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1255">8 U.S.C. 1255</external-xref>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H23D09904DE234C8CB1752A771AF42CAF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Prohibition on fees</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not charge a fee to any eligible Ukrainian national in connection with—</text> <paragraph id="HD5905E0BFCAB4C72B9A85E93240BB442"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an application for adjustment of status or employment authorization under this section; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA351B6B70ED4A60BB86B81B5A8979D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the issuance of a permanent resident card or an employment authorization document.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5989F71B3D6D49D9873D63E6E9F0685C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Pending applications</header><text>During the period beginning on the date on which an alien files a bona fide application for adjustment of status under this section and ending on the date on which the Secretary of Homeland Security makes a final administrative decision regarding such application, any alien and any dependent included in such application who remains in compliance with all application requirements may not be—</text> 
<paragraph id="H72900FE80FE54CEB803DDC89A6A4A647"><enum>(1)</enum><text>removed from the United States unless the Secretary of Homeland Security makes a prima facie determination that the alien is, or has become, ineligible for adjustment of status under this section;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A56C4E0579D4D9CB1556F77C6E2D351"><enum>(2)</enum><text>considered unlawfully present under section 212(a)(9)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(9)(B)</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D1D99A5636944F2AECBA0AA0D1511AF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>considered an unauthorized alien (as defined in section 274A(h)(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1324a">8 U.S.C. 1324a(h)(3)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H902D4844C1134B43A7EDAE4264B76B01"><enum>(l)</enum><header>VAWA self petitioners</header><text>Section 101(a)(51) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(51)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9627B078FFE747C1996241C22E6D832F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>or</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AD0AC5853DC4BD3B34315B25B84F110"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H690391E7DA8B4C768FBADBBD93368608"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HC5768F0F39564DA6BB807388271FB443" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HEB0A701F515F4522A8AE935C87BD4041"><enum>(H)</enum><text>section 2(a) of the <short-title>Ukrainian Adjustment Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4068F6D0667A4504B0FF4DFF76ED9F6C"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Exemption from numerical limitations</header><text>Aliens granted adjustment of status under this section shall not be subject to the numerical limitations under sections 201, 202, and 203 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151</external-xref>, 1152, and 1153).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1A381B2321874DEB9C0234B8925E5001"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to preclude an eligible Ukrainian national from applying for or receiving any immigration benefit to which the eligible Ukrainian national is otherwise entitled.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

