<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4115427719574AFDA50F658B62DE6969" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 873 IH: Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 873</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230208">February 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to award grants and contracts for projects that use emerging technologies to address threats to water quality, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H679ED13620A34111ACCDD710250ABAF5" style="OLC"><section id="H13916EB9AD234BA9980BF11B056E561A" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5D79713743C94DEB9B06DF0DD2BE68C0" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H9432D2FE2C5C430DA1C11015697A9129" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Science, technology, and innovation are major cornerstones of the economy of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0259C1452F724A55BCAB6AC6ACBA3AC3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Throughout the United States, there is a growing momentum to address traditional and emerging threats to the Nation’s water resources through innovative technological approaches.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27BDA5843C1F475585EB27239A7BC0BD" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Water quality continues to negatively impact communities in the United States in a variety of ways.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70575600635A4570A60313FA0E6CCD47" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Water quality improvement and protection efforts pose a unique opportunity for private and public innovators to develop lasting market-based solutions.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H56386EFCD2ED4249AD81689E088A3945" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HCE3F1C3944034071BA07FA1653C206DF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Government should support innovative solutions to address water quality in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CE3EF06F6D445FB8525EC18828535EE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">forward-thinking applications of new and existing technologies will be vital for the ability of communities in the United States to treat and monitor vital aquatic and environmental resources; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B9A86BAFB394B849DCF7AF1E4FFBCB0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting an innovative approach to addressing or avoiding water quality degradation will ultimately result in positive changes pertaining to water quality and environmental well-being; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7B15D0E4ECB442684EDAEEE2676F909" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilizing emerging technologies will spur market-based innovation and will further amplify the ongoing efforts to resolve water quality degradation; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3313727DA3314D4C98C4CB6BC6932A4C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Environmental Protection Agency and State environmental agencies should prioritize the use of emerging technologies, including artificial intelligence, quantum information science, distributed ledger technology, mechanical harvesting, aquatic muck dredging, living shorelines, living seawalls, robotics, nanotechnology, environmental DNA (eDNA), and cultivation of aquatic species, such as seaweed, seagrass, kelp, clams, oysters, and mussels, when creating programs and solutions to address water quality.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H64AF92B4D1DC4CAEACA860278C22FF16" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of the Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Fund</header><subsection id="HB4A0B8A769A5443D8AFB922895C17AF3" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established a fund, to be known as the Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Fund. </text></subsection><subsection id="HBA01230DF9F04CA5B551E72B27B531DF" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfers to the fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On October 1 of each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, there shall be transferred from the special account described in section 6501(e) of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4370c">42 U.S.C. 4370c(e)</external-xref>) to the Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Fund, an amount that is equal to the amount that the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency determines will be collected in such fiscal year from fees and charges under the Motor Vehicle and Engine Compliance Program of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></subsection><subsection id="H53FDB4C5A52048D5804AC39C38931213" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the Water Quality and Environmental Innovation Fund—</text><paragraph id="HC76F5A9986414CD8821F84CFDB40DA9D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be available, as provided in appropriations Acts, for awarding grants and contracts, and for other expenses associated with administering such awards, under section 5; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA974181DB6464A27A1791A7B4F29FD0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall remain available until September 30, 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3B0BDCD87BDE4CAA9F5F04709128BFB4" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Awards for projects that use emerging technologies to address threats to water quality</header><subsection id="HB9BA31E21E25449699D6608DAC9D46EA" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may award grants and contracts to eligible entities in accordance with this section. </text></subsection><subsection id="H7A1F06202C7A4494895B5A8B5F2C4F5C" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><paragraph id="H64E5399BD2C44B96AF35154544431DFF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity may use a grant or contract awarded under this section to carry out a project—</text><subparagraph id="HAF1E70E784BD46169DB02FA5FDE5AEEB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that uses an emerging technology, including artificial intelligence, quantum information science, distributed ledger technology, mechanical harvesting, aquatic muck dredging, living shorelines, living seawalls, robotics, nanotechnology, environmental DNA (eDNA), and cultivation of aquatic species, such as seaweed, seagrass, kelp, clams, oysters, and mussels, to address threats to water quality; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C9935962101465381FE15802B903D72"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the research, development, or design of such an emerging technology to be used to address threats to water quality.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE02B5A8AE9734D71BBA046AF551E55BB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Water quality threats</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Threats to water quality that may be addressed under a project carried out using a grant or contract awarded under this section include—</text><subparagraph id="HB3C39BB869124429ABB8524D59D65C39" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>acidification;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AACE424D1144FAC9BB8DA230849549E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the accumulation of plastics, trash, and microplastics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37ECCAD080B14C0FA7B48473BFFCBB68" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hydrologic alterations, such as restricting tidal flow;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2C334AC01094E46B542FB60F60BB8B6" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>nutrient release and eutrophication, including harmful algal blooms;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D6EE841A9734885BE473CE192659BD2" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>sea-level rise;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09103C97DB2A4E2BBA1DEE6184AE8F9F"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">waste carbon dioxide accumulations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A9401D8183649AEBE0A7F409BAB3480"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adverse soil health conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66A6D37281E440CBA9CDC7A9A26F59A6" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>erosion and sedimentation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFDE95A2DC1345FE9B0535789A9078DF" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>karst, sinkholes, and land subsidence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD337D3A1EFC74B94BFA581F4627A8B88" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may—</text><paragraph id="H4A6372DE4E824CA1A12EA0E17FA86F45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>award grants under this section to any institution of higher education, nonprofit organization, or any other entity located or headquartered in the United States that the Administrator determines appropriate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E5AAB479458481E85841FC0871ED169"><enum>(2)</enum><text>award contracts under this section to individuals or private for-profit companies that the Administrator determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H241DBB3BBFFE44279D16D031743AD63A" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any results, including data and statistics, from a project carried out using a grant or contract awarded under this section shall be freely accessible and useable by the public, including local, State, and Federal government entities. </text></subsection></section><section id="HE0D8B2183F00485B8D0FE0E3A352FEC3" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report describing—</text><paragraph id="H8B4B7EB89C1141EDBE09BF9956586796" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">additional benefits that may result from the use of emerging technologies, including emerging technologies described in section 5(b)(1)(A), to address threats to water quality, compared to use of existing technologies to address threats to water quality;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F87871D329A4019874779F8F568A59A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the recipients of the grants and contracts awarded under this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2DA1FD6921449AF968B7F728B69650D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the types and goals of projects carried out using the grants and contracts awarded under this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AD7ED662DCD4F2BA63DCE679FBA00CC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effectiveness of such projects in achieving such goals; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2287F8DF8AC84F5FA4C766EA23BF43A9" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other information that the Administrator determines necessary.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBD21E73A6D2B4534A97829FF33CEA076" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H8BCD9DE1804547909FB7BCE6AE9B63F1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H684F89E02D4947C4B76260A38D74B1D6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66350307C0ED4CF3858915C218841A47" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Distributed ledger technology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>distributed ledger technology</term> means technology that enables the operation and use of distributed ledgers that—</text><subparagraph id="H51594EB5AE0B4E2EA246F9A610100866" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are shared across a set of distributed nodes, including devices or processes, that participate in a network and store a complete or partial replica of the ledger;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA670EA207C6F489AA81534118CD139F4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are synchronized between the nodes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06E5A58465834157B90D7CD0D3313E44" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have data appended to it by following the ledger’s specified consensus mechanism;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01455EA19412498DB61ECF3791F4B26C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>may be accessible to anyone (public) or restricted to a subset of participants (private); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8F5472E8AE5429B8FE69C52B4A4F963" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>may require participants to have authorization to perform certain actions (permissioned) or require no authorization (permissionless).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD41261258BFE4FF78DF06D56335F1E48"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity described in section 5(c). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3C7678E7C5144A7AC0407A498F6B585" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Quantum information science</header><text>The term <term>quantum information science</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the National Quantum Initiative Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8801">15 U.S.C. 8801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

