<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0D6C9CB955794C5CB65B9CCC60EA70D1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 762 IH: Building Resilient Supply Chains Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 762</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office in the Department of Commerce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE98A63F38D7D4E969D73486947613C83" style="OLC"><section id="HD13E8F9E33504A479B6ED38245CCDFEB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Resilient Supply Chains Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD2168AA958E34161BA76822191A7E8BE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Critical Supply Chain Resilience Program</header><subsection id="H21FA475D3A494B9085F4D321CA4E8030"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Office of the Secretary of Commerce a Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office to carry out the Critical Supply Chain Resilience Program described in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="H3EB24363BAB64D4AB0E0CE7D73F27FB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Office shall be the following:</text><paragraph id="H700F47F04B5A46B1A11353FDB3792FE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Help to promote the leadership of the United States with respect to critical industries and supply chains that—</text><subparagraph id="H45F3C4711A814FAE8BDB8A0CADFEBBCF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strengthen the national security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7C0B5DC258046EFBE1DEB89B72F54C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a significant effect on the economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6D562FF1F5B4B728D342E0B751E2EAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Encourage partnerships and collaboration with the Federal Government and the private sector, labor organizations, the governments of countries that are allies or key international partners of the United States, State governments and other political subdivisions of a State, and Tribal governments in order to—</text><subparagraph id="H5B849BC0D1A44C8683A75A96BF8E63CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote the resilience of supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H956E883AE07842AAA1F6E138F3AF8CF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>respond to supply chain shocks to—</text><clause id="HF18FE12D84664B488BFF4173B812B57B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical industries; and</text></clause><clause id="HB9A70B1557064DEF992FC7801D29A2BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>supply chains.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD49EA07C0D7A4EE3806E166CAD83E926"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Support the development, maintenance, improvement, competitiveness, restoration, and expansion of the productive capacities, efficiency, and workforce of critical industries and domestic manufacturers of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4824502566A4430DB25C61934F90DF27"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Prepare for and take appropriate steps to minimize the effects of supply chain shocks on critical industries and supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6C15F7CC6C34A8B8120527CCDB6CBF8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Support the creation of jobs with competitive wages in the manufacturing sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2968FD294B8C4BDD94F2B6B34778EFF7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Encourage manufacturing growth and opportunities in economically distressed areas and communities of color.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7FE1719ACC34C58A6AE6B0161C7757A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Promote the health of the economy of the United States and the competitiveness of manufacturing in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2FCA2CE4E3C44EC85F0CE8D021C345A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Coordinate executive branch actions necessary to carry out the functions described in paragraphs (1) through (7).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A4F35559C7F4E0A92774C683088C371"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Under Secretary of the Office</header><paragraph id="HBB43E112AAB34747A78D89D2E6117173"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment and term</header><text>The head of the Office shall be the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response, appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, for a term of not more than 5 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E5FBFFC5B804EB59F38189BD438FA84"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pay</header><text>The Under Secretary shall be compensated at the rate in effect for level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB39939E3365B4171994B5C3F9BB6E034"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative authorities</header><text>The Under Secretary may appoint officers and employees in accordance with chapter 51 and subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F2D415BAAD14F93BD378C02A816B852"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Critical Supply Chain Resilience Program</header><paragraph id="H2BC4DD79F9F1455B82AA84CF739E8367"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary shall support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains by providing grants, loans, and loan guarantees for eligible activities described under subsection (e) to eligible entities described under subsection (f).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BA9E19527DB44C89E4CFDF9BCEF5163"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section, an eligible entity described in subsection (f) shall submit to the Under Secretary an application at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Under Secretary may require, including—</text><subparagraph id="HC7FF43073B124C0B9237F9311FC83F53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the proposed activity to be carried out with such a grant, loan, or loan guarantee;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H329B4C910A9148098790CE240793F1F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the supply chain supported by the proposed activity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7CC46D49DFE46A5A4AAAEE21B113463"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an estimate of the total costs for such activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D143465341345B09BA0889D60121BB5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header><text>The following activities may be carried out with amounts made available under this section:</text><paragraph id="H9AC239ECDD5443B5B116F6131D84D5A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The development, diversification, preservation, improvement, support, restoration, or expansion of supply chains and the domestic manufacturing of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, and manufacturing technology, including activities that support any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8998775D76DA458C8EBF0B8DC0E12994"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The domestic manufacturing of a critical good or service or industrial equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD17635E45910466CB816359498A01BA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The commercialization, adoption, deployment, or use of manufacturing technology by domestic manufacturers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDA0B3594F054D46B44CD84B82A12B39"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The design, engineering, construction, expansion, improvement, repair, or maintenance of critical infrastructure or a manufacturing facility in the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H429F72646D23449D8FE36B1CE2E1AAD6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The purchase, lease, enhancement, or retooling of industrial equipment for use in the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD37BD5746BCD40AD9ACEDB6868A431ED"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The purchase, lease, or acquisition of critical goods and services, industrial equipment, or manufacturing technology from reliable sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA12E3370CAC43799761A19ABC7A14BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The manufacture or acquisition of a substitute for a critical good or service, industrial equipment, or manufacturing technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H504F606E693944A18501440DC2D98FD8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The establishment, improvement, development, expansion, or preservation of surge capacity or stockpiling of a critical good or service or industrial equipment, as appropriate and necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57232092406D4274ABFECCC03DDE1226"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The establishment, improvement, or preservation of diverse, secure, reliable, and strong sources and locations of a critical good or service in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E9511C906934E77A93F5CF41AF69BBC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>The following entities are eligible to receive grants, loans, and loan guarantees under this section:</text><paragraph id="H5BB9E91E05384FA2992067D799EB6596"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A domestic manufacturer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71A03762734343E8A89EFC9A3C925324"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A domestic enterprise.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D6D72FADA19444E9D7466CF38542CBE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A State, county, city, or other political subdivision of a State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1A013B243A4318A13BA5D85BFA3FD0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A Tribal government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38426C6E6DE2450A97A1C8F30E015FE7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A manufacturing extension center established as part of the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BDE1C734F284B2E8644A245C539855B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A Manufacturing USA institute as described in section 34(d) of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278s">15 U.S.C. 278s(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H074932E05BFA42968FBB94B3612F04BF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An institution of higher education acting as part of a consortium, partnership, or joint venture with another eligible entity described in paragraphs (1) through (6).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C1CD035A3594C1D958F9A2E3F01AC06"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A public or private nonprofit organization or association acting as part of a consortium, partnership, or joint venture with another eligible entity described in paragraphs (1) through (6).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD96A5E0849924F6C858CEDF745FB3986"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A consortium, partnership, or joint venture of two or more eligible entities described under paragraphs (1) through (8).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A355A8EDC0A4834AB5F129D893166CC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Under Secretary may only make a grant, loan, or loan guarantee available to an eligible entity if the Under Secretary makes a determination of the following:</text><paragraph id="HA67B4CDCA8F442E4B0752068FE31B983"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The grant, loan, or loan guarantee is for an activity described under subsection (e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB5D0D85896643D8B17D236AD63E9F37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Without a grant, loan, or loan guarantee the eligible entity would not be able to fund or finance the activity under reasonable terms and conditions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82A13FA836E144CABBB437CFA16AE1B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A grant, loan, or loan guarantee is a cost effective, expedient, and practical financial assistance for the activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37A5206A34D94BD6B8AB270B6E875D9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>There is a reasonable assurance that—</text><subparagraph id="H834415EC90374930894CEB1756A27747"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the eligible entity will implement the activity in accordance with the application submitted pursuant to paragraph (2) of subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25971501654B4C96A7983B19BD52DFF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the activity will support—</text><clause id="HAB80C07A75C54A0B9234576291BBD94D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the resilience, diversity, security, or strength of a supply chain; or</text></clause><clause id="HE9C50C6B3AB54EC19183F085E069099D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the national security or economic security of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H21EBD2E95EAD458886778C62E4E770DD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The eligible entity agrees to provide the information required under paragraph (3) of subsection (m).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3323EC2302B46EEA7D539B2E117A90F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Under Secretary shall establish criteria for the awarding of grants, loans, and loan guarantees that meet the requirements under subsection (g), including the following:</text><paragraph id="H2469F3D1B9094AAB989E67689839A4A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The extent to which the activity supports the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3B572EE367440D185DCBD426FE34483"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The extent to which the activity is funded or financed by non-Federal sources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEAD6E0194484A1C8C26B0FF189421A7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The extent to which the grant, loan, or loan guarantee will assist small and medium-sized domestic manufacturers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58A6115085574A6E8BFBB258B82D6F6D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The amount of appropriations that are required to fund or finance the grant, loan, or loan guarantee made available under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9B5DC54617DA41B7B5CCBD2B12384100"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Grant cost share</header><paragraph id="HF5AA65316A2B40DD8F36411233984582"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of a grant awarded to an eligible entity under this section may not exceed 80 percent of the total cost of the activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EBF6B82B6EE418596AEA0AD8713CFF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>Upon providing written justification for a determination made pursuant to this paragraph, which may be submitted with a classified annex to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Under Secretary may waive the cost share requirement under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H88719ABE8BBF487D961B715F22FF1E72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during a period of national emergency declared by an Act of Congress or the President; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H173A233556D64B38A22FF898983BB31B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>upon making a determination that a grant is necessary to avert the disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a supply chain that would severely affect the national security or economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFD70818F9F64935B85E88DA85A00CF5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maximum Federal involvement</header><text>Federal assistance other than a grant under this section may be used to satisfy the non-Federal share of the cost of the activity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17E2B36DE3684FC293C45998AE23B95E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Loans and loan guarantees</header><paragraph id="HE0FC40DCA30543B885189864075E53A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary may enter into agreements with one or more eligible entities to make a loan, the proceeds of which shall be used to finance eligible activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F12FD3A123F48D1B4477B688117C2F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The amount of a loan under this section shall not exceed 80 percent of the reasonably anticipated costs of an activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H067DD434DB7D4351951CC8856316028D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>Upon providing written justification for a determination made pursuant to this paragraph, which may be submitted with a classified annex to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Under Secretary may waive the requirement under paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="HA458D1AA5E9B48678C0F6AB19FB2B7EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>during a period of national emergency declared by an Act of Congress or the President; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF20E041BC1F4500A036218B320FDEC3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>upon making a determination that a loan or loan guarantee is necessary to avert the disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a supply chain that would severely affect the economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87C6B2018D9E46588128856A42412982"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maximum Federal involvement</header><text>The proceeds of a loan under this section may be used to pay any non-Federal share of activity costs required if the loan is repayable from non-Federal funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8672DBDA67484CB9937E79CD2F9EE01C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Loan guarantees</header><text>The Under Secretary may provide a loan guarantee to a lender in lieu of making a loan under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30BD04B2A78E4355B0F89E11F26C4FDB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Loan guarantee terms</header><text>The terms of a loan guarantee provided under this subsection shall be consistent with the terms established in this subsection for a loan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C827D8BFA1746339E64D68B27B963E0"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Creditworthiness</header><paragraph id="H43EA81C14C184B4B847A04943D540CA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For a loan or loan guarantee issued under subsection (j), the eligible activity and eligible entity receiving such loan or loan guarantee shall be creditworthy, which shall be determined by the Under Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66478FB527E2431A913219798E4937FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In determining the creditworthiness of an eligible activity and eligible entity, the Under Secretary shall take into consideration relevant factors, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H887DB5F2BD2847FFA38EC181A6A6CDF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The terms, conditions, financial structure, and security features of the proposed financing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01856FCDF791419090858FEB994E3D7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The revenue sources that will secure or fund any note, bond, debenture, or other debt obligation issued in connection with the Federal financing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10FFBA02E12940E09998FDEFB8C6D099"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The financial assumptions upon which the loan or loan guarantee is based.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D989CF3E1E5473CAA47FCDC39B099DF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The ability of the eligible entity to successfully achieve the goal of the activity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15AA914F35494120A0E82B6E883A53A4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The financial soundness and credit history of the eligible entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26EBE8465AB743189BF74BE065DFE6C8"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The Under Secretary is authorized to prescribe—</text><paragraph id="H5324B8F3A1BB47BD8279EBDE7EBFD8C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>either specifically or by maximum limits or otherwise, rates of interest, guarantee and commitment fees, and other charges which may be made in connection with a loan or loan guarantee made under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC142E4ADBDC4B398295102CA3B1F170"><enum>(2)</enum><text>regulations governing the forms and procedures (which shall be uniform to the extent practicable) to be used in connection with such loans and loan guarantees.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22968898E828489AAEE7A0B5FD6036F7"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Performance measures</header><text>For grants, loans, and loan guarantees awarded under this section, the Under Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H6DAEB7682DED4E1784681DDC69A84F0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop metrics to assess the extent to which the activities meet the criteria under subsection (h);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H993DFF9536754729AA0ABDAC1FF45BAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the extent to which each eligible entity awarded a grant, loan, or loan guarantee is meeting the criteria under subsection (h); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF1FEE858E714425A2887098FE64E64A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>require that any information the Under Secretary determines to be necessary for the evaluation described under paragraph (2) be provided by eligible entities awarded a grant, including subawardees.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H099AE6E03AB345F1AF3F31065C837952"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>The Under Secretary may revoke a grant, loan, or loan guarantee if the eligible entity fails to meet any requirement under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H440AFBD8B8BD413AB42FFD938CFC3488"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Construction projects</header><text>Section 602 of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3212">42 U.S.C. 3212</external-xref>) shall apply to a construction project that receives financial assistance from the Under Secretary under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H153128FC7A1F4E4388BFA486513D3439"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Critical supply chain resilience fund</header><paragraph id="H1D574EE250E942F28AD5E4104437B8E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury of the United States a fund to be known as the <quote>Supply Chains for Critical Manufacturing Industries Fund</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Fund</quote>) which shall solely be used by the Under Secretary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DB3EBB1C27F4BCB9D0F58A85B57A686"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revolving loan fund</header><text>The proceeds of any conditions prescribed under subsection (l)(1) shall be deposited into the Fund.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B4220E9A519483AAA006BF1FDAE2292"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Program evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 4 years thereafter, the Inspector General of the Department of Commerce shall conduct an audit of the Office to—</text><paragraph id="HEA058356E66A4BCF907AA015A1595F2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the performance of the activities supported by a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36070E2850284372AD3912BDF13F3970"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the extent to which the requirements and criteria under this section are met; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D48D0798BE84E9C8631730BC39B965A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide recommendations on any proposed changes to improve the effectiveness of the Office on meeting the mission under subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9EE360E26534A74BD65B5CA0A8E9F9D"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Under Secretary may promulgate such regulations as the Under Secretary determines to be appropriate to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H63486AF8D8594061A8F762CAA4323622"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated—</text><paragraph id="H1D9A22AEE63F4824BF10E6B545B11646"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the Fund $41,000,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, of which not more than—</text><subparagraph id="H3927F6ABEFEF43228A3B3E1ECCDE241A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$31,000,000,000 may be used for loans and loan guarantees to eligible entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A639B749D02492390AE91B6CA9627DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$10,000,000,000 may be used for grants; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H669BB2C82C3B45FD9B340289A1E95B19"><enum>(C)</enum><text>2 percent per fiscal year may be used for administrative costs; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BC1DB23CD0044D28925EDAC7AF82AE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the Inspector General of the Department of Commerce $5,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, to carry out subsection (q).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7971C5BCBAE04AC1AD11D3722E7A765A"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Consistency with international agreements</header><text>This Act shall be applied in a manner consistent with United States obligations under international agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H43BA4CA875094DA482B45073DC1B2358"><enum>(u)</enum><header>Workforce protections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any eligible entity applying for a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section and with 100 or more employees shall make a good-faith certification that—</text><paragraph id="H16116A97A19040C1A480A0DE9F657BAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the eligible entity will not abrogate existing collective bargaining agreements for—</text><subparagraph id="HF9E42E087DE64A8986FAE110647DBA7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term of the grant; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H956695BD720B40E7B9BF6A0357713727"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term of the loan or loan guarantee and 2 years after completing repayment of the loan; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CE6BC98A8214E2C9BA50E49247B8514"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the eligible entity will remain neutral in any union organizing effort for the term of the grant, loan, or loan guarantee.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCEF7C86668EE46C1A8996D74A245F7D3"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H5B0013EB01DA4B69980735A3D84B7CE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ally or key international partner</header><text>The term <quote>ally or key international partner</quote> does not include countries that pose a significant national security or economic security risk to the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11AAC64137A845A7B1B762CC9C9AE7AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical good or service</header><text>The term <quote>critical good or service</quote> means any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including any mineral, metal, or advanced processed material), article, commodity, supply, product, or item of supply the absence of which would have a significant effect on—</text><subparagraph id="HC3803C11C4B241F5BC2DABB1F44372DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the national security or economic security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85B1DB35509C4830B0CB796861F7BF91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F3683C827964F4286F6CE09625643B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical industry</header><text>The term <quote>critical industry</quote> means an industry that is critical for the national security or economic security of the United States, considering key technology focus areas under this section and critical infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7302B5F836E40EE9A780B14097D6751"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given to that term in the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE25CE9DD9AAC4AE19A88BE368E561750"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Domestic enterprise</header><text>The term <quote>domestic enterprise</quote> means an enterprise that conducts business in the United States and procures a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3299998FC3E42D5B519F6BE9EE642E1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Domestic manufacturer</header><text>The term <quote>domestic manufacturer</quote> means a business that—</text><subparagraph id="HE2467D6A1E2E4C79A68D0F7C0E48CE40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducts in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D9BD036E7484754861262D652D2226B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if provided a grant, loan, loan guarantee, or equity investment pursuant to this section, will conduct in the United States the research and development, engineering, or production activities necessary or incidental to manufacturing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5786A7336A3401C913CA54E8ABF7B15"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Industrial equipment</header><text>The term <quote>industrial equipment</quote> means any component, subsystem, system, equipment, tooling, accessory, part, or assembly necessary for the manufacturing of a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A21346E7B3B492B96ABCAFA04461DE8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given that term under section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B6578533A064BA980DFEA3768CC156A"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Key technology focus areas</header><text>The term <quote>key technology focus areas</quote> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2C694FC9A12843FF99B7C48D1623A70F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Artificial intelligence, machine learning, autonomy, and related advances.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9FFFF6FD1A54FB38A2C35DFEDB5BE29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>High performance computing, semiconductors, and advanced computer hardware and software.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61438D4B9AF74BFC80A499D8EE0A6D7B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Quantum information science and technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A742043934748A38310F79325731597"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Robotics, automation, and advanced manufacturing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8134E0A40914A2FA285E91D94B3CBD6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Natural and anthropogenic disaster prevention or mitigation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B087B2AF6A14F6BBC0CEB878C6EDE5C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Advanced communications technology, including optical transmission components.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EC8CDEDDC5E488EB86BE18D97939FE4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Biotechnology, medical technology, genomics, and synthetic biology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95B5EE3A65E44623969ABCA955C95D11"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Data storage, data management, distributed ledger technologies, and cybersecurity, including biometrics.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05644E44AE70485880096C3DB928C071"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Advanced energy and industrial efficacy technologies, such as batteries, advanced nuclear technologies, and polysilicon for use in solar photovoltaics, including for the purposes of electric generation (consistent with section 15 of the National Science Foundation Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1874">42 U.S.C. 1874</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE28E9F9E7C8148B6B2292D72CAE21379"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Advanced materials science, including composites and 2D materials and equipment, aerospace grade metals, and aerospace specific manufacturing enabling chemicals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA710068528DF43FF89AF63E39FC15330"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Lender</header><text>The term <quote>lender</quote> means any non-Federal qualified institutional buyer (as defined in section 230.144A(a) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations or a successor regulation).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAF9882611FC415DBEA923A2DA999AF1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Loan</header><text>The term <quote>loan</quote> means a direct loan or other debt obligation issued by an eligible entity and funded by the Under Secretary in connection with the financing of an activity under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA9024BFCB6C49B388E66DA53C96E3B5"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Loan guarantee</header><text>The term <quote>loan guarantee</quote> means any guarantee or other pledge by the Under Secretary to pay all or part of the principal of, and interest on, a loan or other debt obligation entered into by an eligible entity and funded by a lender.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB7B93CEC1484F9A9E77749903993814"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Manufacture</header><text>The term <quote>manufacture</quote> means any activity that is necessary for or incidental to the development, production, processing, distribution, or delivery of any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including minerals, metals, and advanced processed materials), article, commodity, supply, product, critical good or service, or item of supply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A932554B5B04CC0976AF4DF882E2ABC"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Manufacturing facility</header><text>The term <quote>manufacturing facility</quote> means any type of building, structure, or real property necessary or incidental to the manufacturing of a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7EF81B25450A46EF9FF4FA96B303549A"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Manufacturing technology</header><text>The term <quote>manufacturing technology</quote> means technologies that are necessary or incidental to the manufacturing of a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5C04F004F3C47778F7259C8A9431884"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <quote>nonprofit organization</quote> means an organization that is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC1863797F914EFFBCCB36BD17937119"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <quote>Office</quote> means the Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response Office established under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3AD88E908F3446DB3820019DADE3343"><enum>(18)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands of the United States, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3553C03931E64B8CBEF9390453706CFE"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain</quote> means a supply chain for a critical good or service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H670AC9C6DD2C4D26A390AA4F3BDE8FF2"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <quote>Tribal government</quote> means Indian Tribes, Alaska Native Tribal entities, and Native Hawaiian communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46157214D01E4DE6B74F5AC8A8392FC1"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Under Secretary</quote> means the Under Secretary of the Office of Supply Chain Resiliency and Crisis Response appointed pursuant to subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

