<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56F6A8C991E249E1A3E75239643EC5D3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5991 IH: Close Agency Loopholes to the Jones Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5991</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231019">October 19, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Committee on Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require the Commandant of the Coast Guard and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection to make certain determinations in enforcing the Jones Act, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H1A36A3A3FF884F1FB6AB7E1990112E6F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBDBD46EE31444277910274136CE573D5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Close Agency Loopholes to the Jones Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H999A893E2562404EAA89FE4773238B28"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H3116D1CDFCC04F65BF6845D2E246113A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 1920, Congress enacted the Merchant Marine Act (chapters 121 and 551 of title 46, United States Code), commonly referred to as the <quote>Jones Act</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41B75DEE80FC45ABBB5AFE285FC78749"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 1953, Congress enacted the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>) applying the Constitution, laws, and civil and political jurisdiction of the United States to the outer Continental Shelf.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBA28F12AB4E94543AE3BB49B6BCB82F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2020, Congress enacted section 9503 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>) affirming that application of the Constitution, laws, and civil and political jurisdiction of the United States to the outer Continental Shelf also applies to non-mineral energy resources and exploring for, developing, producing, transporting, or transmitting such resources.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F162E9F00DD4CA7A5E196F9EB5A6F25"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Therefore, the Jones Act prohibits the use of a non-Jones Act qualified vessel for the provision of any coastwise transportation of merchandise to or from a port of the United States (including territories or possessions to which the coastwise laws apply) to any point on the outer Continental Shelf, or between any two points on the outer Continental Shelf.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H90FFA702ECD640CA9A76AEA88F0999D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>U.S. Customs and Border Protection (hereinafter referred to as <quote>CBP</quote>) is responsible for interpreting and enforcing the Jones Act. CBP has issued ruling letters and other interpretative guidance to requesting parties that provide the description of proposed activities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAFF43A358D014ABEA22C89B9286ACBF0"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unlike most federal agencies, CBP is required by section 625(c) of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1625">19 U.S.C. 1625(c)</external-xref>) to follow its past interpretive guidance and treatments of <quote>substantially identical transactions,</quote> unless it institutes a public notice and comment process to modify or revoke that interpretative guidance. As a result, CBP and market participants treat as binding ruling letters and interpretative guidance in addressing whether and how the Jones Act applies in substantially identical factual situations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H14E48B1FE3684B8699B66FC93CEDB303"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Thus, CBP’s ruling letters—even if legally incorrect—have substantial impacts: When CBP purports to authorize a foreign vessel to transport merchandise between coastwise points, unless ordered by a Federal court to rescind such ruling letters, CBP does not take enforcement action against other foreign vessels engaging in substantially identical transactions, and vessel operators accordingly rely on CBP’s past ruling letters and guidance issued to other parties.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC374436919624D4FA0AE5650BC62DA91"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Over several decades, CBP has purported to create an array of exemptions from the prohibitions of the Jones Act for the benefit of foreign vessels.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA95147DDC481486F83C6C07F8EACFD81"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On December 11, 2019, CBP published Customs Bulletin and Decisions, Vol. 53, No. 45 (hereinafter referred to as the <quote>2019 Decision</quote>) revoking a handful of its interpretations, recognizing that the analyses employed therein were inconsistent with the Jones Act and original congressional intent, including by using statutory language <quote>out of context,</quote> having been superseded by amendments, or being predicated on CBP-created distinctions that had always been <quote>irrelevant</quote> under the Jones Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4F6EBF1D5244C8488F950365C1C14B2"><enum>(10)</enum><text>However, the 2019 Decision still left in force many ruling letters inconsistent with the Jones Act and original congressional intent, espousing the same unlawful doctrines, revoked others that properly interpreted the Jones Act, and created several new loopholes that purport to immunize much of the same foreign vessel activities that are now, and have always been, prohibited under the Jones Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F8F09F2BF5249F18BF2006BC1A7CECD"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Thus, CBP has created invalid exemptions from the prohibition embodied in the Jones Act, using a variety of new and old doctrines inconsistent with original congressional intent. In 2014, the Supreme Court of the United States found in Utility Air Regulatory Group v. Environmental Protection Agency (573 U.S. 302, 328) that it is a <quote>core administrative law principle that an agency may not rewrite clear statutory terms to suit its own sense of how the statute should operate</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13BD5E277F88408C9173F4617DF23D8D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>These invalid, ultra vires doctrines, and their uses, include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF3DC1180960841F6B3BCDBA1854C0C71"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an unlawfully broad interpretation of <quote>vessel equipment</quote> which conflicts with Congress’ statutory description of <quote>merchandise,</quote> and the explicit, limited statutory exemption;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H70324BA7A33B425DBFF56CFD853BFA5C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>paid out not unladen</quote> doctrine, which provides that pipe or cable laying operations are not coastwise trade subject to the Jones Act—even when the pipe is laid between two coastwise points, and in spite of Congress’ statutory prohibition against foreign vessels performing <quote>any part of the transportation by water</quote> of merchandise;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DA31CB03EE84A89A8B54C1C117137FB"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>paid out not unladen</quote> doctrine is also used by foreign vessel operators to justify the transportation of merchandise attached to the paid out pipe or cable;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5C11070F62BE4801907C729E8AC6034D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>lifting operations</quote> exemption, which purports to permit self-propelled movements by a vessel when using a crane or like equipment to install or remove merchandise on or from offshore facilities or subsea infrastructure;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2D2C2DE3A73642339BF96121B3CA961E"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>decommissioning activity</quote> exemption, which purports that merchandise transported as a result of decommissioning—i.e., the restoration of the sea-floor and the water surface by plugging and abandoning the well and removing the installation and facility—is not subject to the Jones Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1247CE018A464697B9CE8E2AFADD8DAF"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>offshore research vessel</quote> misapplications, which improperly extends the exclusion for oceanographic or limnological research vessels to commercial research activities that directly support the exploration for, or development, production, transportation, or transmission of, resources, on the outer Continental Shelf; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2735FD09F48D404288CB1B2B9D572F73"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <quote>pristine seabed</quote> exemption, where CBP has purported to hold that Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act’s explicit application to the <quote>subsoil and seabed</quote> of the outer Continental Shelf does not include the <quote>pristine seabed</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67FCEDB426774505838E96344FCDE7C6"><enum>(13)</enum><text>If a ruling letter is contrary to the statute’s plain text and the expressed intent of Congress, or found unpersuasive by a Federal court, it will be invalidated as arbitrary and capricious.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD9761E8CC5C4042BB167B96E66322C3"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Federal courts have not squarely addressed the interpretations contained in these CBP ruling letters and other guidance, and thus have never upheld these interpretations as valid and authoritative.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H8C6A4003801F4EFDA24671D61B2441B5" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Precluding exemptions from Jones Act requirements for certain foreign vessels</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may not provide any exemption from the requirements of chapters 121 and 551 of title 46, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Jones Act</quote>), to the owner of a foreign vessel engaging in commercial transportation services to directly support the exploration for, or development, production, transportation, or transmission of, resources, including non-mineral energy resources, from a planning or leasing area designated by the Secretary of the Interior under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></section> 
<section id="H4B16F75C32324EEFAAF3700284FD875A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>4.</enum><header>Oceanographic research vessels</header> 
<subsection id="H53F2ED3CB37D47F08F7DE152E2064F10"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not determine that a vessel engaging in commercial research activities to directly support the exploration for, or development, production, transportation, or transmission of, resources, including non-mineral energy resources, from a planning or leasing area designated by the Secretary of the Interior under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>) is not engaged in trade or commerce under such chapter.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H240F01C4E3144B209DA783BA4F454E0A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Oceanographic research vessel clarification</header><text>Section 50503 of title 46, United States Code is amended by inserting <quote>, except that any vessel engaging in commercial research activities to directly support the exploration for, or development, production, transportation, or transmission of, resources, including non-mineral energy resources, from a planning or leasing area designated by the Secretary of the Interior under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>) may be determined to be engaged in trade or commerce under this section</quote> after <quote>trade or commerce</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0B612E36B1EF42A8B99E9F473F6C4645"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commandant of the Coast Guard shall deny any request from a foreign vessel to be designated as an oceanographic research vessel for any such vessel engaging in commercial research activities to directly support the exploration for, or development, production, transportation, or transmission of, resources, including non-mineral energy resources, from a planning or leasing area designated by the Secretary of the Interior under the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H250DD39050F941B1A2BB3500B4A8BEF6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain ruling letters</header> <paragraph id="HDAA1A9095C43426796C16C24C5D85E1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, the following headquarters ruling letters:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H800C92EADE814B5093E8ACE5193895BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ H216579 (May 15, 2012).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD7D56E1053F3488D9D57B03CCBBF0BB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>HQ H205655 (March 20, 2012).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDCF30AA0A607454888D0337946795353"><enum>(C)</enum><text>HQ 112830 (August 12, 1993).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EEC01CC0F8D4CD784CE43AB6A976684"><enum>(D)</enum><text>HQ 110364 (September 29, 1989).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2B1BF97D08E412983F2CF3B4D0688A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Substantially identical transatcions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letters listed in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H3EE1BE23598B4C71A6FBB831370D810F"><enum>5.</enum><header>U.S. Customs and Border Protection rulings</header> <subsection id="HBFD6541AB9CB4BA4A5FAB6D5607E1BDB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Vessel equipment</header> <paragraph id="H29A5CC49FA0D4EAD943E22578717CC2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not apply an interpretation of the terms <quote>vessel equipment</quote> or <quote>equipment</quote> that conflicts with the definition of the term <quote>merchandise</quote> or sections 55105, 55106, 55107, 55108, 55110, 55113, and 55115 of such title. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0DA13190DA24C34AA19B1ACC7E3B6CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain ruling letters</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD00D16B29E4D4A4EA79A79107BC4158F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any ruling letters that apply an incorrect interpretation of the terms <quote>vessel equipment</quote> or <quote>equipment</quote> as described in paragraph (1), including the following headquarters ruling letters:</text> <clause id="HF8FEED74C621456891792E7FB4D01E3C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ H032757 (July 28, 2008).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H97ABAFF271B643739898EDA5794FAA71"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>HQ H029417 (June 5, 2008).</text></clause> <clause id="HBC0FAC63EB4040B69DD0F7E015462F02"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>HQ H004242 (December 22, 2006).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1EF3D0E36A1949B091FA60377FB3428A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>HQ 116078 (February 11, 2004).</text></clause> <clause id="H3B3710E3354B4A1BB9622C44755EBA4F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>HQ 115938 (April 1, 2003).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H689B8D234E094DEFADF111EABF9C919F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>HQ 115771 (August 19, 2002).</text></clause> <clause id="H860621E94651487FB22B4B97F88E1AF6"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>HQ 115333 (April 27, 2001).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBC4156B9725F4E178822050DAEFAA47A"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>HQ 115487 (November 20, 2001).</text></clause> <clause id="H5434B61E06C24ECE927D4A86CCFC718B"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>HQ 115381 (June 15, 2001).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE9FE6D9E0DF740EB93799A9935AEE967"><enum>(x)</enum><text>HQ 114435 (August 6, 1998).</text></clause> <clause id="HB125A2CE754A47B7B6691D2E8253085C"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>HQ 114305 (March 31, 1998).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB0925DFF3A0434DB3BA2A249E8289EE"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>HQ 113841 (February 28, 1997).</text></clause> <clause id="H0B0BF0C86D8648F687B207C7D1131966"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>HQ 113137 (June 27, 1994).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA122888724464048B1D1850B5C6C4502"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>HQ 112218 (July 22, 1992).</text></clause> <clause id="H1D015583E60A4B458D944AFBB34336B6"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>HQ 111889 (February 11, 1992).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9BE8095376294D42BF341D6554B0A499"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>HQ 111892 (September 16, 1991).</text></clause> <clause id="HE349D0640F6E4E7884ECF877E7573A40"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>HQ 110402 (August 18, 1989).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD3FA5921F79C46D493FA7CAD655E68F0"><enum>(xviii)</enum><text>HQ 108223 (March 13, 1986).</text></clause> <clause id="HC789A46237994AC0AE0561A0A45805D9"><enum>(xix)</enum><text>HQ 105644 (June 7, 1982).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCFBA6B7E6D3F48668A821FCBBCDB960A"><enum>(xx)</enum><text>HQ 101925 (October 7, 1976).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5918191A270B4BA3B29A36AF9811361F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Substantially identical transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letters listed in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC9E2AE43AB444668A04AF172BE40D911"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Paid out not unladen</header> 
<paragraph id="H7349E22E1BB94A0E8C1E378D7DBA45F3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not determine that pipe or cable laying operations, including the transportation of merchandise attached to such pipe or cable, are not subject to such chapter because the vessel pays out the pipe or cable to a coastwise point.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D35686C5CA0404A8E2C370AB3EB2AD4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain ruling letters</header> <subparagraph id="HC1C4A411C62942C6B143FC1D3CB0AA66"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any ruling letters that apply an incorrect determination with respect to pipe or cable laying operations described in paragraph (1), including the following headquarters ruling letters:</text> 
<clause id="H998DEA518228426084D235C4DF8B8FF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ 115522 (December 3, 2001).</text></clause> <clause id="H618C3310AA0A44BDB01FEF9B565679DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>HQ 115487 (November 20, 2001).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3A74D7047795415594EF091BD55660BD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>HQ 115311 (May 10, 2001).</text></clause> <clause id="HAFD5A5ED4F8441D993EA79B95C20DC82"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>HQ 115333 (April 27, 2001).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB9FF03EA895A40EFB8C45E9CA7ACA9EE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>HQ 114435 (August 6, 1998).</text></clause> <clause id="H09AF3E4C55E04C3BB780570BAAEADB55"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>HQ 114305 (March 31, 1998).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD6D882B38B2A46968FB2CA89332AD798"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>HQ 105644 (June 7, 1982).</text></clause> <clause id="H0FA3689093AA42C4AF77DD58C8E1F2CC"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>HQ 101925 (October 7, 1976) (also referred to as T.D. 78–387).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H71BE05617B2D41C080AA80F92C400B0B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Substantially identical transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letters listed in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF18119BA1B514EB5B73F0E7BE102A947"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Lifting operations</header> <paragraph id="HC7D1604972194703B47D53713F946F29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not exempt lifting operations from the requirements of such chapter.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H25398914381F43C2B2C34B111CE14E7E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain agency actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H0819BF3AFB344CAF819810EF983B9181"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">revoke or modify, as appropriate, any ruling letters that apply the exemption described in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB70B377BC6FF467099B43446CC4A2FCF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">modify the Customs Bulletin and Decision issued on December 11, 2019, titled <quote>Modification and revocation of ruling letters relating to CBP’s application of the Jones Act to the transportation of certain merchandise and equipment between coastwise points</quote> (Customs Bulletin and Decisions, Vol. 53, No. 45) to be consistent with paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H446EAD5A64CB4AB6A1437132126E1DF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">revoke or modify, as appropriate, any other treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7EC9B7EB21F4CD79793E22BFBAA2A0C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reinstatement of certain ruling letters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon revoking and modifying the agency actions under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall reinstate the following headquarters ruling letters (popularly known as the <quote>Koff rulings</quote>):</text> <subparagraph id="H134E5EC7FD1F4E8797A289A2B9A87F01"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ H242466 (July 3, 2013).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47A3BFAADA3D44FEA46BFC66E63CD4B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>HQ H235242 (November 15, 2012).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC7EEA1C7EE3F4397ADB6124C5091908F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>HQ H225102 (September 24, 2012).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4C357F0A19C64D68A35079D13A85E7B5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Installation activities</header> 
<paragraph id="HC2CCF44555564015B0609DCFD39D2769"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke the following headquarters ruling letters in which the Secretary determined that certain installation activities do not involve transportation of merchandise between points in the United States for purposes of section 55102 of title 46, United States Code:</text> <subparagraph id="H1F174CD39EC2498ABB97E3E1584E9E7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ 115185 (November 20, 2000).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6F52B1151B1D472F9CCA74B28A6881A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>HQ 115218 (November 30, 2000).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5DC510DD4534426CB2FB3E61D89269C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>HQ 113838 (February 25, 1997).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFFBEFDB8B9264B27BBA147294BD80047"><enum>(D)</enum><text>HQ 108442 (August 13, 1986).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDEB61FBB6C474A218EE8FC8733BCF701"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Similar ruling letters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letters described in paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3AE9EC56A1504E31B91A68D0DF075835"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Decommissioning</header> 
<paragraph id="HEEE4761D30FE4EF398CFB645BBDFFECF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not exempt merchandise transported as a result of decommissioning an installation or facility on the outer Continental Shelf from the requirements of such chapter.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H506DE5A80FD942C0B53A8EFA168EEABD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain ruling letters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8ED17A9951F14D68A283CCF888B1A802"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any ruling letters that apply the exemption described in paragraph (1), including the headquarters ruling letter HQ H004242 (December 22, 2006); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0425D0C1754546548C80E09B4B220ADD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letter described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H389F1C85FDCA446B9455FFA4330467DD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Subsoil or seabed samples</header> 
<paragraph id="HE412DC2B3FB84B9EB53A1B95FB15CC24"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not determine that—</text> <subparagraph id="H1F06F513C95745C89ACC9720D2A150B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subsoil or seabed samples are not merchandise for purposes of section 55102 of title 46, United States Code; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2424D0B2A3454E019F5299A1012855D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">taking subsoil or seabed samples from the seabed is not considered an installation or other device for purposes of section 4(a)(1) of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1333">43 U.S.C. 1333(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB9570F3B2EC549E69924D7CDD1C7D56D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revocation or modification of certain ruling letters</header> <subparagraph id="H6614AAF02FEC468FBCAA31404CDB039C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any ruling letters that apply an incorrect determination described in paragraph (1), including the following headquarters ruling letters:</text> 
<clause id="H1E37F59272B94ACF88FBE3546BCA8597"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ H317289 (March 25, 2021).</text></clause> <clause id="H5B75882B2A0F4DE4A82E93B0142238C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>HQ 115799 (September 30, 2002). </text></clause> 
<clause id="H60F102FFD2204B3D8C975BA6D0856FFB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>HQ 116602 (January 30, 2006).</text></clause> <clause id="H6C635543A9A0417AA9D0498C7ADCB3F2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ 108442 (August 13, 1986).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H29922B89CC1C43909FA42C6C3710D99F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Substantially identical transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any treatments, including ruling letters, accorded by the Secretary to transactions that are substantially identical to the transactions described in the ruling letters listed in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H51119B3E4FEB44F49787AFEA5A863768"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Pristine seabed</header> <paragraph id="HA7728C03F83141CC8A4873837C905B4B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary may not determine that such chapter does not apply to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H808F7267FE2C4DF6A7E4929D796BF324"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the pristine seabed of the outer Continental Shelf; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H729E6BEA626447E5BE9329132C90349F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">articles or devices, including seismic nodes or rock, aggregate, or other scour protection materials, either temporarily or permanently placed onto or embedded into the seabed on the outer Continental Shelf.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9044174CA93A404BA13CA28450C52549"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attached articles</header><text>In enforcing <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, the Secretary shall determine that any articles or devices described in paragraph (1)(B) that are attached to the seabed are merchandise for the purposes of section 55102 of such title.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H319A1A473A87471786825D8E170E9611"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Revocation of certain ruling letters</header><text>The Secretary shall revoke or modify, as appropriate, any ruling letters that apply an incorrect determination described in paragraph (1), including the following headquarters ruling letters:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2AAD6E37A55C48AB80B91A9FB19B3B35"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">HQ H317289 (March 25, 2021).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF6410C62092E43B682E2FE38CE16BC46"><enum>(B)</enum><text>HQ 115799 (September 30, 2002).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED79D117C98E4AC38100696DE8B93540" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reinstatement of ruling letter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon revoking and modifying the agency actions under paragraph (3), the Secretary shall reinstate headquarters ruling letter HQ H309186 (January 27, 2021).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H34F7D6F148B045B4A213B73BD57B4EF2" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Petitions by domestic interested parties</header> <subsection id="HEA34EF0323DE465CB11EFA001943BA64"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">Chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H82F58A8322B843CB8D28F7824EFD2054" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H061DEF3FC8EB4D5BA5494C300F6F8F0B"><enum>55124.</enum><header>Petitions by domestic interested parties</header> 
<subsection id="HF47775EBC2064B4DAC55B2FB66CAE9D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Request for interpretive ruling</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall, upon written request by an interested party, furnish, within 60 days, an interpretive ruling regarding a non-coastwise qualified vessel’s activities and compliance with Federal laws in the internal waters of the United States, the territorial sea, and the waters of the outer Continental Shelf, including the vessel’s compliance with this chapter and section 50503. If the interested party believes that the conclusion of such interpretive ruling, or any other interpretive ruling regarding the interpretation, application, or enforcement of the coastwise laws, is incorrect, such party may file a petition with the Secretary setting forth the following:</text> <paragraph id="H241CB08B3CFC47E6AED78257C617E9E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Such party’s understanding of the factual scenario.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB521AE7213174063AE459EFA6BB60781"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The outcome of the decision that such party believes to be proper in the provided factual scenario and the reasons supporting such party’s belief.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H155F3491528C46B5A5461FE27084178C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination on petition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, after receipt and consideration of a petition filed by such an interested party, the Secretary determines that the conclusion reached in the contested letter is not correct, the Secretary shall determine the proper outcome and notify the petitioner of the Secretary’s determination within 60 days.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1D9E06538DE5427CB72EE9561AB7A608"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contest by petitioner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary determines that the contested interpretive ruling filed pursuant to subsection (a) is correct, the Secretary shall notify the petitioner within 30 days. If dissatisfied with the determination of the Secretary, the petitioner may file with the Secretary, not later than 30 days after the date of the notification, notice that it desires to contest the ruling. Upon receipt of notice from the petitioner, the Secretary shall cause publication to be made within 7 days of the Secretary’s determination as presented in the ruling letter.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEA9FEC516483498991417BF4D7D9F0F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Review of interpretive ruling</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the petitioner files the notice of a desire to contest a ruling under subparagraph (c), any interested party may commence an action in any district court of the United States, subject to the venue requirements of section 1391 of title 28, by filing concurrently a summons and complaint, each with the content and in the form, manner, and style prescribed by the rules of such court, contesting any legal conclusions of the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4525DFC01252457199E2A24DDDBEC0DE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall issue such regulations as are necessary to implement this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA820E158DFC34F0CB76E7962BA0D843D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFECF2F7B49534CAF8D4D75D0879D3A5F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coastwise qualified vessel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>coastwise qualified vessel</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 55108(a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB0E9F078E5C4F2486E7B701C5493934"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interested party</header><text>The term <quote>interested party</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2A9B87BADF7B478781510D94D534E140"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the owner or operator of a vessel engaged in coastwise trade;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE05565841E044C7292586FABEA61E06E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a manufacturer of coastwise qualified vessels;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4F45EF01A3DE495B9D385D231B3D7B17"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a certified union, recognized union, or group of workers or mariners which is representative of an industry engaged or employed in—</text> <clause id="H74F61ED03D074CDEBDBEFE061D19F45F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the coastwise trade; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6C03E968025D4A75BA68449C32056C07"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>construction of coastwise qualified vessels;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8A142D354A14B52A2582CC48F72B427"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a trade or business association of which the majority of members are—</text> 
<clause id="H902479CB84DC4097BDD8EFD2D802073D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>owners or operators of vessels engaged in coastwise trade; or</text></clause> <clause id="HC39FA390F7C547C8BF2A6409984CFCEC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>manufacturers of coastwise qualified vessels; or</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H81F4076AA83848CC80C9477D15E1B795"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an association of which the majority of members are persons described in paragraphs (1) through (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H736747057D6144078B8BE7749917C61F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue such regulations as are necessary to implement the amendments made by subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA30A2AE8755D4C84B9BD2230BF4A3194"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="HA43871AB74844CBFADA3A5749EAEBD12" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">55124. Petitions by domestic interested parties.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HB0B2E7DAC77C441C8E8DD89BC93E48D8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Congressional Review Act applicability</header> <subsection id="H1697AD5DCD004F65BAAC43577A4EACDE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 804(3)(A) of title 5, United States Code, for purposes of the application of chapter 8 of such title to a covered ruling letter, the term <quote>rule</quote> shall be read to include such a covered ruling letter.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8D8AAF3E6F9847A6A9D8DD252369C14A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>covered ruling letter</quote> means a ruling letter issued after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H9E24482FA1764B3BBED58E029FD295E9" commented="no"><enum>8.</enum><header>Notification</header> <subsection id="HC1924CD4136A482B8C050EA9F9F7DB86" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Advance notification required</header><text>Prior to engaging in any activity or operations on the outer Continental Shelf, the operator of a foreign vessel used in such activity or operations shall file with the Secretary a notification describing all activities and operations to be performed on the outer Continental Shelf and an identification of applicable ruling letters issued by the Secretary that have approved the use of a foreign vessel in a substantially similar activity or operation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H57722A0C42AC407983329F18878721E9" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Publication of notices</header> 
<paragraph id="HBEFA2B0FAC4A432790FBDE75636F5EBD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Secretary shall publish a notification under subsection (a) in the Customs Bulletin and Decisions within 14 days of receipt of such notification.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H473DF016747444998CC5178144F35F3C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Confidential information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall redact any information exempt from disclosure under section 552 of title 5, United States Code, in a notification published under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H35F428496711427A975463B35F982A29" commented="no"><enum>9.</enum><header>Publication of fines and penalties</header> 
<subsection id="HB6D10AA36A564712BFD0E13E59518BD9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 55102 of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6AC38C163CA948EFA514A77247D32F2F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H1FC07321359444CB954AAAB623D2FD7C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Publication of penalty</header> <paragraph id="HFE09C855D4304CF69400A4BD34FFFE3B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the issuance of a pre-penalty notice or a penalty, including a settlement, under subsection (c), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall publish such pre-penalty notice or a notification of such penalty in the Customs Bulletin and Decisions to the party impacted by the penalty.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H88B19131830C4EED9C1D69F262FA298B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>A pre-penalty notice or penalty notification published under paragraph (1) shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H2D36D91D87B44CE590AB569B56FE12B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the name and the International Maritime Organization identification number of the vessel that is the subject of the penalty;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13FD33983B9F4D4996AD7E7771DCCD92"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the name of the owner of the vessel that is the subject of the penalty; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34E74B9DFC454F5E80B8DD66E0FB14C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the amount of the fine or value of merchandise seized; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H39CD6B231B59428AAEEFC0B3854B65EB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a summary of the alleged misconduct and justification for imposing a penalty.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H5C114FA0AB3F4AB0A18F456C99E24B05"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue such regulations as are necessary to implement the amendments made by subsection (a), including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H50D2D3F5163744509078B87D7E9A4189"><enum>(1)</enum><text>regulations regarding the information to be contained in a penalty notification under section 55102(d) of title 46, United States Code (as amended by such subsection); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H006D3969EC9B4D029AF94BAC622EEFA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any changes to existing regulations relating to penalties issued by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC79AC16F8D394B23AEBEA0A0C465825F"><enum>10.</enum><header>Prevailing wage requirement</header> 
<subsection id="HCBB704C4E47D427DA995FE7826882256"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/81">Chapter 81</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H5C6664813DE842768AAF2DAA1ED7FFFF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H45FF412F2A93493D8D7C33CBCB659C90"><enum>8108.</enum><header>Prevailing wage requirement</header> <subsection id="HE2C30D43D12049D2A6070477946B1471"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require the owner or operator of a covered facility to provide each individual who is manning or crewing the covered facility a prevailing wage (as such term is defined in section 3141 of title 40) as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40 (commonly referred to as the Davis-Bacon Act).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE852805738FC47B5BAA25EF23598241A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review of compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall periodically, but not less than once annually, inspect each covered facility to verify that the owner or operator of such covered facility is in compliance with this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H631DB30AD2AF4F23A0C5AF8953F3B9FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may impose on the owner or operator of a covered facility a civil penalty of $10,000 per day for each day the owner or operator is not in compliance with this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDFB7F342BC9B449A9DB72B55FDA6A915"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition of covered facility</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered facility</quote> means any vessel, rig, platform, or other vehicle or structure, over 50 percent of which is owned by citizens of a foreign nation or with respect to which the citizens of a foreign nation have the right effectively to control and operates under section 302(a)(3) of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1356">43 U.S.C. 1356(a)(3)</external-xref>). </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HC574479363A54CA59D755686A828E6E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, promulgate regulations that specify the prevailing wage requirements under section 8108 of title 46, United States Code, as added by this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDD42C460E636488892E7211211677C99"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Existing exemptions</header> 
<paragraph id="H8BA72EBB3ECD4BF7A21189A41514F56E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effect of amendments; termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each exemption under section 30(c)(2) of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1356">43 U.S.C. 1356(c)(2)</external-xref>) issued before the date of the enactment of this Act—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BB6370C6E2B4855ABB01D4066CD4F47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not be affected by the amendments made by this section during the 120-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7320B94356DB4E8FBB2B0E8364F53736"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be effective after such period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9355115159814C0280695A40FAB470A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification to holders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall notify all persons that hold an exemption described in paragraph (1) that such exemption will expire as provided in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H04164CCB9F444BBC888660B8AE136D19"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prevailing wage requirements under section 8108 of title 46, United States Code, as added by this section, shall not be construed to apply to collective bargaining agreements at ports, marine terminals, or similar facilities that are in effect as of the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB6475BD435BC43E0842DCAAA25FF1DCD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/81">chapter 81</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H610527433BAD464B89B78589EF71A71B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">8108. Prevailing wage requirement.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H053355A444B748A7A1EB49B4B9F281D3"><enum>11.</enum><header>Rulemaking on Garamendi amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commandant of the Coast Guard shall issue such regulations as are necessary to implement the amendments to section 4(a)(1) of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1333">43 U.S.C. 1333(a)(1)</external-xref>) made by section 9503 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>).</text></section> <section id="H30D8E17A3C1D495E87DFB10B31C3011B"><enum>12.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header> <subsection id="HB8A96D16989348109CC8EB656940C2DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to nullify or supersede any other provision of law relating to the outer Continental Shelf (as such term is defined in section 2 of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331</external-xref>)).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H94063E2C88E641D0A1A8322E722F4685" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ruling letters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed as congressional validation of a ruling letter, interpretative guidance, doctrine, or other action relating to the enforcement of chapters 121 and 551 of title 46, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Jones Act</quote>) issued by the Secretary.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H6B0771A260FB4FE89C22401333365A97"><enum>13.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HDAF0AFEFCBE84C0B84F66C15317B731B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Lifting operations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>lifting operations</quote> means self-propelled movements by a vessel when using a crane, or other similar equipment, to install or remove merchandise on or from offshore facilities or subsea infrastructure.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CE660D1EEC849D4A1FC9592A3AB554A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Merchandise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>merchandise</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 55102(a) of title 46, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D352BDAFFED41A5B947B3F64508B967"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Oceanographic research vessel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>oceanographic research vessel</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2101 of title 46, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47D2F2AF65C1430EB1ECBAE1D98C260E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Outer Continental Shelf</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>outer Continental Shelf</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4F7A5934C9040ACB0B7B8AD56C1B04D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Ruling letter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>ruling letter</quote> means any ruling letter or headquarters ruling letter relating to the enforcement of chapters 121 and 551 of title 46, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Jones Act</quote>), issued by the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection pursuant to sections 502(a) or 625 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1502">19 U.S.C. 1502(a)</external-xref> and 1625).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H07F2CAA0956F4D2E90684ACB0D91A62B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


