<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6DCC2E65DA04494480590CE15DE00D9D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6353 IH: Veterans Heroin Overdose Prevention Examination Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6353</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct a review on opioid overdose deaths among veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1C46CE6CFA2C4FC8819A62F7E9CAA20D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H23AE7A8446624E1AAE0DC79ACB34E15E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Heroin Overdose Prevention Examination Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Veterans HOPE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE31230982EFE42EE82CC1AE2B261C13B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header> <subsection id="H0B2A63632CD44B6698F4305A7722B6B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9138B5795C2B423D9C57AE1F8321B2F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>New research shows that a dramatic rise in opioid overdose deaths among veterans in recent years has happened increasingly among veterans dying from heroin and synthetic opioids.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA9BADDD8F4564B1BAFF83A950FC2481E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Furthermore, patients of the Veterans Health Administration of the Department of Veterans Affairs are seven more times likely to suffer from an opioid use disorder than commercially insured patients.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H87AB76138C1446429DBCD30D6EE20555"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using records of the Veterans Health Administration linked to National Death Index data, the veterans’ rate of overdose deaths from all opioids increased by 65 percent from 2010 to 2016, a rate change that includes adjustments for demographic changes in the veteran population over time.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H592CF553D3F546B7A4248BE280B3A6DB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Furthermore, among all opioid overdose decedents, prescription opioid receipt within three months before death declined from 54 percent in 2010 to 26 percent in 2016, yet veteran overdoses resulting in death from heroin, synthetic opioids such as fentanyl, and nonprescription opioids still occurred.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE31C290D32DB41018599107600278929"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In fact, between 2010 and 2016, the veteran death rate from heroin or from taking multiple opioids almost quintupled and the death rate from synthetic opioids such as fentanyl increased by more than five-fold.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H897B5C63198D4C5EBADA06C57D88C800"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Trends would suggest that, while the aggregate rise in opioid overdose deaths among veterans parallel those seen in the general population, the increase occurred mainly because of a rise in deaths from nonprescribed sources such as heroin, fentanyl, other powerful synthetic opioids, or multiple opioids in concurrent use.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1295064983D844369A7122088B224AAA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that further veterans overdose prevention efforts and research should extend beyond patients actively receiving opioid prescriptions.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H227F7405B96B4D3DB5D4A00C010A43F7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Review of deaths of veterans relating to opioid use</header> <subsection id="HC6721A90CAF547B09D2A51B977013D51"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall complete a review of the deaths of all covered veterans who died from opioid overdoses during the five-year period preceding the date of the enactment for this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9AC9500DD83D4FDBA34FD5FF4C7559E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text>The review under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H42B6C36052174C3583A0ECBB57062389"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number of covered veterans who died from opioid overdoses during the five-year period preceding the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HABD430D7ADCA4DDB961391B437FBB51A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A summary of such veterans that includes the age, sex, and race, and ethnicity of each such veteran.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EB519EA26E34C22B35A1E8ABD0F8DFB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A comprehensive list of the medications prescribed to, and found in the bodies of, such veterans at the time of death, specifically listing any medications that carry a black box warning, are off-label, or are psychotropic.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H00FB75E336B54BF988D9DEA5A0E76B0F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A summary of medical diagnoses by physicians of the Department of Veterans Affairs that led to any prescribing of the medications referred to in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA509200D97A14480895A3B660EFD40D1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of instances in which such a veteran was concurrently on multiple medications prescribed by physicians of the Department.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CD4922CCCBE4D68A4930FF47BCDF9A5"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A summary of—</text> <subparagraph id="H060F7FE1D8AD48ECAD87917434567362"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the average period that elapsed between the last prescription opioid receipt and the date of the death of such a veteran; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5A841D0D2DFA4816A328958C0E16F74A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the cause of death for each such veteran.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H88FC87AE68B04E73958537D513A31B28"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The percentage of such veterans with combat experience or trauma (including military sexual trauma, traumatic brain injury, and post-traumatic stress).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2271F348C8024AFEBA29BF2F413C6486"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Identification of medical facilities of the Department with high prescription and drug abuse treatment rates for patients being treated at those facilities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FC78E0B2EF44B19BD73B9D00A2194D4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A description of policies of the Department governing the prescribing of medications referred to in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB1360630DE44334B69DC70352304DFC"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A description of efforts by the Secretary to electronically track, collect, and properly dispose of prescription opioids that are either unused, past the prescription date, or not in the possession of the properly prescribed patient.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H984BC0EDC2024CC1BC68D21F5B2F93CB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>A description of any patterns apparent to the Secretary based on the review.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA48F0D550A74808A7E796CDFDA0616D"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Recommendations for further action that would improve the safety and well-being of veterans and reduce opioid overdose rates for veterans, especially concerning research regarding such veterans who had not filed for a opioid prescription in the three months before death by overdose.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H03CDED23F3C54019B28309DC86FEA378"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the completion of the review under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5DF1A8EEA69A4DB8AAA1493A7EB0A303"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report on the results of the review;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5742273CCD54E0FB82A32EB83C0A7F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make such report publicly available; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF0B2D2F130B4DAD94C39EE221B38783"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a briefing on such review.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H94C515D5896D4B2DA7C84174F071DC20"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H35FE1DB9D5E04DFBAA91F3C7B7406390"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>black box warning</term> means a warning displayed within a box in the prescribing information for drugs that have special problems, particularly ones that may lead to death or serious injury.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6DBF222EBC2D46A5B505D0C24C494430"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered veteran</term> means any veteran who received hospital care or medical services furnished by the Department of Veterans Affairs during the five-year period preceding the death of the veteran.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

