<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB598DC98A0D84374BD587542F5A36A33" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6727 IH: United States Foundation for International Conservation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6727</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231212">December 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the United States Foundation for International Conservation to promote long-term management of protected and conserved areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H61C570A4792F48AE82016421F85D4D75" style="OLC"><section id="H8BCFFB20A3C34A7AAFAD903665302D40" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States Foundation for International Conservation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1B3B5C3660A342F5AD6DAFEF2C7D9199" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act: </text><paragraph id="HF514B009025D4C5AAA13A5205CA5CD59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6C88C99960014496B2361B4A114C181F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDF1EE3CEFCE4187A4C034FB70A6398A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01BC5FFA454444048264942B744F58F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0584B5B682B2469591B1E28F83FEBE64"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEB303CAC194403BA3F51B8B4FE503D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Board</header><text>The term <term>Board</term> means the Board of Directors established pursuant to section 4(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2209A84C03E6407983D48D8D916B039F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HD01F3A4E525346ADA280C996D237F961"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an initial member of the Board appointed pursuant to section 4(a)(2)(C); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5CCB5D9DCF740B799D451B939E49274"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a member of the Board selected to fill a vacancy pursuant to section 4(a)(3)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EE5EEE238554F6BB1F242E6B69A1A5C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible country</header><text>The term <term>eligible country</term> means any of the countries described in section 7(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H593C37848F484E89A2C852D1989995CF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible project</header><text>The term <term>eligible project</term> means any of the projects described in section 7(a)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC35C7613DD434EF1B599971029E1DFC8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Executive director</header><text>The term <term>Executive Director</term> means the Executive Director of the Foundation hired pursuant to section 4(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H887321950C644B2F96ED748FCAB90815"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Foundation</header><text>The term <term>Foundation</term> means the United States Foundation for International Conservation established pursuant to section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19904B1EC96F4D078B85074552E3E16D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of State.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H76D582EAC96B4380B8D1090D82E8B8FC"><enum>3.</enum><header>United States Foundation for International Conservation</header><subsection id="H47AF455EC2604610968261AF5C90F939"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="H8D26C83D616F4E5483FDE61A2FAD41B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established the United States Foundation for International Conservation (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Foundation</quote>). The Foundation is a charitable and nonprofit corporation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBB91BADAFCE4D1E86571C80C62B3493" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination of operations</header><text>The Foundation shall terminate operations on the date that is 10 years after the date on which it is established pursuant to paragraph (1), in accordance with—</text><subparagraph id="HC70E9C3B93F8451BAE761189D737000C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a plan for winding down the activities of the Foundation that the Board shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees not later than 180 days before such termination date; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3277CBE08B045709C6D39CDD4A66367" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the bylaws established pursuant to section 4(a)(9).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1731A38E4C204BDE9C07FDF85B696BA7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the Foundation are—</text><paragraph id="HFC294213D1FE40A8A5120B98AA72C729"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to provide grants for the management of priority protected and conserved areas that have a high degree of biodiversity or species and ecosystems of significant importance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4902D3420EAC427A856A9C944F428D8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to promote effective, long-term management of protected and conserved areas and their contiguous buffer zones in eligible countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AC7A541F13C4FEC80ADFE853E6EF4E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to advocate for, incentivize, accept, and administer governmental and nongovernmental funds, including donations from the private sector, to increase the availability and predictability of financing for long-term management of protected and conserved areas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5836908C2BE4AA3B6885F8E8192265F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to close critical gaps in public international conservation efforts by—</text><subparagraph id="HF8709E8F3B564604B0FB90E131DDB0FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increasing private sector investment, including investments from philanthropic entities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD1A4B086EE749C39714B31E29B4781C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>collaborating with partners providing bilateral and multilateral financing to support enhanced coordination;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB41D52C1B90C43D089FA124B5266FC0D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to identify and financially support implementation-ready projects—</text><subparagraph id="H7624E7DA161C4174909E4453DEECA985"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that promote long-term management of protected and conserved areas and their contiguous buffer zones in eligible countries, including supporting the management of terrestrial, coastal, freshwater, and marine protected areas, parks, community conservancies, Indigenous reserves, conservation easements, and biological reserves; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E31A48A9FA14CCB98294FE61201B07A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that provide effective area-based conservation measures, consistent with internationally recognized best practices and standards for environmental and social safeguards; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA798175A894A51A2FA052E6559C791"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to coordinate with, and otherwise support and assist, foreign governments, private sector entities, local communities, Indigenous Peoples, and other stakeholders in undertaking biodiversity conservation activities—</text><subparagraph id="H74DB30944B4D4F219AE8C87E05A2818C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to achieve sustainable biodiversity conservation outcomes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF8ABC859B5A4F678E8AAEC8A9E1F9F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to improve local security, governance, food security, and economic opportunities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H329E467CA63243B2B7914BE4C9BD138B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Governance of the foundation</header><subsection id="H7B4CA2AD40C44A178B8DDFF18E56E19F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Board of directors</header><paragraph id="HEBE9BF2768FC4DC0B05A88C5ACE1739B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Governance</header><text>The Foundation shall be governed by a Board of Directors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5311B75D09BF4F9F87D28071873AD20D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><subparagraph id="HE8392E3F9676469D850BF644CADDE019"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall be composed of—</text><clause id="H9DCBF52E8B464B2D82078CEB2CF8224A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Directors described in subparagraph (B); and</text></clause><clause id="HD5323C4D75FF42AAB55C42F6DEC675ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>appointed Directors described in subparagraph (C).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D92B484C0EC4104A288E8CA424629EA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Directors</header><text>The following individuals, or designees of such individuals, shall serve as Directors:</text><clause id="H6F1E607A283548CDB422CDEB9923AABE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary of State.</text></clause><clause id="HB754C545EA7346E39B8892D85A7615FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development.</text></clause><clause id="HFA93F8BB5D82401584B67727A8C96231"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Interior.</text></clause><clause id="H2267CF9B2ECD4BA1A4F7D0F3D74DD377"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Chief of the United States Forest Service.</text></clause><clause id="HE8F9B64ED7694761A6A2C06C20BFC1B2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF91BB1F23E24875A88FFF23153D5298"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appointed directors</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the other Directors described in subparagraph (B), the Speaker and minority leader of the House of Representatives, and the majority and minority leader of the Senate, shall appoint, as Directors of the Board—</text><clause id="H73E54E8BB6404453995EEF9CB31801D4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>4 private-sector committed donors; and</text></clause><clause id="HFD8348357832466683978ABFE71D0F68"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>5 independent experts who represent diverse points of view, to the maximum extent practicable.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE38A2E8A1A244FD9A371ED5E20E8D3D1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Appointment structure</header><text>There shall be an appointment structure that applies to directors in subsection (C) such that—</text><clause id="H79E8174E27344BC2B3EDD9A1C2E0C00B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Speaker of the House of Representatives after consultation with the chair of the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House and the minority leader of the House of Representatives after consultation with the ranking member of the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House shall each submit a list of five individuals to be considered by the Secretary for appointment to the Board of Directors, of which the Secretary shall appoint one individual from each list submitted; and</text></clause><clause id="H53ED31CD6C084A79A5D5B4CC6E9D1046"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the majority leader of the Senate after consultation with the chair of the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the minority leader of the Senate after consultation with the ranking minority member of the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate shall each submit a list of individuals to be considered by the Secretary for appointment to the Board of Directors, of which the Secretary shall appoint one individual from each list submitted.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H438DE7CA9C6D438CA099531A970B4FB3"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>Each independent expert appointed pursuant to subparagraph (C) shall be knowledgeable and experienced in matters relating to—</text><clause id="H914EB326E8DD43E48F2DE1F0848BCA1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>international development;</text></clause><clause id="HEF51B221E89F4956BC0369DA1885BFED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>protected area management and the conservation of global biodiversity, fish and wildlife, ecosystem restoration, adaptation, and resilience; and</text></clause><clause id="H6BA5A4E9F1B442BE88B2D90061610DDF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>grantmaking in support of international conservation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE55CD2636EDC47A6AAB984BC7B1E1832"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Board shall elect, from among its Directors, a Chairperson, who shall serve for a 2-year term.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H42F69E0FDCD642BCA4F3B67D50CD0837"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Terms; vacancies</header><subparagraph id="HFA0F8F19C27847829D65C5F295655B5D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Terms</header><clause id="H869A75F44A464E38AF9F2AD236916341"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term of service of each Director appointed pursuant to paragraph (2)(C) shall be not more than 5 years.</text></clause><clause id="HCF74E7AE29EC478CB13E953E101F453E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Initial appointed directors</header><text>Of the initial Directors appointed pursuant to paragraph (2)(C)—</text><subclause id="H03E3C79FFEDE40C6B5BA2E885FB22E67"><enum>(I)</enum><text>5 Directors, including at least private-sector committed donors, shall serve for 4 years; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D9309B9A6064E8E9D1507D9C1F1421A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>4 Directors shall serve for 5 years, as determined by the Chairperson of the Board.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67C71D00828B44E7B93C494D9210498E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the membership of the appointed Directors of the Board—</text><clause id="H15747A68DF9043329A751F2513B301BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be filled in accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation by a private sector committed donor or an independent expert who meets the qualifications described in paragraph (2)(E), as corresponding to the vacating Director;</text></clause><clause id="HA61E5520B0F940D2B9FDF32368EAB14E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not affect the power of the remaining appointed Directors to execute the duties of the Board; and</text></clause><clause id="HDE65D429D326478EA05D15D57F2CD23E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall be filled by an individual selected by the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EEB67F1A67A4472A64569950F807226"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the current membership of the Board shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of Foundation business.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D56FE3A3D5F4B158DA4650D24E56296"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Meetings</header><subparagraph id="H364BABEE86F64C9EB7CA34EB566E429E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall meet at the call of the Chairperson not less frequently than annually.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEAAEC0A265148F8915EBDDD78DC5685"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Initial meeting</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the Board is established pursuant to section 3(a), the Secretary shall convene a meeting of the ex-officio Directors and the appointed Directors of the Board to incorporate the Foundation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE6251D50CAF4B94BD00950CABE4D658"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>Any Director who misses 3 consecutive regularly scheduled meetings may be removed from the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A54DE7236254196985B3EFF0182743B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reimbursement of expenses</header><text>Directors of the Board shall serve without pay, but may be reimbursed for the actual and necessary traveling and subsistence expenses incurred in the performance of the duties of the Foundation. Such reimbursement may only be made available for expenses incurred outside the United States if at least two Directors concurrently incurred such expenses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9CA77C693694BBDB323908D36304053"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Not Federal employees</header><text>Appointment as a Director of the Board shall not constitute employment by, or the holding of an office of, the United States for purposes of any Federal law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H425B3962961F4F5D963F4D6FBD307904"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Board shall—</text><subparagraph id="H64CAD33B57AD4D338D5459185368D1CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish bylaws for the Foundation in accordance with paragraph (9);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A904DDFFAAC4E8896A033A525230437"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide overall direction for the activities of the Foundation and establish priority activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B7F1F6751924FFA8E1F329F921E13B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>carry out any other necessary activities of the Foundation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E270E22B1384DDAB07E31AEFD34A436"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evaluate the performance of the Executive Director;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD43F44C77664B6E9C1532C3E0D1A183"><enum>(E)</enum><text>take steps to limit the Foundations administrative expenses to the extent practicable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCEE144C588643AEAD99E1FE209FEB0C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>not less frequently than annually, consult and coordinate with stakeholders qualified to provide advice, assistance, and information regarding effective protected and conserved area management.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDA9DF36A0FA489B9EA433EB8BA73079"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Bylaws</header><subparagraph id="HA9845CCD3B7A497388E1C4A5F7E68BB4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The bylaws established pursuant to paragraph (8)(A) shall include—</text><clause id="H9C3412DBD11A4C9D9552F3EC91AB31C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>policies for the selection of Directors of the Board and officers, employees, agents, and contractors of the Foundation;</text></clause><clause id="HEE3129FC11C643588B1CC29A7853B0A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>policies, including ethical standards, for—</text><subclause id="HEF487B6EDBF3494CA52AAD111EB24B9B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the acceptance, solicitation, and disposition of donations and grants to the Foundation; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HCEAEE5758C5C4EDDA4B6AA0D51DC36CA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the disposition of assets of the Foundation;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0A1029B0BAFB44508E6F669121F53140"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>policies that subject all employees, fellows, trainees, and other agents of the Foundation (including ex-officio Directors and appointed Directors of the Board) to conflict of interest standards;</text></clause><clause id="H3D2CA76A2F6F42C19AD106C9D59D5B27"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the specific duties of the Executive Director;</text></clause><clause id="HD151C8E4D75F46938CACE301C6A2C9C4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>policies for winding down the activities of the Foundation upon its termination, including a plan—</text><subclause id="H045DF12E8339498EA3A90665136C59E9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to return unspent appropriations to the Department of the Treasury; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H65971CBF82E34CD6A0A2BFA2DC772DFF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to donate unspent private and philanthropic contributions to projects that align with the goals and requirements described in section 7; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H98FF32CE88434F2081E3C5C81562D38F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>policies for vetting grantees to ensure the Foundation does not provide grants to for-profit entities whose primary objective is activity other than conservation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9280BF69707E4E0CB19A22D227038B21"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Board shall ensure that the bylaws of the Foundation and the activities carried out under such bylaws do not—</text><clause id="HDE5B06F7B2534DC7A56B7AD1AF32C984"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reflect unfavorably on the ability of the Foundation to carry out activities in a fair and objective manner; or</text></clause><clause id="H860C3673AC054A7A932125CEC792909A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>compromise, or appear to compromise, the integrity of any governmental agency or program, or any officer or employee employed by, or involved in, a governmental agency or program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1744EBEF6B7849E1871EBB5284CDFCE9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive director</header><text>The Board shall hire an Executive Director of the Foundation, who shall serve, at the pleasure of the Board, as the Chief Executive Officer of the Foundation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6C5BAF40D2554D85A16DF907B49AC650"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Foundation staff</header><text>Officers and employees of the Foundation—</text><paragraph id="H95BE8C9B66AD42618D01FB5B94D5158A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may not be employees of, or hold any office in, the United States Government;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3C4F479B667430A833C704E8CBB97E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be appointed without regard to the provisions of—</text><subparagraph id="H423883ED90524D3E8BCF1B81EBA88B01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE27779F32C8549D28890D30A2BB5FBFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>chapter 51 and subchapter III of chapter 53 of such title, relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2991DF40F79A403F90CD43269AFECC81"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may not receive a salary at a rate in excess of 150 percent of the maximum rate of basic pay authorized for positions at level I of the Executive Schedule under section 5312 of title 5, United States Code, for that fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H268A6107943B4146B791B6366917C418"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation and conflicts of interests</header><paragraph id="HBA50B5D6FC2040BE93AB09DCC4C98264"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Political participation</header><text>The Foundation may not participate or intervene in any political campaign on behalf of any candidate for public office in any country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H975F3EDFC4F34C4FB291196EAB13DB76"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Financial interests</header><text>Any Director of the Board or officer or employee of the Foundation is prohibited from participating, directly or indirectly, in the consideration or determination of any question before the Foundation affecting—</text><subparagraph id="H13E13B9D0FBD4B4C84B9C31D1DE98646"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the financial interests of such Director, officer, or employee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A846396674841D882BBA6BE5E4A858B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the interests of any corporation, partnership, entity, or organization in which such Director, officer, or employee has any fiduciary obligation or direct or indirect financial interest.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H81F0D65B197540DB99B1DB2A61A7563C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Corporate powers and obligations of the foundation</header><subsection id="H635681E34E7140568E68BDE89F0FF6B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General authority</header><paragraph id="HAB4EE77650684EDCA3970004F7F066CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation—</text><subparagraph id="H789905A6A07C4EBD973B747267BD4AE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may conduct business throughout the States, territories, and possessions of the United States and in foreign countries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDACA30787304CFEAFE7EE3309E06F03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall have its principal offices in the Washington, DC, metropolitan area; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H573A955F6BB941BC8F4A813C3418A766"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall continuously maintain a designated agent in Washington, DC, who is authorized to accept notice or service of process on behalf of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A8D8E8A2A5D4AAC90A43D0F9275A317"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice and service of process</header><text>The serving of notice to, or service of process upon, the agent referred to in paragraph (1)(C), or mailed to the business address of such agent, shall be deemed as service upon, or notice to, the Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8F45A7F46F749BEAE49B7526FC5BB4F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Seal</header><text>The Foundation shall have an official seal, which shall be selected by the Board and judicially noticed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D4FD3068E5E4042A1C3163BD9CB0ECB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorities</header><text>In addition to powers explicitly authorized under this Act, the Foundation, in order to carry out the purposes described in section 3(b), shall have the usual powers of a corporation headquartered in Washington, DC, including the authority—</text><paragraph id="H44F4C94E397D4926887A387356C6CA13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to accept, receive, solicit, hold, administer, and use any gift, devise, or bequest, either absolutely or in trust, or real or personal property or any income derived from such gift or property, or other interest in such gift or property located in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBE1FFA279DE4B81A45A991AD394BACC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to acquire by donation, gift, devise, purchase, or exchange any real or personal property or interest in such property located in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC366029105D444FB9F29B9D993B2E600"><enum>(3)</enum><text>unless otherwise required by the instrument of transfer, to sell, donate, lease, invest, reinvest, retain, or otherwise dispose of any property or income derived from such property located in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D37E012E5FE426A88CE76BDDA9670A6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to borrow money and issue bonds, debentures, or other debt instruments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAFA3335BD7A4239A7543E38E7DA4EAA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to complain and defend itself in any court of competent jurisdiction (except that the Directors of the Board shall not be personally liable, except for gross negligence);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7EFC18922234F69BCC5DB191F902271"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to enter into contracts or other arrangements with public agencies, private organizations, and persons and to make such payments as may be necessary to carry out the purposes of such contracts or arrangements; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB04197DC5C9845299F8B043BB4FFFDE5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to award grants for eligible projects, in accordance with section 7.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE1102842D274273B9853BDB380A0C0F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation of public liability</header><text>The United States shall not be liable for any debts, defaults, acts, or omissions of the Foundation.</text></subsection></section><section id="H02D71DF94DFA4CE88CF0DF25FB956A33"><enum>6.</enum><header>Safeguards and accountability</header><subsection id="HCA098A3A09784BA4BAC8FDFE3EEEF4AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Safeguards</header><text>The Foundation shall develop, and incorporate into any agreement for support provided by the Foundation, appropriate safeguards, policies, and guidelines, consistent with internationally recognized best practices and standards for environmental and social safeguards.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA1EC969D7B3E43248B3BA55C8F7B5C44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Independent accountability mechanism</header><paragraph id="H64E6BEFEC44F4CED98CF2963F095A07E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation shall establish a transparent and independent accountability mechanism, which shall provide—</text><subparagraph id="H8B4C3565A83A4433ADAD1454DB74DF82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a compliance review function that assesses whether Foundation-supported projects adhere to the requirements developed pursuant to subsection (a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BBE29E46642445F8FD3F376AF8701CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a dispute resolution function for resolving concerns between complainants and project implementers regarding the impacts of specific Foundation-supported projects with respect to such standards; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA054390DB88141B7B16AEB4A7AF26F2B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an advisory function that reports to the Foundation on projects, policies, and practices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8647B97893C84A35888B6C78A0058D47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The accountability mechanism shall—</text><subparagraph id="H6DAEFAD455FC4771BF6BE2E3629D7EBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>report annually to the Board and to the appropriate congressional committees regarding the Foundation’s compliance with internationally recognized best practices and standards in accordance with paragraph (1)(A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A58CC28EB00453E98641FAD01243EC6"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9405B109B39E46A4B56DF6D7D041D830"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have permanent staff to conduct compliance reviews and dispute resolutions; or</text></clause><clause id="H8AD6C0DF8F574035887B40C40A625D77"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>maintain a roster of experts to serve such roles, to the extent needed; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA41B2F50CD64FFB9A96D34A32FBB65E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hold a public comment period lasting not fewer than 60 days regarding the initial design of the accountability mechanism.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76D75645FAEC46E3860E6369B48F095E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Internal accountability</header><text>The Foundation shall establish an ombudsman position at a senior level of executive staff as a confidential, neutral source of information and assistance to anyone affected by the activities of the Foundation.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2A14CEDEE74E4A2B91976A04F9943851"><enum>7.</enum><header>Projects and grants</header><subsection id="HB9D2E8163ECF411F90070C1A919E5646"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Project funding requirements</header><paragraph id="HD71BEA0BB5C74F2AB45B520F8E23D9A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation shall—</text><subparagraph id="H84DA8215CFAA4364B6C0DE31F310D68C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide grants to fund eligible projects described in paragraph (2) that support its mission to provide long-term funding for the effective management of protected and conserved areas and their contiguous buffer zones in eligible countries; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AF5F503C59A43338CE8095420B902BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognize the importance of a landscape or seascape approach to conservation that includes buffer zones, wildlife dispersal and corridor areas, and other effective area-based conservation measures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEACF5C5765EE42628EB59491F220EE68"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text>Eligible projects shall include projects that—</text><subparagraph id="HF59FB93C4DC841AEAA22B0789A0C0096"><enum>(A)</enum><text>focus on supporting—</text><clause id="H644FA9BAA77345B289CBF64D7FD6360F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>long-term management of protected or conserved areas and their contiguous buffer zones in countries described in subsection (b), including terrestrial, coastal, and marine protected or conserved areas, parks, community conservancies, Indigenous reserves, conservation easements, and biological reserves; and</text></clause><clause id="H6A8612A412F4499A856DC0E0013078DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other effective area-based conservation measures;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42B84108781C44F3A333D6B506E738F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are cost-matched at a ratio of 2 from other sources to 1 from the United States Government;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44AD519D21BB4738B39E6E49A05E0D11"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have host country and local population support, as evidenced by a long-term binding memorandum of understanding signed by the host government that respects free, prior, and informed consent of affected communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5956C56FD8B74609B1A1F233AB018B60"><enum>(D)</enum><text>incorporate a set of key performance indicators;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7775C84D271C430C88A727F0DBA6073B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>demonstrate robust local community engagement, with the completion of appropriate environmental and social due diligence, including—</text><clause id="H83260BB7C4A44298AAF709F59FEFD86A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>free, prior, and informed consent of Indigenous Peoples and prior consultation with relevant local communities;</text></clause><clause id="HFD3FAB8BB2534C018753C5051A8B908D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>equitable governance structures; and</text></clause><clause id="H72A4092F5F854190B52CEBA0794FD923"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>effective grievance mechanisms;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC304924A4D9D447D8C827D4AE6C9BFF0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>create economic opportunities for local communities, through activities such as—</text><clause id="H51BDDB676574499FBF68B0200DBCECD8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>equity and profit-sharing;</text></clause><clause id="HD2A4EB63C35947318B1B14716C79BB36"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>employment activities; and</text></clause><clause id="H5FFAA0973BD9421B93848E55A2D71990"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other economic growth activities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1541645800014B81AD8B8C77D6BC7265"><enum>(G)</enum><text>provide stable baseline funding for the effective management of the protected or conserved area project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1AD1BE9EF0A442EB4DF2D1CB32DEB1E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>are implementation-ready; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39B0144DF05A4C0590C7107663A5EE3E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>where possible, demonstrate a plan to strengthen the capacity of, and transfer skills to, local institutions to manage the protected or conserved area before or after grant funding is exhausted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DE7627218C248EB991789FC3401C2E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible countries</header><paragraph id="HEC1846B485424E7187DD456BF54F7726"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before awarding any grants or entering into any project agreements for a given fiscal year, the Board shall conduct a review to determine candidate countries in which the Foundation shall be eligible to fund projects to determine which countries—</text><subparagraph id="H354040007D5B41A4B73A24F58B678183"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are low-income, lower middle-income, or upper-middle-income economies (as defined by the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4E9BBF6728B4C109961E96A0BEFF4EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have—</text><clause id="H3A6A340BB56643A7A816EF8F9F7726D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a high degree of threatened or at risk biological diversity; or</text></clause><clause id="H2174FC8A7F0144AEA7B9ACB3A235DCED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>species or ecosystems of significant importance, including threated or endangered species or ecosystems at risk of degradation or destruction; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB13A0DEFBF824018B22EDB139DABD54A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have demonstrated a commitment to conservation through actions, such as protecting lands and waters through the gazettement of national parks, community conservancies, marine reserves and protected areas, forest reserves, or other legally recognized forms of place-based conservation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE75F2E3DA3DD48FF971291DC82342503"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Identification of eligible countries</header><text>Not later than 5 days after the date on which the Board determines which countries are eligible countries for a given fiscal year, the Executive Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="H68D7C0E82EC44C4EA36BF9CB03DF455D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that includes—</text><clause id="HBE5F62066D0E4D59AEABF58DCE08E049"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a list of all such eligible countries as determined through the review process described in paragraph (1); and</text></clause><clause id="H1335ED2DB71C42FE9B67BE8D10E66DBE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a justification for such eligibility ; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFE4FDA8CC724D8DA6F30BA05C18081E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publish the information contained in the report described in paragraph (A) in the Federal Register.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0995DE64163B45659F90F174E9F4C998"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grantmaking</header><paragraph id="HCDD036FDBC424512AA87788FB7726B82"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order to maximize its program effects, the Foundation shall—</text><subparagraph id="HBF559F0000444CB185B4BC83BA57C609"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate with other international public and private donors to the extent possible;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B8968E3DA344046B6FD713BE1909A66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seek additional financial and nonfinancial contributions and commitments for its projects from host governments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55A853E8434342509E27349BE9254013"><enum>(C)</enum><text>strive to generate a partnership mentality among all participants, including public and private funders, host governments, local protected areas authorities, and private and nongovernmental organization partners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC8A2362CF1145109381A46C82E1FD3B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>prioritize investments in communities with low levels of economic development to the extent practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E55EB9E975248A58E15287FEFADDF2D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grant criteria</header><text>Foundation grants—</text><subparagraph id="H98359419F1B3464FB544D505A01C8EDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall fund the management of well-defined protected or conserved areas and the systems of such conservation areas in eligible countries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2BE729C60554B5581818D606093BCAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>should provide adequate baseline funding for at least 10 years, indexed for inflation, without replacing or duplicating existing baseline funding, for each protected and conserved area and the system that supports that area in an amount sufficient to maintain the effective management of the area over the long term;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00E60CD2FE614DE8989233C3054718A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>should, during the grant period, demonstrate progress in achieving clearly identified key performance indicators (as defined in the grant agreement), which may include—</text><clause id="H094D203AA6394C319C9F7C22E53E7925"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the protection of biological diversity;</text></clause><clause id="H6A96FE3E5ADA4EA28EF872E2E26E1FA5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the protection of native flora and habitats, such as trees, forests, wetlands, grasslands, mangroves, coral reefs, and sea grass;</text></clause><clause id="HFFD5A9CE62EE43D6A7FDF154040E85D8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>community-based economic growth indicators, such as improved land tenure, increases in beneficiaries participating in economic growth activities, and sufficient income from conservation activities being directed to communities in project areas;</text></clause><clause id="H9FA7391A68DF426982B0DCACE35DF09F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>improved management of the protected or conserved area covered by the project, as documented through the submission of strategic plans or annual reports to the Foundation; and</text></clause><clause id="HE3C5A3E5FFD34B91BAF2612E5229EDBC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the identification of additional revenue sources or sustainable financing mechanisms to meet the recurring costs of management of the protected or conserved areas; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2E1DE41CB254235AD5384BC0931716A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>may be terminated if the Board determines that the project is not meeting applicable requirements under this Act or making progress in achieving the key performance indicators defined in the grant agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9E4BC0B27B6B40CBA47A6AC1CFDC2D89"><enum>8.</enum><header>Prohibition of support in countries that support terrorism or violate human rights and of support for sanctioned persons</header><subsection id="HFA4F41D4AB6445A0A4B28F781BD72086"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Foundation may not provide support for any government, or any entity owned or controlled by a government, if the Secretary has determined that such government—</text><paragraph id="H1F6B512517AB4382BEFB5E3CF228379D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism, as determined under—</text><subparagraph id="H3126705FBAE2473681C7CD0DFF7C0214"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 1754(c)(1)(A)(i) of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/4813">22 U.S.C. 4813(c)(1)(A)(i)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9807BCD8ED44D1A81657CC9EC8757C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 620A(a) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371(a)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A4D58F0C5A547D6AC42BC396AB80A92"><enum>(C)</enum><text>section 40(d) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780(d)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE430FEA6809C4C92AEEF571323891A43"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other relevant provision of law; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H41F48A95842A4049951187A66B704D8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has engaged in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights, as determined under section 116(a) or 502B(a)(2) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151n">22 U.S.C. 2151n(a)</external-xref> and 2304(a)(2)) or any other relevant provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H98434644D99F46C78B438E84B71D7739"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition of support for sanctioned persons</header><text>The Foundation may not engage in any dealing prohibited under United States sanctions laws or regulations, including dealings with persons on the list of specially designated persons and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury, except to the extent otherwise authorized by the Secretary or by the Secretary of the Treasury.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5415F665C9D24E319B79D3545E1C0A30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition of support for activities subject to sanctions</header><text>The Foundation shall require any person receiving support to certify that such person, and any entity owned or controlled by such person, is in compliance with all United States sanctions laws and regulations.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6C4A96C83C5F4EEE983661856372D666"><enum>9.</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 360 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter while the Foundation continues to operate, the Executive Director of the Foundation shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that describes—</text><paragraph id="H83DE9D6E9E9D4CCFB3E31CDA36004CF5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the goals of the Foundation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA200A34C094AF7AE23F4E4067BC0E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the programs, projects, and activities supported by the Foundation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85427ADEB63645709AB57AA6778BBC17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>private and governmental contributions to the Foundation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F9CC4D5AD8B48AA938C77BF62A39375"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the standardized criteria utilized to determine the programs and activities supported by the Foundation, including baselines, targets, desired outcomes, measurable goals, and extent to which those goals are being achieved for each project.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H1F7CF43A6C0E4EB28E392FE3C9322B08"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="H4CEA04F83C7F4B90824799B77B57BDA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Foundation $1,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and $100,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2025 through 2035 to carry out the purposes of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H92DF3B90152640979258E809413993A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cost matching requirement</header><text>Amounts appropriated pursuant to subsection (a) may only be made available to grantees to the extent the Foundation or such grantees secure funding for an eligible project from sources other than the United States Government in an amount that is not less than twice the amount received in grants for such project pursuant to section 7.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB7BA5C17261446C18ED526041EC6581B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of grant amounts for lobbying expenses</header><text>Amounts provided as a grant by the Foundation shall not be used for any activity the purpose of which is to influence legislation pending before the United States Congress.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

