<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H73936E1FCED2427C91F8E0B59C123EEC"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1501 RH: Unmanned Aerial Security Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 119</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1501</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–151]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000603">Mr. Luttrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="L000597">Ms. Lee of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 9, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the Secretary of Homeland Security from operating or procuring certain foreign-made unmanned aircraft systems, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="H5C9D2615349248D2901A9A9017AE42E7" reported-display-style="italic" changed="added" committee-id="HHM00"><section id="H2783028E0DA040B382A9AF5A5C7C5A55" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Unmanned Aerial Security Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>UAS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5842687983AD49EB8B27A911D96E9C52"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on operation or procurement of certain foreign-made unmanned aircraft systems</header><subsection id="HA6E1702F344444B6BE7A6DBD75344A61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on agency operation or procurement</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b) and subsection (c)(3), the Secretary of Homeland Security may not operate, provide financial assistance for, or enter into or renew a contract for the procurement of—</text><paragraph id="H23EEDF080BF64E099240696892900E2B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an unmanned aircraft system (UAS) that—</text><subparagraph id="H9394219CA53948E6ADCE5B39237E50B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is manufactured in a covered foreign country or by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CE8491DB7C14B2197C51E1713D194EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>uses flight controllers, radios, data transmission devices, cameras, or gimbals manufactured in a covered foreign country or by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H471E100EB7E642CE844A1B8286CB33E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>uses a ground control system or operating software developed in a covered foreign country or by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3653DE0E087D463F9F20A67B7B51665A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>uses network connectivity or data storage located in a covered foreign country or administered by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB3334261A3C4789B3E69A2F499930F9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a software operating system associated with a UAS that uses network connectivity or data storage located in a covered foreign country or administered by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39D558F03B4649BF98ABEC28F07B36F8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a system for the detection or identification of a UAS, which system is manufactured in a covered foreign country or by a business entity domiciled in a covered foreign country.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E13F90E865940868FBF6AC17CD96BF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiyer</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id08ea41c88e3446d2af4e245e4777b597"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security is authorized to waive the prohibition under subsection (a) if the Secretary certifies in writing to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate that a UAS, a software operating system associated with a UAS, or a system for the detection or identification of a UAS described in any of paragraphs (1) through (3) of such subsection that is the subject of such a waiver is required—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id93e1d59ca7e04ceab8fa063159767ab6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the national interest of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id03e85200b644425ea108ae81b09289d7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for counter-DAS surrogate research, testing, development, evaluation, or training; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1772ebb2c35e49a8a915f46e881268d7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for intelligence, electronic warfare, or information warfare operations, testing, analysis, and or training. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7fb422e4f612451d98cb685660b3de1c"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The certification described in paragraph (1) shall be submitted to the Committees specified in such paragraph by not later than the date that is 14 days after the date on which a waiver is issued under such paragraph.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id5c6e5633fbf643db8ed1a630798b027b"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><paragraph id="id3568ac20ea6b4ae6a90394b67def395f"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This Act shall take effect on the date that is 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf9fa3baa3bc44954bd5d36559d4f1e47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiyer process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish a process by which the head of an office or component of the Department of Homeland Security may request a waiver under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd0b2c7f5867941479083e0a052ec278d"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the prohibition under subsection (a), the head of an office or component of the Department of Homeland Security may continue to operate a UAS, a software operating system associated with a UAS, or a system for the detection or identification of a UAS described in any of paragraphs (1) through (3) of such subsection that was in the inventory of such office or component on the day before the effective date of this Act until—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5ced07a163804df19b70bbe009fd70b7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such time as the Secretary of Homeland Security has—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide1f67b423fc54beb9be2faa004c761b9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">granted a waiver relating thereto under subsection (b); or </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id242918d5011f4e9a902d258b7d90900d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">declined to grant such a waiver; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2c00ec5779614167a35039a70163de70"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, whichever is later.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id23ad68d42ed14a29b59307327338c25e"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Drone origin security report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a terrorism threat assessment and report that contains information relating to the following: </text><paragraph id="id76ba2141bd6b457196360f6ef22e4a6c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The extent to which the Department of Homeland Security has previously analyzed the threat that a UAS, a software operating system associated with a UAS, or a system for the detection or identification of a UAS described in any of paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a) operating in the United States poses, and the results of such analysis. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0f9409e6d8ea4f3ca1e002e1737a1333"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of UAS, software operating systems associated with a UAS, or systems for the detection or identification of a UAS described in any of paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a) in operation by the Department, including an identification of the component or office of the Department at issue, as of such date.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idddcd160efa574b65b41473a872966917"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The extent to which information gathered by a UAS, a software operating system associated with a UAS, or a system for the detection or identification of a UAS described in any of paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a) could be employed to harm the national or economic security of the United States. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idaad1e9f794fc49dbaa818377d83f72d3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDCD77E260984D12B4D47EB765F5809F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Business entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>business entity</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 334 of the Graham-Leach-Bliley Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6764">15 U.S.C. 6764</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id443e81d295504b42b41fa628f6876d0e"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered foreign country</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered foreign country</quote> means a country that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6c0c4b530c56461f868848dbe298c993"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the intelligence community has identified as a foreign adversary in its most recent Annual Threat Assessment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida8df17dc4c1447cbbad397fd729976eb"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, has identified as a foreign adversary that is not included in such Annual Threat Assessment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id232b4fc292754556bd98b323077575e2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2a87e9b1df554105a982810e5f4891cf"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Unmanned aircraft system; UAS</header><text>The terms <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> and <quote>UAS</quote> have the meaning given the term <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

