<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE650C9ADAC994EFBBCBEFDAA93EC595A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 607 IH: Booster Seat Safety Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 607</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to revise regulations relating to child restraint systems, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE49E9B04241B456F82BC790F86E5D728" style="OLC"><section id="H195742EDA3594FC99CAC79306F74ED86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Booster Seat Safety Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H04D410FDFABD496092921DAFE77AA9AD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Child restraint systems</header><subsection id="H44121739FAEB44F48340C1E09A39C028"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Child restraint system labeling</header><paragraph id="HEADFAE8AD275485BBEA94A435BF07270"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="H80400926150E460FB33518075E3CD5BA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Revisions required</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall revise section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations—</text><clause id="H0A45F08DFB244078931769597DF5CD0D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in S5.5.2(f), by striking <quote>13.6 kg</quote> and inserting <quote>18.2 kg</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H4EADC7CBD72843D7BD887669FBE5CF3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end of S5.5.2 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD8F28551AC954EC9B30AC384DA3CE227" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H85DBF98D864D4F299DB3659681D862FE"><enum>(o)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The packaging for each booster seat shall be permanently labeled with the information specified in S5.5.2(g).</text></subsection><subsection id="HBE5C54AA0CCB429E96A04746BEFB5E2C"><enum>(p)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On each booster seat, and on the packaging of such booster seat, there shall be placed—</text><paragraph id="HA6E7A25FF9B64B1C86DC9150825D575A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a permanent label stating: <quote>For use by children [_] years old or older and who are over [_] pounds.</quote>, with respect to which—</text><subparagraph id="H4A649E3F39AD4D218C994CD574D7ECB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the first bracket is replaced with the minimum age recommended for a user, which may not be an age younger than 4 years old; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34B5D6E53C8745EB8004909C7B951009"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the second bracket is replaced with the minimum weight recommended for a user, which may not be under 40 pounds; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H55BCCA4BB7574673802EEFEB07AF21C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a permanent label stating: <quote>Strongly recommended children use this seat only when they reach either the height or weight limit for a child restraint system with internal harness as indicated by the manufacturer.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B709881C1CC403B96F128C999A404F1"><enum>(q)</enum><text>On each child restraint system with internal harness, and on the packaging of such child restraint system with internal harness, there shall be placed a permanent label stating: <quote>To prevent possible injury or death, it is important to delay the transition from a child restraint system with internal harness to a booster seat as long as possible, until the child reaches the weight or height limit of the child restraint system with internal harness as indicated by the manufacturer.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F93C26C24314DB198EEF52FBFFCFFCD"><enum>(r)</enum><text>On each combination car seat, there shall be placed a permanent label stating: <quote>Please use this seat with the internal harness as long as possible, until your child outgrows the maximum weight of [_] or reaches the maximum height of [_]. Once they have exceeded such weight or height, this seat can be used as a belt positioning booster seat with the vehicle seat belt.</quote>, with respect to which—</text><paragraph id="H79472B78D93645689D67421FD4A8A5C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the first bracket is replaced with the maximum weight recommended for an internal harness user, which may not be under 40 pounds; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41E444160D3A41E1B066F9138D3D852E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the second bracket is replaced with the maximum height recommended for an internal harness user.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1581EE77EB44A2BA478E3A2FEDE07F7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The revisions to section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, under subparagraph (A) shall take effect not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB93D1A707A914731B736F55CC71061AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum height labeling requirement for booster seats</header><subparagraph id="H48810058E35E425AAC9CB4E22B0BAB4C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Revisions required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall revise section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, so as to—</text><clause id="HF01FF786FC9F45528205A6DEB54C4844"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require the permanent label required by S5.5.2(p)(1) for a booster seat and the packaging of such booster seat to state the minimum height recommended for a user of such booster seat; and</text></clause><clause id="HF1E343F6176C4997BC0F74C09985E175"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specify—</text><subclause id="HCDA19C364DF64FB5997F4C8DF46B2463"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the minimum height required to be stated on such label; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HAD65F06C05114FA1BB3DC51B868EC249"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a method by which a manufacturer of a booster seat shall determine the minimum height required to be stated on such label for such booster seat.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07F9040B4B554835A9699DF899C85E4A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The revisions to section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, under subparagraph (A) shall take effect on the date that is 1 year after the Secretary of Transportation completes such revisions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBEC46741DE3426DB2A292A0C8EA4028"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Side-Impact crash testing</header><paragraph id="H948E94A4B7294389A1165DBD7FE180D7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General standards</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator shall issue regulations to establish standards with respect to side-impact crash testing for child restraint systems, which—</text><subparagraph id="H4BE267D85EF640B291E79877D3273224"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall include standards for booster seats; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2595B5509C24CB19F42487F9CD55816"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include the use of the most appropriate test dummy available at the time of such side-impact crash testing. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4442C5BC6FAC463D8CAE36F05D8DD169"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Near-side and far-side impact testing</header><text>In issuing regulations under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall include procedures for testing—</text><subparagraph id="HC0286B632E2144ECA1E1AFFB71B8DE74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>near-side impacts, in which the child restraint system being tested is positioned on the side of the point of impact; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BCD216195E34721AC798DAEFAC52E4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>far-side impacts, in which the child restraint system being tested is positioned on the opposite side of the point of impact.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA88710A6B5643CE86786D68E4C71A7A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Booster seat test devices</header><subparagraph id="H1654826B264142BF8434EAD053D58834"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Design</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator shall issue regulations that provide guidelines for a test dummy that approximates a 6-year-old child for the purposes of side-impact crash testing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C3DB15E329641F9AA1365F93D304CAE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date on which the Administrator issues regulations under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall require that side-impact crash testing for booster seats (for both near-side and far-side impacts) includes the use of a test dummy that meets the guidelines provided under subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC0E2A485C264FEA89B82D5EA65AF59F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tether systems study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator shall provide to Congress a study of the functionality of tether systems and the variability that exists in tether use recommendations by car seat and vehicle manufacturers, with recommendations on how such tether systems may be used or modified to increase the usage of child restraint systems with internal harness to maximize child safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE60E3B128B09458296D03ED10783C73C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF1449C3470154FA1A79B14137F93FACE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B96A01D6F1B489E960DDAD30FE6985F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Booster seat</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>booster seat</term> has the meaning given such term in section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D8770E09A744A5B1C2CC78A0F45CF6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Child restraint system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>child restraint system</term> has the meaning given such term in section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C9F1BF64D23446CB1AFE167CB48DB1D" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Child restraint system with internal harness</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>child restraint system with internal harness</quote> means a child restraint system designed to be used rear-facing or forward-facing employing a 5-point harness to position the child in the seat.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE29DBEE083B4492993F3BD7685C13A5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Combination car seat</header><text>The term <quote>combination car seat</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HFA9C0DDB21A743FEA44939E5B0FAFB8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any child restraint system designed to be used in a forward-facing position with a 5-point internal harness, where the harness may be removed and the seat utilized as a belt-positioning booster seat; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7861403AA6EA4088A77D49F08DB04F00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a child restraint system that may be—</text><clause id="HE7FDD1DA3FC040F5B46DCE857B2CF933"><enum>(i)</enum><text>converted between rear-facing with an internal harness and forward-facing with an internal harness; and</text></clause><clause id="H5A5782BBFBA8446087D0B157DFF560D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>commonly referred to as <quote>3-in-1</quote> or <quote>all-in-1</quote> seats.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07E329A924ED4304A58F3868C146E5D2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Test dummy</header><text>The term <quote>test dummy</quote> means an anthropomorphic test dummy as such term is used in section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBF74A99E36D4543A102E7D395E8C94D" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Tether system</header><text>The term <quote>tether system</quote> means a system utilizing a tether anchorage, tether strap, and tether hook (as such terms are defined in section 571.225 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations). </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

