<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H271889549BCB4B4DB875A0D31B49F220" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 3938 RH: Build It in America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 99</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3938</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–127]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on June 9, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to encourage economic growth.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HWM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H3CDA23E8F73D4D67B2200FA851940CD2"><section id="H44362ED921BA497A9F550132D4A45814" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents, etc</header><subsection id="H0841506FC091404EA2C3E2530708CC69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Build It in America Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89F9013C7F964686B5470519F811E502"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendment of <enum-in-header>1986 </enum-in-header>Code</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise expressly provided, whenever in this Act an amendment or repeal is expressed in terms of an amendment to, or repeal of, a section or other provision, the reference shall be considered to be made to a section or other provision of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD1703AE392A54A9F8AA29FA8BAE6D949"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc-entry idref="H44362ED921BA497A9F550132D4A45814" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents, etc.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA2151A4D3900438DBB9B5B67DE71D629" level="title">Title I—Investment in America</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBFBD0D099370469EBD20428A9C3DF619" level="section">Sec. 101. Deduction for research and experimental expenditures.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H92E401616C424E29A725DC891C0EEA06" level="section">Sec. 102. Extension of allowance for depreciation, amortization, or depletion in determining the limitation on business interest.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6054105CF13542278826B182EA9349CB" level="section">Sec. 103. Extension of 100 percent bonus depreciation.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H650391CE9D154E7EB7F4540B970021CE" level="title">Title II—Supply Chain Security</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8A82F2CD8224B55A648B1B2A23E560B" level="section">Sec. 201. Termination of Hazardous Substance Superfund financing rate.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8FC8C26B5D514BDEAD03550CE192B356" level="section">Sec. 202. Election to determine foreign income taxes paid or accrued to certain Western Hemisphere countries without regard to certain regulations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7DF6EDEF435E47CBA080BCF673BD9E11" level="section">Sec. 203. Imposition of tax on the acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE2A8F09A4C55442BB4185C05C92170C5" level="title">Title III—Repeal of Special Interest Tax Provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H920CE0DD19DD4F3E8D85B9EDF08D76D5" level="section">Sec. 301. Repeal of clean electricity production credit.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H569AFD66E85C485694D5F112CBF945AC" level="section">Sec. 302. Repeal of clean electricity investment credit.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0F3867BDAAA840849E4F83912875AA05" level="section">Sec. 303. Modification of clean vehicle credit.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H932FFBC5346A462D8403547C3C41CC4D" level="section">Sec. 304. Repeal of credit for previously-owned clean vehicles.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEA850133F661416B84B042F462FB1CAF" level="section">Sec. 305. Repeal of credit for qualified commercial clean vehicles.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><title id="HA2151A4D3900438DBB9B5B67DE71D629"><enum>I</enum><header>Investment in America</header><section id="HBFBD0D099370469EBD20428A9C3DF619"><enum>101.</enum><header>Deduction for research and experimental expenditures</header><subsection id="H9910D5CAF2BC481F9D6EA25D092A6234"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Delay of amortization of research and experimental expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/174">Section 174</external-xref> is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE965550A35DF415B817E71C9187BDA01" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subsection id="H9DB308C0C9F14EF7A1009DD150444910"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Suspension of application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after December 31, 2025 (and shall not apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning on or before such date).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HEE462C4C70E84C1EA5145A65C61856AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reinstatement of expensing for research and experimental expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part VI of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by inserting after section 174 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFBA2B170F85B48A89EAFA032310B9F21" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><section id="H4DB21AEAAA3147E5A5F7C3A73731BB90"><enum>174A.</enum><header>Temporary rules for research and experimental expenditures</header><subsection id="H8C867FE6987948499AE81F181FD5A8B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Treatment as expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 263, there shall be allowed as a deduction any research or experimental expenditures which are paid or incurred by the taxpayer during the taxable year in connection with the taxpayer’s trade or business.</text></subsection><subsection id="H220D354B33FB4E6FB1658C7541B839EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amortization of certain research and experimental expenditures</header><paragraph id="H77AF3346A4A846718C73FC7DA09DEFD6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>At the election of the taxpayer, made in accordance with regulations or other guidance provided by the Secretary, research or experimental expenditures which—</text><subparagraph id="HA6FB4F95DEFB4A12ADA02660F6953B01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are paid or incurred by the taxpayer in connection with his trade or business, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A18B6E288F44761AE62C77AA3C1AEF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>would (but for subsection (a)) be chargeable to capital account but not chargeable to property of a character which is subject to the allowance under section 167 (relating to allowance for depreciation, etc.) or section 611 (relating to allowance for depletion),</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">may be treated as deferred expenses to which subsection (a) does not apply. In computing taxable income, such deferred expenses shall be allowed as a deduction ratably over such period of not less than 60 months as may be selected by the taxpayer (beginning with the month in which the taxpayer first realizes benefits from such expenditures). Such deferred expenses are expenditures properly chargeable to capital account for purposes of section 1016(a)(1) (relating to adjustments to basis of property). </continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD66C2560FB8448E6B0A760A9581A5461"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Time for and scope of election</header><text>The election provided by paragraph (1) may be made for any taxable year, but only if made not later than the time prescribed by law for filing the return for such taxable year (including extensions thereof). The method so elected, and the period selected by the taxpayer, shall be adhered to in computing taxable income for the taxable year for which the election is made and for all subsequent taxable years unless, with the approval of the Secretary, a change to a different method (or to a different period) is authorized with respect to part or all of such expenditures. The election shall not apply to any expenditure paid or incurred during any taxable year before the taxable year for which the taxpayer makes the election.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9CC13BA8367946C09BA99E468CEE9A38"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Election to capitalize expenses</header><text>In the case of a taxpayer which elects (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may provide) the application of this subsection, subsections (a) and (b) shall not apply. Such election shall not apply to any expenditure paid or incurred during any taxable year before the taxable year for which the taxpayer makes the election and may be made with respect to part of the expenditures paid or incurred during any taxable year only with the approval of the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H382873BC6CFA427D94BACA495DF7BEEB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Land and other property</header><text>This section shall not apply to any expenditure for the acquisition or improvement of land, or for the acquisition or improvement of property to be used in connection with the research or experimentation and of a character which is subject to the allowance under section 167 (relating to allowance for depreciation, etc.) or section 611 (relating to allowance for depletion); but for purposes of this section allowances under section 167, and allowances under section 611, shall be considered as expenditures.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE5F4FB9C16694109BE847BA47CA803F5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exploration expenditures</header><text>This section shall not apply to any expenditure paid or incurred for the purpose of ascertaining the existence, location, extent, or quality of any deposit of ore or other mineral (including oil and gas).</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2FA14D9821841EFBA4C3F638F1009FB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Software development</header><text>For purposes of this section, any amount paid or incurred in connection with the development of any software shall be treated as a research or experimental expenditure.</text></subsection><subsection id="H00BC440B0B744AEA9D7707B66FF4996E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Only reasonable research expenditures eligible</header><text>This section shall apply to a research or experimental expenditure only to the extent that the amount thereof is reasonable under the circumstances.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89FADD78015B4027B883BE6D2EEA7C1F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Coordination with research credit</header><paragraph id="H7BD0BEBCAD7242679F81D48258115A93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 41(d)(1)(A) shall be applied by substituting <quote>expenses under section 174A</quote> for <quote>specified research or experimental expenditures under section 174</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB29123F17D7F49FD9BB99AA22E7496CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Denial of double benefit</header><subparagraph id="HA0910847B11542138B661FBE45D074AC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 280C(c) shall not apply and the amount taken into account under this section as research or experimental expenditures shall be reduced by the amount of the credit allowable under section 41(a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF25E48D5C29D4F9DB1C9C9CDCF3445F1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Election of reduced credit</header><clause id="H47E104AEB9D84CABB7DA6AAA2ACD26BB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any taxable year for which an election is made under this subparagraph—</text><subclause id="HE0785358FBBF44DB8825861FB4CB0444"><enum>(I)</enum><text>subparagraph (A) shall not apply, and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC6FC7E2236C64BB1952D8776A179D9D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the amount of the credit under section 41(a) shall be the amount determined under clause (ii).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H48865CEEC9CB4B6CA382DA4799F2E2C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Amount of reduced credit</header><text>The amount of credit determined under this clause for any taxable year shall be the amount equal to the excess of—</text><subclause id="HA9D033C5A9944D4EA35B18C513ECCDF6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount of credit determined under section 41(a) without regard to this subparagraph, over</text></subclause><subclause id="H38E7349B15CB4204A8F461AF458FDF83"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the product of the amount described in subclause (I), multiplied by the rate of tax under section 11(b).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H86001FBD1E9E4DB49945F222861AA4BE"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Election</header><text>An election under this subparagraph for any taxable year shall be made not later than the time for filing the return of tax for such year (including extensions), shall be made on such return, and shall be made in such manner as the Secretary may prescribe. Such an election, once made, shall be irrevocable.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BF2977099D24A4F98E9BE390219013A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Controlled groups</header><text>Paragraph (3) of section 280C(b) shall apply for purposes of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75732517408D4B26BFF6E9B48A6F69EB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Coordination with long-term contract rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of determining percentage of completion under section 460(b)(1)(A), any research or experimental expenditures paid or incurred by the taxpayer in connection with the taxpayer’s trade or business shall be taken into account as a cost allocated to the contract for the taxable year in which so paid or incurred.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8879DCBC23464AF8AE3CA1AA0D355334"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Coordination with certain other provisions</header><text>A reference to the corresponding provision of this section shall be treated as included in any reference to section 174 in section 56(b), 59(e), 144(a), 168(i), 170(e), 195(c), 263(a), 263A(c), 469(c), 543(d), 864(g), 993(d), 1016(a)(14), 1202(a), or 1298(e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0A1E2A6412694042BB0225A9FA671B3F"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H6DBA2DA428F249BBBE330B3DAAC3D5A4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall not apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after December 31, 2025.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA69AC3062A1A4A12960E2C9612E21C4F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Change in method of accounting</header><text>Paragraph (1) (and the corresponding application of section 174) shall be treated as a change in method of accounting for purposes of section 481 and—</text><subparagraph id="H412B754F142046869A64B6454BFE9DA9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such change shall be treated as initiated by the taxpayer,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95DE33A10EDC422F92EA9357E61C93C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such change shall be treated as made with the consent of the Secretary, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA85A318142B4CED93D40C862DF08A8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such change shall be applied only on a cut-off basis for any research or experimental expenditures paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after December 31, 2025, and no adjustment under section 481(a) shall be made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H9BBBABBF25E543B28B268047AA32F8C1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination of amortization with certain other provisions</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/174">Section 174</external-xref>, as amended by subsection (a), is amended by redesignating subsection (e) as subsection (f) and by inserting after subsection (d) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0B7509E564CE4040A4B6F7142174EA90" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subsection id="HFEDE0E23A3A84C2E8C766251A5DE8380"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination with certain other provisions</header><paragraph id="HD6ABD0D804D3425CB0F1F534C3F6FCD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coordination with alternative minimum tax</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 56(b)(2) and 59(e)(2)(B) shall not apply to specified research or experimental expenditures to which this section applies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63B9053FD2F94855AE345A8E0EF0D463"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination with basis adjustment rules</header><text>Section 1016(a)(14) shall be applied by substituting <quote>an amortization deduction under section 174(a)</quote> for <quote>deductions as deferred expenses under section 174(b)(1)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99107F8A9B014BDABF1ABD5AA410DC9C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination with long-term contract rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of determining percentage of completion under section 460(b)(1)(A), the amortization deduction under subsection (a) shall be taken into account as a cost allocated to the contract.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7EEEE990742B457388ACB6AD2B96CA41"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H20F32EBC24024830B10D89E472A5E4AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 13206 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> is amended by striking subsection (b) (relating to change in method of accounting).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8250AB35D954255B54F20C60D9AFAAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for part VI of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 174 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2F20D34E1BB7486F8E6B4AE46931BC8C" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HFBA2B170F85B48A89EAFA032310B9F21" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc-entry idref="H4DB21AEAAA3147E5A5F7C3A73731BB90" level="section">Sec. 174A. Temporary rules for research and experimental expenditures.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF8DD84EDDF3544BE95D08EA8F797788D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H19F904B9737B463DBD96B05B6699BDFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after December 31, 2021.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3673ABB557404FF9B5C26D43F4422132"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Repeal of superceded change in method of accounting rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (d)(1) shall take effect as if included in <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96BB3AE76376401A994DF92076F7EEBE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Transition rules</header><paragraph id="HEB8ACCE9DC704E83B7B5F242553AEF57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Election regarding treatment as change in method of accounting</header><text>In the case of any taxpayer which (as of the date of the enactment of this Act) had adopted a method of accounting provided by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/174">section 174</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as in effect prior to the amendments made by this section) for the taxpayer’s first taxable year beginning after December 31, 2021, and elects the application of this paragraph—</text><subparagraph id="HAD2153D7B0B84C1A803E626E4ACE54E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amendments made by this section shall be treated as a change in method of accounting for purposes of section 481 of such Code,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD82E70B438945D79346BE7E42FDF037"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such change shall be treated as initiated by the taxpayer for the taxpayer’s immediately succeeding taxable year,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DDDD6AC486D40588577BB06E4ED450F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such change shall be treated as made with the consent of the Secretary, and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86F4F39BBF5E4859B997310FD5152A07"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such change shall be applied on a modified cut-off basis, taking into account for purposes of section 481(a) of such Code only the capitalized expenditures which were not allowed as an amortization deduction by reason of section 174 prior to amendment by this Act for the taxpayer’s first taxable year beginning after December 31, 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0011ACF963C64C8DB321031884EF5516"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Election regarding 10-year writeoff</header><subparagraph id="HEA72D186B9234E10A460403CE50143F6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible taxpayer which files, during the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, an amended income tax return for the taxable year described in subparagraph (B)(ii) may elect the application of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/59">section 59(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 with respect to qualified expenditures described in section 59(e)(2)(B) of such Code with respect to such taxable year. Such election shall be filed with such amended income tax return and shall be effective only to the extent that such election would have been effective if filed with the original income tax return for such taxable year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4071A237C1804A0887C179E2D86D1A55"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible taxpayer</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <quote>eligible taxpayer</quote> means any taxpayer which—</text><clause id="H67FA56E85A274ABDA1D1E02E5215F5AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>does not elect the application of paragraph (1), and</text></clause><clause id="H5ABFD1B95D0E4EFBB478A8E5BADBD6CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>filed an income tax return for such taxpayer’s first taxable year beginning after December 31, 2021, before the earlier of—</text><subclause id="H61F07C450B0F40F7AF64C4863817707A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the due date for such return, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8FD0FF9473374CBD8B279FD9E1BEE862"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H92E401616C424E29A725DC891C0EEA06"><enum>102.</enum><header>Extension of allowance for depreciation, amortization, or depletion in determining the limitation on business interest</header><subsection id="H68150975E2344299BA61F828684303BA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/163">Section 163(j)(8)(A)(v)</external-xref> is amended by striking <quote>January 1, 2022</quote> and inserting <quote>January 1, 2026</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE5C682EFCAC84342B30F72BF674C93A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H82F2EC9D4C9D47E98F83E90DB4A656C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26668DB90B6F492A95AA0049738E7418"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Election to apply extension retroactively</header><text>In the case of a taxpayer which elects (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may provide) the application of this paragraph, paragraph (1) shall be applied by substituting <quote>December 31, 2021</quote> for <quote>December 31, 2022</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6054105CF13542278826B182EA9349CB"><enum>103.</enum><header>Extension of 100 percent bonus depreciation</header><subsection id="H942B5D871A7147BE8547DE2D8A57B9DC" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/168">Section 168(k)(6)(A)</external-xref> is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2295131BC1FA4C54B2227FE67C16C4C0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><subparagraph id="H5503EAFD933E4533B947ECDA1378E129"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2026</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B7CE058413F42C3AB0D566E5CD091E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8D07C23F9F74DF69F559E9670C54521"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking clauses (ii), (iii), and (iv), and redesignating clause (v) as clause (ii).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7475DD40A5834AF1B2BD0BD73B0FEBDD" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Property with longer production periods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/168">Section 168(k)(6)(B)</external-xref> is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2440892587CA422CA02C58A293E9F526"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><subparagraph id="HA4CF1220E4B74A0798B3D885258AB131"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2024</quote> and inserting <quote>2027</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F6615CB4C2C4F2AB31BF82BB699F173"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end, and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66B1C4E18A234C34A52D70C0B511BF3B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking clauses (ii), (iii), and (iv), and redesignating clause (v) as clause (ii).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3ADA59EF1704598B3C376D264CE79C6" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Plants bearing fruits and nuts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/168">Section 168(k)(6)(C)</external-xref> is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE64C1F55DB4F45B2BCA0E42C393D4B18" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><subparagraph id="H30AD99705D1B40DF8D44AE90DF73181B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2026</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8242E44C2006490087838F96F909E91F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC40F7070C6443C3992A548BF0B6254A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking clauses (ii), (iii), and (iv), and redesignating clause (v) as clause (ii).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6F1D429AE4934922848D9A0C0E4BCEB8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><paragraph id="HD910CF90929E492CAC4C115DA33B0AA2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the amendments made by this section shall apply to property placed in service after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H454AC251606A45D9A454663541F065FE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Plants bearing fruits and nuts</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (c) shall apply to specified plants planted or grafted after December 31, 2022.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H650391CE9D154E7EB7F4540B970021CE"><enum>II</enum><header>Supply Chain Security</header><section id="HC8A82F2CD8224B55A648B1B2A23E560B"><enum>201.</enum><header>Termination of Hazardous Substance Superfund financing rate</header><subsection id="H7386E81E559645949BEB6AFF99A809DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4611 (as amended by section 13601 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subsection (d) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9E4CEEAB53524B06A8E463CEF85A0E69" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subsection id="H61E3B0FABE8543DCB8A0D590222048AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application of Hazardous Substance Superfund financing rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Hazardous Substance Superfund financing rate under this section shall not apply after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H71D7B6BB53C34092A195717E4B64EC39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination of authority for advances</header><text>Section 9507(d)(3)(B) (as so amended) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H488309F8E8434839B527AED1D235C840"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>December 31, 2032</quote> and inserting <quote>the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Build It in America Act</short-title></quote>, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBB57DD5CA984DBBB381E064C05C6459"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>on or before such date</quote> and inserting <quote>as soon as practicable thereafter</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H169057B36EC74C0EA03E034D23DFB2C0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H5D03ED005F164416963722EC0A428B87"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on January 1, 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E372AE721584AB1BB1087A94A53F3BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination of authority for advances</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (b) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8FC8C26B5D514BDEAD03550CE192B356"><enum>202.</enum><header>Election to determine foreign income taxes paid or accrued to certain Western Hemisphere countries without regard to certain regulations</header><subsection id="HD7707A6B373345E3B061507646F7D3E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Election with respect to determining certain foreign income taxes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any taxpayer which elects (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may provide) the application of this subsection, the determination of whether any Western Hemisphere tax paid or accrued by such taxpayer is an income, war profits, or excess profits tax for purposes of any provision of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall be made without regard to any specified regulation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H99C2734C0AA04D3B973F347DE53F66F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Separate election with respect to allocation and apportionment of foreign income taxes relating to disregarded payments from certain disregarded entities</header><paragraph id="HE7E0B18CF7CD4F3C8927752C6686BC82"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the owner of any specified disregarded entity elects (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may provide) the application of this subsection with respect to such entity, then for purposes of allocating and apportioning any foreign income taxes (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/986">section 986(a)(4)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and determined after the application of subsection (a) of this section) paid or accrued by reason of any remittance made by such entity to such owner during the applicable period, any items of foreign gross income included by reason of the receipt of such remittance shall be assigned to a category based on current and accumulated earnings and profits of such entity (in lieu of being assigned on the basis of the tax book value method described in a specified regulation).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91BA0E5D32894F089C53F558AF2B7AA1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specified disregarded entity</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>specified disregarded entity</quote> means any entity (including any trade or business) if—</text><subparagraph id="H216CE46936544CE889985C252ACD938A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such entity is disregarded as an entity separate from its owner for purposes of applying <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0034665CCEFC4E4AB4FAD2269B41F805"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such entity is created or organized in a possession of the United States or a foreign country described in subsection (d)(1)(B),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89EED34E5D3A456284601AD167E7E834"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at all times after December 31, 2019 (or, if later, the date on which such entity is created or organized) substantially all of the income of such entity is derived from trades or businesses conducted in the possession or country referred to in subparagraph (B), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F8953AF67AE420082C13FCBCB6B7F2A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at all times after the date on which such entity is created or organized, such entity maintains separate books and records.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9643B76C4C5D4078A3263E0DB45E0810"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application to deemed paid credit</header><text>In the case of any tax paid or accrued by a controlled foreign corporation and deemed to have been paid by a United States shareholder under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/960">section 960</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986—</text><paragraph id="H521AEA829F144577AA405C45F379F372"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any election under subsection (a) or (b) shall be made by such controlled foreign corporation and shall be binding on all United States shareholders of such controlled foreign corporation, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H274C80610B9A466489FC9A155005CC42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the applicable period under subsection (d) shall be determined with respect to the taxable years of such controlled foreign corporation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88F938FE32FE44338032F30ED1B6ABB5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Western Hemisphere tax</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HC1B8D073CB074E99AD30BA69A7D7BE80"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>Western Hemisphere tax</quote> means any tax which is paid or accrued for a taxable year which is in the applicable period to—</text><subparagraph id="H207381B569FC4478B5C9D8F5EDF7F2AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any possession of the United States, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86F0E0C9938445B4909C5F48B3CE5D3D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any foreign country (other than Cuba and Venezuela) which is located in North, Central, or South America (including the West Indies).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D120468BB084A14B4FE005A22A131EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>applicable period</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HBCC9D6B85F794D6EBEEA9BEB6B5265E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of any election made under subsection (a), all taxable years beginning after December 31, 2021, and before January 1, 2027, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B1F1463AA0B498BA41FF0260D7578B0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of any election made under subsection (b), all taxable years beginning after December 31, 2019, and before January 1, 2027.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H898CD6694C484316A6C221EC5CF892D3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determination based on taxable year for which tax actually paid or accrued</header><text>The determination of the taxable year for which any tax is paid or accrued for purposes of determining whether a foreign tax is paid or accrued for a taxable year which is in the applicable period shall be made without regard to any taxable year with respect to which such tax is deemed to have been paid under section 904(c) or 960 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC71D83A523A4CE29BAA65CB7517DD9D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Specified regulation</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>specified regulation</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HC6A7075F07D946DDBF70DBEB142B5ACF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Treasury Regulations relating to “Guidance Related to the Foreign Tax Credit; Clarification of Foreign-Derived Intangible Income” (87 Fed. Reg. 276; published on January 4, 2022), </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H589FE6EE5EED493A9BB8BCB6622ADB57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>proposed Treasury Regulations relating to “Guidance Related to the Foreign Tax Credit” (87 Fed. Reg. 71271; published on November 22, 2022), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25C90562867E41B2AD4F838622E7FC27"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any regulation or other guidance published after January 4, 2022, to the extent that such regulation or other guidance is substantially similar to, or predicated upon, any portion of the regulations referred to in paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">In the case of any regulation or other guidance which is published after the date of the enactment of this Act and any portion of which is described in paragraph (3), the Secretary shall identify such regulation or guidance (or portion thereof) as not applying with respect to taxpayers which have elected the application of subsection (a) or (b), as the case may be.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="H71603D4E9A024558996A1DC0CE78A7A7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary’s delegate.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7DF6EDEF435E47CBA080BCF673BD9E11" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>203.</enum><header>Imposition of tax on the acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="H867A28AD92054A70B9DB843E670308D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle D is amended by inserting after chapter 50A the following new chapter:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDB07C143DF7B464C8ED650BF88FE8129" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><chapter id="HBB72187A206C4C109D70A4B27C9762A8"><enum>50B</enum><header>Acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><toc container-level="chapter-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HBB72187A206C4C109D70A4B27C9762A8" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HB2E13AA3F8A74427B626DD1F0ED5C6A2" level="section">Sec. 5000E. Imposition of tax on acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><section id="HB2E13AA3F8A74427B626DD1F0ED5C6A2"><enum>5000E.</enum><header>Imposition of tax on acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="H72D77B7E414D49739ABA986AD3135FF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest by any disqualified person, there is hereby imposed on such person a tax equal to 60 percent of the amount paid for such interest.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2AB5607D32104E488EAF95F11813484E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disqualified person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H1E8A9640B9B449BCB16BA72D1932B432"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>disqualified person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HAB0EEF1A07004734A12F8F4EB6EC0D29"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any citizen of a country of concern (other than a citizen, or lawful permanent resident, of the United States and other than an individual domiciled in Taiwan possessing a valid identification card or number issued by the government of Taiwan),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF452F494C1204D10BD7BB736A3B27402"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any entity domiciled in a country of concern (other than an entity domiciled in Taiwan),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECC5CF821B784BE3B477E545C6BB8694"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any country of concern and any political subdivision, agency, or instrumentality thereof, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3442EE8503F046A0B3BB9E3F662F2F65"><enum>(D)</enum><text>except as provided in paragraph (3), any entity if persons described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) (in the aggregate) 10-percent control such entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H939C1F3A60424FBA9F722274314FE826"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>country of concern</quote> means any country the government of which is engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or the security and safety of United States persons, including the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, Iran, North Korea, Cuba, and the regime of Nicolas Maduro in Venezuela.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED1D0A69556F4DC198660F73AD8456D1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception for certain publicly traded corporations</header><subparagraph id="H11EF4ACB9CD046B2AA7E3F2BB1055755"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity shall not be treated as described in paragraph (1)(D) if—</text><clause id="H7F49F092783A4EFC92DEB98B7B4A6E8A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such entity is a specified publicly traded corporation, or</text></clause><clause id="HDFD2001CF51440A88FAF63E6B2951188"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specified publicly traded corporations (in the aggregate) control such entity.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BAC49425742446584E685035E25D629"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Specified publicly traded corporation</header><clause id="HD7CA88B03541492B963BA806CD740CB5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>specified publicly traded corporation</quote> means any corporation if—</text><subclause id="H8C15F87C6DF940AC9F9096D188B58D90"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the stock of such corporation is regularly traded on an established securities market located in the United States, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H95FE7F21E0D84320ACEA8875A2E7EE07"><enum>(II)</enum><text>specified disqualified persons do not (in the aggregate) control such corporation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBB74C5F0E3764653BA4D7DB97833C111"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Specified disqualified persons</header><text>The term <quote>specified disqualified persons</quote> means, with respect to any corporation referred to in clause (i), any person which—</text><subclause id="HDBEB23991D4440B788382A2914B5FE15"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of paragraph (1), and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1ECA2BDC33D244A89735C15DB3D9D9F1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>10-percent controls such corporation.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02892F3F6390427E875AA533538850B7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prorated tax on acquisitions by entities not more than 50 percent controlled by disqualified persons</header><paragraph id="H74320C9A0A934B6492C813B008E3874F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any disqualified person described in subsection (b)(1)(D) with respect to which persons described in subparagraphs (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) do not (in the aggregate) control such disqualified person, subsection (a) shall be applied by substituting <quote>the applicable percentage of the amount</quote> for <quote>the amount</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09A7673E92FF46B5A6C219BEB96C02B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>applicable percentage</quote> means, with respect to any disqualified person to which paragraph (1) applies, the highest percentage which could be substituted for <quote>50 percent</quote> both places it appears in section 954(d)(3) without causing persons described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (b)(1) (in the aggregate) to control (determined by taking into account such substitution) such disqualified person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H04FA1BAC73D9429CB5DBD532050BC194"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Control</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H3B6182902F4C4D3D877B833364D56483"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>control</quote> has the meaning given such term under section 954(d)(3), determined by treating the rules of section 958(a)(2) as applying to both foreign and domestic corporations, partnerships, trusts, and estates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82B2610EB2B84495BFB7A1E3FE9ACEE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>10-percent control</header><text>The term <quote>10-percent control</quote> means control (as defined in paragraph (1)), determined by substituting <quote>10 percent</quote> for <quote>50 percent</quote> both places it appears in section 954(d)(3). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88008393AA1B48A9A2D93E2960F8D66A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>United States agricultural interest</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HC5A65DBB913749B686F70AF78FC86870"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>United States agricultural interest</quote> has the meaning which would be given the term <quote>United States real property interest</quote> by section 897(c) if—</text><subparagraph id="H2BDE7BF75A8B46E9AB2D4BF95FE72162"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paragraph (1)(A)(i) were applied by substituting <quote>an interest in agricultural land</quote> for <quote>an interest in real property</quote> and all that follows, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F9E4672436F4D52905807F1B72977EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>paragraph (1)(A)(ii) were applied by substituting <quote>such corporation was not a United States real property holding corporation at the time of acquisition</quote> for <quote>such corporation</quote> and all that follows,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECBBD9052D7742D287A584D01E047996"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">paragraph (1)(B) did not apply, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB86A108A13574D0FBC73930217518ADE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>paragraph (3) were applied by substituting <quote>at the time of acquisition</quote> for <quote>at some time during the shorter of the periods described in paragraph (1)(A)(ii)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC93C3F43CDD340FCBEC086B6C2DCF416"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agricultural land</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <quote>agricultural land</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6C3C008CFA2C43ADBADE878F287AE21A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">agricultural land as defined in section 9 of the Agricultural Foreign Investment Disclosure Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3508">7 U.S.C. 3508</external-xref>), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D2DEDD5B1394051B238BAF91A87D75E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>land located in one or more States and used for livestock production purposes (determined under rules similar to the rules that apply under such section 9).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H23914A73A0ED4078AE2DE6EB9F152C01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="H577ABBB4A884459DB300D9BB175C413F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subpart B of part III of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/61">chapter 61</external-xref> is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H34E912AF878149A290FA992F3AE0CE18" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><section id="HEDA483BEFA3C4244AD1CA21C8073DF7E"><enum>6050AA.</enum><header>Returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons</header><subsection id="H3FB40ABA4EC14AF68BE180C10622D987"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The required reporting person, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest by a presumptively disqualified person to which section 5000E(a) applies, shall make a return at such time as the Secretary may provide setting forth—</text><paragraph id="HB7E33D4E21C14D93A51F4AB74E57B0DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, address, and TIN of such presumptively disqualified person,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89242255192748CA9B0A7EC163BB7C0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of such United States agricultural interest (including the street address, if applicable), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EE9D7FC3F9E489B812F3EDE3DBAC57F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the amount paid for such United States agricultural interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5A62CACB39E84D7C9655E3394242FEEA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement to be furnished to presumptively disqualified person</header><text>Every person required to make a return under subsection (a) shall furnish, at such time as the Secretary may provide, to each presumptively disqualified person whose name is required to be set forth in such return a written statement showing—</text><paragraph id="H7D2967C3B48743EEB39C7A33FC337099"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name and address of the information contact of the required reporting person, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF97E4B25E0254A959A3B5446493ABA45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the information described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a) which relates to such disqualified person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H87AB0265AF2744079C80BA705196CD8E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required reporting person</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>required reporting person</quote> means, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest—</text><paragraph id="HCF5CDFEFF84440D092E7F2FA70692DC6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person (including any attorney or title company) responsible for closing the transaction in which such United States agricultural interest is acquired, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H450D6BE3A4674595AD4569603E8F22E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if no one is responsible for closing such transaction (or in such other cases as the Secretary may provide), the transferor of such United States agricultural interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8EE49AE7D2174AC7A61846EB883EB1F5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Presumptively disqualified person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>presumptively disqualified person</quote> means any person unless such person furnishes to the required reporting person an affidavit by the such person stating, under penalty of perjury, that such person is not a disqualified person (as defined in section 5000E(b)).</text></subsection><subsection id="H586148FF053F48EAADA9275FD6D603A6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirement to request affidavit</header><text>If the required reporting person, with respect to any acquisition of any United States agricultural interest, has not, as of the time of such acquisition, been furnished the affidavit described in subsection (d) by the acquirer of such interest, such required reporting person shall furnish to such acquirer, at such time, a written statement informing such acquirer of the required reporting person’s obligation to make the return described in subsection (a) with respect to such acquisition and including such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5A86BA5F92E34E719DEDF773966E4780"><enum>(f)</enum><header>United States agricultural interest</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>United States agricultural interest</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 5000E.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B33E4CB5A1E4DA48291DF03586CC1AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6724">Section 6724(d)</external-xref> is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H1A06B132A8E940F1957CD840A8C68438"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of clause (xxvii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (xxviii) and inserting <quote>or</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H982559FFDD12481A9E96EE516B916BBD" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><clause id="H35616AE095A64817BAB7FE607FEE13D9"><enum>(xxix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 6050AA(a) (relating to returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons), and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AE9BB9FB4264B18AAB40DB0BE2233DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (KK), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (LL) and inserting <quote>, or</quote>, and by inserting after subparagraph (LL) the following new subparagraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC4CBE079A1B34AF7B5885C969C93C6D8" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subparagraph id="H441408DB785F4B45913A5FEE2E29B33B"><enum>(MM)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subsection (b) or (e) of section 6055AA (relating to statements relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76A0AB28EA074D7B8B1F144FEA7C723C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><paragraph id="H372BDAD2D1AE4226B6B8909AF5E45332"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of chapters for subtitle D is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 50A the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBAFC57F84FE642D489B47C759B48CAFA" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HDB07C143DF7B464C8ED650BF88FE8129" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc-entry idref="HBB72187A206C4C109D70A4B27C9762A8" level="chapter">Chapter 50B. Acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HADE93A1A981D42D4A5DEED8608968C2B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart B of part III of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/61">chapter 61</external-xref> is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4B86205188874699912DC62409A50537" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H34E912AF878149A290FA992F3AE0CE18" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc-entry idref="HEDA483BEFA3C4244AD1CA21C8073DF7E" level="section">Sec. 6050AA. Returns relating to acquisition of United States agricultural interests by disqualified persons.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H251E3E56D2FC47CDB9920D8375DD942D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to acquisitions after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HE2A8F09A4C55442BB4185C05C92170C5"><enum>III</enum><header>Repeal of Special Interest Tax Provisions</header><section id="H920CE0DD19DD4F3E8D85B9EDF08D76D5"><enum>301.</enum><header>Repeal of clean electricity production credit</header><subsection id="H27158C01D0634F2EAD009095B261F29C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by striking section 45Y (and by striking the item relating to such section in the table of sections for such subpart).</text></subsection><subsection id="H812091E013214C3FB1AC993FF3096C97" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H2F1205236AC247E1A814244E504FC8AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/38">Section 38(b)</external-xref> is amended by striking paragraph (39) and redesignating paragraphs (40) and (41) as paragraphs (39) and (40), respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7088F400C5E4972A7E8751513A60EA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6417">Section 6417(b)</external-xref> is amended by striking paragraph (8) and redesignating paragraphs (9) through (12) as paragraphs (8) through (11), respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD956AF15BA6D4762B4F06E2B6DF15D82"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6418">Section 6418(f)(1)</external-xref> is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H0FA6D649B8FE4CA08EB92D660B51B8A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking clause (vii) and by redesignating clauses (viii) through (xi) as clauses (vii) through (x), respectively, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FDE69A458DD4ECD978C79525535EE70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>(v), or (vii)</quote> and inserting <quote>or (v)</quote>. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA7E1D59C3D7046A8824F34AC7983B8AA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall take effect as if included in section 13701 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H569AFD66E85C485694D5F112CBF945AC"><enum>302.</enum><header>Repeal of clean electricity investment credit</header><subsection id="H70A02BF7A2C34B409B0912B9AE253C76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart E of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by striking section 48E (and by striking the item relating to such section in the table of sections for such subpart).</text></subsection><subsection id="H041C82C08E3346EEA663B49150B38610"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="HC4938B1488B040E694148BAFC0D2DA46" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 46, as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H177681B6D52A42C09D0F3E722037AE5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF41C4982499149468B04C599E2B3D441"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>, and</quote> and inserting a period, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF36EA618953D421184DD9F118A432269"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (7).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0471F4D127A140DEAF481D437C81EE13"><enum>(2)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/48">Section 48(e)(4)(D)</external-xref> is amended by striking <quote>except as provided in section 48E(h)(4)(D)(ii)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83175A6DEC8940D5BCFDFC588CAC7C61"><enum>(3)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/48C">Section 48C(f)</external-xref> is amended by striking <quote>48E,</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70DEC27D230D42B985F243705C6EB7A6" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 49(a)(1)(C), as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HC6EC7E5ADEB24548BA8EF3587935F292" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (v),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A9ABC19287F4A138284F03B0BCE1521" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the comma at the end of clause (vi) and inserting a period, and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B5D46811FFC4E41B01E9EFE8949B7BD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking clauses (vii) and (viii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7487D6743489430184F955FD683AE2E3" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 50(a)(2)(E), as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended by striking <quote>48D(b)(5), or 48E(e)</quote> and inserting <quote>or 48D(b)(5)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D5542A7DA6D4DE6BB13B77C4D8D6C43" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 50(c)(3), as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended by striking <quote>or clean electricity investment credit</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26DFE267869A4E66992F2A25F3D09D49"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 168(e)(3)(B), as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H5F383272367245D99D07D788A36000CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (vi)(III), by inserting <quote>and</quote> at the end,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1267B83769F478DA8B0E3FB7F5FBBD9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (vii), by striking <quote>, and</quote> and inserting a period, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BD07D7CFFDF4BD58896BA6EB5B4618D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking clause (viii). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F4BF4FE6D164ADC9712ACA7554C8595" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6417(b), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act, is amended by striking paragraph (11).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC738D9B62074DB8BB75B814DE40F13B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Section 6418(f)(1)(A), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act, is amended by striking clause (x). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8132AC8D4E3B4C5FBDE957B654201C1A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall take effect as if included in section 13702 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H0F3867BDAAA840849E4F83912875AA05" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>303.</enum><header>Modification of clean vehicle credit</header><subsection id="HC72C114687FE44F386E1C3343E071325" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Per vehicle dollar limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D(b)</external-xref> is amended by striking paragraphs (2) and (3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5AB08152D0834BC58769015B73615994" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><paragraph id="H424758C3231F4D209249239C59D17382" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Base amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount determined under this paragraph is $2,500.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE58DAD5D89204DF9807FE7C3E29669CA" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Battery capacity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a vehicle which draws propulsion energy from a battery with not less than 5 kilowatt hours of capacity, the amount determined under this paragraph is $417, plus $417 for each kilowatt hour of capacity in excess of 5 kilowatt hours. The amount determined under this paragraph shall not exceed $5,000. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAC877EED9606433A87D6D5006A6FD79D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final assembly</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D(d)</external-xref> is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC71A3572FAFD47A6A61A48D9800B8FD4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by striking subparagraph (G), and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE43A1BD179EE416F851B0E0133EF1783"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (5).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF160DF0A9B6045FD9F86CAEBEB638C35"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional modifications to vehicle definition</header><paragraph id="HB0B68E131D7F44418F31D9C2CD51B9D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 30D(d), as amended by subsection (b), is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HCB7B3431F40443DABE4DE5DBF750E347"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Clean</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Qualified plug-in electric drive motor</header-in-text></quote>,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0D549986BFD43E0BA719E439371F6B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H7E9395A808AD42778EA1969F387A5FC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>clean</quote> and inserting <quote>qualified plug-in electric drive motor</quote>,</text></clause><clause id="HDD02850A3C6F46E7A9E6636C895108CD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>qualified</quote> before <quote>manufacturer</quote>,</text></clause><clause id="H88A107F67F9149968C9E24475231D83E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end, </text></clause><clause id="H61417105B9634C4EAF1CE8FF57174E75"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (F)—</text><subclause id="H2F7885C6FDE34C7FA610499C6E8405F2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>7</quote> and inserting <quote>4</quote>, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7CC9ABE24277447B8B72F5DAEDEFD29D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the comma at the end and inserting a period, and </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB8CF5EEAD97F42C9B4E747F20270631A" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (H), </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H056587F1A02A44B395C8795052603296"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><clause id="HCF91B9331D9148B4A4538DDD934B8957"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">qualified manufacturer</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Manufacturer</header-in-text></quote>, and</text></clause><clause id="H75929E008CEE44B3BFBAB1164AE92E8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The term <quote>qualified manufacturer</quote> means</quote> and all that follows through the period and inserting <quote>The term <quote>manufacturer</quote> has the meaning given such term in regulations prescribed by the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency for purposes of the administration of title II of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7521">42 U.S.C. 7521 et seq.</external-xref>).</quote>, and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36DCDE8EDF9C4D0F94ED2FDC6F36F4A7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (6).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA9A4AC5263E449B8818B85288F270D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D</external-xref> is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H4D57F417A1214049BE8E43EC5D1CDED3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>new clean vehicle</quote> and inserting <quote>new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicle</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35991A8867FF4C15A417443239114CCF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(1), by striking <quote>new clean vehicle</quote> and inserting <quote>new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicle</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBA8085CD05AB4E8395918A7D74C332F5" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Critical mineral and battery component requirement modifications</header><paragraph id="HC905F2106A344FA28C15225F6437E2EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 30D(e), as added by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, is amended by striking paragraphs (1) and (2), by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4), and by inserting before paragraph (4) (as so redesignated) the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H813DD5F376324C6CAA43F690CF98B5DB" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><paragraph id="H8DCBDE85203445E8870B520C3C5CEA80"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical minerals requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit shall be allowed under this section with respect to any vehicle unless, with respect to the battery from which the electric motor of such vehicle draws electricity, the percentage of the value of the applicable critical minerals (as defined in section 45X(c)(6)) contained in such battery that were—</text><subparagraph id="H7A27B70C4C0E4F51A062FA84ED75A961"><enum>(A)</enum><text>extracted or processed—</text><clause id="H279C6F7F3A7B42EE8DC315C5804A44B6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the United States, or</text></clause><clause id="H38981B3E154647348A92C6D8736F487D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in any country with which the United States has a free trade agreement in effect, or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9090E1DC2ACA40F49F6F9031DF94810E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recycled in North America,</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">is equal to or greater than 80 percent (as certified by the manufacturer, in such form or manner as prescribed by the Secretary). For purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii), the term <quote>free trade agreement</quote> means an international agreement approved by Congress that eliminates duties and other restrictive regulations of commerce on substantially all the trade between the United States and one or more other countries.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55EC003C28FA42859F9DEA5CA9748601"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Battery components</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit shall be allowed under this section with respect to any vehicle unless, with respect to the battery from which the electric motor of such vehicle draws electricity, all of the components contained in such battery were manufactured or assembled in North America (as certified by the manufacturer, in such form or manner as prescribed by the Secretary).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5889D0999292427D93C677ECB8827026"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Restriction on foreign entities of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit shall be allowed under this section which respect to any vehicle placed in service after December 31, 2024, if any of the applicable critical minerals contained in the battery of such vehicle (as described in paragraph (1)) were extracted, processed, or recycled by a foreign entity of concern (as defined in section 40207(a)(5) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18741">42 U.S.C. 18741(a)(5)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H1087C0DBA4B44B299D6D693381D514A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D(d)</external-xref> is amended by striking paragraph (7).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB636C19D0D3E4EB0B6601D506EAB05FB" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Transfer of credit repealed</header><paragraph id="HC2BCFB0EE2D94A9780436300A202A3DE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D</external-xref> is amended by striking subsection (g).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBECF46F3EB024777831B9B0419FB2364" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments reversed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D(f)</external-xref> is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H45094F370BA144AE998EAE893A77C248" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8396F16753AB44CAAA4CD2B4BF32DF3B" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subsection id="HBE6EB8C33D7040868FC80105E2A601A0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Property used by tax-exempt entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a vehicle the use of which is described in paragraph (3) or (4) of section 50(b) and which is not subject to a lease, the person who sold such vehicle to the person or entity using such vehicle shall be treated as the taxpayer that placed such vehicle in service, but only if such person clearly discloses to such person or entity in a document the amount of any credit allowable under subsection (a) with respect to such vehicle (determined without regard to subsection (c)). For purposes of subsection (c), property to which this paragraph applies shall be treated as of a character subject to an allowance for depreciation.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>, and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74209E6C549648FE83906C571A19F5A9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking <quote>, including any vehicle with respect to which the taxpayer elects the application of subsection (g)</quote>. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C65C95B563A4552BF4A425084738A95" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reinstatement of limitation on number of vehicles eligible for credit</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D</external-xref> is amended by inserting after subsection (f) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H006123B5312648D1B18E93D3B6BC2698" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><subsection id="H218DAF5B27F0461F84D1E714E8CA28E6" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation on number of new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicles eligible for credit</header><paragraph id="H5D584B3DE30E488CA3806D9B11E3E775" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicle sold during the phaseout period, only the applicable percentage of the credit otherwise allowable under subsection (a) shall be allowed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19D198011F4E47AD851A9A4358AD1DBE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Phaseout period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the phaseout period is the period beginning with the second calendar quarter following the calendar quarter which includes the first date on which the number of new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicles manufactured by the manufacturer of the vehicle referred to in paragraph (1) sold for use in the United States after December 31, 2009, is at least 200,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B4B3707DD374CD3A9D0670333341AC3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the applicable percentage is—</text><subparagraph id="H20F733E2D9554CC1B188712205F2C7FF" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>50 percent for the first 2 calendar quarters of the phaseout period, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5095C9F31B454EE7BB3FC139E107D446" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>25 percent for the 3rd and 4th calendar quarters of the phaseout period, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H397A72D8AD7B4C4797F64ED61EFAC2B1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>0 percent for each calendar quarter thereafter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3631E22613FC404F95CF9FA9CB30EDD1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Controlled groups</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rules similar to the rules of section 30B(f)(4) shall apply for purposes of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H0F1A9E342AB64FA492A80760DC55926D" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination repealed</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">Section 30D</external-xref> is amended by striking subsection (h).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9827EBFE28174EBFBC8EF9541E61FAB9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Additional conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H7115273F02CC455A91987AA3CFEC2B51"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The heading of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">section 30D</external-xref> is amended by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">clean vehicle credit</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">new qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicles</header-in-text></quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BD8FCD306E0482B888E8D8631CBE943"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30B">Section 30B(h)(8)</external-xref> is amended by inserting <quote>, except that no benefit shall be recaptured if such property ceases to be eligible for such credit by reason of conversion to a qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicle</quote>, before the period at the end.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8432A40880E94FB18C9FD511B5FA178B"><enum>(3)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/38">Section 38(b)(30)</external-xref> is amended by striking <quote>clean</quote> and inserting <quote>qualified plug-in electric drive motor</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACC6C82E524E4D5D8B4365BAF63E5AF4"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart B of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by striking the item relating to section 30D and inserting after the item relating to section 30C the following item:</text><toc regeneration="no-regeneration" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><toc-entry level="section"><quote>Sec. 30D. New qualified plug-in electric drive motor vehicles.</quote></toc-entry></toc></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E9C354BF6824925BCFF2787A5F0819B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Gross up repealed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13401 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> is amended by striking subsection (j).</text></subsection><subsection id="H4B9B2AA6979145F2B59E3A22BB9280BA" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Effective dates</header><paragraph id="HFE718BA4790E42A58E548CDE2DA30F39" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided in this subsection or subsection (k), the amendments made by this section shall apply to vehicles placed in service after June 9, 2023. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1467DA9D87141FD949733905C56D722" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final assembly and manufacturer limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by subsections (b) and (f) shall apply to vehicles sold after June 9, 2023. Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, the phaseout period (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/30D">section 30D(g)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by this section) shall be determined by taking into account all vehicles described in section 30D(g) of such Code (as so amended).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE5A885545AC45B299D40E97767FB56E" commented="no"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Transition rule</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (j) (other than the last sentence of subsection (j)(2)), the amendments made by this section shall not apply with respect to any vehicle which is—</text><paragraph id="H00DBA719E6A947219A7B4F16A564F7FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>acquired by the taxpayer pursuant to a written binding contract that was in effect on June 9, 2023, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDE354CC8C2340E8B0C7337D293B9E43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>placed in service before June 9, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8239DAE60B54B838B062991013DBB10"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Coordination with provisions which have not taken effect</header><paragraph id="H3DB9919DBC6B4A258E7635B05C83912A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Transfer of credit</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (k)(4) of section 13401 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, the amendments made by subsection (g) of such section shall not apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19D5BECD04DD47DBB1610EB3C878FC99"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Per vehicle dollar limits and related requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (k)(3) of section 13401 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, the amendments made by subsection (a) of such section shall not apply unless the guidance referred to in such subsection (k)(3) is issued on or before June 9, 2023.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H932FFBC5346A462D8403547C3C41CC4D"><enum>304.</enum><header>Repeal of credit for previously-owned clean vehicles</header><subsection id="H9365182E1C3044169BDA3EE4CF77B874"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart A of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by striking section 25E (and by striking the item relating to such section in the table of sections for such subpart).</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D0B8F5747A742E586A2E92A1D8720FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6213">Section 6213(g)(2)</external-xref> is amended—</text><paragraph id="H526FEC7B731C4C1BAFA73A897949DE3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (T), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2510AE4E65B547F9BE0CFE4202AA80C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (U), and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2E576987AAC4BDAA8E95A7AAAE2A23C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (V) as subparagraph (U). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08FF91EB95354E32ACE4BF13261EA73F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to vehicles acquired after June 9, 2023.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFE99F336781E4BC6B35C3D66D12BD70A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transition rule</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (c), the amendments made by this section shall not apply with respect to any vehicle which is—</text><paragraph id="H444C5121CC5D4E129E27803A90D61950"><enum>(1)</enum><text>acquired by the taxpayer pursuant to a written binding contract that was in effect on June 9, 2023, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F7E175B913C4B948B91ED6B2E8585C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">placed in service before June 9, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H72C3335345654A669CC68CAE611EC826"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination with provisions which have not taken effect</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (c)(2) of section 13402 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, the amendments made by subsection (b) of such section shall not apply.</text></subsection></section><section id="HEA850133F661416B84B042F462FB1CAF"><enum>305.</enum><header>Repeal of credit for qualified commercial clean vehicles</header><subsection id="H6CB385B14DE840BBA5A7AE297474E35D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> is amended by striking section 45W (and by striking the item relating to such section in the table of sections for such subpart).</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD84318BAC5A4E229DCC4E73F9E1D738"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="HA18EA5ADB7624E72B75C11747E150B29"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 38(b), as amended by the preceding provisions of this section, is amended by striking paragraph (37) and redesignating paragraphs (38) through (40) as paragraphs (37) through (39), respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE6898016DAA41D4BC360BB96E994503"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6213(g)(2), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H69A461B58BC646E4B78F6EB2EF4DD944"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (S), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F9F5B2E22534910A89EA987EFAD41C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (T), by striking <quote>, and</quote> and inserting a period, and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED65CE05D6D34F0FAC485A89375581C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (U).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H83A61FE7950D4C179C3305FBBB733C15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 6417(b), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act, is amended by striking paragraph (6) and redesignating paragraphs (7) through (10) as paragraphs (6) through (9), respectively. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A8EB00A94BC4E76B80738DE9293E400" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply to vehicles acquired after June 9, 2023.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5977A0E77BC64042B28F2BBFDAA39D99" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transition rule</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (c), the amendments made by this section shall not apply with respect to any vehicle which is—</text><paragraph id="HED4EEF8BEDA04AB992718FCF1D3D60D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>acquired by the taxpayer pursuant to a written binding contract that was in effect on June 9, 2023, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H250241C7DCB346108D7BF6FA95587C16"><enum>(2)</enum><text>placed in service before June 9, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

