<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0CD42A3C890D4366862B7492B6FB56CE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6181 IH: U.S.-ASEAN Center Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6181</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of State to support the establishment of an ASEAN Center in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3FC8A27DFF464974BB1EA7A517FA162C" style="OLC"><section id="H1B3F32DD35624983B400D5DA75298E98" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>U.S.-ASEAN Center Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB98E4FFBE5B2435DBA88C41603D1B6A5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of an ASEAN Center</header><subsection id="H7A76C3D850B944A2ADF6EAE108DE7D7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Defined term</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>ASEAN</quote> means the Association of Southeast Asian Nations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB1F90596C61648F4BD1EA162B6321C60"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of State is authorized to enter into a public-private partnership for the purposes of establishing a US-ASEAN Center in the United States to support United States economic and cultural engagement with Southeast Asia.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE5B078864899405799DA55F785B9B850"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, Secretary of State and the US-ASEAN Center established pursuant to subsection (b) may—</text><paragraph id="HB2C360AACB1B48CC98F8C2FC49E7FDFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide grants for research to support and elevate the importance of the US-ASEAN partnership;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED6723B685B14863A576ED87894B21A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate activities to strengthen US-ASEAN trade and investment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63CB8F268E4541D380561ADDEC90EFB8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>expand economic and technological relationships between ASEAN countries and the United States into new areas of cooperation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE5D0B549A4B4BAFB7B76F31F2DFBC16"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide training to United States citizens and citizens of ASEAN countries that improve people-to-people ties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DE14CD3A93C4A96A6B8DD25F28A2F22"><enum>(5)</enum><text>develop educational programs to increase awareness for the United States and ASEAN countries on the importance of relations between the United States and ASEAN countries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99DA208CC6C8466C9C5046AAF2EA02DE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>carry out other activities the Secretary considers necessary to strengthen ties between the United States and ASEAN countries and achieve the objectives of the US-ASEAN Center.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E8D3E9D66254353AC8AE91A1D16EF5D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>This section may be carried out using any amounts authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of State, including amounts authorized to carry out chapter 4 of part II of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2346">22 U.S.C. 2346 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF12026C779024FFF80773B117D0E2413"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Parameters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary shall ensure that the activities of the US-ASEAN Center do not duplicate current lines of effort being conducted by the United States Government or its grantees.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

