<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF395607A8CDF43E38567B45EF4EFCFAE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2595 IH: Forfeiture Funds Expenditure Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2595</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require State and local law enforcement agencies receiving forfeited funds and property to report how such funds and property are used, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD3F7C24B979B4DC1899D8A7BD3555616" style="OLC"><section id="H372CFD45D21944D8B5C976BBDE02DDED" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Forfeiture Funds Expenditure Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H62EAAC8471A0435282EF10844D1C0533"><enum>2.</enum><header>State and local reporting</header><subsection id="H6C698E9258D74ED29B9E3047775F133F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Department of Justice Assets Forfeiture Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 524(c)(6) of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7999D7EEC76140F8B6BE57A79FCDE677" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HF21CB4D3D13C4C329589C9E492052FFA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Not later than January 1, 2024, and every 6 months thereafter, each State and local law enforcement agency with the authority to prosecute a criminal case that receives property or funds under this subsection, section 511(e) of the Controlled Substances Act, or section 981(e) of title 18, shall transmit to Congress a report detailing each receipt of property or funds and the activity to which the property or funds were directed for the previous fiscal year, in the case of the first report, and for the previous 6-month period, in the case of each subsequent report. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H3AB29D8C5F254D45ABEC48B10E78DBF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Controlled substances forfeitures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 511(e) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/881">21 U.S.C. 881</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0D3995AED05C4CE68B053CCE12F86E8C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HB1FD60EAD6464B268D04223B340604B2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State and local law enforcement agency with the authority to prosecute a criminal case that receives property or funds under this subsection shall include in the report transmitted to Congress under section 524(c)(6)(E) of title 28, United States Code, information detailing each receipt of property or funds and the activity to which the property or funds were directed.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H02AAC7647DDF4E57B4E7747D9520A00E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Civil forfeitures</header><text>Section 981 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HCB6C4BBE9DEC40379968066AEC50AB9E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H575FBAE7B0D24CBC8D807F6921D37694"><enum>(l)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State and local law enforcement agency with the authority to prosecute a criminal case that receives property or funds under subsection (e) shall include in the report transmitted to Congress under section 524(c)(6)(E) of title 28 information detailing each receipt of property or funds and the activity to which the property or funds were directed.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

