<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC942136C241C45308CE5BBCFB1117F7E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 2441 IH: Servicemembers and Veterans Empowerment and Support Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2441</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to expand health care and benefits from the Department of Veterans Affairs for military sexual trauma, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE780C312FC3240A686BB3352C6A04662" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HFAB4575A67694DA4BC7F3F596D9BDCAF" changed="not-changed"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H3F37161552FC4EEF8394ED968EEEF07A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Servicemembers and Veterans Empowerment and Support Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H58472EC185EE45BFA473768E57DF8E88" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="HFAB4575A67694DA4BC7F3F596D9BDCAF">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="H03B40B26E38749E2AD20F82BDB60638C">TITLE I—Defining military sexual trauma</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H8008D251FFE54C73BAF3BB147793A9EA">Sec. 101. Report on military sexual trauma in the digital age.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HBD93AC49CF6E42889006B23713D06F3B">TITLE II—Disability compensation and claims processing</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H5F312B1B623F4949B1E1095FFE038D62">Sec. 201. Definition of military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HB3121136D9464E4EB6AD8DA9EAB34E7C">Sec. 202. Conforming changes relating to specialized teams to evaluate claims involving military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H93E6E61DE7DB4511A3A3F181AE2BCFAD">Sec. 203. Evaluation of claims involving military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H4A3D451AA6294E0893A73C5C3669FC3A">Sec. 204. Choice of location of Department of Veterans Affairs medical examination for assessment of claims for compensation relating to disability resulting from military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HAC41A008F2EA46F88D1299C284AB52AE">Sec. 205. Communications from the Department of Veterans Affairs to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF2BAC1F1DB254A36A560476291857E97">Sec. 206. Study on training and processing relating to claims for disability compensation relating to military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HB1920275AE8F48668A9CCBE43931933F">Sec. 207. Annual special focus review of claims for disability compensation for disabilities relating to military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HCEC6408BF3D246F39B439F0822C46A4D">TITLE III—Access to Health Care</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HAF7DFEDEBD26411DB18EC722192F30E7">Sec. 301. Expansion of eligibility for counseling and treatment for military sexual trauma to include all former members of the reserve components of the Armed Forces.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H68CAD3AEA15244DE8FAB0E5710E861F7">Sec. 302. Connection to Veterans Health Administration when a disability claim related to military sexual trauma is submitted to Veterans Benefits Administration.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HD3790436ECA5402C9C78E8751977A732">Sec. 303. Pilot program for interim access to mental health care for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H891CD39151B34A64BB3E54C2CFAAF329">Sec. 304. Comptroller General study on access to care from Department of Veterans Affairs for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><title id="H03B40B26E38749E2AD20F82BDB60638C" changed="not-changed"><enum>I</enum><header>Defining military sexual trauma</header><section id="H8008D251FFE54C73BAF3BB147793A9EA" changed="not-changed"><enum>101.</enum><header>Report on military sexual trauma in the digital age</header><subsection id="H6CD144A5AB874030A554A0C9E003CBBB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on military sexual trauma in the digital age.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB69DB948CA334FB187E456CED6AB8CE2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H45E0A143947D4D2596BC4849067E59D7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A comprehensive evaluation and assessment of current Department of Veterans Affairs statutes, regulations, and agency guidance relating to military sexual trauma for the purposes of access to health care under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, and compensation under chapter 11 of such title to identify—</text><subparagraph id="H589992E0E3FE4D6CAA4171C33FCCD076"><enum>(A)</enum><text>gaps in coverage for health care and compensation eligibility relating to military sexual trauma involving online or other technological communications; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5427AB8E9634C208C8437D8BDF84F0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the feasibility and advisability of expanding health care and compensation for trauma that is nonsexual in nature involving online or other technological communications. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3E350229AA543A596C89B3E2A0230DD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recommendations for revising statutes, regulations, and agency guidance in response to the evaluation and assessment under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8B44010855445CAB6EC4783546D3742" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall consult veterans service organizations and such other stakeholders as the Secretary considers relevant and appropriate. </text></subsection><subsection id="H069F814F620A45E49D6133416DFB9BC2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Military sexual trauma defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>military sexual trauma</term>—</text><paragraph id="H167C13A5B8CF4F758C3AD701C40A008A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to eligibility for health care, has the meaning given such term in section 1720D(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 301; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA7BFF7EAB0419E95370020327D83DE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to eligibility for compensation, has the meaning given such term in section 1169(i) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 203(a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HBD93AC49CF6E42889006B23713D06F3B" style="OLC" changed="not-changed"><enum>II</enum><header>Disability compensation and claims processing</header><section id="H5F312B1B623F4949B1E1095FFE038D62" changed="not-changed"><enum>201.</enum><header>Definition of military sexual trauma</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title, the term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1169(i) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 203(a).</text></section><section id="HB3121136D9464E4EB6AD8DA9EAB34E7C" changed="not-changed"><enum>202.</enum><header>Conforming changes relating to specialized teams to evaluate claims involving military sexual trauma</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (d) of section 1166 of title 38, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B834FEE3C1844B1A71CB9E3335ABDDC"><subsection changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H88FDA5DD90344983A269B74D6A9EB6D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <term>covered mental health condition</term> and <term>military sexual trauma</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 1169(i) of this title.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H93E6E61DE7DB4511A3A3F181AE2BCFAD" changed="not-changed"><enum>203.</enum><header>Evaluation of claims involving military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="H08075359E90C4C288230F39E432FB7A4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter VI of chapter 11 of such title is amended by inserting after section 1166 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55AAA088A8B34F7FA9EA29305A23C587" changed="not-changed"><section id="H000D54B31A8643FAB84EFAB6C8FF6BBB" changed="not-changed"><enum>1166A.</enum><header>Evaluation of claims involving military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="HCF6579163AFE4894B28C662E3095C73F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF97A1B3563754C6586B9DC91FFE4B292" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of any veteran who claims that a covered mental health condition based on military sexual trauma was incurred in or aggravated by active military, naval, air, or space service, the Secretary shall consider the following:</text><subparagraph changed="not-changed" id="H54B7B9C551EA40BD91A662B99D8BD613" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A diagnosis of such mental health condition by a mental health professional.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph changed="not-changed" indent="up1" id="HB8553DE25CC944BC918C1077915C2284"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A link, established by medical evidence, between current symptoms and a military sexual trauma.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph changed="not-changed" indent="up1" id="H3F3875F0ACB3475D91765A124D71F0EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Credible supporting evidence, in accordance with subsections (b) and (c) that the claimed military sexual trauma occurred.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="HD7F81239E4CB49DDA28AC8C3EDE3B978" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The reasons for granting or denying service-connection in each case described in paragraph (1) shall be recorded in full. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2EE8DF32ADD941DB82B6ECBCEE15BD24" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nonmilitary sources of evidence</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7C828278088041C08CFAA775280307FB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For purposes of subsection (a), evidence from sources other than official records of the Department of Defense regarding the veteran's active military, naval, air, or space service may corroborate the veteran's account of the trauma. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CA3CF5FC11B4524A60CBBC94210F781" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Examples of evidence described in paragraph (1) include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8F6F20C0B8DA44FAAF04C7A68E4A1095" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Records from law enforcement authorities, rape crisis centers, mental health counseling centers, hospitals, and physicians.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B1BE8AFB95A4B4594EA3076A88DC64E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Pregnancy tests and tests for sexually transmitted diseases.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H357583476AB64F5AB3510AE8D118D387" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Statements from family members, roommates, other members of the Armed Forces or veterans, and clergy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H90B022F6AEA346E997CD8FE2BDB6E78A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Evidence of behavior changes</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4028CCA4C2E04A19BC83A3CAC34A8532" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For purposes of subsection (a), evidence of a behavior change following military sexual trauma is one type of relevant evidence that may be found in sources described in such subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B6EFD82BC124284B472691A98D73427" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Examples of behavior changes that may be relevant evidence of military sexual trauma include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3609C632C6A448A7B1A531D7F0135C88" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A request for a transfer to another military duty assignment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41444E6462E6432695B5535D779BA27F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Deterioration in work performance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE755BE055B494D8FA92BC7E6D134C221" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Substance abuse or substance use disorder.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4B0CE8C0AAE4150A07B2642436E434E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Episodes of depression, panic attacks, or anxiety without an identifiable cause.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D9FE12FC6E549349E3EF6AB7FBC723F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Unexplained economic or social behavior changes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4BDE78D7FA2C4D8CA7277D0AC8F9DA0B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity To supply evidence</header><text>The Secretary may not deny a claim of a veteran for compensation under this chapter for a covered mental health condition that is based on military sexual trauma without first—</text><paragraph id="HF542D7C9753A454A823719511CCAA981" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advising the veteran that evidence described in subsections (b) and (c) may constitute credible corroborating evidence of the military sexual trauma; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F922C099948487099FB1B36FE55235A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allowing the veteran an opportunity to furnish such corroborating evidence or advise the Secretary of potential sources of such evidence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF02278123ED54BB098DB3B370D29D86C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Review of evidence</header><text>In reviewing a claim for compensation described in subsection (a)(1), for any evidence identified as part of such claim that is described in subsection (b) or (c), the Secretary shall submit such evidence to such medical or mental health professional as the Secretary considers appropriate, including clinical and counseling experts employed by the Department, to obtain an opinion as to whether the evidence indicates that a military sexual trauma occurred.</text></subsection><subsection id="H02B5EEE59D7646829C02A04059B92C73" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Point of contact</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that each document provided to a veteran relating to a claim for compensation described in subsection (a)(1) includes contact information for an appropriate point of contact with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H730908DE982D4F3F98C9F928E254AD4A" changed="not-changed" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Specialized teams</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that all claims for compensation described in subsection (a)(1) are reviewed and processed by a specialized team established under section 1166 of this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7ACD586B151D4519BB8BA0E285662C02" changed="not-changed"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding application to nonsexual personal assault</header><text>The Secretary shall not construe this section as supplanting the standard of proof or evidence required for claims for posttraumatic stress disorder based on nonsexual personal assault, which the Secretary shall continue to define in regulation. </text></subsection><subsection id="H261838A071AB43D099F171C85428E47F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section: </text><paragraph id="H521EAE6A11D4409D832A42BDC5DAA4AB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered mental health condition</term> means post-traumatic stress disorder, anxiety, depression, or other mental health diagnosis that the Secretary determines to be related to military sexual trauma and which may be service-connected under section 1110 of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph changed="not-changed" id="H2FB25552A59C40B984C9BDCBBBDA8578"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>mental health professional</term> means a provider in the field of mental health who meets the credential, licensure, education, and training requirements established by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20B0F0953D84401A93C409F6BF33795D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> means, with respect to a veteran, a physical assault of a sexual nature, battery of a sexual nature, or sexual harassment that occurred while the veteran was serving in the active military, naval, air, or space service.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H996018BDCAC048F499C3C75A529B41F6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall implement, with input from the veteran community, an informative outreach program for veterans regarding the standard of proof for evaluation of claims relating to military sexual trauma, including requirements for a medical examination and opinion.</text></subsection><subsection id="H61CF84753650463CB2CC655A500A8D3C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1166 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H74707F49CA0349FE9C3FAE1418D2325E" changed="not-changed"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration" changed="not-changed"><toc-entry level="section" changed="not-changed">1166A. Evaluation of claims involving military sexual trauma.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H4A3D451AA6294E0893A73C5C3669FC3A" changed="not-changed"><enum>204.</enum><header>Choice of location of Department of Veterans Affairs medical examination for assessment of claims for compensation relating to disability resulting from military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="H13020297E27B433F9B6E5E9C98067E05" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1165 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HDDB1C768EBDE4257A77AEE94F4290ACF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the section heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text style="USC" level="section">and location of medical examination</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text style="USC" level="section">examiner</header-in-text></quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B5410F0B868429994AA25D060C7E9AB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>a physical assault of a sexual nature, battery of a sexual nature, or sexual harassment</quote> and inserting <quote>military sexual trauma (as defined in section 1166A(i) of this title)</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDC0FFAEA9F3449CBDF10CCBDD7969A9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA398EC6B8E04B4493E1C7DBFAE3EBF2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection (c): </text><quoted-block id="H26C46B7EFFD640D396622F0E8E686342" style="USC" act-name="" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="H7039A1FC33B94004B2D6478FABAEF418" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Choice of examination location</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA3F4F55B929943969579CEFD6330CA5C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that a veteran who requires a medical examination in support of a claim described in subsection (a) may request that the medical examination take place at a medical facility of the Department by a qualified employee of the Department rather than at a location designated by a Department contractor that performs such examinations on behalf of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43DD113089234466968B7F492777C821" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary— </text><subparagraph id="H9FAE1D71D1874DEA8FD1F6B5A5A6D1BD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall grant any request under paragraph (1) if a medical facility of the Department is available not further than 100 miles from the veteran’s home; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF334E16CEBD149F9BFDE7D2A87065EAF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may not issue a decision on a claim described in such paragraph before the requested examination is completed, or notice is provided per paragraph (c)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F6E702DD5B345A7B871577630A01865" commented="no" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>If a medical facility of the Department is not available within 100 miles of the veteran’s home, the Secretary shall notify the veteran and provide the veteran the opportunity—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H507F6BC5424848298C85D3F0575CF675" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to have the examination completed by a contractor of the Department; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0A433019012E49FFA4B6BCFD4A999002" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to complete the examination at a medical facility further than 100 miles from the veteran’s home. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H701F7851EC204F1B9288CA48A952BE81" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 11 of such title is amended by striking the item relating to section 1165 and inserting the following new item: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H704145486EA44077B38F9D1C63BBD88E" changed="not-changed"><toc changed="not-changed"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off" changed="not-changed">1165. Choice of sex of medical examiner and location of medical examination for certain disabilities.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HAC41A008F2EA46F88D1299C284AB52AE" changed="not-changed"><enum>205.</enum><header>Communications from the Department of Veterans Affairs to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="HBF072B1C2DDD4F168F25045D4439311C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review board</header><paragraph id="HAFEAB3EA89344362BFFE560BCA1F607C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a board to review correspondence relating to military sexual trauma. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4769A33F49984A609FE002B13CD94346" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The board established under paragraph (1) shall be composed of members who shall be appointed by the Secretary from among employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs who are experts in military sexual trauma and mental health, of whom—</text><subparagraph id="H5FECF2ACBF65405BB174D7402597A557" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one or more shall be appointed from among mental health providers of the Veterans Health Administration; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1602146643144DDCB32F9591E8439870" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one or more shall be appointed from among experts on sexual assault and sexual harassment of the Veterans Benefits Administration; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2975BFE8C044477FA6170AE1988EACB3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>one or more shall be appointed from among experts on sexual assault and sexual harassment of the Board of Veterans’ Appeals. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94729695E4BC414982DEE7477AC3FCA4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The board established under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4E2E745D5596447E86F7C570C6C5484C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review standard correspondence, which may include templates for notices under sections 5103, 5104, 5104B, and 7104 of title 38, United States Code, from the Department to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma for sensitivity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CB63CE1C4714CCE89858510817CEFDD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that the correspondence— </text><clause id="H742FB8D3299345BF8F7E088D3480DD4E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>treats such individuals with dignity and respect; and </text></clause><clause id="H4A1A6722F39F469E9F7FA1C8C676EB5D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not re-traumatize such individuals.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0606AFD611C418CADDE51F35228B6E0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Individual who has experienced military sexual trauma defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>individual who has experienced military sexual trauma</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC90067312101454FA80AEF5AFCBB1E8F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a veteran who has filed a claim for compensation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, relating to military sexual trauma; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H191AEEAF1CAE44F8B00C8CC57C86AB58" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a veteran who has been awarded compensation under such chapter relating to military sexual trauma; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC34AA5DB8334478285DED1C45167652E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a former member of the Armed Forces or a veteran who is receiving care from the Department relating to military sexual trauma. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB7447C24F7CB427FAF1A124CC025C881" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of certain written communications to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HDF3D943B82E0414EA67E0CF2BD89351E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice to claimants of required information and evidence</header><text>Section 5103 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block id="HAAB57094F22348DAA05E4ED0F68E0CF1" style="USC" act-name="" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="HFA20031D01EC490BA7814ECEC356C1F4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Written communications to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H23A8EF1E1DA34CD29EEB2D6C1EEC2F6D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma includes contact information for each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HFD4179EC64C6444D97FF4BBAA60AC2F7" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HAE2CBD976B7446C8B466B9D531B83F67" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H29362C63F10E46BDA6AE28915A01A7F8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H6A4C0E25D43F4D1686CD90BEACB94F0A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The facility of the Veterans Health Administration closest to where the individual resides.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="HCC73148F60824320B02E1DA7546A0326" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In this subsection: </text><subparagraph id="HC4B209EB807D415292FD883BD4AF6B3A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>individual who has experienced military sexual trauma</term> means—</text><clause id="HBAF133549B184AC79CA0B56D7BAFE155" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a veteran who has filed a claim for compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma;</text></clause><clause id="HE70E99693D42449B8895E89A367D0AD4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran who has been awarded compensation under such chapter relating to military sexual trauma; or </text></clause><clause id="H289C97A1C0734A5E8812CC61B25061C3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a former member of the Armed Forces or a veteran who is receiving care from the Department relating to military sexual trauma. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F760C7413E540EFBA8873A57E2C25BC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1166A(i) of this title. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AB370788E4F463E864B9FF1EC8CD334" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H60105233FAE440D3B8A56701B1E08AEA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Decisions and notices of decisions</header><text>Section 5104 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block id="H7EF2E877E4F54CB095CAD4E464E7701F" style="USC" act-name="" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="HA5C18D4F75644F91AE72B37DA8B4BFCB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H400FDF24DDF7461E96CDB0419C82AEC6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma includes contact information for each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H80AB1993009B4CFB831211349173A30B" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H10201479A8FC4F939054D40903704E96" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HE55C48C572774113AABC2FC8FD95C78B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The facility of the Veterans Health Administration closest to where the individual resides.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H6D84E40638404F3086466B1017000A2D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma that includes notification of an award of compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma includes—</text><subparagraph id="H4E94CFD77F674AEC8F494AE75A16BEB3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text> the contact information described in paragraph (1); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D41D6AD1CA644969EB0F951D473C3DA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the contact information for the military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H56413C1E1C7D4D708E96F5A631C05A31" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In this subsection: </text><subparagraph id="H646B8C03FDC14464B9AA07EB910A28DB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>individual who has experienced military sexual trauma</term> means—</text><clause id="HCCA249401C7048718DB5F23D27F41B21" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a veteran who has filed a claim for compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma;</text></clause><clause id="H37A757CA546C45EFB857605E02AB3460" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran who has been awarded compensation under such chapter relating to military sexual trauma; or </text></clause><clause id="H66BC91B90BE3432B9EE5F9B3FE09033F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a former member of the Armed Forces or a veteran who is receiving care from the Department relating to military sexual trauma. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBBB04229D1A43EDA12C39AD2B597EE5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1166A(i) of this title. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4A7FBFC99D64A7E830743D41CA0DE11" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HB2B3A3C9BC0D484D8D7151DC4D5D2D9B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Higher-level review by the agency of original jurisdiction</header><text>Section 5104B of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="H9097FA5F8CE74B4AAF0949A1A2F946CB" style="USC" act-name="" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="HF450D4DB3A3D4A68B30315CA07131FA5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Written communications to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5810CCB64E3D43CABE4C39A1B2FE0009" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma includes contact information for each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8191428A0F304A4DBAD1D554E4EBEA4F" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H839EA6D12E95489B84C7584C25D09C4D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H68AB00E7DFAF4EA7834E148A8D443416" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The facility of the Veterans Health Administration closest to where the individual resides.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H6B83EEBF91A1437DBC665FEA08D3B66A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma that includes notification of an award of compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma includes—</text><subparagraph id="H5403A03D7A284B1D9AF9C04888DE479B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text> the contact information described in paragraph (1); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF72832231F6D46308EB92270153C7CF1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the contact information for the military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H503520F9A5174412AC7ACDDE5D2BAF2A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In this subsection: </text><subparagraph id="H13E2D35908614C428371EBDE90BD789C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>individual who has experienced military sexual trauma</term> means—</text><clause id="H67C30BDE5A824DE1A42249A4984C82A9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a veteran who has filed a claim for compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma;</text></clause><clause id="HD2D51FCAAE754E09B94EE4E4D760FD0A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran who has been awarded compensation under such chapter relating to military sexual trauma; or </text></clause><clause id="H2DE7880C90F4450F83AA7A942C39A5E8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a former member of the Armed Forces or a veteran who is receiving care from the Department relating to military sexual trauma. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3A853E7C4D74DD8AF09CE6FFB3903FE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1166A(i) of this title. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EC66554EC33416EBA6722411926FE7B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HA1A7E3C57FB844AD8153CE72B6D75A47" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Board of Veterans’ Appeals</header><text>Section 7104 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block id="H4C8B28828E8742A6A820FDC3CFE6E092" changed="not-changed" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="USC" act-name=""><subsection id="H723533D199B74E7DB45FF09340278D37" changed="not-changed"><enum>(g)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H68E7989874964A628B9D08AA138E0055" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma includes contact information for each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8F3B224BB6B34AB1AE231B12F8B7C5DB" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H0481D3BE5D4A4440B773B9BDAACD3BD0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H9F2D784D9FB2419BA00EEF61E7DDCB45" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The facility of the Veterans Health Administration closest to where the individual resides.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H0837E10A0D6E471497C8319861DD5B4A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any written communication under this section from the Department to an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma that includes notification of an award of compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma includes—</text><subparagraph id="HB5D8E030DEFA475999A54BD4FDFE292C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text> the contact information described in paragraph (1); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3505B9DD3FD24C2781D60E2865972EEE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the contact information for the military sexual trauma coordinator of the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" id="H3298DD82A79F44658044EAAF63987EE3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In this subsection: </text><subparagraph id="H84210C7918FA4E65AC9616606A1AD858" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>individual who has experienced military sexual trauma</term> means—</text><clause id="H5E118489B2FE4E27BD410084DD2C7D21" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a veteran who has filed a claim for compensation under chapter 11 of this title relating to military sexual trauma;</text></clause><clause id="H1751C91361924DC48B6A4FF9A717D5BE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran who has been awarded compensation under such chapter relating to military sexual trauma; or </text></clause><clause id="H4C8B565FC8CB4C05B45B0DC44BE55F73" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a former member of the Armed Forces or a veteran who is receiving care from the Department relating to military sexual trauma. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3560DDE4FEEF4F1192168C82891CF7CA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1166A(i) of this title. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD75ABC64B3264BC9B152147A846CD7FE" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF2BAC1F1DB254A36A560476291857E97" changed="not-changed"><enum>206.</enum><header>Study on training and processing relating to claims for disability compensation relating to military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="HDD3E211EC7D44DB3A5D53C2F471E1877" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a study on—</text><paragraph id="H004DB38F5C7741FDBEAA913B8A8B4C76" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the quality of training provided to personnel of the Department of Veterans Affairs who review claims for disability compensation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, for disabilities relating to military sexual trauma; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDE8FE6DC8C54EE9A37F7D9900D69E22" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the quality of the procedures of the Department for reviewing the accuracy of the processing of such claims. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A1464C03FB144B3BEAE2CB448096C6A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study required by subsection (a) shall include the following: </text><paragraph id="H6E22D2CACC5B43BEA5F7746046F0B7BA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>With respect to the quality of training described in paragraph (1) of such subsection: </text><subparagraph id="HD2C6D5A8993B4A5C9F956B515A03EAC7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Whether the Department ensures personnel complete such training on time. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAB5130A98BA4272B44A1ECC0D237A4A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Whether the training has resulted in improvements to the processing of claims described in such subsection and issue-based accuracy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42B49682100B4A2984B0BDFEDCC01198" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such recommendations as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may have for improving the training. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCADDF0D100F144269DC9A2576647AB4A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to the quality of procedures described in paragraph (2) of such subsection: </text><subparagraph id="H90E35544396F43F29DCDF34B1032F678" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Whether the procedures of the Department for reviewing the accuracy of the processing of claims described in such subsection comport with generally accepted statistical methodologies to ensure reasonable accuracy of such reviews.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4333C2FD7E649AF928C883D8A9B3618" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Whether such procedures adequately include mechanisms to correct errors found in such reviews.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F141CD881FE44A4B6969B8B8748BC79" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such recommendations as the Secretary may have for improving such procedures. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H61BC9D7434304BBCA919D45EC8EA8C3D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report detailing the findings of the Secretary with respect to the study conducted under subsection (a). </text></subsection></section><section id="HB1920275AE8F48668A9CCBE43931933F" changed="not-changed"><enum>207.</enum><header>Annual special focus review of claims for disability compensation for disabilities relating to military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="HD93D9D7A26544671B27EAA23310C973A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual special focus review</header><paragraph id="H578E3289E0BD406EA860EFF208E1E894" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each year, the Under Secretary for Benefits of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a special focus review on the accuracy of the processing of claims for disability compensation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, for disabilities relating to military sexual trauma. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99FA23FC1BB942BCB05F351905B320C8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each review conducted under paragraph (1) shall include a review of the following: </text><subparagraph id="H38370FB0A69F4A83A10932CF783F8437" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A statistically significant, nationally representative sample of all claims for benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs relating to military sexual trauma filed during the fiscal year preceding the fiscal year in which the report is submitted.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FA34F8606D249DA9864132E910A1798" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The accuracy of each decision made with respect to each claim described in subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H419D322ED6464013A80F178B711814BA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The types of benefit entitlement errors found, disaggregated by category.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0312673D458E45118C5A6716900FC8F7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Trends from year to year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46C8C1C725574942AD9EA6FDBCFB56BF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Training completion rates for personnel of the Department who process claims described in paragraph (1). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC3C7066CB4443A2A9B80E71F45D3F2D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reprocessing of claims</header><text>If the Under Secretary finds, pursuant to a special focus review conducted under subsection (a)(1), that an error was made with respect to the entitlement of a veteran to a benefit under the laws administered by the Secretary, the Secretary shall return the relevant claim of the veteran to the appropriate regional office of the Department for reprocessing to ensure that the veteran receives an accurate decision with respect to the claim. </text></subsection><subsection id="H18C195320CA44CCE9D732C0ED390D3D5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Re-Reviewing of claims</header><text>If the Under Secretary finds, pursuant to a special focus review conducted under paragraph (1) of subsection (a), that the accuracy rate, under paragraph (2)(B) of such subsection, is less than 90 percent, the Secretary shall conduct a review of each claim for benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs relating to military sexual trauma filed during the fiscal year preceding the fiscal year in which the report is submitted. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA45A6437C1924D6A845F928C9125B90C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Section 5501(b)(2) of the Johnny Isakson and David P. Roe, M.D. Veterans Health Care and Benefits Improvement Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/315">Public Law 116–315</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 5048) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph: </text><quoted-block id="H0A7901D6EB62409EBE13580F790B64DF" style="OLC" act-name="" changed="not-changed"><subparagraph id="HC5E942D8913B4FCA999B4281DFA19BC5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The findings of the most recent special focus review conducted under subsection (a)(1) of section 207 of the <short-title>Servicemembers and Veterans Empowerment and Support Act of 2023</short-title>, including— </text><clause id="H3F9A93BDFAF441C6A6795BD0C5039F93" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the elements under subsection (a)(2) of such section; </text></clause><clause id="HB9F300CB9D034A7C921F45F02937EB97" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of claims returned for reprocessing under subsection (b) of such section; and</text></clause><clause id="H2A719C76054F4498A12CFCF25B2F0021" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of claims described in clause (ii) for which the decision relating to service-connection or entitlement to compensation changed as a result of reprocessing the claim.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAE2A81477AFF4F3DA7E83AA070539AA4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>On the date that the Under Secretary determines, pursuant to special focus reviews conducted under paragraph (1) of subsection (a), that the accuracy rates under paragraph (2)(B) of such subsection have been 95 percent or greater for five consecutive years—</text><paragraph id="H65158CD7428148FD9321F50C57BFF9AC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>subsection (a)(1) shall cease to be in effect; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DEB62ABE36540BA88E5297EFD40DEB7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subparagraph (I) of section 5501(b)(2) of the Johnny Isakson and David P. Roe, M.D. Veterans Health Care and Benefits Improvement Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/315">Public Law 116–315</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 5048), as added by subsection (d), is repealed.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HCEC6408BF3D246F39B439F0822C46A4D" style="OLC" changed="not-changed"><enum>III</enum><header>Access to Health Care</header><section id="HAF7DFEDEBD26411DB18EC722192F30E7" changed="not-changed"><enum>301.</enum><header>Expansion of eligibility for counseling and treatment for military sexual trauma to include all former members of the reserve components of the Armed Forces</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1720D of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H55484F317B264AF785EDCA96E4E5A403" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HF8593A3C107B47EFAFFA8ACEFBAB2C1D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>a physical assault</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>military sexual trauma.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H189B14D4AA854D319A88F2A074F084A1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>was suffered</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>resulted from military sexual trauma.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC69E99730C174B86B19BB9A097007C94" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subsections (f) and (g) and inserting the following new subsection (f):</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8AA38188C8F4351A770163D3BE81A9A" changed="not-changed"><subsection id="HCD28EEC893DE4C8E97671FDE61403EBF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0554D9E2A4EA47D58DE9BDD4C90E0BFA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>former member of the Armed Forces</term> means a person who served on active duty, active duty for training, or inactive duty training, and who was discharged or released therefrom under any condition that is not—</text><subparagraph id="HA09B1735158E4E06B67AADD84809F33A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a discharge by court-martial; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEFD2840B789449090F603D126E0D41F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a discharge subject to a bar to benefits under section 5303 of this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CE5DB773FD14ED6B72F97BB00314D2A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> means, with respect to a member of the Armed Forces or former member of the Armed Forces, a physical assault of a sexual nature, battery of a sexual nature, or sexual harassment which occurred while the member or former member was serving on duty, regardless of duty status or line of duty determination (as that term is used in section 12323 of title 10).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EFFA656D4A34D70BD1672FCC3FEE6F1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>sexual harassment</term> means unsolicited verbal or physical contact of a sexual nature which is threatening in character.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H68CAD3AEA15244DE8FAB0E5710E861F7" changed="not-changed"><enum>302.</enum><header>Connection to Veterans Health Administration when a disability claim related to military sexual trauma is submitted to Veterans Benefits Administration</header><subsection id="H47D9974329DA444A83152EC35A64E973" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 14 days after the date on which a veteran submits a claim for disability compensation to the Veterans Benefits Administration for a disability related to military sexual trauma, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall send a communication to the veteran with the following information:</text><paragraph id="H7CCC27BA6A644397B58707C064F9BD56" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The contact information for the nearest military sexual trauma coordinator for the veteran at the Veterans Benefits Administration and a description of the assistance such coordinator can provide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E11E48EE19F42E3B249D81C2FF3B50B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The contact information for the nearest military sexual trauma coordinator for the veteran at the Veterans Health Administration and a description of the assistance such coordinator can provide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DFDB1D54A5C437F9E3DD565542211EA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The types of services that individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma are eligible to receive from the Department of Veterans Affairs, including the nearest locations and the contact information for such services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B60533598604F60977E7BFE2920DE23" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The contact information for the Veterans Crisis Line established under section 1720F(h) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49588E4BE5CB41518598738EF63DCD1E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Such other information on services, care, or resources for military sexual trauma as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H137FC7D8AA864E6F9000E2D32D263219" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of military sexual trauma</header><text>In this section, the term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1166A(i) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 203(a). </text></subsection></section><section id="HD3790436ECA5402C9C78E8751977A732" changed="not-changed"><enum>303.</enum><header>Pilot program for interim access to mental health care for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="H6E3F5837E5F94F308D39DD2BED0A9A7C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Commencing not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a pilot program to provide intensive outpatient mental health care to current and former members of the Armed Forces who have experienced military sexual trauma when the wait times for residential mental health care from the Department of Veterans Affairs for the individual is more than 14 days.</text></subsection><subsection id="H792B49988C87486981153DD965337DD0" commented="no" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program under subsection (a) for a three-year period beginning on the commencement of the pilot program. </text></subsection><subsection id="HA3C48A7B9CAA49B3B7065EB2D63ECBB6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Locations</header><paragraph id="H549ED33334F147EF8F9329AD8F7BFD7A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program under subsection (a) at not fewer than four Veterans Integrated Service Networks of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H268A5143FDA446D1AA7201D1350C5FBF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of locations</header><text>In selecting locations for the pilot program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall select locations that have the longest wait times for residential mental health care, particularly for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H593F8CC4AF0D4A6185139D3CCC9CA128" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Before commencing the pilot program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall notify the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives of the locations selected for the pilot program. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H943504E027994A37BB57B2F3670D30D1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Types of services</header><text>Subject to the preference of the individual participating in the pilot program under subsection (a) and the capacity of facilities of the Department, the Secretary may provide services under the pilot program via telehealth or in person at a facility of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA53B5EC492CA48F5A57F5CAE3EB68DC3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Participation</header><paragraph id="H278D26656C8848C59405BEB918877B5A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Clarification on participation</header><text>Participation by an individual in the pilot program under subsection (a) shall be during the period in which the individual is waiting for a residential mental health bed opening and shall not disqualify the individual from receiving residential mental health care following their participation in the pilot program. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42B4246D83984D1F9A8F2F15E198092E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Decisions on participation</header><text>Decisions about the participation of an individual in the pilot program and the transition of the individual to residential mental health care shall be made by the individual and their health care provider.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H01CB6A1A2E01439E89EBC1E40F73BA06" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the conclusion of the pilot program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on—</text><paragraph id="HB7B04C50A0EC456484F7E75D940FB44D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>participation in the pilot program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52EB7BA05E044619919A4F253D1BB3F3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>clinical outcomes under the pilot program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA4A1675CB9B424884C49232F6D63108" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such recommendations for continuation or termination of the program as the Secretary may have, including recommendations for legislative or administrative action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB838FA1D6B524330BC31515D6BFA7E6D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definition of military sexual trauma</header><text>In this section, the term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1720D(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 301. </text></subsection></section><section id="H891CD39151B34A64BB3E54C2CFAAF329" changed="not-changed"><enum>304.</enum><header>Comptroller General study on access to care from Department of Veterans Affairs for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma</header><subsection id="H22590B8336DD478DB14B54603E552356" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on access to mental health care at facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBC0BE8DA5BCB4BA88F157795D6068F16" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study conducted under subsection (a) shall include an assessment of the following:</text><paragraph id="H52491EF9B0A843CCA1334097C1645559" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The availability of residential and outpatient services, including wait times and geographic disparities for such services, to include—</text><subparagraph id="H9D1A6F24004A4A2DA5A098075CCAD2F6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the availability of bed spaces in the mental health residential rehabilitation treatment programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma, including an assessment of the suitability of those programs for such individuals and the wait times for services under those programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99F36F17088E4A1E8B44F0E77D844797" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of geographic disparities in access to those programs for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma, including by region and by rural and urban areas;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67C5170B7BF54020BAB5C4B54A6C58EA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment of alternative care options provided when an individual who has experienced military sexual trauma is waiting for residential care, the efficacy of those alternatives, and the satisfaction of patients with those alternatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF373755AB2DC46BE8AA7898A3B67B121" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations for reducing the average wait time for services under those programs to 14 days or less, including by increasing bed space or addressing staffing needs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAC98809D4184B50A5EC267A10D1C0F9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment of the satisfaction of patients with the tracks of those programs specific to military sexual trauma, an assessment of the wait times for services under those tracks, and recommendations for increasing or changing the number of locations for services under those tracks to better meet the needs of individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H43CE19B647634B5F95B697A2BED6D713" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The communication and advertisement by the Department of the care, services, and resources available for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78274B0AE5AD42DCBD3BD5F150399B68" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The barriers to accessing health care related to military sexual trauma at a facility of the Department for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma, including transportation, child care, lack of telehealth, gender-specific barriers, and more.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A4B7ABE0F034CF2AD060B7F553A551A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The extent to which the Secretary has assessed the quality of the training provided to providers of the Department on military sexual trauma and made any adjustments in response to such assessment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82B4549B6CC940F9BBFA304895DE2EB8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The role of Vet Centers in providing care to individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma, including current and former members of the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBE79D1FDE00494392BA5A1F1B599E74" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any current actions by the Secretary to strengthen access to high-quality care for individuals who have experienced military sexual trauma and such recommendations for improving access to care for such individuals as the Comptroller General considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70EB9EC432384263BF4BE22CAABF11E6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to Congress a report on the findings of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDBE9DFE11EC043BF8FEC47D64310A286" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H36B895E4C64C40B187CBBF621FBE6FC6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Military sexual trauma</header><text>The term <term>military sexual trauma</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1720D(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 301. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA298B32BCD254CC8A194A6B2BCC79CD2" changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vet Center</header><text>The term <term>Vet Center</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1712A(h) of title 38, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

