<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5FB437AE743748B193A0D2D739D594D4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2683 IH: VA Flood Preparedness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2683</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to authorize the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to make certain contributions to local authorities to mitigate the risk of flooding on local property adjacent to medical facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B2365B3F946451D887F9B819966B46E" style="OLC"><section id="H91D35B6487AF4F79AAB76107F6F3036B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Flood Preparedness Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HCB1BB7A795EE41A0AB92094E4ED68EA7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Contributions to local authorities to mitigate the risk of flooding on local property adjacent to medical facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H545E5FBDE5E04EDF8B60E3088A1F241C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8108 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, or to mitigate the risk of flooding, including the risk of flooding associated with rising sea levels</quote> before the period at the end. </text></subsection><subsection id="H59A24316DE334EC09E3010609E92F504"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report that includes an assessment of—</text><paragraph id="H6C068EB68E8744848D58EEAE23845D73"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which each medical facility (as such term is defined in section 8101(3) of title 38, United States Code) is at risk of flooding, including the risk of flooding associated with rising sea levels; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70F9A98C69A14549B5903658E9CA5CEA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether additional resources are necessary to address the risk of flooding at each such facility.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

