<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H671C614CC2CE4C24B5E642EF73BDC1D6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4056 IH: Ensuring Medicaid Continuity for Children in Foster Care Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4056</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230613">June 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to ensure that medical assistance is available to children in foster care who are placed in a qualified residential treatment program under the Medicaid program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2DA4AED6F79143C5921CB9B84184AEEB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBC151B963DA145518C84E1355DCDE59F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Medicaid Continuity for Children in Foster Care Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE94164BACB584F3D9BE59DEE4E29C0E1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring that medical assistance is available to children in foster care who are placed in a qualified residential treatment program under the Medicaid program</header> <subsection id="H2DACBBB8947B4112ABAC39CB803475E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1905(a)(31)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(a)(31)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and care and services provided to any individual who is a child in foster care under the responsibility of a State who has been placed, in accordance with the requirements of section 475A(c), in a child care institution that is a qualified residential treatment program (as defined in section 472(k)(4)), but only if payments are being made on behalf of such child under section 472 with respect to which Federal payments may be made under section 474(a)(1) and only if the child continues to be in foster care under the responsibility of a State</quote> after <quote>section 1915(l)</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HADCAD3C4F19E494AA788C70A13B491A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to medical assistance furnished in calendar quarters beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

