<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H274E4C25274E47FB96E4BB6293CD8C4D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6764 IH: Patient Privacy and Caregiver Awareness Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6764</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to modify the HIPAA privacy regulation with respect to the disclosure of certain protected health information.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA0D679E4C2BA41568EB02514780EDF20" style="OLC"><section id="H623475A97B6A45D4B440A9562C885BAA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Patient Privacy and Caregiver Awareness Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC73DBADCF4645E48BC2EF14E677B61A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of HIPAA privacy regulation</header><subsection id="HE537828F54C04C7E8152950563757652"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall revise the HIPAA privacy regulation to require that, if an individual (or a personal representative of the individual or another person responsible for the care of the individual) provides consent in accordance with such regulation for a covered entity to use or disclose any protected health information of the individual that is related to a mental health condition or a substance use disorder—</text><paragraph id="H7D3F40BE0CE04D7D941F33CA3ACB21ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the authorization with respect to such use or disclosure shall have an expiration date that is not less than 2 years after the date on which such consent is provided; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12EECCBF7D1B4946BA32BD426FFFD7D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the covered entity shall provide the individual (and, in the case that such consent is provided by a personal representative or another person responsible for the care of the individual, such personal representative or person so responsible) with written notice of the expiration of such authorization not later than the date that is 30 days before such expiration date.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21952B164CDB4E468DA9FA28324EFD84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H4187375D12EA4E45B6C7B2DFB71899D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>HIPAA privacy regulation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>HIPAA privacy regulation</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1180(b)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320d-9">42 U.S.C. 1320d–9(b)(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89B919AB505E45CB817B59B29C7C2E54"><enum>(2)</enum><header>HIPAA terms</header><text>The terms <term>authorization</term>, <term>covered entity</term>, and <term>protected health information</term> have the meanings given such terms for purposes of the HIPAA privacy regulation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

