<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0E9E9D57666E446C839B747D406AEC39" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5881 IH: Rim of the Valley Corridor Preservation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5881</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To adjust the boundary of the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area to include the Rim of the Valley Corridor, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H01F0F0DD8BC1473C92B0FDD5FFE80209" style="OLC"><section id="H22946E24ECC5479380167816AEDC2421" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rim of the Valley Corridor Preservation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1DF47DED2B3B458CA88CF06286B790C3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="HB346FD659B63445A9DCF7DA56D586F3D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area was authorized as a unit of the National Park System on November 10, 1978.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB6AB7669B294CD39157484636B34514"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Santa Monica Mountains and the Rim of the Valley Corridor include—</text><subparagraph id="H10FB8ADCC233473AA766C1AC48BD66CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>nationally significant resources—</text><clause id="HAB56C3DFE3544FF99DDC350DA27F2D5F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>outstanding examples of geologic history, including the evolution of the Transverse Ranges Province;</text></clause><clause id="HB2764AE82F3D4E64BA3BB6D3C8C7DB07"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a diversity of well-preserved marine and terrestrial paleontological resources; and</text></clause><clause id="HD00D35FEA90C472EA18B4B3E8513BFBB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>high biodiversity, including outstanding examples of native grasslands, coastal sage scrub, chaparral, dry coniferous forests, and alluvian fan sage scrub; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56C8314D575040A6843E70E3DB70AE51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>nationally significant cultural resources that represent a wide range of themes related to human use and settlement in the region—</text><clause id="HE0A3216B7EA649C4B1DAB6257A7BFE13"><enum>(i)</enum><text>high concentrations of archeological resources that provide insight into more than 10,000 years of Native American history; and</text></clause><clause id="H29EC10F8B17B41639B381EC57D2731FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>landmarks that represent topics such as architecture, recreation, and space exploration.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F07815441B44C05AC6CF83873DE1574"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Expanding the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area would provide new opportunities for the National Park Service to serve a broad range of urban communities, including many that are underrepresented in national parks and underserved by State and local parks.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC26D7EC351D54E869C42784FDD356BA8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Boundary adjustment</header><subsection id="H3CF0D19942DF43E2ADD7BDC3C98E6F79"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Boundary adjustment</header><text>Section 507(c) of the National Parks and Recreation Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/460kk">16 U.S.C. 460kk(c)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0EBC0B7FFE20459AAF0EF2A081143986"><paragraph id="H371B5BF5D055405DBB9178700682ADB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Boundary</header><subparagraph id="HE609F7DCE59D492C99E1FA559C5D37D8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The recreation area shall consist of—</text><clause id="HC1C2C2994A0341489DE0CB367A1D5CBE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the land, water, and interests in land and water generally depicted as the recreation area on the map entitled <quote>Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area and Santa Monica Mountains Zone, California, Boundary Map</quote>, numbered 80,047–C, and dated August 2001; and</text></clause><clause id="H7ED4749CCBA74DD4ABD03CC6196A0A8B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the land, water, and interests in land and water, as generally depicted as <quote>Proposed Addition</quote> on the map entitled <quote>Rim of the Valley Unit—Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area</quote>, numbered 638/147,723, and dated April 2023. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5712097909D747BDA6469F8663FBCDBB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Availability of maps</header><text>The maps described in subparagraph (A) shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96D2B95268CE4BCD8CD609F56571C114"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Revisions</header><text>After advising the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives, in writing, of the proposed revision, the Secretary may make minor revisions to the boundaries of the recreation area by publication of a revised drawing or other boundary description in the Federal Register.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HF0D19B4CA11741C1980D077186E18701"><enum>4.</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any land or interest in land acquired by the Secretary of the Interior within the Rim of the Valley Unit shall be administered as part of the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area (referred to in this Act as the <quote>National Recreation Area</quote>) in accordance with the laws (including regulations) applicable to the National Recreation Area.</text></section><section id="H5010E7144E074D209DA710031F24A2D8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Utilities and water resource facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The addition of the Rim of the Valley Unit to the National Recreation Area shall not affect the operation, maintenance, or modification of water resource facilities or public utilities within the Rim of the Valley Unit, except that any utility or water resource facility activities in the Rim of the Valley Unit shall be conducted in a manner that reasonably avoids or reduces the impact of the activities on resources of the Rim of the Valley Unit.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

