<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2633422924604751A0412AA6EA800D0B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1423 IH: 911 Community Crisis Responders Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1423</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, to award grants to States, territories, political subdivisions of States and territories, Tribal governments, and consortia of Tribal governments to establish an unarmed mobile crisis response program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC4A8FE9810614349B2D1133272CCA8E0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC10FD85DFF7D49318E55878E6B2F1ABD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>911 Community Crisis Responders Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0C6673F5B6DC498699051F9E46803B17"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants for unarmed mobile crisis response programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 552 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290ee-7">42 U.S.C. 290ee–7</external-xref>) the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9825A61B9BDA45789FC3DFE07C4877FB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H5F64C2FCB54943EC862F6560DEC4D7DF"><enum>553.</enum><header>Grants for unarmed mobile crisis response programs</header> 
<subsection id="H3954BECE83204F238F2D528ED01AC9CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, may award grants to States, territories, political subdivisions of States and territories (such as counties), Tribal Governments, and consortia of Tribal Governments to establish an unarmed mobile crisis response program under which nonviolent emergency calls are referred to unarmed professional service providers for response, instead of to a law enforcement agency.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H22921772AF1D44089C5F044ED88D8719"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An unarmed mobile crisis response program funded under this section shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE613C0911B6F433FA14662D069F25FA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">dispatch unarmed professional service providers in groups of two or more in a timely manner;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36326ED242DF4D5F8422799B12B58C85"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be capable of providing screening, assessment, de-escalation, trauma-informed culturally competent services, engagement and referrals to community-based treatment providers, and transportation to immediately necessary treatment;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5333C1FCDA7E48EFBD25174B56038FAA" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>when necessary, coordinate with health, housing, or social services; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1AC7B36AFEEA4D7DB3D2757E7EE7EDD0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not be subject to oversight of State, Tribal, or local law enforcement agencies; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9E4F8D27471F43E8A4F1C7084763510A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">clearly outline the scope of calls that must or may be referred to the unarmed mobile crisis response program as first responders.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H68068772BEA04451AC053FD56FE2E484"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant under this section may be used for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA1920134AB7D43C0A76D39832770BC7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hiring unarmed professional service providers and public safety telecommunicators;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B31A4B13D5140EFAC7C1AB501E03F9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">training unarmed professional service providers to respond to emergency calls by identifying, understanding, and responding to signs of mental illnesses, physical disabilities, developmental or intellectual disabilities, and substance use disorders, including by means of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB7B8E6B1D9DC41149B302E4ACAD4CEA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>de-escalation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDEEDC93A56134E668311CFF4FF2A20FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">crisis intervention; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H02C8807D9E6A439D8DF02B28F8E7B65C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">connecting individuals to local service providers, health care providers, housing providers, community-based organizations, and the full range of other available providers and resources, with a focus on culturally competent service providers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA8E09AF575974C118BE45EDA9F293A8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>updating 911 response systems to enable triage between nonviolent 911 calls and those that require a response from law enforcement;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FDDE14DD3064E579AB6EDD8060D1504"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing curriculum to train, and conducting training of, public safety telecommunicators on de-escalation and call processing;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8166CCA2ADD447569E3438B42BD82C0C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating with 9–8–8 call centers to establish a process for dispatching an unarmed mobile crisis response program;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9127362F88A40BBAA5CD54901417111"><enum>(6)</enum><text>building the capacity—</text> <subparagraph id="HBF6B69D5A3CA42E3BA95701DC70162CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to coordinate with local trauma-informed social service providers, health care providers, and community-based organizations; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA16BFE7BEEC1449396265E35CB77DC7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide multilingual and culturally competent services; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51195D5F2E39400A9A633C4466162E54"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collecting data for reports to the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0E5EA24B1474431AA025E91BF9CC9E37"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An applicant seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, including the applicant’s plan to train 911 public safety telecommunicators to determine when a call requires a response from an unarmed mobile crisis response program. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HEF89F52A6ECD409C80033A49B8923608"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports to Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary, on a biannual basis, a report on the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF99E565C6A334FBC95EA0DC8018C924F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of calls placed to 911 that were diverted to the grantee’s unarmed mobile crisis response program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H821EBA5FD6BB4A7FAFD536FD97A55045" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Demographic information on the individuals served by the grantee’s unarmed mobile crisis response program, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, age, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, location, mental illness, physical disabilities, developmental or intellectual disabilities, substance use disorders, and housing status.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE08B6423FD8440679EF5BF4D2DB34F63"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effects of the grantee’s unarmed mobile crisis response program on emergency room visits, hospitalizations, use of ambulances, and involvement of law enforcement in mental health or substance use disorder crises.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14F8997C3BDC46F3BEB9B5AED3521B86"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of the types of events and crises to which the grantee’s unarmed mobile crisis response program responded and the services provided, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3BD56AE4FBDD409AAFE37D6B7C6BCB52"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of individuals successfully transferred to an alternative destination;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBCB0B18ACDDC48D59B26597062A8FCB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the time between notification by a public safety telecommunicator and arrival at the scene by a provider; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H58AF4DCA05134FD2BDB43030ABAFAE38"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the time spent by providers at scene.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40B1C520802B4391A8ED0C6545019E79"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cost analysis of the grantee’s unarmed mobile crisis response program.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H8758AFEF33B4485C97CFDD678F08131D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to the Congress, on a biannual basis, a report on the program under this section, including a summary of the reports submitted by grantees pursuant to subsection (e).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H34E5C455094541CCACD3BB8D077BF596" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>The Secretary may make grants to applicants that do not meet all of the criteria under subsection (b)(1), but applicants that do not meet all such criteria may not receive the full grant amount. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBC644B0243A04F12A628F0752B785729"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H751C7CEC0C984453A0F8F706ED84DB51"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> The term <term>alternative destination</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HED8A868058A94E768866F65961E01D99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any service- or care-providing site other than a hospital emergency department or jail; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H294D56E84C1848CE8D51A770C41092FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes an outpatient clinic, primary care provider’s office, crisis apartment, crisis home, respite home, crisis stabilization center, urgent care facility, and community care center.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8258AB1B0894DF79585107891CCDA1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>nonviolent emergency call</term> means a 911 call that—</text> <subparagraph id="H0204A878A6EA4206A9191E8321260965"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relates to mental health, homelessness, addiction problems, social services, truancy, intellectual and developmental disabilities, or public intoxication; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7B2255E0584A45E6ACD85A4CFCED0FAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not involve obvious violent behavior. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63CB02A4256C4B99A0D6877A4C213645"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>unarmed professional service provider</term> means a professional (which may include a nurse, social worker, emergency medical technician, counselor, community health worker, trauma-informed personnel, social service provider, substance use disorder professional, or peer support specialist) who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H00D4DBF0DD1C40BFB1167AE26E4C9318"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is trained to deal with mental health or substance abuse crises or intellectual and developmental disabilities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6B120E979AB443D689AC6F1AA56346C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not carry a firearm.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H22ACAB2BF5124BF787AC35A00978D964"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No person in the United States shall, on the basis of actual or perceived race, color, religion, national origin, sex (including sexual orientation and gender identity), or disability, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any program or activity funded, in whole or in part, with funds made available under this section.</text> </subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

