<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8398D7D801DE4FC5BC515204FB46C121" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3078 IH: Sunlight in Workplace Harassment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3078</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230502">May 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to require disclosure of payments for settlements of disputes regarding sexual abuse and certain types of harassment and discrimination, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCE291E9AC0AC4A75B58EF2E8C3412A23" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HBD654ACF9D2441A4A2A55866F905D5AF"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sunlight in Workplace Harassment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H643093F7C0E54E718503DA139A99765C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disclosure of payments for settlements of disputes regarding sexual abuse and certain types of harassment and discrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9794AC28D7DE433AAD4700BF574E30DE"><subsection id="H034AA0DF77B04315A31F3B9C2372FCEE"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Disclosure of certain activities regarding settlements of disputes relating to sexual abuse and certain types of harassment or discrimination</header><paragraph id="H901053EE41544D07BDC53BB426EF10A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H6036374028654824BF1CBC854FBAF80B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>covered discrimination</term> means—</text><clause id="H9A1AB1796643428694852FE012922A73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>discrimination described in any of clauses (i) through (vi) of subparagraph (B); or</text></clause><clause id="H9C0625F1AF1F403A8B7499A06E2AD6CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H708B50B53725406FAB363887B5639F7B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a violation of section 704(a) of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e-3">42 U.S.C. 2000e–3(a)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(i) or (B)(vi)(I);</text></subclause><subclause id="H48A28049CFA343C7931A9C2B2313EB5E" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a violation of section 4(d) of the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/623">29 U.S.C. 623(d)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(ii);</text></subclause><subclause id="H1A836044E05C4238942B00C5A7E6A46F" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a violation of subsection (a) or (b) of section 503 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12203">42 U.S.C. 12203</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(iii);</text></subclause><subclause id="H8CAD35933C6D4C09A40B85CE7F70CD15" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a violation of section 207(f) of the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ff-6">42 U.S.C. 2000ff–6(f)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(iv);</text></subclause><subclause id="HF5E29CEB0B334963B40206CA6DF8E29E" indent="up1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a violation of section 4311(b) of title 38, United States Code, that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(v); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H64EF161EC6BF431E9072FDAEEE1257D4" indent="up1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a violation of section 40002(b)(13)(A) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(13)(A)</external-xref>) that—</text><item id="H870E2A96DD584D15BB2E4C77EE3DE29D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may cover retaliation described in a provision specified in any of subclauses (I) through (V); and</text></item><item id="HF37A440012E542D09F75C3685599E1AB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(vi)(II);</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06C52CFDB61840E693FADFAB2BB7DD03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered harassment</term> means harassment that is—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2CE6BBA6B78E4A2FAA1C07CA74587BE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>discrimination because of a characteristic consisting of race, color, religion, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, or national origin, whether the characteristic is actual or perceived, under title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e">42 U.S.C. 2000e et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H962C8FAD4CC1475C87922384B0DCB779"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>discrimination because of actual or perceived age under the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/621">29 U.S.C. 621 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H200A192DD2C441CDA9C776A113C85C12"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>discrimination on the basis of actual or perceived disability under—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H581E92B4FEE6450DB0650EDB2B800E66"><enum>(I)</enum><text>title I of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12111">42 U.S.C. 12111 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E0125305A504646B73FEAD4391686FD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>section 501 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/791">29 U.S.C. 791</external-xref>);</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD6380C06DCD485D9695ADAD6EA81939"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>discrimination because of actual or perceived genetic information under title II of the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ff">42 U.S.C. 2000ff et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H726260B7978E47B8AAF12EEF46B71395"><enum>(v)</enum><text>discrimination on the basis of actual or perceived status concerning service in a uniformed service under section 4311(a) of title 38, United States Code; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B8B95337725415FA710D75A74492AE0"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>discrimination because of a characteristic consisting of sexual orientation or gender identity, whether the characteristic is actual or perceived, under section 40002(b)(13)(A) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(13)(A)</external-xref>);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE416B67B80F74CFDAFFAACBA7D55EDBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>covered issuer</term> means an issuer that is required to file Form 10–K;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75C1D92B1BE147BEB1D9897143C0831C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the term <term>Form 10–K</term> means the form described in section 249.310 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF251D827CEF4AB09E441444525199CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the term <term>gender identity</term> means a characteristic consisting of the gender-related identity, appearance, mannerisms, or other gender-related characteristics of an individual, whether the characteristic is actual or perceived, regardless of the designated sex of the individual at birth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H826814086864428DA4F0493F6BC3DA3D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the term <term>judgment</term> means, with respect to an issuer, a judgment entered against the issuer, whether imposed by a court or through arbitration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3712913EF0134815AB53C2F74F320367"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the term <term>settlement</term> means any commitment or agreement—</text><clause id="HCC0E712127974F19A13623AA18D31793"><enum>(i)</enum><text>without regard to whether the commitment or agreement, as applicable, is in writing; and</text></clause><clause id="HC76A0A8C92D64981A370A1F5B5586BB4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>under which an issuer directly or indirectly—</text><subclause id="HE75D0CDD52AF40FBB3EF9090C9DE98CA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provides to an individual compensation or other consideration because of an allegation that the individual has been a victim of covered harassment, covered discrimination, or sexual abuse; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA8E7577443D44B099047A138BD37CEF4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>establishes conditions that affect the terms of the employment, including by terminating the employment, of the individual with the issuer—</text><item id="HB30CE8D72C0E4C599253508B235286A8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>because of the experience of the individual with, or the participation of the individual in, an alleged act of covered harassment, covered discrimination, or sexual abuse; and</text></item><item id="HEC39290D44CE4DBBAB671A3535D09459"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in exchange for which the individual agrees or commits not to—</text><subitem id="H219F3564E7CA4EF486A3F5B18B6D7C5E"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>bring legal, administrative, or any other type of action against the issuer; or</text></subitem><subitem id="H05C06F680F454A6DB58521E218A48288"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>publicly disclose, for a period of time of any length, any portion of the alleged act described in item (aa) on which the commitment or agreement, as applicable, is based;</text></subitem></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA307D4E6BF5447D38E222F25849DD432"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the term <term>sexual abuse</term> means a nonconsensual sexual act or sexual contact, as such terms are defined in section 2246 of title 18, United States Code, or similar applicable Tribal or State law, including such an act or contact in a circumstance in which the victim lacks capacity to consent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62582F4228BF44399E4E5F05A25DC633"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the term <term>sexual orientation</term> means a characteristic consisting of homosexuality, heterosexuality, or bisexuality, whether the characteristic is actual or perceived.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD02555EE93A4C71A07D0A9FF7D5BE41"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure requirements</header><subparagraph id="HF7021797293F4595B14ED840D1525777"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning in the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this subsection, each covered issuer shall disclose annually on Form 10–K, to shareholders of the covered issuer, and to the public—</text><clause id="HDF175EB0AA1941F68184B51EE59A27BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the time periods, and in the manner, described in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="H0F24B970C3274A23AF25888FA80E3454"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of settlements entered into by the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text><item id="H1678ED1C0EB74295994173CDC7766449"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; or</text></item><item id="H4C91178877654DE6A1CDB454D0BFE045"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>involves the behavior of an employee of the covered issuer, or of a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, toward another such employee, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or the subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor, as applicable;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4398F3F0DDC441CCAF57C4BE8A36A1CB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total dollar amount paid with respect to the settlements described in subclause (I);</text></subclause><subclause id="HD5C6E78D5A3846A2B02E47D43DACF887"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the total number of settlements entered into by the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text><item id="HAEAEF5AC9D644172BC53A159D954D4FC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>was committed by a corporate executive of—</text><subitem id="HE62F1F09C919468D8BFAFDF51F6AD680"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the covered issuer; or</text></subitem><subitem id="HAB222CAE02064D20AEF6BA3639538860"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; and</text></subitem></item><item id="HFBB09696672F485E8CF90911E75ABB49"><enum>(bb)</enum><subitem commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFE448BEE134D47B7AC66AA93D8575DD9"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable; or</text></subitem><subitem id="H7B7EBF2D312C42ED83063485340F7487" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>involved the behavior of a corporate executive described in item (aa) toward another employee of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer;</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="H0075D52B3B144AC7803BDA0B7B424C71"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the total dollar amount with respect to the settlements described in subclause (III); </text></subclause><subclause id="H7FD619C869C947F7BFE750DAEF05B60C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the average length of time required for the covered issuer to resolve a complaint relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination, covered harassment, or sexual abuse; </text></subclause><subclause id="HDF598263F12848F79457187D008A029F"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of judgments entered against the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text><item id="H6B19D70C7A19448796FC0EDFA206868A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; or</text></item><item id="HECA9EF8051BD468C903C368F95A892EE"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>involves the behavior of an employee of the covered issuer, or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, toward another such employee, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or the subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor, as applicable;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H839C0F865CAD4BBBB8BCB7A7F780B25E"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the total dollar amount paid with respect to the judgments described in subclause (VI);</text></subclause><subclause id="H023A068440B241058442239948F64D5A"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>the total number of judgments entered against the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text><item id="HD5F6B46D154449ACB39131766BA99AEC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>was committed by a corporate executive of—</text><subitem id="HDDDF3F6A8AA54BE68FB83F0664D7B493"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the covered issuer; or</text></subitem><subitem id="H88D2BF90DB40470F9A8BF07C4993CF75"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; and</text></subitem></item><item id="H26C333A9675A4D0CB76C5B34D47C1E08"><enum>(bb)</enum><subitem commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8B7EEAA9918847A2AB4C0A79D9AA7C64"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable; or</text></subitem><subitem id="HEBF3FB83E7DB49968402DFBE9C7716B8" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>involved the behavior of a corporate executive described in item (aa) toward another employee of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; and</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="H2581D5DA368A4A3A962EF54583CD1860"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the total dollar amount with respect to the judgments described in subclause (VIII); </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6F07FBE6D3BD42E9A28F308887B76E74"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>as of the date on which the disclosure is made, the total number of complaints relating to covered discrimination, covered harassment, and sexual abuse that the covered issuer is working to resolve through—</text><subclause id="H285A02A43881421A99B6AC70572D016B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>processes that are internal to the covered issuer; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC55254D88D9A427A86D62160F7DD7EFD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>arbitration; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H58033A13538C4354BB14561AFC8D1D5A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>litigation; and</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFCE4D8F6EA4D42F2B24AEFEB0AFFFFCC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to each alleged act of covered discrimination, covered harassment, or sexual abuse that is the subject of a complaint or settlement described in clauses (i) and (ii), the date on which that alleged act occurred, with as much specificity as is practicable under the circumstances.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68412D44524F481EADD3C7A1C6716E92"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Categories</header><clause id="HCD85D66D13064262A764EC80FA834EAF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), in each disclosure required under subparagraph (A), a covered issuer shall report the following:</text><subclause id="H6723110A331941CE88B649AA44AF4246"><enum>(I)</enum><text>For the fiscal year that is the subject of that disclosure, the following:</text><item id="H5240B3BF18DA448B94E4EEE96AE858C9"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The total number of settlements in subclauses (I) and (III) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate. </text></item><item id="H9B6DE0BF948848B3B51C0D142A457700"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>The total dollar amounts in subclauses (II) and (IV) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate.</text></item><item id="HBB38024CFFDB4665A299B3326348EF38"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>The number of settlements in subclauses (I) and (III) of subparagraph (A)(i), individually.</text></item><item id="H1069C2EB5B844B9F820BBADCEFED879C"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>The dollar amounts in subclauses (II) and (IV) of subparagraph (A)(i), individually.</text></item><item id="HD6A9457145AE4690888ADAF0DCEFB09A"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>The total number of judgments in subclauses (VI) and (VIII) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate. </text></item><item id="H2AC438D2A8A94066980F9749657718E8"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>The total dollar amounts in subclauses (VII) and (IX) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate.</text></item><item id="H5E5BFD588E36474382926F9A9B2986EF"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>The number of judgments in subclauses (VI) and (VIII) of subparagraph (A)(i), individually.</text></item><item id="H2D52141C0ECC4E5BB49BB23D70647EE1"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>The dollar amounts in subclauses (VII) and (IX) of subparagraph (A)(i), individually. </text></item></subclause><subclause id="HD263BB0892184E419470C4E4004AB728"><enum>(II)</enum><text>For the 7-fiscal year period that is comprised of the fiscal year that is the subject of that disclosure and the 6 fiscal years that precede that fiscal year, the following:</text><item id="H89B938C737914E1695572D326DD0BC6E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The total number of settlements in subclauses (I) and (III) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate.</text></item><item id="H422FD99FE145422391934D4FFED4BAA9"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>The total dollar amounts in subclauses (II) and (IV) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate.</text></item><item id="HE74C1B2791AC4977A3A9437CD7C0790F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>The total number of judgments in subclauses (VI) and (VIII) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate.</text></item><item id="HB45A0991478F4359B943FFD2D1F188C3"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>The total dollar amounts in subclauses (VII) and (IX) of subparagraph (A)(i), in the aggregate. </text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H447181C1432447458678791FE84FBF15"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Listing</header><text>In disclosing information in the manner described in clause (i), a covered issuer shall list a settlement or judgment, as applicable, by any of the following categories that apply to the settlement or judgment:</text><subclause id="HF3BEF348B3814A129E16C6B868F9A1E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of sexual abuse, covered discrimination, or covered harassment because of sex.</text></subclause><subclause id="H0EE302462B0E4D809542B8DBB818D6FE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment because of race, color, or national origin.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6C23452384624AB1A5ED50751B46E391"><enum>(III)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment because of religion.</text></subclause><subclause id="H2C87F35B5D3D47A2A340034C4A827CA4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment because of age.</text></subclause><subclause id="H509F98C5A5034325B824CA9AAD438A6C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment on the basis of disability.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB72CBC59D4A2425A81D39C12CF83EF2B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment because of genetic information.</text></subclause><subclause id="H84562EDF94B141E48A1F1C8D0AD68230"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment on the basis of status concerning service in a uniformed service.</text></subclause><subclause id="H4DB180EDCBA04315A4CAC6486D7257B7"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>A settlement or judgment relating to an alleged act of covered discrimination or covered harassment because of sexual orientation or gender identity.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DF72F5AB8E24B5586C5AF49511CF2B2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prohibitions on certain disclosures; victim choice</header><clause id="HD30D2FBE45AA40FF8D8026C8CB401B5F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Prohibition on disclosures by covered issuers</header><text>A covered issuer may not—</text><subclause id="HD7168F4A1D544E79986CD3B9B2D19BA3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in any disclosure made under subparagraph (A), or in any other public disclosure, disclose the name of a victim of an alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which a settlement, judgment, or complaint, as applicable, described in subparagraph (A) is based; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H5E7A68B258DE488AACEE4B856619BCE0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>under subparagraph (B)(ii), include the categorization of a settlement or judgment described in subclause (I), (III), (VI), or (VIII) of subparagraph (A)(i), as applicable, in any disclosure made under subparagraph (A) if the victim of the alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which the settlement or judgment is based objects to the disclosure of that categorization.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H823C9D6D734A4C9D942852FB345B62DC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prohibition on disclosures by the Commission</header><text>The Commission may not disclose the name of a victim of an alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which a settlement, judgment, or complaint, as applicable, described in subparagraph (A) is based.</text></clause><clause id="HA12A4F2A85D34F94AD3798DA4E930B9B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Victim choice</header><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38DC4EA500FE49CFA695A64AC90B6204"><enum>(I)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>A covered issuer shall not be required to report information under subparagraph (B)(i) if the victim of the alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which the settlement or judgment, as applicable, is based objects to the reporting of that information.</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67658392776E4E019183C0735CC217B0"><enum>(II)</enum><header>No effect on subsequent years</header><text>If information is not reported in a fiscal year because of an objection made under subclause (I), that information shall be reported in subsequent fiscal years under subparagraph (B)(ii).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3959A056FFD64AF6A5DA0E8CF77AD1E8"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Prevention of sexual abuse, covered harassment, and covered discrimination</header><text>In each disclosure required under subparagraph (A), the covered issuer making the disclosure shall include a description of the measures taken by the covered issuer and any subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer to prevent employees of the covered issuer and any subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer from committing or engaging in sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F6D5ACD7BFD47FBBF9801AEC1DC3C1A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may promulgate such regulations as the Commission considers necessary to implement the requirements under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

