<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H66F2DA2E1C284C19B04BB40ADFF77FED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4850 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for a retroactive effective date of law regarding charge to entitlement to Department of Veterans Affairs educational assistance for individuals who do not transfer credits from certain closed or disapproved programs of education.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4850</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for a retroactive effective date of law regarding charge to entitlement to Department of Veterans Affairs educational assistance for individuals who do not transfer credits from certain closed or disapproved programs of education.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCE1AC13AA4AA4EACA61AF233D523F243" style="OLC"><section id="HF480900C1E22497781C9EB572FC114F2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Retroactive effective date of law regarding charge to entitlement to Department of Veterans Affairs educational assistance for individuals who do not transfer credits from certain closed or disapproved programs of education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3699(c)(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking subparagraph (C) and inserting the following new subparagraph (C):</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H92D80A98264B41069173D3B9416C8659" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H268FBDDE893D4BDCA15919A9C252B530" indent="up2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This paragraph, including clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (A), shall apply with respect to the closure or discontinuation of a course or program of education, as described in subsection (b)(1), that occurs during the period beginning on August 1, 2021, and ending on September 30, 2023.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

