<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<billStatus>
  <version>3.0.0</version>
  <bill>
    <number>9409</number>
    <updateDate>2023-07-31T18:15:19Z</updateDate>
    <updateDateIncludingText>2023-07-31T18:15:19Z</updateDateIncludingText>
    <originChamber>House</originChamber>
    <type>HR</type>
    <introducedDate>2022-12-02</introducedDate>
    <congress>117</congress>
    <cdata/>
    <committees>
      <item>
        <systemCode>hsgo00</systemCode>
        <name>Oversight and Accountability Committee</name>
        <chamber>House</chamber>
        <type>Standing</type>
        <activities>
          <item>
            <name>Referred to</name>
            <date>2022-12-02T14:00:25Z</date>
          </item>
        </activities>
      </item>
    </committees>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2022-12-02</actionDate>
        <text>Referred to the House Committee on Oversight and Reform.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>H11100</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>2</code>
          <name>House floor actions</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committees>
          <item>
            <systemCode>hsgo00</systemCode>
            <name>Oversight and Accountability Committee</name>
          </item>
        </committees>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2022-12-02</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>Intro-H</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2022-12-02</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>1000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
    </actions>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>L000583</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Rep. Loudermilk, Barry [R-GA-11]</fullName>
        <firstName>Barry</firstName>
        <lastName>Loudermilk</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <state>GA</state>
        <district>11</district>
        <isByRequest>N</isByRequest>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
    </policyArea>
    <subjects>
      <legislativeSubjects/>
      <policyArea>
        <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
      </policyArea>
    </subjects>
    <summaries>
      <summary>
        <versionCode>00</versionCode>
        <actionDate>2022-12-02</actionDate>
        <actionDesc>Introduced in House</actionDesc>
        <updateDate>2023-07-31T18:04:36Z</updateDate>
        <text><![CDATA[ <p><b>Modern Employment Reform, Improvement, and Transformation Act of 2022 or the MERIT Act of </b><b>2022</b></p> <p>This bill revises provisions related to federal employment, including the furlough and removal of federal employees, the calculation of federal employee retirement benefits, and the length of the probationary employment period.</p> <p>Specifically, the bill repeals the process for taking action against a federal employee for unacceptable performance, accelerates the process for removal or suspension based on performance or actions, and prohibits grievances based on adverse personnel actions and reductions in force. The bill also authorizes an agency to remove a senior executive from the civil service for performance-related reasons, and it revises provisions covering performance- or conduct-related actions against senior executives.</p> <p>The bill authorizes agencies to furlough employees for such cause as will promote the efficiency of the service, and it prohibits appeals to the Merit Systems Protection Board based on short-term furloughs or furloughs due to a lapse in appropriations (i.e., government shutdown).</p> <p>Additionally, the bill limits the retirement benefits of a federal employee who is removed due to a felony conviction related to their official duties by prohibiting felonious service from being taken into account when calculating the employee's annuity.</p> <p>The bill also authorizes an agency to order the repayment of a bonus or award when performance or conduct issues are discovered and such bonus or award would not have been paid had such issues been known when they were made.</p> <p>Lastly, the bill extends from one year to two years the probationary period for competitive service appointments and members of the Senior Executive Service.</p>]]></text>
      </summary>
    </summaries>
    <title>MERIT Act of 2022</title>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>MERIT Act of 2022</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Title(s) as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>MERIT Act of 2022</title>
        <billTextVersionName>Introduced in House</billTextVersionName>
        <billTextVersionCode>IH</billTextVersionCode>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Title(s) as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Modern Employment Reform, Improvement, and Transformation Act of 2022</title>
        <billTextVersionName>Introduced in House</billTextVersionName>
        <billTextVersionCode>IH</billTextVersionCode>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>To amend title 5, United States Code, to provide for an alternative removal for performance or misconduct for Federal employees.</title>
        <billTextVersionName>Introduced in House</billTextVersionName>
        <billTextVersionCode>IH</billTextVersionCode>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <textVersions>
      <item>
        <type>Introduced in House</type>
        <date>2022-12-02T05:00:00Z</date>
        <formats>
          <item>
            <url>https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/BILLS-117hr9409ih/xml/BILLS-117hr9409ih.xml</url>
          </item>
        </formats>
      </item>
    </textVersions>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2022-12-02</actionDate>
      <text>Referred to the House Committee on Oversight and Reform.</text>
    </latestAction>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>
